<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="4" Month="Jun" Year="1986" Vol="113" No="3" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 4 Meitheamh 1986" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 4 June 1986" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="173">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="173" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Mark Killilea, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, that he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Education to accede to the request of the board of management and teachers of the Currandulla national schools, Co. Galway, to enable the amalgamation of the two schools there to take place in September of this year and that eight teachers be retained to take into account the special circumstances of the location of the two schools.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Séamus de Brún of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Justice to have investigated the proliferation of pornographic videos which is causing widespread concern particularly in Roscommon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I regard the matter raised by Senator Mark Killilea as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken from 8 p.m. to 8.30 p.m. or earlier if the business ordered is concluded.  I regret I have to rule that the matter raised by <Col N="174" /> Senator de Brún is not suitable for discussion on the Adjournment on the ground of involving amending legislation.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1, 2, 4, 5 and 6 in that order and, assuming that it is convenient with the course of the business, to suspend the sitting from 5.30 p.m. to 6.30 p.m. and according to the usual custom, to take the Private Members' business from 6.30 p.m. until 8 o'clock.  I might indicate for the information of Senators that there has been a general agreement that the business tomorrow would be, first, to take No. 15 on today's Order Paper, which is a series of amendments to the Road Transport Bill, a Bill we have already dealt with.  After that it is proposed to take the Committee Stage of No. 2, the Dublin Transport Authority Bill, and following that to continue and hopefully conclude motion No. 7, the Report of the Development Committee on the Bilateral Aid Programme.</P>
      <P>Senators are aware that there is a large amount of legislation on the Order Paper. There is also a large amount of legislation on the Dáil Order Paper.  I am sure in consequence, many Senators are becoming anxious in regard to the adjournment of the House.  Following discussion with representatives of the groups it appears that there is a desire that the House should, while continuing to meet two days a week, work longer hours and accordingly the proposal is, and I am just giving notice of this as a proposal, that from next week onwards the House would meet on Wednesday at 12 noon instead of at 2.30 p.m. and that it would sit until 10 p.m. rather than 8 p.m.; that on a Thursday the House would assemble at 10 a.m. instead of at 10.30 a.m. and that the time of adjournment would depend on the amount of business to be done.  Most Senators would find it convenient if we were able to adjourn as we presently do, at about 5 p.m. but that may not be possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="175" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not sitting tonight until 10 p.m.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>No, assuming that the Second Stage of the Dublin Transport Authority Bill would have been concluded and that we would be then be on the Domicile and Recognition of Foreign Divorces Bill, the Minister in charge of this would not be available between 8 p.m. and 10 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, I want to ask a question concerning the Transport (Re-organisation of Córas Iompair Éireann) Bill.  I had a conversation this morning with the Leader of the House and I agreed, as my party's spokesman, that we would try to take it on Wednesday of next week.  It is very important that we should.  I know there are major problems concerning this Bill between the Labour Party and the Fine Gael Party but I hope they will resolve their problems this week so that we can proceed with it.  It is very important legislation and we should deal with it as quickly as possible.  It was in the belief that that would be done that we agreed to No. 15 for tomorrow.  I want to thank the Leader of the House for the courteous way in which he went about his business this morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CatherineMcGuinness" hpid="Mrs. McGuinness Mrs. McGuinness">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGuinness</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we go into the business of the House there is a matter which I would like to mention as a woman Member of this House.  I would like to pay tribute to Senator Mary Davidson who died during the past week. She was an important woman Member of this House, one of the earlier women Members of this House, who was, above all, a woman of devotion and conscientiousness to all the business of the Seanad. In particular she took a great interest in the matter of the registration of nursing homes and the protection of old people who lived in nursing homes.  As Senator Ryan and myself recently had a motion on this matter, in which we referred to her, I felt it was appropriate that one of us should pay tribute to her in that she <Col N="176" /> was the first person who looked for legislation and indeed was instrumental in getting legislation about the registration of nursing homes.  I understand that she died during the past week and I would not like the occasion to pass by without paying tribute to the qualities she brought to the Seanad and to the work she did in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to join with Senator McGuinness and with other Members of the House in paying tribute to the late Mary Davidson.  She was, as everybody knows, general secretary of the Labour Party for many years and a Senator in her own right, arising out of her nomination. She was held in the highest esteem in the party and in this House during her long period in office.  It was a matter of regret to us, as a political party, that we lost somebody of Mary's calibre.  It is appropriate that this House should recognise the sterling service she gave.  I hope she is in her eternal resting place where she deserves to be after serving her country and her party well for many years.</P>
      <P>Whereas I accept the comments of Senator Killilea, it is appropriate that we reach agreement on when we would take any legislation.  There are other people in this House with whom we have also to reach agreement and that includes the Labour Party, Fine Gael and the Independents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I know.  It is an awful problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>In an effort to reach agreement with everybody, Senator Killilea will be accorded the courtesy of being informed when we have reached agreement about it.  There are problems with the legislation.  We have had discussions with the Minister.  It is appropriate that he should be given time to consider our suggestions as a Labour Party.  We owe apologies to nobody for making those suggestions on the legislation.  When it reaches the House I hope there will have been agreement on all sides about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="177" />
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You have already spoken, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not want an apology from anybody.  I only wanted to have the legislation put before the House.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Sentor Ryan is being intimidated, it is very easily done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is worse than that, it is the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I never noticed that that was possible at all.  Perhaps I do not have Senator Killilea's technique.  Last week I, perhaps naively, welcomed the statement by the Deputy Leader of the House about the Bill on the abolition of the death penalty.  I got the distinct impression that it was the intention that it would be discussed today.  In that context I welcomed it and said very flattering words about the Deputy Leader.  I do not want to withdraw the flattering words.  I am mindful of an old latin proverb &ldquo;Timeo Danaos et dona ferentes&rdquo;: I am fright ened of the Greeks when they come bearing gifts.  I obviously mistook a gift for something else.  I am sorry it is number 5.  It would have been very appropriate on the twenty-fifth anniversary of the founding of Amnesty International to abolish once and for all that barbarous activity or proposal for activity which is the death penalty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I was under exactly the same impression as Senator Ryan.  I would like to ask about No. 5 because this has been ordered and has been jumping up and down on the Order Paper for a very long time.  We have had a three hour debate on it.  I have asked the Leader of the House on several occasions if it is the Government's intention to give us time for this Bill.  Another death sentence was commuted last week.  We are still going through the farce of death sentences <Col N="178" /> being imposed and then being commuted. There is a perfectly good Bill on the Order Paper of this House to abolish the death sentence.  What I would like to hear, even if we are not going to be given time, is what the Government's position on the death penalty is, whether they have any intention of abolishing it or whether they have any intention of accepting this Bill or debating it at all. Although it is ordered No. 5 this evening, everybody knows it will not come up.  It has been ordered in that position before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF" hpid="Mr. Cassidy Mr. Cassidy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cassidy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Leader of the House when it is proposed to take No. 26.  He was to have word for me on several occasions but I read in the paper over the last week that last Friday the Coalition partners were having a chat about it.  I want to know if there is any news from that meeting.  Will it be taken before the summer recess or before the end of the Government's term of office?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to No. 5, I was asked what is the Government's position.  My understanding of the Government's position in regard to the question of the abolition of the death penalty is precisely that for which the Government parties voted in this House on Second Stage on a previous occasion. I am speaking for myself and, I am sure, for all my colleagues when I say I will be only too glad to repeat that vote at the earliest possible opportunity.  I will once again convey the anxiety of Members of all groups in the House that this matter should be resolved as soon as possible. This was done by the Deputy Leader last week and by me on previous occasions. I do not want to give any pledges whatsoever but I do feel there is a growing sense of urgency in the responses which are being received.</P>
      <P>In regard to No. 26, I am sorry that I was not privy to the discussions last week on the Broadcasting and Wireless Telegraphy Bill which would enable me to inform Senator Cassidy whether any progress was made.  I have to confess ignorance in this regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Finally, I could not allow the occasion <Col N="179" /> to pass without joining in the tribute to Mary Davidson.  There are very few of us here who served with her in the Seanad. Anyone who did serve with her could not fail to be impressed by her commonsense and useful and constructive contributions to our debates.  She was for many years the only woman Member of the Seanad. She was not merely a representative on women's issues.  Her interests were wide. In her quiet manner she was a most effective and valuable Member of this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like, on behalf of the Fianna Fáil Party, to be associated with the vote of sympathy to the relatives of Senator Davidson.  I had the privilege of knowing the lady.  She was here in my time in the House.  She was a person for whom I had great regard.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Combat Poverty Agency Bill, 1985 (Seanad Bill" RHead="Amended by the Dáil): Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Combat Poverty Agency Bill, 1985 (Seanad Bill Amended by the Dáil): Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Seanad Bill which has been amended by the Dáil.  In accordance with Standing Order No. 82 it is deemed to have passed its First, Second and Third Stages in the Seanad and is placed on the Order Paper for the Report Stage.  On the question that the Bill be received for Final Consideration the Minister may explain the purport of the amendments made by the Dáil and this is regarded as the Report of the Dáil Amendments to the Seanad.  The only matter, therefore, that may be discussed is the amendments made by the Dáil. For the convenience of Senators I have arranged for the printing and circulation to them of those amendments.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for Final Consideration.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusPattison" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Mr. Pattision) Séamus Pattison">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Mr. Pattision)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Combat Poverty Agency Bill, 1985, as passed by Seanad Éireann in July 1985 <Col N="180" /> has been passed by Dáil Éireann with two amendments.  The first amendment relates to section 1 &mdash; interpretation.  In page 3, lines 30 and 31, &ldquo;31st day of December, 1985&rdquo; has been deleted and &ldquo;31st day of December, 1986&rdquo; substituted. The effect of the amendment is to define the first financial year of the agency as the period from the establishment day to 31 December 1986.  It is proposed to establish the agency in 1986 and the amendment was necessary in order that the first financial year will end on the last day of the agency's first year as intended.</P>
      <P>The second amendment concerns section 5 (2) in page 5, line 31: &ldquo;31st day of December 1987&rdquo; has been deleted and &ldquo;31st day of December 1989&rdquo; substituted. Subsection (2) of the section obliges the agency to draw up a strategic plan in respect of each three year period.  It is proposed to establish the agency this year but the initial plan is not due to be submitted until six months after the date of the first meeting.  The plan will then have to be examined by the Minister and the Minister for Finance must be consulted.</P>
      <P>Senators will recall that in the Bill as initiated it was provided that the approval of the Minister for Finance also had to be otained, but on consideration of arguments made in the House I agreed to amend the Bill so that consultation only with the Minister for Finance would be required.  Because of the obvious necessity to give careful consideration to the agency's first plan it is inevitable that it will be some way into 1987 before the plan will be approved.  The amendment was made, therefore, to provide that the first plan will cover the period of two and a half to three years to the end of 1989 which is in keeping with the general intention that each plan will be for a period of three years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I call on Senator Fallon, Members are aware that they may speak only once on this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>This Combat Poverty Agency Bill is a Bill to advise the Minister for Social Welfare on all aspects of economic and social planning in relation <Col N="181" /> to poverty in the State; to initiate measures aimed at overcoming such poverty and to evaluate such measures.  We have had a long debate in this House and similarly in Dáil Éireann.  That is right and proper because it is a very serious problem and one that needs to be overcome as quickly as possible.  All I can say in dealing with the actual amendments, which I understand is all I can discuss, is that in the knowledge that we have so much poverty in this country, in the knowledge that we have so much unemployment as a result of which we have so many people in receipt of social welfare benefits, we are paying something like £2.6 billion in social welfare.  Nearly 40 per cent of the population is in receipt of some form of social welfare benefit. These are staggering figures and indicate a great deal of poverty within the State. I would have thought, therefore, that every effort would be made to speed up all aspects of this Bill.  Yet we find from the amendment to section 5 that there will be no strategic plan available until 1990.</P>
      <P>Despite all the agencies, and groups that are involved in doing so much for poverty I have to say that I am extremely disappointed that this is the case.  I really felt that speed in this area of poverty was so necessary that the Minister and the Government would proceed as quickly as possible with all of the interested groupings. There are many groups in this country who have an interest in poverty and have proven themselves and have a track record.  I am talking about groupings like the St.  Vincent de Paul Society and all the various groups who are well known to have an interest in this area. They would have their records, the personnel would be available and any plans that are appropriate to deal with this Bill would be quickly on stream and therefore people who are on the poverty line would benefit most.  I am somewhat disappointed that this matter has not been dealt with, that we are going to have no plan until the 1990s.  I think the losers in this whole situation are the people who need it most.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="182" />
    <Speaker pid="AndyOBrien" hpid="Mr. A. O'Brien Mr. A. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>In my opinion the amendments are necessary to ensure the smooth operation of the Bill when it becomes law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the undertaking by the Minister that the agency will be established within the present year of 1986.  At the same time I want to register my disappointment at the very long period &mdash; almost a year if my memory serves me right &mdash; that it has taken the Dáil to process this legislation. The area of poverty is in need of urgent attention and the agency is part and parcel of the machinery to try to tackle that key problem facing Irish society.  The legislation as we will pass it today is already overdue.  I would like to think, now that it will be passed today, that no effort whatever will be spared to establish the agency as rapidly as possible.</P>
      <P>With regard to section 5 I welcome the proposal for a strategic plan.  It implies a continuing offensive on poverty and I hope that our plan &mdash; the Irish plan &mdash; will extend beyond the period of the European Community plan, namely 1989.  In other words, I hope that national initiatives in the poverty area will extend beyond the European Community programme in both time and content.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusPattison" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Mr. Pattison) Séamus Pattison">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Social Welfare (Mr. Pattison)</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to thank the House and the Members who spoke for their contribution on this occasion.  We had the Bill in the House almost a year ago as Senator Hillery has said.  I want to correct the impression under which Senator Fallon appears to be regarding the dates.  He mentioned that the first plan will not be available until 1990.  I thought I made it clear in my opening remarks that the agency will be set up this year, as quickly as possible, and that they will be obliged within six months from their first meeting to have the plan and that plan will cover the period from approximately the middle of 1987 up to the end of 1989.  That is the first strategic plan.  The agency will be getting down to work in the near future. It will be producing its first plan within <Col N="183" /> six months after meeting and I think that having regard to all the circumstances that kind of a timetable is a reasonable one.  It has to be balanced between, on the one hand, the obvious urgency of having the plan and, on the other hand, the obvious need to ensure that the plan will be an effective one and that there will be nothing rushed about it, that it will be well thought out and effective.  I consider that the timetable which is laid out is one that is reasonable and one that will get the best results.  I want to emphasise that the plan will commence about the middle of 1987.  I think that explains to the House the amendments which have been made in the Dáil and again I thank the House for the way they have received the Bill and for their valuable contributions.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question, &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;, put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Dublin Transport Authority Bill, 1985:" RHead="Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Dublin Transport Authority Bill, 1985: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackFitzsimons" hpid="Mr. Fitzsimons Mr. Fitzsimons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzsimons</NameTxt>
      <P>I had made a great part of my contribution on the last day here and my contribution today will not be a long one because it is not an area in which I have any expertise or great knowledge.  Nevertheless it is a very important area.  The explanatory memorandum which accompanies this Bill tells us that it provides for the establishment of the Dublin Transport Authority for the purpose of improving the planning and operation of road and rail transport and the management of traffic in the Dublin area and it goes on to list the main functions and deal with them in some detail: transport planning, transport funding, public transport services and traffic management.  These have already been gone into in some detail in the <Col N="184" /> Green Paper.  Clearly it is a Bill of great importance.  I welcome it and I hope it will be as successful as the Minister in his introductory remarks led us to believe it will.  As I mentioned very briefly on the last occasion the car and motorised transport has had a much greater impact on society than we realise, to such an extent that, unfortunately, much of our planning is centred around the motor car rather than people, as it should be.  People have suffered; the environment has suffered; the aesthetics of building and planning have suffered.  While the car has been a great influence for the better it has like many other similar influences this unsatisfactory side also.  The motor car has been to a large extent responsible for unsatisfactory side also.  The motor car has been because without the motor car transport from the rural areas to the urban areas would not have been possible.  In consequence there is the high cost of the infrastructure necessary in those situations, the roads, telephone services, water services and sewerage facilities.  To a large extent we could blame this on the motor car.  In other areas not immediately associated with planning such as the risk factors involved, the accident rate and so on are all related to the motor car.</P>
      <P>One of the consequences of living in a rural area and commuting to the urban or city areas is that in some family situations two cars are necessary.  This in itself brings on other pressures such as wage increases and so on.  The motor car has this major impact which has not yet been fully comprehended or assessed.  It is reasonable to believe that in future this influence will intensify rather than otherwise.</P>
      <P>We have a major problem in the Dublin area and it is necessary to deal with it.  It is of the utmost importance that it would be dealt with comprehensively and as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the Confederation of Irish Industry Information Sheet No. 3, May 1986, there is comprehensive coverage of the Green Paper and the views of the Confederation with regard to aspects of the <Col N="185" /> Green Paper.  It mentions on page 6 under &ldquo;Urban Transport&rdquo;:</P>
    <P>Transport infrastructure in the Dublin region, must provide an adequate infrastructure and traffic management system, to increase the efficiency of transport services and reduce costs.  It should also be borne in mind that the road system in the Dublin region is part of the overall national transport infrastructure.  It must not therefore be regarded in isolation or related solely to the provision of public or private passenger urban transport services.  The Confederation fully supports the road development programme now under way.  Improvements in the infrastructure would clearly benefit public and private transport operators.</P>
    <P>I would try to emphasise that point, that while we are dealing primarily with the situation in the Dublin area it is most important to remember that this is only part of the larger national system and it is only in that context that we can deal adequately with this Bill and this problem.  In so far as the Bill comes to terms with this requirement and the necessity to remember that at all times we are dealing with the capital city of this country but nevertheless that it should be part of the overall strategy and plan to deal with transport &mdash; only in that context will the problem be solved.</P>
    <P>On my very few visits to London I noticed that the traffic seemed to move more smoothly.  Delays seemed to be very short.  The traffic lights seemed to hold up the traffic for shorter periods. Everything seemed to be more in line with clockwork than in this city.  I wondered why and I still wonder at the great difference.  One of the reasons must be the network of roads and the infrastructure and consequently investment to improve the situation is most important. I am not too clear as to what plans will result from this Bill regarding the actual investment.  I know that there is provision to make recommendations to planning authorities and to the local authorities to take part in that area.  I am not too clear <Col N="186" /> as to what is the actual investment.  There can be no satisfactory solution to this major problem without substantial investment.</P>
    <P>We have a road structure which is very much behind the times.  Apart from the road surface which in many instances because of potholes is in a bad state of repair, the base for the roadwork was not adequate to cope with the present day traffic.  Our major problem seems to be that there was not enough investment in our roads.  As one, who for many years was involved in road design, road operations, and seeing the problems that were involved, I know the great difficulties regarding improvement, but the major problem is finance.  With our accession to the EC this was one area which I felt should have got greater support.  This year a major campaign for road improvement is supposed to start.  I hope it will.</P>
    <P>We are all particularly concerned about our own areas.  I came in from Navan to Dublin and while the road from Donegal to Dublin is a first class road and by and large is designed for traffic flows of 60 m.p.h. &mdash; and even parts of the road are still be improved &mdash; when one comes to Clonee, for about three miles of the road there is a bottleneck.  The road is narrow: there is no grass margin on one side.  It is impossible to overtake slow-moving traffic.  It seems strange to me how roads well away from the city were improved and this bottleneck was left unattended.  It would seem to me logical to start with the city and to improve the roads leading into it.  In fact, this was done generally but for some unknown reason this particular road got no attention and the result is that if one is behind a JCB in the morning or is behind slow-moving traffic one must move at a snail's pace at about 5 m.p.h. into the city.  No improvement would be possible I think with that situation.  While I pinpoint this case which is known to me personally I am sure that many other Members of the House would be able to pick out similar situations in their own areas.  So, if you take that on a national level there is a <Col N="187" /> major problem with regard to the infrastructure and design of roads, the foundations, with widths of roads, the alignment and so on.  It is necessary to deal with all of this before any great improvement would be possible.  This demands investment and without nit picking it seems wrong that no provision is being made for this.  However, that may well be otherwise provided for and I would welcome a comment on this from the Minister when he is replying.</P>
    <P>I found the Green Paper on Transport Policy very helpful.  It was very comprehensive. The problems were dealt with and the solutions listed in an easily-understood manner.  There is reference to the Transport Consultative Commission's report which was published in 1980. We are told that the commission saw the first priority in Dublin as a reduction in traffic congestion, particularly at peak hours and proposed a series of traffic management measures to bring about improvements in the short and medium term.  Over the years I have noticed, particularly recently, a great improvement with regard to traffic flow.  This morning I came in from Ashbourne and there was no delay.  This must be due in large measure to the proposals of the Dublin Transport Task Force.  The Minister has paid tribute to that task force and I would like to do likewise.  It is obvious that in some instances, particularly in the outskirts of the city, the problem has been dealt with to a large extent by the provision of traffic lights, and while traffic lights may have an important role to play, in many instances the provision of traffic lights has resulted in slowing up the traffic.  I realise that gardaí cannot be on point duty in all these places and some consideration will have to be given to that aspect of it.  While I would be critical of it to some extent, I must pay tribute to the work of the task force.  My experience is that a great improvement has been effected over the last few years.</P>
    <P>The Green Paper stated that progress in achieving the objectives of the commission has been slower than expected and it lists a number of reasons <Col N="188" /> for this.  No. 1 was industrial relations problems and that is one I do not want to go into.  I do hope that some improvement will be made in this area and I am sure it will.  In a situation where workmen are not satisfied and find it impossible to carry out their work properly and well, there will be discontent.  If this Bill is a success it will bring about a situation where there will be an improvement with regard to traffic flow and other areas and I am sure the industrial relations problems will also be reduced.</P>
    <P>Progress in the introduction of parking controls has not been as fast as recommended by the commission.  The Green Paper has stated that the levels of parking charges and on-the-spot fines to date has not been sufficiently high to discourage long-term parking.  It is hard to understand why this has not been a success. With the increase in the numbers of traffic wardens to 109 full time and 15 part time, it is difficult to understand this problem.  I know the traffic wardens have a difficult role to play.  I would like to see part of their role being to help motorists rather than appearing to be ready to pounce on the motorist who is parked illegally.  While saying that I do not have any sympathy for the motorist &mdash; and I know there are many of them who want to drive right up to their shops or places of destination and have no regard for anyone else.  Constantly we see white or yellow lines ignored and we see traffic lights being ignored.  Notwithstanding the substantial increase in the traffic warden service and increases in the penalties for illegal parking enforcement measures have not succeeded in effectively controlling illegal parking.</P>
    <P>Finally, we are told that the statutory body with responsibility and necessary powers for overall transport management which the commission envisage as essential will only come into being following the enactment of this Bill which is before us.  So, for that reason it is most important.</P>
    <P>The duties of the Dublin Transport Authority are set out in section 8 (4). It states that in the performance of its <Col N="189" /> functions the Authority may (a) promote, engage in and participate in programmes of public education relating to road and rail transport in the authority's functional area; (b) promote, engage in and participate in research relating to road and rail transport in the Authority's functional area and (c) promote the greater use of public transport in the Authority's functional area.  These are all very important rules.</P>
    <P>Education is most important and this is an area where the traffic wardens could also co-operate.  Regarding the flow of traffic, to promote the greater use of public transport within the Authority's functional area is perhaps the most important objective of all.  To discourage private motorists from overplaying their role it is important to provide a good public transport service and anything of that kind that follows from this Bill can only help in that regard.</P>
    <P>Section 15 is the longest section in this Bill and deals with traffic wardens, so I am quite sure the Minister would agree with me about the importance of the traffic warden's role.</P>
    <P>Part 3 of the Bill deals with town planning and this incorporates section 24 to section 28.  Section 23 empowers the Authority to make recommendations to the Minister for Communications as to public transport facilities which the Authority consider should be provided in their functional area.  Section 24, as we are told by the Explanatory Memorandum, empowers the Authority to make recommendations to the relevant planning authorities in their functional area as to the content of their development plans prepared under the Local Government Planning and Development Act.  These two sections empower the authority to make recommendations but what is the value of making recommendations?  I am sure these recommendations do not have to be accepted, that it is possible to make recommendations at present.  For example, under the five year plan prepared by the planning authority it is possible to make recommendations.  Indeed I believe that it is the practice at present to make submissions and these must be <Col N="190" /> taken into consideration.  As I understand it, the Bill does not have much further bite in that regard.  Recommendations would be considered, I am sure, but could be rejected for various reasons, mostly from the point of view of finance.  I cannot see any great advance from the present situation where submissions have to be taken into consideration by the planning authority under the provision of the five year plan.  This Bill does not envisage any further developments.</P>
    <P>The Minister, in his comprehensive introduction, told us that the strategy of the Bill was aimed at keeping Dublin's traffic moving swiftly but safely.  It is important that we consider the safety element and at the same time consider the provision of adequate short term car-parking facilities for persons coming to the city to do business.  It is also envisaged that it will secure better physical planning and as I have already said, there is adequate provision at present for proper planning if the finance is available.  In implementing the five year plan it is important to consider the finance available.  Of course the five year plan is not mandatory in that what is proposed in it does not have to be carried out: it simply means that proposals would have to be accordance with the provisions of the plan.  There is no compulsion to see the plan through.  In fact at the end of the five year term I am sure many of the provisions will not have been accomplished. In that respect we have at present adequate provision to secure better physical planning.</P>
    <P>In this country, as in Sweden and other advanced countries, it should be a provision of any plan that the local people would have an input.  For example, in Sweden when envisaging the design of a housing scheme the local people make their input at an early stage and indeed throughout the entire scheme.  We should encourage this type of input here and in that way we would make people more responsible and more concerned about their own environment.  The Bill should encourage that type of participation of liaison which would be very important. <Col N="191" /> As I have said, in other advanced countries where something as small as a variation in a streetscape is envisaged, the local people are involved and what ultimately transpires is, they feel, part of their plan.  In this way the people become more responsible and this extends even to litter and concern for their environment generally.</P>
    <P>The Minister, quite rightly, emphasised the importance of transport and he listed the three Bills concerning transport that have gone through this House in a very short time.  Three further transport Bills are now before the Dáil and he mentioned that it is his intention to initiate further Bills in this House.  I would take this opportunity to thank him because this House can play an important part in any Bill.  In my short time here many important Bills have been initiated in this House and I welcome the Minister's promise to introduce more Bills here.</P>
    <P>The Minister in his introductory speech stated that the Authority would have the right to make recommendations to the local authorities and I would be critical of this.  Something more definite is needed there.  They will also have the right of consultation with the local authorities and An Bord Pleanála.  They have this right at present.  In the case of any appeal that goes before An Bord Pleanála it is open to any interested party to make submissions.  In the whole area of transport I cannot see a situation in which bodies such as CIE involved in that area would be ignored if they made submissions to An Bord Pleanála or to the planning authority.  They would have to be taken into consideration.  The Bill does not make any great advance in that regard.</P>
    <P>With regard to giving power to local authorities to provide ramps, I know of a number of situations in the recent past where elected representatives suggested that ramps be used in certain locations. The situation at present is that a local authority do not have the power to provide ramps.  While this only refers to the Dublin area, I realise it is a start.  I see <Col N="192" /> ramps used on private property to slow down traffic and they seem to be a success. I am quite sure that in built up housing areas they could be equally successful, if they were discretely used.  It will be interesting to see what improvement this change will make.</P>
    <P>It would be interesting to know if there is any back up in the way of engineering advice with regard to the provision of ramps.  Ramps to me, seem rather horizontal on the surface.  Traffic would be slowed up equally well by bends for example.  I have mentioned before that in road design the emphasis is on removing bends and in some cases replacing them with curves.  Nevertheless the whole emphasis is on increasing speed.  It seems, with regard to ramps and bollards, the emphasis is on the other direction, slowing it up.  I would make the point that while ramps have the effect of slowing down traffic &mdash; simple bends I suppose from the environmental point of view, are far more attractive than straight roads and curves always look more attractive &mdash; bends and cul-de-sac roads would be a more acceptable way of dealing with this problem.</P>
    <P>The Minister paid tribute to the task force and I have also paid tribute to them. There is no doubt in my mind that their achievement, all the more so since they are a non-statutory body, is measurable and they have achieved much.  The Minister told us that the Authority's planning functions exclude a substantial element recommended by the commission, namely that the Authority would draw up a comprehensive Dublin transport plan. The Minister told us that such a plan, when approved by the Government, would be binding on all concerned.  This recommendation was not accepted because of the risk of duplicating the ongoing planning work of the local authorities and CIE.  I am slightly confused in this area.  It seems that the proper course would be to draw up a comprehensive Dublin transport plan.  Nevertheless, the local authority have the expertise and the engineers to do that.  I suppose, if the requirements are laid down by the Dublin <Col N="193" /> Transport Authority it would be a relatively simple matter to have the actual plans prepared.  The implementation of the plans of course, is another matter.  I hope, in implementing these plans, whatever they may be, that conservation, the buildings and all the aspects with regard to the environment would be taken into consideration.  I have no doubt that this will be done.  I suppose, to a large extent, we could say that the problems regarding what has been called the destruction of Dublin have not been related to roadworks or to improvement in the infrastructure. I simply make the point in passing that whatever is done should take congnisance of the onus that is on us to preserve what is worth preserving.  In this city we have much to preserve.</P>
    <P>With regard to the power which this Authority will have to make recommendations with regard to roadworks, I agree that it seems necesasary to impose some constraint in this regard.  I hope that the tourist season will be taken into account, the impact on tourism which is most important.  It seems that in many ways our policies have not been integrated over the years.  The Confederation of Irish Industry leaflet makes that point on page 3.  It states:</P>
    <P>In many cases investment decisions have been in response to issues which are not related to transport.  This would include decisions to stimulate employment in such sectors as construction or as a result of political pressures.</P>
    <P>Some employment schemes involving roadworks might not necessarily be as a result of political pressures.  They could very well be related to social pressures, and reducing the stresses regarding unemployment in certain areas.  I feel that transport cannot be taken in isolation. All these things must be taken into consideration.  It is like seeing roadworks done in certain areas where land reclamation might be carried on a few years later and where the top soil could very well have been properly used and the two schemes could be integrated.  This does not seem to take place.  It is unfortunate. From that point of view, whatever kind <Col N="194" /> of co-operation results because of this Bill, everybody will welcome it.</P>
    <P>We have those problems which should be integrated.  I am not too sure what impact the Transport Authority will have regarding the actual times when roadworks are carried out, because they will be disruptive no matter when they take place.  At some times they will be more disruptive.  This must be the important consideration.</P>
    <P>Towards the end of his contribution, the Minister then referred to the heavy penalties, £1,000 and up to one year's imprisonment on summary conviction or £50,000 and or five years imprisonment on conviction on indictment.  It seems that these are very heavy fines.  They are related to unauthorised disclosures of information by a member of employee of the authority.  I cannot understand how divulging this information could be of such importance.  Perhaps the Minister would elaborate on this in replying to the debate.  The fines seem particularly high. They are also related to unauthorised roadworks.  I am not too sure in what situation unauthorised roadworks are carried out.  Even for a simple connection to a water main it is necessary to get permission from the local authority.  It is necessary to pay a fee and to restore the road properly.  I am not aware in what situation unauthorised roadworks could be carried out except in a situation where somebody, deliberately, for some reason, would attempt to interfere with roads.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill, which is a comprehensive one.  I do not underestimate the difficulty with regard to developments in this area.  We have seen this development over the last 30 years and I am sure it will continue.  It is very difficult to envisage the further developments that will take place.</P>
    <P>There is provision in this Bill, by way of order, to deal with other problems which may arise and to make provision for problems which could not be envisaged. I welcome that aspect of the Bill. Motorised transport, particularly the motor car, has made a major impact. While I welcome progress, in many areas <Col N="195" /> it is unfortunate that all of our planning now seems to hinge on the car rather than the person.  Perhaps this Bill, is acheiving its objectives, will bring back the individual as the focal point in our planning laws and regulations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisJGFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. A. FitzGerald Mr. A. FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I, like Senator Fitzsimons, would like to welcome this Bill. I say this in particular because of a very longstanding commitment that other members of Dublin Corporation and myself were responsible for exhorting what is now known as the Department of Communications, during the 1974-76 period to get on with, namely the formation of a Dublin transport authority.  The necessity for having a Dublin transport authority becomes particularly real when one examines the number of agencies that are involved in dealing with the broad issue of providing for public and private transport in the Dublin region. We have not only Dublin Corporation and Dublin County Council but within each of these two large local authorities we have at least three departments handling different sections of the problem: on the one hand, providing the necessary road framework, and on the other hand, dealing with long term planning and handling the management of traffic in conjunction with bodies such as the Garda Síochána, CIE, who are responsible for public transport, and at least three Departments of State whose functions impinge on this area.  It is important to get one organisation responsible for the movement of traffic, public or private, and for goods within the greater Dublin area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Dublin Transport Authority Bill setting up the Dublin Transport Authority not only deals with that, but goes on to deal with a whole range of improvements in the management of traffic which I know are very welcome and very necessary. Many of these have been sought by my traffic authority over the past five years, issues such as the need to give proper legislative authority to bodies like Dublin Corporation and to provide bollards, road ramps and wheel clamping. <Col N="196" /> Such provision is very necessary with the congestion of our streets and the degree of the abuse of the residential areas of the city by through traffic and by traffic which abuses it by not only rat-running through it but parking in it during daytime hours.</P>
    <P>I notice that part 2 of the Bill in defining the Dublin Transport Authority, mentions that the Authority is there for &ldquo;the proper and efficient planning and operation of road and rail transport in its functional area&rdquo;.  It goes on in subsection 2(c) to mention that the particular role of the Dublin Transport Authority will be to promote the greater use of public transport in the Authority's functional area.  I very much welcome the emphasis given in that subsection to the need to increasingly provide public transport.  As other contributors to this debate have mentioned, including the Minister in his very expansive introduction to the Bill on Second Stage, over 600 new or re-engined buses have been provided to CIE's Dublin service fleet, which now number about 840 buses in all.  This has come since the Dublin transportation task force went into operation.  He said the bus lanes have been successfully implemented in 65 locations covering virtually all the main arterial routes in the city centre, that the traffic warden service has grown from a small number working on a part time basis to 109 full time and 16 part time wardens and that 1,700 on-street car park spaces, formerly available for all day parking, have been converted into short stay space used for the provision of parking meters.</P>
    <P>It is good to have recorded in the Minister's speech the successful moves that the Dublin transportation task force have been able to make in relation to the provision of new buses, the introduction of bus lanes and the increased provision for temporary car parking.  They have achieved other things which have not been mentioned in this speech: they were responsible for recommending the contra-flow on the quays following the building of two additional bridges, which has considerably eased congestion in the city.</P>
    <P>I hope on two counts that the Dublin <Col N="197" /> Transport Authority will be exhorted to look further at the way forward in relation to traffic management.  The Minister said:</P>
    <P>I wish to see the authority develop a comprehensive parking strategy in favour of the short stay parker as against the all day parker.  Such a strategy would embrace off street and on street spaces, charges, parking periods and types of parking controls.</P>
    <P>I come to the types of parking controls that could be available in this city.  We seem to have a rather blindfolded approach over a lengthy period of time wherein the only available method of controlling car parking on the streets of this city is the parking meter.  I hope that we can look in the immediate future at alternative ways of controlling car parking such as the disc system which works successfully in other cities, and which does not disfigure the city to the extent that 4,000 steel units do at present even around the No. 1 area of this city, which incidentally is an important tourist attraction. This affects the tourists who come into this city, as well as the residents, many of whom have had to put up with the existence of increasing numbers of these rather disfiguring units.  There could be a great deal more attention given to looking at the other ways of controlling car parking, particularly as the parking meter has not been conspicuously successful in relation to enforcement.  We have no reason to take off our hat with any degree of certainty that that is the method that is likely in the future to be the most successful in controlling our car parking arrangements in the city.  For that reason I exhort the Dublin Transport Authority to look at the type of parking controls that could be used and to see if other systems could be looked at as well.</P>
    <P>I gave some attention to this when I started to notice in Part II of this Bill the emphasis placed in drafting the Bill on the greater use of public transport.  In this regard I am, unlike Senator Fitzsimons, happy with the fact that we have by way of the arrangement on communication between the new Transport Authority <Col N="198" /> and the local authorities, the word &ldquo;recommendation&rdquo; used rather than any form of direction relating to the way in which the Transport Authority may have, at planning stage or at a stage in which a local authority may be preparing their development plan or a recommendation in relation to road development, an understanding that it is important that the local authority continue to have a fair degree of accountability and a fair degree of independence in relation to these areas.  I hope that in the first place the position of the local authority within the framework of this Bill will continue to be one of importance and that there will be an increased communication from the Dublin Transport Authority over the years and one that will be increasingly valuable to the construction of a transport system, both public and private, that will be an improvement on what we have got as of now.</P>
    <P>It is important that the use of public transport, within the framework of the overall interests of the transportation Authority, will be such to promote greater use of this area and avoid, as far as possible, the rather single-minded approach that has been the fate of city engineers in Dublin for a considerable time past in promoting almost exclusively the development of a road system almost without any cognisance of the varied types of uses or the alternative uses that could be brought into the city centre.  I say this fully conscious of the decision of the Minister for the Environment a fortnight or three weeks ago relating to a particualar sensitive part of the centre of this city in the vicinity of Nicholas Street and Patrick Street where it is now intended to improve the road, I contend totally out of proportion to what is necessary in this area.  There has been a reduction in the use of this stretch of road.  It was the subject of a compulsory purchase oral hearing earlier this year and which was confirmed by the Minister for the Environment.</P>
    <P>The scale of this road in this area is totally out of proportion to the historic attraction of the area centred between St. Patrick's Cathedral and Christ Church.  It <Col N="199" /> removes the contour of the ancient street line.  It is the sort of road development that does not balance out with what could have been done by road improvement while still retaining the character and appeal of the area.  It does not result out of enough significance given to the modes of public transport that could be developed and the bias that could be given to public transport in central city areas.</P>
    <P>My criticism of that proposal is well known in the sense that I took the opportunity of making my views known at the oral hearing about a year ago.  I have been very closely associated with those who would like to see this proposal scaled down.  We will have another opportunity of scaling it down when the detailed road design is presented to us at City Hall presumably within a short period.  As I understand it the detailed road design in this has yet to be presented to us.</P>
    <P>I welcome this Bill for a variety of reasons not just because it sets up the need to face the issue of a transport authority which has been long sought in this city and indeed in the county of Dublin but also because it manages to deal with so many areas of traffic management improvement which have been sought over the last five years.  Many of these are important in themselves but also important because of the environmental improvements they are bound to bring with them, such as the bus ways, bollards protecting residential areas from through traffic and from the kind of abuse that we are all too well accustomed to and which residents have great difficulty in dealing with, road ramps to try and control the speed of traffic and wheel clamping in order to attempt to deal with cars and vehicles that are parked where they should not be parked.</P>
    <P>There are two particular areas that I want to mention at this Stage.  I hope that the Minister between the conclusion of the Second Stage and Committee Stage will consider the need for an amendment to the Bill in relation to one area.  There is no doubt that one of the most frustrating areas is the lack of by-laws and legislative powers affecting traffic management in <Col N="200" /> this city, and I am sure affecting many other urban areas throughout the country. I refer to the lack of control in the matter of the parking of articulated trucks and vehicles in the centre of towns, more particularly in residential areas, at night time, many of these parked in an unlit fashion, sometimes with the vehicle and the articulated component either badly lit or unlit.  It is fair to say we have experienced over the years a worrying number of fatal accidents which involved people driving into these vehicles.</P>
    <P>We also have the problem of the number of skips that are left around areas where building construction may be going on.  We have a provision in this Bill, section 41, dealing with vehicles involved in building construction sites.  There is not just the problem of vehicles but also the problem of skips which are not drawn by a vehicle.  They are deposited there and are more likely to be seen on smaller construction work than on the larger sites.  Very often these skips are left unattended for months on end, and I hope it will be possible for the Minister to move a minor amendment of his own on section 41 in relation to this area.</P>
    <P>On the parking of commercial vehicles, of these articulated trucks and lorries in residential areas particularly, I should mention that in 1980 the Dublin City Council passed a new set of by-laws which went for approval to the Department of Local Government at that time relating to the control of these articulated trucks and commercial vehicles and particularly the ones that offend me most, the vehicles that are very often parked in residential areas, either unlit or parked in an area which is badly lit.  They cause great danger to road users and pedestrians and everybody concerned, quite apart from the unaesthetic way in which they harm the amenities of an area.</P>
    <P>When this by-law was passed and brought to the Department of the Environment or sent for the seal of the Minister, the Minister declined in 1980 to have this enforced by way of a by-law, whereas he adopted a number of other by-laws that were requested at the same <Col N="201" /> time.  I have been in consultation with senior officers of the corporation, including the chief traffic engineer and others in recent weeks and I am quite satisfied that there is no area &mdash; and I speak here of the need for bollards, road ramps, wheel clamping and busways and all the other measures that are included in this Bill &mdash; which is of more concern to the vast population of this city or to the hundreds and thousands of residents' associations throughout the city than that which is the plague of every public representative who has to contend with this problem of commercial trucks and articulated vehicles parking in residential areas.  An answer has got to be found.  I would hope that because of the numbers of complaints received &mdash; and I am told in the County Borough of Dublin alone they receive a complaint once every day and it continues throughout the year.  Those are new complaints, not to talk of the numbers of repeats coming from people who are concerned about getting some law into this area of controlling these vehicles.  Particularly when there are commercial car parks available for these vehicles, encouragement could be given that these vehicles be parked elsewhere.</P>
    <P>I would hope, with the co-operation of the Minister, that an amendment which I intend presenting on Committee Stage will be considered seriously by him with a view to improving this Bill as it stands. I am talking particularly about sections 33 and 34 which deal with the whole question of parking of vehicles on public roads and the immobilisation and removal etc. of unlawfully parked vehicles. It seems to me that the section dealing with the control of commercial vehicles parking in residential areas, the articulated truck in particular, would be very much an improvement of the Bill which would thus finally emerge not just as a Bill concerned with the future road and rail development of the Greater Dublin Area but as one concerned, as it is, with so many improvements of an environmental character, which would be a prelude presumably to a future Bill which would apply to other urban areas in the country that would enhance so <Col N="202" /> many towns and cities and residential areas in particular and give much greater safety and protection to the people.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianJHillery" hpid="Professor Hillery Professor Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>In the course of this short contribution I want to refer briefly to the delayed action on a Dublin Transport Authority.  Secondly I will refer to privatisation which the Minister dealt with, and third, I will comment briefly on the area of industrial relations.</P>
      <P>The laws and framework for transport in Ireland were designed for an era when railways formed the basis of our transport system.  That era is long since past and the reality today is that CIE have a very small share of the total market for both passenger and freight services.  Privately owned road transport, including, of course, the motor car and trucks, as we can all observe, have now grown to such an extent that rail-based CIE transport continues to be in a serious financial position. Transport reforms are, therefore, necessary and an updating process is necessary.  Although we, on this side of the House, have serious reservations about certain aspects of the legislation, including the Bill before us, new legislation is both necessary and, generally speaking, welcome.</P>
      <P>I want to refer to the delayed action in relation to establishing a Dublin Transport Authority.  I first want to register my disappointment at the delayed action on the 1980 Report of the Transport Consultative Commission.  I should like to pay tribute to the Chairman of that commission.  Professor Michael MacCormac of UCD who, with his very hard working committee, produced an excellent report which received widespread acceptance.  The MacCormac report envisaged that within six months an interim transport authority would be in operation.  Here we are, however, more than five years later with this Bill before us which represents a considerably watered down version compared with what was proposed by the MacCormac Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the issue of privatisation, the Bill envisages that the Dublin Transport <Col N="203" /> Authority will take over responsibility from the Minister for Communications for the licensing of private bus operators to provide public transport services in Dublin if thought necessary.  I welcome this provision and hope that it will be addressed in a serious manner.  Public transport does not have to be publicly owned.  If the DTA see fit to license private bus operators, then there should be a mixture of profitable routes and less attractive ones.  There is no point in allowing the private sector to cream off only the most profitable routes.</P>
    <P>That having been said however, private ownership of some services would have a favourable effect on two critical factors, namely, price and service.  There is clear evidence available that privately run freight and passenger services at present are able to offer lower prices than CIE.</P>
    <P>Again, on the question of service, there are indications that job satisfaction and morale are lacking among CIE employees.  As far as Dublin City buses are concerned, one cannot help but get the impression that some busmen are not really interested in business.  Private operators could not afford such a luxurious attitude.  If properly monitored, private bus services should lead to a more efficient and cheaper service and the bigger market share that would be generated would mean that jobs would not be in doubt.  Given the background that there is a shortage of State funds in this country as in most west European democracies, several countries abroad are moving towards privatisation of public transport and Germany and the Netherlands readily come to mind in this respect.</P>
    <P>I now want to turn to industrial relations in CIE about which the Minister in his opening speech expressed considerable concern.  In his speech, the Minister expressed the view that the new organisation structure for CIE &mdash; that is the other Bill before the House at present &mdash; will enable any management defects in the industrial relations area to be remedied. I hope he is proved right.  The reform of <Col N="204" /> industrial relations is not solely a structural problem.  One yardstick for the measurement of the industrial relations problem in CIE is the number of working days lost.</P>
    <P>The Department of Industrial Relations in UCD, with which I am personally associated, has been engaged in a study of strike activity in Ireland from 1960 onwards.  We have some hard statistics on this.  Among other things, the study shows that in the 25 year period 1960 to 1984, 94 strikes took place in CIE which accounted for 857,200 working days lost. The Minister in his speech drew particular attention to the problem of unofficial strikes in CIE.  Our strike data at UCD showed that of the 94 strikes in the 25 year period, almost two-thirds were unofficial strikes.  Dublin city bus services accounted for most of the working days lost.</P>
    <P>The railways and the provincial road transport services were rarely involved in the strike activity.  While both management and unions have a joint responsibility to foster good industrial relations, management have a particular responsibility for their creation and maintenance. CIE are in need of a greater commercial orientation and measures must be adopted to improve motivation and performance.</P>
    <P>One of the more positive developments that has occurred in CIE in the recent past is the DART service.  Earlier I made reference to the importance of the quality of service.  I am happy to record that DART is providing an excellent service in every sense of the word. It must, of course, attract many more passengers if it is to make a profit.  It must be clearly understood by all who work in CIE that passengers, that is, customers, are vital to the progress of the company. If the company, including DART, is sufficiently sensitive to customer needs, then the necessary increase in the number of customers using DART will be facilitated. The overall impression is that DART is giving a high quality service and it has boosted the image of CIE.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I would like to raise one question to which I hope the Minister will <Col N="205" /> reply when responding to Second Stage. Is it still proposed to have an integrated rail transport centre in the Temple Bar area in Dublin city?</P>
    <Speaker pid="TedNealon" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Communications (Mr. Nealon) Minister of State at the Department of Communications (Mr. Nealon)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Communications (Mr. Nealon)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has asked me to thank all the Senators who have contributed here in the earlier part of the debate.  I should like to express my own thanks for the excellent contributions this afternoon. The Minister is very much heartened by the support for the concerted efforts to remedy the road traffic and transport problems of our capital city.  As we know, a great effort has already been made by the Dublin Transportation Task Force.  I know that this will be continued by the Dublin Transport Authority who will pursue this with renewed vigour and vision.  This is the work that the task force has begun and it will be continued by the Dublin Transport Authority.</P>
      <P>Some Senators suggested that the Authority will not have enough power to undertake its vital tasks.  I think, &ldquo;no teeth&rdquo; was the manner in which Senator Mark Killilea expressed the reservation that he had about the Authority in this respect.  The Minister is satisfied that the Authority have sufficient power under this Bill to start with.  With dedication they will achieve very worthwhile results and will be able to achieve them quickly. From all the contributions we have heard in this House the speed with which these results will be attained is of great importance. It is not, of course, as important as the end results themselves but ranks with them.  The Minister will be monitoring the Authority's performance very carefully from the start and if in the light of their performance it would be desirable to give them extra functions, then section 9 of the Bill will provide the means for doing this.  While the detailed examination of the provisions of the Bill will arise on Committee Stage, I would like to take the opportunity to reply to a number of points raised during the Second Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards CIE's proposals for rapid rail, Senator Killilea asked if the Minister had discussed these proposals with CIE. <Col N="206" /> He has not.  These proposals were made in a report commissioned by CIE and completed in 1975.  They involve the provision of electric rapid rail transit links to the Tallaght Ronanstown/Clondalkin area linked by an underground city centre network to the electrified Howth-Bray line.  These proposals have been discussed at official level over the years since then.  It is quite a while ago, 1975.</P>
    <P>CIE's stance in relation to the proposals centred on the availability of resources &mdash; some hundreds of millions of pounds would be involved in funding the proposals &mdash; rather than an adequate appraisal of the need for rapid rail and its full capital and operating costs or considering lower cost alternatives, like busways.  It will be for the Dublin Transport Authority to comprehensively examine public transport needs for the Dublin area and to make their recommendation to the Minister as to the nature and extent of the new provision to be made, whether road, rail or a combination of both.</P>
    <P>Senator Ferris in his contribution referred to the underground railway system in Boston and the recently completed one in Brussels.  All of us who have travelled on the one in Brussels &mdash; and it is modern by comparison with the better known and more famous undergrounds &mdash; will have recognised the great advantage that exists in this particular underground in movement around that city. Senator Ferris urged that consideration be given to such a system for Dublin.  He rightly referred to the high capital cost of such systems and, of course, many of these projects all come back in the final analysis to the cost factor, not to desirability. Most of these would be desired and welcomed by everybody but it comes back to the cost involved and the cost benefit and looking at all the alternatives to find out which is the more appropriate both as regards the service it would give in the final analysis and the cost to put it there.</P>
    <P>The question of an underground system such as that referred to by Senator Ferris or an extension of DART needs to be considered in the context of overall <Col N="207" /> public transport needs whether by road or rail and, of course, in the final analysis, the available resources.  This will be a function of the DTA.  Its immediate priority will be to review public transport needs in the Tallaght and other developing areas to the west of the city, as the Minister emphasised in his opening remarks in the House here on 28 May. I think everyone accepts that a chaotic situation exists at the moment for people seeking to move in and out of the city and indeed around the city from Tallaght and those highly-populated developing areas to the west of the city.</P>
    <P>A number of Senators raised the question of how it is intended that the Dublin Transport Authority will relate to CIE's Dublin bus and suburban rail services. The main purpose of establishing the Dublin Transport Authority is to radically improve the planning and operation of road and rail transport and the management of road traffic in the Dublin area.  Improvement of CIE's Dublin transport operations is a key element of that remit.  Section 8 (c) of the Bill makes it a function of the Dublin Transport Authority to promote the greater use of public transport in the Dublin area. Having regard to overall public transport needs of that area the Dublin Transport Authority will specify the requirements that CIE should try to meet in the provision of their Dublin bus and suburban rail services within the limits of the Exchequer subvention decided by the Government.  Before CIE can vary their fares for such services, they will require the approval of the Authority with ministerial consent so as not to undermine Government decision on the overall CIE subvention which has been working very well with considerable improvement in it in this respect in recent years.</P>
    <P>The Dublin Transport Authority, in close co-operation with CIE will be endeavouring to foster greater and better usage of the expensive public transport resources entrusted to CIE through the elimination of unnecessary duplication between road and rail services, provision of proper feeder services for DART, <Col N="208" /> tailoring or devising services to meet transport needs of major new areas of population and so on.  The Dublin Transport Authority will have the responsibility to complement CIE's operations and to arrange adequate taxi services with scope for appropriate private bus services so that overall, they will be properly co-ordinated with a varied public transport service in the Dublin area giving the best possible service to the citizens and again, all the time taking into consideration the cost factor.</P>
    <P>Senator Ferris referred to a general provision for State bodies whereby persons who are nominated for election to the Seanad, even against their will, cease to be members of those bodies on such nomination although they may not, in fact, be elected to the Seanad.  I am glad to inform the House that the Bill was amended by the Dáil to ensure that parliamentary candidates <i>per se</i> will not be required to give up their membership of the DTA board or to be seconded if members of the DTA staff, until they take their seat in the Dáil, Seanad or European Parliament as the case may be. I know that an objection could naturally arise if a person had to give up the seat on the DTA board as such by being nominated for the Seanad.  I am sure that any Member who successfully gets into the House will be rather pleased to give up the seat on the DTA board, important and all as that will be for the future development of transport in the capital city.</P>
    <P>Section 16 of the Bill deals with DTA staff and paragraph 4 of the Schedule to the Bill deals with members of the DTA board.  Senator FitzGerald drew attention to the fact that the only form of parking restraints, if you like, other than parking in an illegal fashion, was parking, meters in the Dublin area whereas Dún Laoghaire has had disc parking recently introduced and Cork has a similar system which has been successfully operated for a good period.  The Dublin Transportation Task Force is considering this whole question at the moment.  I understand that a pilot Pay and Display scheme as operated elsewhere will be introduced in <Col N="209" /> the Dublin area shortly and I understand that part of Senator FitzGerald's own area of Dublin South East &mdash; the Ballsbridge area &mdash; may in fact be the area in which the pilot system will be tried out.</P>
    <P>Apart from what the Dublin Transport Authority can do under this Bill there is much that the local authorities can do, whether as road authorities or as planning authorities, in the ordinary way to avoid unnecessary congestion and disruption to road traffic.  It is very much to be hoped that they will keep an eye on this aspect, not least the cost effectiveness element. Unfortunately as far as planning public transport is concerned, development plans under the Local Government (Planning and Development) Acts do not generally give adequate coverage to public transport provision.  Senator Fitzsimons referred to this particular aspect. It is for this reason that section 24 of the Bill specifically empowers the Dublin Transport Authority to have an input into local authority development plans and it requires the local authorities to respond to the Dublin Transport Authority.  As it is, CIE have little opportunity for making an effective input into the physical planning process.</P>
    <P>Section 23 &mdash; these are points again raised by Senator Fitzsimons &mdash; gives the Authority the entree to the Minister for Communications enabling them to make recommendations to him as regards what public transport facilities are needed from time to time.  Taken together, sections 23 to 26 make it clear that the Dublin Transport Authority have a role in the planning process under the Planning Acts and in the provision of the transport infrastructure.  Referring back again to what Senator Killilea said about the lack of teeth, which I think was unfounded, this is another area in which it can be seen that the Dublin Transport Authority will have real power and influence and teeth, to use the terminology used by Senator Killilea.</P>
    <P>Public investment in roads and public transport needs to be assessed in a co-ordinated way because of the need to provide a comprehensive solution to the transport problems in the Dublin city <Col N="210" /> area.  Lack of co-ordination has been a source of grievance down the years as best exemplified by one particular authority tearing up the roads, doing a lovely job and returning it to its normal situation, when it is followed in a month or a week later by some other authority.</P>
    <P>Section 21 of the Bill in particular gives power in this particular area.  Under that section the Authority will be obliged to assess the position and make recommendations to the Ministers for Communications and the Environment, having regard to the available resources and the Government's financial position.</P>
    <P>Section 90 of the Road Traffic Act provides power for control of parking on public roads via the by-laws that require the approval of the Minister for the Environment.  This is <i>apropos</i> of the point raised by Senator FitzGerald on which he announced his intention of perhaps introducing an amendment on Committee Stage of the Bill.</P>
    <P>Section 90 of the Road Traffic Act provides power for the control of parking on public roadways and this is done via the by-laws of the various local authorities which in turn require the approval of the Minister for the Environment.  The reasons such by-laws have not been made use of should be made known and perhaps it might be possible for Senator FitzGerald to explain the precise difficulties that arise in the Dublin area.  I understand the problem as far as skips are concerned.  I do appreciate the danger they can be, unlighted and in particular at night, but I understand that the Garda are particularly vigilant in this area as far as the public roads are concerned.</P>
    <P>I also fully accept the point Senator FitzGerald made about the large articulated trucks that are being parked in residential areas overnight or for, perhaps, two or three days and there is a difficulty there.  We certainly will be pleased to see what is incorporated in Senator FitzGerald's amendment.  The on-the-spot fines of course have been used in many instances and are one of the methods to combat illegal parking with the large number of traffic wardens in use, but they have not succeeded in making a worthwhile impact <Col N="211" /> on illegal parking.  That is the reality of the situation.  The effectiveness of the on-the-spot fines system and associated follow-up where fines are not paid within the required 21 days is currently being assessed at interdepartmental level.  It is hoped that improvements will manifest themselves.  Back-up physical measures such as tow-away and wheel-clamping measures were referred to by a number of Senators and these measures need to be resorted to on a widescale basis. Section 34 of the Bill makes the first provision for wheel-clamping in Irish law. The UK experience of some years proves how effective this can be.</P>
    <P>Senator Hillery asked a specific question and I will communicate with him later.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday, 5 June 1986.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Domicile and Recognition of Foreign" RHead="Divorces Bill, 1985: Second Stage">
    <Title>Domicile and Recognition of Foreign Divorces Bill, 1985: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill now be read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="NualaFennell" hpid="Minister of State of the Department of Justice (Mrs. Fennell) Minister of State of the Department of Justice (Mrs. Fennell)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State of the Department of Justice (Mrs. Fennell)</NameTxt>
      <P>The main purpose of the Bill is simple.  It is to amend the law relating to domicile by abolishing what is called the domicile of dependency of married women.  That is a reference to the discriminatory rule under which the domicile of a married woman is deemed to be the same as that of her husband.  The principal provision in the Bill would enable her to have an independent domicile.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some changes in the rules relating to the domicile of minor children and the recognition of foreign divorces are also proposed in the Bill.  These are in the main consequential on the change in the law as to the domicile of a married woman.  As I will explain later, once the domicile of dependency of married women is abolished, some changes must be made in the rules as to the domicile of minor children and the rules as to the <Col N="212" /> recognition of foreign divorces and that is why these matters are dealt with in the Bill.</P>
    <P>But I want to stress from the outset &mdash; in case the fact should be lost sight of during the debate on the Bill &mdash; that the Bill is a minimum measure only, confined to dealing with limited aspects of the law of domicile where changes are needed as a result of the main provision in the Bill that is to say, the abolition of the wife's domicile of dependency.  In particular, these consequential provisions should not be seen as major proposals for reform of the law of domicile.  That is a matter which is being considered separately in the context of recommendations which the Law Reform Commission have made in that general area of the law.</P>
    <P>Domicile is a legal concept that arises only in certain cases, all of these being cases which have a foreign element.  The concept of domicile is an irrelevance, for most people, even if they are involved in some legal dispute.  In the great majority of cases that come before our courts there is no foreign element involved and the court simply applies the ordinary internal Irish law.  Accordingly, the proposals in this Bill have no practical implications for the vast majority of people in the State. For example, the question whether a person is guilty of an offence, or is liable to pay damages for negligence, if they are involved in a road accident in Dublin depends solely on Irish law, irrespective of where they come from or whether they are Irish citizens or not.  But if, for example, a man who is an Irish citizen and married to an Englishwoman leaves his wife and goes to live in France, gets a divorce from his wife and marries a Frenchwoman, the question of domicile could be important.  For instance, if he dies leaving property in Ireland to his second wife, the Irish courts may have to decide whether his French divorce and remarriage should be recognised as valid in Irish law, to say nothing of the liability of his estate to taxation in Ireland.  Part of the importance of domicile is that for some purposes, especially those of family law, the Irish court, when it has to decide these questions, has to apply the law of <Col N="213" /> the country in which the person concerned was domiciled at the material time.</P>
    <P>Although it is generally true, in countries such as our own which have the common law system, that questions of this kind are decided according to the law of the domicile of the person concerned, in many other countries the test used is that of nationality and not domicile. Another test, habitual residence, is being increasingly used as the connecting factor in specific areas of the law, especially in connection with recent international agreements.</P>
    <P>As a general proposition, it is true to say that a person is regarded by the law as being domiciled in the country in which they have their permanent home.  Every person acquires a domicile of origin at birth, usually that of their father.  That domicile of origin remains unless or until they acquire a different domicile of choice by going to reside in another country with the intention of residing there indefinitely.  If they subsequently cease to reside in that country without acquiring a domicile of choice in another country, the law is that their domicile of origin revives.  These rules, however, do not apply in relation to married women.  A married woman is deemed by law to have the domicile of her husband.  For convenience, I have made these statements without qualification, but it should be understood that there may well be a question mark, to put it no stronger, whether such a rule, or at all events some applications of it, could have survived the enactment of the Constitution.  That issue has not been tested before the courts.</P>
    <P>The concept of domicile has been criticised in a number of respects.  The central importance of intention in establishing domicile has been said to make for difficulty and uncertainty.  The revival of the domicile of origin can sometimes produce strange results.  However, the feature which has been most criticised in recent years is the rule that denies to a married woman the ability to determine by her own actions and intentions where her domicile should be.  The present rule in relation to married women means that <Col N="214" /> even if the couple are separated and even if the wife has never lived in her husband's country of domicile &mdash; which may be different from the country in which the couple have been married and have lived together before separating &mdash; and even if she has no intention of ever living in her husband's country of origin, she will be fixed with a domicile in that country. In these circumsances she can find that important legal questions affecting her will fall to be regulated by the laws of a country which is totally foreign to her.</P>
    <P>It is unnecessary to labour the point that the rule is clearly discriminatory.  If it may have been appropriate in other times &mdash; though I doubt it &mdash; few, I think, would argue that it is a rule that should remain part of our law.</P>
    <P>The abolition of the domicile of dependency of married women is achieved by section 1 of the Bill.  Under that provision a married woman will have an independent domicile which will be ascertained by reference to the same factors as apply to other persons generally.</P>
    <P>The enactment of this section will have significance in relation to a number of international conventions.  There are a number of these conventions which prohibit discrimination between men and women in respect of various matters, including domicile.  Among these agreements are the United Nations Convention on the Elimination of all forms of Discrimination against Women, the United Nations Covenant on Civil and Political Rights and the Seventh Protocol to the European Convention on Human Rights.  Our existing law on domicile has been one obstacle in the way of ratification of these agreements.  This Bill, when enacted, will remove that obstacle.</P>
    <P>The other provisions in the Bill dealing with domicile are, broadly speaking, consequential on the main provisions in section 1 and, as I have mentioned already, are strictly limited to that context. They do not, for example, purport to introduce general reforms in the law of domicile, for example, in the law as to the domicile of minors.</P>
    <P>Section 2 provides that the Bill will not <Col N="215" /> have retrospective effect.  In other words, any questions arising in future as to what domicile a woman had at any given time before the commencement of the Act will be decided according to the law in force at that given time.  As a matter of principle, that is as it should be, since it is impossible to know what injustices might arise from any attempt to change people's domiciles retrospectively.  For example, the question whether a will is valid, or whether a marriage or a divorce is recognised in Irish law, may depend on where the person or persons concerned was or were domiciled at the material time; so clearly the Bill should not be so framed as to make invalid something which was valid when it was done or <i>vice versa.</i>  In relation to the recognition of foreign divorces, I should perhaps mention at this point &mdash; because the matter was raised when the Bill was debated in the Dáil &mdash; one particular result of the provision in section 2 that the domicile married women had before the commencement of the Act shall not be affected by the Act.  After the commencement of the Act a divorce granted in a foreign country will, as I shall explain, be recognised in Irish law under section 5 if either spouse was domiciled in that country at the time when the divorce proceedings were commenced.  This rule will apply only to divorces granted after the commencement of the Act.  But even in the case of such a divorce it will be necessary that a spouse should have been domiciled in the country in question at the time of the commencement of the proceedings.  Therefore, if, for example, a married woman, living abroad but having her husband's Irish domicile, obtains a foreign divorce in proceedings that she initiated before the commencement of the Act, and the divorce decree is granted after the Act's commencement, it will not qualify for recognition under section 5 because, as a result of the provision in section 2, no independent domicile will be conferred retrospectively on the married woman so as to affect anything she may have done before this Act becomes law.</P>
    <P>On the other hand if it is necessary to <Col N="216" /> determine what domicile a woman has at any time after the commencement of the Act, section 3 provides that the matter will be determined as if the legislation had always been in force.  This means that if the domicile of a woman who is married at the time the Act comes into force falls to be determined in relation to any date in the future, the new rule contained in the Bill will be applied in considering her history and circumstances without reference to any concept of dependency of domicile.  To put it another way, her domicile will be determined as if there never had been a domicile of dependency of married women.</P>
    <P>Section 4 is necessary because the present rule in relation to the domicile of minor children of a married couple is that the child takes the domicile of their father.  This section provides new rules for the situation where the spouses are living apart.  If the child has their home with the mother, and has no home with the father, the child will take the domicile of the mother.  If later on the child ceases to have a home with her they will continue to have her domicile unless and until they have a home with their father. If the mother is dead, the domicile of the child will be the domicile the mother had at the time of her death if at that time the child had that domicile by reason of having or having had their home with their mother, as I have just mentioned, and if they have not since had a home with their father.</P>
    <P>Where the spouses are living together, the child will continue to have the domicile of their father.  Since normally both spouses who are living together will have the same domicile, this is not of special practical significance.  It might be argued that, ideally, there should be a new rule making no distinction between the spouses.  But there would be practical difficulties.  It would be difficult to devise a rule which could operate satisfactorily in all the different circumstances that can be envisaged.  If the spouses, although living together, have different domiciles, it would be hard to see what logical basis there would be for deciding whether the <Col N="217" /> child should have the domicile of one parent rather than the other, and the result would be that the child would have to be assigned a domicile separate from either of the parents on whom they are dependent and that would be undesirable. None of these solutions is wholly satisfactory and the Bill, therefore, proceeds on the basis of preserving the <i>status quo</i> in this very limited area, unless and until some better solution is found.</P>
    <P>This is a matter which will be considered again in the context of decisions that will be needed on the recommendations of the Law Reform Commission on reform of the law of domicile.  The commission recommended that the concept of domicile should be replaced by habitual residence as the general connecting factor for the purpose of private international law.  Any general reforms in this area might involve a recasting of the law of domicile as it affects minors. So, for the time being, we are proposing minimum changes in the present law relating to the domicile of minors.</P>
    <P>Section 5 of the Bill deals with the recognition of foreign divorces.  In the main the section is consequential on the change made in section 1, but I would like to explain why it is necessary to deal with the matter of foreign divorces in this Bill.</P>
    <P>At present domicile is a central factor in the law relating to recognition of foreign divorces.  The present law, as interpreted by the courts, is that a divorce obtained in a foreign country will be recognised if both spouses were domiciled in that country at the date of institution of the foreign proceedings.  The existing rule does not &mdash; and has had no need to &mdash; take account of the possibility that husband and wife would have different domiciles.  Because, under existing law, a married woman has the same domicile as her husband, the rule means that a divorce is recognised in Irish law if it was granted in the country where the husband was domiciled at the date of the institution of the proceedings.  That, at all events, is the effect of the rules as commonly stated, but it is right to mention that in the course of a judgment <Col N="218" /> given by him in the Supreme Court Mr. Justice Walsh remarked that it is possible &ldquo;that some day (the rule) may be challenged on Constitutional grounds in a case in which the wife had never physically left her domicile of origin while her deserting husband may have established a domicile in another jurisdiction&rdquo;.  However, at present and pending any such challenge the law has operated on the basis that the spouses have a common domicile in all circumstances, and clearly the Bill must proceed on that basis.</P>
    <P>In the absence of specific legislative provisions setting out new rules for recognition of foreign divorces, there would be no way, short of expensive and perhaps long-drawn-out litigation, of establishing how an existing rule linked to the concept of a single domicile for the two parties would be applied or adapted in circumstances where husband and wife had separate domiciles, as they may have once the legislation is in force.  On one view a foreign divorce would be recognised here only where both spouses were domiciled in the foreign country.  On another view, a lacuna would be left in the law because the present rule, being based on the concept of a common domicile for both parties, could not be regarded as having any application in a situation where that was no longer the case.  It is to deal with that problem that the provision in section 5(1) is proposed.  Section 5(1) provides that in future a divorce will be recognised if it is granted in the country where either spouse was domiciled.  By virtue of section 1(7) the relevant date will be that of institution of the divorce proceedings.</P>
    <P>I would like to stress that, once the domicile of dependency of married women is abolished, some change, either increasing or decreasing the grounds of recognition is inevitable in the rules of recognition of foreign divorces.  It is simply not possible to preserve the <i>status quo</i> in that new situation.</P>
    <P>At first glance it might appear that section 5(1) will greatly increase the incidence of recognition of foreign divorces. Inevitably there will be some increase, but for the following reasons I think the increase will not be great.  First, domicile <Col N="219" /> is not something that is casually changed. A person does not become domiciled in another country merely by moving there for a short period.  To acquire a new domicile, they will need, on or after going to the other country, to have the intention to make that country his or her permanent home in the sense of intending to reside there for the indefinite future. A court here would have to be satisfied to that effect if the issue arose.  Divorces which are obtained on the strength merely of a brief period of residence in another country are not recognised under the existing Irish law and will not be recognised under the Bill when in force. The strength of domicile as a connecting factor means, in practical terms, that a person hitherto domiciled here must virtually have severed their connection with this country before a divorce will be recognised here, and where that happens it seems right that the divorce validly obtained under the laws of the foreign country should be recognised here in accordance with the established principles of private international law which are accepted and acted on in our legal system.</P>
    <P>Subsection (4) of section 56 states what may already be part of our existing law. There is a question as to whether the existing rule that a divorce is recognised here if it is granted in the country of domicile of the spouses is complemented by a further rule.  This is a rule laid down in 1906 in the English case of Armitage v. A.G. to the effect that a divorce will also be recognised if, while not granted in the country of the common domicile, it would be recognised by the law of that country.  The rationale of the rule is that if a change in the status of the spouses has been accepted in the country where they are domiciled it should be accepted in other countries.  The reason a doubt may exist as to whether this rule is part of our law is simply because the specific point has never come before our courts for decision.  Subsection (4) provides for a similar rule adapted to the new system under which the spouses may have different domiciles.  It provides that, if <Col N="220" /> neither spouse is domiciled in the State, a divorce obtained in a foreign country will be recognised if, though neither spouse is domiciled in that country, the divorce is recognised under the law of the country where both the spouses are domiciled or (in a case where they are domiciled in different countries) if it is recognised under the laws of both these countries.  The practical effect of this provision is likely to be small.</P>
    <P>Subsection (3) of section 5 is a special provision relating to neighbouring jurisdictions and takes account of a particular feature of British law.  The jurisdictions mentioned in that subsection are different &ldquo;countries&rdquo; for the purposes of private international law, but under British law a divorce obtained in any of them is automatically recognised in all the other jurisdictions mentioned.  It seems right to provide, as subsection (3) does, that such a divorce will also be recognised here as long as one of the spouses is domiciled in any one of these jurisdictions. If, for example, the spouses were domiciled in, say, England, and a divorce were obtained in Scotland, that divorce is of course recognised automatically in England and it would be artificial to refuse recognition here.  A secondary but valid reason for what is proposed is that, as between Scotland and England, for example, it would be artificial to require our courts to decide whether the spouses were domiciled in the one rather than the other.  At this point I should apologise for a slip in paragraph 13 of the explantory memorandum.  In the third last line &ldquo;that subsection&rdquo; should read &ldquo;subsection (3)&rdquo;&mdash; the subsection listing the British territories.</P>
    <P>There are a number of States which comprise within them different territories with different systems of law in relation to divorce and which do not themselves have automatic recognition of each other's divorces.  For example divorces granted in one of the United States are not automatically recognised throughout the other states.  In relation to such countries which in matters of divorce have different systems applying in the different territorial units, each such unit will be <Col N="221" /> treated as a separate country as a result of subsection (2).  This reflects the ordinary rule of private international law which treats a territorial unit with its own system of law as a separate country.  As a result of subsection (2) the different states of the USA will each be regarded as a separate country.  A divorce obtained in one state of the United States will be recognised under subsection (1) if one of the spouses is domiciled in that state, and it will be recognised under subsection (4) if, while not granted in that state, the divorce would be recognised in the state or states in which the spouses are domiciled.</P>
    <P>Canada and Australia are composite states which have the same law in relation to divorce applying throughout all the constituent territorial units of these states.  Because of that, the different territorial units will not be treated as separate countries under subsection (2). Accordingly, a divorce obtained in any part of Canada or Australia by a spouse domiciled in any other part will be recognised.</P>
    <P>I should mention two other provisions of section 5.  Subsection (5) provides that the new rules for recognition will apply only to divorces granted after the commencement of the Act.  It would be clearly undesirable to make the new rules retrospective because the result would be to change a person's matrimonial status retrospectively.  I mentioned this point earlier in relation to section 2.</P>
    <P>Subsection (6) is a saving provision for the power of the Irish courts to refuse on grounds unrelated to domicile to recognise a foreign divorce.  For example, the court may refuse recognition if a spouse is divorced without having been given proper notice of the proceedings.</P>
    <P>In regard to the matters covered by the Bill Senators will be aware that the Law Reform Commission have published two relevant reports.  In their Report on Domicile and Habitual Residence as Connecting Factors in the Conflict of Laws they recommended, as I mentioned in relation to section 4, that habitual residence should replace domicile as a general connecting factor.  In their Report <Col N="222" /> on Recognition of Foreign Divorces and Legal Separations they proposed wide-ranging changes in the rules relating to recognition of foreign divorces based mainly on the concept of habitual residence as a connecting factor.</P>
    <P>As I have mentioned already the basic purpose of the present Bill is to get rid of the discriminatory rule under which a married woman is deemed to have the same domicile as her husband.  As I have explained also the Bill deals with the rules of recognition of foreign divorces only because some change in those rules is inevitable once the domicile of dependency is abolished.  In fact the changes made in this area are in the main minimum changes to enable that desirable change in the law of domicile to be effected.</P>
    <P>It is the Government's view that the time is not ripe for any wide-ranging review of the rules of recognition of foreign divorces.  The question to what extent we should recognise foreign divorces is one which has an obvious link with internal policy in regard to divorce.  The whole policy of the law in this matter will depend on the outcome of the current proposal to amend the Constitution in relation to the matter of divorce.  In that context it seems to the Government inappropriate to embark on changes in the rules of recognition beyond those changes that it is necessary to make in order to achieve the main purpose of this Bill.  Any decision to change from domicile to habitual residence as the test for recognition of foreign divorces would mean that our rules of recognition would have to be recast to take account of habitual residence, and, since that concept is different in very important respects from domicile, we would have to embark on a complete rethinking of our attitude to recognition.  As I have indicated the Government do not consider that the present time is opportune for such an exercise.</P>
    <P>For that reason, I would emphasise very strongly that the proposals in the Bill do not mean that the recommendations of the Law Reform Commission have either been forgotten or been <Col N="223" /> rejected.  Because of the other circumstances I have mentioned, the Government regard them as matters that should be left aside for the moment.  The matters covered in their reports will be taken up later.</P>
    <P>Finally, I think I should refer to the fact that there is no provision in the Bill that would enable a court to make ancillary orders relating to such matters as maintenance and matrimonial property, where a foreign divorce is recognised here.  The Bill is a minimum measure only, for the reasons already explained. The inclusion of provisions dealing with the financial and property rights and obligations of former spouses whose marriages have been dissolved by a foreign court would represent a substantial extension of the measure that would be outside the scope of the Bill.  This is not to say that there may not be a need to give special protection to spouses with close connections with this country who have been divorced abroad, in relation to such matters as maintenance, the family home or barring orders.  But the question of making any such provisions, or their nature, can hardly be isolated from similar questions of policy that arise in connection with our own divorce jurisdiction, if introduced.</P>
    <P>Accordingly, there are good reasons for awaiting the outcome of the debate on the domestic divorce issue before considering whether to make provision for ancillary matters in relation to former spouses whose foreign divorces are recognised here.</P>
    <P>I can give an assurance that the matter will be considered in the context of legislative proposals that would be necessary if the forthcoming referendum is carried, or otherwise in connection with an appropriate family law measure.</P>
    <P>I commend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CatherineMcGuinness" hpid="Mrs. McGuinness Mrs. McGuinness">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. McGuinness</NameTxt>
      <P>I very much welcome this Bill.  As the Minister of State knows I have raised in this House before now the necessity for abolishing the domicile of dependency of married women.  I am extremely glad that the <Col N="224" /> Minister is here before us today to introduce this Bill.  I know it is something to which she has had a commitment for a considerable length of time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to refer to a few things which arise from the Minister's speech. It is an important factor that we still depend on this issue of domicile not just in the recognition of foreign divorces but in many of our ways of dealing with foreign decrees of other types.  I commend to the Government that they should have another look at this in the light of the proposals made by the Law Reform Commission.  I know the Minister of State has said they are doing this but I think it is an important issue.  It affects our legal relations with other countries in Europe who have different styles of recognition and our ability to accede to various international conventions on private international law where habitual residence is used as a connecting factor.  Certainly the law of domicile is one which is well recognised as being a very complex one, the establishment of a person's domicile being a sort of mixed question of law and fact.  In the obvious case there is no question about where a person's domicile is but many cases are not particularly obvious and one must remember that, for instance, the fact that you are born in Ireland does not necessarily mean that your domicile is Irish because you take the domicile of origin of your father at the time of your birth.  Despite the fact that you are born in Ireland and you are an Irish citizen it may so happen that your father had a different domicile at the time of your birth and therefore you have not got an Irish domicile.  There are lots of difficult, knotty points that there is no point in going into at this stage which arise in connection with the law of domicile. For instance, the Minister referred in her speech to a person domiciled abroad leaving property in Ireland to his second wife.  The question would arise, to begin with, whether it was real property or personal property, whether it was immovable land property or money or something like that.  One rule would apply to landed property and another rule would apply to personal property.  It does <Col N="225" /> seem to me to be a ridiculous situation where a wife who was deserted by her husband here and had never lived out of Ireland could find herself in the position that if she died her personal property could fall to be distributed under the succession law of a country where she has never lived simply because her husband had acquired domicile there.  Naturally these situations may not arise all that often but travel from one country to another and mobility from one jurisdiction to another is increasing all the time and these kinds of problems are going to arise more and more.  I am all the more glad that a married woman under this Bill will now establish her own domicile and that she will not get involved in this kind of situation.</P>
    <P>I would also agree that the revival of the domicile of origin can sometimes produce very strange results as the Minister has said.  I would suggest that possibly when we are looking at the law of domicile in this Bill it might be a good idea to provide that the domicile of origin would not revive, as it were, between domiciles of choice.  If you have already acquired a domicile of choice in, say, England and then you move to France and you have an in between period where your domicile of origin revives, my own feeling is that it would make more sense if you stuck to the former domicile of choice until you had acquired a new domicile of choice.  I would hope to deal with this in more detail at Committee Stage.  Certainly the revival of the domicile of origin can sometimes make for very strange results as has been stated by the Minister.  Again there is this query which was raised by Mr. Justice Walsh in one of his judgments where he suggests it is possible that the dependent domicile of a married woman is unconstitutional.  This is one of these queries that has been left hanging because there has never been a suitable case brought before the courts where it would be decided as to whether this was the position or it was not.  This Bill will rectify this position.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to the case of Armitage and the Attorney General and to the recognition of divorces which <Col N="226" /> would be recognised by the law of domicile of the parties.  This is an area which is in doubt so far as decisions have been made so far.  It is a question which to my knowledge was likely to arise in one or two cases but unfortunately the cases never got as far as coming to hearing. There has never been a decision in the Irish courts as to whether Armitage and the Attorney General applies in Irish law. It is a good thing to have that decided here and to let us know what the situation is.</P>
    <P>It is important to realise when we are talking about domicile as a ground for recognising foreign divorces that we are talking in terms of domicile as defined in Irish law.  Our law of domicile, is a fairly strict law of domicile, because there are, for instance, certain states in America which will accept a person as being domiciled in that state if they have only been resident there a very short time.  They do not require the same strict rules of domicile as we do.  Up to now the courts have always accepted that it was the Irish law of domicile we were talking about.  It is clear from what the Minister has said in her speech that this is what is referred to in the Bill, that when we talk about domicile as a connecting factor in these cases we are talking about the Irish law of domicile as opposed to the law of domicile in the country where the divorce is granted.</P>
    <P>During the Minister's speech she referred to subsection (6) of section 5 where there is a saving provision for the power of the Irish courts to refuse on grounds unrelated to domicile a foreign divorce.  For example, the court may refuse recognition that the spouse is divorced without having been given proper notice of the proceeding.  One can accept an obvious thing like that but there has been a certain amount of uncertainty in these kind of cases as to whether the court can actually look behind the decree of divorce.  If you have a decree based on some kind of ground which would have no relation at all to Irish law or anything that we might think sensible can you look behind that decree?  The accepted view would be that you do not look behind that <Col N="227" /> decree.  The matter of notice is slightly outside that.  If the decree would be recognised under the domicile rules, then you do not look any further.</P>
    <P>There are a couple of situations: for instance, in the case of Gaffney and Gaffney which is the one in which the judgment of Mr. Justice Brian Walsh occurred, it was clear that the English court that granted the divorce had no jurisdiction whatsoever to grant it and therefore, the Irish court looked at the jurisdiction and said: &ldquo;We cannot recognise this, that, among other reasons&rdquo;. There was a more recent judgment by Mr. Justice Barrington in which he looked behind the decree to some extent of a French divorce.  He looked behind it and saw that it was totally collusive on the part of the parties, that the parties themselves got together and lied to the court about the grounds of the divorce. He refused to recognise the divorce more or less on those grounds even though the domicile rule was fulfilled.  We need to be very clear about this.  How far under subsection (6) are we going to allow a court to go behind the actual decree which is given?  Do we recognise it if it is given by the court where either party is domiciled, or are we going to look at it to see if there is real justification, or to see if the people are lying to the court? Perhaps the Minister would comment on this in her reply or later on Committee Stage if she wants to have time to think about it.</P>
    <P>In the final part of the Minister's speech she points out the reason why there is no provision to make ancillary orders relating to maintenance in matrimonial property and so on.  While I accept that she has reason in what she has said, at the same time I am worried about this.  There is again a grey area about how much is recognised and how much is not recognised. Since the case of Mayo-Penott v. Mayo-Penott, the general rule has been that ancillary orders made in pursuit of a divorce abroad which would not be recognised here or in pursuit of a divorce abroad would not necessarily be enforced by the Irish courts, there is an exception <Col N="228" /> to this in another case where it was purely a matter of maintenance.  That English decree was enforced because it was a matter of maintenance only and we would have had a maintenance order in similar circumstances.  Nevertheless it is a fairly messy situation.</P>
    <P>A few years ago a situation arose where women who had been divorced by husbands who had gone to England and established domicle had problems about maintaining their entitlements to social welfare allowances, such as the deserted wife's allowance because the Department of Social Welfare maintained that they were no longer spouses.  This matter was met and arranged and they now get the deserted wife's allowance.  It is a confused situation and I would not like it to happen that there would be a hiatus because even if the referendum is passed there would still be a considerable amount of time before the enactment of divorce legislation which would include all the necessary protections that will be demanded by the amendment to the Constitution.</P>
    <P>This will take time particularly if it includes and I hope it will, the various matters dealt with in the Government's statement of intent relating to family courts and so on.  It is not something that can be done in a few weeks.  There is a case for an interim measure here as this is in a sense an interim Bill to provide for maintenance in matrimonial property in the case of recognised foreign divorces so that people will not lose the benefit of the maintenance Act by the fact that they got a foreign divorce.  This is particularly important now, as those of us who are pressing for the passing of the amendment to the Constitution are anxious to establish that where people are granted a decree of divorce the first family will not suffer financially.  We stand firmly by this situation in regard to what we see as the Irish divorce.  This is something we see as essential and I am sure the Minister will agree with me on this.  It should be an essential part of any divorce legislation which the Government would propose that we look after the people where divorce decrees are pronounced.  We could show by our attitude to foreign <Col N="229" /> divorce decrees that this is our principle and that we will protect what is described as the first family in this situation as well as in a situation where we would have Irish divorces.</P>
    <P>I am delighted to see the Bill in the House.  I support and commend the Minister for bringing it here and I would like her to consider the points which I have made in connection with it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickDurcan" hpid="Mr. Durcan Mr. Durcan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Durcan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a short, technical Bill and is one which deals with a complex area of law.  The Minister in presenting the Bill was at some pains to stress the fact that it is a minimum measure, as she termed it.  It is also a proposal, as the Minister stated, which, if enacted, will have no practical implications for the vast majority of the people in the State.</P>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is simply to remove one anachronism from the law of domicile, namely, the discriminatory rule under which a married woman is deemed to have the same domicile as her husband. In so far as the Bill does this, I welcome it.  This rule is inequitable; it should not be allowed to survive in our society and it is one which basically recognises the wife as the chattel of the husband. In so far as this concept and idea is departed from I welcome the Bill.</P>
      <P>The section which effects that change is section 1.  It is right that the phrase &ldquo;independent domicile&rdquo; is used and that a married woman should be deemed to have a domicile of that nature as distinct from a dependent domicle which is that of her husband.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As other Senators have stated and as the Minister has also stated, the importance of domicile lies principally in the area of matrimonial jurisdiction; that a woman can find herself in a situation where, for the purpose of giving effect to a court order, her domicile may have changed.  Her domicile will have changed because it will follow that of her husband. A woman may find that by virtue of a new domicile acquired by her husband a court order may be given over which she has no control.  In so far as that situation <Col N="230" /> which totally lacks independence is removed from our legal code, I welcome it.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides for two consequential measures: first, the change of the rules with regard to the dependent domicile of minors and, second, the position regarding the recognition of foreign divorces.  I take the Minister's point that this is a minimum measure and that it is not a Bill which gives effect to the recommendations of the two Law Reform Commission's reports.  Having said that, I believe that section 4 is somewhat incomplete in that it now provides in statutory form what the domicile of a dependent child who has its home with its mother shall be, whereas on the other hand the situation of a dependent child in other circumstances is still dependent on common law rules, that is, the domicile of a child who is living with his father.  The rules in this regard should also be specified in statute.  As the Minister has said this is a minimum measure.  She should have gone a little further in terms of completing the situation with regard to the domicile of dependent children.  I welcome the necessary and consequential change with regard to the recognition of foreign divorces contained in section 5.</P>
    <P>I also welcome what the Bill contains and I will be addressing myself to it further on Committee Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrowne1" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Browne) Acting Chairman (Mr. Browne)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Browne)</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Leader of the House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had one hour's debate on the Bill.  I do not know how many more speakers there are.  The House is due to break from 5.30 to 6.30 p.m. but we might be unduly fragmenting the debate by doing so.  I suggest that we continue this debate between now and 6.30 p.m.  I am not sure if that is the wish of those Senators waiting to speak.  If the debate is not concluded by then, we will interrupt it to take Private Members' Business at that time; if it is concluded before 6.30 p.m. the House should then adjourn until that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="231" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I assume we are talking about the Second Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackFitzsimons" hpid="Mr. Fitzsimons Mr. Fitzsimons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzsimons</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to take this opportunity to welcome the Bill.  I appreciate the comprehensive introductory speech by the Minister which covered all aspects of the Bill.  This is an area where expertise is required.  I have no legal background to deal with it.  It is a short Bill and an important one.  My party published a Bill last December which proposed to abolish the concept of domicile and replace it with habitual residence, thereby giving the woman independent status and eliminating this blatant discrimination.  There is general consensus in welcoming the Bill.</P>
      <P>The Minister has stated in her introductory speech that the basic purpose of the Bill is to get rid of the discriminatory rule under which a married woman is deemed to have the same domicile as her husband. The Bill also deals with the rules of the recognition of foreign divorces only because some change in these rules is inevitable once the domicile of dependency is abolished.</P>
      <P>Senator McGuinness has dealt with that in some detail.  I understand that domicile will be interpreted as it is understood in the Irish courts.  Domicile is rather an involved area because there are many types of domicile: domicile of origin; domicile of choice; domicile of dependency.  These have been dealt with in some detail.  I also accept the Minister's point that on account of this Bill there is going to be no great rush to get foreign divorces because domicile is something that is not easily established.  I accept that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the divorces the Explanatory Memorandum tells us in regard to section 5 that the present rule as it is generally stated is that a foreign divorce is recognised in the State if spouses were domiciled at the commencement of the divorce proceedings in the country where the divorce was granted, or possibly if, although the divorce was granted in a different country <Col N="232" /> from the country where they were domiciled, the divorce is recognised by the law of the country where they were domiciled. It seems to me therefore, that in the present situation where the wife has the domicile of her husband, no matter where she resides, it will be possible for a husband to go to a foreign country, to England, for example, to establish a domicile there and get a divorce.  That divorce will be recognised in this country.  By reason of the fact that the domicile of the wife is that of the husband it would not be possible for a wife to do the same.  In other words, where the husband could go to a foreign country and establish a domicile it seems to me that it would not be possible for the wife to do likewise. Therefore, there is that discrimination. Where a divorce is granted in a foreign country and recognised here, by reason of the fact that the husband would be domiciled in that country, problems arise with regard to payment of social benefits. Clearly, it is an area where many people are not involved but there is great discrimination against women.  For that reason I want to say that I welcome the Bill.</P>
    <P>The Minister has also told us that there is further legislation pending with regard to this matter which is postponed until the outcome of the divorce referendum. Some people might think that a more positive approach could be taken and assume that the referendum will be passed.  In the light of that it might possibly have been better to postpone this for the short period that is involved and to deal with all that in comprehensive legislation. Nevertheless, I suppose the Bill having been started and dealt with so far the proper course is to proceed with it.  I welcome it.</P>
    <P>In conclusion I would like, along with the other Members, to pay a tribute to the work of the Law Reform Commission in this area and to their publications.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I too welcome this Bill. I would have to begin by saying that I am flattered at the extent to which this Bill copies in very similar language the Private Members' Bill which I tabled on the subject of an independent domicile of <Col N="233" /> married women in 1980: the Domicile Bill, 1980.  I have been examining the two Bills while I have been waiting for my turn and I note that particularly in section 1 the language is almost precisely the language used in that Private Members' Bill of 1980 in relation to the abolition of the wife's dependent domicile and also in section 4 in relation to the dependent domicile of the minor and the language is almost word for word as in that Private Members' Bill in 1980.</P>
      <P>I know the Minister of State was not responsible for her present area of jurisdiction in 1980 but I am somewhat puzzled because when that Private Members' Bill was tabled it was specifically geared to the issue which is the primary concern of this Bill, in other words, to remove the situation where a wife automatically took the dependent domicile of her husband and continued to have it regardless of the position until the husband had died or indeed obtained a foreign divorce which our courts would recognise.  Otherwise, no matter what he did, if he emigrated to Australia and she remained in Ireland or if she left the country and live permanently elsewhere and he remained here, she retained his domicile and had no capacity to change it.  She was the only adult of sound mind who was incapable of having an independent domicile.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What puzzles me is why it has taken so long for this Bill to be produced.  Why is it that the Bill was only produced by this Government in December 1985 and we are discussing it here in the Seanad in June 1986?  When the Private Members' Bill which I moved was introduced and debated on 19 November 1980, I was informed at that time that the Bill would not be acceptable because the Government are awaiting the report of the Law Reform Commission, the working report on the whole question of domicile and habitual residence.  That working party report on the Law Reform Commission was published in 1981; it is working paper No. 10 of 1981 on domicile and habitual residence as connecting factors in the conflict of laws.  That working paper was prepared by the Law Reform <Col N="234" /> Commission because they had been asked by the Attorney General to undertake an examination of and conduct research into the law relating to the domicile of married women.  That was their specific brief; that is why they looked at it because they were looking at this subject and they brought in the working paper in 1981.  Then, as is their normal approach, when in working order, they issued a report.  The Law Reform Commission's report on this subject which is entitled &ldquo;Report on Domicile and Habitual Residence as Connecting Factors in the Conflict of Laws&rdquo; was published in December 1983, two full years before a Government Bill was introduced.</P>
    <P>Yet, the Government Bill does not adopt the approach of the Law Reform Commission and does not really explain why not.  I find it very hard to accept the Minister's apparent explanation that this is just on a simple one line that the Government want to deal with and that whatever other issues in relation to changing from domicile to habitual residence may occur, the Government have not had time or opportunity to reflect on them.  That simply cannot be true.  The whole issue has been fully researched, fully before the Government for two years as a final report, but for five years, from 1981 to now, as a working paper which effectively sets out all the possible thinking in the area.</P>
    <P>I feel it necessary to stress this, because it seems as though the wheels of Government grind extremely and unnecessarily slowly in these areas.  I could call to mind numerous reports from women's organisations and bodies which have called for the abolition of independent domicile of the married woman.  It is in the report of The Council on the Status of Women; it has been passed in resolutions; it has been raised in correspondence and it was a matter raised by the Attorney General and referred to the Law Reform Commission prior to 1980.  What was the source of the delay in making a change in the law in this area?  Not only was it deplorable that we did not make a change for internal reasons, but it meant that we were one of the very few European <Col N="235" /> countries which could not sign and ratify the United Nations convention on the abolition of all forms of discrimination against women.  We were severely embarrassed by not being able to sign and indeed we still have not ratified that convention because we did not have this legislation on the Statute Books.  It is necessary for the Minister to explain the delay.  It may be that she herself was pressing for early consideration of this measure and that it was not possible to get Government time or attention.  It is a matter of interest to this House if that is the case.  Are married women such a low priority?  Is the whole area of law reform such a low priority that it cannot get Government attention within an adequate timescale?</P>
    <P>For obvious reasons I welcome the fact that we now have this Bill although I regret that it is such a limited measure. There was ample time and opportunity to consider the recommendations of the Law Reform Commission on the whole issue of whether we should retain the concept of domicile or whether we should move to a more factual based understandable concept of habitual residence. That was the recommendation they made.</P>
    <P>I am also disappointed that the Government Bill is now, even within its own terms confined as far as domicile is concerned to dealing with the domicile of the married woman and providing that from the commencement of the Act a married woman will have an independent domicile.  It deals with the dependent domicile of a minor child as a consequence of that for which provision must be made.  In the Private Members Bill which I tabled in 1980 there was also a section relating to the age at which a person can acquire a domicile.  That was in section 2 of that Private Members' Bill, that a person becomes capable of acquiring an independent domicile on attaining the age of 16 years or on marriage whichever is the earlier.  That was a Bill published in 1980.</P>
    <P>I note that both in its working report and in its final report the Law Reform <Col N="236" /> Commission also recommend that a person be eligible to acquire a domicile at the age of 16 or on marriage whichever is the earlier.  That is the position in a number of other countries.  It is the position in Northern Ireland, England and other common law jurisdictions such as New Zealand and I think I am right in saying, Australia.  I would like to ask the Minister if this matter was considered.  It is certainly something which it would be appropriate to consider in the context of this Bill and is something I would propose to table by way of amendment for consideration by this House.  It is an important issue on which the Government have had recommendations from the Law Reform Commission and which could be dealt with in the context of this Bill.  So much for the provisions in relation to domicile which, as I say, subject to their being enlarged a little, I strongly endorse.</P>
    <P>I would like to turn now to the recognition of foreign divorces.  The Minister in her speech made it clear that she is dealing with this issue primarily as a necessary consequence and only as a necessary consequence of the provision of an independent domicile for a married woman and that she does not feel it is appropriate to make any major proposals in this area pending the outcome of the referendum on the proposals to amend the Constitution and remove the ban on divorce.  It is worth considering what effect the present position in relation to the recognition of foreign divorces has because it raises a number of issues which are part of the present debate but which do not seem to have been appreciated by those who are raising queries and expressing doubts about the implications of the present proposal to amend the Constitution and remove the ban on divorce.  In so far as our courts do recognise a divorce based on the domicile of the parties in the country where the divorce was obtained and &mdash; as the Minister has pointed out that effectively means the domicile of a husband because it is he who determines domicile of the couple &mdash; that will be recognised here.  What does that mean when we say that the divorce will be recognised here?  It means that the Irish <Col N="237" /> courts recognise that divorce as having dissolved the marriage.  It means that if either party come back to Ireland they are free to marry in the State.  By marrying in the State they can found a family based on marriage.  They can found a second family.</P>
    <P>We have in that context already as part of our law and constitutional interpretation the possibility in those circumstances of having two constitutional families, the first family where the marriage was ended by the foreign-recognised divorce and the second family founded on the remarriage of whichever of the parties, husband or wife, has remarried in the State and thereby founded a family with full rights under the Constitution.  That, in fact brings up all the issues being discussed in such a scaremongering context at the moment when we look at the proposal to amend the Constitution.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt that the Bill by making it clear that a divorce will be recognised if it is based on the domicile of either party will extend the scope and potential for obtaining a divorce which will be fully recognised in Ireland.  This is certainly a matter of concern to quite a number of women who wish to obtain a divorce but have been prevented from doing so.  These are women who would be in a position to obtain a divorce because their husbands live in a country where the courts have divorce jurisdiction.  They would be the only ones who would be able to obtain a fully recognised divorce now but the position would be that they would be able to have the same possibility of seizing a court through being domiciled in a country and obtaining a divorce there.</P>
    <P>I would agree with the Minister that it is not going to open any floodgates in that the establishment of domicile is a very far reaching step.  It is a much more substantial step than moving to reside either on a temporary or a relatively long term basis in a country.  It must be done with the intention of remaining indefinitely in the country.  It was interesting that in one of the more recent cases before the Supreme Court concerning the issue of <Col N="238" /> recognition of a foreign divorce, MTT, the Supreme Court had to consider whether an Englishman who had a domicile of origin in England and who had been married in England to an Irish woman and had some children there who subsequently came and was employed by Cork Corporation, had changed his domicile of origin and acquired a domicile of choice in Ireland.</P>
    <P>Relatively shortly after he and the family had moved to Ireland when he took up the job there they separated and he filed for a divorce in England and he wished to have that divorce recognised by the Irish courts and the Supreme Court did recognise that he remained domiciled in England which was his domicile of origin, that the onus of establishing that he changed his domicile had not been met and therefore he continued to be domiciled in England and his divorce was therefore one that would be recognised by the Irish courts.</P>
    <P>That case does raise and leaves a number of questions as to the position of a wife in those circumstances or indeed, a husband if it is the wife after this Bill is passed who will file for a foreign divorce, and I would agree with Senator McGuinness that in that context we do need to have regard to the necessity to protect any dependent spouse particularly in circumstances where the other spouse is domiciled abroad and files for a divorce in the particular jurisdiction.</P>
    <P>I am concerned at present about two different problems which have emerged in the context of the obtaining of a foreign divorce which our courts would recognise. The first of these relates to the position under the social welfare code. Perhaps the Minister would clarify in her reply precisely what the position is in relation to the continuing of payments of deserted wife's benefit or deserted wife's allowance.  I will express to her my understanding of the situation and she can confirm whether I am correct in my understanding or whether the position is different from what I understand it to be.  As I understand the present position where a woman is in receipt of deserted <Col N="239" /> wife's benefit or deserted wife's allowance and her husband obtains a divorce which our courts would recognise because he is domiciled in the country where it is obtained, she continues as a matter of practice to obtain the deserted wife's benefit or allowance.  But, if she is in a position where the divorce comes through before she has applied for, and certainly before she has obtained, the deserted wife's allowance or benefit, she will not be enabled to obtain the deserted wife's allowance or benefit.  In other words, if she has to meet the requirements on application at that stage and she has been divorced by a husband who is domiciled abroad then that is it, she cannot obtain the deserted wife's allowance.</P>
    <P>That is the first area of problem.  It is not satisfactory that there be a sort of policy decision in certain cases and that the matter is not dealt with.  It seems to me that it would be appropriate to deal with it in this Bill.  It is a matter that we could consider at Committee Stage, as to whether it would be possible to both clarify the position and ensure that there is adequate and continued protection for dependent women and their children. That is the social purpose of having a deserted wife's allowance.</P>
    <P>The other issue is a different one but it is one that has arisen on a number of occasions and that relates to the definition of what constitutes an unmarried mother.  The unmarried mother's allowance is payable under the Social Welfare Act 1973 to an unmarried mother.  The conditions describing an unmarried mother are in the ministerial regulations of 1973 and those regulations specify that an unmarried mother is a woman who has a child and must not be married and never have been married.  What about the position of a woman who was married but in respect of which marriage a divorce has been obtained abroad that would be recognised in Ireland?  Up to now that would have been where the husband had obtained the divorce where he was domiciled or she could apply for the divorce if <Col N="240" /> her husband was domiciled in the jurisdiction and then she came back to Ireland and then had a relationship and had a child and had no sort of income.</P>
    <P>She cannot get the deserted wife's allowance or benefit because the foreign divorce having been obtained she cannot then apply for it and she cannot get the unmarried mother's allownce.  What is her position and is it not time that we addresed that situation?  It is occurring: there are problems in that area.  Cherish are aware of a number of cases where all benefits have been refused on those grounds and it appears to be an area that requires to be examined and tidied up and it may be again that it could be a matter that could be dealt with at Committee Stage on this Bill.</P>
    <P>Finally I would welcome some indication from the Minister as to when the broader question of domicile and when the substantial recommendations of the Law Reform Commission in this area will be considered by the Government because it does seem to me anyway, that there are strong arguments for moving from such a technical concept of domicile to the preferable and more realistic concept of habitual residence.  I cannot see what is so complicated about it or why it is a matter that could not be dealt with given that a report on it was submitted in December 1983 to the Government and given that there was an earlier substantial working paper provided by the Law Reform Commission which had all the arguments on both sides both for attaining the concept of domicile and for moving to habitual residence.  Therefore, I think it would be useful to have the Minister's more detailed comments on this whole area and an indication of when we can expect further proposals for reform from the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like briefly at Second Stage to indicate to the Minister the support she has on this side of the House in respect of this Bill and also to take the opportunity of indicating a number of the matters which might be considered by the Minister between this and Committee Stage and about which <Col N="241" /> queries may be raised at Committee Stage during the course of our consideration of this measure.</P>
      <P>As the other Members said, the choice has to be made as to whether one is to govern these relationships and govern these considerations by using the criterion of a domicile or of habitual residence. I note what the Minister has said in regard to the fact that the purpose of this Bill is a minimal change in the law and that it leaves open the possibility of the consideration of the changing of the law in general to recognise the habitual residence as a more proper criterion for the determination of questions which had traditionally been determined on the basis of domicile.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would be wrong in my view to say that this Bill was introduced purely as a response to a Private Members' Bill of Fianna Fáil which was far broader in its approach.  This raises the validity of the point made by Senator Robinson that in fact a Bill like this could have been published and dealt with a long time ago. We all recognise that if one is to change the concept of domicile to one of habitual residence a more fundamental look at the law is necessary.  In the meantime I do not think there is any great reason for our being denied an amendment such as this and I do not think it should have been necessary for this measure to be produced almost as a response to the Fianna Fáil measure which I think is in fact what happened.  That certainly was the public perception of it.  The Minister might or might not like to take up that point.  Domicile is of course a difficult concept to imagine.  One thing we have got to recognise, whether we are dealing with the question of domicile or habitual residence, is that different jurisdictions will always have different definitions of these concepts.  What we mean by domicile is not what other countries mean by domicile and even when we call habitual residence by that name it will not necessarily be identical with what other countries mean by habitual residence. Problems of definition and problems of that kind within international law will remain irrespective of the change in the <Col N="242" /> Irish Constitution or of the change of the definition of habitual residence and the enactment of that concept.</P>
    <P>There is no area of law where the domestic prejudices of a country come into play to a greater extent than in their marriage laws.  States guard very closely the right to determine, in respect of their own citizens and other people in habitual residence or domicile in their countries, the circumstances in which marriages are recognised or terminated or recognised at various stages of their existence or decay.  In examining these problems we should not fool ourselves into believing that the change in the Irish Constitution will necessarily get rid of these difficult and thorny problems.  As long as we have our own independent Legislature and our own independent way of defining these things, problems will continue to exist in this area.  No rational person could continue to support the concept of domicile of dependency in respect of married women.  It is a concept which has no place in the twentieth century.  It has no place not only in the eighties but for many years before that.  It should never have had a place but we cannot change history.</P>
    <P>The domicile of dependency will continue to exist in respect of children and of other categories.  I note the answer given by the Minister in the other House to the effect that, taking into account the provisions of the Age of Majority Act 1985, all married people, irrespective of their age will, of course, acquire an independent domicile after the enactment of this Bill.  The House will remember that the Age of Majority Act 1985 lays down that in respect of any marriage the contracting parties to that marriage automatically acquire their majority.  As a result of that they will automatically acquire an independent domicile.  That is to be welcomed.</P>
    <P>We are then left with the thorny problem of the recognition of foreign divorces.  There was a time when this was a very thorny question in Ireland.  A certain segment of the population got very hot under the collar at the whole concept of the recognition of foreign divorces but that time has long passed. <Col N="243" /> As the Minister has said there are consequential amendments necessary as a result of the changes which she proposes to make with the approval of this House in the abolition of the wife's dependent domicile.  I support those amendments.</P>
    <P>The Minister will remember that in the other House there were a series of amendments proposed to the legislation. In the rather unique way they have of dealing with amendments in that House some of them were never considered. The amendment in the name of the Minister's constituency and Party colleague. Deputy Alan Shatter, which dealt with the question of the maintenance of spouses and children and the application of the 1976 Act to foreign divorces recognised in this State was never dealt with. The Minister in her Second Stage speech said:</P>
    <P>Finally, I think I should refer to the fact that there is no provision in the Bill that would enable a court to make ancillary orders relating to such matters as maintenance and matrimonial property, where a foreign divorce is recognised here.  The Bill is a minimum measure only, for the reasons already explained.  The inclusion of provisions dealing with the financial and property rights and obligations of former spouses whose marriages have been dissolved by a foreign court would represent a substantial extension of the measure and would be outside the scope of the Bill.</P>
    <P>One of the reasons we are discussing it on Second Stage is to try to establish what the scope of the Bill is.  That is what the Second Stage does.  Recognising the Minister's view in that regard the Minister should be warned that it is my intention &mdash; I cannot speak for other Members of the House but I know there are other Members who share my view &mdash; to discuss this matter at Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>We should repair the omission of the other House and give the matter more detailed consideration.  I say that to the Minister not in any way to embarrass her or to do anything other than to give her <Col N="244" /> notice of my intention to put down an amendment in the same terms, if not identical, to what Deputy Shatter put down at Committee Stage in the Dáil but which was not reached because of the rather extraordinary system in that House of terminating debates for no better reason than that 7 o'clock arrives. That appears to be a very queer reason for passing anything.  The Minister does not appear to recognise what I am saying. It was amendment No. 81, Deputy Shatter was dealing with amendment No. 7, as reported at column 2289 of the Dáil Official Report for 30 April, 1986.  The amendment read:</P>
    <P>This section shall apply to a divorce granted in divorce proceedings initiated after the commencement of this Act.</P>
    <P>That was an amendment to section 5 while the other one was a new section 6. The question then was &ldquo;That section 5 stand part of the Bill&rdquo; and Deputy Glenn made an interjection, which was typical of the views she holds.  Then the Ceann Comhairle replied saying:</P>
    <P>As it is now 7 p.m.  I must put the following question: &ldquo;That Committee Stage is hereby agreed to, that the Bill is reported to the House without amendment, that Report Stage is hereby completed and the Bill is hereby passed.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>It appears that the reason the Bill was passed was that it was 7 o'clock.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CatherineMcGuinness" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mrs. McGuinness) Acting Chairman (Mrs. McGuinness)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mrs. McGuinness)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has made his point and I would rather he did not go into too much detail as to what went on in the other House.  That is not proper procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>It sounds as if they got their tea break.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>It sounds as if they were so determined to get their tea break that they passed the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NualaFennell" hpid="Mrs. Fennell Mrs. Fennell">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Fennell</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendments the Senator mentioned were already ruled <Col N="245" /> out of order and were not before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>That would not have stopped somebody getting up and proposing under section 6, as there was an amendment relating to section 6, that so and so would be considered.  We all have experience of amendments being ruled out of order but that does not stop us from getting up and discussing the contents of the amendments.  That is normal procedure. The main point I am making is that the completion of the Stage seems to coincide with the arrival of 7 o'clock rather than with the conclusion of the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has made his point about the Dáil debate and he has given the Minister notice of what he intends to do.  The Minister is well warned that he will not be willing to sit down just because it is 7 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is being very protective of the other House.  I wish that the Chair in the other House was as protective in respect of this House.  For all these reasons the sooner we take the Committee Stage of this Bill the better. Having said that, I assure the Minister that she has our support in the general thrust of the legislation.  It has the support of all right thinking people.  I note that there was no opposition to it in the other House.  It is only fair to say that.  Certainly there was criticism but there was no opposition.  I am sure that that will also be the constructive attitude of the Members of this House with regard to these matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not understand why England, Wales, Scotland, Northern Ireland, The Isle of Man and the Channel Islands are specifically mentioned.  I can understand that they are separate jurisdictions and I understand that some provision must be made for them but it appears to be rather strange that they were specifically mentioned. I am sure the Minister has a good reason for that.  That is a matter I will be teasing out during the consideration of section 5.  The Minister mentioned the <Col N="246" /> contrasting position in Canada and in the United States of America which are not specifically mentioned.  I am anxious to understand the system whereby these things happen automatically.  That is more important than making a specific provision in respect of one country and one group of countries.  I would like to understand how it operates automatically. I am sure the Minister will help us in that regard.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill.  I hope that we can proceed to consideration of Committee Stage quickly and, in doing so, I am sure the Minister can rest assured of the support and help of this House in not only approving the legislation before us but, hopefully, also improving it if it requires improvement having been examined by the Members of this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NualaFennell" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mrs. Fennell) Nuala Fennell">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice (Mrs. Fennell)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank the Senators who contributed to the debate and for the various points they have raised.  I look forward to dealing on Committee Stage with the points raised.</P>
      <P>With regard to Senator Robinson's point about the delay, the Law Reform Commission examined the question of domicile and its replacement by dual residence and reported in 1983.  However, because the issue of domicile is so closely intertwined with the rules for the recognition of foreign divorces the Law Reform Commission undertook a further examination of this particular aspect of the matter and only reported in 1985.  I am sure the Senator will accept that this was something that needed to be dealt with in the context of the new concept of independent domicile recognition for married women.</P>
      <P>The questions raised by Senators McGuinness and Robinson in relation to the deserted wifes' benefit and allowance are a matter for the Minister for Social Welfare.  I would like to have had the facts and details which were requested but, given that I am replying immediately, that is not possible.  I certainly will look into this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is no need to repeat in the Bill the age at which independent domicile <Col N="247" /> can be acquired because one of the effects of the Age of Majority Act, 1985, is that a person has the capacity to acquire an independent domicile at 18 years or earlier on marriage.</P>
    <P>There were a number of other points that were raised and they will be taken note of and considered.  I do not want to label the point Senator O'Leary made on the debate in the other House but the amendments to which he referred were ruled out of order because they were not related to the Bill in question and to the long title.</P>
    <P>I thank the Senators for their contributions. I will be back to discuss their proposals on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 11 June 1986.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Sitting suspended at 6.20 p.m. and resumed at 6.30 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Development of the Philippines:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Development of the Philippines: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann, affirming its support for the forces of democracy, national reconciliation, peace and stability in the Philippines, welcomes the efforts of the Philippine Government to promote the social and economic development of the country and its declared intention to draw up a new democratic constitution for the Philippines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am very pleased and, indeed, privileged to be in the position of proposing this Fine Gael motion.  It is a personal pleasure for me to propose this motion today because I had the greatest privilege of my political career in January this year when I was contacted by Trócaire, the Catholic Relief Development Agency and invited to join a group of 11 other Irish people on an exposure trip to the Philippines at a most historic time and, indeed, a <Col N="248" /> juncture in the political life of the Philippines. I spent four weeks there in January just prior to the election and had an opportunity to observe, in as much as one can in that short time, something of the life and realities of the people in the Philippines.</P>
    <P>It has certainly stimulated my interest in that country.  I have watched events evolve there, as, indeed, the whole world did, with bated breath in January and February and find myself opening the foreign affairs section of the Irish daily newspapers, and, indeed, today and yesterday I have been amply rewarded in that <i>The Irish Times</i> correspondent in the Philippines, Tom Fawthrop, whom I met while I was there, has given us very up-to-date briefing as to the current situation there.</P>
    <P>The Philippines and the Filipinos can feel justly proud that their revolution was largely a bloodless one and was achieved by sheer weight of numbers and, what they like to call in the Philippines, &ldquo;people power&rdquo; because in the sequence of events that finally led to the departure of Ferdinand Marcos and his entourage it was the thousands and thousands of men, women and children who manned the human barricades in front of the tanks outside Camp Crame in Manila who finally speeded up the departure of the dictator.  These people were finally rewarded with the defections of Defence Minister Enrile and General Ramos to the Aquino side which brought about a resolution of the difficulties and a transfer of power.  Many people are sceptical, understandably sceptical, about what might be considered to have been a death bed conversion of Ramos and Enrile and it remains to be seen how that situation evolves and develops.  I will refer to that later in my contribution.</P>
    <P>It is understandable, in the wake of this revolution and change after so many years of dictatorship augmented by martial law, that there should be a euphoria in the Philippines about the nature of the change.  Indeed, the casual observer of the scene could be forgiven for thinking that all was resolved there and that the departure of Marcos must mean a new <Col N="249" /> era for the country but, in fact, anybody who examines it closely will see that the difficulties and troubles are only being addressed at this stage and that there is a long long haul back to some sort of economic stability and political viability.</P>
    <P>Mrs. Corazon Aquino is a beloved figure in the Philippines and there is no doubt but that she has massive popular support in a personal capacity.  Her husband, former Senator Ninoy Aquino was also a very respected figure.  His assassination was a watershed in the political life of the Philippines.  From it there was a mobilisation of people and forces which eventually led to the events of last February.</P>
    <P>Mrs. Aquino has an extremely difficult situation to contend with because she is seen as a seminal figure and as somebody who, for this period at least, has brought together all the conflicting forces who are opposed to Marcos but it has yet to be firmly established what Mrs. Aquino stands for.  Everybody knew what she was against and for that reason, because they, too, were against the dictator Marcos; rushed to support her.  Many of the people I met while I was there talked of it being a time of grace for the Philippines. There was a quasi-religious dimension to the revolution and indeed the Catholic Church played a very strong role in the eventual resolution of the difficulties.</P>
    <P>Many of the people who voted for change and for the departure of Marcos expect and, indeed, demand some sort of instant remedies to the many ills which beset the Philippines and President Aquino is faced with this most formidable challenge of meeting the demands of these people.  She will need the goodwill and practical support and encouragement from all concerned people, both within the Philippines and, indeed, without and Senators will have an opportunity today and next week also to extend to that fragile democracy their good wishes and pledges of solidarity and support.</P>
    <P>As a first step, President Aquino has established an independent commission of 48 members.  She has given them very clear instructions that they must complete writing a Constitution within three <Col N="250" /> months so that the Philippines can become &mdash; and these are her own words &mdash;&ldquo;a full-blown democratic republic before the end of this year&rdquo;.  At present she governs this fragile coalition under a provisional Constitution which she herself proclaimed until the new charter is written and approved of by the people. She has set in motion a promise of a Constitution on which her republic will be based.  It is hoped that these 48 independent members do not get into an intense political wrangle and that they come up with a Constitution which will be a viable way forward for the peoples of the Philippines.</P>
    <P>Meanwhile, there is a guerilla war raging in the country.  Again I am indebted to Tom Fawthrop and his reports in <i>The Irish Times</i> giving the most up-to-date information on that war.  This guerilla war severely threatens Mrs. Aquino's position and her hopes for peace, stability and unity in the Philippines. The left-wing guerilla army is known as the NPA &mdash; the New Peoples Army &mdash; and is approximately 20,000 members strong.  It operates largely in the rural areas on a fairly skilled type of operation over rugged terrain.  It is helped, fed, and assisted and supported by the rural people, many of whom I met, because during the course of my stay in the Philippines part of the exposure literally was that you lived with the rural people in the countryside and slept on their bedding of coconut matting and shared food at their table.  So I am under no illusions about the harsh reality of their lives, nor am I under any illusion about the practical support they give to the New Peoples Army in the rural areas. I am convinced that it is a fairly potent force and one that must be reckoned with in the course of political life in the Philippines.</P>
    <P>The NPA have indicated a wish for dialogue.  Of course, they want certain basic minimum demands which are largely ones of structural change, redistribution of wealth and land reform.  The Government are demanding that they would lay down their arms as a basic requirement.  This is a precondition which <Col N="251" /> the military are demanding so the fragile authority of Mrs. Aquino is being undermined, on the one hand, by the NPA and, on the other hand, by the hard line policies of her military, who, to say the least, are unenthusiastic about any posibility of a compromise with the beleagured NPA.</P>
    <P>In <i>The Irish Times</i> of 3 June 1986, Tom Fawthrop stated that there was a raging military offensive taking place in Cagayan Valley, that is in the province of Northern Luzon, involving bombing and straffing of villagers by helicopter, gunships and fire fights.  This followed on an announcement on 12 May from General Ramos ordering more aggressive military action against the NPA.  In <i>The Irish Times</i> today, Tom Fawthrop again wrote an even more up to date account of what was happening.  In that he said that General Ramos had ordered a field commander to discard any local ceasefire agreement with the NPA or, indeed, the Muslim Rebels in defiance of the civilian Government's policy of reconciliation, dialogue and peace.  Over 800 people have been killed in the guerrilla warfare since February, 1986. Indeed, I came upon a victim of such an operation while I was in central Luzon Province and it was a very disturbing sight indeed.  I was given some idea of the oppression on the people from the NPA, on the one hand, and then the military who are poured into an area, on the other, to contain the incursions of the NPA.</P>
    <P>President Aquino's hopes for peace, reconciliation and dialogue, therefore, are being very much threatened internally because there are continued human rights violations by the military.  Indeed, the guerillas are most suspicious of the new democracy and these are two strands which are quite polarised and which have to be dealt with.  Her Minister for political Affairs, Antonio Cuenco has admitted that the NPA may be confused by the conflicting statements coming from the Government, because you have President Aquino, on the one hand, talking about peace, reconciliation and dialogue <Col N="252" /> and ceasefire and the laying down of arms and, on the other hand the military who are part of that Government are adopting a hard line approach and going on the offensive.  So conditions for stability certainly do not obtain at present.</P>
    <P>The revolution, it is true to say, was largely Manila based and largely occurred among the middle classes.  Again, to quote Tom Fawthrop, who is an acknowledged expert on Far Eastern Affairs and is particularly knowledgeable about matters in the Philippines, he talks about a heady atmosphere of freedom in the capital.  He goes on to state, and I can understand it, having been there, that that concept of the new democracy has not percolated down into the poverty stricken provinces because there the military oppression and the presence of the NPA continue.  The offensive that occurred last week in Cagayan was a dismal failure.  There were heavy casualties among the military and civilians and General Ramos was forced to admit that the Philippines may become another Vietnam or Cambodia.  That is a most devastating possibility and one that we would all be well to be aware of and concerned about here.  One hopes, of course, that that will never happen.</P>
    <P>Meanwhile, President Aquino has declared that the root causes of insurgency are in the economic conditions and the social structures that oppress the people.  Certainly from my observations that is a completely accurate viewpoint. She wants to have a six month's ceasefire leading to an assimilation of the guerillas into normal society and the legalisation of the Marxist political parties which of course, will be and is being resisted by the military elements in the Government. Those military establishment elements have ordered the scrapping of all local <i>de facto</i> ceasefires and an all-out offensive has been launched.  All of this clearly undermines President Aquino's authority and makes clear the very difficult and almost impossible task she has to face and the danger of her Government splintering.</P>
    <P>The NPA adopt the attitude that the military are trying to pre-empt peace <Col N="253" /> talks by launching a nationwide offensive. So President Aquino is caught in this pincers movement between the hawkish elements in the army and, again, it must be stated that she has not, to date, been capable of purging the army of those hawkish elements and, indeed, almost exists because of the support which she is receiving from people like General Ramos.  On the other hand, the NPA are making demands that she cannot instantly or, indeed, easily satisfy.</P>
    <P>Those are the immediate problems but also I should like to refer in the course of my contribution, to the enormous structural difficulties which exist in that society.  They were largely created and then ignored by General Marcos and they demand immediate and urgent attention from the new regime.  In the course of my visit to the Philippines, I had an opportunity of living among the urban poor in Tondo, which is a large slum on the outskirts of Manila, a shanty town, rather like many of the shanties which have sprung up in central and southern America and, indeed, as I said earlier I moved among the fishermen and the farmers and the agricultural poor out in the provinces.</P>
    <P>It is important to remember that the population of the Philippines is an enormous one and is growing rapidly. Again, this is part of the difficulty.  There are some 55 million people there at the moment.  About 50 per cent of the labour force is either unemployed or under employed which, again, points up to an enormous problem.  The infant mortality rate is shocking, 62 out of 1,000 babies die before reaching the age of one.  The nutrition level is extremely poor.  The daily meals of the average Filipino household remains deficient in protein, vitamin A, thiamine, riboflavin, calcium, ascorbic acid and iron.  I shared some of these meals so I have a very keen appreciation of the paucity of the diet.  I saw children who, at home, I would expect to be in the age range of one to two, but in the Philippines were three or four.  That for somebody coming from the western world is an extremely disturbing experience.</P>
    <P>Despite all that there is an enormous <Col N="254" /> cheerfulness, a tremendous friendly outgoing quality among the people.  They were certainly very keen to talk about their difficulties and discuss quite openly their various problems with visiting strangers.  It is true to say that the poverty level is deepening there and that the majority of the people have a real feeling of powerlessness, though one hopes, since the succession of President Aquino, that that feeling of powerlessness is lessening somewhat.</P>
    <P>There is an enormous burden of foreign debt.  At least $26 billion is owed. That is a most daunting task and makes our own debt problems seem infinitesimal in contrast.  The debt crisis can be traced to a number of fundamental factors. There is the perpetuation of historic colonialism and certain patterns that flow from that in the economy.  There are tremendous class inequalities.  I had read about this sort of thing but to perceive the inequality between the haves and the have-nots is a very moving experience. The middle class or upper class housing areas in the capital, Manila, are palatial. We do not have the like of these areas here in Ireland.  Even our very best residential districts pale into insignificance compared with the affluence of some of the housing areas in the Philippines.  I think they were called villages.  When they are contrasted with the shanties, where there is deplorable poverty, it is a mind blowing experience to come across it.</P>
    <P>Part of the fundamental difficulties that have brought about the crisis are those of domestic elitism and a distorted set of economic priorities.  One saw, under the Marcos régime, the extraordinary follies built and created along the lines of giving the people bread and circus games. There were beautiful theatres, cinemas and centres of culture.  But, of course, the poor people, who form the majority of people in the country, could not hope to aspire to enter any one of these places. The economic priorities that led to the spending of money on these follies must be questioned and one feels confident that under the present Government of President Aquino that such distortions <Col N="255" /> will not recur.  The economy, as a result, is dependent, it is undercapitalised and underdeveloped and it is rife with social inequalities which must be addressed by President Aquino.</P>
    <P>The whole world was made aware of the corruption that was rife in the Philippines. Government and public institutions made the public purse their own personal treasury.  We all know of the millions and millions of dollars that were siphoned out of the country by Marcos and his cronies.  All that has to be attended to and I think President Aquino is making vigorous efforts in that direction.</P>
    <P>While this collective greed may seem in a way so extraordinary and surprising to us, to an extent that it is almost humorous &mdash; indeed, it was the focus of many cartoons in newspapers during the course of the revolution &mdash; it must be remembered that what it actually did on the ground was to deprive the Filipino people of so much of their own wealth which could have been ploughed back into their economy to create a better way of life for them and to give them a possibility of enterprise.  This exploitation of the nation's wealth and the surrender of its sovereignty proceeded under the coercion of martial law at the time.  The people were deprived of basic rights and freedoms.  It is true to say that their humanity, in the course of all of this, was diminished.  President Aquino has a job now to restore their morale, to restore their confidence and restore that damaged and diminished humanity.  I think that a power based on violence, oppression and martial law is one that undermines severely the morale of a people. That must be one of President Aquino's prime considerations.</P>
    <P>The Filipino people need now the widest possible democratic space in which they can be enabled to respond creatively to the complex transformational problems that confront their country at this time because it is now a decisive juncture in the life of the Philippines. One can only wish Mrs. Aquino well in her mammoth task.  Only in freedom can <Col N="256" /> the Filipino people proceed to participate fully in the very, very difficult decision making which lies ahead of them.  They have to resolve the existing economic injustices and they have to assert their nation's sovereignty because for too long the Philippines has been regarded as something less than a democracy.  I hope I will have time to speak briefly about that.  They will have to come to terms with decision making about the presence of the US bases in their country and the dominance of the United States in their state.  They will have to learn to relate to the world community with equality and dignity, which has not been their good fortune to do until now.</P>
    <P>In the little time remaining to me I should like to make some references to the bases.  No discussion of the Philippines would be complete without reference to the bases.  The country hosts two of the largest United States bases, that is, outside the United States itself, the Subic Naval Base which I visited while I was there and Clarke Air Force base.  The Pentagon sees these bases as being absolutely irreplaceable in their scheme of things.  So you have had a difficult situation in the attitude of the United States towards the Philippines.  On the one hand, you have had the thinking of the Pentagon which sees the scenario in terms of world strategy and then you have had the thinking of the State Department which has favoured political change and reform initiatives.  Of course, the Pentagon has been wary of these political reform initiatives, fearing their impact on the presence of the bases.  President Aquino has a difficult decision to make but she has decided she will meet that decision when the leases for the bases run out and when they come up for review which will be in the nineties.</P>
    <P>Meanwhile there is an increasing body of opinion in the Philippines which is deeply unhappy about the presence of the bases because it sees them as having a very adverse effect on the life of the country.  It is true to say that the moral fabric and the social cohesion of the areas around the bases have been very damaged by the presence of these bases <Col N="257" /> because these areas surrounding the bases &mdash; I saw them and visited them &mdash; have been turned into large camp towns with gambling and prostitution and vice.</P>
    <P>I should like to comment particularly on what the presence of these bases has done to the women of the Philippines. They have been demeaned and degraded and the pride of the Philippines has been deeply affected by the presence of these bases.  Filipinos, who are nationalists and who are thinking, have come to recognise the fact that there is a price to pay for the presence of these bases.  We in the Western world, who look to the defence strategy of the United States, must not be allowed forget that that defence strategy means that somebody somewhere pays a price.  Certainly, my experiences in the Philippines have opened my eyes to the very real price that is being paid in the Philippines because of the presence of those bases.  I hope that the Minister, in the course of his contribution to this debate, will make some reference to the bases and to his view of them.</P>
    <P>I should like to conclude by quoting from a distinguished Senator, José Diokno, whom it was my pleasure to meet in the Philippines. This man loved his country with a palpable passion.  He took time to meet with us and to speak with enormous affection and concern about his country.  He called it:</P>
    <P>an &ldquo;independent&rdquo; country that is not sovereign, a &ldquo;democratic&rdquo; country whose people are not free, a state that is not yet a nation, a rich land filled with poor people.</P>
    <P>That sums up the Philippines I had an opportunity to see in January this year &mdash; a country filled with the most delightful people, a beautiful blend of Spanish, Chinese, Malayan and indigenous people, a people with hybrid vigour because of all those strains and development, a country of enormous potential and one that all people of goodwill should wish well for and for its President in her task of bringing about national reconciliation, peace and stability.</P>
    <Col N="258" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish formally to second the motion and reserve my right to speak at a later stage in the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I read in some of the newspapers in the past few days that there was a certain amount of tension and uncertainty in the Philippines at present.  It is very appropriate that this motion is before the House at this time.  I want to congratulate Senator Bulbulia on her very fine and enlightening contribution.</P>
      <P>My knowledge of the Philippines, apart from what we all know and have read regarding the events of the last few years, comes mainly from friends of mine, some of them school pals, who are working as missionaries abroad, especially in the Philippines.  The Columban Fathers, who have a house at Navan, have approximately 200 missionaries in that part of the world.  There are also Carmelites and congregations from Belgium, Italy, Germany, the United States as well as Spain and Canada working in the Philippines.</P>
      <P>The Philippines, because of the situation there at present is a country that is very difficult to administer.  The country is made up of about 7,000 islands.  I think 55 million is the official figure for the population but I have been told that the population is approaching 60 million. However, what is 5 million between Senator Bulbulia and myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>It is growing rapidly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelLynch" hpid="Mr. Lynch Mr. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Bulbulia is quite right in what she says about the wealthy and the poor because one third of the population of the Philippines hold two thirds of the wealth.  That is inequality from the word go.  As far back as ten years ago I was told of many of the horrific atrocities and tragedies that were occurring in the Philippines.  I always felt shocked and frustrated at the attitude of the United States who were witness to and partly to blame for some of it, if not all of it but it must be remembered, as Senator Bulbilia has said, that the United States are paying big money for bases there.  I, too, would like the Minister's comments on the American role in the <Col N="259" /> Philippines at some stage during this debate.  I am told this lease does not expire until 1990.  The bases, as has been mentioned by Senator Bulbulia are the Clarke Air Base and the Subic Naval Base.  I understand that the American Congress has taken a stand to limit military aid to the Philippines.  I am not sure what effect this will have on the present position.</P>
      <P>I believe President Aquino has the goodwill of this nation, and she certainly needs it.  I have been told reliably that the President has many good people around her.  I believe she is holding in the near future what we would call a local authority election and that all who hold office will have to resign their positions prior to the election.  We must remember that anyone who was a mayor or a governor under the Marcos regime was relieved of office when Mrs. Aquino became President.</P>
      <P>It is ironic that we are discussing this motion today.  The late husband of the President of the Philippines, Benigno Aquino, was a Senator under Macamagol and Marcos.  I believe he was a very brilliant man but was seen as a threat to Marcos who put him in jail and indeed put him in the stockade at the start of martial law.  I believe he was sentenced to death.  In about 1980 he was allowed go to the United States for treatment for a heart condition.  When he returned to the Philippines he tried to convince President Marcos that, as a missionary said to me, the country was going through hell and going to hell.  For his efforts and advice, Aquino was assassinated.</P>
      <P>I am not going to hazard a guess as to what is going to happen in the future except to say the goodwill of the people of Ireland will be with the new President. I would like during my short contribution to give some details as to the background of the situation in the Philippines.  Hopefully we will then understand what the new President has to accomplish.  How she will accomplish it is another matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In 1963 the Philippines had a two party system made up of the Liberals and the Nationals.  The then president was Mr. <Col N="260" /> Mapagal.  During that time democratic principles were, I believe, more or less adhered to.  However, I have been reliably told that there has been always a corrupt aspect to politics in the history of the Philippines.  In 1965 Marcos was elected president.  He was seen at that time as a person who was capable of achieving great things.  His inaugural address as president created a great impression.  I believe his first term in office could be described as reasonably good.  However, for his re-election the campaign he carried out was, in the words of a missionary, &lsquo;the worst of all time.&rsquo; We should be grateful that democracy prevails in Ireland.  That campaign was not necessary because he had come through his first term reasonably well and would have been re-elected anyway.  He had a landslide victory in that election.</P>
    <P>What led to much of the trouble was that the Constitution of the Philippines provided that the office of President could not be held for three consecutive terms.  President Marcos decided to hold a constitutional convention.  He put pressure on the delegates to have included in the Constitution a provision which would allow him to stay in office indefinitely.  At that stage the country's students had become very restless and very vocal and our media became more prominent in the reporting of events in the Philippines.</P>
    <P>The knowledge I had up to that was from missionaries who had come home on leave.  I felt some of them had been sent home because they had become too vocal.  The students had been infiltrated by organisations with leftist feelings.  As the unrest grew Marcos used the opportunity in 1972 to declare martial law on the pretext of suppressing the communist influence.  Marcos became both President and Prime Minister.  He silenced all the privately controlled radio, television and press.  He allowed only Government press, television and radio to operate. He ruled by decree for eight years.  He allowed an assembly to be elected and it was very much under his thumb.  His cabinet were all yes men.  Martial law was lifted in 1980 but it was lifted only in <Col N="261" /> theory &mdash; anyone who spoke out against the President was taken away and silenced. Salvaging was the word used to define the killing of people by summary execution.</P>
    <P>Senator Bulbulia mentioned the New People's Army, which is the armed wing of the communist party.  The NPA became strong.  The Marcos army had become more abusive and thereby created a situation where the people had to turn to the NPA who were seen as the defenders of the rights of the people.  The NPA was very ruthless.  They took away local government officials and executed them.</P>
    <P>It is against that background that we have a new government, democratically elected, in the Philippines.  They have promised under their new president to abide by democracy.  As Senator Bulbulia has explained, there are many factors and problems which President Aquino has to overcome.  We should add our goodwill to the Philippine Government to promote the social and economic development of the country and help in any way we can in their declared intention to draw up a new democratic Constitution for the Philippines.  We wish them well.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Minister for Foreign Affairs (Mr. P. Barry) Peter Barry">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Foreign Affairs (Mr. P. Barry)</NameTxt>
      <P>I found those two contributions extraordinarily interesting.  The way Senator Bulbulia told of her moving visit to the Philippines, her obvious concern for the people there and for the future of that country was one of the most impressive contributions I have heard in a debate in this House or in any House for a long time.  The amount of research that Senator Lynch has done, from contacts with his old school pals also gives an insight which, like Senator Bulbulia's contribution, is very revealing.  In their contributions &mdash; Senator Lynch's coming at second hand and Senator Bulbulia's at first hand; Senator Lynch reflecting the views of the people whom he has spoken to who are following their vocation there, and Senator Bulbulia from visiting there &mdash; both Senators show concern for a future democracy for the Philippines and <Col N="262" /> for the Philippine people themselves, and their sense of love, loyalty and great affection is also manifest.  It is an appeal to me to do what I can to help and it is a challenge I gladly take up.</P>
      <P>All of us in this House and indeed in Ireland have followed with sympathy the recent events in the Philippines and the very courageous efforts being made by the new administration to put that country back on the road to progress and prosperity.  In considering events in the Philippines it is necessary to sketch the general background in recent years which has led to the end of the Marcos era &mdash; an era that started with very favourable prospects and ended with the people's revolt against the corruption, greed and exploitation by their political masters. Faced like every other country with the enormous problems caused by the international recession, the people of the Philippines had also to shoulder the intolerable burden of a ruling élite using their political power and their control of state revenues for their personal enrichment. The administration sought by all possible means to manipulate events for its members benefit, as was evidenced very clearly by the events surrounding the presidential election earlier this year. Healthy political debate had all but disappeared. Life in a very real sense had become cheap.  Violations of human rights were an everyday occurrence.  A country which had once been among the most prosperous and progressive in South East Asia was fast sliding into bankruptcy and lawlessness.</P>
      <P>At the UN Commission on Human Rights the Irish Government have spoken at length on human rights violations by the Marcos administration.  We have condemned the summary executions and other killings, of which there is wide evidence that most were the work of the security forces, although on occasion other persons and groups, including some opposed to the authorities, have been responsible.  Irrespective of the political ideologies or motives of their authors, we have condemned such killings unreservedly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There was also numerous allegations <Col N="263" /> of torture being used against persons arrested by the security forces, usually in the period when the victims were being held incommunicado and before charges had been preferred.  At the Commission on Human Rights we appealed to the Marcos administration to ensure that all such allegations would be fully, impartially and swiftly investigated, that proceedings would be instituted against the presumed authors and that if they were found guilty the severity of the sentences should match the gravity of the offence.  Unfortunately the available evidence indicates that this happened all to rarely.  In many cases, statements by the military that a person had been killed in an encounter with subversive elements were accepted as the truth even in the many cases when the victim was last seen alive in military custody.  There have been numerous reports of intimidation of witnesses by security personnel.  Investigations were rarely carried out by bodies independent of the security establishment.</P>
    <P>I was reminded very much of this when I saw at the United Nations the then Foreign Minister of the Philippines.  I spoke to him about Fr. Niall O'Brien who was imprisoned at the time and asked that he be released.  He alleged not to know who I was talking about.  He asked me was he one of these rebel priests in a tone of voice that left me in no doubt about what he thought about rebels or priests and the best place for them was where they were.  At that stage he said he would look into the matter and communicate with me.  I never heard from him afterwards.  We became acutely aware of this state of affairs in connection with the detention of Fr. Niall O'Brien. There is no need for me to remind Senators of Father Niall O'Brien's sufferings which happily ended in his total vindication and release.  If one was to conjure up the image of a rebel priest, it is not Father Niall O'Brien who would come to mind: he was an ordinary curate doing his job as best he could.  His order were in a difficult position.  As Senator Lynch is aware that order has about 160 <Col N="264" /> members in the Philippines.  Those members were put in a difficult position because of Father O'Brien's imprisonment at that time.</P>
    <P>More recently there was the disappearance of Father Rudy Romano, last seen on 11 July 1985, which is almost 12 months ago, when he was picked up by men who appeared to be in the military services.  As you will be aware, we have raised this matter on several occasions with the Marcos authorities and also with the new government.  There is still no news about the priest's whereabouts but inquiries are still being made as to where he might be.</P>
    <P>This then was the background to the political crisis earlier this year in the Philippines.  In the months prior to the collapse of the Marcos administration, when the serious situation in the country was only too apparent, Ireland in cooperation with our partners in the European Community made efforts to promote peace and stability there.  On 30 December 1985 the then Ten issued a statement expressing the hope that the forthcoming presidential election would be in order from a legal and constitutional point of view.  The decision to do this was in response to a widely expressed fear at the time that the election might be manipulated.  Sadly this fear was justified by events surrounding the 7 February election, which provided the catalyst for the remarkable peaceful revolution of the Philippine people.</P>
    <P>It was evident to the international community as well as to the people of the Philippines that justice was not being done in the conduct and aftermath of the election.  On Friday, 14 February, Ireland and the other member states of the European Community in a public statement expressed their deep concern about the developments arising from the presidential election in the Philippines and, in particular, about reports of fraud and violence.  I should like to remind the House of what Senator Lynch said earlier about the composition of the parliament, the way they voted and declared who had won the election a few days afterwards <Col N="265" /> which clearly shows the way that parliament was constituted.  The Twelve stressed the great importance they attach to strict respect for legal and constitutional procedures so as to ensure democratic elections.  In order to meet the expressed wishes of the Philippine people, the Philippine authorities were urged to facilitate a full and impartial investigation of these reports.</P>
    <P>Later that weekend the National Assembly which was, of course, dominated by his party, the New Society Movement &mdash; KBL &mdash; declared that Mr. Macros had won the presidential election. In common with other western countries we were very disturbed at this announcement, since observers' reports had made it clear that there had been massive fraud and intentional disorder in the lists of voters which had made it impossible for many to vote at all.  It was evident also that there had been intimidation and changing of votes and tally sheets.  Other abuses, including the denial of adequate media coverage to the opposition during the campaign, were common.  Nevertheless, there was an admirably stubborn desire of a large number of concerned citizens to see the will of the people freely expressed and to defend their right against threats and intimidation &mdash; a defence which in some cases ended in death.</P>
    <P>On 20 February Ireland's Ambassador to the Philippines &mdash; we do not have a resident Ambassador in the Philippines; our Ambassador in Peking is accredited to that country &mdash; together with other Heads of Mission of our partners in the European Community met Mrs. Aquino. This meeting was an expression of Community support for the democratic process in the Philippines.  It was a clear message to the still surviving Marcos administration of the deep concern of the Twelve member states of the European Community about recent developments. Mrs. Aquino reiterated her determination to vindicate the people's verdict and assume the Presidency at the earliest possible time.  She pointed out the expectation of the Philippine people that the community of civilised states would share <Col N="266" /> their moral judgment and behave accordingly in respect of the election.</P>
    <P>Together with his colleagues, the Ambassador also conveyed our concern at the events surrounding the election as expressed in the 14 February statement to the then acting Foreign Minister, Mr. Castro.</P>
    <P>There can be little doubt that the will for change has existed in the Philippines for many years, though the discontent lacked a focal point.  The turning point was the murder of the political leader Benigno Aquino in 1983 at Manila airport as he returned from exile to the Philippines. The country's outrage at this assassination brought the disparate strands of opposition together.  His wife, Mrs. Corazon Aquino, emerged as a leader in her own right and forged an alliance which has achieved what many thought unattainable &mdash; political change based on the people's will.  With a strong insistence on non-violence she imbued the people with a determination to demand their rights and courage to achieve that goal.  In all these developments the support of the Church was very important, not least in helping to maintain the peaceful character of the people's revolt.  The massive demonstrations totally lacking in violence which brought about the fall of Marcos must be among the most remarkable scenes to have ever appeared on our TV screens.</P>
    <P>The good sense and calm control of the ordinary Filipinos in such chaotic circumstances are indeed a lesson to the rest of the world.</P>
    <P>The events of February which led to the final collapse of the Marcos regime and the inauguration of President Aquino represent the beginning of a new chapter in the history of the Philippines.  The rebirth of the democratic tradition of the Philippines will, I hope, enable its people to work together in an atmosphere of peace and stability for the development of their country and to fulfil their proper role in world affairs.  In this effort, they can be assured of the sympathy and support of the Irish people.</P>
    <P>At their ministerial meeting in The <Col N="267" /> Hague on 25 February 1986, the Ministers of Foreign Affairs of the Twelve commended the adherence of the Philippine people to democratic principles and warmly commended Mrs. Aquino for her consistent stand in defence of these principles. We conveyed our congratulations to her who as President of the Philippines would have the heavy responsibility of fulfilling the wishes of the Philippine people.  Reaffirming their belief that democratic processes must be respected the Twelve stated that they would continue to support the forces of democracy in the Philippines.  They welcomed the fact that President Marcos had decided to step down and were confident that this action would contribute to the restoration of democracy in the Philippines and the promotion of national reconciliation.</P>
    <P>In the short time since she has taken office President Aquino has begun the process of national reconciliation bringing her country back to the full enjoyment of human rights.  She has established a special investigation committee into human rights abuses under the Marcos regime.  Other important steps include the release of many political prisoners and the dissolution of certain military units and private armies.  Of particular significance was the announcement of the full restoration of the right of <i>habeas corpus,</i> a right which, in our view, constitutes one of the simplest and most efficient barriers against human rights abuses.</P>
    <P>On 25 March 1986 President Aquino declared a provisional constitution to replace the Marcos 1973 martial law constitution. Under it the Philippine National Assembly, dominated by the party of Mr. Marcos, has been abolished. Mrs. Aquino has announced her intention to draw up a new constitution within a few months.  She has since appointed a commission to undertake this task.  As I understand it the new constitution will then be submitted to the people for approval in a plebiscite prior to parliamentary elections within one year.  The speed with which these actions have been <Col N="268" /> taken and the time-scale for the completion of the commission's work are welcome evidence of President Aquino's determination to re-establish fully democratic institutions of Government as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>At the economic and social level the Philippine Government also face the exceedingly difficult and complex task of reconstuction.  This includes coping with a large foreign debt and budget deficit, combatting corruption, improving labour relations, taking measures to increase employment, dealing with the communist insurgency and many other very serious problems.  Rescuing the Philippines from years of economic decline and political corruption is a formidable challenge. There are encouraging indications that the country's foreign creditors, appreciative of the Government's determination to tackle the debt problem, are prepared to seek means of assisting the Philippines in its efforts to reduce its financial liabilities.</P>
    <P>Last month President Aquino introduced a significant change in labour laws guaranteeing, <i>inter alia,</i> a minimum of Government interference in labour dispute and encouraging employees to form unions.  She has also cut prices of petroleum products in a move to boost the purchasing power of consumers and increase industrial activity.  It is to be hoped that these first measures in the industrial field will generate enough response to enable the President to progress to further measures for economic development.</P>
    <P>At their meeting of 12 May 1986 the Twelve Foreign Ministers of the member states of the European Communities discussed current developments in the situation in the Philippines and welcomed the efforts of the Philippine Government to promote the economic and social development of the country.  They agreed to examine the possibility of providing Community and/or bilateral aid in this process.  For our part, although it is not one of our priority aid targets and lies outside Africa to which, for very good reasons, most of our aid is directed, we have indicated that we would be prepared <Col N="269" /> to examine sympathetically any specific project which might be put to us for assistance to the Philippines.</P>
    <P>President Aquino's Government are faced with the fact that they have practically no money.  A great deal was spent on the 1986 election and there is a foreign debt of 26 billion dollars and little improvement is in prospect for the prices for the basic commodities which in the past were the source of the Philippines' relative prosperity until the seventies.</P>
    <P>The Aquino administration have said that their primary concern is going to be to build the agricultural framework of the country and to feed their own people. The emphasis on agriculture being put by the new Philippine Government comes back to the old problem of land reform. The Communist New People's Army have given as a condition for their laying down arms that new land reform should be undertaken.  But land reform is a slow and difficult process, if it is to be done fairly, and it is hard to see the Government being able to take quick and just decisions in that area.</P>
    <P>One of the keys to the future economy is whether the Philippine businessmen who sent their money abroad in recent years will repatriate it.  It is still thought that the economy in the Philippines could contract this year.  It dropped by approximately ten per cent in 1984 and 1985 combined.  1987 may be the first year in which it may begin to grow again but this will depend a great deal on commodity prices &mdash; sugar, copper, coconut, timber, palm oil etc.</P>
    <P>In my view the success of Mrs. Aquino so far can be outlined as follows.  Perhaps the first success which is worthy of mention is Mrs. Aquino herself, who appears to be as popular as ever.  Secondly, a certain amount has already been achievred in identifying, if not laying their hands on, the Marcos money hidden abroad. Thirdly, Finance Minister Ongpin and Central Bank Governor Fernandez appear to be having some success with the nation's creditors and looking for a better deal for the country's debts. Fourthly, a certain amount of confidence seems to have returned to the business <Col N="270" /> sector and at least some money of Filipino businessmen is being repatriated.  The peso has strengthened, and the Manila stock exchange has shown big gains. Fifthly, within hours of President Aquino's victory, there was complete freedom of the media and press in the Philippines.</P>
    <P>However, a serious threat to her is posed by the Communist New People's Army.  At first it appeared that President Aquino's appeal for an end to fighting would be heeded by the rebels.  But they are now saying they will not lay down their arms, and they insist <i>a priori</i> on land reform, and other conditions.  There have been many clashes between them and the military.  I have seen press reports that the military are refusing to co-operate with President Aquino's call for a ceasefire and are refusing to recognise any local ceasefire agreements.  If true, this is a very disturbing development which I hope will be resolved as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>Senators Bulbulia and Lynch asked me to say a word about the American bases on the Philippines.  I think what Senator Bulbulia said about them is correct especially in regard to what are termed as the recreation areas and the influence for what is not good, to put it at its very mildest, which emanates into those recreation areas.  They have agreements dating up to 1991 and the President has said she will look at them again at that stage.  This will be a very difficult choice for the President and I presume at that stage there will be a democratically formed Government.  It will be a very difficult choice for them to make at that stage.  There are two very big bases, perhaps the biggest the American Government have outside their own territory. They are easily the most important bases the Americans have in that part of the world.  There is a lot of personnel involved. The bases are of financial assistance to the Philippines.  More important than that, they are of strategic importance to the American Government in the military sense and the American Government in the financial sense, is strategically important to the Philippine Government. <Col N="271" /> They are caught in a difficult position. They find it difficult to reconstruct their economy and to restructure their debts without the assistance of the American Government who see the bases in the Philippines as being very important to them militarily.  It is not an easy choice that Mrs. Aquino and her Government will have to make in approximately four year's time.  The basic problem is that these bases would not be the problem they are in the Philippines if in the past the disparities and the incomes of the Filipino people themselves had been levelled out so that there was not a huge mass of very poor people who took any kind of largesse no matter from where it was distributed.  That is not a criticism by any means.  Understandably if they had been working, well-fed, well housed and earning salaries the temptations of the recreational bases would not have been there.  I do not pretend to have a solution nor would I dream of giving advice to the Filipino people as to how they should treat these bases because I recognise the very difficult position in which they are. I would hope that when they come to make their decision they will have built their economy and got over some of their economic problems so that they will be able to come to a conclusion about what they should do about the time beyond 1991 without the pressure of economic necessity with the United States remaining. I hope they will be able to make it in a genuine spirit of friendship for the United States and in partnership with them in other fields.</P>
    <P>In conclusion I fully endorse the terms of the motion before us.  The Philippines have opened a new chapter and we wish President Aquino well in her very difficult task ahead.  I thank Senator Bulbulia for the opportinity she has given this House to debate what I consider to be a very important motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackFitzsimons" hpid="Mr. Fitzsimons Mr. Fitzsimons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzsimons</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to have the opportunity of making my contribution on this very important motion.  It is one with which we are in total agreement. I would like to pay tribute to Senator <Col N="272" /> Bulbulia's contribution.  The Minister and Senator Lynch have already done so.  I know that Senator Bulbulia always speaks on matters of social deprivation with great feeling.  I found her contribution very moving as I invariably do.  While listening to her the time passed very quickly which is a good yardstick to measure the interest which is involved in a contribution.</P>
      <P>I would like to refer to a few matters raised by Senator Bulbulia.  She spoke of her great personal pleasure when she had the greatest experience of her political career when in January she visited the Philippines prior to the elections.  Indeed it would be a great experience for anybody. As she said the whole world waited with bated breath during all that terrible time.  She is proud that the revolution was successful without too much blood being shed.  We all concur with that.  Senator Bulbulia referred to Cory Aquino as a beloved figure.  She stated, if I recall it correctly, that people know what she is against but it has yet to be established what she stands for.  In a sense during that period coming up to the elections the politics involved personal tirades.  During that time Cory Aquino was well able to hold her own.  Marcos criticised her political inexperience and she definitely turned it around and said she had no experience in lying, cheating, stealing or assassinating her political opponents.  In that sense we certainly know what she stands for.  She stands for justice, for civil rights and liberty.  I realise these are the specifics that Senator Bulbulia spoke about but in general we do know that she stands for everything that is right.  She and the Filipino people need moral support. In a sense that is why I stand up here with some trepidation to make my contribution this evening in the presence of the distinguished Minister and Senator Bulbulia who is so knowledgeable in this area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To me the objective of a full blown democratic republic before the end of this year is something that is impossible to achieve but I suppose it is an ideal.  It is admirable and we hope it will come in the near future, possibly not in such a <Col N="273" /> short space of time.  The guerrilla war which is raging and threatens her position is something that is a cause of grave concern. The bloodless victory which was achieved by Cory Aquino after the election should be an example to all those who use arms.  It might influence the guerrillas and hopefully bring about a peaceful situation.</P>
    <P>Senator Bulbulia spoke about the shanty town she visited and I know, of course, that these are caused again by deprivation and poverty.  We are told that in those shanty towns, in spite of the deprivation, there is enormous pride and social concern and a high standard of morality and that many of the shanty towns subsequently develop on the lines on which they have grown up.  Perhaps this will happen in the near future there too.  I hope indeed it will.  It is sad to see such extreme affluence and extreme poverty side by side.</P>
    <P>With regard to the two bases, and if there is time I will return to those again, I would certainly share Senator Bulbulia's concern and I too would say that the price that is being paid for this strategy in terms of human misery in the instances that the Senator spoke about is far too high.  I would like too to pay tribute, along with Senator Michael Lynch, to all the missionaries who work and have worked there over the years, missionaries of every religion.  I suppose in particular I should pay special tribute to the Columban Fathers who are established at Dalgan Park, County Meath, which I pass every time I am coming to Dublin and indeed quite a few of whom I know personally.  Father Paddy Reilly is one from my neighbouring parish of Moynalty who has suffered and done wonderful work on the foreign missions.</P>
    <P>With regard to the Minister's contribution, we were all overjoyed at the release of Fr. Niall O'Brien and I would like to compliment the Government on their efforts in that regard.  The disappearance of Fr. Rudi Romano is unfortunate and I hope and pray that there will be a satisfactory outcome in his case as well.</P>
    <P>If I could refer very briefly to what I might call the history of the rise of Cory <Col N="274" /> Aquino.  On 26 February 1986, 20 years rule by President Marcos came to an end. Just three days before that the Defence Minister and the Acting Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces, Lt. General Fidel Ramos &mdash; and Senator Bulbulia put a question mark after him with regard to his conversion &mdash; rebelled and called for the resignation of Senator Marcos.  That was the beginning of the end and Marcos and his family fled to Guam in a United States Air Force jet.  The provisional government of President Aquino was immediately recognised by the United States.</P>
    <P>The peaceful transition of power occurred after what was regarded as the most fraudulent and violent presidential election in the history of the Philippines. An official United States delegation sent by President Reagan to observe the February 7th elections returned with firsthand information of the widespread fraud and the voters intimidation by the forces of President Marcos.  It was stated by them that the Government had come upon a strategy of trying to shape the results.  It was a rather quaint and metaphorical way to describe cheating the election results.  They referred to the disappearance of the voter lists and several other irregularities.  Those misgivings were confirmed when 30 computer technicians working at the Government's Commission on Election left their jobs. This was a significant factor in the resignation of President Marcos and it is easy to speculate as to what would happen if they had not done so.  Tribute should be paid to their integrity and their courage in doing what they did.  Of course Marcos was embarrassed and he tried to organise the election to the Government of the Batasan Parliament which formed two-thirds of the Government to declare himself officially the winner.  This failed through the watchdog group of nearly 500,000 volunteers who monitored the election and presumably were doing the same kind of work that Senator Bulbulia had tried to do.  They came to the conclusion that Cory Aquino had won the election by the margin that President Marcos had claimed.  Following that there was the <Col N="275" /> campaign that Senator Bulbulia spoke about.  It was a non-violent campaign of civil disobedience.  There was a threat of withholding taxes, a boycott of regime supported business establishments.  It has also been stated that there was&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has three minutes left.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackFitzsimons" hpid="Mr. Fitzsimons Mr. Fitzsimons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzsimons</NameTxt>
      <P>Time passes very quickly.  I am glad that the Catholic Church supported President Aquino at that time too.  Could I just make one quotation in conclusion seeing that I will not be able to develop any point.  It is a paragraph from <i>Current History</i> published April 1896:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One of the most dramatic developments in Philippine society over the last decade has been the emergence of the left as a major political force.  This development is also one of the most misunderstood, if not misrepresented, particularly by Western sources, which invariably emphasise the &ldquo;Communist&rdquo; nature of the insurgency.  The movement reportedly counts between 12,000 and 15,000 armed regulars operating in 59 of the country's 73 provinces. It is important to remember, however, that the opposition from the left includes far more than Communist cadres, although the Philippine Communist party is the largest leftist group. The leftist opposition wants to eliminate United States military bases and abrogate all &ldquo;unequal treaties&rdquo; with the United States; it opposes the massive and unregulated flow of foreign investments and the heavy reliance on foreign loans; and it advocates structural economic reforms, especially with regard to ownership and control of the means of production.  It believes that these ends can be attained only through the mobilization of the masses and it asserts that armed struggle is a legitimate mode of political behaviour. Francisco Nemenzo stresses the poly-centric character of the Philippine left, which includes three ideological <Col N="276" /> streams: Marxist, Christian and Islamic.</P>
    <P>I was glad to get an opportunity to contribute to the debate.  We welcome the motion.  Once again I would like to pay tribute to Senator Bulbulia for her contribution.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>Earlier this evening I formally seconded this motion and did not make use of my right to speak at that particular point in the debate.  I did this for a particular reason, because I thought it would be more appropriate in debating a motion like this if both on this, the first evening of the debate, and a week from now, on the second evening of the debate, there were contributions from as many groups as possible in the House.  I now find myself speaking because, despite all that is said to the contrary, particularly on the Order of Business, when the press are paying particular attention and the items reported are liable to get into the newspapers, we heard a number of Independent Senators in this House expressing criticism of the work done by the major parties in the House.  Yet we find ourselves here this evening with the whole burden of discussing this important issue borne by these parties.  When it really comes down to discussing, not just the Order of Business or the little points that are going to get attention, but this most remarkable event which has occurred in the Philippines, here we find&mdash; I am referring to the parties not the individuals &mdash; it is left to the two old war horses to carry on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The events which occurred in the Philippines are some of the more remarkable political developments that we have seen in our generation.  I was lucky enough at the critical time that I was fulfilling lecture engagements in the United States to be able to see the massive television coverage of the events and the very detailed commentary.  Thinking back on that and thinking back on what has happened in the Philippines, what did strike me then and what still strikes me now is what a remarkable thing happened.  Were these various turning points accidental or were they inherent in the situation?  What <Col N="277" /> is interesting here is watching not just democracy at work, not just a once democratic leader like Marcos having become corrupt both in the political and financial sense and also an abandoned democracy being overthrown but also the democratic process in the United States. Because what happened within the democratic process in the United States was as important as what was happening in the democratic process in the Philippines. There are many questions that we can ask ourselves about this.  Why did Marcos not order his troops to fire in the early days?  Why did he not clear out that first small barracks that held a few hundred men?  Was it that this ailing, elderly man had now lost his nerve or was it that he was receiving blunt warnings from the United States?</P>
    <P>We must pay tribute to those politicans of the United States who made an extremely real contribution to the solution of this problem.  It is only appropriate that we here in the Seanad should pay tribute to a Senator who played a very key role, Senator Lugar, not a man of leftish tendencies by any standard&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Not at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and perhaps not very favourable to some of the things which we cherish at this particular moment, but I wonder, if Senator Lugar had not kept an open mind, had not looked with a clear eye at what was happening in the Philippines in the immediate aftermath of that corrupt election, whether we would have had the peaceful transition to power.  I am sure the Minister hopes that his eyes will be similarly opened in regard to other issues which could affect us more directly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I am trying to aid the process.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>What we have seen here is an illustration of something which we have always assumed to be relatively simple such as this process of democracy and which seems to be merely a question that we go out and vote now and then <Col N="278" /> and things carry on, both in effect, any attempt to apply this in a society like the Philippines or South East Asia, in a vast hegemony such as the United States or in our own State is a most complicated process.  We had here a splendid example of democracy winning out.  We have had here an example for many countries of the Third World, for many countries in South East Asia, for many countries in Central and South America, but if they were to follow that example too blindly the result might indeed be very different.</P>
      <P>We have a responsibility here in discussing with representatives of those other countries to be careful in how we express admiration for what happened in the Philippines lest we should give the impression that all that is needed is to crowd into the streets and to face the military.  If we do this we may well be encouraging people to their deaths. Every one of these unfortunate countries of the Third World which are economically backward, politically dominated by self-interested individuals and groups, is going to have to find their political salvation in their own way.  Having said that we have here in the Philippines, in this most remarkable development, as it were a case study from which so many valuable lessons can be learned.  It might well be that if we look close enough we could find lessons, not direct lessons but indirect lessons about&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Leader of the House move the Adjournment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very unkind to be asked to move it in mid-sentence but I must bow to you.  I move the adjournment of the debate.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. - County" RHead="Galway Schools Amalgamation">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - County Galway Schools Amalgamation.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I will take this opportunity of wishing the Minister well in his new post because it is a difficult one.  It is nice <Col N="279" /> to see a west of Ireland man getting the job and I hope that Deputy Kenny will have many happy years in that position &mdash; that is, of course, if the next general election does not come between him and that happiness.</P>
      <P>I want to thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for the tolerance you showed last week in a very precarious situation and to assure you that anything I have ever said in this House was never said by way of offence to you personally.  I was complaining about the regulations of this House and not about you personally in case I might have been misinterpreted.</P>
      <P>We are discussing a matter this evening of serious concern to the community of Corrandulla.  Corrandulla is a renowned parish in County Galway.  I am sure you will all remember the famous poems about Anach Chuain which is part of the parish of Corrandulla.  This time last year the Minister's predecessor, Deputy Donal Creed &mdash; a very fine Minister and a man for whom I have great respect &mdash; was here at my request to answer a similar question.  He gave a remarkable performance here in the House in consolidating the situation from a ministerial point of view on what the Department's feelings were concerning Corrandulla schools.  At that time the major question was, and, sad to say, still is, the amalgamation of the two schools in Corrandulla.  To explain it a little more, the then Minister said on that occasion that the amalgamation should take place in 1985.  The community of Corrandulla and I were very satisfied with that response and certain promises regarding other matters &mdash; which I will deal with later &mdash; also came into play that evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will deal first with the question of amalgamation because that is the primary concern of that community.  The people of Corrandulla and the school management board are placed in a most peculiar situation &mdash; and I sympathise with them &mdash; in that the need for a new school is paramount but in the circumstances and having regard to the financial constraints the idea of building a new school seems <Col N="280" /> to have been shelved for the moment.  I will deal with that later, too.</P>
    <P>The two schools which would be involved in the amalgamation are the boys' national school and the girls' national school which are in two different town-lands but only about 250 or 300 yards apart.  There are eight classes in the two schools, four in each.  The request is that, taking into account the Department's desire and the community's desire for amalgamation, they would retain their eight teachers.  At the moment there are 219 children on the rolls; there will be more if amalgamation takes place next year and there may be fewer if amalgamation does not take place.  That is an optimistic viewpoint.</P>
    <P>The chairman of the board of management, Father O'Brien &mdash; a very fine parish priest &mdash; has made many visits to the Department to try to iron out the problem, his most recent visit being last Monday week.  His case, which is a very reasonable one, is that they are entitled with 219 children to have seven teachers under amalgamation, plus one for amalgamation, which is eight teachers, but the problem is that if one of the teachers were to leave either of the schools they would then only be entitled to seven teachers.  The board of management made the fair request that until such time as the new school in Corrandulla is built they would be guaranteed eight teachers. This was sought for many reasons, the principal one being that they would have a teacher for each class.  Taking into account the geographical location of the two schools, it would be absolutely impossible if the two schools were amalgamated due to the distance between the two schools for seven teachers to operate the eight classes.  That does not demand a wild imagination.</P>
    <P>The board of management, the community and I made a very reasonable request to the Department in asking, if until such time as a new school is built, the Department would guarantee that if any member of the present teaching staff left he or she would be replaced.  That is a very reasonable request because of the fact that the schools are separated by <Col N="281" /> approximately 250 yards.  In a telephone call to the Department last week I was given the impression that if any teacher left in the next 12 months consideration would be given by the Department to the replacement of the teacher.  My question was, of course, would that replacement be until such time as a new school is built? I got no response to that question from the person I was speaking to in the Minister's office but I assumed it to be in the affirmative.  However, the chairman of the school management board was in the Department the previous day and he subsequently received a letter &mdash; which I did not get &mdash; of confirmation from which I will quote:</P>
    <P>Should a vacancy arise in the 1986-87 school year the Department, in the special circumstances of the school, would give favourable consideration to the appointment of a replacement temporary assistance up until the end of the 1986-87 school year.</P>
    <P>That is not acceptable and hence this matter is on the Adjournment of the House tonight.  It would be impossible for seven teachers to operate in two separate schools in an amalgamation process.  I would ask the Minister to give due consideration to that point.  I would ask him to change the ending of that letter, delete &ldquo;up until the end of the 1986-87 school year&rdquo; and insert &ldquo;until the new school in Corrandulla be built&rdquo;.  That would resolve the problem regarding amalgamation.</P>
    <P>I do not know if any of the teachers are going to leave but if they are I assume they will leave within the year.  The school management board asked that the term should be within three years but I think they would be satisified if they were guaranteed an eight-teacher school until the new school is built.  I know the Minister is a reasonable person and understands what I am saying.  I hope he will respond accordingly because there is a great deal of hysteria being generated in the parish. I am sorry to say there is much division in the community over this issue, because people are confused.  There are many people waiting for the Minister's <Col N="282" /> response tonight and I hope he makes it in a very positive way, so that the matter will be closed.</P>
    <P>I would like to go on then to the second matter.  I wrote a letter to the Department as early as last February listing five points in a letter to which I asked the Minister to respond.  The second matter raised was if amalgamation takes place, taking into account that we are in two separate grounds and two separate townlands, would the Department consider giving an allocation of money for the girls' school to have a boys' toilet provided?  This is a natural, normal requirement.  I also asked if in the boy's school we could have a girls' toilet.  It is as simple as that.  I know that a certain Deputy in our county got his lines crossed and thought we were being given a big extension to the Corrandulla National School.  I suppose it was given by a hint or a nod or a wink.  Obviously, he did not know the real problems of Corrandulla, and hence he ran off to press thinking he had a great scoop.  In fact, he found out the scoop was not what he thought it was and he got into rather stormy waters over it.  But that is the reality of the problem.</P>
    <P>The strange thing is that the Minister we have here tonight wrote a letter to the board of management.  I was not afforded the courtesy of getting it myself, even though I made representations about it I suppose it will come in another week's time.  I would like to make the point that the Minister was apparently confused also because he granted one of the toilets and he did not grant the other.  I would like him to clear the air on that matter: I do not want to make a joke of it.  It is a serious matter.  You cannot have the boys and girls in one school having toilets and only the girls in the other, or <i>vice versa.</i></P>
    <P>The other burning question is the matter of the building of the new school in Corrandulla itself.  We were told here last year that there were no plans and no application had been made for that school.  The statement to me by the then Minister, Deputy Creed &mdash; I quote from the Seanad Report of that time &mdash; states clearly that no application had been made.  That was denied vigorously by the <Col N="283" /> board of management and by many responsible people in Corrandulla.  I am afraid I have to believe the people of Corrandulla against the Minister because some mix-up has happened in the Department, or they have become confused. When I think about the confusion regarding the toilets, I would not be surprised. I would like that matter to be clarified now.  Is there, or is there not an application for a new amalgamated school for boys and girls in Corrandulla? It is badly needed.  There was a time last year when the children were taught in the local hall up on the stage.  I thought it was a bit too much that in 1985 such a situation would obtain in this country at all, much less in Corrandulla, such a renowned parish.</P>
    <P>Next there is the question of playgrounds. It might not be a very important question now, taking into account the serious situation as regards amalgamation, but it is nonetheless very important to have playing facilities for the children. I hope the Department will include, when they are building the new school, a complete facility for a community which is on the environs of Galway city.  The population is growing rapidly in that parish and I believe only the best is adequate for the people.  Generally speaking, that is a normal request for any public representative to make on behalf of any school anywhere in this country.  They are as much entitled to it there as they are in any other place.  I hope that the Minister will give serious consideration to that request.</P>
    <P>It should not be &mdash; and I say this honestly &mdash; the job of politicians to have to come to the Oireachtas to press for a response to such needs.  I am absolutely amazed that the Department would have allowed this situation to develop to the present stage.  I know from the indications I get from talking to the officials in the Department that they are probably in a slightly confused state as regards the whole operation.  Different messages, it seems, are being sent but in order to bring it all to a point and to clarify the whole situation the Minister should give <Col N="284" /> us the amalgamation so that work can start.  We must remember if we do not get the OK from the Minister tonight, amalgamation cannot start in 1986, because planning permission has to be obtained.  That is a two months programme at least.</P>
    <P>I would appreciate if the Minister would take it upon himself tonight to allow the amalgamation to start in 1986; it was promised in 1985.  If he could make that announcement tonight this matter would be clarified and it would bring to an end the politicising of the circumstances in a parish that is in need of so much and particularly from the schooling point of view.  The parish is well known to the Minister himself personally and he knows what I am talking about.  I want to thank him for coming here tonight and I want to thank you a Chathaoirligh for allowing me the time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EndaKenny" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Kenny) Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Kenny)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Education (Mr. Kenny)</NameTxt>
      <P>Ba mhaith liom ar dtús mo bhuíochas a ghlacadh leis an Seanadóir Killilea as ucht é seo a chur ar an gclár.  Bí cinnte go n-inseoidh mé go díreach an fhírinne faoin fhadhb seo.</P>
      <P>I want to say at the outset we deal in the primary section with many schools throughout the country.  The problems vary from school to school.  Many are in a state of completion.  Many are nearing completion; some are near tender and some have various problems related to them.  Corrandulla, as I am well aware, is about 12 miles from Galway city and is in the Archdiocese of Tuam.  There are two primary schools there; one serves girls and the other boys.  They are about 150 yards apart, separated by a cemetary and by a building owned by the Franciscans. Growth in enrolments enabled the creation of new teaching posts in recent years, so that there are now four teachers in each school.  The boys' school was built in 1947.  It is a three-classroom building. The fourth teacher is housed in a general purposes room which was added in 1978 as a result of representations having been made over the previous period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The girls' school was built about 1930 and is also a three-classroom building.  A <Col N="285" /> pre-fabricated building was provided to accommodate the fourth class in 1985.  In that year £18,000 was spent on accommodation and repairs to the school and substantial grant towards the cost was sanctioned by the Department.  Over the years, the Department of Education had proposed the amalgamation of the two schools in the educational interest of the pupils.  These proposals did not find favour with the management and parents.  In April 1985 the boards of management indicated that all parties concerned now favoured amalgamation.  The target date of 2 September, 1985 did not prove possible in view of some practical difficulties that arose and amalgamation was postponed until after the Christmas holidays, 1985.  Subsequently, at the request of the chairperson of the board of management it was agreed that amalgamation be further deferred until the start of the 1986-87 school year.</P>
    <P>The general conditions governing school amalgamation or reorganisation provide for the retention of one teacher more than the enrolments would normally allow.  This concession applies only to staff serving at the time of amalgamation. If, after amalgamation, a teacher retires, resigns or dies, the concession ceases and such a teacher can be replaced only if warranted by the normal pupil-teacher ratio.  In this case there would be about 220 pupils in the amalgamated school at the start.  This would normally support a staff of seven teachers.  There are at present eight teachers between the two schools.  Under the special concession I have referred to we could retain all eight teachers for as long as the average daily enrolment of all the pupils for the preceeding year did not fall below 210. But should any vacancy in the staff occur an average enrolment of 245 would be necessary to allow and sanction a replacement.</P>
    <P>In a question tabled for answer today in Dáil Éireann, in which a guarantee was sought for the employment of eight teachers over the next five years as part of the amalgamation of Corrandulla schools, the Minister for Education <Col N="286" /> replied that the appointment and retention of teachers in amalgamated schools are subject to regulations which are of general application and that it was not possible therefore to give the assurances sought in regard to staffing over the five year period.  That remains the position.  I recognise, of course, that there may be some difficulty and inconvenience in the matter of school organisation where a school is conducted in separate buildings at some distance removed but this could not be accepted as warranting a departure from the requirements of the rules for national schools.</P>
    <P>If it were possible to make an exception for, say, one year, it would mean that instead of effecting savings by suppressing a post, as the rules would require, we would have a surplus teacher in the school until the next vacancy occurred.  This might not happen for several years at a salary average cost of about £14,000 per year.  While a specially favourable pupil-teacher ratio would be to the educational benefit of the pupils in Corrandulla or in any school it has to be borne in mind that the primary purpose of the concession is to safeguard the posts of the local teachers involved in amalgamation and to facilitate the amalgamation.  It is already quite generous; so no limit is set on the length of time that a surplus teacher may be continued in the central school provided the appropriate retention average is maintained for the previous school year.  The expense involved is quite considerable and the present request would make it much more so.  A very undesirable precedent would be set as word of the Corrandulla concession would spread through the managers and teachers unions.  It would then become a basic condition of local agreement in any other amalgamation case.  To concede it in these cases would be very costly and would require Department of Finance sanction, as the Senator is well aware.  In this context it would have to be borne in mind that while amalgamations are mainly for educational reasons, financial savings can accrue from them so that they are to be encouraged both from the <Col N="287" /> financial point of view and from the educational point of view.</P>
    <P>Special circumstances have been pleaded.  Senator Killilea has made a case which would militate against amalgamation. The fact that the two school buildings are 100 yards or more apart could make for some difficulty in the immediate aftermath of amalgamation.  This, of itself, would not however, justify a departure from the general requirements of the rules for national schools.  However, it is fairly normal official procedure, where a school loses a teacher during the school year and a successor cannot be appointed, to consider representations from the school management for a temporary appointment until the end of the school year in order to avoid undue disruption of classes in mid-term.  Each application is naturally considered on its merits and in the light of a special report from the inspector.  Such a concession would fall far short of what is demanded for Corrandulla but, realistically, is the most that could be granted even if it proves so unacceptable that it might jeopardise the amalgamation.</P>
    <P>Senator Killilea has referred to the necessity for facilities with regard to toilet blocks.  I have examined this matter carefully because it deserves careful examination. The Senator may take it for granted that I am aware that the amalgamation will naturally necessitate building work at both schools, especially with the provision of toilets in what were previously single sex buildings.  The Department have now authorised in very clear English that a boys' toilet block will be provided in the girls' school and a girls' toilet block will be provided in the boys' school.  I have personally signed the letter to the good Senator and to his colleagues, authorising sanction of this.  He should have it for his own good use in the Corrandulla area within a short time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure you have it already.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EndaKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of the postal regulations in Galway but Senator <Col N="288" /> Killilea was Minister of State at the Department of Posts and Telegraphs and I understand that he was quite adept at particular deliveries in certain areas of the county and he is well aware of the procedures in these matters.</P>
      <P>The amalgamation will proceed on the basis of the physical buildings being provided in terms of toilet blocks in 1986. The amalgamation could not proceed if the toilet blocks were not provided.  I am aware of the desire of the boards of management in both areas.  In fact I met representatives of one of the boards of management some time ago when they came to me in a neighbouring town about the new school in Corrandulla.</P>
      <P>My predecessor, Deputy Creed, stated in the House here that a new building would be the ideal solution.  On 10 July, 1985, he said:</P>
      <P>Ideally there should be a new building with modern furniture and equipment but the practicalities of the situation, such as the acquisition of a suitable site and the time necessary for the preparation of plans and contract documents would not allow the immediate achievement of that objective.</P>
      <P>I do not think he stated in the House that an application was not received.  An application is before the Department.  I can assure Senator Killilea and his parliamentary colleagues that there will be no hindrance on that new application, at least until it comes to the time for allocation of tenders and I would hope that the works that have to be gone through at the various stages would be proceeded with as quickly as possible in that area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>When might they build it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EndaKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>They will build it as soon as the contract is placed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>When will that be?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EndaKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot answer that until the various stages have gone through. But no doubt the Senator will have ample opportunity to raise it by way of a Seanad motion again or have some other people <Col N="289" /> raise it in the Dáil.  He is free to contact us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I might be able to raise it in the Dáil soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EndaKenny" hpid="Mr. Kenny Mr. Kenny">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kenny</NameTxt>
      <P>He might even be answering it: I am sure he would like that if he got the opportunity.  I will take him back to his remark about when happiness comes &mdash; that might be a long way off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We will be able to deal with the application for Corrandulla National School on its merits.  It is a priority case from the point of view of staff, parents and management.  To have two buildings <Col N="290" /> 100 yards apart is not an ideal solution from an educational point of view or from a practical point of view.  The application will receive proper consideration.  In the meantime it would be my hope that the amalgamation would proceed.  The authorisation given for the provision of the physical buildings in respect of the toilet blocks has been confirmed officially. I trust that work will proceed as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.30 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 5 June 1986.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>