<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="27" Month="Jun" Year="1946" Vol="32" No="2" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 27 Meitheamh 1946" DateEnglish="Thursday, 27 June 1946" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="111">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="111" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In accordance with the arrangements come to last evening the discussion on the Local Government Bill in Committee will be interrupted at 6 o'clock.  On the resumption of business at 7 p.m., the Committee Stage of the Hire Purchase Bill will be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>And, I presume, will be concluded, if possible?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the idea&mdash;to conclude the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Government Bill," RHead="1945&mdash;Committee (Resumed)">
    <Title>Local Government Bill, 1945&mdash;Committee (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on amendment No. 17.</P>
    <P>At the end of the section to add a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;()  A copy of the report of any local inquiry under sub-section (1) of this section shall be sent to the rating authority concerned at least fourteen days before the issue of a notification under sub-section (2) of this section.&rdquo;&mdash;(Senator Sir John Keane.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>When the train of my thoughts was broken last night by the intervention of Senator Ryan on a point of order, I was trying to develop the background of the past in relation to local government services and the prospects of the future in relation to which the whole of this Section 30 has to be examined.  In so far as the past is concerned, I would not very greatly object to Section 30.  I should like to know from the Minister how many times, within recent years, his Department has been confronted by a refusal to strike an adequate rate and how, in the absence of Section 30, he has acted?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="112" /> I would like to repeat that because, although I do not wish to be discourteous, I have asked so many questions that he has never answered that I would like to know how many times in the past, in recent years, the Minister has been confronted by a refusal on the part of the rating authority to strike an adequate rate, and how he has dealt with the situation? I imagine that such occasions have been very few, and that he has been able to deal adequately with such a situation under his existing powers.  So far as the existing services are concerned, although I object to the principle, I would not be very much concerned at these new powers that he has taken, but I would ask Senators to have in their minds what are the prospects facing us with regard to the possible requirements of the Department of Local Government and Public Health.</P>
    <P>In passing, I must refer to a Bill which has been before the Dáil for some time and which is, I understand, only held up for the moment owing to a certain dislocation in the personnel of the Minister's Department.  Many members of the House will realise what the powers in that Bill are.  The Minister takes power to order a local authority to provide and maintain a health institution of any size or character or with any equipment he may require. There is no provision for consulting such a local authority and there is no indication of the grant from central funds which such local authority is to receive.  I ask the House to accept in general terms the statement that that is a complete departure from the spirit of local government as we have heretofore known it.</P>
    <P>I do not mean to say that services have never been imposed on local authorities.  I do not mean to say that there has ever been any resistance to the imposition of such services, but such resistance has never been strong and the requirements have been, in the main, moderate.  Although there has been a steady tendency towards reaction, centralisation and dictatorship from the centre in local government, that has been slow and gradual and local authorities have got used to the change.  They have usually been consulted <Col N="113" /> and they have accepted any new burdens that came their way.  I remember when such offices as that of tuberculosis officer and public health officer were permissive.  Some councils adopted those services and some councils refused to do so.  When the idea had sunk in, those appointments were made mandatory.  By that gradual method of approach, there was a general feeling of agreement and acceptance.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>May I suggest that the Senator has forgotten that we have passed the Second Reading and that he should speak to the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit that my remarks are entirely appropriate to the conclusions I have reached with regard to the amendment.  I consider that we have to look at this section in relation to a completely different situation from that which confronted us in the past.  We have to face a situation in which burdens of undisclosed and unknown magnitude are to be imposed on local authorities, whether they like it or not.  In fact, the local authorities will have to accept the Minister's dictation in respect of services which, I think, the Minister will not deny will be of considerable magnitude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's remarks apply more to the Public Health Bill, which is not yet before the House than to this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that I have said enough on that point.  I wish to ask the Minister what I have already asked him&mdash;can he give us figures with regard to the total rates raised in the past year, because I have been able to get from official sources only the return of rates for 1942-3.  These are the latest figures given in the <i>Statistical Abstract</i>, the compilers of which have, no doubt, better access to official information than I have.  I have seen figures showing that the burden has risen from £4,000,000 at the outbreak of war to £7,000,000 two years ago.  I should like to know what the rates were last year.  We are very much hampered in examining a section such as this by our ignorance of the burden <Col N="114" /> of rates imposed upon the local authorities.</P>
      <P>In justification of the amendment which I am proposing, I ask the House to appreciate the difference between rates and taxes.  In the main, taxes are paid out of profits.  A person who has made no profits and who does not drink or smoke pays little or no taxes.  Rates are of a completely different character.  They are a charge on the primary producer.  One has to realise that the imposition of rates without the consent of the local elected representatives places a very serious burden on our main industry&mdash;agriculture. Some of us who do not farm do not realise the significance of the matter.  To a man who lives in a small house rates are a matter of little or no significance.  When the burden is heavy, amounting to 10/- or 12/- an acre as a charge on the production of lands, I think the local authority require every protection before such burdens are imposed.  In the past, these burdens were imposed by agreement. We are facing a situation in which such burdens are to be imposed by the ukase of the central Government on top of burdens which are at least&mdash;I am speaking without official information&mdash;100 per cent. higher than they were before the war. The Minister can correct me if I am wrong.  Presumably, he has what we have not, the latest figures.</P>
      <P>The Minister has power to impose in the future services of untold magnitude. He can come along and say to the local authority: &ldquo;If you refuse to supply these services we are going to dissolve you, and appoint our own servants to impose rates on the production of our primary and most important industry, to impose trading charges, working expenses&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is a very serious matter indeed and the Minister proposes to offer as an excuse for such dictatorial action only what I can call the farce of holding an inquiry.  I say it is a farce because under the present Bill the report of the local inquiry is not going to be published.  The local authority is going to be abolished.  That in itself may not matter very much but the manager who is under the direct orders <Col N="115" /> of the central authority is going to have a free hand to impose whatever rates he likes on our primary producers, mainly the members of the agricultural industry.  I say that is an intolerable situation, a complete turn of the wheel from the basis on which local government was founded.  Local government was founded on the idea of service through local elected representatives. It has passed a long way from that original conception of allowing responsibility to local representatives, initiative on the part of local representatives, the fixing of rates by local representatives and the fixing of services by local representatives.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I again in-vene? The Senator's remarks are dealing with the section as a whole, not with the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely, Sir, I am giving the reasons why the report of any inquiry held before the local authority is abolished and the servants of the central authority put in, should be published?  It is all leading up to that.  I am leading up to the very serious state of affairs that will arise when the rating authority is abolished owing to its failure, in the opinion of the Minister, to strike an adequate rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That could be more appropriately dealt with on the section as a whole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit it is within the scope of my amendment.  My amendment is very wide in its purpose but I think I have come to the end of my remarks in any case.  Here we are in this position.  Without cause stated, without trial, without any semblance of judicial procedure, the Minister, as head of the Department, is going to bring about a position which will enable him to impose what burdens he likes on the local authorities.  Before he does that, surely in all reason it is fair that the local authority should have some knowledge of the report on which such high-handed action is likely to be taken. That is the purpose of the amendment, that before the Minister takes power to impose, through the county manager <Col N="116" /> what rates he and the county manager in association see fit, the local authority should know the grounds on which he is acting and that his report should be somewhat in the nature of a quasi-judicial document which will be published and available to the local authority before it is extinguished.  I say the amendment is perfectly reasonable. The Minister will at present not publish any reports.  There was a very disquieting case not long ago where the Minister acted on an undisclosed report and, as some quarters believed, in a manner contrary to the spirit of the report but that is only conjecture.  I say if he wants to put himself right with the local authority and give an answer to the charges that are definitely being made that he is acting in an unreasonable manner, he should publish such reports before he takes action to extinguish a local authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment proposed by Senator Sir John Keane goes considerably further than a more limited amendment to another section which stands in my name but, between them, they propose the only possible alternative to a state of affairs which is now regarded as profoundly unsatisfactory.  Local government inquiries were originally introduced for two purposes.  They were to inform the mind of the Minister as to certain facts which he might have difficulty in ascertaining by himself in the secrecy of his own office and they were made public inquiries in order that the public might have the same opportunity of knowing the evidence on which findings of fact could be based as the Minister himself might have.  It was understood, and it has been believed for a long time, that the Minister would act upon the findings of fact made by the person whom he put in charge of the inquiry.  That was the original object and for a long time it was the practice, but the state of affairs which now has arisen is that, rightly or wrongly, a public local inquiry is associated in the minds of most people with a previous Ministerial determination to achieve a certain state of affairs, an inquiry which has no effect whatsoever upon assisting the Minister to make up his mind, because that mind is already <Col N="117" /> made up, but which operates merely as a smoke-screen to conceal the fact that the action has been predetermined.  I may be right or I may be wrong, but that is the belief of the majority of the citizens of this country, a belief which certain matters referred to by Senator Sir John Keane have helped to augment.  I think that in the present juncture it is not open to me to lend point or pungency to my remarks by further references, so I shall omit them and deal with the matter purely in the abstract.</P>
      <P>There has been an amazing amount of clotted nonsense talked on the subject of these inquiries and I regret to say that a very appreciable portion of it has emanated from the Minister's Department.  It has been suggested that these inquiries are judicial inquiries.  They are not judicial inquiries.  It has been denied that they are quasi-judicial inquiries.  They are quasi-judicial inquiries.  They possess all the elements of a judicial inquiry except one and that is a very important one which, in fairness to the Minister, must be always stressed. They involve an investigation of facts by the well-known method which centuries of experience in courts of law have shown to be best for ascertaining those facts.  They involve to a certain degree opposite parties.  They involve considerations of law and they involve the presentation of views as to facts and views as to law by the persons concerned.  In all those respects they are the same as a full judicial inquiry, but there the resemblance ceases.</P>
      <P>In a judicial inquiry the determination of the action which arises out of the facts found rests with the person who is in control of that inquiry.  In other words, it is the judge presiding in a court of law who not merely hears the evidence and decides the facts with or without the help of a jury, but it is he who determines what is to be done in view of those facts.  That element is completely absent from these local inquiries.  It is the Minister who decides what eventually must be done and, therefore, it is absurd to call them judicial inquiries and it is equally absurd to withdraw from them the name of quasi-judicial inquiries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now, what is the position?  The <Col N="118" /> Minister is in complete charge of what is to be done.  It is his discretion and it his responsibilty, and for that he answers only to the Oireachtas and, more particularly, to the Dáil.  But in so far as the facts are to be ascertained by judicial methods the Minister ought to be bound by the findings of fact as found by the person who takes the inquiry, and that for two reasons.  It is only the person who takes the inquiry and hears the witnesses who can form a correct view as to the reliability of the witnesses.  It is only that person who knows when he is satisfied and when he desires further information, and even if the Minister were a trained lawyer it would not lie in his mouth to refuse to accept the conclusions of fact come to by an inspector or other person who is taking the inquiry.</P>
    <P>Observe now that I say &ldquo;conclusions of fact&rdquo;.  The evidence adduced is a completely different thing from the conclusions of fact which are based upon that evidence.  The mere publication of evidence or the mere admission of the public does not cure the evils of the refusal to disclose what were the conclusions of the one person who can draw conclusions from the evidence which has been adduced before him.  There can be very little doubt that when these inquiries were first inaugurated the intention was that just as the inquiry itself was public so the conclusions of the person acting in a quasi-judicial office should also be made public.  It is quite obvious to everybody I think that the Minister will not come here and arrogate to himself any particular right to be able to judge evidence from a written print, but in fact unless those portions of the report which deal with conclusions of fact are published the Minister has a free hand to disregard anything which is put before him.  I say that when these inquiries were first inaugurated, although there was no particular provision that the inspector's report should be published, I consider that that was probably the intention.</P>
    <P>Let us now skip the years to a period when the matter had to be considered as to whether it was or was not desirable that the report should be <Col N="119" /> made public.  Departments, not merely the Department of Local Government in this country, but other Departments in this country and other Departments in other countries have found it very convenient to keep reports secret.  It was not a universal rule.  Reports were published, but it was found convenient to have the power to keep them secret. The matter was considered at length by eight judges, the contention being the somewhat absurd one that as the law then stood no adverse decision could be given unless as an indispensable prerequisite the Department concerned published the report.</P>
    <P>Now, that was an untenable legal proposition at the time, but of the eight judges who considered the question one only was of opinion that publication of the inspector's report would, as a general rule, be undesirable. Of the eight judges who considered it, three were in favour of the general practice of always publishing the inspector's report, four judges were of the opinion that though there should be no general rule that the inspector's report should be published, yet that in many cases, or in most cases, it was in the public interest and it was desirable that publication should be made.  Now, that is a summary of the views of the eight judges who were concerned in Arlidge's case. The matter did not rest there, because it was referred to a select committee of exceedingly eminent publicists in England who considered, amongst other things, the question of Ministerial tribunals.  That report, which recent events have made quite familiar to the people of this country, was the Donoughmore Report.</P>
    <P>Now, that report, first of all, at page 73, gives substantially the definition of judicial and quasi-judicial tribunals which I have given in shortened form to the House.  Secondly, it came to consider, after having put before it all the arguments for and against publication of inspectors' reports, whether it was or was not, all things considered, desirable.  I would like to read a short extract from that publication. It deals, first of all, with the arguments for and against publication <Col N="120" /> and it comes to the following conclusions:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;To these various arguments for and against publication we have given prolonged consideration and on balance have come to the conclusion that publication is right.  By that we do not mean that the expense of printing a long report should in every case be incurred; but that in all cases the report of the inspector should be made available to the parties concerned and to the Press, and in important cases should be officially published by the Department responsible for the inquiry.</P>
    <P>We fully appreciate the importance of not undermining the confidential relationship between the Minister and his officials and, however strong the case for publication in order to allay a public suspicion, we should, in the public interest, resist the demand for publication if any such consequence were, in our judgment, likely to ensue.</P>
    <P>We have considered the question whether the inspector or other person who holds the public inquiry should be entitled to make a confidential report to the Minister in addition to the report for publication.  In our opinion this should never be done in the case of an inquiry preliminary to a judicial decision.  If judicial decisions are to be given by Ministers at all, it is essential that they should be given as far as possible in accordance with the forms of justice and that nothing should reach the ears of the judge behind the backs of the parties. Most inquiries, however, are held in connection with quasi-judicial decisions and in the case of such inquiries, we do not take so strict a view.  Whilst we think that there should be no confidential reports on those matters of fact or law which come strictly within the scope of the report of the inquiry, we see no objection to the tendering by separate report or otherwise of such advice as the Minister may call for on any questions of Ministerial policy which may be involved.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I read that passage because it is that intervening course which is proposed <Col N="121" /> in certain amendments which I shall be moving later.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We have heard the objection made to the publication of the inspector's report that it might lead to a demand for a hearing by way of appeal of the question upon which evidence was taken on the inquiry, and that, for obvious reasons, there ought to be finality in such matters. With the last point we entirely agree, but we do not fear any such results from the publication of the inspector's report.  We do not recommend that there should be any further investigation of the facts after full public inquiry.  Indeed, our view would be met if the inspector's report was communicated, with the Minister's decision, to the parties concerned.</P>
    <P>In certain cases the Minister's decision may be influenced not only by reasons of law or public policy which lie entirely outside the field of public inquiry but by information which reaches him through channels other than the inspector's report.  We do not think there is anything improper in this; but when it happens, and the Minister feels it right to make a decision which is against the weight of evidence of the inquiry, we are of opinion that he should, in communicating his reasoned decision, include the statement as to the nature of extraneous evidence by which he has been influenced and thereby remove, at least, one possible source of misunderstanding and decision.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That was the view that was unanimously come to.  It is the view that has been reinforced recently, because a habit has grown up in this Department, not merely of withholding the inspector's report which is sometimes done in England, because the general recommendation of publications has not yet been implemented in England, a habit not only of withholding inspectors' reports but of publishing a summary produced by a person or persons unknown which purports to be a finding of facts on the evidence.  And those summaries are so mendacious, so totally devoid of any reasonable conclusion which any person with any <Col N="122" /> training or skill could possibly draw from the evidence, that the whole of public confidence in local inquiries is completely undermined.  We are left to the conclusion either that the persons who drew up some of those reports and made those alleged statements as to what the evidence proves, have not got the ability of the ordinary office boy, or they have the ability and are deliberately abusing it to mislead the public.</P>
    <P>I have had occasion to look at one or more of those documents.  I can understand the Minister saying this: &ldquo;I will go my own line, I am responsible, I have made up my mind to do so-and-so, and I will do it and give no reasons.&rdquo; I can understand him saying: &ldquo;Here are the findings of the facts by the inspector: there are other matters which I have taken into consideration which have influenced me and caused me to act.&rdquo;  But I cannot understand the withholding of the findings by the only person qualified to make findings and the publication of alleged findings of fact which to any person with any skill or training, are on the face of it not only merely misleading, but either deliberately distorted or completely incompetent.  That is not playing fair to the public and is not playing fair to whatever persons may be in fault. That is a system which shows at once either that local inquiries should be abolished or the present system of holding them should be discontinued; and the only way in which the public can have any safeguard is that there should be a publication either of the inspector's report other than such portions of it as merely give advice or at least that there should be publication of those portions which are deliberate findings of facts by the person who was there and was qualified to judge.</P>
    <P>Senator Sir John Keane has chosen the course in his amendment of desiring that the whole of the report should be published and he is probably right in asserting that he has the backing of the unanimous findings of the Donoughmore Report.  For myself, realising the difficulties in which a Minister may find himself, I would not be prepared to press the matter on to that length, but I am prepared to press that in so far as facts are <Col N="123" /> found, they should be found by the person who hears the witnesses, and that those facts should either be binding upon the Minister as being the findings by the person best qualified to find, or if not binding on the Minister, they should be disclosed so that the public may know that the Minister has chosen to put his own interpretation upon the evidence or has chosen to neglect the evidence, or has chosen despite all the evidence, to take into consideration other extraneous matters for which he may have to be responsible to the Dáil and even to a certain amount of criticism in this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Minister concludes, I would like to say that I have listened to Senators Sir John Keane and Kingsmill Moore on this question of the publication of a report of the inspector.  We had that matter up before in this House and I do not think we got any further enlightenment on it that would help us to change our mind and the opinion expressed at the time.  Senator Kingsmill Moore states that eight judges considered the matter and that three were in favour of the publication of the report, if I took him up rightly. Three out of eight decided that the report ought to be published.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Ought always to be published.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>That would throw a very big suspicion on the opinion of the three if they were in the minority, but apart from what any judge would hold in proceedings of that kind, I think we ought to approach the matter as people of common-sense purely and simply.  We ought to consider it, first of all, from the point of view of the unfortunate inspector who has to go down the country and listen to the evidence of that public inquiry at which members of the Press are present. As a rule, those local inquiries catch the interest of the big majority of the people in the area.  So great is the interest that the Press generally finds it necessary to publish a verbatim report of all the evidence given.  If <Col N="124" /> there is any danger that the Press will not publish a verbatim report, I think it would be very easy for any interested persons to get a verbatim report, setting out word for word the questions and answers, cross examination, etc.</P>
      <P>It is suggested that the inspector should give his findings of fact.  What exactly does that mean?  It would be very easy to give statements of fact if there were no contradiction in the evidence, but supposing that the evidence is given and contradicted and that an inspector reports to the Minister: &ldquo;I find as a fact that such and such is the case&rdquo; what does that mean?  It is the same as saying: &ldquo;I find that the people who gave evidence to the contrary were perjurers and that there was no truth whatever in their statements.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Not necessarily perjurers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>That is if there is a direct conflict, if there is contradictory evidence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>It may be mistaken observation, mistaken expression, confusion of mind, a hundred things other than deliberate perjury.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Especially where the question of competence comes in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>I take the point of view of some of us down the country who read all these reports carefully word for word.  &ldquo;John Kelly swore so and so, Patrick Murphy contradicted him and the inspector found that Patrick Murphy was committing perjury.&rdquo; That would be a dreadful position in which to put the inspector.  I imagine that very few inspectors would like to hold inquiries if they were compelled to draw conclusions of that nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I admit it is very difficult for a Minister to judge by the evidence if he has not seen the persons giving evidence, but I take it he will be guided, firstly, by the evidence and, secondly, by the confidential report of his inspector, who will give reasons for believing some witnesses and not <Col N="125" /> believing others.  I think that is the ideal way to hold an inquiry.  The inspector can be more independent and can state his mind more freely than if he is liable to be called to book in the public Press or anywhere else for his findings of fact.  There may be debates in the local council:&mdash;&ldquo;The inspector disregarded the evidence of So-and-so, that respectable man we all know who would not tell a lie to save his life and the inspector held that that man was committing perjury.&rdquo; There would be no end to the rows on that matter and I would not like to be the inspector.  If we pass into law any section that would compel an inspector to publish his report, we will be doing a very serious injury to local government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Every time a judge decides a case, he has contrary evidence before him.  He decides one way or another and finds that such and such are the facts.  That does not mean finding people are perjurers.  The inspector merely finds that such and such things are proved and not others. There may be sometimes a reflection, but there is inherently no reflection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>That is perfectly right. Every man who takes up the position of district justice, Circuit Court judge, High Court judge or Supreme Court judge knows when he is taking the appointment that he will be called upon to find facts publicly in that manner.  He enters into a contract with the State that he will do so and knows it will be his painful duty to do so when he takes the salary allocated to that office.  That is not the position of a local government inspector who may have given up his appointment say, ten or five years ago, being doubtful as to whether he should take the appointment or continue in his position as auditor.  He is probably undecided as to whether the salary is worth it.  He certainly would not take up that appointment if he were put into this position of deciding whether some respectable people are telling the truth and others are committing perjury and having that published in the local and daily papers, having it debated in public councils and possibly brought <Col N="126" /> into the Seanad and the Dáil.  I do not think his life would be worth living and I do not think any official would put himself in that position unless he had nothing else to do.</P>
      <P>With regard to the officials at present in existence, I say now that if you put that responsibility on them you are committing a breach of contract, by asking them to do what they never contemplated, by asking them to do something unfair and unreasonable.  I would ask the House not to place an undue burden of that nature on people who never contemplated that they would be called upon to carry the dangerous and ugly job of finding facts as between different people.</P>
      <P>I had certain fears about this Section 30, but when I read it carefully I found it said:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(1)  If, at any time after the rate in the pound of the rate for a local financial year has been determined by a rating authority, it appears to the Minister that such rate at such rate in the pound is likely to be insufficient to meet the part defrayable out of rates of the expenses to be incurred by the rating authority in that financial year in&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) maintaining at a reasonable standard the public services for the maintenance of which the rating authority is responsible, and</P>
      <P>(b) paying to any other body any sums which the rating authority are bound to supply to that body,</P>
      <P>the Minister, after holding a local inquiry into the sufficiency of such rate, may require the rating authority either to revoke such determination and determine a new rate in the pound for such rate or (if by reason of any steps already taken for the making, levying or collecting of such rate, such a course is more convenient) determine a rate in the pound of a supplementary rate for that local financial year.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>In regard to the words &ldquo;maintaining at a reasonable standard&rdquo;, perhaps if we devote ourselves to some little improvement there we might be able to make it better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="127" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That can be dealt with on the section, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. MacEntee) Seán MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I might intervene at this stage to try to correct an impression which, perhaps, some Senators may have formed as a result of the speech of Senator Kingsmill Moore.  It came to me as a surprise to learn that the report of the inspector in regard to a public inquiry had always been published, had customarily been published, and this particularly in respect of an inquiry held under the Department of Local Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think anyone made that statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I gathered that Senator Kingsmill Moore suggested that it had been the custom to publish the report of the inspector, but that gradually that had been replaced by the issue of mendacious summaries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I think that is not correct.  I think we all approached the subject on the assumption that the report was never published, and that the amendment asks for an alteration of the custom.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to create any confusion.  My information is that, in the earlier days after the introduction of this system, the reports of local inquiries were frequently published.  I do not say in this country, but in England.  There is a statement in a book quite recently issued&mdash;and I think it was stated in a letter&mdash;that the reports are still sometimes published in England.  As far as I know, for a very long time, local government reports have not been published in this country, though reports to the Minister for Industry and Commerce, on questions such as accidents, are customarily published.  I will accept any correction from the Minister on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The latter are concerned with entirely different matters. <Col N="128" /> As there seems to be a conflict of opinion in the matter, perhaps I can do nothing better than to give the opinion of a very eminent lawyer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that the best you can do?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, at least it is as good as the Senator can do.  We have heard a great deal said in favour of one course: that three lawyers out of eight favoured one interpretation of the law, and that the others, I assume, favoured another interpretation of the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I was specific on that.  There were three different views.  One judge was against publication in general, three were in favour of always publishing, four thought that it would be generally desirable to publish but not desirable to have a rule in all cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>And, finally, there was the decision of the House of Lords.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not clear the air if Senator Kingsmill Moore would say whether the eight judges sat together? I gathered from him that there was one judge in the court of first instance, that there were three judges in the Court of Appeal and four in the House of Lords.  Am I correct in that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I can give their names.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say that the Senator presented his case as a skilled but not ingenuous advocate.  The suggestion has been made here that in some way&mdash;and it has been repeated by the Senator, unless I am unable to interpret correctly his meaning&mdash;that while the reports of these public inquiries were not invariably published, nevertheless the general custom was to publish them.  Well, as a layman I can only set against that the opinion of a former Attorney-General and Lord Chancellor, Sir John, now Lord Simon, who, in a case which came before the House of Lords, of which Senator Ryan seems to have cognisance, said this:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="129" />&ldquo;The inquiry referred to is the ordinary local inquiry with which Parliament was familiar.  The holding of local inquiries by the Local Government Board is directed by many statutes.  May I say in parenthesis that they are held for many purposes&mdash;and it has always been the practice of the board to treat the reports of their inspectors on such inquiries as confidential documents for their own use.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That, apparently, was the practice up to 1914, unless the opinion of the then Attorney-General of Great Britain is going to be challenged by Senator Kingsmill Moore.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>That was not judicial.  That was a statement in argument.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>He was merely pointing out what the practice was.  Are we going to assume that the Attorney-General&mdash;perhaps I should say the learned Attorney-General&mdash;tried to mislead the court by misstating the practice or the law?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the practice, and I believe that was not a completely accurate statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We come, then, to the decision of the court, and find the Lord Chancellor of the day, Lord Haldane, said:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;It is said that the report of the inspector should have been disclosed. It might or might not have been useful to disclose this report, but I do not think that the board was bound to do so, any more than it would have been bound to disclose all the minutes made on the papers in the office before a decision was come to. For the reasons I have given, I have arrived at the conclusion that the judgments of the Divisional Court and of Lord Justice Hamilton in the Court of Appeal were right, and that this appeal should be allowed with costs here and in the Court of Appeal, and that the order of the Divisional Court should be restored.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The appeal was taken on behalf of the Local Government Board of Great Britain.  Lord Justice Hamilton's <Col N="130" /> judgment in the Court of Appeal was to the following effect:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The practice of the board, like that of its predecessor, the Poor Law Board, had always been to dispose by correspondence of appeals even in important matters, ... and in treating the inspector's report as confidential it was only following an old and well-known practice.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In the course of his judgment, Lord Shaw said that:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The next proposition is this, that when a local inquiry has been held in compliance with statute, the person whose interests are affected is entitled to something more, namely, a disclosure of the views of the inspector written out by him, in jottings or otherwise, for the guidance or consideration of the Department. ... I incline to hold that the disadvantage in very many cases would exceed the advantage of such disclosure.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Then he went on and said that</P>
    <P>&ldquo;To set up any rule&rdquo;&mdash;such as it is proposed should be set up by this amendment&mdash;&ldquo;that that decision must on demand, and as a matter of right, be accompanied by a disclosure of what went before, so that it might be weakened or strengthened or judged thereby, would be inconsistent, as I say, with efficiency, with practice, and with the true theory of complete parliamentary responsibility for departmental action.  This is, in my opinion, implied as the legitimate and proper consequence of any Department being vested by statute with authority to make determinations.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Lord Parmoor said:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The second objection raised is that the respondent was entitled to see the report of the inspector, and that to withhold this document deprived him of a fair hearing in accord with the principles of substantial justice.  The only word in the statute on which a claim to see the report can be based is the word &lsquo;public&rsquo; prefixed to &lsquo;local inquiry.&rsquo; This word is said to have been used for the first time in the 1909 Act. In my opinion, a public local inquiry <Col N="131" /> means no more than that an inquiry should be held in the locality and be open to the public.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Then he went on to say:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The obligation on the Local Government Board to hold a public inquiry in the locality is to enable the facts on either side to be ascertained by oral testimony, subjected to the test of cross-examination if either party should so require, and to ensure, in this respect, a full opportunity to the appellant to be heard before dismissing his appeal against the decision of the local authority.  In my opinion, the appeal (the appeal of the Local Government Board) should be allowed with costs here and below.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Lord Molton, the last remaining member of the court, said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;There is one point which needs notice&mdash;namely, the claim that the respondent was entitled, as of right, to see the report of the inspector who held the public inquiry.  No such right is given by statute nor&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I ask the Seanad to note this in relation to Senator Kingsmill Moore's speech&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;by an established custom of the Department.  Like every administrative body, the Local Government Board must derive its knowledge from its agents and I am unable to see any reason why the reports they make to the Department should be made public.  It would, in my opinion, cripple the usefulness of these inquiries.  It is not for me to express my opinion of the desirability of an administrative Department taking any particular course in such matters, but I entirely dissociate myself from the remarks which have been made in this case in favour of a Department making reports of this kind public.  Such a practice would, in my opinion, be decidedly mischievous.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the date of that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>1914.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="132" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator have patience?  I had to listen at length to his speech which, in my view, was not directed to his amendment.  I cite that judgment to show the House that the practice in this matter has been established over a very long period and that the law in the matter was finally determined so far back as 1914.  What it is proposed by Senator John Keane to do here is to change the law and to impose upon a Minister of this State a disability which the legislature and the judiciary of Great Britain refused to impose upon Ministers of the Crown in that country.</P>
      <P>Upon what grounds is it proposed to impose that disability?  Upon a suggestion that there is some public disquiet in relation to the manner in which the Minister's power to come to a decision upon the evidence elicited at a public inquiry is exercised.  I see no evidence of such public disquiet&mdash; certainly, no evidence of public disquiet on the part of the majority of the people.  On the contrary, so far as the Dáil is concerned, this matter has been fully thrashed out and there has been nothing to suggest that there is any uneasiness in the public mind as to the manner in which the Minister has exercised his discretion and has discharged his responsibilities in relation to the administration of local authorities or institutions.  The other ground upon which we are asked to adopt this amendment is that 14 years ago a commission or committee set up in Great Britain reported, in that rather careful and diffident manner which Senator Kingsmill Moore has made the House aware of, that, in some circumstances, the report of the inspector should be public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>In all circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>If they said in all circumstances, it does not make any difference because the legislature which set up that committee has not approved of its findings and has not accepted its recommendations.  What <Col N="133" /> is not good enough for Great Britain is, apparently, in Senator Kingsmill Moore's opinion, good enough for us. There never was a more preposterous example of trying it on the dog than this attempt to foist on this Government, this legislature and this State the findings of a committee set up in another country.  These are the only two reasons adduced in support of this amendment&mdash;that the Donoughmore Committee had recommended it and that there was widespread public discontent and suspicion as to the manner in which the Ministerial powers had been exercised.  I see no substantial evidence that such disquiet exists.  I have told the House that the findings of the Donoughmore Commission have not been adopted in the country of their origin and I shall ask the House to reject this amendment and every other amendment which would compel a Minister to disclose any report made to him by one of his own officers.</P>
      <P>If the House were to give effect to any such proposal, we should be at the end of representative Government here and we, certainly, should not be able to keep the Civil Service above and aloof from politics.  A question would arise every time a Minister, who remember is responsible to the Dáil, ventured to form his own independent judgment in relation to evidence secured and obtained for him by an inspector.  That is the inspector's function. He is appointed only to hear evidence, to collate it and to submit it to the Minister.  That is laid down in the House of Lords decision.  He may, for the Minister's guidance, express his own views.  He may, for the Minister's further assistance, disclose to him matters that may not appear in the script as to the conduct and behaviour of witnesses.  But the only thing that an inspector does in relation to a public inquiry is to elicit the facts. It is on that basis that the Minister must form his judgment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would be absurd to hold the Minister responsible to the Dáil if one of his officers happened to err in his judgment or happened to give a judgment which was inconsistent with the evidence.  As I have said, if the evidence, and any memoranda which the inspector might attach to the evidence <Col N="134" /> in submitting it to the Minister, were to be published; if he were to express his views as to what the findings should be and the Minister, having read the evidence, came to the conclusion that the inspector did not attach sufficient importance to something that had transpired in the course of the evidence and the Minister, rating this more important than the inspector had done, overrode the inspector and made his own judgment in the matter, what would be the position if the subject were to go to the Dáil?  Invariably, you would have a motion down condemning the Minister because he had not become a rubber-stamp for his own officer.  You would have at once two parties aligned in the discussion&mdash;a party upholding the Civil Service and the Minister's officer and condemning the Minister, and a party upholding the Minister and condemning the Minister's officer.  How can we in such circumstances keep the Civil Service, as we are trying to do, as we want to do and as I believe it is in the public interest to do, remote from the hurly-burly, the dissension and the controversy of political life?  We should, by doing what Sir John Keane wants, politicalise the Civil Service beyond yea or nay.  We would, I submit, fetter the Minister and make him less responsible than he is at present to the Dáil, because he could right away say: &ldquo;It is not my opinion; the inspector recommended me to do this and I signed on the dotted line.&rdquo;  That is the position which would be created if this amendment were to be accepted.</P>
    <P>There is another point that is overlooked here.  That is, that these local inquiries deal with very many diverse subjects.  You have the inquiry which is related to the proposed acquisition of property.  You have, on the other hand, the inquiry which is related to the discharge of its responsibilities by a local authority, such as is contemplated here in Section 30.  You have the inquiry which is related to the discharge of his duties by a particular official.  You have inquiries related, say, to the technical efficiency of an engineering scheme.  There are in relation to all these, many matters which would have to be considered. The Minister, no doubt, would be very <Col N="135" /> largely guided, I am sure, in relation to engineering matters, almost entirely by his engineering officers.  He would be a foolish man if he ventured to override them.  But when it comes down to the question of the efficiency or the inefficiency, the zeal or the negligence of a public body or a public officer in the discharge of his duties, the Minister must be the final judge because it is he who carries the responsibility for seeing that the local authorities administer the affairs of their functional areas satisfactorily.  It is the Minister who has the responsibility for seeing that all the officers of such authorities, particularly those who are charged with the care and the assistance of the poor, discharge their duties zealously and honestly.  There is no intermediary between the Dáil and these people except the Minister.  It is the Minister who is responsible to the Dáil for seeing that these various agencies discharge their duties satisfactorily.</P>
    <P>We have many instances of that in the Dáil when the Estimates for the Department of Local Government and Public Health are under consideration, because then what a public functionary does or does not, is charged against the Minister.  It is the Minister who has to satisfy the Dáil that he is zealous in ensuring that these public officials will, as I have said, function efficiently and satisfactorily.  The Minister cannot carry that responsibility if he is to be bound by the reports of his inspectors.  In the last analysis he must be the person who will say: &ldquo;This man was or was not in my view negligent&rdquo;.  It is not a question of fact very much in many cases; it is a question of opinion&mdash;whether he was or was not so negligent that he should not be allowed to continue to hold his office or whether, having been negligent, there are mitigating circumstances and whether the mitigating circumstances are such that he can overlook the negligence or whether they are not sufficient to justify him in overlooking the negligence.  The Minister is put finally, in relation to these matters, in the position of a judge. There is no other person who can step into the shoes of the Minister in that regard.  It cannot be left to the <Col N="136" /> opinion of an inspector or to any officer of the Minister.  The Minister in the last resort must have the power of effective decision.  For these reasons, I would ask the Seanad to reject this amendment and any other amendment similar to it which would compel the Minister to disclose the report of an inspector or any memoranda, made either by the inspector or by an officer of the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I should say at the outset that if there were a division on this amendment I would not vote for it.  At the same time I should like to say that I suffer from no uneasiness of any kind.  I have never been at a local inquiry.  I have never read the decision of the House of Lords.  I have never read the Donoughmore Report and I look on this matter entirely from the point of view of a person interested in Irish government.  I sympathise with a good deal of what the Minister has said but there is, I do feel, a problem here with which the Minister has not dealt with at all.  In his usual, shall I say, excitement to &ldquo;down&rdquo; people on the one principle of the inspector's reports, he has refused to look at what the real problem is.  It was apparently the practice always to publish reports but the House of Lords decision on the matter&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh no, it was not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg your pardon&mdash;not to publish the reports.  I do not see any relevancy in this House of Lords decision.  The judges were not considering the advisability of publishing reports.  They were considering what the law and the practice were and, therefore, their opinions are only valuable to establish what the law or the practice should be.  We have power to change the law.  We have the power, if we like, to argue quite calmly, without all the controversy about which the Minister talks, that the law is defective and might be changed in a particular degree.  But the Minister wraps himself in the mantle of the British Attorney-General and the Lord Chancellor.  Then he charges Senator Kingsmill Moore with trying to do the same thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="137" /> I have not the same fervent admiration for the House of Lords as the Minister and Senator Kingsmill Moore have, not by any means.  I do not feel any uneasiness about these reports.  I do not feel if this amendment were passed that we would have reached what the Minister calls in his grandiloquent manner &ldquo;the end of representative Government&rdquo;.  The Minister did his best to put an end to representative Government in this country and so did many others.  But representative Government has survived in this country for a long time back.</P>
    <P>Let us look at how this particular section compares with the present position in local government.  Sub-section (1)  of Section 30 says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;If at any time it appears to the Minister that such rate is likely to be insufficient to meet the part defrayable out of rates of the expenses to be incurred by the rating authority in that financial year in&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  maintaining at a reasonable standard the public services for the maintenance for which the rating authority is responsible and,</P>
    <P>(b)  paying to any other body sums which the rating authority are bound to supply to that body,&rdquo;&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;If it appears to the Minister,&rdquo; that is to say if it appears to someone in the Department of Local Government, that the rate struck by a particular local body is not sufficient to maintain the public service at a reasonable standard, then the Minister orders an inquiry.  That is the position under the section.  Whom does he order to conduct the inquiry?  A servant of the Minister and that servant of the Minister is one of the Minister's advisers.  I have complete sympathy with the Minister in his position relating to the civil servants, but the fact remains that one of the Minister's advisers, bound to his policy and who shares his view, presumably, about the rate he has struck is sent to hold the inquiry.  He goes out to find that the rate struck is not an adequate rate.</P>
    <P>Thus, an official of the Minister's Department, bound to the Minister, bound to accept the Minister's policy goes out from the atmosphere of the <Col N="138" /> Local Government Department, to whom, in the words of the section, it appears that the rate struck is not a sufficient rate, goes out to find is the rate sufficient.  Surely he is bound to find that it is not.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>But he would be a very foolish person if he did not so find.  I have great admiration for the civil servants.  I know their independence and their great qualities, but let us not forget that we are dealing with people who are in the Minister's own office.  Are these people to go out and say that though the rate appears not sufficient to the Minister, it appears to them that it is sufficient?  A man would want to be a very brave fellow to do that and, apart altogether from my admiration for the Civil Service, I do not think there are many of that kind going around.  I think there is a real problem here in so far as there is confusion of the advisory capacity of civil servants, which is their old capacity, and the new capacity being thrown upon civil servants of acting in a judicial function.</P>
      <P>I think this amendment does not solve the problem because I agree with the Minister that if an officer of his gives advice to the Minister, that advice should be private and confidential and it should be the Minister's responsibility to accept or reject it. But remember that we have had that practice adopted when it was the business of civil servants, like a good boy, to be seen and not heard or rather to be neither seen nor heard.  Surely civil servants must advise the Minister and it is the business of a civil servant not to give the Minister the advice which he thinks the Minister would like but to give him the advice in which the civil servant believes himself.  When you send out a man from the Custom House to conduct an inquiry, and he is to be confronted by lawyers like Senator Kingsmill Moore and my other friends here, and asked to decide the admissibility of evidence and other things, then you are bringing in a new function for the civil servants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="139" /> Whatever may be said about 1914, everyone knows that Local Government, like other Departments of Central Government, is taking on more and more functions every day but I would like to suggest here and now that there is something to be considered in regard to the general question of carrying out inquiries by these people who carry out the inquiries on the order of the Minister.  The Minister says he is eventually the judge, but I am not so sure that the Minister ought to be the judge in certain cases.  There are certain analogies which like every other analogy are not quite sound or complete.  If we take the conduct of an inquiry into a railway accident, we find there, not only the inquiry report but the decision and the recommendations and the findings of the inspector. Of course the Minister for Industry and Commerce had not at one time the function towards the railways that the Minister for Local Government has towards local bodies.  Even that has changed, however, and the Minister for Industry and Commerce has now a different relationship to the railways than the Minister for Industry and Commerce had some years ago.  The situation has altered.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>No, not in respect of inquiries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, yes, it has.  There is no use in telling me that the Minister for Industry and Commerce is in the same position in regard to Córas Iompair Éireann as the Minister was in regard to the Great Southern Railways in 1913.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to railway accidents, for instance, he is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but his relationship to the railway as a whole has changed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>And that in turn may mean a change, too, in relation to inquiries. We do not know.  We must see that there is a certain confusion here between the function of civil servants <Col N="140" /> who advice the Minister and the function of civil servants who carry out public inquiries, and it is for that reason that as a general principle, it seems to me that it ought to be altered.</P>
      <P>I have in mind one particular inquiry in which I had no interest and about which I have no uneasiness.  It lasted for five weeks and it concerned an individual's future.  I do not know anything about that individual or about the sky over him, but the inquiry concerned some sort of a quarrel between a county or city manager and the manager of a gas company.  To have the chief engineer of the Local Government Department inquiring into this thing for weeks and that the Minister should have then read a voluminous report and decided whether individual A, B or C should be dismissed, suspended or reduced, seems an extraordinary business.  It seems an absurd function for a Minister to have from his own point of view.  It seems a complete waste of the time of a very important officer of the Department. Perhaps Senator Kingsmill Moore and Senator Ryan thought it was a rather good scheme.  I do not.</P>
      <P>Secondly, the Minister's theory is quite all right, but in practice, a man must feel that he is not getting a fair crack of the whip if he is convicted by somebody who was not there, who did not hear the evidence, who did not see the witnesses and who just sits in his office and reads the report.  I know the Minister is very industrious.  The Minister probably read all the evidence in that case, but how he did it I do not know because it was enormous.  I suggest that some kind of judicial functionary, even if he were a civil servant invested with special powers, should be entrusted with making a decision of that kind, and that it should be public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister says the Dáil can challenge this matter.  You could not have a more incompetent body than the Dáil to challenge these things except perhaps the Seanad.  The Dáil is quite incompetent in these things. So is the British Parliament, or the French Parliament and all Parliaments. They are incompetent to <Col N="141" /> decide whether Patrick Murphy in Ballymaguthery was guilty of dereliction of duty.  I think there should be officers attached to the Department whose special business it would be to conduct these inquiries and who would have special functions and who on particular things would publish their reports.  People are dismissed automatically, for example, after a judicial decision and the Dáil has no power to question it.  In our modern and complicated system of Government there is a necessity to distinguish between the judicial functions and the advisory functions of civil servants. In the Department of Local Government I suggest there might be people whose sole business it would be to conduct inquiries and publish their findings then.</P>
    <P>I have not got a very definite scheme on this.  I am not very skilled in local government matters now, but it seems to me that this is one of our national problems and for the Minister to say that he is the final judge&mdash;if I may say so without offence&mdash;is really a kind of platform oratory.</P>
    <P>If I were the Minister for Local Government I would not like to be the final judge in these matters and I think there should be some scheme devised whereby the person making the decision would be able to see the demeanour of witnesses and hear the evidence.  It is all right to say that a person in the Custom House reads all the evidence but he does not see the witnesses and he is not in the same position as a judge in that regard. He is not in the position of a judge presiding in an open court where the matter is tried, where the witnesses give evidence and are examined and cross-examined and where the person presiding comes to a conclusion on certain fixed principles.  You must remember that in local bodies there was a definite Governmental policy that they should be political and the Minister, in his capacity as a Party politician, advocates that local bodies should be political.  What is going to happen when an official clashes with the poltical body where the Minister has functions to decide, having got an inquiry to deal with that particular office?  It would be much better, <Col N="142" /> instead of generating a certain amount of heat, if we considered it was a real problem, and in the complex nature of Local Government there should be some other practice adopted rather than the practice of the Department in conducting the inquiries, refusing to publish the report and having a Ministerial decision on it.</P>
    <P>I am not challenging the Ministerial decision, and I am not full of uneasiness about any particular report, but I think that when we read this particular section, the wording of it makes it clear that before the inspector goes out to conduct an inquiry, he and the Department of which he is a member and the policy of which he must perforce carry out, will know that it appears to his Department that a reasonable rate had not been struck. In these circumstances something is necessary.  I feel that the Minister and myself would agree in concluding that we have sufficient Irish ingenuity to reach a decision, even if the British had not reached any conclusion at all.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are speaking now on an amendment moved by Senator Sir John Keane.  This amendment would require, under sub-section (1) that after an inquiry a copy of the report should be sent to the rating authority concerned at least 14 days before the issue of the notification under sub-section (2) of the same section.  I do not know what is meant by a copy of a report of an inquiry&mdash;that might mean a newspaper report of the proceedings. I assume that Senator Sir John Keane intended that a copy of the report of the inspector holding the inquiry should be sent to the local authority. That is only a small point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Very small.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a small point, I agree.  I think the time has come in this country to clear the air about the publication of reports of inspectors holding local inquiries, because local inquiries have been established by statute for a number of purposes.  Public local inquiries have been held in connection with the acquisition of land, the clearance of slum districts and the demolition of house property on the one hand, and with purely administrative <Col N="143" /> matters confined, let us say, to the Department of Local Government and Public Health, on the other hand.</P>
      <P>Now the Donoughmore Report was a report of the committee that was set up to report on the powers of Ministers, not the ordinary powers, but what I might call the extraordinary powers of the Ministers&mdash;powers of legislation which are, of course, the proper function of the Legislature, and judicial powers, on the other hand, which are the proper functions of the judiciary.</P>
      <P>The proper power of Ministers is the executive power but in some cases Ministers must exercise what I call extraordinary powers of legislation, or extraordinary judicial powers.  Ministers exercise legislative powers by the making of statutory Orders under statute and the making of statutory rules, and the exercise of judicial powers, which are called quasi-judicial powers principally in respect of local inquiries.</P>
      <P>I have a feeling myself that the Donoughmore Commission was set up to investigate the use of judicial and quasi-judicial powers, not in reference to the administrative Departments of the Ministers concerned, but rather to the exercise by the Minister of quasi-judicial powers which affect the rights and the interests of persons who were in no way concerned with the administration of Departments, and, in particular, by the exercise of the Minister concerned of judicial powers affecting the property rights of persons who were not concerned with the Minister's Department.</P>
      <P>There was a case in the courts, reported in 1924, where in the City of Jarrow the local corporation proposed to demolish some property for the purpose of building new houses or clearing a slum area and a local inquiry was held about the proposed clearance of the area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would appear that the inspector, or the person holding the inquiry, was rather in favour of not advising the Minister concerned to make a clearance Order, but after the inquiry was held, I think the Mayor of Jarrow and <Col N="144" /> some members of the council went to London and interviewed the Minister of Health or his chief officials in the absence of the owner of the property, and having heard the representatives of the corporation in London, in the absence of the owner of the property, the Minister's advisers apparently changed their minds and made the Order which had the effect of demolishing the property.</P>
    <P>That was brought to court and it was held that it was a denial of natural justice to the owner of the property that a decision to deprive him of the property should be taken on the representations of the other side in his absence.  In other words, he had a right to be heard.  These were matters which brought about the setting up of the Donoughmore Commission, and not what I might call the purely administrative matters or what I might call the internal matters affecting the administration of, we will say, the Ministry of Public Health, or any other Government Department.</P>
    <P>I have not got before me the Report of the Donoughmore Commission&mdash;I have it at home&mdash;but I remember reading it, and as far as I remember the commission did make recommendations as regards the publication of reports in matters affecting administration. Senator Moore will correct me if I am wrong, but if he reads the report, he will probably find that there is a reservation, and therefore, the Donoughmore Commission Report would not apply to a public local inquiry held in conjunction with the administration of a Minister's Department, and the intention of the Donoughmore Commission in reporting that the report of a public local inquiry should be made public was limited to the cases where outsiders&mdash;persons not at all under the jurisdiction of the Minister administratively&mdash;were concerned. Senator Moore will correct me if I am wrong.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>You are perfectly right.  You are referring to the passage at the bottom of page 106&mdash;&ldquo;matters in the ordinary course of administration.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. M.J. Ryan Mr. M.J. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not the report with we.  That would have an <Col N="145" /> application to every local inquiry directed by the Minister in relation to the administration of his own Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Senator a question?  I am not trying to obstruct him.  Into what category would a matter of this kind fall?  If it were a question of a conflict&mdash;the Minister may say a building is adequate and the local authority may say it is not adequate, but that another building is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is an administrative matter, in the proper sense of the word, where the person concerned is an outsider who is not under the administrative jurisdiction of the Minister.  My own conclusion from reading the Donoughmore Report is that the recommendation as to publication has no application to the report of any inspector holding a local public inquiry in respect of matters which comes within the administrative sphere of the Minister for Local Government and Public Health.  That is my opinion where it applies to the inquiries concerned with an official of the local authority, the county manager or the county council.  Therefore, the decision of the House of Lords referred to by the Minister applies to-day as much as it applied in 1914 in Arlidge's case.</P>
      <P>For those reasons, I am satisfied that there is no case whatever for publication in respect of matters of administration. The making of rates is a matter of administration by a local body, by local representatives who are exercising the function of a local body. They are in no better position and should not be in any more privileged position than the county manager who is exercising his executive functions on behalf of the local body.  A number of elected representatives of the people style themselves a local authority. There is no such thing; they are only part of the machinery of local administration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The important part.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Self-styled importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="146" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Not self-styled, they are elected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Now we know where Senator Ryan stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>One might be elected as a white-washer.  The mere vote of election does not give you any special privileges beyond people who pass a competitive examination and are appointed county managers by the Local Appointments Commissioners.  Is a man who gets a number of votes at an election in a better position or entitled to more respect than a man who gets to where he stands by his own energies and abilities?  The county manager is entitled to as much consideration and respect as the self-styled elected representatives of the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>If a man tried to come into the Seanad without being elected, Senator Ryan and I would kick up a queer fuss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There never has been at any time any question of the publication of inter-departmental reports.  The Senator might as well ask for the publication of the report of the assistant secretary of the Department to the secretary of the Department, as ask for the publication of the report of an inspector to the Minister.  For these reasons, I ask that the amendment be rejected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>One never knows what Senator Ryan is going to say, as he always says the opposite to what you expect.  I will concede to the Minister that it is quite impossible to get an inspector to make a report which he knows is going to be published and have the report anything but the most limpid, unconvincing document ever presented to any Minister or public authority.  Whatever course the examination might take, the fact that the inspector was going to have the report published would mean, I frankly admit, that he would look around to see who were concerned on both sides and would weigh up the strength and weaknesses of both sides and the consequences to himself of reporting on the facts.  If I were the Minister and if someone who was a colleague of mine <Col N="147" /> on the county council of my native county appeared for some reason in a not very shining light as a result of an inquiry, the inspector would know all that and I am afraid the report would be coloured by that knowledge.  In appreciation of those facts, I see where the Minister stands, but to make that the argument for not publishing any report is begging the whole question. I am absolutely convinced that, in certain specific cases, a report ought to be published.  I am a member of a local authority and curiously enough, the one instance in which I think the report should be given is the one where Senator Ryan says it should not. Senator Ryan is not a responsible member of a local authority.  There are such people in this House on both sides.</P>
      <P>They regard themselves as having sufficient knowledge and a sufficient appreciation of their responsibilities to be able to determine the charges that should be imposed for the maintenance of the local services, as well as the level at which those charges should be maintained.  When you have such people on local bodies, when their decision is disputed by the Minister, and when in the course of the dispute there is an examination of the facts, it is going to be suggested that these people are to be held up to public odium in the sense that they are not capable of determining the amount of money that should be levied to maintain the local services up to a reasonable standard.  If the point of view is held by the Minister that they are not capable of doing that, there is then to be a local inquiry.  When that inquiry is held, why should not the ratepayers of the county be made aware of the report which the inspector made on the competence or incompetence of the local men that took that decision?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The argument made by Senator Ryan with regard to that was absolutely inexcusable.  I was astonished at the Senator making it. If it were made by somebody who had no contacts with country life in Ireland, or whose upbringing or associations had been different from those of <Col N="148" /> Senator Ryan, one could, perhaps, excuse the expression of such an opinion.  With regard to certain issues which have to be determined by way of an inquiry, I think that, from the point of view of the public good, of stability and order in local affairs, there are times when the reports of these inquiries should be published. If there is one instance where they should be published, it is on the question as to whether or not the rate levied by a local body was or was not sufficient.  Senator Ryan referred to the people who are elected on local bodies.  To an extent he poured ridicule on them.  Apparently, they seem to be very irresponsible people in his view with a peculiar kind of mandate.</P>
    <P>I would remind the Senator that the people who give a mandate to their representatives on local bodies are the very same people who are privileged to give a mandate to people elected to Parliament, and, of course, when they give a mandate to Senator Ryan or to myself or to others to come here they are magnificent people.  In my opinion they are no less a sovereign people when they elect their representatives on the local bodies than they are when they act in the capacity of voting for Deputies to sit in Dáil Éireann or for the representatives of universities to sit in this House.  Perhaps a Senator with the legal mind of Senator Ryan can define a sovereign people in such a way as to make them sovereign at one moment and to restrict their sovereignty at another time.  I cannot understand the Senator's argument.</P>
    <P>The representatives on local bodies are freely elected by the people.  Are such people to have no sense of responsibility? Are they not to take cognisance of the charges that they are expected to levy on the people for the maintenance of the local service?  Is it not their responsibility to strike a balance between the demands of the local services and the competence of the people to pay?  In my opinion that is a moral obligation which the sovereign people impose on them.  There is no use in suggesting that the county manager is equally responsible.  He is not.  I do not want to say anything at <Col N="149" /> this stage about the functions of the county manager, but there is no use in pretending that he has equal responsibility. On the net point, if you are going to have an inquiry as to the rate which is to be levied, what is wrong with publishing the findings of the inspector?  If it can be shown that I and others who serve on local authorities are not doing our duty, then we should be shown up.  That would be the right way to treat us.  It would help to establish a spirit of responsibility in the minds of those who serve on local authorities.  I suggest that is the way to create a civic sense.  If the findings of the inspector indicate that the local representatives are not performing their duties faithfully, and discharging their responsibilities in the way they are expected to do, then the local people should be told that their representatives are unworthy of their trust.  I give that as one instance to support the suggestion that the reports of the inspector should be published.</P>
    <P>I am not very much concerned with what was said by the Donoughmore Committee or with what Lord Haldane or Sir John Simon said.  But I do agree with what Senator Hayes said.  I would like to see Irish intelligence exercised and applied to our own problems in trying to find a proper solution for them.  I confess that I think it is quite hopeless for Senator Sir John Keane to ask the Minister, in the form in which he is asking for it in this amendment, to have publication of the findings of an inquiry.  In my opinion we would not get what we want in that way.  We want decent local administration, with a sense of responsibility on the part of those who compose the local councils.  We want harmonious relations between the Department and the local authority, an appreciation of the responsibility of each in its own sphere, with a desire for co-operation. These are the things which in my opinion would be calculated to raise local services to the level that we should all desire.  How is that going to be provided?</P>
    <P>In certain instances, of course, it will be necessary to hold inquiries, but, no matter how the Minister may argue, nothing will convince the people of a <Col N="150" /> county that the holding of an inquiry by an official of his Department is a satisfactory procedure so long as the report is not published.  Therefore, when inquiries have to be held, the Minister should find some method of holding them, other than the procedure which is adopted at present. It is essential that that should be done. I believe that if it were done local administration would become much more healthy.  It would also provide an excellent method for educating public opinion.  It would make the local people appreciate the fact that these inquiries can be impartial, and that the reports of whatever body was set up to hold them&mdash;somebody other than an official of the Department&mdash;can be fair reports.  At present it is terribly easy to argue that that is not true of these reports.  It is unfortunate that it should be possible for people to make such a case as that.</P>
    <P>To some extent I was brought to my feet to speak on this by the annoyance which Senator Ryan's attitude of mind towards it caused me.  I suggest to Senator Sir John Keane that if we want protection for local authorities, that if we want to ensure that when local authorities are found unworthy by the Minister or his representative that the public will be made acquainted with all the facts, so that the people will be able to form their own judgment, I believe we are not going to get that by the method which the Senator has suggested.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Duirt an Seanadóir Bacster gurbh é an fáth gur éirigh sé chun labhairt ar an leasú seo an fhearg a chuir an Seanadóir Ó Riain air mar gheall ar an dóigh in ar phlé sé an cheist.  Is é an fáth is mó a éirímse, le cur in úil don tSeanadóir Ó Riain chomh mór agus atá an Seanad fá chomaoin aige agus an scéal a phlé chomh cúramach, chomh soiléir agus chomh cruinn agus a rinne sé.  Thaispeáin sé go soiléir dhúinn lochtaí na leasuithe seo a thug an Seanadóir Ó Catháin os ár gcomhair.  Roimhe seo, bhíomar faoi obligáid ag an Seanadóir Ó Riain agus ní lú an oblagáid sin anois.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Do léigh mé tamall ó shoin, nuair a bhí díospóireacht ar an gceist seo, <Col N="151" /> tagairt do Thuarascáil Donaghmore agus an méid a bhí inti maidir le tuarascála rúnda.  Ós rud é nach bhfuil tréineáil i gcúrsaí dlí agam, bhí mé níos mó ná sásta gur mhínigh an Seanadóir O Riain an pointe sa Tuarascáil sin maidir le tuarascála rúnda, mar ní raibh tuairim ro-chruinn agam air.</P>
    <P>Fuarthas locht inniu ar na daoine a a bhios i mbun fiosrúchán phoiblí. Níl mórán eolais agam ar na fiosrúcháin sin.  I rith mo shaoil ní raibh mé i láthair ach ag cúpla ceann acu. Ní raibh baint agam leo ach chuaigh mé chucu chun a fháil amach conus a scrúdaíonn siad na ceisteanna a bhíos ós a gcómhair agus conus a iompraíos na cigirí, na fiadhnaithí agus na dlío-dóirí a bhíos pairteach sa gcúis iad féin.  Caithfidh mé admháil gur iom-pair na cigirí iad féin ar bhealach an-chothrom agus an-uasal.  Chuir siad rompu teacht ar an bhfírinne agus, do réir mo thuigsiana, bhí siad an-chúramach. Bhí dlíodóirí i láthair ar gach taobh agus bhí cead acu ceisteanna a chur ar na fiadhnaithí.  Thug mé fá deara go raibh lucht na bpáipéar nuaíochta i láthair agus an chéad lá eile bhí cuntas cruinn, iomlán ar imeachta an fhiosrúcháin sna páipéirí. Fuair na daoine eolas cruinn iomlán ar an gceist tríd an bhfiosrúchán agus tré na paipéir nuaíochta.  Do réir mar thuigimse, cuirtear cóip iomlán den fhiadhnaise chuig an Aire agus is ar an tuarascáil sin a tugas an tAire a bhreith.</P>
    <P>Taobh amuigh de sin, an cheist atá ós ár gcómhair inniu is ceist shimplí i.  An ceart údaras a bheith ag Aire&mdash; sa gcás seo, an tAire Rialtais Áitiúil &mdash;seirbhíseach a thoghadh chun fios a fháil ar cheisteanna áirithe tré fhios-rúchán agus an ceart don Aire iar-raidh ar an seirbhíseach sin tuarascail rúnda a thabhairt dó, má shíleann sé gur gá é.  Is ar an gceist sin a chaith-feas an Seanad breithiúnas a thabhairt.  Duine ar bith ag a bhfuil eolas ar chúrsaí poiblí, duine ar bith a bhí ar Choiste Leabharlainne, nó Choiste Gairm-Oideachais nó Chomhairle Chontae, tá a fhios aige gur gá eolas rúnda a bheith acu ar ócáidí chun an n-intinn a dhéanamh <Col N="152" /> suas ar cheisteanna áirithe.  Ar an gcaoi chéanna, nach ceart, mar a míníodh inniu, údarás a bheith ag Aire&mdash;agus go háirithe an tAire Rialtais Áitiúil&mdash;iarraidh ar sheirbhíseach iontaofa eolas faoi rún a thabhairt dó, nuair atá gá leis, i dtreo go mbeidh sé i ndon a chuid oibre a dhéanamh go sásúil?  Labhair Seanadóirí ina aghaidh sin agus sin an méid a rinne-adar. Duine ar bith a tháinig isteach inniu chun na hargóna pro agus con do chluinsint agus breithúnas a thabhairt orthu, b'éigin do admháil gurb iad na hargóna ba láidre na hargóna ar son cúise an Aire.</P>
    <P>Rinneadh tagairt don imní atá ar na daoine mar gheall ar na tuarascála seo.  Dúirt an tAire féin nach raibh fhios aige go raibh a leithéid ann.  Tá an ceart aige.  Tá a fhios agam Comhairle Chontae a cuireadh fá chois cúpla bliain ó shoin.  Cuireadh Coimisin-éara isteach in ionad na Comhairle Contae.  Bhí trácht air sin sa Teach seo agus dúradh go raibh muintir an chontae mí-shásta mar gheall air.  Tar éis tamaill, bhí toghchán sa gcontae sin chomh maith le contaetha eile. Fuair muintir an chontae sin seans a dtuairim a thabhairt an raibh siad sásta nó mí-shásta le breithiúnas an Aire.  Tá a fhios againn toradh an toghcháin sin.  Thaispeáin na daoine go raibh siad ar aon intinn leis an Aire, agus na daoine a chuaigh suas ar an taobh eile bhriseadh iad.  Má tá fiadhnaise ag teastáil nach bhfuil aon imní ar na daoine mar gheall ar an gceist seo, ní gá dul thairis sin.</P>
    <P>Mhínigh an tAire dhúinn go bhfuil sé freagarthach don Oireachtas, faoin gcórus polaitíochta atá againn, ar ceisteanna poiblí agus deirimse nár cheart réiteach na gceisteanna sin a fhágáil ag seirbhísigh an Stáit.  Ba dainséarach an rud é an dualgas sin a chur ar seirbhísigh poiblí.  Ar mhaithe le rialú poiblí agus leis an saol poiblí, tá súil agam go seasóidh an Seanad leis an Aire agus go n-aontóidh an Teach leis sa tuairim a thug sé, gurb é féin ba cheart a bheith freagarthach don Pháirliméid agus do na daoine as réiteach ceisteanna poiblí.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>But for the remarks made by Senator Ryan, I had no intention <Col N="153" /> of speaking on this amendment. I must confess I have never really been so grateful to any Senator as I was to Senator Baxter when he spoke after Senator Ryan because if I had stood up to speak immediately after Senator Ryan concluded, I might have said things for which I would have been sorry after I had some opportunity of cooling down.  As it is now, I am merely sorry for Senator Ryan because in his usual alacrity to defend the Minister in his attitude to any amendment that might be proposed, he did not seem to realise that the Minister has travelled somewhat in the past three or four years and that the Minister now realises, as he did not realise three or four years ago, that the elected representatives on a local authority are entitled to a certain primary function in regard to the carrying out of the duties of a local authority.  The Minister's view now, as it was not then and as Senator Ryan did not seem to realise when he got up, is that the manager is carrying out his duties in a manner subservient, not to the individual elected representatives, but to the collective authority of the elected representatives of the people in any particular area.  If we are going to move away from that in local government, then we might forget completely the farce of having in any area elections every three or four years for the purpose of constituting county councils and we might as well say that those who do give their time without reward to carrying on the local government business of their county, could easily save themselves that trouble and devote their time to their own business.  Happily, as I feel that view is not accepted in all its implications by the Minister, I think that the speech that was made by Senator Ryan does call for the most emphatic denial that along that road in regard to local government lies any hope of their being any tradition of co-operation from the people of a county with central government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So far as this amendment is concerned, I do not think that the position is such that the amendment in its simple form can be adopted.  I take another view in regard to the position <Col N="154" /> as visualised in Section 30.  I find it somewhat difficult to discuss the amendment as such, without infringing slightly on a discussion of the section itself.  It seems to me that the essential thing to consider is what is the best method of achieving voluntary successful co-operation between the Central Government and the local authority.  The Minister's view is that that can best be achieved by all the time wielding the big stick in his hand, the big stick that is particularly included in the Minister's power of striking an additional rate set out in line 21 onwards.  I do not think that that is the way the Minister is going to get from local authorities the co-operation that is essential if local government is going to be a success.  I think we shall eventually reach a successful system of local government only if the people of a county&mdash;I am dealing with county councils for the moment&mdash;are enabled to see, appreciate and understand and be made to appreciate and understand, where the people who have elected them have let them down.  If the elected representatives make, so to speak, a &ldquo;muck&rdquo; of it, the people must be allowed to see where they have been led, where the mess has been created and by whom the mess has been created, and they must be permitted to suffer as a result of that or else you are not going to achieve anything in the future under the new authority that will be elected.</P>
    <P>The Minister's point of view is that the desirability of that is completely overriden by the necessity of having co-operation and direction from the Central Government.  I differ from him in that view.  We shall discuss these differences later on the section but, in regard to this amendment, I suggest that if there were some functionary analogous to the arbitrator appointed by the Minister in connection with the acquisition of land, somebody appointed by the Minister but who yet would not be in the Minister's Department, to hold these inquiries, to publish, not recommendations, but findings of fact upon which the Minister would be the person, not exactly to make a recommendation except in <Col N="155" /> so far as he was recommending a certain course to the Oireachtas, but to take a decision on certain facts presented to him and presented to the public, presented not by a servant of the Minister&mdash;I entirely agree with the Minister in that&mdash;but by some outsider appointed by him in the same manner as an arbitrator is appointed in connection with the acquisition of land, then and only then in my view would you get from the people of an area that loyal and voluntary co-operation which is necessary for the success of local government.  If the facts were published the people of the area would know exactly where they stood. If there had been default by the local elected representatives that default would be known beyond yea or nay. Then there could not be any dispute about it and there could not be any possibility of faction being created because representatives who were being ousted felt that they did not get, whether in fact they did or not, a fair crack of the whip.  That would give no possible excuse to the people, who in the long run, and it will always be so, are the best judges of what is going to be best for their county.</P>
    <P>Although we cannot do it in this amendment I would earnestly ask the Minister to consider the possibility of appointing some other person of the nature I have suggested to deal with inquiries such as these merely on the basis of facts.  In addition, if the Minister likes he could have his own civil servant at the inquiry for the purpose of being able privately to make recommendations to the Minister as a result of what he saw at the inquiry, and then to have a fact finding statement&mdash;I will not call it a report, because a report is a colourable document&mdash;but a fact finding statement which would mean that there could not be any argument afterwards about what were the facts and that it was on the facts that the decision was ultimately founded so far as the dissolution of a local authority is concerned. I think that along those lines the Minister would get more co-operation from the people who, I believe, and I think he believes, too, <Col N="156" /> are the essential feature in local government&mdash;the elected representatives, not the managers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not desire to say much on this amendment except to draw attention to what I think is the atmosphere of unreality in which this discussion is proceeding.  Part of that, I think, is due to the desire of the Minister and perhaps of some of the other speakers to dramatise the subject under discussion.</P>
      <P>As I understand it what we are discussing here is the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad someone has drawn attention to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>To what?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHearne" hpid="Mr. Hearne Mr. Hearne">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hearne</NameTxt>
      <P>To the fact that it is the amendment we are discussing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing an amendment to Section 30 and the whole question of local government inquiries and the publication of reports does not arise on this amendment. What does arise is the proposal in the amendment to publish a particular report in regard to a particular matter.  The whole issue is not raised here.  As I understand it, under sub-section (1) of Section 30 the Minister is required to hold a local inquiry before he determines that the rate struck by the local authority is insufficient.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>And if he considers the rate is insufficient he sets it aside and orders the striking of a new rate. Before he does that, however, he is required under this section to hold a local inquiry and the proposal, as I think the amendment contemplates it, is that the result of that inquiry in regard to the insufficiency of the rate, if insufficiency is alleged, should be made public.  Now there is no use in the Minister talking about signing on the dotted line.  That does not arise here at all and the opinions of the Lord Chancellor and other distinguished lawyers in England have got nothing to do with this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In saying that I have grave doubts as to whether the amendment would achieve its purpose.  I gather from <Col N="157" /> the speech which has been delivered by Senator Sweetman that he too, has the same doubt as to whether the amendment if inserted in the Bill would achieve its purpose.  I think it will not and I agree entirely with what Senator Hayes said earlier in regard to this matter.  If the person holding an inquiry is an officer of the Minister's Department and if that person knows that his report is going to be published I think it is not unfair to say that having regard to the relationship between the Minister and his officials that report will be presented in a form in which it may with safety to the Minister be published.  I do not think that is what you want in relation to this question when the matter involved is the setting aside of a rate which is struck by a local authority.</P>
    <P>Let us assume, for instance, that the county manager requires a certain sum for a particular purpose.  It may be a good purpose, a purpose in which the county manager would have the support of a great many people in both Houses of the Oireachtas, but at the same time it might be a purpose which would not commend itself to the local authority.  One example has occurred to my mind.  I do not know whether it is a good one or whether it is safe for me to cite it or not.  I can imagine a county manager taking the view in some particular town, let us say in West Cork, that there should be a fair green and that the cattle in future should not be exposed for sale on the public street.  In his submissions to the county council the manager might propose that a sum of £5,000 or £10,000 would be included in the rate to enable him to provide a fair green.  The county council may take the view that that is an extremely bad thing though I personally would think that it is a good thing.  Then the county council by a majority decides to strike this item out of the rates and probably there would be other items of a similar kind in which I will hold or the Minister will hold with the county manager.</P>
    <P>That brings us down to this point: are the elected councils to have any say at all in the administration of local affairs?  They may be wrong and the</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="158" /> Dáil or Seanad may be wrong too but unfortunately we have to obey decisions arrived at by a majority and I am afraid we will have to put up with decisions of the county council, even though some members will think they are unwise decisions.  Once we accept the principle that the local authority has that power of refusing to strike a rate or the power of striking a rate, then we ought to hesitate before we permit the Minister to set aside the rate struck by the local authority and to determine that there shall be a new rate which will include this item that the county council desires to exclude. Inquiries are held before that decision was taken by the Minister and I cannot see anything wrong in requiring the person holding the inquiry to make his report in public.  As I have said already, I do not think that requiring the publication of the report of the person holding the inquiry will achieve anything if that person is an official of the Minister's Department.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of correction, I do not know if Senator Duffy&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Senator Duffy giving way?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>The requirement is that it should be sufficient to meet the part defrayable out of the rates of the expenses to be incurred by the rating authority for that financial year in maintaining at a reasonable standard the public services for the maintenance of which the rating authority is responsible.  I do not know how he can bring in the fact that the county manager can order a matter of that kind to be done.  There is a provision in the Act of 1941 that the council may order certain things to be done&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>1940.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>He may order certain things to be done and if a certain number of persons called a meeting and decided by a majority of two-thirds they can require things to be done, but they must provide the money before the manager can do the work and they <Col N="159" /> do not know what authority has authority to order for itself that certain things must be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am making the point that the county manager requires the rating authority to levy a particular sum.  The Minister is of opinion that the sum is insufficient.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>May I again try to emphasise what Senator O'Dea has already tried to convey to Senator Duffy?  The county manager cannot require the local authority to do anything. He can recommend.  He can say: &ldquo;if you want these local services maintained it will require such-and-such an amount of money to maintain them,&rdquo; but he cannot require the local authority to do a single thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>The local authority can require him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it is essential for the case I am making.  Let us assume that a county manager considers that fairs should not be held on the public streets.  Is he not entitled to suggest to the local authority that a fair green should be provided so that fairs can be held there?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of correction, that is a matter which is governed by another Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Duffy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Where is the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>The question arises whether the sum provided by the rating authority is adequate&mdash;adequate in addition to what they have already provided.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not specially essential to the case I am making.  I am only drawing attention to this fact, that a conflict may arise between the county manager and the county council in relation to the sum of money which should <Col N="160" /> be provided.  If that conflict arises, the Minister is entitled to step in and to say that in his opinion, the county council is not providing sufficient money for the local services they are required to maintain.</P>
      <P>Having formed that view he appoints an officer of his Department to hold a local inquiry.  By the way, he does not say it shall be a public inquiry; it shall be a local inquiry.  This inquiry is held. The report of the inquiry reaches the Minister.  I do not know the form in which it reaches the Minister. It may be that what reaches him is a transcript of the evidence without any recommendation or observation at all by the officer holding the inquiry.  Therefore, that is where I think the amendment is defective because there may be nothing to publish whatever except a transcript and if the matter is of sufficient public importance that will have been read in the local newspapers, so that the amendment does not achieve its purpose in that regard.</P>
      <P>The point I am trying to make is, that the Minister has to make up his mind in relation to this matter, a matter of outstanding importance&mdash;the question whether he is going to order the making of a new rate in the middle of a financial year.  Therefore, a very important responsibility is placed on him.  That responsibility cannot be passed on to the shoulders of any officer and I therefore think it is entirely unrealistic for the Minister to talk about signing something on the dotted line.  He is obviously required to make up his mind, because he is requiring a local authority to strike a rate, and then to strike a new rate, and probably upsetting the whole collection of rates in the area of that particular local authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister attached a lot of importance to the fact that there is no legal right here or in Great Britain to insist on the publication of a report made by an officer of the Department holding the inquiry.  That is admitted. There is no question about that.  There is no legal obligation, but what is proposed in relation to this particular incident is that there shall be an obligation <Col N="161" /> on the Minister to publish a report. As I have said already I think that is ineffective because, in fact, there may be no report at all.  Senator Keane doubts that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not doubt it at all.  It could be got around in lots of ways.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>There may be no report and what is in the Minister's Department is a transcript of evidence, the publication of which will enlighten nobody, but at any rate what I have in mind is that the Minister, in a matter of this kind and also on the other occasions on which inquiries are held for this type of case, should appoint a person who is not attached to his Department, for the purpose of holding the inquiry and having received a report on the outcome of the inquiry, the Minister ought to communicate to the local authority the contents of that report.</P>
      <P>That does not mean that the Minister is required to adopt the report. The fact that he communicates it makes it public, but imposes no obligation on him to accept the report.  He is entitled to say: &ldquo;There is the report of the officer or inspector who held this inquiry.  I do not propose to accept it. I propose instead to make the following Order...&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I do not see any embarrassment in that course for the Minister.  He is in, at least, a better position than he is in now under the present procedure, where a suggestion is being made and being reported abroad that the Minister is in fact doing something which is in conflict with the person holding the inquiry.  What is running through this whole discussion is the suggestion that the Minister appoints somebody to hold an inquiry, ignores the report, and does what he set out to do in the first instance, despite the report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is the suggestion and, therefore, the Minister would be in a better position to say: &ldquo;I am making the report available in this case, but I do not propose to follow it; I think it is wrong and that the person who made the report ignored certain considerations <Col N="162" /> which I, as head of the Department, am bound to take into account.&rdquo;  If the Minister would view it in that way, instead of becoming involved in the legal decisions of learned judges in the House of Lords and legal institutions in England, he would be doing himself credit and be removing some of the difficulties with which he is confronted when these questions arise here and elsewhere.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenaConcannon" hpid="Mrs. Concannon Mrs. Concannon">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Concannon</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one small point not raised in this debate which is important&mdash;it arises in connection with the amendment, as the amendment speaks of a report.  It is important to remember that it is the Minister who holds the inquiry&mdash;that is the wording of the section&mdash;and, therefore, no report can issue until the Minister issues it.  The Minister will issue it in the form of a decision.  The inspector is his agent.  It is not a question of his appointing anyone to make the inquiry. He holds the inquiry and I presume he is at liberty to use any instrument he likes for the purpose of that inquiry. Therefore, any report that will issue must be the final report of the person who holds the inquiry&mdash;the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Every time we have the pleasure of having the Minister here, my very genuine admiration for his adroitness, ingenuity and ability grows.  I thought I had spent a good portion of my remarks in making it perfectly clear that the decision in all these matters rested with the Minister, that I appreciated it, that I did not desire to alter it and that it could not be otherwise.  I drew a distinction between a judicial and a quasi-judicial tribunal, largely for the purpose of emphasising that the ultimate decision as to what should or should not be done must rest with the Minister.  Then the Minister gets up and, with a mixture of blandness and passionateness, suggests that I am condemning him because he is not a rubber stamp, that he should sign on the dotted line because the inspector recommended him to do a thing, and a lot more to the same effect.  I am not suggesting that the inspector should influence in any way the Minister's decision.  That is <Col N="163" /> the Minister's own business.  There is a Spanish proverb which says: &ldquo;God says, &lsquo;Sin and pay for it&rsquo;.&rdquo;  That should be up before every Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister prefers not to sin and pay for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister must make decisions and he will not always be right and, if he is wrong, he may have to pay for it; but I would be the last person to suggest that his power of making a decision should be controlled.  He may have to justify it, but he must take it.  That is not what I started to say and it is not what I did say.  I said that, when the Minister was seeking to inform himself as to facts, he should adopt rational methods.  It is all very well for him to suggest that he spends the majority of his time in reading lengthy verbatim reports of commissions.  I have already paid tribute to his ability, but the Minister has also something else to do.  It takes me, a person who has had some practice in these matters, four days to read, with such discrimination and intelligence as I may have, the report of an inquiry which has taken a week.  It would take the Minister at least ten days to assimilate and judge the report of an inquiry which Senator Ryan said, I think, took three weeks&mdash;whether that has anything to do with Senator Ryan appearing in it or not, I do not know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Sin and pay for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TheodoreMoore" hpid="Mr. Kingsmill Moore Mr. Kingsmill Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kingsmill Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I am making is that the Minister is not going to suggest to me that he has time personally to examine all the evidence, because he has so many other things to do.  Furthermore, even if he had time, I do not think it follows necessarily that he is the person best qualified.  I am leaving out for the moment the point that he has not heard the witnesses.  If you have not heard them, it requires a pretty long legal or semi-judicial training to understand the drift of contrary evidence merely on the written page.  It is never as good as hearing it.  I say boldly <Col N="164" /> that the Minister does not spend his time reading verbatim reports and, even if he did, he could not get as good a summary of facts as the inspector would have given him.</P>
      <P>I agree entirely with the remarks that it would be better for more or less skilled people to take these inquiries and come to a conclusion on the facts.  The Minister has evaded the issue&mdash;as least as far as put by me&mdash; that where he takes the decision he should inform himself as to the facts which are reasonably deducible from the evidence, by looking at the finding of facts of the person who took the inquiry, and in order to keep himself safe, he should allow that portion of the report&mdash;which is merely a statement of the facts which are properly deducible from the evidence&mdash;to be published.  He could then say: &ldquo;I have followed that finding of fact or have not followed it, because I had very good reasons.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The only other matters I wish to make clear arise on certain suggestions by Senator Ryan and certain remarks about the Arlidge case.  The only reason I referred to Arlidge's case was that the Department of Local Government, when in a difficulty, took Arlidge's case and put it up over their heads like an umbrella and have kept it up ever since to try to avoid the drips.  I move to report progress.</P>
      <P>Progress reported; the Committee to sit again on Wednesday, 3rd July.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at 6 p.m. and resumed at 7 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Hire Purchase Bill," RHead="1946&mdash;Committee">
    <Title>Hire Purchase Bill, 1946&mdash;Committee.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before sub-section (2) in page 3, to insert the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(2) Before any hire-purchase agreement is entered into in respect of any goods, the owner shall state in writing to the prospective hirer, otherwise than in the note or memorandum of the agreement, the total <Col N="165" /> hire-purchase price at which such goods are being offered for sale:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Provided that this sub-section shall be deemed to have been sufficiently complied with&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  if the hirer has inspected the goods or like goods and at the time of his inspection tickets or labels were attached to or displayed with the goods clearly stating the total hire-purchase price, either of the goods as a whole or of all the different articles or sets of articles comprised therein, or</P>
    <P>(b)  if the hirer has selected the goods by reference to a catalogue, price list or advertisement, which clearly stated the total hire-purchase price either of the goods as a whole or of all the different articles or sets of articles comprised therein.</P>
    <P>This section provides that the cash price shall be marked on the goods in certain cases.  The amendment seeks to ensure that the hire-purchase price will also be marked, as showing the total sum.  The usual practice with firms dealing in hire purchase is that they tell you a suite of furniture is £100 for cash, and so much per month for three years.  The hire-purchase agreement itself will set out the total hire-purchase price, but in the memorandum which is handed to the hirer, in the first instance, there is no obligation to state the total hire-purchase price.  The obligation is to state the cash price and the amount of the instalments. I suggest that this amendment would improve the structure of the Bill inasmuch as it would ensure that the hirer will know not merely the cash price but the total sum for which he will be liable under the hire-purchase agreement which will be made subsequently.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>I confess that I cannot see the necessity for this amendment. I think that Senator Duffy must have misread the provisions of sub-section (2).  The memorandum of agreement, which is to be made under that sub-section and a copy delivered to the hirer within seven days of the making of the agreement, must contain a statement <Col N="166" /> of the hire-purchase price, the cash price, the amount of each instalment by which the hire-purchase price is to be paid, the date on which each instalment is to be paid and a list of the goods to which the agreement relates.  Personally, I cannot see what further particulars the hirer of the goods requires.  In my view the sub-section places sufficient obligations upon the owner of the goods, and it is not necessary to add to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>The first sub-section deals with the cash price.  The memorandum, which will be handed to the hirer before he purchases the goods under sub-section (2), deals with the agreement which is made after he has purchased the goods.  I am merely asking that the information which will subsequently be given to him in the hire-purchase agreement should also be given to him in the memorandum which is handed to him before he purchases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister is right in this case although I think I can see what Senator Duffy is getting at.  When I first read the amendment I did not.  I am afraid the amendment would not work out in practice and would lead to serious complications. I think that Senator Duffy has in mind a certain type of trader who is not a <i>bona fide</i> cash trader at all.  He only exists for the purpose of getting as much as he can for goods in the way of hire purchase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are, of course, genuine and useful hire-purchase arrangements made by firms which do a large proportion of their trade in cash.  Occasionally, they convenience a person by agreeing to a hire-purchase price.  It would be extremely difficult, and I think almost impracticable, in the case of a firm that prefers to do, and that intends to do, a cash trade to insist that it must have all its goods marked not only with the cash price but with the hire-purchase price as well.  That would mean that it would have to instruct its assistants that if a person asked for goods under a hire-purchase arrangement the assistant would have to take out a memorandum and hand <Col N="167" /> it to the intending purchaser.  I am assuming now the case of a <i>bona fide</i> trader who has, or ought to have, his goods marked with the cash price.  If he has not done that, then he must hand a memorandum or a <i>pro forma</i> invoice to the intending purchaser. That is a perfectly proper provision but, generally, the hire-purchase customer does not say anything about hire-purchase until afterwards.  He may come in and examine, say, a wireless set two or three times.  He eventually decides to purchase a particular make and he mentions that he proposes to do so by hire-purchase.  Such a provision as Senator Duffy contemplates might be onerous on the trader and cause a great deal of trouble for no purpose except to save the purchaser the trouble of adding up.  If the purchaser cannot, from all the particulars supplied him, ascertain the hire-purchase price, I am afraid it would be almost impossible for the State to help him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The owner will not allow the goods out of his possession until the memorandum contemplated in sub-section (2) is signed by the hirer. If the memorandum is not signed by the hirer and if the provisions of sub-section (2) are not complied with, the owner will have no right to recover the goods from the hirer.  Before the hirer gets possession of the goods, he will have signed the memorandum containing all the information set out in subparagraph (b).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing with two aspects of this matter.  Sub-section (1) provides that, before any hire-purchase transaction is entered into, certain things will have to be done.  The prospective hirer will be told the cash price, the number of instalments and the amount of each instalment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Not under sub-section (1).  Under sub-section (1) he will be told the cash price.  He may decide to buy the goods on the hire-purchase system and the firm may agree to sell him the goods on that system.  Before the hirer gets possession of the goods, he will have to sign a memorandum which will set out the hire-purchase <Col N="168" /> price, the cash price, the instalments he has to pay, the dates on which he will pay the instalments and a description of the goods he is buying.  I do not think that any more effective method could be adopted of bringing to his notice the nature of the arrangement he is entering into.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>The instrument mentioned in sub-section (1) is &ldquo;a note or memorandum&rdquo;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The words in sub-section (1) are &ldquo;otherwise than in the note or memorandum&rdquo;.  That is the note or memorandum referred to in sub-section (2).  What sub-section (1) provides is that the hirer will be informed in writing of the cash price or be given an opportunity of seeing the goods marked clearly with the cash price or provided with a catalogue setting forth the cash price.  If he decides to buy on the hire-purchase system, sub-section (2) comes into operation. Under sub-section (2) before he gets the goods, he must sign this memorandum of agreement in which is set out the cash price, the hire-purchase price, the instalments he has to pay, the dates on which he has to pay them and a description of the goods he is buying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister may not be aware that all the houses concerned in this business are not of the best type.  A case was brought to my notice some time ago in which a customer living in the country came into a Dublin house and bought certain articles of furniture for the sum of £75 under a hire-purchase agreement. The customer took the goods home and discovered that they were not what they purported to be.  He wrote to the traders and asked them to take the goods back.  They agreed.  They told him to come along and they would give him goods in substitution.  The assistant who was dealing with the transaction brought the customer around the shop and showed him goods which were to replace those he was returning. The manager came on the scene in the course of the discussion with the customer and the customer asked him how much the goods were. <Col N="169" /> The manager butted in before the assistant could say anything and said £95.  They were the same goods but an additional £20 had been added to the price for the trouble of taking back the goods sent out.  I can give the Minister the name of the firm and the names of the people concerned if he wishes.  That is why I thought it would be desirable that a person should be told the total hire-purchase price as he is told the cash price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not only told that but he has to sign an agreement containing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>The case Senator Duffy makes is met by the provision that the cash price must be shown or marked on the goods.  That is a wise and proper provision.  I notice shop windows where you see a certain article marked &ldquo;This as so much weekly&rdquo;.  That has misled thoughtless people.  They think they are getting something much more cheaply than they are really getting it.  If the total cash price is marked, the hire-purchase price can be arrived at quite simply.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 2 and 3 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>On the section, in sub-section (2), there is reference to a note or memorandum which is commonly called the hire-purchase agreement.  I am concerned about the interim period in regard to this agreement.  The persons engaged in this business have hire-purchase agreements drawn up and it may take some time to get new agreements printed.  It would seem to be desirable to provide for an interim period of about two months during which it would be sufficient to have a memorandum of the kind prescribed typed.  Otherwise, you would hold up the completion of hire-purchase agreements until new forms could be printed. The matter is only a small one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>An addendum to the present agreement form could be printed containing the schedule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure that that would comply with the provisions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="170" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not read the provisions as meaning that the whole memorandum must be on the same sheet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Neither do I, but I am not sure that the attaching of another sheet to it would satisfy the law.  I am only thinking of the interim period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that any change of the law will mean the scrapping of some documents prepared in relation to the previous position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not objecting to that.  This Act will require a certain amount of consideration.  I understood from the Minister that the object of this Bill is to protect the hirer and that the owner of the goods can protect himself, provided he does not commit a breach of the Act.  That is a perfectly sensible point of view.  I am not much interested in this business and frankly I am not bothering personally, but I know from those who are a little bothered that they want to get some legal advice in regard to their new purchase agreements and to protect themselves in the way that seems desirable.  That may take two or three months and I want to be sure that in the meantime pending the printing of new forms that it will be all right to attach a memorandum to this effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I should think it would.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I say that this section is already operative in Britain? It has been in operation there for some years.  A number of the firms which finance hire-purchase in this country are, in fact, British Finance Corporations. I understand they have these forms in use at the moment.  They have been in use for some time because they happened to have used them in Britain so I do not think the section is going to create any difficulty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill has a much wider scope that the British Act.  It applies to many classes of commodities to which the British Act does not apply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>But to the extent that it applies to goods which are covered by the British Act, these forms are already in use.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="171" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the situation will be met by the statement made by the Minister because it really means that for a short period he would not take any action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a question of my taking action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am well aware of that, but the opinion which he has expressed will probably meet the case. It is only a question of whether the Act should be applied strictly in the first month or so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly interpret the section as meaning that all the documents constituting the memorandum would be the memorandum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a common practice for insurance companies to paste additions to the terms of the policy over the policy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but they have not got an Act like this.  I am not trying to make a lot out of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The same problem will have to be faced by people who sell motor cars on this system.  They will have to make their agreements subject to the provisions of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), page 4, line 9, to delete the word &ldquo;five&rdquo; and substitute the word &ldquo;two&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This section deals with credit-sale agreements as distinct from hire-purchase agreements and it provides that before making any credit-sale agreement under which the total purchase price exceeds £5, the seller shall state in writing to the prospective buyer what is required in the section.  I am endeavouring to secure that the provisions of the section shall apply where the total purchase price exceeds £2.  The Minister, in fact, mentioned in the Dáil certain commodities which form the subject of such sales&mdash;for <Col N="172" /> instance, books like Dalton's <i>History of Ireland.</i>  If I remember aright the sale price of that book on the instalment system was £2 5s. 0d.  There are also some encyclopædias which are sold on the instalment method.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>But not on the hire-purchase system.  Under hire-purchase the ownership of the books does not pass to the hirer until the transaction is completed.  I think it is extremely unlikely that there are very many credit sales under £5.  Even if there were, the purpose of this Bill is to prevent undue hardship on persons entering into such transactions.  It seems to me that there is no likelihood of hardship arising out of a credit sale for an amount less than £5 amongst the class of persons who are likely to get credit sale facilities.  I think the Senator is mixing up hire-purchase and credit sales.  In the case of credit sales, the ownership of the goods passes to the buyer forthwith and he is under an obligation to pay for the goods by instalments.  In the case of such transactions under £5, the people who get those credit sale facilities are not likely to suffer undue hardship I should think.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that the credit sale agreement refers only to a case where there is a specific agreement to pay an instalment of £5 or more.  If the Minister goes into a shop and orders a suit and they gave him credit there is no agreement.  He might pay at once or he might pay in five instalments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It would not be desirable to reduce the limit mentioned in the section.  In fact the limit of £5 is small having regard to the purpose of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>The other amendments to the section are consequential.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 5, 6, 7 and 8 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 9:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In sub-section (3), page 5, lines <Col N="173" /> 11/12, to delete the words &ldquo;wrongfully retains possession of the goods&rdquo; and in lieu thereof insert the words &ldquo;fails to return the goods to the owner&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>I put down this amendment to raise a point which to me involves some little difficulty.  Sub-section (3) says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Where a hirer having determined a hire-purchase agreement under this section, wrongfully retains possession of the goods ...&rdquo;</P>
    <P>It seems to me that if he were to hand the goods to his neighbour next door and did not retain possession of them himself, he would defeat the object of this section.  I think that if he fails to return the goods to the hirer, then he should be ordered by the courts to deliver the goods to the owner.  Incidentally, I am told by people carrying on this business that one of the difficulties with which they have to contend is that when they go to take back certain goods, they find that they are not there and that a neighbour has taken care of them.  This involves the question of what is retaining possession. My wording seems to meet the case better than the present wording of the section as to what a hirer is obliged to do when he terminates an agreement.  When the hirer wishes to determine a hire-purchase agreement, it seems to me that the proper thing to do is to return the goods to the owner.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be more unreasonable to put on the hirer the obligation to return the goods.  If the hirer has bought a grand piano on the hire-purchase system, it is not reasonable to expect him to hoist that on his back and trot up with it to the trader's door.  In any case, it would be a considerable hardship to expect him to be responsible for the physical return of the goods to the trader's door.  I should not like to express a legal opinion as to what is the exact significance of the phrase &ldquo;wrongfully retains possession of the goods&rdquo; but I think that all that it is necessary to secure is that the owner of the goods has the right to get them back&mdash;in other words the right to go to the hirer's house to collect the goods.  It <Col N="174" /> would I think be going too far in the other direction to expect the hirer of the goods to deliver them back to the trader particularly in a case where the goods might consist of a suite of furniture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>At the same time though I can see the point of view of the Minister this is a section by virtue of which a hirer can say at a particular point: &ldquo;I do not want to continue this transaction&rdquo; and having said that he is not put under any liability at all.  It is finished.  Supposing for example the hirer wanted to take a dishonest view. He is doing something on his own, something on his own volition, as Senator Douglas said, and having done something on his own volition and having given notice he then does not retain possession of the goods.  The goods are next door and I do not see how he can be brought within the terms of sub-section (3).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps if I drew attention to the provisions of sub-section (8) it would clear this up.  That places on the hirer the obligation to tell the owner where the goods are and makes it an offence if he fails to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That does not get over my point at all.  Under Section 8 he can say: &ldquo;I have not got them any more: they are with the neighbours.&rdquo; He is obliged to do that but that does not get over the difficulty.  It seems important to me to have this provision correct.  The Minister could possibly pick a hole in my wording but I do not think it is a very serious hole because no owner is such a lunatic as to prefer to go to the court instead of sending out a van for the grand piano, for instance.  Surely it is unlikely that he would do that.  I could not conceive it.  There are better minds than mine in other places concerned with this thing but I think it should not be hastily passed over.  It should be given some further consideration.  I want to be sure that the hirer has refused to hand the goods to the owner when the owner has taken whatever steps he should take to get them.  That is one of the difficulties which arises here, I think.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="175" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>When the hirer has determined the agreement and has paid half the purchase price then it is unlawful for him to retain possession of the goods when the owner comes to collect them.  He must under sub-section (2) take good care of the goods or be liable to pay damages for his failure to do so. If the owner requires the information, the hirer must tell the owner where the goods are.  Taking all three points I think the owner is sufficiently safeguarded under the circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>My only object was to draw attention to this matter and to try to make the provision workable.  I still think that that point was not taken advantage of fully when the drafting took place, but I am not going to press this.  I am fully in favour of this Bill and I read it through only to see if I could improve it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That section is similar to a corresponding section in the British Act.  As I already said, we had, in the preparation of this Bill, the advice of people concerned with the administration of the British Act and they brought to our attention sections in the British Act which, in application, had proved to be weak. This was not one of the sections in connection with which they mentioned that any difficulty arose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I see, what Senator Douglas is proposing is to reverse the idea of the Bill.  The idea in the Bill is that a person may not retain goods where he is given notice that he is terminating the agreement. Apparently Senator Douglas wants the person concerned to be responsible for returning the goods.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think what Senator Douglas really meant was that the hirer must give every chance to the owner of the goods to collect them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That is all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>But that is not what the amendment suggests in its present form.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not an expert on <Col N="176" /> amendments, but I put that down to draw attention to what might be a difficulty.  I am in a similar position as the Minister inasmuch as the advice I got in this matter came from people who operated on the other side.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Sections 5 and 6 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 10:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), line 52, to delete the word &ldquo;four&rdquo; and in lieu thereof to insert the word &ldquo;seven.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is a very small point.  I consulted some people in relation to it and the actual fact is that in many cases, with the week-end intervening, it would not be possible to do this in four days.  I am well aware of the fact, of course, that there is no big penalty if you do not do it but I think we ought to make the provision more general there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no penalty unless a month elapses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that we should do something that is practicable in a Bill of this kind.  Where you are dealing with a lot of accounts in some cases on a Friday morning or a Saturday, it is not possible to guarantee that this will be done in four days.  Seven days would, in my opinion, be better. You will be able to carry out that obligation in that period.  I know of course that a person would not be penalised until a month elapsed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I consider that four days is ample.  This is only a simple copying job and having regard to the fact that the penalties do not operate until a month elapses I think it is better to leave the Bill as it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to press this but I still think that it might be impossible for anyone carrying on a considerable business.  I do not however place much importance on it.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 11:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="177" /> At the end of the section, in page 6, to add the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(3)  It shall not be lawful upon the termination of the default mentioned in the preceding sub-section or at any time to require from the hirer or buyer the payment otherwise than by an extension of the time within which under the agreement payments are required to be made of any arrears which may have accumulated during such default.</P>
    <P>I want to say at once that this amendment is not satisfactory to me.  I want to draw attention to a matter which I think requires looking into.  The section itself deals with a case of failure &mdash;where the owner of the goods fails to deliver particulars asked for by the hirer and one of the penalties is that no payment will be made while the default continues.  If the default continues for a month, in the case of weekly payments, four weeks' arrears will have accrued at the end of that month.  I want to ensure that the owner will not be entitled to go to the hirer at the end of the month and demand four weekly instalments in one lump sum.  That is what is aimed at in the amendment.  I do not think the amendment is very satisfactory but that is its purpose.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not agree with that.  As a matter of fact, I am somewhat perturbed at the provision of Section 7 myself.  It is taken from the Moneylenders Act and seems to put a rather severe obligation on the owners of goods engaged in hire-purchase transactions and I would not like to add to its severity.  If the owner fails to give information requested by the hirer under this section that does not alter the hirer's obligation to pay instalments as they become due.  We do not relate the failure to any provision of the agreement, but we say that if for a month he fails to do this he is guilty of an offence and is liable to prosecution and fine.  I think there is little reason for believing that the owners of goods will fail to provide the information, realising the severity of the penalties involved for them.  I would hesitate to go further than we have gone&mdash;to go the length suggested by Senator Duffy&mdash;because I think it <Col N="178" /> might become an abuse and be used, perhaps, by hirers to their own detriment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>But he may not be a defaulter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That is true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Supposing someone enters into an agreement to pay £1 a week on furniture or on some other article and the owner for some reason fails to supply the particulars which are asked for, then under this section he can come along at the end of a month or before the expiration of a month and ask the hirer to pay four weekly instalments, £4.  That might be a very substantial sum for the hirer in that case.  I am seeking to provide that, if this default takes places, the hirer on resuming payment, will continue to pay £1 a week but will pay for four weeks longer than provided in the agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>In practice, the person paying a weekly instalment knows quite well and, if there is the slightest doubt, the shop would send the account to him two or three times to remind him.  That is the usual case.  It is only necessary in the case of death or illness, where another person requires information, and it will be sent at once.  The very odd case is where there is a wrong entry in the books, or where it is credited to the wrong address, and the wrong account is sent.  That is a rare case.  I do not want anything that provides undue harshness.  I know there are some firms who take a rather brutal line, but the majority of traders want to keep their customers, and to do so they must pay attention to their circumstances. That is a commonsense attitude.  Of course, there are some individuals one may never want to see again and they are treated harshly.  I do not want anything that would provide for non-payment, as that would be very much to the detriment of both sides.  My own experience with some of the poorer customers is that they are very anxious not to hold up payment and it is sometimes even a nuisance that, instead of monthly instalments, they want to pay by smaller amounts more often in the <Col N="179" /> month.  The staff do not want it, but I say they will have to put up with it, as anything that accumulates may mean hardship.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 7 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 8.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 8 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I raised a point on the Second Reading, and the Minister met me quite well by his reply, but I want to get it perfectly clear.  The provision in the hire-purchase agreement that the goods are not to be taken out of the jurisdiction is a legal provision?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Such a provision is not avoided by this section.  Similarly, a provision that the hirer is at all times bound to give information if he changes his residence, his ordinary home in the ordinary sense, is also a legal provision, I take it, for the purposes of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>An agreement can require the hirer of the goods to keep them in his personal possession, or any such provision can be attached to the agreement, including a provision that the hirer shall give notice if he changes his address.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I rather had the view that anything that was legal in the way of protection for the owner is still legal unless prohibited by this Bill and that is the correct attitude to take.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That is correct.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 12:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), page 6, to delete all words after the word &ldquo;quality&rdquo; in line 48 to the end of paragraph (d), line 54.</P>
      <P>The paragraph with which I am concerned reads something like this:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="180" />&ldquo;In every hire-purchase agreement there shall be an implied condition that the goods shall be of good merchantable quality, so however that no such condition shall be implied by virtue of this paragraph as regards defects of which the owner could not reasonably have been aware at the time when the agreement was made or, if the hirer has examined the goods or a sample thereof, as regards defects which the examination ought to have revealed.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I have been told that in Great Britain this has given rise to many difficulties. One example mentioned to me was that of someone going into a shop and buying furniture which was alleged to be mahogany but which in fact merely had a veneer of mahogany.  No one but an expert could have seen that defect until he brought the furniture home and then discovered he had purchased something which was not of the type he thought he was buying.  I was endeavouring to meet that, and it occurred to me it could best be met by taking out all the words after &ldquo;quality&rdquo; and finishing there.  I see no weakness in that, but I think there is a good deal of weakness if we insert the words after &ldquo;quality&rdquo;, particularly the last paragraph, where a sample can be taken as an indication of the quality of the goods.  One is not always sure that the goods are supplied in accordance with the sample, and there is, further, the fact that many a person going in to buy furniture would not be an authority on the quality of the goods exposed in a furniture shop.</P>
    <P>Another type of case was mentioned when a similar clause to this was going through the British House of Commons.  Someone complained of an incident where a customer went in to buy a mattress and believed he was buying a hair mattress, but when he took it home he found it was filled with shavings.  It is not easy for an ordinary person to discover that without more minute examination than can be given when you see only a sample in the furniture shop.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>May I suggest that an article of furniture made of <Col N="181" /> veneer is still of merchantable quality? The two cases he has set out come under the heading of false description. A mattress is merchantable, even if filled with shavings.  I think the paragraph is absolutely essential.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>Goods are covered by warranties in a general sense.  If an article is described as being of mahogany and turns out to be something else, the person can be prosecuted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the Sale of Goods Act.  What is proposed is to extend to goods purchased under the hire-purchase system the same protection as is provided under the Sale of Goods Act, 1893.  I think Senator Summerfield is quite right, that that does not protect the owner of goods who misdescribes them.  If he passes off the veneered furniture as solid mahogany, or a mattress filled with shavings as a hair mattress, they are, certainly, defects in the goods of which the owner was aware, or should be aware, when selling them.  The only protection we are giving here is a reasonable protection.  The agreement must be interpreted as implying that the goods are of merchantable quality.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Except?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Except the defect is one which the owner of the goods could not be reasonably expected to know of or the buyer of the goods, having inspected the goods, had an ample opportunity of discovering any defect in the goods for himself.  A defect may cover suitability of goods for the particular purpose for which the hirer requires them.  I said, on the Second Reading, that I did not think it was desirable to go any further than to extend to persons buying goods on hire-purchase the protection which is at present available to a person buying goods for cash.  That is what the section sets out to do, to give to such persons the protection which the other class of purchaser has under the Sale of Goods Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="182" />
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Except that there is the danger that people buying goods on hire-purchase and paying for them at £1 or £2 a month are very likely to be less discriminating than the customer who can pay £100 cash down.  I think that is recognised in the Bill. I am in agreement with part of what the Minister has said, but I suggest to him that the latter part of this paragraph, which says, &ldquo;or, if the hirer has examined the goods or a sample thereof, as regards defects ...&rdquo;  I think that these words ought not to be in the paragraph because they pretty well deprive the hirer of any protection, once he has examined the goods or a sample of the goods.  I would ask the Minister to look into the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We must give some protection to the trader, too.  I think we cannot leave him completely defenceless.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a certain amount of sympathy with Senator Duffy's point of view as regards the words &ldquo;sample thereof&rdquo;, but I do not think that, otherwise, he has made a case for his amendment.  I am all in favour of a hire-purchase customer being put in the same position as a cash customer as far as warranty and everything else is concerned.  If he carries out his obligations, he should have the same warranties and be as well off as the cash customer.  I understand from the Minister that is what the Bill does.  I am in agreement with the Minister on that.  Senators must bear in mind that, with the very best will in the world, it is not possible for a trader when he buys goods from a manufacturer to examine everything. I know, of course, that in the case of a cash customer if the goods turn out to be unsatisfactory they come back to you, and the trader then gets on to the manufacturer.  He backs his own customer against the manufacturer and the thing is settled.  If the penalty under a hire-purchase agreement were to be that if such a thing happened it invalidated the agreement, then I think business people would hesitate about having hire-purchase agreements at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="183" />
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>It very often happens that the actual article the hirer is going to get is not in stock at the time the purchase is made.  That happens very often in the case of commercial transactions when people are buying for cash.  They make their purchase by examining a duplicate of the article they require.  Therefore, I think there is a lot of wisdom in the retention of these words which at first sight may seem to be to the disadvantage of the hirer.  We all know that it very often happens that the actual article, whether it be a suite of furniture or a motor car, that a person is going to get may not be in the shop at all at the time the purchase is made. The purchaser will see a duplicate of it, and on that will enter into the agreement.  So long as a person gets an article that is no less good in quality than the one he has inspected, I do not see that there is any hardship in this provision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that if this provision were to be deleted it might lead to some abuse.  One can contemplate a person going to a cycle shop and entering into negotiations to buy a bicycle under a hire-purchase agreement. He notes that a spoke in the bicycle is broken.  The trader has not detected it, but the intending purchaser says: &ldquo;O.K., I will take it in a hurry,&rdquo; knowing that he can claim that the bicycle was defective when he got possession of it, and in that way he could invalidate the hire-purchase agreement. I think there must be some protection, namely, that the defect was one that the trader could not be reasonably expected to know of himself, and, secondly, that the buyer did not know about when he was buying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister's point is not relevant to this amendment because even though the spoke in the bicycle was broken the bicycle was still merchantable.  This paragraph relates to warranty, that the article is of merchantable quality except in particular cases and where these considerations apply there is no warranty. In other words, there is no warranty where the hirer sees the goods if he could be reasonably expected to know of the defects, or if he has seen a <Col N="184" /> sample.  I am stressing the word &ldquo;sample&rdquo;.  If someone goes into a shop to buy goods under a hire-purchase agreement, and if he is not sufficiently skilled to see the defects, he is deprived of his warranty because of the later provision in this paragraph.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be very dubious of the effect of deleting this provision. It could easily bring hire purchase to a standstill.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Sections 9 and 10 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 11.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 11 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister say what the section means?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked that question myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked two lawyers and I could not get an answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>This section is designed to simplify the proofs required, and consequently to reduce the costs involved, in actions for the recovery of goods let under hire-purchase agreements. In such actions, proof of demand by the owner and subsequent failure or refusal to deliver, by the person in possession of the goods, is invariably required, and may entail the production of a considerable volume of evidence.  This section provides that proof that a written demand for the return of the goods has been made by the owner, after the right of possession accrued but before the commencement of the action, and that the hirer continues to retain possession of the goods will be sufficient evidence on this point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That would seem to be in favour of the owner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>It appears to me that what the section does is that instead of proving (a) you must prove (b).  I quite appreciate that, in the ordinary way, if an action is started for possession of an article you must prove that before you commence the action you demanded possession and that possession <Col N="185" /> was refused.  Now, instead of proving that, you have got to prove that you made a request in writing to get the goods.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The point is that evidence that the demand was made and that the hirer failed or refused to return the goods must be produced in the action.  A great deal of evidence is very often necessary to establish that point.  The purpose of the section is to simplify that procedure by making the mere possession of the goods by the hirer, after a demand for their return has been furnished, evidence of the fact that he has failed in his obligations, and that his retention of the goods is adverse to the owner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I have got it now. What it really means is that whereas, in the ordinary way, you had to prove a demand for possession, you will still have to prove that demand but you are being let off proving refusal to give possession.  It has been drafted in the most abstruse manner.</P>
      <P>Section 11 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 12.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 13:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), line 33, to delete the word &ldquo;one-third&rdquo; and substitute the word &ldquo;one-fourth&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This section deals with the case of a person who has paid part of the hire-purchase price of the goods and then defaults.  Sub-section (1) states: &ldquo;Where goods have been let under a hire-purchase agreement and one-third of the hire-purchase price has been paid ... the owner shall not enforce any right to recover possession of the goods from the hirer otherwise than by action&rdquo;.  That deprives the owner of one of the privileges he enjoyed of sending somebody around with a van and seizing everything he could get in the house, including goods which were not his.  The purpose of my amendment is to prevent his recovering possession if the hirer has paid one-fourth of the price instead of one-third.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the hire-purchase price of the article was £100 and the hirer has paid £25, I am endeavouring to secure that <Col N="186" /> the owner will have no right to seize that article without going into court and obtaining an order.  Under the Bill, there is no obligation on him to go into court unless the hirer has paid one-third of the purchase price, which is £33 6s. 8d. in the case I have mentioned.  That is the difference between what the Minister proposes and what I am endeavouring to secure. I am proposing to give to the hirer who has paid 25 per cent. of the purchase price the security which the Minister is offering the hirer who has paid one-third of the purchase price.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a question of judgment as to the point at which hardship begins.  We are trying in this Bill to establish a proper balance of rights as between the owner and the hirer of the goods.  It is, obviously, a hardship on the owner of goods if somebody enters into a contract to buy them on the hire-purchase system, gets delivery and pays one instalment and no more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>One instalment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>At what stage are we to shift protection from the owner to the hirer?  What the Bill proposes is that the owner will not be able to recover possession of the goods, except through court action, after one-third of the purchase price has been paid. Let us consider the position from the point of view of the owner.  He has goods for sale.  By entering into this agreement and delivering the goods to the hirer, he denies himself an opportunity of selling the goods to somebody else.  He loses possession of the goods for some time.  He takes a chance that the goods may be damaged or that some situation may develop which will involve him in loss. He may get the goods back after only a few instalments have been paid with a very reduced re-sale value.  I think it is a tradition of the motor trade in normal times that a new motor-car loses one-third of its value when the owner drives it home for the first time. It is quite clear that we must give the owner certain protection, too, and recognise that people will often rush into those hire-purchase agreements and regret them on payment of the first <Col N="187" /> instalment or after only a small number of instalments have been paid.</P>
      <P>On the other hand it is clear that, where a substantial amount has been paid, the hirer of the goods is entitled to protection.  It is only when a substantial amount has been paid that hardship is likely to be experienced by him if, for any reason, he defaults in payment and the owner recovers possession of the goods.  I think that one-third of the price is reasonable, having regard to all the circumstances, in the case of the hirer, and I think that, if we went below one-third, we would be acting unfairly to the owner.  For that reason, I should not like to accept Senator Duffy's amendment.  As the Bill stands, once one-third of the purchase price has been paid, the owner has no longer the right to recover possession of the goods, on default by the hirer, except through the court, and the court may make various types of order.  The order of the court may mean that the owner will not get back the whole of the goods or there may be some alteration in the agreement to the detriment of the owner.  In my judgment, it would be moving the point of balance too far from the owner if we were to reduce the figure from one-third to one-fourth. I agree that, if the hirer has paid one-third, he is entitled to the protection the Bill gives.  If he has not paid one-third, the owner is entitled to get recovery of the goods in the normal way.  If the figure were altered to one-fourth, I think that we should be acting unfairly to the owner, who is, inevitably, bound to suffer loss if the transaction does not go through.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I gave this matter some consideration when I read the Bill and I agree with the Minister. One of the difficulties is that this Bill applies to cheap wireless sets, costing £6 or £7 in normal times, and to an expensive motor-car.  If the majority of wireless sets sold on hire-purchase terms were to come back after one-third of the price had been paid, hire-purchase would cease.  The loss would be too great.  We must leave hire-purchase a workable proposition for the trade, while protecting the hirer. <Col N="188" /> In the case of hire-purchase, I know most about wireless sets.  If a wireless set came back in normal times after one instalment had been paid, a trader would be very lucky if he got half-price for it.  That is apart from any loss he might suffer by having his money out.  As a rule, the instalments are not pressed for a month or so after they are due.  If the figure were changed to one-fourth, one set of traders would get out of hire-purchase and the other would add to the total charge in order to cover unsatisfactory purchases.</P>
      <P>The net result, if you fine the thing too closely, would be to defeat the very object you are seeking to achieve, because it will add to the cost of these goods and, therefore, impose a hardship on poorer people.  I think, as I said before in this House, that as a general rule the experience is that the poorer people of the artisan class are the most satisfactory in payments.  I would not think that they are by any means the most difficult customers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that if Senator Douglas considered the purpose of the amendment, he would not talk of the problems that would arise if too many articles sold under a hire-purchase agreement are returned.  He spoke of goods being returned after one instalment had been paid.  That has nothing to do with the amendment.  I think the Minister was right when he said that what is involved is a matter of judgment&mdash;whether the court should intervene when one-fourth of the purchase price is paid or whether it should be ousted until one-third is paid.  Let us assume that somebody buys £100 worth of furniture and that he pays £30 in three instalments, and then defaults. There is no protection for the hirer under the Bill, as I understand it, any more than there is to-day.  The owner or the finance corporation who is collecting the instalments then has the right to send his van to the home of the hirer, to send a few strong men to take possession of the goods.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>He has the right to recover under the terms of the agreement. But the point I was making is that the hardship we are eliminating <Col N="189" /> under this Bill really arises in the case of a person who has paid 60, 70 or 90 per cent. of the purchase price and then defaults.  Under his existing agreement, he is liable to lose the goods.  At the present time, hire-purchases are carried out under the law of contract and the hirer may not fully appreciate the obligation he is entering into when he signs the contract.  The contract may give the right to recover the whole of the goods, if there is any default in payment at any stage of the transaction.  It is because cases have been reported of hirers who have paid three-fourths or perhaps 90 per cent. of the purchase price and then lost the goods because of inability to complete the transaction, owing to unemployment or something of that kind, that we are legislating to protect them.  We are bringing that protection right to the point where they have paid only one-third of the purchase price.</P>
      <P>I think that is as far as we can reach and if we go further we shall be acting unfairly to the owners of goods, and the consequences will be as Senator Douglas suggests.  Some traders will cease to engage in this trade because they cannot make a profit and others will remain in it by increasing the price of goods sold on hire-purchase to those who have to buy their goods by that method.  The owner of the goods generally loses if the transaction is not completed.  He loses by reason of the fact that he denies himself the opportunity of selling those goods to somebody else and because, when they come back, they are second-hand and cannot be sold at the same price at which they could be sold when new.  Then he has the additional trouble of delivering the goods and collecting them again when the transaction is terminated. I think we would be taking an undue risk of being unfair to owners if we reduce the limit set out in this section below one-third of the purchase price.  The recovery of the goods cannot be secured except through the courts after one-third of the value has been paid and it would be unreasonable to go below that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I was quite as clear as I might have been <Col N="190" /> when I spoke earlier on this amendment, as clearly Senator Duffy did not understand me.  My point is that the trader does not want back his goods during the first instalment periods because, if he takes them back, he loses on the transaction.  He will not be anxious to get them back during the period while the first one-third of the purchase price is being paid because he may lose on the transaction.  Generally he will lose if the goods come back before one-third of the price is paid. It will be with the greatest reluctance that he will take them back.  When it comes to the time, however, that he has received two-thirds of the price, he may be getting something out of the transaction and if he is not too scrupulous he may be anxious to take them back.  If you are going to reduce the fraction of the purchase price from one-third to one-fourth for the purposes of this section, you are only going to add to the total cost of the goods, particularly having regard to the fact that the owner will have to take into account the possibility that he will have to incur the legal expenses of going to court should he wish to recover the goods if there is a default in payment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nobody contemplating the owner taking back the goods at all except&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Except it pays him to do it.  It only pays him if a substantial amount of the purchase price has been paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder.  Take a case where a man buys £100 worth of furniture under a hire-purchase agreement. Three instalments of £10 each, or £30 in all, are paid on that furniture.  Under the Bill the owner can send his van to the house of the hirer and take that furniture back into his shop.  He has then £100 worth of furniture again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not worth £100 then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have shown here from actual experience of cases in the City of Dublin that the profit which the hire-purchase trader has on the cost price of the goods is over 100 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="191" />
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>That is ridiculous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is ridiculous but it is true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it is true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have had experience of talking to a certain Dublin shop craftsman who made furniture here in Dublin.  He identified for me, a suite of furniture which he had made.  He told me the cost price, the price at which it could be bought in an ordinary cash sale, and the hire-purchase price. The hire-purchase price showed a profit of well over 100 per cent., so that this suite of furniture would not cost the trader more than £50.  I am prepared to say that in some cases it did not cost more than £40.  After £30 has been collected in instalments on a hire-purchase agreement the stuff is taken back again into the shop.  Is that not the kind of conduct we should stop?  I agree with the Minister that there is a point at which we can allow the owner to seize the goods, because that is what he is doing, but we ought to make that point as near as we can to the starting point.  I do not think I am putting it unduly low when I suggest that that point should be 25 per cent. of the purchase price.  Let us bear this in mind. We are not depriving the owner of the right to get his goods.  We are only prescribing the procedure under which he is entitled to get the goods.  If two members of this House were to have a quarrel about the ownership of a horse they would be obliged to have that quarrel resolved in the court, no matter how strong one of them might consider his claim to be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>And get one-third of the horse back?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us say it is a greyhound. He at any rate must submit his claim to the determination of the court.  Under my amendment we are not asking the owner of the furniture to submit his claim to the court unless the hirer has paid more than one-fourth of the price which he contracted to pay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister takes the same view, only that he is prepared to allow the boys with the van to come along and, <Col N="192" /> without leave or licence from anybody, to exercise the right to seize goods if less than one-third of the value is paid.  That is just what is between us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>They have no right to seize goods unless the hirer has defaulted on his part of the contract.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Or the owner alleges he has defaulted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is basing his argument on the assumption that a trader in furniture, under the hire-purchase system, makes 100 per cent. profit.  Let me say in support of his contention that there has been the complaint during the war years that traders in furniture under hire-purchase agreements were unduly disposed to exercise the right to recover property on default of payment particularly when substantial sums had been paid because furniture had risen very steeply in value and the re-sale prices might be substantially above the price at which it was sold originally.  In normal times, however&mdash;and we must relate this Bill to normal times&mdash;there has been no trade in this country which suffered so much from price-cutting and sweated labour conditions in order to have cheap prices, than did the furniture trade.</P>
      <P>We have had many discussions in the House concerning these small back-room furniture factories that were operating and which were so detrimental to the interests of the better and larger concerns.  So I think it is true to say that in that particular trade before the war competition was so intense that 100 per cent. profit could not have been made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Competition was intense in the manufacturing end only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Intense in the trade too.  I will say this in support of my contention: that there was no class of goods more consistently advertised in the newspapers than furniture, particularly furniture available on the hire-purchase system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Which proves that they had the money, and had money available for advertising.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="193" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know if they pay for advertising until they see can they keep it up.  Seriously, however, my chief objection to this is that if you make it too tight the net result will be it will be only the firms such as described by Senator Duffy that will do the business.  You have to make it easy for the firm which does a <i>bona fide</i> cash business so that it can sell hire-purchase furniture at a reasonable price and make enough money just as if they sold it for cash.  If you make it very difficult and if you cut into their rights to have the goods back again, all that will happen is that only those who can by trick methods sell at a big profit will do this trade and you will not be helping the people who want to keep as near as they can to the conditions of the cash customer.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 14:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add to the section a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(4)  Nothing in this section shall prevent an owner from taking temporary possession of goods for the purpose of repairs or other agreed purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer to that is that there is nothing in the Bill which prevents it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the point I wanted to raise and I think it is well that everybody should be satisfied that that is so.  It all depends on the meaning of the words.  In the first place, it talks about enforcing the right to recover and then it goes on to say: &ldquo;if an owner recovers possession of goods in contravention of the foregoing sub-section....&rdquo; I put down this amendment, which may not meet the point I want to cover, in order to get this thing clarified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is rather important for the operation of this Bill that the people interested in operating it should know exactly where they stand.  There should be nothing whatever to prevent an owner from sending his van and taking an article at any particular time and having it put in order and repaired.  He <Col N="194" /> may require to do that if he wants to keep the article in order and the hirer wants that done in his own interest because he wants the article kept in proper order.</P>
    <P>There is another form of this practice I have come across particularly where people not in such good circumstances but who are scrupulously honest are concerned.  I know of several cases where the hirer came to the owner and said: &ldquo;I am out of work.  I am sorry I cannot pay the instalments, but I will pay them ultimately.  Would you mind taking this thing back and keeping it safe for me?&rdquo; A decent trader will do that for the hirer.  He knows he is losing some interest, but he wants to keep his customer, and that has in fact happened.  I would like to be quite sure that that thing can still be done.  I am not sure that it cannot and it may well be that it can.  I was a little doubtful about that matter and I am anxious to see that there will be no suggestion that there is a danger that hirers will lose their rights when an article is taken back for repairs in that way.  If there was any question of them losing their rights they would be indeed chary of sending the article back, but instead they might get a man to do temporary repairs which would not be satisfactory.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am advised that there is nothing in this section which prevents the owner and hirer agreeing as to the repair of an article by the owner, or even for the periodic inspection of an article by the owner.  The section relates to the recovery of possession of an article and only to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>But possession would be recovered if a wireless set, for instance, was brought into the shop of the owner for repair.  Possession would then be parted with and would then go back to the owner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I should say &ldquo;the right to recover possession&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I can see a particular case happening quite easily.  Supposing all the instalments have not been paid and the owner sends out <Col N="195" /> notice that he will take over possession unless the instalment is paid.  Then at the commencement of the enforcement of the right to possession, the hirer says that if the wireless set is put in order it will be all right.  The owner then only goes and gets that wireless set by agreement with the hirer, and I think that under the previous sub-section&mdash;sub-section (1) of Section 2&mdash; there has been there a contravention of the section, that the owner is recovering in contravention and is liable to the penalty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>If I understand the Senator properly, he is contemplating a situation in which the owner cannot recover possession of the goods except through the court, because more than one-third of the purchase price has been paid, but there has been a default on some subsequent instalment.  Instead of going to the court for the recovery of the goods, however, he persuades the hirer of the wireless set to send it down to him to be repaired and, having got it in his possession, holds on to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>No; he is going to send it back, but he is confronted with this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>And he would have recovered possession by means of a trick only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a trick to keep goods sent back for repair.  The owner finds that these goods of his want repair and he brings them back to his shop for a fortnight.  He repairs them and then redelivers them to the hirer, but he has then broken the provisions of this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>He has not; no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>That is clearly my reading of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure how far the fortnight would come into it.  I think that that may often happen.  You take a wireless set, but it could apply just as much to a motor car, especially at the present time.  It is the time taken for the purpose of repairs that counts.  You may have certain types of wireless, American and other classes, <Col N="196" /> and you cannot get the necessary parts for them.  It is useless for anyone to think that the repairs may be done in a fortnight.  It may take six or seven weeks to get the repairs done.  During that period I am not at all certain that the trader would not run a danger by keeping that article even though it was understood and agreed on.  Nobody will agree that it will take seven weeks for the purpose of repairs even though it is agreed that it should be repaired. I must confess that from the discussion we have had on this I would be very much inclined to advise our mechanics to be very careful if they were to take anything back for repairing. I am not at all happy about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not see where the Senator's difficulty comes in.  I do not know how that section could be read to imply that the owner and the hirer could not agree for the repair of the goods, or why the original hire-purchase agreement could not provide for inspection of the goods to ensure&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Inspection is quite different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>We are all quite happy about inspection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am referring to taking back to the premises of the goods for repair.  That is in the case of many articles of furniture, probably in the case of a motor car and certainly in the case of a wireless set, the only really satisfactory way of doing proper repairs of any serious kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>I am becoming a little alarmed about this, now that it has come to the question of a motor car.  In the case of a motor car, it is the common practice that the payments extend over 18 months or two years, in normal times.  After 18 months, it will happen that a car will come in in the ordinary way for extensive engine overhaul. If I am to read into Senator Douglas's remarks that there is a danger that, in doing that, even though we ourselves would not be doing the hire-purchase business&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That is different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="197" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>What you must not do is enforce a right to recover possession of the goods.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>I am worried about the danger which Senator Douglas seems to envisage.  If he is correct, one could not even repair a car.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I am afraid is the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to be quite clear.  Sub-section (1) merely debars him from enforcing a right to recover, a right he might have under the contract. He cannot enforce that right if one-third of the purchase price has been paid.  It is only where he acts in contravention of sub-section (1), that is, enforces a right to recover, that he becomes liable to the penalties set out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Take the case of a motor car.  Suppose I have a motor car on hire-purchase from Senator Summerfield.  I do not want to go into the position in which somebody else is doing the financing for him, because that is a complication.  So far as I am concerned, the contract is with him. Suppose I drive that car into his garage and say that I want an overhaul, telling him that I want it in a fortnight's time.  I know a little about the motor business and I know that, with the best will in the world, it will not always be done in the time specified.  Suppose, at the end of a fortnight, I walk in and find that the engine is down and then tell him that I must have that car back again, that he must send it back to me. He cannot do it and I then say that he has refused to deliver it.  This may seem a little fantastic, but I want to know what is enforcing a right to recover. I think that getting hold of it in the street, or getting it into a garage and keeping it, would be held to be enforcing a right to recover.  At what point is it to end?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am only arguing for a provision that nothing will prevent its being brought in for the purpose of repairs. I am not arguing that it is a bad section and I am not arguing against the section.  I am arguing that it would be wise to put into the section <Col N="198" /> some such amendment as I suggest. From what Senator Duffy and Senator Sweetman have said, I am convinced that it would be wise.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It convinces me of this: if you buy a car from Senator Summerfield, pay three instalments and then default in the fourth instalment, get it repaired somewhere else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the law, as Senator Sweetman knows, a motor repairer has a lien for repairs, irrespective of any agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot have a lien on your own property.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>But it is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>It is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been sold through a hire-purchase firm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>We are assuming that you are doing your own hire-purchase financing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister is right in his contention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope so, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>In this case, if a conflict arises, as it probably will in rare cases, it must be determined eventually by some court of competent jurisdiction.  I think that is the answer to the whole point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it could undoubtedly be so, but what Section 12 provides is that if the owner enforces a right to recover, where one-third of the purchase price has been paid, the hirer becomes absolved from the terms of the contract and has the right to recover from the owner through the court whatever he has previously paid under it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the issue not arise for decision in the court whether the owner acted properly or not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="199" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a question of whether he acted properly or not, but whether he exercised a right to recover.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Enforced a right to recover.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is worth a little consideration as to whether some such proviso would not be advisable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>When I got the Senator's amendment, I had the point examined, and I was assured that, on a purely legal interpretation of the section, it did not preclude the possibility of the owner and hirer agreeing to have repairs carried out and that that would not involve under any circumstances, an enforcement of a right to recover.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 12 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 15 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 16:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (4), line 30, after the word &ldquo;part&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;the length of time that instalments had remained unpaid after the due date&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The amendment raises a point which I think is of some importance.  Where the court has to deal with the distribution of the goods between the hirer and the owner, it seems to me that it is essential that the court should take into consideration the relative cost up to that date, and that, in order to do that, it must be allowed to take into consideration the amount of interest which the owner will have paid on his money through instalments not having been paid.  On the previous amendment, Senator Summerfield made reference to a hire-purchase company.  It is well known that in many cases, particularly in the more important transactions, the person who sells the goods, and who would normally sell them for cash, if they happen to be sold on a hire-purchase basis, goes to a particular firm.  There are various types of agreements, but in most cases the person who sells the goods will have to pay cash to that firm which is carrying out <Col N="200" /> the cash transaction if the hirer does not meet the instalments.</P>
    <P>For instance, if I sell an article on the basis of 12 months' instalments&mdash; in normal times, it would be convenient for me, but I am sorry to say at the moment stocks are so small that it is not much advantage&mdash;the article is handed out to some reputable hire-purchase firm and I have to meet them by means of payments over 12 months. There are, of course, other methods. If on this article A.B. is six months in arrears, I am paying interest at 5 per cent., 5½ per cent. or whatever rate the hire-purchase company has and I am losing actual money all the time.  If you do not let the court take that into consideration, you force the owner to take action very much sooner than he otherwise would.  That is my main concern.</P>
    <P>I am looking at this matter from the point of view of a person who has had only a very limited experience of hire-purchase, but who, because of that limited experience, has learned enough to talk about this Bill to a number of other people who have very wide experience and who have come to see me.  I look at it from the point of view of the ordinary cash-trading firm which does a limited amount of hire-purchase.  In practice, we would never dream of enforcing any right to recover or go to the courts, probably for six months.  Possibly, if it were a large article or an easily perishable article, it may be sooner.  The general tendency is to be very reluctant indeed to use any undue pressure, as one does better business and one is able to keep the customer. Also, one may get one crook and will not do any more business with him, while the majority of hire-purchasers are going to pay and will pay if given time.</P>
    <P>As this Bill stands, the firm which is most lenient and which waits longest before pressing for recovery will lose most, if the court cannot take into consideration the length of time during which the instalments have remained unpaid.  The length of time is the main factor in the cost of hire-purchase and, if that is excluded and the court cannot do anything about it, this is not going to work satisfactorily <Col N="201" /> and will work against the hirer.  I am pretty well convinced that that is right, though I have not consulted a Senator like Senator Summerfield to see his point of view about it.  The only answer that would satisfy me would be that the court can do it.</P>
    <P>Let me make it clear.  A person comes in and takes a 12 months' hire purchase and makes it into a two-year one.  If they had asked for a two-year period, they would have had to pay a higher rate of interest.  If they take two years on the 12 months' agreement the court should be able to take that into consideration and allow the rate in apportioning it as though it ought to be 18 months or two years.  Otherwise, the effect of this will be to tempt people to take a 12 months' agreement when they know it will really be 18 months.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>I am willing to join Senator Douglas in asking the Minister to look into this matter, as at the end of his remarks the Senator did produce a very vital factor in the cost of hire purchase.  There are different scales where the cost of the article itself is very considerable and, human nature being what it is and as we are not all angels, there will be people deliberately taking advantage of the situation if there is no penalty incurred in so doing, to buy a motor car on hire purchase spread over 12 months and have the payments extended to two years.  It would be well if the Minister could consider some wording whereby, in the event of payments being delayed, the hirer would become responsible for the scale of payments that is normally laid down on the form originally furnished, that is, if the agreement signed was for 12 months and he took 18, I think in equity the court should be obliged to make him pay on the 18 months' scale. Otherwise, there will be a reaction which will affect adversely the scheme outlined in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not attempting in this Bill to lay down in precise form what a hire-purchase agreement must contain or may not contain.  We are making it the law that, no matter what is in the agreement signed by the hirer, he will have certain rights and <Col N="202" /> that certain clauses in the agreement may be void.  It seems to me that whether the court can take into consideration any delay in making the payments must depend on what is in the agreement.</P>
      <P>So far as the Bill is concerned, it provides that where the owner is taking an action for recovery of the goods, one-third of the purchase price having been paid, &ldquo;he shall not take any step after the action has been commenced to enforce payment of any sum due under the hire-purchase agreement, or under any contract of guarantee relating thereto, except by claiming the sum in the action.&rdquo;  It is quite clear that the court can take into account whatever may be due to the owner and the length of time which it is due and the amount of interest, under the provisions of Section 3, which requires the court, in making an order for the transfer of ownership of portion of the goods to the hirer, to have regard to the amount already paid in respect thereof.</P>
      <P>Having regard to those provisions and having regard to the power still left to the trader to draw up the agreement in a form which protects his interest, and the obligation of the court to take it into account, it seems to me that the danger does not arise.  The agreement can be in whatever form the owner wishes, subject only to the provisions of the Bill.  We provide here that, once the owner has taken action for the recovery of the goods, he cannot press for payment of any instalments except by claiming whatever sum is due or may become due before the case is determined and the court, on making an award under (c), has to have regard to the amount already paid under the agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Has to have regard to the matters mentioned in clause (c) and only those matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>My trouble is that, when you are making an order under (c), the Minister says you can protect yourself.  I doubt very much if that is a matter where you can protect yourself under this Bill.  I do not think you could put in a proviso that there will <Col N="203" /> be interest added, as you have to state the cash price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing to prevent putting in the agreement a provision for interest on unpaid instalments. Even if the instalments are not paid, we do not compel the owner to go to court.  If he thinks he will get paid eventually by the hirer, he may let the additional interest accumulate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot conceive a hire-purchase agreement in which the interest accumulates and it would not be workable.  We are dealing now with the operation of (c) in this section.  I can see the possible difficulty in putting into a hire-purchase agreement that, in the event of this operating, interest will be calculated on the unpaid instalments. It is not the practice, nor would it be practicable to provide the calculation of interest day to day, as it may be for only two or three days or even a month.  No one would want to do it. It is only when you come to apportion the value where the owner is to retain one section and the hirer the other, that in calculating the cost of the unpaid portion, the time is a factor that is recognised in this section.  The length of time the hirer has the use may be taken into consideration, but you cannot take into consideration in the value the additional cost to the owner by the period of default.</P>
      <P>I put this forward in a helpful way and have not been pressing any amendments I put down.  It seemed to me to be a possible flaw.  The clause has not been operating sufficiently long in England.  I made some inquiries, but was not able to find a case of division.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Paragraph (c) has been altered considerably from the scope of the English Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>In conversation, I asked if there were a case where there had been a division and I could not come across one, but that does not say there has not been one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>We assume an agreement where there is a clause <Col N="204" /> providing that interest shall be payable on overdue instalments.  Let us take the Minister's point of view that such can be incorporated.  Such an agreement comes to the court for consideration under this clause (c).  I suggest that, if the Minister reads line 28 to the end of the clause, he will see that, even though there is that clause in the agreement, the court cannot consider it, because the court is bound under this clause to have regard to the amount already paid. That does not bring in the question of interest.  It is not to have regard to the amount already paid and the date of payment.  It says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Having regard to the amount already paid in respect thereof, the price of that part, the use which the hirer has had of the remainder of the goods and their depreciation in value, as the court thinks just.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The court is bound to take these four things into consideration, and only these four.  Though there may be other terms about over-due interests in the agreement the court could not take that into account as it would mean in effect as I see the situation that the court would never think in a case where there has been delay that it was just to make the order at all and, therefore, clause (c) would not achieve what is intended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Senator has read paragraph 4.  It says that the court may make an order for the specific delivery of all the goods to the owner, may make an order for delivery subject to the arrangement contemplated in paragraph (c), or</P>
      <P>&ldquo;make an order for the transfer to the hirer of the owner's title to a part of the goods and for the specific delivery of the remainder of the goods to the owner, subject, if the court thinks fit, to the condition that the hirer or any guarantor pays to the owner within a specified time such further amount in respect of the hire-purchase price as the court, having regard to the amount already paid in respect thereof, the price of that part, the use which the hirer has had of the remainder of the goods and their depreciation in value, thinks just.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="205" /> In other words, these conditions relate to the court's determination of any further sum&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That is where the instalments have been paid.  It is apportioning the proper amount to be paid. The court must, in fact, take that into consideration.  The more I think of it the more I think I am right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The owner of the goods has a claim on account of the sum due to him in respect, to unpaid instalments, and whatever other payment of interest the agreement may provide for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>In the British courts, where people have gone to court to enforce payments of sums due in this manner, the court has regard to the cost price of the goods.  In one case the court made an order for payment of an amount at 1d. per week, and it was calculated that it would take 3,000 years to pay it off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Such an order would come under paragraph (b).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister not agree to look into this between now and the next stage?  We will give him all stages on Wednesday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I will examine the point.  I think Senators are leaving out of account the fact that the agreement will protect the owner.  The owner may have rights under the agreement which are not invalidated by this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister is forgetting that he is forced to try to protect himself in this matter by introducing interest on the payment of instalments.  That is not done.  It might be done, but it would also be to the disadvantage of the hirer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be to the disadvantage of the hirer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>On consideration I am prepared to say that it could be done. Personally I would hate to see that practice started.  People might be obliged to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the Senator asking, if the owner of goods fails to take <Col N="206" /> action under Section 12, when there has been default, or delay in exercising his rights, that he should be recompensed for that delay by the court when the matter is decided by the court?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>You could put it that way if you like.  What the Minister calls delay I call a reasonable attitude towards the hirer.  It is true that if this provision works out unsatisfactorily&mdash;and I do not want to see that happen&mdash;it would kill hire purchase as a useful adjunct to business, and would hit some people extremely hard, particularly those who cannot get cash easily.  But I am sure Senator Summerfield will bear me out when I say that the general experience is that we do not go to court unless there is a clear case.  As far as I am concerned I had to go to the court in only one case, and that concerned the director of an extremely well-to-do company who paid up before the case came on.  That is the only case I allowed to occur, and I think that is the general attitude.</P>
      <P>This is a case where a person cannot go on, where, for various reasons, he is unable to continue the agreement. The court has to decide what is to happen in that case.  It does not give all back to the owner.  It gives portion to the owner, portion to the hirer, and decides what further sum the hirer must pay.  My contention is that it would be much better if it could take into consideration the factor of interest. That is what I ask the Minister to consider.  I think I am safe in saying that no further amendment will be put down to this Bill.  He may take it that if he says there is no need for further amendment I will be satisfied. The whole attitude here was to make this Bill a success.  There is no attempt to obstruct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no objection to leaving over the Report Stage until Wednesday, assuming that I will not be then engaged in the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid we will be sitting on Wednesday, Thursday and Friday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure if Senators gave full weight to sub-section (1), which provides that where action is <Col N="207" /> taken for recovery of possession of the goods, action may be taken also for recovery of any sum due under the agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the whole point that I wanted to make clear.  It is true that if a man makes a hire-purchase agreement for 12 months, when he should have made one for 24 months, there is only the amount for 12 months due, unless he introduces a new system to provide interest, which is not the practice.  Under the old system, if he was an extremely hard trader, he just took the goods back. If he was a decent trader he did what was done in some businesses.  Nine months out of 12 had been paid; he took the goods back, agreed as to what was the second-hand value of the goods, and handed the difference to the customer.  Certain firms did that.  The trader, of course, took into consideration what it cost him and said: &ldquo;There is the second-hand value of the goods; that is the amount I can get for them; if you can get that, well and good, but all I want is to get the thing settled.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That was really ultra legal, but that is the kind of thing for which you are making provision under the law now. You are providing what I contend a good trader, who wanted to keep his customers, would have done in any event.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>When the case comes to court, the court can settle it as it thinks equity requires.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Within the four walls.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly.  It can order the delivery of the goods to the owner but it can postpone the delivery and it can make such adjustments in the terms of payment as it thinks fair to the hirer; or it can divide the goods.  This section was amended in the Dáil because it was pointed out there that division of the goods might not be a practicable solution.  If, for instance, the goods consisted of a dining-room suite, a court could not take one certain piece of furniture and say that it represented the value of the total amount which should be allowed to <Col N="208" /> remain with the hirer.  In order to meet that practical difficulty, we amended the section so as to provide that the court could order that one piece of furniture would remain with the hirer, subject to the hirer paying a certain sum to make up the actual difference between the value of the piece and the value to which he was entitled in the judgment of the court. Part of paragraph (c) is intended to provide for that contingency.  I do not see that that affects the case made by Senator Douglas in any way.  In fact I am not at all sure how that case can be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid my power of argument is exhausted.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 13 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 17, 18 and 19 not moved.</P>
      <P>Sections 14 to 22, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Schedule stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I should be glad if the Minister would look into the point I made at the beginning with regard to the persons in the Schedule and the wording of the Schedule as to the way in which they can be attached.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill, of course, will come into operation on a date to be fixed, and that date will be some date subsequent to the enactment of the Bill; therefore, there will be some notice to traders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is going to be a couple of months I would be quite satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not say a couple of months, but some weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>You would be very clever if you could get a new agreement drawn up in two months at the present time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Any trader who is interested in this matter knows now that the Bill is going through with the <Col N="209" /> Schedule in it and can make arrangements accordingly against the date upon which the Bill will come into operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>That is true, but possibly the Minister does not know the difficulties of getting anything done at the present time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>What is more, there are traders all over the country who will never realise that this Bill is passed until they are prosecuted under it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>The only thing is that such traders buy the printed hire-purchase agreement and it is with that <Col N="210" /> in view that I raise the point.  I personally do not like the business.  I would be quite content not to do any for three months, if the Government passes this Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Wednesday, 3rd July, 1946.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 9.10 p.m. until 3 p.m., Wednesday, the 3rd July, 1946.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>