<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="5" Month="Jun" Year="1946" Vol="31" No="22" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 5 Meitheamh 1946" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 5 June 1946" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1875">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1875" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with the Order Paper to-day, the order will be somewhat changed from what appears on the paper.  It has been suggested, for the convenience of the Minister concerned, that Item No. 5 should be taken after Item No. 2.  The subject matter of No. 5 is generally taken as formal.  It has also been suggested, and I understand the arrangement has been agreed to, that Item No. 4, in the debate on which the Taoiseach will attend the House, should be taken on the resumption after tea at 7 o'clock.  I understand that arrangement would be of convenience to the Taoiseach.  Items Nos. 6 and 7 will not be taken this week, but it has also been arranged, I may say, in consultation with the Senators interested in No. 6, that it will be taken next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Land Bill, 1945&mdash;Message" RHead="from the Dáil">
    <Title>Land Bill, 1945&mdash;Message from the Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The following Message has been received from the Dáil:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Dáil Eireann has agreed to amendments Nos. 2 to 5, inclusive, made by Seanad Eireann to the Land Bill, 1945; it has disagreed to amendment No. 1; to which the agreement of Seanad Eireann is desired.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Seanad do not insist on amendment No. 1 made by it to the Land Bill, 1945, with which the Dáil has disagreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoylan" hpid="Minister for Lands (Mr. Moylan) Seán Moylan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands (Mr. Moylan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am completely unfamiliar with the method by which the Seanad does its business, and, therefore, I was at a <Col N="1876" /> loss in the Dáil during the past week in regard to the manner in which I should deal with the Land Bill as returned to the Dáil from the Seanad. I understood from Senator Sweetman that his three amendments were interdependent and that when one of them was defeated&mdash;particularly when amendment No. 1 had not been agreed to&mdash;it seemed to me that the passing of amendment No. 2, also moved by the Senator, was a rather useless proposition. Therefore, I recommended to the Dáil that the amendment which was passed in the Seanad should not be accepted by the Dáil.  I think that I have indicated to the Seanad my sympathy with the viewpoint expressed by the Senators who supported that particular amendment.  My reason for not recognising that point of view is that my proposal in regard to this legislation has a limited aspect.  It is not related to general legislation. There is also the point that we have to meet a particular difficulty in a particular manner.  Here we have one particular difficulty which we cannot meet otherwise than by the method which I have proposed.</P>
      <P>After a long discussion in the Dáil, the members of that House agreed, without any division, to accept all the proposals in the new Land Bill.  It was only in the Seanad that we found objection to particular proposals.  I regret that I have to refuse to accept the point of view expressed particularly by Senator Sweetman in regard to the question of &ldquo;residence&rdquo;.  I feel that if the Land Commission have the power and the authority given to them by the Oireachtas to give land to allottees that they, too, should have the power to insist that these allottees shall fulfill their commitments to the country.  That really is the reason why I feel that the amendment moved by Senator Sweetman and passed by the Seanad to substitute <i>prima facie</i> for &ldquo;conclusive&rdquo; should not be insisted upon by the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, if I may say so, has been extraordinarily innocent in the remarks that he has just made.  The plain facts of this matter are very, very simple.  The <Col N="1877" /> question, as the Minister has stated, was discussed at very great length in the Dáil.  In the Dáil Debates&mdash;Volume 100, No. 4&mdash;that discussion is set out very fully.  It appears quite clear from the report&mdash;column 510 and onwards&mdash; that the Minister based his whole case on the fact that it was not possible to make a verbal definition of the word &ldquo;residence&rdquo;.  When the Bill came to this House the Minister continued to base his case on the fact that a definition of the word &ldquo;residence&rdquo; was impossible.  His whole viewpoint at that time was quite clear.  What he was expressing to the House was that it was impossible to define &ldquo;residence&rdquo;, but that if anybody gave him a good definition of it he would be only too glad to accept it with open arms, so as to get over the impossible position in which the Land Commission is going to be judge, jury and prosecutor all combined. Then, he came along to this House. With the assistance of some other Senators, I put up the definition which is set out in column 1756.  The Minister was honest enough to admit that the form of words which I put up was perfect.  That was the Minister's description of them in this House. Having been given the answer to his question and having had the prop upon which he was relying knocked away, he had to come out in the true colours of the Land Commission and show that what the Land Commission wanted was not really a formula for &ldquo;residence&rdquo; but power to act as judge and jury themselves.  That has emerged clearly from the discussion of this Bill in the two Houses.  They were not concerned with a formal or technical objection; what they were concerned about was that their opinion should count and nothing else.  The amendment passed by this House, the rejection of which has now been moved by Senator Quirke, marked the end of the series of discussions in which we saw what was in the Minister's mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister was very naive in the way in which he referred to the matter in the other House.  I must, however, be perfectly fair to him and say that he made it quite clear in the other House that what happened here was not the fault of those who sponsored the <Col N="1878" /> amendment.  In justice to the Minister, I must pay tribute to his fairness in that respect.  It is quite clear, as the Minister says, that the amendment inserted by the Seanad cannot now be insisted upon.  If it were, the Bill would be complete and absolute nonsense. Senators will have had an opportunity, since then, of reading the report.  It was made clear in the beginning of the discussion that the main principle was being discussed with the amendment. If certain people did not want to accept amendment No. 1 as being consequential to No. 2, it would have been better to make that objection in the beginning.  The chaotic position into which the Bill was allowed to lapse would not then have occurred.  The responsibility must rest not on the Senator whose name appears in the report but on the whole of my friends on the other side who said &ldquo;Níl&rdquo; when the consequential amendment was being put.  On them must rest the responsibility for refusing to accept the earlier decision of this House.  In that situation, the amendment must now be left. The people concerned must be left to the mercy of the Land Commission instead of having the right, which, I thought, was their due, of explaining their case in the proper place.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>As one who supported the amendment moved by Senator Sweetman and carried by this House, I cannot understand why he faded out when No. 1 amendment was called by the Chair.  I do not think that it is fair for Senator Sweetman to say that there was a chorus of &ldquo;Níls&rdquo; from this side of the House when No. 1 amendment was called.  In fact, Senator Sweetman failed to insist upon No. 1 amendment. If he had called for a division, he would have got it.  Be that as it may, it is clear that the amendment which was inserted in this Bill by the Seanad cannot now stand and that the Seanad must agree to delete it from the Bill.  I voted for the amendment not because I felt that it would have any effect, in practice, when the Bill would become law but because I felt, as I always feel, that nothing conclusive should go into a court. The practice of Government Departments fortifying themselves by certificates <Col N="1879" /> which are conclusive leaves nothing to the court to decide and necessarily makes the court a rubber stamp for a Government Department. In this case, Senator Sweetman was too generous.  He was quite prepared to allow the certificate under the seal of the Land Commission to be conclusive evidence of the fact that a direction was given and that the direction had not been revoked.  But he was not prepared to agree that the certificate of the Land Commission, that the purchaser had failed to comply with the direction, should be conclusive evidence.  If Senator Johnston's amendment had been accepted, and the words <i>&ldquo;prima facie&rdquo;</i> substituted for the word &ldquo;conclusive,&rdquo; there would have been no difficulty.  I have learned the lesson that the simpler an amendment is, the more likely it is to be carried by the House.</P>
      <P>I pointed out on the last occasion that it is immaterial now whether the words <i>&ldquo;prima facie&rdquo;</i> appear in the Bill or the word &ldquo;conclusive,&rdquo; because Section 2 (b) (i) provides that the direction to be given to the purchaser is to reside continuously &ldquo;to the satisfaction of the Land Commission&rdquo; in the dwellinghouse.  For that reason, I voted against Senator Sweetman's amendment defining &ldquo;residence.&rdquo;  It would have been otiose and unnecessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The object of defining the word &ldquo;residence&rdquo; would be to enable the court to determine whether or not the person had resided in the dwellinghouse but inasmuch as the Bill provides that the purchaser must reside in the dwellinghouse continuously &ldquo;to the satisfaction of the Land Commission&rdquo;, the court would never get an opportunity of construing the definition of &ldquo;residence&rdquo; if it had been inserted in the Bill.  Under the Bill as it stands and as it will now pass into law, the Land Commission can make their own definition of residence.  The Bill provides that the purchaser is to reside continuously in the dwellinghouse &ldquo;to the satisfaction of the Land Commission&rdquo; and whether a person sleeps and eats in the house or whether he spends his week-ends there or not, <Col N="1880" /> the Land Commission are the sole judge of &ldquo;residence&rdquo; and &ldquo;continuous residence&rdquo;.  For these reasons, the proper thing to have done would have been to delete the words &ldquo;to the satisfaction of the Land Commission&rdquo; from the Bill.  As that was not done at the time, it is now too late to lock the stable door.  Therefore, I agree that the amendment, for which I voted and which was passed by the Seanad, should not be insisted upon.  I feel that I am losing nothing, especially as I made my protest in voting for the amendment against the practice which I hope will not be repeated in future legislation of Government Departments endeavouring to obtain the consent of the legislature to what I may call <i>letters de cachet</i> or governmental legislation providing for executing governmental judgments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a new procedure for me too.  Are discussions on this matter in Committee or in the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In the House.</P>
      <P>Motion put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>Message to be sent to the Dáil accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Tourist Traffic (Amendment) Bill, 1946 &mdash;(" RHead="Certified Money Bill )&mdash; Second Stage">
    <Title>Tourist Traffic (Amendment) Bill, 1946 &mdash;(  Certified Money Bill )&mdash;  Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Seán F. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill as Senators will have noticed has for its purpose the authorising of advances to the Irish Tourist Board to a total sum in excess of that provided in the Act of 1939. That is the sole purpose of the Bill and presumably, therefore, effective discussion of the proposal will take place on this stage.  The Bill is not one that lends itself to Committee Stage debate, having, as I say, that one purpose.  The Irish Tourist Board was set up under the Act of 1939 but owing to the outbreak of the war its activities since its establishment up to date have been very considerably curtailed.  In fact, when the war began it was considered necessary to suspend activities by the board almost entirely.  For a period, the board maintained only a nominal <Col N="1881" /> existence with a skeleton staff which was engaged upon certain preparatory work.  After a period, however, it was decided that some wider activities could be authorised, particularly with a view to having prepared by the board plans for the development of holiday resorts and similar schemes which would be useful in providing employment in the immediate post-war period.  The board prepared a number of such plans and submitted them for approval in accordance with the provisions of the Act and approval was, in fact, given in a number of cases.</P>
      <P>The necessity for this Bill arises, not because the actual expenditure which the board has undertaken has exceeded the amount authorised under the 1939 Act, but because the total expenditure involved under the approved plans is slightly in excess of that sum and it is considered desirable that the authority of the Oireachtas should be obtained through the enactment of this measure before further plans which the board have in contemplation are considered.</P>
      <P>During the years up to 1944 the board was exclusively engaged in the preparatory work to which I have referred, in planning the various resort development schemes and to a limited extent in the acquisition of property for the purpose of such schemes.  The only actual work undertaken by the board was at Tramore where the work which the board had in contemplation was begun earlier than might otherwise have been the case because of the request from the Army authorities to the board to assist in providing suitable employment schemes for the men of the Construction Corps.  The work at Tramore was in fact carried out by the Construction Corps.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In 1944 the part of the Act dealing with the registration of hotels was brought into operation.  Senators will remember that the Act gave the Irish Tourist Board control of the word &ldquo;Hotel&rdquo; and of the term &ldquo;Guest-house&rdquo; and only premises which were registered by the board as hotels or guesthouses could be so described. To secure registration certain standards in accommodation and <Col N="1882" /> comfort must be maintained.  That part of the Act was brought into operation in 1944 and was actively applied in 1945 though on account of circumstances obtaining last year the standards sought by the board were necessarily less exacting than those which the board will usually apply.  It will, I think, be recognised that last year it would not be reasonable to require hotels to install equipment and carry out improvements because of their inability to secure suitable supplies.</P>
    <P>In addition to preparing resort development schemes and bringing into operation the hotel registration provisions of the Act the board also acquired certain properties suitable for development as hotels.  They acquired them with Government approval because these properties were available at the time and it did not appear probable that private enterprise was ready to develop them. I have explained elsewhere that it is the intention of the board and the policy of the Government so far as the development of hotels is concerned to rely entirely, or almost entirely, upon private business enterprise.  The properties which have been acquired by the board and which are now being developed as hotels have been transferred by the board to a company which it caused to be formed and which is only a temporary arrangement, the intention being that shares in the company will be ultimately offered to the public.  The various properties, whether they continue to be managed by this new company when transformed into a publicly owned company, or disposed of to other private firms will not be the direct concern of the board.  I have always considered it a necessary part of the whole scheme upon which the 1939 Act was based that the Irish Tourist Board, as such, having direct responsibilities for the supervision of hotels, should not be actively engaged in the hotel business.  The main work of the board, the work for which the money provided by this Bill is required, is the development of holiday resorts.  The board receives advances under the Act for the purpose of expenditure <Col N="1883" /> on holiday resorts only when it certifies, and when its certificate is accepted by the Government, that a particular scheme is of a profit-making character.  The board is required to confine its activities to schemes which are of a profit-making character, which will enable it to recover the whole of the expenditure, and to repay the amount of the advances to the Exchequer.  The normal procedure of the board in meeting that obligation is to acquire properties at holiday resorts, and having acquired a property to proceed to develop it by the construction of public amenities of one kind or another, thereby endeavouring to increase the value of the property which it has acquired and to put itself into a position to dispose of it by sale or lease to private firms willing to take over the property to develop it for any commercial purpose.</P>
    <P>The progress made along these lines to date has not been considerable, first of all, because the board was not permitted actually to embark upon schemes of that kind in the abnormal circumstances of the war years, and secondly, because the preliminary steps necessary to ensure the proper development of the lands required by the board often involved delay.  If it is necessary to acquire property the board has been given certain powers of compulsory acquisition but they decided to avoid, if possible, the use of those powers.  Even if they decide to use their compulsory powers&mdash;and in some cases it will be necessary to do so&mdash;the procedure laid down by the Act does not permit of the rapid transfer of the ownership of the desired property to the board.  Secondly, it will be obvious from the very brief picture I have given of the board's method of working that, in every case, the co-operation of the local authority is essential.  The development of any holiday resort area is not practicable unless water supply, sewage services and similar public services are provided by the local authority.  In a number of cases, the resort development schemes which have been planned by the board are awaiting the consent of the local authority to provide these services.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1884" /> The board has submitted and secured approval for proposals for resort development at a large number of centres and perhaps the Seanad will be interested to obtain particulars of these projects for the purpose of illustrating the nature of the plans which the board is elaborating.  At Ardmore, the board has purchased the lands, buildings and effects of the Irish college and is arranging for the internal reconstruction of the college.  The total cost of that project will be about £10,000.  In that connection, I might mention that one of the obligations placed upon the board by the Government was to give special regard to the development of facilities for holiday-makers who might wish to combine their holidays with the study of the Irish language, by ensuring that facilities of a suitable kind existed in the Irish-speaking areas.  In some cases, these facilities may be provided by private companies or other authorities assisted by the board, and in other cases directly by the board itself.</P>
    <P>At Arklow, in County Wicklow, the board has acquired certain properties and proposes to undertake their reclamation and development.  There may be some difficulty in completing the plan of the board at Arklow, owing to problems associated with the character of the property, but the board has a development scheme for Arklow which involves a total expenditure as at present planned of about £27,000. At Bundoran, the board has acquired a town park, recreation centres and buildings and is proposing to undertake expenditure which, including acquisition, will amount to about £25,000 on the development of the property as a recreation centre.</P>
    <P>At Garryvoe, the board has made a loan to an operating company for improvements. At Glengariff, it has acquired some 300 acres and proposes to develop the area for the provision of recreation facilities to a cost of about £10,000.  There is a similar scheme for Kilkee, involving expenditure of about £20,000 and a scheme for Killarney involving acquisition of property and construction of a sports club, pavilion and restaurant, to a total cost of about £25,000.  The board has made an advance to the Lisdoonvarna <Col N="1885" /> and Rooska Spa Wells Trust for certain development works in connection with the spa and has acquired the Queen's Hotel at Lisdoonvarna which it is developing in connection with the general scheme for the improvement of the facilities at Lisdoonvarna and the attraction of holiday traffic to it in connection with the spa.  At Portmarnock, County Dublin, the board has acquired St. Marnock's house and lands.  The scheme involves the transformation of the house into a hotel, provision of roads, levelling of sand-hills and the construction of recreational facilities.</P>
    <P>At Rosses Point, it has acquired certain property and it is proposing also to develop recreational facilities.  There is a scheme also for Skerries, involving the acquisition of ground for an amusement park and the provision of general recreation facilities.  That scheme may not be proceeded with, as it seems possible that private enterprise will undertake the development work which the board had in contemplation.</P>
    <P>At Tramore, to which I referred already, the total cost contemplated by the board amounts to £114,000.  It includes the acquisition and conversion of properties and the development of sites, so as to provide recreational facilities appropriate to a popular seaside resort.  There is also a scheme for Youghal, involving the acquisition of a site and its development so as to provide hot sea-water baths and recreational facilities, as well as suitable areas to be leased for the operation by private enterprise of cafés and restaurants.</P>
    <P>In addition to those I have mentioned, the board has acquired Ballinahinch Castle and lands and also the fisheries at Recess.  That property is being transferred to the hotel company which the board has established and will be developed by that company as a hotel.  Similarly, the board has acquired property at Courtown, County Wexford, of a similar character, which is being developed as a holiday hostel and as a hotel.  I mentioned also that St. Marnock's is being developed as a hotel, having been transferred to the hotel company to which I have referred.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1886" /> The board also acquired a house and lands in Newtown, County Louth, which is being transferred to the hotel company, and which will be developed as a holiday resort with hotel accommodation.</P>
    <P>The total value of all the schemes which have been approved as at present planned, amounts slightly to over £1,000,000.  It is contemplated also, that the board will now proceed on the lines generally intended when the 1939 Act was being framed, in affording financial accommodation to hotel proprieters who desire that accommodation for the purpose of improving and enlarging their hotels.  It is not clear that any number of hotel proprietors will, in fact, desire to obtain or need the board's assistance for that purpose, or, at least, need it to the extent which it was originally considered they might in 1939.</P>
    <P>If, however, hotel proprietors require the aid of the board, the board will be in a position to grant them that aid.  I have stated already that the provision of better and increased hotel accommodation must be undertaken mainly by private business concerns, and in so far as it is obviously desirable that the available hotel accommodation should be enlarged and improved, it is necessary to provide some assistance through the board for hotel proprietors, that need is covered by the Act.</P>
    <P>At present, hotel accommodation at holiday resorts is completely inadequate to serve the needs of our own people, and assuming that these resorts will be more largely patronised in the future as a result of the work done by the board in improving them, it is necessary that private enterprise should not be dilatory in following up the board's work, by extending and improving holiday accommodation. I expressed the view in the Dáil that it may have been a mistake to have called the Irish Tourist Board by that name in the Act of 1939, the Tourist Act, because it appears that to some people the word tourist is always associated with <Col N="1887" /> tourists from abroad.  It is, of course, to be expected that in present circumstances throughout the world a number of holiday-makers from other countries will desire to come here and that position may continue for a time. I have, however, tried to make it clear that in present circumstances, we cannot possibly hope to cater for any substantial number.  The hotel accommodation does not exist, and the Tourist Board has in fact been confining its activities in that regard to advising persons in other countries not to come here, unless they are sure of having hotel accommodation arranged in advance.  In future years, when conditions are more normal, we must, I think, make an effort to attract holiday-makers from other countries.  That is a form of export business developed in a number of countries, and which before the war was increasing in volume very rapidly indeed.  We have got facilities here which would be attractive to holiday-makers of a particular kind.  We cannot provide all forms of holiday-facilities, but, taking advantage of our circumstances, it is clear that we can secure a substantial share&mdash;a significant share&mdash;of that business and by doing so add considerably to the national income and secure a revenue which, relative to our own resources, will bear comparison with that obtained by other European countries from that trade in the pre-war years.</P>
    <P>The improvement of traffic facilities throughout the world has been going on since the emergency ended, and it is to be expected that holiday traffic will continue to increase for a long time to come.  I hope, however, that the future possibilities of the tourist business as ordinarily understood, will include a continued development of the holiday habit which has been growing among our own people.  It is not merely that those who in the past ordinarily ceased work for two weeks or more in the year have been inclined to spend their holidays here, and can be induced to spend their holidays here in greater numbers if the facilities are attractive, but the enactment of legislation concerning holidays for workers and the growing movement to provide longer <Col N="1888" /> holidays, will also create a situation which calls for action on the part of the Government as well as private enterprise, to ensure that workers will be able to get adequate and reasonable holiday facilities within their resources. One of the obligations of the Tourist Board is to procure the development of or to develop itself, holiday hostels, and holiday camps, where attractive holidays at seaside resorts or inland areas can be provided at low cost and in circumstances which will permit of enjoyable and healthy holidays by those patronising them.</P>
    <P>It will be understood that the board cannot take immediate steps to that end at the moment owing to the scarcity of materials, and particularly of the type of equipment required to make these holiday camps and hostels suitable and adequate for the needs of those using them, but plans to that end are being prepared, and with the enactment of this Bill, the Government will be in a position to give approval to any suitable plans which the board may prepare and submit to it.</P>
    <P>I think what I have said covered the greater part of the board's activities and future intentions.  Many of these individual resort plans could be described in detail, but I do not think that is necessary.  I should imagine that the Seanad would require just a general indication of the type of work it has in mind and the general methods by which it proposes to proceed.</P>
    <P>In addition to the advances repayable to the board under the Act of 1939 which represented the amount the board will invest in these profit making resort development schemes, the board also receives by way of grant by annual vote of the Dáil, an amount to cover its administrative expenses.  In the present year, the total amount granted will be £38,000, of which £18,000 will be expended on general publicity and advertising and which represents part of the board's general work which cannot be made directly remunerative by any scheme.  The balance of the advance, £20,000, is expended by the board on staff salaries, rent, rates and establishment charges in connection with its premises, and on furniture, <Col N="1889" /> bedding, travelling expenses, and similar normal items of expenditure.</P>
    <P>On the assumption that the Oireachtas which approved of the Bill of 1939, will be anxious that the Tourist Development Board should now get into activity along the lines contemplated in 1939, and that the wider the field of its work and the larger the number of resorts in which it can be enabled to carry out schemes, the better, this Bill will offer no difficulty to the Seanad.  The actual expenditure by the board for this year, and probably even for next year, may not reach the total of the advances fixed by the 1939 Act.  We might, therefore, have postponed the introduction of this measure for a period, although it would have been, perhaps, doubtful practice for the Government to approve in principle of projects which would ultimately involve raising the total of the advances to the board above the limit fixed by the Act without prior consultation with the Oireachtas.  It was decided, however, that even though the expenditure had not reached the limit fixed in 1939, the Bill should have been brought forward. I would have preferred if it were possible to postpone bringing the measure forward here until it would be practicable to judge in a more concrete form the results of the board's work.  At present it has nothing more than plans. The board has acquired properties in certain areas, but it has not yet under taken the development of these properties adequately.</P>
    <P>It is, perhaps, unsatisfactory from the point of view of members of the Seanad that they should be asked to increase the limit fixed in the 1939 Act without having the opportunity of seeing, in a precise detailed way, the nature of the work which the board proposes to do.  In a year or two there should be more visible evidence of that work.  The Seanad will, of course, understand that even the resort development schemes which will be begun this year will, in most cases, not be begun until after the present holiday season.  It would be undesirable, and from the point of view of private persons engaged in the provision <Col N="1890" /> of holiday facilities objectionable, to have large-scale construction works proceeding during the holiday season itself.  Therefore, the commencement time for most of the board's schemes which have reached the point where construction work could begin is fixed for October or November next when the holiday traffic will have ceased.  The aim of the board will be to carry through these schemes, as far as possible, and to round off the construction work in connection with them before the holiday season for 1947 begins.</P>
    <P>I think I have now given the Seanad the information which it desires to enable it to consider the Bill.  I will be glad to supplement that information when concluding the Second Reading discussion if it is desired.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>In the first place, I want to make it crystal clear that any view I may express to the House on this Bill is being expressed by me as a Senator and not by virtue of any position that I may hold in any other organisation.  It is my own personal view, and is, therefore, not to be construed as being in any way the view of the association.  As one who has always been interested in the development of the tourist industry, I was particularly glad to hear certain portions of the Minister's statement to-day, those portions which were a tacit admission that the views expressed by him in 1931 on the Committee Stage of the Tourist Traffic Development Act of that year were not, in fact, the correct view.  Those views can be found in Volume 38, column 19, where the Minister was inclined to sneer at the efforts that were then being made in regard to tourist development.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In discussing this whole question of tourist development, I think it is quite correct, as the Minister has stated, that we should have clearly and exactly in our minds what we mean by these words.  I agree with the Minister that the name Tourist Board is, perhaps, unhappy, and that such a name as a &ldquo;visitors' board&rdquo; or a &ldquo;tourist holiday-makers' board&rdquo;&mdash;though perhaps more cumbersome&mdash;would have been a far better name to signify the aim at which we should strive.  A <Col N="1891" /> tourist was defined in 1937 by the League of Nations as a person who spent more than 24 hours in some country other than the country in which he usually resides.  When speaking of tourists and of tourist travel, I do so in the strict sense of having that definition in mind, but when dealing with the holidays of our own people, I think it is better to describe them in some way other than by using the term tourist so that we may see clearly what we mean.</P>
    <P>So far as the tourist industry itself is concerned, I think we are all agreed that there are certain intangible advantages as well as tangible advantages in it.  I think it is agreed that the movement of people amongst each other is a thing that is going to promote peace.  It is a thing that is going to mean that people will get to know and understand their problems better, problems that affect different nations, and will, therefore, perhaps assist towards that end.  It is also admitted, I think, that travel is a thing which always broadens one's mind.  It enables one to see another person's point of view.  In so far as we here are concerned, that is a matter in regard to which I think it can be of special importance.  It is a matter to which I made reference not very long ago.  I did so in the place where I thought that primary reference should be made to it.  I think it is no harm to refer to it again here.  I believe that, in the promotion of tourist traffic between this country and the United Kingdom, and of holiday traffic between North and South, we are going to make one step that will assist in solving a problem that was thrust upon us by the British before the Treaty.  If we get the opportunity of explaining the position in regard to Partition to British tourists, if we get the opportunity of explaining the position and of getting to know and understand the point of view of our fellow-countrymen in the North through tourism&mdash;we all know the importance of getting everybody to understand the other person's point of view&mdash;it is only then that we will get the first prerequisite to a solution of the Border problem, namely, goodwill and understanding on both sides. <Col N="1892" /> It is because I feel so strongly on that, that I urge that is one of the intangible results that we may hope to get out of the industry as a whole. Quite apart from these intangible results, there are also some very important substantial and economic advantages to be got.  So far as the present machine age is concerned, holidays are more than ever necessary. The machine-like operations by virtue of which workers have to repeat <i>ad nauseam</i> a particular movement&mdash; in which they have to repeat that movement to the tempo not of their own natural ability but to the tempo of the machine&mdash;produces a nervous tension which calls for relaxation. Holiday facilities are now fairly universal throughout Europe.  People have become entitled to holidays with pay.  These facilities have in the last 15 years extended beyond all question, and have, in fact, quadrupled themselves. The Minister was perfectly correct when he said that, so far as the tourist industry is concerned, it is just as much an export industry as the making of clothes or shoes here to send abroad.  That fact was first recognised in the Banking Commission's Report. They stated that the development of the tourist industry was a thing that had a very special value in regard to the balance of payments, and went on to say that they regarded our advantages here as being very special because of the position we occupy and so forth.  Let us consider the export trade of a particular country&mdash;Canada. We have always thought of Canada in terms of wheat exportation.  We always considered that that was Canada's main export but the fact remains that, in the last year before the war, the value of the tourist industry to Canada was 291,000,000 dollars, while the value of the wheat exported from that country was only 260,000,000 dollars.  In France, before the war, the tourist industry was regarded as worth about £80,000,000 per annum.  The Italian tourist industry was worth about £26,000,000.  It is common knowledge that, in Switzerland, the value of the tourist industry was inestimable. Those countries will be making energetic efforts in the future to recover that trade.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1893" /> Let us consider for a moment what the value of the trade was to us in previous years.  It was estimated at one time&mdash;the Minister referred to this estimate in introducing the Bill in 1939&mdash;that the gross value to us of the tourist industry was £2½ millions.  I do not know whether the figures were then available or not but subsequently I was able to ascertain that there were figures available to show that, in 1938, that was an under-estimate.  Figures were published in that year which showed the number of travellers to this country from the United Kingdom, the U.S.A. and elsewhere.  Making the modest estimate&mdash;everybody will agree that it is modest&mdash;that £10 per head would have been spent by each traveller, the value resulting, excluding American travellers, would be about £3,300,000.  A further estimate was officially made by the American Government that the amount spent by American residents in Eire in 1938 was £700,000.  Seven hundred thousand pounds converted into dollars would be a valuable asset now.  I want to make perfectly clear that, if we are to obtain any benefits from the moneys introduced in this way, we must be certain that our own people do not detract from the value of the asset by going out of the country to take their holidays.  We must give attention to the question of saving before we get these additional moneys into the country.  Therefore, our object should be to make certain, in the first place, that there are proper and adequate facilities for our own people.</P>
    <P>I regret very much that the Irish Tourist Board appear to have forgotten the first essential to the success of the industry&mdash;goodwill amongst those who are the operating factors in the industry.  Unless there is complete and absolute goodwill between the Tourist Board and the hotel-keepers, there will not be any real success for the tourist and holiday industry.  The Minister, in winding up his speech, said that it would have been &ldquo;doubtful practice&rdquo; for the Government to approve any particular plans for the development of resorts before the Oireachtas had given legislative sanction to the full amount to be expended.  I entirely agree with <Col N="1894" /> him.  I go further and say that it is doubtful practice, indeed, that the powers given under the Act of 1939 for a particular purpose, powers granted by the Oireachtas on particular explanations by the Minister, should have been utilised in another fashion. When the Bill of 1939 was being put through, it was made very clear by the Minister that the whole purpose of advances to the board was to assist those already in the trade and that there was but the minutest chance that the moneys made available would be utilised by the board for the purchase of hotels which would be in competition with those existing.  That was made clear not only in this House but in the Dáil.  It was made clear that, in the view of the Government, the advances to be made available under that Act would be used to assist the existing trade in carrying out works to provide necessary facilities.</P>
    <P>There has been universal condemnation by hotel-owners that up to the present no system has been available by which they could get the loans and facilities promised them in 1939.  It has been universally condemned that, before those facilities were made available to hotel-owners, the board were themselves taking over and operating, either themselves or through a dummy company, hotels which were bound to take some traffic from the existing institutions before they had an opportunity of getting on their feet.  The Minister is as well aware as I am that one of the main features of the tourist industry in France prior to the war was the national credit company which made available a sum of 80,000,000 francs by way of long-term loans to hotels to enable them to be modernised.  A credit corporation was set up by the Government in the same way in Switzerland, which, I think, advanced about 50,000,000 Swiss francs to hotels.  An assistance board was set up in Italy which lent to hotels and such establishments which required improvement or modernisation about 100,000,000 lire.  That was the way in which the Tourist Board should have operated here.  If they had, they would have got the co-operation which the hotel-keepers were anxious to give. <Col N="1895" /> The Minister, in his speech, said he was doubtful that the people who owned hotels at present wanted the facilities which were thought desirable in 1939. It is peculiar, if the Minister's statement is correct, that the last available report of the Irish Tourist Board&mdash;the report for the year ending 31st March, 1945&mdash;contains this sentence: &ldquo;Numerous applications have been received for such loans.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>If there is any doubt in anybody's mind as to whether these facilities are required, why did the Tourist Board themselves express the exact reverse in that report that is laid on the Tables of the Oireachtas in accordance with the Act?  I suggest to the House that the first thing that should have been done&mdash;and there was plenty of time to do it during the war years&mdash;was to make available a scheme of finance so that those hotel proprietors who were anxious to expand their business, who were anxious to modernise their establishments, should have been enabled, so far as State assistance was concerned, to go ahead if and when, as was undoubtedly felt and as is still apparently felt, ordinary credit facilities were available merely for short-term loans and not for the long-term loans of the type required for the modernised improvement that is necessary. Instead of that, we have the Irish Tourist Board launching out into the ownership of hotels, launching out into State ownership either through themselves or through a dummy company&mdash;it does not matter&mdash;launching into State ownership, State control, State operation of something that is very much better done by individuals and that has been very much better done by individuals in every country under the sun.</P>
    <P>I suspect that is all being done because of the fact that the Tourist Board has been completely influenced by the visit of its chairman to America.  I think it is within the memory of almost everyone in this House that when the chairman of the Tourist Board came back from America having had a tour in that country, he gave an interview on the 7th November to the newspapers in which he described the luxury hotels, <Col N="1896" /> with every type of modern and extravagant convenience, that were going to be erected here.  I shall be fair to him; I will say that he came out the following day with an additional statement in which he said that the first interview was not as quoted.  Of course the plain fact of the matter is that he knew the reception that his interview got and decided that he had better change his tune as quickly as ever he could.  What is going to happen in regard to these luxury hotels because there are going to be luxury hotels apparently?  We are going to find ourselves in the same position in which the American hotel industry found itself about ten or 15 years ago when it was estimated that 85 per cent. of the hotels in America were in the hands of banks, insurance or mortgage companies because they were not able to operate at effective costs.  They had been constructed with such elaboration and on such a luxurious basis, that it was found that the overhead costs that had to be met took away the profits unless the charges were fixed at a very high figure.  The charges having been fixed so high to meet these overhead expenses, sufficient guests could not be found to stay in the hotels.</P>
    <P>I am not a cinema goer but I understand that at the moment there is a &ldquo;flick&rdquo; showing in the city.  It gives a good indication of a week-end in a luxury hotel in New York and it shows how hard it is to get accommodation at present in hotels in America.  That was not always so.  There was a time not so very long ago&mdash;I would say about ten or 15 years ago&mdash;when no hotel in America was ever more than half full. This film typifies the attitude of the Irish Tourist Board in its approach to this problem.  What we want in this country is not luxury hotels of that type.  We want hotels that are good and clean, in which the cooking, if I may say so, presents an Irish appearance&mdash;not bad foreign cooking but good clean Irish cooking.  We would get far more respect and utilisation for hotels equipped in that way and far more appreciation from visitors.  People on holidays do not expect wonderful luxuries.</P>
    <P>They expect cleanliness, civility and <Col N="1897" /> recreation; they expect a rest from the machine-like operation of their daily lives to which I have referred. If we make up our minds to give them that, then the money that we are asked to vote by this Bill will be money that will be utilised for a good and effective purpose.  It is not too late for the Minister to mend the hand of the Irish Tourist Board and I would sincerely appeal to him to do so.  The principles upon which the board will operate are the principles which he lays down.  In one direction there is a future; in the other there is no future except squandermania and megalomania in regard to public moneys.  There are many other ways in which this money could be more effectively utilised so as to make certain that there would be a real benefit to the country as a whole as a result of this expenditure.</P>
    <P>We all know that one of the great difficulties in connection with the tourist industry is the fact that holidays are concentrated so much into August and perhaps the last week in July.  If a real attempt were made to tackle the problem of staggering holidays, we would be getting somewhere and we would be able to utilise to the fullest the accommodation that is available.  A questionnaire was sent out in another country to discover why people liked to take all their holidays at one particular time of the year.  Of the replies received, 45 per cent. showed that the reason was that the head of the family wanted to make his holiday coincide with the school holidays of his children.  Has any attempt been made here to face up to that position, to see whether it would be possible to operate school holidays in a way in which they would not clash with what is the busiest month, as far as holidays are concerned?  Has the Minister also discovered that it is quite a waste of time to discuss anything with the Minister for Education?</P>
    <P>A reference was made by the Minister to the company that has been formed for the purpose of carrying out certain agency work for the Irish Tourist Board.  I do not know the legal basis upon which the <Col N="1898" /> Minister and the Tourist Board rely for the setting up of Failte Teo. Section 14 of the 1939 Act is the Section which deals with the powers of the board.  I suggest that it is, at least, straining the terms of that section to suggest that the Tourist Board are to be entitled to set up a company which is going to carry on, or which is even empowered to carry on, the business of victualler, wine merchant, spirit merchant, brewer, maltster, distiller, the manufacture of pleasure steamers or other sea-going or river-going craft, importers and brokers of food, of live and dead stock, farmers, theatre owners, cinema proprietors, dairymen, merchants and purveyors, messengers, chemists, tobacco merchants, hair-dressers&mdash;is there anything else the Irish Tourist Board would like to operate through this dummy company of theirs?  Or do they want to go into a new industry, an industry which one Senator has reminded me of?  Do the Tourist Board want to do that by a trick and by evading the 1939 Act which permits them to carry on?</P>
    <P>I know it will be said that these are only enabling powers and that they are not going to be used, but let us remember that in 1939 the same Minister said that the powers to acquire and operate hotels were only enabling powers and would not be used except in a particular and minute case.  It has been shown that once the power is given through a Government Department that that power may be used and that sooner or later that is going to be done unless there is a public outcry and unless the Minister realises what the people are feeling about it.  Unless these things happen, we are going to have the Irish Tourist Board set up as a butcher, set up as a dairyman and set up in every single aspect of our business life with a view to preventing the ordinary people from being able to get the profits from this industry which they should get if it is handled in the right way.</P>
    <P>The main responsibility lies with the Minister and again I would appeal to the Minister to make certain that the necessary goodwill is provided by withdrawing these powers and having <Col N="1899" /> them excised from the memorandum and articles of association of the company. I understood from this Bill that the articles of association and the memorandum would be placed in the library but they have not been placed there yet.  There are also a few other businesses which may be included in the board's operations and I had not the time when I was up in the board's offices and paying my shilling for this information to go through everything which the board proposed to do, and I may have to apologise to the House for some omissions in this matter.</P>
    <P>I believe, sincerely and absolutely, in the future of the tourist and holiday industry in this country.  I believe it can be one of the greatest national assets to our people and it can be one of the principal ways in which we can dispose of our surplus agricultural produce without the need and cost of transporting that produce to the various markets.  There was an estimate made in 1938 by the then Great Southern Railways in respect of their hotels, restaurants and dining cars.  All these things were considered and it was then found that about 50 per cent. of their money was paid for food, about 22 per cent. was for overheads, and about 20 per cent. or so was expended in respect of salaries and wages.  There was a census made in America in respect of the tourist industry there and it was clearly shown in that census that of the money spent in hotels 50 per cent. went directly to the farmers&mdash;48 per cent., I think, was the exact percentage&mdash;in respect of the food used irrespective of what was spent in respect of transportation.  We, here, no matter what anyone will think or may have thought in the past&mdash;because we are all agreed on it now&mdash;are primarily an agricultural country, and it appears to me that this tourist industry so far as outsiders are concerned and the holiday industry, so far as our own people are concerned can be used more and more effectively to deal with the problem of our surplus agricultural produce but that cannot be done unless the Irish Tourist Board make up their mind that they are going to develop the industry to the greatest extent possible.</P>
    <Col N="1900" />
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>My reaction to the Bill is that it is a good one, so good that it is a pity to have it condemned by the provision to which Senator Sweetman has referred.  If the case is going to be made that the powers to which Senator Sweetman has referred are taken in legislation but are never to be used, then they should not be in the Bill if they are not going to be used at all.  The fact remains that the powers are taken and they are in the Bill.  In organisations such as that provided for in this measure where powers of this kind are invoked the circumstances in which they will be used may be dictated by the concern established in the Bill and competition may be entered into with the people who are providing the rates and taxes in this country.</P>
      <P>I could not refrain from smiling when Senator Sweetman was giving the list he has detailed because significantly I think no reference was made to the motor trade.  Unless Dame Rumour lies, the board has acquired an existing business of this nature in the country.  I only want to mention that in passing because it was reported to my organisation and I want to say that if it is so it is somewhat alarming that even for their own purpose an existing trader should be bought out by the Tourist Board.  That presupposes that competition in that particular trade will be bought out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I must emphasise, of course, that the Bill is a welcome one because it makes it clear that this important industry is going to be officially organised.  There has been a haphazard and slap-dash method of approach to the creation of holiday attractions in this country, and let us be wise to that now.  The people who got out of this country before the war for their holidays, in the main went out for good reasons, and I would like to suggest that they did not do so because all was well with the hotel and holiday resorts here in those years. Therefore, we should make every effort now to make a success of this whole industry from the top to the bottom. Irrespective of the income of the holiday-goer, proper facilities must be provided.  I believe the back-bone of the holiday industry here will have to <Col N="1901" /> be the family, but at present how much consideration and encouragement is given to them to spend their holidays here whether the amount of their income is £5 or £10 a week?  If we are to provide holiday facilities for our own people then these facilities will have to be properly organised.  We will have to provide them with those facilities before we ask them to come along and take advantage of them.  I want to emphasise this point that I do hope the Minister will get the whole-hearted support that he should get for this, or any Bill, calculated to improve our holiday attractions, but I do urge this, too, that he should delete the dangerous power in the Bill which enables the board which is State supported and for which moneys have to be provided by the Oireachtas to do these things which have been referred to. This is a board over which the Oireachtas will have little control from now on, and that being the case, we should make sure what its activities will be before we give it those powers.</P>
    <P>The giving of such powers to the board is a dangerous thing.  The Minister has stated and I completely accept it that he is in favour of private enterprise but it has also been said that we may not always have the present Minister in his present position.  He may even be raised to a more exalted office in the lifetime of the oldest of us here.</P>
    <P>The power is a dangerous thing, as Senator Sweetman has told us at length.  I say again, as a matter of common sense, that if the power is not to be used why put it in and if it is to be used we should do all we can to keep it out.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill and suggest that the board will have to remember that there is precious little use in providing an attractive hotel and facilities if the means of getting to and from the hotel are not developed also, if the roads are bad and there are dangerous corners&mdash; of which we have had examples recently, unfortunately.  These things should have prior consideration by the board.  I heartily welcome the Bill and hope the plans which the Minister has will be carried out.  I hope also that he will listen to the suggestions made with <Col N="1902" /> regard to the board competing with the people who have to pay the piper.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>I have just a few general remarks to make on the operations of the board as I know them.  My knowledge of this is not very extensive, but from the outline Senator Sweetman gave of all the activities the board could indulge in, I was surprised they had not yet taken over their own law courts.  My experience practically amounts to that.  Everyone welcomes a check on the hotel keepers to prevent over-charging and so long as that check is exercised fairly and justly it is very desirable.  However, I know of a case recently, where a hotel proprietor was prosecuted for a nominal overcharge and duly turned up at the courts with counsel and solicitors to defend him. The board's representative walked in rather indifferently and told the judge they were not prepared to go on that day.  I do not know whether that is a common experience or not, but it is an outrage that a board of this kind can put an ordinary hotel proprietor to the expense of attending court with counsel and then, because it does not suit the board, the case is not proceeded with on that day.  They are not even informed of that, but the judge is told it is not convenient for the board.  I have heard rumours of other hotel keepers able to get the ear of certain important politicians and they never even had to go to court at all.  That is a very serious aspect of tourist development and I sincerely hope it will get first consideration.  Otherwise, we may have a partial administration of the law, which would be very serious for those in the tourist trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been said that tourist development has the idea of bringing people here to consume our food, instead of sending it over to them and involving costly transport and that to that extent, this country will benefit substantially.  Would anybody tell me that the conversion of the magnificent place at Portmarnock will improve the consumption of our agricultural produce to any great extent? It will be a luxury hotel, for profiteers and people who made a lot of money in recent times.  A very limited number can stay there and, consequently, <Col N="1903" /> the consumption of food will be limited in proportion.  But what about the number of people in proportion to the amount of money spent on the development?  If we want to attract people here to increase the consumption, we would have to establish Blackpools and Isles of Man, instead of the elaborate hotels, such as in Portmarnock and, possibly, elsewhere, if this board is allowed to have its head.</P>
    <P>Our people are getting annual holidays now.  What special arrangement is being made to facilitate them to spend their holidays to the best possible advantage of themselves and the country?  I know that the Tourist Board was organising funds, but they did not put much energy into it. At any rate, that plan has not been a great success so far.  The Tourist Board must consider the great number of our own people who would take advantage of the opportunity to go to some seaside place with their families, so that they might get the full advantage of their holidays.</P>
    <P>Generally, I am not satisfied that this board up to now is composed of the best people to handle tourist development. I have outlined a few of the reasons which strike me as very important if we are to get anything like value for the money we are putting into this development.  I welcome tourist development, but I think there should be consideration and sympathy for the people who are putting up the money.  If that is given, I believe the development will be a success.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasHonan" hpid="Mr. Honan Mr. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>My apology for speaking is that I come from an area where there is a great shortage of hotel accommodation&mdash;and all sorts of accommodation, for that matter&mdash;due to the incidence of visitors.  In our town, we have a newly-formed progressive committee, working in close association with the local hotels.  I can say at once that, in our provincial town, we have probably the three best provincial hotels in Ireland.  Still, they are entirely unable to deal with the amount of tourist traffic they could get if they <Col N="1904" /> had more accommodation.  Notwithstanding this progressive committee, working in close co-operation with the local hotels, they are calling a special meeting this week to ask the Government to erect a hotel for the further accommodation of those tourists who have to remain over in our town, in Limerick and in neighbouring towns, for maybe two or three nights, the period being always uncertain.</P>
      <P>We are not calling for luxury hotels. I do not think the Tourist Board or the Government or the Minister ever described the hotels they might undertake to erect as luxury hotels.  The term is only a paper, journalistic expression. I have met most of the tourists that have come into our part of the world and I am satisfied that they do not want luxury.  They want a clean room to sleep in and a clean tablecloth on which to take their meals.  All of them are simple people who wish to be accommodated in a simple way with simple food such as this country produces.  My point is that most of the existing hotels had not made any attempt so far as I could see to increase their accommodation.</P>
      <P>A lot of them have made an attempt to increase their accommodation in the way of saloon bars but I have not seen any of them adding a sleeping-room to their hotels in the last eight or nine years since this business came to our particular area.  If they do not do it somebody else will have to do it.  These visitors have often to travel 40 miles to get a place to sleep for the night. In the middle of the night possibly they are roused from their beds and dragged back to the airport only to find that the plane is not starting after all and then they have to travel back another 40 miles.  That state of affairs cannot continue indefinitely.  The provision will have to be made for them and as private hotel owners are making no attempt to do it, I hope the Tourist Association will take the matter in hands and make the provision as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is most important that these people who are visitors and not tourists should be given a favourable impression of the part of the country they are in in the course of their journey.  While <Col N="1905" /> they are here, I would give them a reasonable time, reasonable food and reasonable accommodation.  You could eliminate the word &ldquo;luxury&rdquo; from the hotel business altogether.  There is nobody looking for luxury and I hope somebody will erect plain hotels and give our visitors the good, plain food we produce at home.  So far as I know them, they are quite prepared and delighted to take what is put on the ordinary countryman's table.</P>
    <P>Some of them have said to me that there is no change here; that hotels are too much like New York with tubular chairs and fancy cooking, although I would say that all the material put on the tables is Irish food.  They want something Irish, something the Irish countryman uses.  They want to get away from luxury, they want a plain, simple, clean room and a clean tablecloth and that sort of thing and if we get away from those high notions of luxury business we will do much better with plain food for plain people.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>There have been a number of speeches made on this Bill already, apart from the Minister's, and I find myself, in the main, in agreement with them.  Senator Summerfield said he was in favour of the Bill.  Now the Bill, as it stands, is one of these interesting pieces of legislation which conveys nothing.  I hope that Senator Summerfield will realise when he said he was in favour of the Bill, that it does not mean anything at all.</P>
      <P>This is a Bill to give the Tourist Board more money and to permit the board to spend that money, and you can only be in favour of the Bill by hearing what that board has done and what it proposes to do.  When he says he is in favour of the Bill, he also tells us that he is against holding companies and the erection of hotels by the board, and I am afraid that shows that he is not in favour of the Bill at all.  That is not the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like the House to consider it carefully, because it is a good example of a widespread tendency with which we have grown rather familiar since 1932.  It is agreed now by Fianna Fáil that tourist development, both for our own people to enable them to spend their holidays with pleasure and <Col N="1906" /> profit at home, and for visitors to this country from abroad, is a good thing. It used not to be considered a good thing.  When Fianna Fáil were in opposition they opposed everything, even the climate.  I think the present Minister for Industry and Commerce said that we had no climate for tourist development.  Now with a different Government I presume it has improved, but there is not much sign of it this month.</P>
    <P>The Bill of 1939 was to give assistance to the people who were in the tourist business already.  There were certain public reasons for that.  That was a good scheme, and we must remember that there are things which, obviously, private enterprise cannot do. For instance, we had to set up a board to provide turf.  I do not think that you could argue that when you want turf cut on a very large scale you could do it with private enterprise&mdash;you must set up some kind of semi-State body or board to do the job.  But when you come to tourist development it is doubtful if the board should go into the hotel business.  We set up a board in 1939 to assist citizens in this business from public funds for the purpose of developing holiday resorts, because we rightly considered that the money would come back in increased employment and from foreigners visiting the country.</P>
    <P>It would be interesting to hear what assistance that board has given to those in the tourist business.  Everything is hypothetical and everything is in plan, and the plans have not been revealed.  As usual, the Act of 1939 had enabling provisions, the provisions which a Minister always wants to put into a Bill but which when he is getting the Bill, he says he never intends to use.  But he tells you he is going to use them now.  Here are other and wider enabling provisions to spend larger sums of money.  We are asked to provide more money and to extend the enabling provisions.</P>
    <P>In other words, the board is going into business, is purchasing several mansions and intends to start several hotels financed by the State.  It is interesting to consider this board. It is a hand-picked board, hand-picked <Col N="1907" /> by the Government, with the managing director picked by the Government for the spending of public money and the making of appointments.  With regard to these boards&mdash;we had so many since 1932&mdash;we are asked to believe that you can get no managing director anywhere who is not a Fianna Fáil supporter. We are asked to believe that in no other sphere except in the political sphere can a suitable managing director be got.</P>
    <P>We are asked to believe the same of other members of the board.  We are asked to believe that people who are supporters of Fianna Fáil can by some spiritual process, which I do not understand, be competent to direct various public activities.  It is fair to ask what use the board has made of its power to help the people in this business, to help hotel proprietors and to make appointments?  Apparently they have done nothing and now proceed to say that hotel-keepers themselves are not competent to do this job and the board must enter the hotel business.  Now of that I will say something later on.  But take the question of appointments.  I do not know how this board makes its appointments.  I see, for example, that £38,000 was required by the board during the last financial year, and that the bulk of it, I think about £20,000, went in salaries, rents and so on.  How are the people who get salaries selected?  I only know of one example, and I propose, with the permission of the Chair, to give it. We had a very intelligent member of the Seanad here, Mr. Hawkins from Galway.  He, unfortunately, was defeated by Senator O'Dea.  We are honoured perhaps by the presence of Senator O'Dea, but it was very unfortunate for Mr. Hawkins that Mr. Hawkins was defeated.</P>
    <P>Speaking for myself, I say quite sincerely that I sympathised with him, but it was also a difficulty for the Fianna Fáil Party as to what they were going to do about Mr Hawkins because he was a first-class organiser.  He had been working very hard for them, and what did they do?  They had a secretary to the organisation.  They took <Col N="1908" /> him out of that and put him into the Tourist Board.  I am sure he was a very estimable and intelligent men.  I am quite neutral about him.  I know that he belongs to a very intelligent class&mdash;at one time he was a secondary teacher&mdash;and I have the greatest respect for him.  He was secretary to Fianna Fáil.  They took him out of that, and they put him into the Tourist Board.  They then put Mr. Hawkins into the Fianna Fáil organisation which was a very intelligent step for them to take, I understand.</P>
    <P>It seems to me that that particular incident indicates that the Minister is able to use, and that the Fianna Fáil organisation is able to use, the Tourist Board for getting the Fianna, Fáil organisation out of its difficulties.  I say that without any reference to the individuals concerned.  As I have said, Mr. Hawkins was a very able and intelligent Senator, and I am sure would be a very able political organiser.  But did anybody else get a chance of competing for the job which the secretary of the Fianna Fáil organisation has at the moment, an organisation which had a very important problem of personnel to solve?  If that is the kind of action that we are to get from the board when selecting its staff it seems to me that it is unworthy to have money, and that we ought not to vote it money.</P>
    <P>On the other question of its plans, the board has plans and plans.  There is nobody who has used the &ldquo;plans&rdquo; more frequently during the last 25 years than the present Minister for Industry and Commerce.  He has always got plans.  This board has plans, but the plans have not been revealed.  They are going to create a paradise for tourists&mdash;hotels, piers, tourist centres, all kinds of things, but it is all going to be done in the future.  So far, nothing has been done.  What we are really being asked to do is to give this board another blank cheque.  We do not know how they are going to spend the money.</P>
    <P>May I say in conclusion that I am in agreement with Senator Honan on the question of what a hotel is?  I think it is quite wrong to think that when you buy a big mansion, furnish it and put in a staff that you have a <Col N="1909" /> hotel.  You most emphatically have not.  The word &ldquo;hotel&rdquo; is rather like the word &ldquo;home&rdquo;.  It is difficult to define.  The definition is certainly not a physical one.  When you put a whole lot of physical things together you certainly have not got a hotel.  You must, first of all, have the atmosphere. I think that is the great flaw in this whole scheme.  There is no synthetic process for producing a good hotel. You cannot take a certain number of things, put them together, and say: &ldquo;Hey Presto, there you have a hotel.&rdquo; What you generally have in those cases is a bad hotel.  I think it was also Senator Honan who indicated that it is wrong to think that the biggest and the best equipped house is necessarily the best hotel.  It certainly is not.  It is open to doubt also whether we are going to get the type of visitor who wants the luxury hotel.  If we are going to get him, are we sure that we are going to continue to keep him?</P>
    <P>There is another point.  I wonder if there is anyone on the board who knows any other language than the English language, or who has travelled in any other country other than an English-speaking country?  I wonder, for example, whether we could not get a great deal of information and a great lot of light and leading from a country like Sweden which was very much in the news a few weeks ago.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Or Switzerland?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that Sweden suits my argument better than Switzerland.  The Swedes have a very strong national spirit and very strong national institutions.  I do not mean a great army or a great police force, but their national institutions are very great.  Sweden impresses one immediately as a country with a very special character.  I suggest that we could get much more information with regard to hotel development from a country like Sweden than we could from the United States of America.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I was very much struck by what Senator Sweetman said, that we need to get away from the machine.  You will get a number of people who want rest. Like everybody here, I sometimes feel <Col N="1910" /> that I would like to hurry up the waitress.  About Easter time, I was in a Southern hotel and met an American Army chaplain.  He was a Jesuit, and he was absolutely enchanted with the way in which the waitress moved about the dining room. He thought it was simply delightful. He found that, after having served in America for a number of years and in the American Army, it was delightful to find what he described as &ldquo;this calm and quiet atmosphere.&rdquo;  He found that it was very soothing to him. I submit that service of that kind can be combined with efficiency.  The efficiency does not necessarily mean glaring lights or, as Senator Honan said, tubular chairs.  Efficiency is something which does not depend on absolute modernisation.  For example, we have the title of this new body&mdash;&ldquo;Fáilte, Teoranta.&rdquo;  I wonder where, in the name of Heavens, they got it? The Minister for Industry and Commerce is a very practical person.  He is rather cynical, I think, but I wonder why are people allowed to select English titles like that &ldquo;Welcome Limited.&rdquo;  They take the words in English, translate them into Irish and produce &ldquo;Fáilte, Teoranta.&rdquo;  Words fail me in Irish or in English to say more on that.</P>
    <P>I do say that I think one of the greatest differences there is between Irish hotels and French hotels, for example, or English hotels, is the reception&mdash;the fáilte, the welcome.  May I say that what I think made France and to a large extent, Switzerland&mdash; although Switzerland is a country where you have big hotels and a number of small hotels too&mdash;that what made those countries attractive to visitors was not the big hotels but the smallish hotels, kept by the proprietor himself and his wife who lived on the premises and worked in an entirely native way?  I agree entirely with what was said here to-day that we should follow that line and make our hotels as Irish as possible.  They should be scrupulously clean, though they need not necessarily be elaborate.</P>
    <P>Take the reception that one gets in a small French hotel.  When you arrive in the afternoon you get the impression <Col N="1911" /> that if Mr. and Mrs. Hayes had not arrived at this hotel the proprietor would not have gone to bed at all he would have been so sorry about it, whereas in the case of the average hotel here, when you arrive the attitude would appear to be this, &ldquo;Well, if you want to stay, you may, but we do not know what brought you here.&rdquo; I think that is very objectionable, particularly in the case of good hotels.  In the case of a bad hotel, I do not mind the reception being bad.  It has been my experience, in more than one place over a period of years, that a hotel, which turned out to be quite a good place, when you got into it, had the appearance of being quite reluctant to receive you.  However, this new company with its dreadful name, if it can inspire some spirit of fáilte in some of our hotels, it will have done a very good job.  I think we certainly should do what would be in accordance with Senator Foran's idea, that is to say provide for our own people in the smaller types of hotel rather than in the very big ones.  I did not understand&mdash;perhaps the Minister would explain in Committee because, I take it, we can have only one more stage on this Bill&mdash;what the proposal is with regard to those holding companies.  In effect, what we are doing is putting money into the hotel business.  The Minister agrees that we are doing that but he says that we are doing it only temporarily, that, after a time, the holding company will transfer its hotels to private enterprises.  I take it that I understand the Minister correctly in that.  What is the process of transferring to private enterprise?  Take places such as Termonfeckin and Portmarnock, where hotels are to be established. Incidentally, both hotels will be near magnificent golf courses.  If these hotels fail, we shall have lost our money.  Suppose they succeed.  At what point shall we arrive at a position in which we can decide that they have succeeded?  That will take from two to four seasons and that will mean that more and more money will be invested in the hotels.  At the end of that time, if the hotels are showing a profit, our old friend the Minister for Finance, or the eternal Ministry of Finance will <Col N="1912" /> come in.  What price will they take from private individuals for profit-making hotels?  I should not mind guaranteeing that there will be a very big file in the Department of Finance before it is decided to whom those hotels will be sold and at what price&mdash;assuming that they are making a profit.  I doubt that there will be any such thing as a transfer.</P>
    <P>While I am on my feet, it occurs to me that, a great many years ago, while sitting in the chair of the Dáil, I heard a proposal for a Dairy Disposals Board. If I do not make a mistake, the argument made&mdash;by a magnificent arguer the Lord have mercy on him&mdash;was that all these creameries would be transferred to co-operative societies.  The Dairy Disposals Board, in this year of grace 1946 is, I understand, either the biggest or second biggest concern in the State.  Is not that so?  It is going strong.  It is under semi-Government control and it, certainly, has not succeeded in carrying out the duties which its name would indicate&mdash;a Dairy Disposals Board.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>And you could not buy anything from it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Baxter knows a great deal about it in its workings.  I know nothing about its workings.  All I know is that, 16 or 17 years ago, a proposal was made similar to the Minister's proposal to-day.  We were to set up this body which was to be a holding company and a transfer of its properties was to be effected.  It is still holding and it has not transferred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It seems to me that we cannot create by investment of public money&mdash;no matter how much we invest&mdash;a hotel industry.  It must be a growth and it cannot be a synthesis.  It cannot be suddenly made up.  You must train managers and manageresses and you must train workers.  I entirely agree with Senator Summerfield that you must make provision for the man with the family.  You must also make a little better provision than is made at present for the man with the total abstinence pledge.  He is a very unwelcome visitor&mdash;not that I myself am exactly in that position.  A suggestion has been made about staggering holidays.  It is <Col N="1913" /> an excellent idea.  The month of June &mdash;though we have a very bad example in the present month&mdash;is an excellent time for holidays for your children. Except for those youngsters who are going for the primary certificate, any school-going children can get holidays then at any time that may be arranged. There will be difficulties here and there but our experience is that practically every kind of difficulty can be overcome if people want to overcome it.</P>
    <P>This Bill cannot be set aside in a few short sentences as more money for tourist development, because it is really a blank cheque to a board which can do what it pleases.  All we know about the money we are giving now is what the Minister tells us his intentions and the intentions of the board are. These intentions are to start in the hotel business, with the declared idea of getting out of it again.  As everybody knows, it is much easier to get into a business than to get out of it. With regard to the board itself, it is run, apparently, on the basis that, if a political organisation wants to be obliged and happens to be the Government's organisation, the board and the board's managing director will oblige it.  When you have public money invested in this way, the ordinary citizen should get fair treatment when looking for a position and, if a citizen has risked his own money in the business, he should not find himself in competition with Government-owned hotels.  Another small point concerns us, and concerns, perhaps, more acutely the lower paid portions of our community.  If we are to have luxury hotels run by the Tourist Board even for a few years, with an influx of the kind of visitor attracted by those hotels, one of the results will be to raise prices on our people here who stay in ordinary hotels.  That is a very bad system.  What we should have in mind is the smaller hotel.  We should aim at giving it as native a character as we possibly can.  What people expect to get when touring foreign countries is something different from what they get in their own.  We can provide that here and we should be able to provide the training which would help us to show that kind of <Col N="1914" /> front to foreigners.  It seems to me that the whole purpose of the 1939 Act has been changed, that the Tourist Board has taken a sharp turn&mdash;I do not know whether it is to the right or left; perhaps, it is left, in the direction of Socialism.  In any event, it is a form of enterprise which is very doubtful, indeed.  It gives more power to managing directors.  It gives more power to the Minister for the time being, whoever he may be, and, if we are to travel, we ought to be sure we know exactly where we are going.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidJohnMadden" hpid="Mr. Madden Mr. Madden">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Madden</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know of any piece of legislation passed by this Government which has created so profound disappointment as the legislation we are considering to-day by which the taxpayers are asked to contribute £1,250,000 for the development of the tourist industry.  I have had 18 years uninterrupted connection with the Irish Tourist Association.  I saw it practically through the pioneer years until the introduction of legislation in 1925.  We were told many a time and oft by our bank manager&mdash;his attitude was definitely endorsed by the Tourist Association&mdash;that it was never the intention of the I.T.A. to enter the field in a commercial way with individual hoteliers.  Those hoteliers contributed much economically and by their attendance, time and again, to the work of the I.T.A.  They assisted in putting the I.T.A. on the map of the world so that the world might come and see Ireland first.  The development of the Tourist Board seems to be completely at variance with the spirit of the I.T.A. and there seems to be a complete change in the vision and the outlook of the Minister with regard to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have here a very fine speech delivered by the Minister at the I.T.A. annual luncheon on the 25th October, 1938.  It seems to be a complete contradiction, in a general way, of the operations of the Tourist Board to-day. Listen to the spirit, the promise and the inspiration he gave us at that time: &ldquo;By the term &lsquo;tourist industry&rsquo; I mean, however, not merely catering for visitors from abroad but to a far greater extent the provision of facilities <Col N="1915" /> and attractions to our own people to spend their holidays at home.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I believe that the tourist industry, if properly managed and directed, constitutes a definite asset to the country. We have here all the elements, both scenic and sporting, to attract visitors. In fact we have a combination that other countries cannot boast of but, by intelligent handling and direction of their industry, those countries can attract to their shores a much greater number of visitors and they can give to their visitors a holiday much more beneficial and at a cost much cheaper than we can here.  I cannot see how the establishment of luxury hotels is going to contribute to the establishment of an economic holiday for our own people at home.  We are asked to give this board £1,250,000 for what? Mainly to experiment with luxury hotels, to absorb money which should be directed to productive industries or to the improvement of amenities here. Many of our seaside resorts are a positive danger to tourists or visitors.  This money might be utilised, for instance, in the erection of shelters at our seaside resorts so that tourists walking along the shore would not be drenched by summer showers.  These shelters would provide them with some protection when they were a half mile or a quarter mile away from their hotels.</P>
    <P>We are asked to spend this colossal sum in order to bring more English currency to Irish circulation and so depress the value of our money.  Goodness knows we have enough sterling assets at present.  It is said that something in the region of £200,000,000 is locked up in these sterling assets.  I think that steps should be taken to ensure that the money which is asked for under this measure, will not be for the erection of luxury hotels.  It is even proposed that the Tourist Board should be enabled to engage in certain luxury trades and even to build cinemas.  I had a long experience of the tourist industry in its widest aspects and I know that the most vital factor in securing improvement is the individual hotelier.  You cannot force people to be efficient.  You may bring a horse to the well but you cannot <Col N="1916" /> force him to drink.  I tell the House that unless people feel that this project is based upon national grounds and upon a well-formulated plan, it will be very serious for the Government and for the Department.</P>
    <P>The Minister is charged with a big responsibility and I hope he will not adopt the pose of omniscience and omnipotence that he has done occasionally.  This is a vast sum of public money.  There are sinister rumours abroad that a coterie of friends of certain Ministers get public appointments and are getting stipends not alone from one, but many, Departments.  There is no surer way of destroying democracy than by such practices and by losing the confidence of the public.  We had an example of it before.  Look at the Transport Board which was set up under the Government of the Six Counties.  I think that the failure there was a signal and a disastrous one and I think I know the reason. These things should be an example to the Minister before he extracts from the taxpayer this colossal figure of £1,250,000.  It is a vast sum and I trust that he shall judiciously face up to his responsibility to see that his expenditure will not be attended by unfortunate results.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCampbell" hpid="Mr. Campbell Mr. Campbell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Campbell</NameTxt>
      <P>I have very little to say on this Bill.  As the Minister said in his opening remarks, it is not a measure that lends itself to a Committee Stage discussion.  There are, however, a few observations which I should like to make more by way of emphasising the points made by Senators who have preceded me than by expressing any new views.  The principal point which I wish to make is that I should like to see this Bill making more provision for holiday accommodation for the middle-class and working-class people of this country than it does and that we should not emphasise so much the tourist aspect of it.  I do not wish to decry the efforts that are being made to develop the tourist traffic but, from my observations, I think this traffic is going to be a very transient business. I imagine that the reason our hotels are full at the moment is because of <Col N="1917" /> the lack of food in Great Britain, a country from which, I think, most of the tourist traffic comes at present.  I fear that when the Continent opens up again, people will not be so quick to come here.  I think that if more consideration were given to the development of small hotels or even large hotels to accommodate people within our own country who desire to take a holiday, our money and our time would be much better spent.  Our own people we shall have always with us. This year workers in general, for the first time, are getting a fortnight's holidays.  These workers have nowhere to go, and I do not see any great development throughout the country or any effort being made to provide facilities for these people.  I think it a terrible pity that we do not concentrate more on the provision of facilities for such people because, as I have said, our own people we shall always have with us.  The tourists who are filling our hotels at present may be birds of passage and may not come here again when conditions improve in Britain and abroad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been my duty during the past three years, since the Advisory Wage Tribunals were set up, to travel extensively throughout the country.  During the last three weeks I spent about 12 days touring through the counties of Wexford, Waterford, Cork, Clare and Limerick and we found it tremendously difficult to get accommodation, even for a few nights.  That brings me to the point that I think very few people of the middle or working-class are going to get any holidays this year because the accommodation is not there.  The hotels are booked up to mid-October.  I think it a great pity that the Tourist Board have not made greater efforts in this respect.  I understand their difficulties of course.  The shortage of building materials and other reasons have precluded the board from embarking on the erection of hotels or even blocks of boardinghouses to accommodate our own people.  Our own people have not had a holiday since the Isle of Man closed down.  What the Isle of Man can do for our people it should be possible and it should be our duty to do for <Col N="1918" /> them ourselves.  There is one other question to which I want to refer.  I have seen our food disguised under foreign names of one kind or another. I do not think it is necessary to resort to that.  It is good Irish food and it should not be translated into French.  In a hotel in the South of Ireland last year I read a menu.  It was in French.  I met a visitor there and he took the menu and read: &ldquo;Entrecôte á la maison et pommes frite.&rdquo;  I am sorry that Senator Hayes is not here because he would be able to check me up.  He taught me French on one occasion in exchange for Irish. The visitor said to me: &ldquo;Is that as good as it looks,&rdquo; and I said to him: &ldquo;It is really steak and chips.&rdquo;  He replied: &ldquo;That is good in Irish or French.&rdquo;  I think it is a pity that we should adopt these devices to deceive the people as to the food they are using whether that food is French cooked or not.</P>
    <P>I remember an occasion, eight or nine years ago, when our worthy Minister was elected to preside at an International Labour Conference at Geneva. There was a precedent there that the President always gave a reception and our Minister had the wise idea of providing some Irish food and liquid on that occasion.  That function was the best of its kind ever held at Geneva and whatever the fare might be called at home it was Limerick ham in Geneva.  It was called by its proper name there and there was no deception.</P>
    <P>I think we should not be slow to call our food by its Irish name if necessary but surely there is no need to call it by a foreign name.  I think the Tourist Board should concentrate more in providing accommodation for our people at home.  There are people in this city, people among the class I come from, who have never seen Ireland. The number of people who have never seen Killarney is amazing.  Their peregrinations out of this city have never extended beyond Dublin or Bray at the farthest.  I think it is our duty to develop facilities for them and that we should make it possible for them to go farther afield for holidays in their own country.  I feel that they should not have to wait for the Isle of Man <Col N="1919" /> boats to come into the North Wall again and bring them out of the country in order that they may get a holiday. We cannot bank on having the tourist traffic from abroad continue here to the same extent as at present and we should concentrate on providing facilities for our own people.  The fact remains that there is not a snowball's chance of anyone in this country having a holiday this year except the profiteer, the black marketeer or some of the <i>nouveau riche</i> who have emerged from the emergency.  Most of the people who had a week's holiday last year will have a fortnight's holiday this year and a lot of them will spend it up and down O'Connell Street.  I think it is a great pity more attention is not paid by the Tourist Board to planning big blocks of boarding houses in Killarney and places like that where the ordinary man would spend a week's holidays.  I think we ought not to depend too much on the the present impetus of tourist traffic continuing over the next few years. I believe that when Europe settles itself a lot of the people now coming here will by-pass this country.  I hope they will not but at the same time some consideration should be given to providing for our own people adequate holiday facilities so that they may not have to go to such places as Blackpool and the Isle of Man.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>The £1,250,000 which is provided for in this Bill would in my opinion be a very sound investment indeed for the taxpayers of this country to put into the tourist industry were it going to be used for the purpose of giving loans to Irish hotel keepers and advancing loans to Irish resorts to improve the hotel amenities that exist there.  I cannot, however, in view of the Minister's statement to-day as to the proposed future activities of the Tourist Board, regard this venture with any great confidence.  First of all I see no reason for placing any great confidence in the personnel of this board.  It is a board which, as Senator Hayes has pointed out, has been appointed by the Government, and I am unaware that any member of it has any <Col N="1920" /> particular qualification or experience in this kind of work.  I trust when the Minister is replying to the debate he will take the opportunity of giving the House some information as to what he considers should be the proper qualifications for members of the Tourist Board.  I also trust that he will give the House some information as to what are the standards of qualification the board insists on, as regards its own personnel.  Particularly am I interested in the qualifications they require in a young man or woman for the position of hotel inspector.  I do not say that all of the board's inspectors are like the example I am going to give now but I do know of more than one case where a hotel proprietor having been visited by one of the board's inspectors for the purpose of registering as a hotel has been so unimpressed by the inspector that called upon him for the purpose of looking into all the essentials of the hotel business that he decided to register his premises as a guest house rather than as a hotel under the board.</P>
      <P>I recall one hotel proprietor telling me that a young man called at a late hour in the evening and announced the fact that he was an inspector of the Tourist Board and that he had come to inspect the hotel.  He was invited to carry on the inspection.  He was asked would he like to see over the hotel, would he like to see the kitchen, the bedrooms and the dining-rooms.  He said: &ldquo;No, all I want to know is, if you have got a bath.&rdquo;  The hotel proprietor replied that not alone had they a bath but they had three baths, and the inspector said: &ldquo;Then you have two more than are necessary for the number of rooms.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator give me the name of the hotel so that I could check up the story?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly, later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be delighted to get it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>That story does not speak very highly for the personnel of the board.  I do not wish to make the allegation that all the employees are of that nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1921" /> I would like to endorse what has been said here about the excellent points of the Irish hotels.  Senator Sweetman gave us some very interesting facts and figures about the value of the tourist industry in European countries.  I presume the Minister, if not the board, is quite aware that the great success of these European countries&mdash;particularly France, Switzerland, Sweden and Italy&mdash;lies in the fact, not that they possess some of the most expensive luxury hotels in the world but that they possess excellent hotels of the smaller type to suit all pockets, hotels where people are welcome, even if they bring their families of young children with them, hotels which make no attempt at luxury surroundings but depend entirely on the native product of the country for their food and drink.</P>
    <P>In Ireland we have many excellent hoteliers who run their hotels on exactly those lines.  They are people who are highly skilled in the trade and they realise that we possess food second to none in the world, that it requires no disguise and they serve it as the plain product of the country. These are the hotels that have always been the most successful, the hotels that have been the mainstay of our tourist trade in the past and are bound to be its mainstay in the future.  I look with grave suspicion on the board's proposal to start luxury hotels on the American system.  Those hotels may enjoy a certain measure of temporary success at the present moment owing to the fact that a particularly wealthy class of person in Great Britain is unable to go abroad to the Continent; but, make no mistake about it, as soon as it becomes possible, those people with vast sums of money are going to follow the sun and we will find these luxury hotels left on our hands.</P>
    <P>Apropos my friend Senator Campbell's remarks, a well-known wit in my native city once said: &ldquo;A little knowledge is a dangerous thing&mdash;and, if you do not believe that, look at the French cooking in the hotel X&rdquo;.  I think the Tourist Board is suffering from a little knowledge.  Their chairman did a tour in America and was very impressed with the standard of luxury in <Col N="1922" /> American hotels, but it does not follow that the Americans visiting this country would look for the same standard of luxury here.  I agree with Senator Honan that they are much more likely to ask for something entirely Irish.  I hope the Minister will give us as much information as he can and that he will reconsider his proposals regarding the activities of this board.</P>
    <P>This money would be much better spent in facilitating those people in this country who are legitimate hotel traders, who know their job and who, if given assistance by the Tourist Board, will make a success of their business.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. Seán O'Donovan Mr. Seán O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Seán O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The attitude of most of the speakers in this debate has amazed me, as all the remarks have clearly indicated the shortcomings of the present hoteliers.  Senators have been mentioning various complaints regarding the circumstances which have existed up to the present, yet the main criticism is pointed towards the Tourist Board, which has had no opportunity to put into operation the powers granted to it in 1939. Judging by the speeches, one wonders why we were foolish enough in 1939 to establish this Tourist Board or why, in our wisdom or ignorance, we thought it was necessary.  It certainly seems to be very necessary to-day and I presume&mdash;as I was a member of the House in 1939 and took part in that debate&mdash;we were satisfied that it was necessary then.  Since then, there has been a war, yet we hear criticism that the Tourist Board up to the present has done practically nothing but plan. If it has done planning, as indicated by the Minister in regard to various places where the plans are to operate, it must have done good work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There have been many references to the Tourist Board establishing luxury hotels, but I have not seen in any official document that these are to be luxury hotels.  We have hotels which are comparable to the hotels in other countries, but this indication of luxury hotels seems to convey the idea that we are to have something nobody else has anywhere else.  I think it is wrong <Col N="1923" /> to adopt the attitude that we are going to produce something that cannot be produced anywhere else.  The whole criticism seems to be directed at the board for this work.  The criticisms made indicate to me, at any rate, that an authorised board is necessary to provide what has not been provided already.  All the criticism has shown that hotels and guest houses generally have not been provided for the foreign visitors or native holiday-makers. Surely, if the board is now trying to do what has not been done by private enterprise up to the present, it does not deserve criticism?  I do not know one member of the Tourist Board, but it seems to me that many speeches have been directed against the board as if it were some extraordinary product of the Minister's imagination.</P>
    <P>It appeared to me to be very commendable that it is proposed to establish Irish-speaking resorts.  I have not had many holidays in my lifetime and have not been out of Dublin City since the emergency began.  Even though I am a Corkman, I have not been able to get to Cork.  Holidays to me always have meant a family holiday and an opportunity of going with my family to a resort beside the sea.  If we can have an Irish-speaking resort by the sea, with facilities for families, it would be my ambition at some future time to spend a holiday at some such resort.  It is very commendable that the board has been thinking on those lines.  I would like to see several of those resorts established, where people with an interest in the Irish language, who desire to become efficient in it and speak it whenever the opportunity arises, might go, with or without families, to spend a good holiday in the sunshine near the sea, and at the same time avail of the opportunity to learn the Irish language as well.</P>
    <P>That would be my ideal of a satisfactory holiday.  When the original Bill was introduced in 1939, I had a different conception from the one I have to-day.  I did think that the board would be able to spend money on projects not meant to be remunerative. I understand that any money they are allowed to spend must be <Col N="1924" /> on a probable money-making basis. Another criticism is that they have not spent money on other things.  Apparently they are debarred from doing that.  Senator Summerfield complained that they were not able to take dangerous corners off the roads.  In 1939 I spoke in the House regarding the provision of facilities for people who have never practically driven out of Dublin except by tram or bus, and I mentioned the development of facilities at Dollymount and Merrion strands, two of the finest in the country.</P>
    <P>No matter how we develop hotels for a great many of our people, Dollymount and Merrion will remain the resorts for a large number of Dublin citizens.  Something has been said recently of development in Dollymount, and I would like to get some information as to how far that has gone.  I was disappointed to find that development could not take place unless it was on a remunerative basis.  That would prevent the lending of money to a local authority or other authority, even for projects in the City of Dublin offering such magnificent possibilities as Dollymount and Merrion.  I think it is unfortunate that the board is debarred from lending money on any project which will not give indications of being profitable.  Senator Sweetman gave a definition of a tourist as a person who spends 24 hours out of the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not my definition; it was the League of Nations definition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Well and good, if it was a quotation from the League of Nations.  My definition of a tourist would be a person who has travelled within the country, even within his own county, and I would not regard the League of Nations definition as an exact one.  I would like to see our people provided for in a satisfactory manner.  We cannot depend on people who come from outside our own country to spend their holidays here, although there seems to be a magnificent field for development on those lines.  But, apart from those who come here, I think there is a great opportunity <Col N="1925" /> to extend facilities for our own people, and in extending these facilities we are also providing them for those who may come from foreign countries.</P>
      <P>But surely no member of the House can lay the blame on the Tourist Board if they have not provided those facilities up to the present.  In 1939, we were satisfied that we would have to provide facilities because private citizens had not provided them.  We brought in a Bill, and, immediately, a world war broke out, and therefore the criticism of the fact that that body has not done what it should have done is unjustified.  These criticisms are more applicable to the people carrying on business up to the present than to the Tourist Board.</P>
      <P>Senator Sweetman referred in a derogatory manner to the Minister for Education.  I think the Ministry of Education, if he will not give credit to the Minister himself, took one of the greatest steps forward which has yet been taken in the development of our hotel industry.  That was the building of Coláiste Tigheas in Cathal Brugha Street, Dublin, for the education of chefs and managers for the future.  I feel that that has been one of the biggest steps taken in the support of tourist development.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>That was done by the Tourist Association providing scholarships for the purpose&mdash;not by the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Sweetman wishes to correct me on that point he may, but the building was put up by the Minister through, of course, your tax money and mine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Sweetman is chairman of the Irish Tourist Association.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Mr. S. O'Donovan Mr. S. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>If he is, I do not think he succeeded in establishing these colleges for the girls and men of the country to fit themselves through proper education to manage and run the hotels of the country.  There is one other point from which the board is apparently debarred by the terms of the legislation&mdash;the development of the scheme of hostels established by <Col N="1926" /> An Óige.  That organisation has done magnificent work in the provision of hostels for its own members.  I am sorry that nothing can be done through the Tourist Board to help the organisation of An Óige.</P>
      <P>It is a pity that organisations like that could not be assisted by loan or grant in the development or establishment of further hostels.  I think the work they have done has been of great national importance.  They have established these hotels and provided the cheapest possible way of living in the open air and far from the madding crowd, which is one of the first requirements for a proper holiday.  I have nothing more to say but to deprecate the attack made on the board, which did not get a chance of doing the work during the world war.  The attack on members of the staff of that board is also unjustified.  I leave it to the Minister himself to deal with the personal attack made on the board in employing only members of the Fianna Fáil organisation.  That, certainly, is not true, but surely it is never meant to be suggested that nobody who is a member of the Fianna Fáil organisation should be appointed to anything in this country?  Senator Sweetman seemed to indicate that membership of Fianna Fáil should debar anyone from appointment in any capacity like that. I hope that the work that has not been done by the private owners of hotels will be done now under the auspices of this Tourist Board as facilities become available to them to do it. The Minister has indicated the activities which they propose to carry out in the future, and my only further remark is to express the hope that moneys could be made available by this Tourist Board for projects which would not be classified as of a remunerative nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the debate.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned until later to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we adjourn for tea might I remind the House of the arrangement agreed to at the beginning of the sitting, that when the House resumes at 7 o'clock, Item No. 4 on the agenda will be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1927" /> When the business has been concluded the House will resume this debate.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 6 p.m. and resumed at 7 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Allegations Against Parliamentary" RHead="Secretary&mdash;Motion for Tribunal">
    <Title>Allegations Against Parliamentary Secretary&mdash;Motion for Tribunal.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally move the motion standing on the Order Paper in my name:</P>
      <P>That it is expedient that a tribunal be established for inquiring into the following definite matters of urgent public importance, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To investigate and report upon the allegations contained in a letter bearing date the 22nd May, 1946, addressed to the Taoiseach and the members of the Government by Dr. Patrick MacCarvill and an accompanying copy letter dated the 17th May, 1946, referred to in the first mentioned letter as a report to Dr. Patrick MacCarvill from Mr. Darach Connolly, solicitor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given a considerable amount of thought to this motion and the manner in which I should present it so as to convince the two Houses of the Oireachtas that it was expedient to set up the tribunal in question.  I came to the conclusion that the least unsatisfactory&mdash;I put it that way&mdash;method that I could adopt would be to read the letters referred to in that motion.  I say the least unsatisfactory because from whatever angle you approach it it is difficult to get a really satisfactory method.  I shall, therefore, read the letters.  The first letter is from &ldquo;8, Fitzwilliam Square, Dublin.&rdquo;  It is dated the 22nd May, 1946, and was received in my office on the 28th May.  It is addressed to: &ldquo;An Taoiseach and each Member of Government.&rdquo;  It is from Dr. MacCarvill and reads:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;A Chara,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My brother, Johnny MacCarvill, has been dismissed from his position as manager and secretary of the Monaghan Curing Company by Dr. F.C. Ward, managing director of the company, by powers that, I am now instructed, were self-arrogated. <Col N="1928" /> The manner and circumstances of his dismissal were such as to give the impression that he must have been guilty of serious misconduct, and accordingly, there has been much local rumour and comment.</P>
    <P>For the benefit of those who do not know my brother, I should say that he is a well-known man&mdash; perhaps one of the best known men &mdash;in County Monaghan.  He has an excellent record in both Irish wars; is an office-holder in the principal Fianna Fáil organisations in Monaghan, being vice-president of the North Monaghan Comhairle Ceanntair and joint treasurer of the Comhairle Dáil Ceanntair; has acted as Fianna Fáil election agent at all elections in Monaghan since 1932, including the Presidential Election in 1945.</P>
    <P>So as to discover, without prejudice, all the facts, I have submitted to Mr. Darach Connolly, solicitor, the company's accounts, balance sheets, much correspondence, and memoranda, etc., for report and legal opinion.  I attach herewith a copy of his report, and the astonishing disclosures therein require no comment, though I would like to draw the attention of the Minister for Agriculture and the Minister for Finance to paragraphs 4, 5 and 6 of the report.</P>
    <P>It is reasonable for anyone to ask why my brother was dismissed, if it is true that he managed the company well.  I have gone very closely into the question myself, and the reason appears to me as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Last January, when Dr. Ward took the first steps in this unwarrantable action, he was hoping in a very short time to be promoted to a Ministry in which case, I understand, he would have been compelled to resign his managing directorship of the company.  From Mr. Connolly's report it is obvious that Dr. Ward would thus have been at a serious financial loss, so he had to find some means of recouping himself. His son, an undergraduate in the Commerce Faculty in U.C.D., has already some experience of the business, acquired during the holiday <Col N="1929" /> periods at Clover Meats, Ltd., Bacon Curers, Waterford.  This young man, before there was any question of dismissal, stated to a reliable witness that he would be going to Monaghan to take my brother's position, and this was later confirmed by Mr. Corr, deputy managing director of the company.  The managing directorship and the managership would have been merged, and a new plan adopted for profit-sharing, as the old one would no longer suit.  My brother was an obstacle, so he must go, the only reason given being that it was &ldquo;in the interests of the shareholders&rdquo;&mdash; a genuine enough reason when one remembers that 5/8 of the shares are held by Dr. Ward, and how better could the &ldquo;interests&rdquo; of at least the majority of &ldquo;the shareholders&rdquo; be served than by installing one of his own family.</P>
    <P>This explanation seems more than reasonable, for it corresponds very closely with Dr. Ward's action some three or four years ago in ordering the dismissal of Mr. Matt Fitzsimons, an excellent agent of the company. The only reason in that case was to make room for Mrs. K. Ward, the lady mentioned in Mr. Connolly's report, as chief agent in the carrying out of undisclosed cash sales.</P>
    <P>On a parallel with the system of conducting undisclosed cash sales in the curing company, is the method adopted by Dr. Ward for drawing by another hidden system, some 50 per cent. of the salary and emoluments attaching to the position of medical officer of the Monaghan Dispensary District.  The system is as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>A temporary medical officer is appointed by the Monaghan Board of Health to discharge Dr. Ward's duties, at the same salary to which Dr. Ward would be entitled if he were still dispensary officer there. (This rate is important from Dr. Ward's point of view, not only because of what he draws yearly from it, as shown hereafter, but also, by keeping up over the past 14 years, the higher rate of salary with the periodic increments, he has now reached his maximum salary, and <Col N="1930" /> therefore, as the pensionable officer, gets the benefit of it.)  The temporary medical officer appointed by the board of health is recommended for the appointment by Dr. Ward, who then lays down his conditions, namely: that all cheques for salary and emoluments paid to the temporary medical officer must be endorsed by the medical officer and delivered uncashed to Dr. Ward, who then pays the temporary medical officer at a rate which has varied thus:&mdash;</P>
    <P>First temporary medical officer who acted from March, 1932, to Septemper, 1935, at £4 4s. per week.</P>
    <P>Second temporary medical officer who has acted from 1935 to the present date, at £5 5s. per week from 1935 to 1943, but increasing since 1943 to the present figure of £29 per month.</P>
    <P>As the salaries and emoluments have varied from, roughly, £450 per annum to £575 per annum, it means that Dr. Ward has drawn and continues to draw an annual sum of not less than £200-£250, while to all appearances the temporary medical officer is getting the entire amount. He is not ungenerous, however, for in return for the payment of this enforced tribute, he allows the temporary medical officer, after the first year, to keep the private fees earned in the district&mdash;where Dr. Ward himself has not practised for 15 years. During the first year he exacted half the private fees as well.</P>
    <P>Dr. J.F. McGeough, Monaghan Street, Newry, filled the position for the first three and a half years.  He was dispossessed in September, 1935, for lodging, in June of that year, the cheques for the April-June quarter to his own account, and informing Dr. Ward that he expected the terms of his appointment as temporary medical officer by the board of health to be fulfilled.  Dr. Ward dispossessed him by the simple expedient of himself asking permission from the board of health to take up duty again.  The permission was granted, and he did, nominally, take up duty (although he was then whole-time Parliamentary Secretary), until <Col N="1931" /> he found another doctor to consent to his conditions.</P>
    <P>At least one doctor, named Murray, at the time refused the conditions, and this man I am trying to trace so that he may testify to the conditions submitted to him.</P>
    <P>Dr. McGeough, who is now beyond Dr. Ward's ex-officio reprisals, is quite willing to prove, on oath if necessary, the facts governing the period 1932 to 1935.  I could invite Dr. M.P. O'Gorman, the occupant of the position since 1935, to submit confirmatory evidence only if the Minister for Local Government and Public Health will guarantee him immunity against Dr. Ward's vengeance, for, in addition to acting as Dr. Ward's deputy, he has recently been appointed to a neighbouring rural dispensary district, and feels that if Dr. Ward had still official power over him, it would not be safe to disclose the position.</P>
    <P>I hope that some means will be devised to ensure that restitution will be made to these two doctors. Until my brother sought my advice regarding his summary dismissal, I was unaware that the Monaghan Curing Company had been conducted in the manner disclosed.</P>
    <P>Since 1932, there had been persistent rumours, widespread among the medical profession, that Dr. Ward was continuing to draw part of the salary of the Monaghan Dispensary District.  I was aware that Deputies Dillon and O'Higgins had tried to get evidence of this, but it is only now that I fully understand why they did not succeed.</P>
    <P>When the curing company affair came to my notice, I decided to make a thorough and impartial investigation, for the reason that I felt that I was in a particularly favourable position to get reliable information. Having got it, supported by documentary and personal evidence, I now feel that it is my duty, before advising or taking any other steps, to submit it to the Government in the interests of the Government itself, <Col N="1932" /> and the country generally, especially my native county.</P>
    <P>Amongst other matters which might profitably form the subject of inquiry, but about which I would find it difficult to get conclusive evidence, is the taking of funds&mdash;it is said some hundreds of pounds&mdash;from the Monaghan Public Utility Building Society to erect a Fianna Fáil Hall at Carrickroe, on land rented by Dr. Ward himself.  I am told that it is known locally as the Ward Hall, and that he exercises the authority of a landlord over it.  The funds were not returned to the society, nor any offer made to do so.  This is my unconfirmed information.</P>
    <P>I have dissuaded my brother from taking any action until the matters disclosed herein have been considered by the Government.  Mr. Darach Connolly, solicitor, has custody of all the available documents concerning the curing company, and is authorised to submit them for inspection, if required.  Dr. McGeough is prepared to submit evidence by way of affidavit or in person, if deemed necessary, and Dr. O'Gorman's supporting proof will be forthcoming, immediately he is assured of protection. Mise, le meas, P. MacCarvill.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The next letter is addressed from 21 Parliament Street, Dublin, and is from Mr. Darach Connolly, solicitor, to Dr. Patrick MacCarvill, 8 Fitzwilliam Square, Dublin:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Dear Dr. MacCarvill&mdash;In accordance with your instructions, I have carefully examined the audited accounts and balance sheets, correspondence and memoranda relating to the Monaghan Curing Company, Limited, placed at my disposal.</P>
    <P>Since 1938, the company has had a share capital of £8,000, divided between the three directors, who are also officials of the company, as follows:&mdash;Managing director, Dr. F.C. Ward, £5,000; deputy managing director, Mr. Joseph Corr, £2,250; manager and secretary, Mr. J. MacCarvill, £750; total, £8,000.</P>
    <P>The audited accounts for the years 1938 to 1944 show that the company, on the average, has made extremely <Col N="1933" /> good profits, especially when considered in relation to the amount of the capital invested.  I should, perhaps, point out that the company has never paid any dividends as such, but the directors drew from the company, by way of salary and otherwise, in exact ratio to the amount of capital held by each.  Since you expressly ask for a statement of the amounts drawn by Dr. Ward, the following is a summary of the amounts drawn by him in salaries during the periods stated:&mdash;</P>
    <P>During ten months of 1938, £916 13s. 4d.; during the year 1939, £1,000 0s. 0d.; during the year 1940, £1,750 0s. 0d.; during the year 1941, £2,000 0s. 0d.; during the year 1942, £2,000 0s. 0d.; during the year 1943, £1,000 0s. 0d.; during three months of 1944, £250 0s. 0d.; total salaries during six years and one month, £8,916 13s. 4d.</P>
    <P>In addition to the profits shown by the properly audited accounts, it is quite clear from the documents furnished, that a well organised system of undisclosed cash sales was in operation during most of the period under review.  It does not appear how the bacon was made available for these &lsquo;unofficial&rsquo; sales, while the company was working on a quota basis, but it is obvious that some method must have been adopted whereby the extraction of bacon and offal from the pigs killed was not disclosed in full to the Pigs and Bacon Commission.  If you should require specific details in respect of this practice, I could furnish dates and names of consignees in respect of some of these undisclosed cash sales, from the records to hand.</P>
    <P>It is quite obvious that the proceeds of these sales were not passed through the accounts of the company, nor included in the audited accounts. From this you will understand that moneys derived from this source were not returned for taxation purposes by the company to the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    <P>It must be assumed from this, that the directors profiting by these undisclosed cash sales have not included them in their personal income-tax <Col N="1934" /> returns, since by doing so they would have to disclose to the Revenue Commissioners the source of this income, thereby involving the company of which they were the directors and officials.  As requested, I have summarised&mdash;I think accurately&mdash;the total amounts drawn by Dr. Ward out of these undisclosed cash sales during the period under review, as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>During the year 1939, £106 14s. 4d.; during the year 1940, £12 19s. 5d.; during the year 1941, £173 0s. 1d.; during the year 1942, £368 10s. 9d.; during the year 1943, £522 19s. 0d.; during the year 1944, £1,027 9s. 9d.; during the year 1945, £753 3s. 5d.; total during the seven years, £2,964 16s. 9d.</P>
    <P>During the period 1938 to 1945, inclusive, therefore, Dr. Ward appears to have drawn from the company almost £12,000, exclusive of any salary which he may have drawn for the year 1945 and the nine months of the year 1944.</P>
    <P>It is abundantly clear from the records to hand that Dr. Ward directed and ordered the carrying out of these cash sales.  One of the letters sent by him to the deputy managing director, and apparently handed over to the manager and secretary for attention, reads as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P Just="Right">&lsquo;Morven&rsquo;,</P>
    <P Just="Right">Nashville Park,</P>
    <P Just="Right">Howth.</P>
    <P Just="Right">13th December, 1943.</P>
    <P>Dear Joe&mdash;You might have two tons of Wiltshire sides dispatched to Mrs. K. Ward at Amiens Street.  The consignment need not be entered up, but send her a note that you are sending her a certain quantity on a certain day.  If you have more on hands than can conveniently be disposed of, you could send three tons. In calculating the quantity available you may assume that Pidgeon will not require any from us this month. I shall explain in detail when I go down.  Please have these matters dealt with without delay.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1935" /> I hope the stocktaking as on the 11th instant has been carried out.</P>
    <P>&mdash;Sincerely yours, Conn Ward.</P>
    <P>Mr. Joe Corr,</P>
    <P>Church Square,</P>
    <P>Monaghan.</P>
    <P>P.S.  The commission on this transaction can be paid in cash.&mdash; C.W.</P>
    <P>(The underlining is not mine, but is in the letter and the P.S. is written, not typed).</P>
    <P>It would appear that the Mrs. K. Ward (Dr. Ward's sister-in-law) mentioned in this letter was one of the principal, if not the principal agents here, outside the local area, for carrying out these undisclosed cash sales.</P>
    <P>An original memorandum, written by your brother as manager and secretary and dated the 7th September, 1942, shows that he raised objections to this practice of undisclosed cash sales.  In spite of the views expressed by him, however, he was at fault in allowing himself to be overruled, and in carrying out the policy adopted, in this matter.  I have discussed with your brother this matter, and its significance from his point of view, and he has intimated to me his intention of paying to the Revenue Commissioners such amount as may be due to them by him in respect of moneys thus received (which amount cannot be too great in view of his small share therein).</P>
    <P>In this connection I would draw your attention to the fact that, in spite of the very large profits which the company paid, relative to the amount of capital therein, your brother received, as manager and secretary, a wage of £5 per week, reduced to £4 per week in October, 1945.  The nature and extent of his work, and the moneys involved therein make this figure appear unusually low, though his co-directors may have considered it adequate when his small proportionate share in the profit-salaries and out of the undisclosed cash sales was added thereto.  Although I am not perhaps the best judge thereof, his management <Col N="1936" /> of the affairs of the company seems to have been efficient and successful, if the returns obtained by the directors and the completeness of the complicated records kept by him are any indication.  With reference to one of your queries, there is, in fact, no suggestion in any of these records, even in the somewhat offensive letters written to him by Dr. Ward subsequent to his purported dismissal, that he misapplied or misappropriated any moneys whatsoever belonging to the company.</P>
    <P>With regard to his purported dismissal, the circumstances seem to be as follows: On January 12th last Dr. Ward telegraphed to Mr. Corr instructing him to give the manager four weeks' leave of absence with pay (your brother was then in hospital). On January 26th Dr. Ward wrote to your brother purporting to terminate his employment as manager and secretary as from the 9th February, &lsquo;in the best interests of the shareholders,&rsquo; no other reason being stated.  In this letter Dr. Ward offered your brother alternative employment as an account-collecting agent for the Counties Cavan and Monaghan, on the basis of a 2½ per cent. commission on all accounts collected within 14 days, a 1½ per cent. commission on all accounts collected within 28 days of the issue of invoice.  Accounts not collected within 28 days were to be collected in any event, but no commission was to be paid thereon.  He was also to ensure a steady supply of pigs to the factory. Remuneration was to be on the basis of this commission alone.</P>
    <P>From the legal point of view, I am of the opinion that the articles and memorandum of the company do not confer on the managing director, Dr. Ward, power or authority to remove from office a person in the position your brother held. In my view, a decision of the board of directors would be necessary to dismiss the manager and secretary. This view is supported by the counsel's opinion which I have obtained from Mr. Cecil Lavery, S.C., and I <Col N="1937" /> would therefore advise that your brother has grounds for legal action on foot of a claim that his employment has not been properly terminated. Arrears of salary would be due to him from the company.</P>
    <P>With regard to the reasons later given by Dr. Ward for the purported dismissal, apparently under pressure from your brother, his allegations of &lsquo;culpable negligence and lack of sense of responsibility,&rsquo; etc., in the discharge of his duties, would, perhaps in the usual way, be clear and sufficient ground for an action for libel.  In this case, however, the obvious difficulty of proving any &lsquo;publication&rsquo; and the probability that these communications and the occasions thereof would be held to be &lsquo;privileged&rsquo; rule out any such proceedings.  The fact that there appears to be no evidence in the records to hand that such statements were warranted, would not be sufficient grounds to sustain an action for defamation in the circumstances.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I should point out that nothing that has occurred affects in any way your brother's position as a director of the company He is still entitled to notice of meetings, and in this connection, any deliberate omission to notify him of such meetings would, in my opinion, render the proceedings thereat invalid.  He is entitled to arrears of salary up to such time as his employment as manager and secretary is properly terminated, which could be done by his co-directors at any board meeting.</P>
    <P>I have dealt at some length with the matters upon which you have asked for my opinion and advice. If there should be any further points upon which you desire advice, or any matters in the foregoing which you would like to have clarified, I will be glad to be of any assistance.&mdash; Yours very truly, Darach Connolly.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>As I told the House I got this on the 28th May.  With the consent of Dr. MacCarvill I furnished copies to Dr. Ward and received from Dr. Ward the following reply:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Further to my letter of even date-and following the most careful consideration of Dr. MacCarvill's allegations, <Col N="1939" /> I would urge that the whole matter be made the subject of a judicial inquiry with the least possible delay.  The charges as to my conduct as Parliamentary Secretary in relation to the appointment of deputy medical officer of Monaghan Dispensary District are of a most serious nature and the fullest investigation becomes in the circumstances a matter of great urgency.</P>
    <P>Pending the setting up of the tribunal and consideration of the report, I should be glad if the Government would permit me to abstain from the exercise of my functions as Parliamentary Secretary.&mdash;Yours sincerely (Signed) F.C. Ward.</P>
    <P>Eamon Uas.  de Valera,</P>
    <P>An Taoiseach,</P>
    <P>Baile Atha Cliath.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>These are the matters and I do not think it would be right for me to make any comment of any kind.  Having considered them, I felt the best thing in the public interest was to ask, as by this resolution I have asked, that a tribunal of inquiry should be set up under the Tribunal of Inquiry (Evidence) Act, 1921.  I think that I should not say any more at this stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I was present in the gallery of the other House when these letters were read and I imagine the feelings I had at the time are the feelings of probably every member of the House here, and that is that we are bound to recognise the extreme gravity of the letters which the Taoiseach has seen fit to read to Parliament.  In fact I might say that as far as the internal political life of the country is concerned I cannot remember anything in the last 20 years or so during which I have been a member which I would regard as very much more serious.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is extremely difficult to decide, and must have been extremely difficult for the Taoiseach to decide, what would have been the correct action.  It would be equally difficult for us if we had individual responsibility&mdash;and of course in a sense we have individual responsibility&mdash;to decide what is the <Col N="1940" /> proper action when charges of this kind are made by a person who in the opinion of the Government is of such a responsible character that those charges must be read to Parliament.</P>
    <P>I think it is extremely important for every member of this House and of the public to remember that we must not under any circumstances allow our minds to assume that the Deputy concerned is guilty of any one of the charges which have been made.  It is extremely common when a case first comes before a lower court for the public to assume that many of the charges are being more or less proved, and sometimes the public do not read any more about it.  It would seem to me that it is only right, especially coming from this side of the House, that one should emphasise, and I hope the newspapers in the interests not only of Deputy Dr. Ward, but in the interests of the good faith of all members to both Houses will emphasise, that the reading of these letters by the Taoiseach or the acceptance of the motion by either House does not assume that we even consider any single point has been proved.</P>
    <P>Everyone, particularly those who have been in public life for some time, knows how ready a certain section of the public is to believe whispers and to accept doubts on the integrity of members.  Whatever our Party affiliations or sympathies may be, and whether we have no Party affiliations, every single member is concerned with the good faith and integrity of public life and that is just as much the concern of any one Deputy as it is of anyone else.  I think I may say it is as much the concern of an individual member as it is for the Taoiseach or the Government and that in anything we may say that must be borne in mind.</P>
    <P>I understand that a vote was taken in the Dáil and that this motion was passed.  That being the case, even if we have some doubts as to this being the best method, it would be a mistake for the Seanad to disagree, particularly as it concerns a Deputy.  Therefore, I would recommend to the Seanad to agree to this motion.  However, I would be glad if the Taoiseach, in replying, <Col N="1941" /> would answer one or two questions I would put to him, if it is possible to do so.  They are questions which have been put to me since the debate took place in the Dáil to-day and questions on which the public would like some information which would add to confidence.  Once this tribunal is set up, will the Attorney-General have any specific function in relation to it, in the interest of justice and in getting the true facts?  We will assume that the Deputy will be represented by counsel or in whatever way he thinks fit and will be given every possible facility to defend himself; but in order that public confidence should be maintained, this being a matter of a public personage, I think the public would like to feel certain that there will be something to take the place of a prosecutor, so that the case for both sides will be before the court.  I am not asking that in any critical way.  I have assumed that, as it is Dr. MacCarvill who made the charges and as it is his letters and the letters of Mr. Connolly that are to be investigated, he will have full legal rights to appear before the tribunal.</P>
    <P>I would also like to ask if it is intended that the judges appointed will be asked to leave their present duties, so that this matter may be dealt with immediately, or will it have to take its place in between the other legal matters they have to deal with? If I understood him correctly the Taoiseach said the desire was that it should be carried through as promptly as possible.  In general, I would agree, but I would suggest that, if there is any appearance of haste or any suggestion at all of haste preventing any possible witnesses, the effect might be rather unfortunate.  We all want the public to have the most absolute confidence in the tribunal.  I do not think it is possible, by any method, to deal with a situation of this kind, in which somebody in the public will not say it is being manoeuvred.  I am certainly making no such charge.  I am speaking in this matter entirely for myself and not on behalf of any group, as this is a matter which concerns the honour of an individual and should not be a Party matter.  I have some misgivings about <Col N="1942" /> the method adopted by the Government. At the same time, I do not think we should oppose it, since it has gone so far, since the letters have been made public and on account of the very serious nature of the subject matter of the letters.</P>
    <P>Some of the charges, if proved&mdash;and I hope they will not be proved&mdash;would be of a criminal character.  Others probably are not so, but would suggest matters which, to put it mildly, would leave an extremely bad taste, from a political point of view.  To my mind, some of them are clearly related to the duties of the Deputy, either as a Deputy or as a Parliamentary Secretary; others are almost entirely coming within his private capacity, that is, if it is ever possible for a Deputy or a Senator completely to segregate his private capacity from his public duties&mdash;which, frankly, I doubt.  On the whole, I think I would have preferred that, when a charge of this kind was made to the Executive of the day, they would consider it and, if they decided it was a criminal charge which must be taken seriously, they would hand it to the Attorney-General for investigation or, if they did not think it would be treated seriously, they would leave it to the Deputy with full power to have all the legal redress he was in a position to have.  They would bring it before Parliament only after that action had been taken, or if the Deputy said that, for financial or other reasons, he was unable to take that action.</P>
    <P>Until we have seen what happens in this case and until the matter can be considered without relation to a particular case, I think this should not be regarded as a precedent.  I hope the Government, having decided on this tribunal, and both Houses, I expect, having agreed to it, special care will be taken that it is not regarded as a precedent.  In other words, if a prominent member of a Party were to make serious charges against other members, whether Deputies or Parliamentary Secretaries, it should not be assumed that that would lead immediately to a public inquiry.  I respectfully suggest to the Taoiseach to endorse that, in his opinion, it was not to be regarded as a precedent, until, <Col N="1943" /> perhaps through a joint committee of both Houses, at a later date and after this case has been dealt with and is no longer a personal matter, the question can be considered and agreement reached as to the normal procedure in somewhat similar circumstances.  On the whole, the right course would be for the House to agree to the motion, without necessarily endorsing it, since it had to be and is the responsibility of the Government in the action they have decided to take.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret to say that the proceedings suggested here are somewhat unusual.  It occurs to me that the whole incident is very regrettable and is presented to us in a particularly distasteful fashion.  We have a very prominent man, who occupied a very conspicuous place in public life, writing a letter, in May, 1946, dealing with incidents, some of them ten and 12 years old, and a letter carrying a kind of suspicion that they would have not been dealt with at all if it were not that his brother was involved.  That does not reflect a lot of credit on the public responsibility of the writer of the letter.  Next, there are very serious charges contained in these letters and I do not know if there is any element of privilege attaching to them.  I do not profess to have any legal knowledge, but if there is no element of privilege, obviously Deputy Dr. Ward was presented with an opportunity to take an action in the manner he himself suggested.</P>
      <P>The first letter he wrote on the 1st June indicated his own mind that this was a matter which should be tried in the ordinary courts, and I assume what he meant was that the action would be an action for libel against the writer of these letters, Dr. MacCarvill.  He changed that attitude during the day, and he asked for a tribunal.  I have grave doubts, and I do not take the same line as Senator Douglas for a variety of reasons, as to the setting up of a tribunal such as suggested, because we have had one experience in recent years of a tribunal set up to inquire into charges of a somewhat similar character.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1944" /> If I remember rightly, that tribunal was hamstrung by the fact that there was no prosecutor to sift the evidence and to put questions on the evidence coming before the tribunal.  I am referring now to the inquiry into the transfer of shares the property of the Great Southern Railways.  Nobody appeared before that tribunal to represent the State or to collect the information to which the State had access, and submit it for the information and guidance of the tribunal.</P>
    <P>I am very anxious to know whether if this House is to acquiesce in the setting up of this tribunal the tribunal will be in the same situation, having to seek evidence, having to set machinery in motion to find out if any of these allegations are true, or to unearth facts which may not easily be unearthed.  When I heard the Taoiseach reading the first part of the correspondence in which there are allegations of serious criminal acts, it occurred to me that the Government in any other case would simply have handed over the documents to the Attorney-General who, in turn, would go to the superintendent of the Guards in Monaghan, Dublin or where the case arose, or to the Commissioner of the Guards and say: &ldquo;Here are the allegations of defrauding the revenue, allegations of other kinds&rdquo;&mdash;I am not speaking of breaches of professional etiquette&mdash;&ldquo;the suggestion of criminal conduct.&rdquo;  The ordinary course to follow would be for the Gárda authorities to take the action they are competent to take, and which normally they do take when allegations are brought to their notice.  I think that was the most satisfactory method.</P>
    <P>I do not think that the first method of taking a libel action would be a satisfactory method, although I think the proceedings should be taken by the Government, and I cannot understand why the Government has adopted this course of setting up a tribunal and asking the House to agree to its setting up without telling the House what are its functions, who is to assist in the production of evidence, who is to present it, does the Attorney-General come in, do the police come in, or is it <Col N="1945" /> a question of Dr. Ward going before the tribunal and saying there is no word of truth in it and it would be nobody's business to get the charges, get the proofs or examine witnesses.</P>
    <P>As I said already, the Dáil having approved of the motion, it would be very unwise for us to take a contrary view.  I think that is the sensible thing to do, while at the moment I say I do not feel happy about the method of what is being done, and I would like to get some assurance that this will be a <i>bona fide</i> investigation in the same way as a trial in a criminal court.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I want, first of all, to echo the statement of Senator Douglas that this is a matter of the utmost gravity and should be so treated, but it should be treated in an objective way in which there cannot be any suggestion by anyone that any person dealing with it is assuming that either one party or the other is correct in the denials made and the allegations made.  But I do not think that the House, as a whole, appreciates and understands the exact procedure that is envisaged in the terms of the motion.  I do not think the House appreciates and understands the methods that are adopted when a tribunal is set up in this fashion; and, in order, perhaps, that the House may exactly appreciate what is proposed, I would like to put to the Taoiseach certain definite questions.  I would like, first, to inquire the number of persons that must form a tribunal under this Act.  I would like, second, to inquire whether all those persons are necessarily judges, and if so, whether they are of the Supreme Court, the High Court, the Circuit Court or justices of the District Court, or what?  I want, thirdly, to inquire as Senator Duffy inquired, whether the Attorney-General appears at such tribunal and puts a case before it?  I would ask the Taoiseach also to make it clear whether the person, Dr. MacCarvill, who has laid the charge contained in the correspondence, has of right, the right to attend, and put such evidence as he wishes before the tribunal.  I would like the Taoiseach, further, to lay it down, or to inform us rather, whether <Col N="1946" /> the tribunal, at the end of its deliberations will have the right, or will not have the right, to say that one side or the other was correct or incorrect and that, therefore, the State or one or other of the party should pay the substantial costs that will be incurred by appearing before such tribunal, and, in respect of that aspect, I do think it is unreasonable that the tribunal has not that right that an individual concerned would have to incur legal liabilities without being able to recoup himself. Apart from that, I think the Taoiseach should inform the House whether the Attorney-General has been consulted in regard to these matters and whether he has directed that in his opinion there is or is not any criminal offence charged.</P>
      <P>If there is a criminal offence charged, then it appears to me that it is unfair on a person to have to appear before a tribunal and, possibly, to have to appear later before a criminal court when his second appearance will be prejudiced by what has transpired before the tribunal.  Equally on the other side, I want to be quite clear whether anything that this tribunal may find, does or does not prejudice any action that may be taken subsequently in a civil court for libel which I presume also is the means suggested by Dr. Ward in his first letter.  If the report of this tribunal does not interfere with the law of the land, would it not appear to be wrong that the functions of the ordinary courts would, so to speak, be prejudiced by what might be read and might be seen of the proceedings before the tribunal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I suggest to the House that these are matters on which, even before there is any further discussion on the motion, it would be better if the Taoiseach were to make the procedure clear to the House so that the House as a whole may understand.  Apart from members of the House who happen to have legal experience as barristers&mdash;because this is not a matter in which solicitors would be experienced &mdash;we have lay members of the House, and I would suggest it would be well that the House as a whole would be put in the position of knowing exactly what it was being asked to discuss in <Col N="1947" /> the terms of this motion.  I make that suggestion to the Taoiseach through the Chair, that before we proceed further with the discussion that the procedure of the tribunal with which, I think, the Taoiseach assumes we are all completely familiar would be outlined by him in an authoritative way before we digress further in any shape or form.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Senator Ryan and Senator O'Dea rose.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Taoiseach intervene for the purpose of answering the questions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are going to hear some legal opinions and perhaps we might let it go at that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>With respect I sat down for the purpose of permitting the Taoiseach to intervene.  I do not want to say anything if he would like to intervene, but if he does not wish to intervene I would like to continue my speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The point is that if other members of the Seanad speak, I have no doubt that the procedure will become more and more plain.  I am in the hands of the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Does Senator Sweetman wish to continue now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Taoiseach does not wish to intervene, I shall continue. I only sat down for the purpose of permitting him to intervene.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it would be easier if I did speak now.  I will have to speak about it at some stage though from another point.  I would prefer that those who are learned in the law would tell us more about it.  This tribunal of inquiry is being set up under the Tribunal of Inquiry (Evidence) Act 1921.  It will have all the powers of the High Court.  Therefore, it can arrange its own procedure and do everything that is necessary in order to get at the bottom, and get the facts of this particular case.  I have been asked whether the Attorney-General will be present as prosecutor.  I do not think so.  The position of the Attorney-General in cases of that sort is simply to <Col N="1948" /> assist the tribunal on any matters in which the tribunal may require his assistance, but he does not appear there as a prosecutor in any sense.  There were a number of questions asked, and perhaps I should take them <i>seriatim.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of procedure, is the Taoiseach closing the debate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No, he is answering questions put to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Because I also have a question to ask.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcGee" hpid="Mr. McGee Mr. McGee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGee</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not all lawyers, and I certainly am not prepared to take the advice I get free from any lawyer because any advice I got was a failure. In my part of the country this case will be very interesting.  What I want to ask is, why the ordinary law is being departed from.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach is in possession, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that I prefaced my statement by saying that this was the least unsatisfactory way of dealing with this question.  That indicates that I do not regard it as satisfactory, but if we examine the alternatives we will find that they would not be satisfactory either.  One suggestion was that a libel action should be taken, and that in that way the matter would be dealt with.  I do not know how long that would take.  It is obvious that during that period the Parliamentary Secretary could not function.  There is work to be done.  His is a very important office, and something has to be done about it from the point of view of public interest.  We do not want to have the case lasting over a long period.  It has been asked why, when there are allegations of a criminal character, we do not proceed by the ordinary law.  I think it would be wrong that the State should be taking action through its Executive Department against the Parliamentary Secretary while he held that office.  It is quite obvious that you could not suggest to the Parliamentary Secretary that he should resign while that investigation of a criminal character was <Col N="1949" /> going on, because it might appear that you were assuming, in advance, that there was some guilt and you could not do that.  Neither could he resign very well himself, because, again, there might be some suggestion of prejudging the case.  So that if you examine the alternatives which appear to be there, and also take into account the desirability of having this ended as soon as possible&mdash;that does not mean that there is any suggestion that there will be anything rushed about it &mdash;you will see that this is as I have said, the least unsatisfactory method. My intention was&mdash;I do not know whether I will be able to secure it in this particular form or not because I do not think I have any power to compel it&mdash;that the tribunal should consist of three judges.  It will be set up either by an Order of the Government or of a Minister.  In this case I would propose to set up the tribunal myself. My intention would be to ask a judge of the Supreme Court to act as chairman, and to associate with him two judges of the Circuit Court.  If I have any difficulty in getting judges of the Circuit Court I may have to try to have a composite court: one a Supreme Court judge, one a High Court judge and one a Circuit Court judge.  There is the question in this case of judges being available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be composed of all judges?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The intention is to have three judges.  I would like to say, in answer to some of the questions that were put, that the tribunal will have full powers of investigation.  It will be composed of competent persons who will be able to weigh the evidence. The tribunal will have full power to compel the attendance of witnesses and the production of records.  It will have all the powers of the High Court, so that I do not think there need be any question of misgivings about the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think I have dealt with the question as to why we are not proceeding by the ordinary court, and with the question of a libel action.  I have also told Senator Sweetman that the <Col N="1950" /> tribunal will consist of three judges.  I also mentioned that the Attorney-General will not be appearing as such as prosecutor.  That, obviously, would not be right either.  We are not taking action in the way of a prosecution. These are charges which are to be investigated.  These charges have been made, and there can be an impartial investigation of them without any <i>prima facie</i> case being accepted by the State.  If, of course, it should appear that there was any reason why action should be taken in the ordinary way it would be taken as a matter of course. It is one of the difficulties, undoubtedly, that the findings of this tribunal will have a certain prejudicing effect on any subsequent action.  I cannot avoid that, and I do not see any way out of it.</P>
    <P>As regards the question of libel, there may be some prejudice but, after all, those who will have conducted the investigation, in the first instance, will be regarded as a competent court.  It was suggested in the Dáil to-day that, if this matter did come to be considered by a jury in a libel action, the jurors would be prejudiced by the findings of this investigating tribunal.  I am afraid that I cannot help that.  So far as the allegations are concerned which might be regarded as coming within the code which would be pursued by the Attorney-General, there is no doubt that there would be a certain prejudicing to the extent to which weight would be attached to the findings of this tribunal.  Again, I am afraid that that is inevitable and I cannot help it. As regards the question of those who will have the right to appear before the tribunal, I cannot imagine an investigating tribunal of competent judges conducting this investigation without giving Dr. MacCarvill and Dr. Ward the right to appear.  I imagine that they would summon them before them.  I was asked a difficult question as regards costs, a question of tremendous importance from the point of view of the individuals.  I should like to see law much cheaper in this country but I think the present position under the Act is that the State bears the expenses of the tribunal, as such, but that individuals who are represented before <Col N="1951" /> the tribunal bear the cost of that representation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The tribunal has no power to impose any kind of penalty?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>So that the tribunal may still leave considerable and lengthy proceedings after it will have given its verdict?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but I think that, when the tribunal will have made its report, the position will be fairly clear. The report might be of such a kind as to relieve us of any responsibility, from the executive side, of pursuing any particular matter.  On the other hand, if there was a question of libel on one side or the other, I do not know how that would turn out.  My immediate interest is the public position of the person affected by these allegations. I take it that his public position would be made clear by the findings of the tribunal.  That is its purpose. At the present time our hands are manacled.  As a result of the findings of the tribunal, the manacles would be removed in one way or the other.  In one event, we could proceed with the work in the ordinary way, and, in the other event, there would require to be a change.  I shall have to leave this matter to those more experienced in the law than I am.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I inquired as to how the facts were to be assembled and placed before the tribunal.  Do the police come in?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator knows the meaning of a &ldquo;tribunal of investigation&rdquo;. The matters it will inquire into are the allegations in those letters.  I think that they are specific enough.  The tribunal will, I presume, set out to clear up point (1), point (2) and so on.  They will ask themselves what they will have to do to get each point cleared up and they will say: &ldquo;We shall want such and such evidence&rdquo;. They will do what, under other circumstances, a Department of State might do.  They will do what, in a private action, would be done by a solicitor or counsel or what, in the case of the State, would be done by the <Col N="1952" /> Attorney-General before he could satisfy himself that there was a case for the prosecution, or what he would do if he were preparing a case for submission to court.  There is no need for any initiating department to work up to them.  They themselves will be the initiating body in pursuing their investigations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LukeDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>All this is related to the experience of the tribunal two or three years ago in dealing with the sale of shares of the Great Southern Railways. The whole thing collapsed because nobody presented any evidence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know about the collapse.  I did not follow out the matter in detail.  But I do know that, if anything collapsed, it was because there was nobody to give evidence, notwithstanding all the allegations that were made.  If the tribunal found that no evidence was being offered, what were they to do?  If the tribunal in this case wants to get information, I do not see why they should not make use of all the available machinery. There may, of course, be limits to that. I can imagine things which the tribunal would not be likely to ask to get done but they have the ordinary powers to get people before them.  In this particular case, we have the person making allegations and we have a person against whom the allegations are made, so that I do not think the investigation will fail through want of presentation of the facts.  If there is any want, it is for the tribunal to supply it.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Mr. Sweetman rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Senator Sweetman entitled to make two speeches?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>He is resuming his speech which he interrupted to hear replies to questions he asked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Senator Sweetman entitled to special privilege in this House, apart from other members?  Is he entitled to make two speeches, calling on the Taoiseach to reply to him personally and refusing to go on unless the Taoiseach so replied?  Are the 39 other members here entitled to the same privileges?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is <Col N="1953" /> resuming his speech in the circumstances I have stated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that Senator Sweetman said he would resume his speech if the Taoiseach did not reply but would finish it if he did.  I submit that he had finished his speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanGoulding" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Sweetman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that Senator Ryan did not understand what I said.  I want to thank the Taoiseach for having answered the questions I put to him.  In the few questions I put, I tried to treat this matter in an entirely objective way, apart altogether from politics.  I am not as familiar with the procedure, and I do not think that other members are as familiar with the procedure, as Senator Ryan or a few other members who had an opportunity of looking into it.  The Taoiseach said, in reply to the last question I put, that the tribunal had no power to direct that the costs of any party should be paid by another party.  I think something should be done to meet that situation.  I think that the Taoiseach would agree that this is an investigation which might take a considerable time.  The cost of it to any party might be very substantial. I think that it should be agreed that, if the tribunal is satisfied that any party by appearing before it has been of assistance to it, that party should have his costs met.  If they cannot be met in the way I indicated, they should be met by the State.  So that it will be in that way clear that a person going before that tribunal, from any point of view will not be incurring a liability by so doing and will not be at the end of the investigation out of pocket in a way that I suggest would be unfair to him.  I would suggest that it should be left to the tribunal to decide whether the submission of the person concerned had been of assistance or had not and, if the tribunal decided that the submission was of assistance, I think the man concerned should not be out of pocket in regard to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1954" /> I am afraid that I do not subscribe to the Taoiseach's point of view that this is the best method of dealing with the matter.  I would have preferred that that matter would have been dealt with by the courts in the ordinary way but I take the view indicated by Senator Douglas that, as a decision has been taken in the other House, it would be wrong for this House to try in any way to vary that decision. Therefore I am concerned purely to ensure that the method that it has been decided to adopt shall be adopted in the best manner possible and with all the facilities necessary for that method.  I assume of course that the tribunal considering this matter will deal with it in public.  I assume that the tribunal, under the powers the Taoiseach indicated, will have the right to call any person or any Government Department.  I take it he meant the word &ldquo;person&rdquo; to cover also all Government Departments, including the Guards, if the tribunal so determine. Finally, having regard particularly to the very great gravity of the whole question, having regard to the fact that a tribunal, not a court, is being set up, I would urge very strongly on the Taoiseach that the tribunal should consist of three persons who are not below the rank of Supreme Court judge or a High Court judge&mdash; in other words, that they should be taken from the Supreme Court and the High Court, even if it does mean that there is going to be delay and inconvenience for ordinary litigants.  The matter is of such gravity that it should be dealt with by judges of that seniority.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRyan" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>A great deal of time would have been saved if Senator Sweetman and other speakers had read the Act of Parliament under which this tribunal is being set up.  That Act of Parliament is the Tribunal of Inquiry (Evidence) Act, 1921, 11 George V., Chapter VII. as adapted by two Orders, one made in 1930, and the other made in 1936 and also as adapted by Section 4 of the Constitution (Consequential Provisions) Act, 1937.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Act under which the tribunal is set up consists of two sections, and Senator Sweetman would find in that <Col N="1955" /> Act answers to at least three-fourths of the questions he asked the Taoiseach.  The Taoiseach is here as the Minister who, under that Act, will appoint a tribunal, but he cannot appoint a tribunal unless resolutions have been passed by both Houses of the Oireachtas.  It is not in every case that the two Houses of the Oireachtas will pass resolutions under this Act.  A Minister can only set up a tribunal in certain cases, having seen that the resolutions passed by each House of the Oireachtas contains, as the Act provides, the statement</P>
    <P>&ldquo;that it is expedient that a tribunal be established for inquiring into a definite matter, described in the resolution as of urgent public importance&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>That is the justification for the passing of a resolution by both Houses of the Oireachtas setting up this tribunal.</P>
    <P>The Act provides that the tribunal has to be appointed for the purpose by a Minister&mdash;in the Act, of course, it is the Secretary of State, but that has been adapted.  The instrument under which the tribunal is appointed will provide that this Act is to apply. When the instrument under which the tribunal is set up by the Minister&mdash;in this case, I presume, the Taoiseach&mdash; contains that provision, then the Act provides that the tribunal</P>
    <P>&ldquo;shall have all such powers, rights and privileges as are vested in the High Court on the occasion of an action, in respect of the following matters:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  the enforcing the attendance of witnesses and examining them on oath, affirmation or otherwise;</P>
    <P>(b)  the compelling the production of documents, and</P>
    <P>(c)  subject to the rules of court, the issuing of a commission or request to examine witnesses abroad.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The Act also provides for the punishment of persons who are summoned as witnesses and who refuse to attend. Section 2 of the Act provides as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;A tribunal to which this Act is <Col N="1956" /> so applied as foresaid:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  shall not refuse to allow the public or any portion of the public to be present at any of the proceedings of the tribunal unless in the opinion of the tribunal it is in the public interest expedient so to do for reasons connected with the subject matter of the inquiry or the nature of the evidence to be given, and</P>
    <P>(b)  shall have power to authorise the representation before them of any person appearing to them to be interested by counsel or solicitor or otherwise, or to refuse to allow such representation.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Sub-section (3) of Section 1 provides that a witness before any such tribunal shall be entitled to the same immunities and privileges, as if he were a witness before the High Court.  If the two Houses of the Oireachtas consider it expedient in the circumstances to set up this tribunal, then such tribunal will be appointed by a Minister under an instrument.  Now, of course, the personnel of the tribunal is a matter for the Minister&mdash;in this case the Taoiseach&mdash;but after the Taoiseach has set up the tribunal the powers and functions of that tribunal are governed solely by the Act of Parliament.  Therefore a number of the questions which were asked of the Taoiseach here were, if I may say so, rather misdirected because the Taoiseach cannot, in other words, prescribe the powers and functions of the tribunal.  These powers are prescribed by law.</P>
    <P>The question of cost has been raised. This Act provides that the tribunal shall be established for the purpose of inquiring into some matter that is of urgent public importance.  That tribunal is an inquiry tribunal and it, so to speak, has to get to the root of the matter that is being inquired into. For that purpose, it is a tribunal with powers to compel witnesses to attend, to call for documents and to authorise the representation before it of any person who, the tribunal considers, appears to be interested.  Now there is no provision in the Act for the payment of costs and the tribunal will not in itself have any power to award costs.  The function of the tribunal will <Col N="1957" /> be to make a report to the Minister by whom it was set up.  For the purpose of making that report it must necessarily have before it the parties who are interested in the matter that is being inquired into and, therefore, in my view, if the parties appearing before the tribunal are to be allowed their costs, or are to be reimbursed in respect of costs, then it would be almost necessary to bring in a special Act of Parliament.  I think so at any rate but there may be powers under some other Act to entitle a tribunal of this kind to award costs.  I am not clear on that point.</P>
    <P>I think that whether this tribunal is the appropriate form of inquiry into the matters raised in those letters is a matter for the Oireachtas because of course the two Houses must be agreed and must act in unison before this inquiry can be set up.  The mere fact that the resolution has been passed by one House will not authorise the Minister to inquire into the particular matter which has been raised and, therefore, if the two Houses of the Oireachtas pass this resolution it will, I submit, be an endorsement of the view that this tribunal is the most appropriate means of investigating the matters that have been raised in the letters read here this evening.</P>
    <P>The Houses of the Oireachtas do not move often, and it is only in a case where the question involves a matter of public importance that such a resolution as this is passed by both Houses of the Oireachtas and that a tribunal should be appointed to inquire into these matters.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. Hayes Mr. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the Taoiseach that this matter, no matter how one looks at it, is unsatisfactory, and we can well imagine that in the short time at his disposal since the matter came to his notice in the letter from Dr. MacCarvill, a considerable number of difficulties presented themselves to him.  He has taken the decision to put the matter before a tribunal of the character which Senator Ryan has just described.  Might I point out to Senator Ryan, however, that there is nothing in the motion which appears on to-day's Order Paper to indicate that the tribunal is being appointed under <Col N="1958" /> the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) Act, 1921, although from a certain amount of experience that I have had myself I came to that conclusion by looking at the motion?  It is easy for Senator Ryan who was able to spend the afternoon, I suspect, looking at this particular Act to say to Senator Sweetman who spent his time in the House discussing the Tourist Bill, that he did not attempt to read the Act.</P>
      <P>Now, there is nothing very remarkable in what Senator Ryan said about the provisions of that Act.  The matter was brought to the notice of members of both Houses by this Order Paper.  I did not in fact get an Order Paper at 9 o'clock, but the Leaders of the Parties in the Dáil were summoned to the Taoiseach's office at, I think, 12 o'clock, and they were told of this particular matter, that the letters would be read and that a motion would be made to set up a tribunal which would be of a judicial character. But the letters were not disclosed to them and they were not, therefore, in a position to determine what particular kind of tribunal would be best to investigate the charges set out in these letters.  I asked Senator Douglas to go to the Dáil this afternoon to see what the whole thing was like, and when I hear the matter now for the first time myself I find great difficulty in making up my mind as to what the proper procedure should be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the first place, there is a general tendency in legislation to oust the jurisdiction of the ordinary courts, and there can be no doubt that from the point of view of the ordinary citizen seeking for justice the best method is the ordinary courts.  I take that to apply not only to a member of the public but to a member of the Dáil or Seanad, a Parliamentary Secretary or a member of the Government.  I agree at once there may be special difficulties and in this particular case there are special difficulties.  Listening attentively to the Taoiseach reading these letters, there appears to me to be a regular medley of charges of a different character and this tribunal will have to sift the different kinds of charges it is to investigate.  In the first place, there is, I gather, a criminal <Col N="1959" /> charge in the evasion of income-tax. In the second place, there is a civil matter where the brother of the writer of the letter, or, at least, his solicitor, takes the view that he has been wrongly dismissed.  That is a civil matter.  As well as that, there is a professional matter in relation to the appointment of a substitute, if that is a purely professional matter, and further to that there is, I think, the idea that the Parliamentary Secretary's political, Parliamentary and Governmental positions were used for the furtherance of his personal ends. It seems to me that it would be difficult for the three judges whom the Taoiseach is endeavouring to get&mdash;I admit at once he is quite <i>bona fide</i> in trying to get the best people for the tribunal&mdash;to deal with all these matters. They will have a difficult task, because they will have charges of different kinds to deal with, and they will be in a different position altogether from the tribunal to which Senator Duffy alluded.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Douglas that we must not get into the position to which many people are wont to get into, of thinking that charges once made have been proved.  We must remember that this tribunal will be in a different position from that of the ordinary courts.  I think the Parliamentary Secretary's first reaction to the whole business was perhaps the correct one, that is that he should be entitled to take an action for libel, bring the matter before the courts in that way, and it would be for the court to disentangle this matter, as they thought best, in accordance with the procedure which I take it has been laid down for a very long period of years.  In this particular instance there are several charges, one greatly different from the others.  If the charge of the evasion of income-tax were made against me or against Patrick Murphy out in the street the whole machinery of State would be brought to bear upon it, in collecting evidence from witnesses and in the sifting of documents, and the Attorney-General and the best counsel the Revenue Commissioners could get would all be made available to prove that Patrick Murphy did in fact evade income-tax.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1960" /> If I understand this matter correctly, when this is brought before this particular court there will be no prosecutor and the police will not be used for the collecting of evidence.  That would appear to me to make a very great difference between a person put before this tribunal, a person who is prosecuting and another person who is there in the absence of a prosecutor.  The State will prosecute in the ordinary way if it seemed to the Attorney-General there was <i>prima facie</i> evidence that there had been evasion of income-tax.</P>
    <P>In this particular case, unless the person who makes the charge, Dr. MacCarvill, is prepared to brief counsel at very considerable expense, I do not know how the charge can be proceeded with at all.  It is quite extraordinary to suggest that any tribunal of this kind, constituted under the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) Act, 1921, should be asked to decide a purely civil matter. I think the lawyers would agree with me in that.  It would be quite unprecedented if this tribunal were asked to decide whether there were grounds for the dismissal of Mr. MacCarvill from his position as secretary and manager of this particular bacon company.  That would be giving it a new job.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach argued that the matter was one which should not brook delay, but surely the procedure set out here will not hasten matters.  In the ordinary way, if I am charged with evading income-tax or with any other ordinary crime, the evidence would go to the Attorney-General or someone acting on his behalf and the matter would go before a court of first instance.  Is not this court, which is to be composed of a judge of the Supreme Court and two Circuit Court judges, really a court of first instance?  I think it is. It is a very remarkable position for a Supreme Court judge to be in.  If he finds there is <i>prima facie</i> evidence that there has been evasion of income-tax, presumably a prosecution must take place in the ordinary way.  I do not profess to be as skilled as Senator Ryan in this matter of procedure, but surely that is the position?  Where is the advantage, therefore, of this particular court?  If, on the other hand, <Col N="1961" /> the court finds that there is no evidence at all to support that, then, with a great amount of publicity and at very considerable expense, something will have been done which the Attorney-General ordinarily does or which a very much lower court would do in the ordinary way.</P>
    <P>The same thing appears to me to apply to a civil action.  I take it that nothing happening now under this resolution will prevent Mr. MacCarvill, the person who was secretary to the bacon company, no matter what this tribunal decides, from having the right to proceed for unlawful dismissal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would say that that is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>In the ordinary way, those proceedings would then drag out in the ordinary courts.  No matter what the tribunal decides, presumably the Parliamentary Secretary would still have the right to take an action for libel, as I assume the publication of this matter is not privileged&mdash;and I feel it would be very inequitable, if not illegal, if it were privileged.  Such an action for libel would carry on for a very long time and, in the meantime, the Taoiseach will be no better off than he is now with regard to getting the work of the Department of Local Government done.  I see no advantage at all in this particular method.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another point about this kind of tribunal.  I was speaking recently to a Circuit judge who had been a member of the Dáil.  He told me he found it was easier to do the work of a Circuit judge than the work of a Deputy, as he had far less correspondence. I have heard judges, some of whom I know, say: &ldquo;The facts are put up to you in the court.&rdquo;  Lawyers like Senators Ryan and Kingsmill Moore put up the facts and state the law and the judges do not have to do anything.  Judges as an investigating tribunal&mdash;I hope I am not being disrespectful in saying so&mdash;are just no use.  The whole notion of asking a judge to investigate a charge by himself is like asking a doctor to make a suit of clothes, as it is something completely outside his ordinary functions. The judge's function, under our <Col N="1962" /> system, which is the British system, is to sit on the bench and show great care, courtesy and patience in hearing the cases, to prove fair to the police and to the witnesses, to hear the evidence of the facts brought before the court at great length by examination, cross-examination and re-examination of witnesses.  There is the presentation of points of law.  The judge can ask, and I understand frequently does ask, for examples of precedent and there are people there paid to go into that matter.  This particular tribunal will have none of those advantages. I think the lawyers would agree with me on that.  There will be nobody to put the facts to it and nobody to put the law to it, yet it is being asked to investigate and sift matters in which both law and fact are inextricably mingled, as well as what one might call political or Ministerial etiquette, which is a different matter, on which possibly a judge also is not very competent to decide.</P>
    <P>While I understand the Taoiseach's desire&mdash;and that is, of course, the desire of the head of any Government and is not a personal matter&mdash;that when a Parliamentary Secretary or Minister is charged, the matter would be disposed of as soon as possible, so that the work may go on, I suggest that this procedure does not effect that end at all.  The matter is one which is bound to take some time and any attempt to take a short cut by appointing a special tribunal will not accomplish that end.  It would be much better to let the ordinary courts operate in the ordinary way.</P>
    <P>There is another point, that the tribunal has no power to award costs. Since the Taoiseach has made up his mind on this matter, and since the Dáil has decided to accept this tribunal, I see no good purpose to be served by our endeavouring to defeat this motion.  Assuming it is going to be passed, while we have merely the knowledge we get at first blush by hearing the documents read, I think the question of costs is one that should be decided.  The tribunal has no power to award costs compulsorily, as the High Court has.  The tribunal has power to make a report to the Minister <Col N="1963" /> and to state it thinks that particular costs should be paid.  If the tribunal were making that report, I am perfectly certain that the Taoiseach or anyone else would at once agree to pay those costs and the Dáil would feel bound to agree to a Supplementary Estimate for that purpose.  The tribunal, however, only makes that as a recommendation and has no legal power to assess costs.</P>
    <P>There is one other point, mentioned by Senator Douglas, with which I would like to deal.  It seems to me that, when all this is out of the way and there is no specific case before us, we should have a discussion on the question of the procedure which should be adopted in regard to any charges made against members of the Oireachtas, whether Deputies or Senators, and I think we should have, further, a joint committee to decide what steps should be taken to prevent Deputies and Senators themselves from making charges against persons who are not members of the Oireachtas. We had several very glaring cases of that kind of thing, of charges made, and quite recently, a Minister speaking from his place in the Dáil, delivered a judgment which might normally be delivered in court.</P>
    <P>The question of a tribunal for X, but no tribunal for Y, and the ordinary courts for somebody else, and the Minister pronouncing about some other person is all quite wrong.  To conclude on this matter, in the way in which it was done and the Dáil having decided it, I think we have no option but to decide on allowing the matter to go to this tribunal.  I do not think it will be settled rapidly by this tribunal, and the argument that the ordinary courts are not being used for the purpose of getting a quick decision is not a sound argument.  The various steps that must be taken when this matter comes to be teased out will prove to be lengthy ones.  However, Sir, the decision has been taken and there is nothing we can do to avoid it.  Therefore, I would not divide the House against the motion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Douglas, in his opening remarks, referred to the responsibility that rests upon each <Col N="1964" /> Senator in the matter of recognising fully and realising his personal responsibility.  I fully realise my personal responsibility.  I am in very considerable sympathy with the Taoiseach in the decision he had to take at short notice in this matter, but I am sorry to say that I feel that he has made a very unwise decision.</P>
      <P>Let us examine this in its salient aspect.  Criminal allegations are made against a citizen.  In ordinary course, I think the Taoiseach admitted that papers would follow the usual line of going to the Attorney-General, and if adequate evidence was forthcoming a criminal prosecution would follow. What has been done in this case?  The Taoiseach says that that course would not be a wise or prudent one to follow on account of the position of the Parliamentary Secretary.  What does that amount to?  There is one law for certain sections of citizens and another law for others, and I am afraid that is the way the public will take it&mdash;one law for the rich and another for the poor.</P>
      <P>I am afraid by our decision that there is to be one law for people in certain Government positions and another law for the remainder of the citizens.  That is most unfortunate. Where is this discrimination to stop? The Parliamentary Secretary is having this discrimination exercised in his favour.  Would a Senator or Deputy be dealt with similarly?  If that was so, it would be most unfortunate.</P>
      <P>When criminal charges are made, criminal charges should follow, irrespective of the position the person occupies.  He should be treated as a citizen and therefore I think the decision as made is unwise.  It will be passed, I know, but I personally cannot support the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel that while we must view this regrettable matter as objectively as possible, at the same time, I do think we must also look upon it as realists.  For that reason, I am in entire agreement with Senator Sir John Keane and in my opinion a most regrettable and very hasty decision was taken by the other House to-day.  Senator Douglas has pointed <Col N="1965" /> out that there is always a tendency, particularly where public men are concerned, that when a charge is made, there are thoughtless people who consider the very fact that the making of a charge denotes guilt.  Smoke and extra-camouflage can be added, and these people who are not really evil-minded so much as ignorant will feel that by the very fact that in this case, instead of letting the common law take its course, the Oireachtas is giving what the man in the street will regard as special protection to one of its members by setting up a special tribunal of investigation.</P>
      <P>I can sympathise with the Taoiseach in the decision he took.  I can sympathise with his desire in this matter to have it cleared up one way or the other as hastily as possible, but I do feel that it is a great pity that there is an ever increasing tendency in this country to override the ordinary civil courts.</P>
      <P>In normal circumstances should anyone except a Parliamentary Secretary be involved in a case like this, there would probably be two actions that would take place, an action for libel before a judge of the High Court and a jury of his fellow citizens, or as a result of the investigations of the Attorney-General and police, there would be a trial before a judge and jury in the Central Criminal Court.</P>
      <P>I feel that in the interests of Dr. Ward and of public men and public life generally, a very unwise decision has been taken in setting up this tribunal rather than leaving the case to the ordinary courts, and I have great doubt whether the Taoiseach will succeed in getting a decision from this tribunal in which case he will not only leave the Government, but this man who has had this attack made on him in a more unfortunate position than at the present time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not like to enter into this discussion at all because the man who has made the complaint and the man against whom the complaint has been made are both friends of mine, and the only reason I do speak is because of the speeches that have been made by certain members of this <Col N="1966" /> House.  I thought that when it would be mentioned here that the Dáil had passed a resolution asking that this inquiry should be set up that this House would without any discussion come to the same conclusion that we would have united action and the motion would be passed without a word on either side.</P>
      <P>Certain members have thought it advisable to get up, and while they deprecated the idea that certain people imagine a charge is proved once it is made, they themselves have by their statements shown that they have fallen into the same mistake and they allege that something is done to hide a particular person.  What are the facts? Does the fact of setting up this inquiry prevent any other proceedings good, bad or indifferent?  It does not.  Does it delay those proceedings?  It does not.</P>
      <P>Any proceeding that can be taken can be taken whether the inquiry is set up or whether it is not set up.  The man charged has asked for the inquiry. Senators know how an inquiry is held. We had the inquiry that was set up to inquire into the purchase of shares in Córas Iompair Éireann.  The judges who presided at that inquiry brought every person before them that ever uttered a whisper about wrong dealings in those shares.  Members of the Dáil were brought there, and were asked about certain statements that they had made in the Dáil.  They were asked if they had any evidence to support the statements they had made.  Some of them cut a very sorry figure, and had to say that they had not a particle of evidence to support the statements they had made.  They heard whisperings going around and because of that they solemnly made statements in the Dáil as if they were facts, and some people did accept them as facts until the investigation was held.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Duffy said that that investigation broke down.  It did not break down.  That tribunal investigated every little-tattle that ever was suggested. There was never a more searching inquiry than that inquiry. The tribunal got a list of the shares that were purchased, they brought <Col N="1967" /> before them every person who had purchased those shares and they brought before them the stockbrokers who acted for the purchasers.  They asked them if they had got any special information from anybody connected with the directorate of Córas Iompair Éireann, and found that they had not. Now, the man that asks for an inquiry is asking for the most searching investigation that ever can be made into his character and conduct.  Nothing is to be hidden.  No other proceedings are to be held up, and no special privilege is being attached to him more than to any other person.  I think it is very wrong to suggest that there was.  I thought that this motion would have been passed without any discussion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMcGee" hpid="Mr. McGee Mr. McGee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGee</NameTxt>
      <P>I happen to know both gentlemen in this matter, and I am rather surprised that their training did not prompt them to write to some other person than the Taoiseach.  If it were my case I would have gone to a lawyer and in that way would have saved this House from wasting its time.  We all have our common rights, and we have been listening to the happenings that have taken place in the last 16 years, especially in my county. I think that the ordinary law should not be interfered with.  I know that if it were my case I would not look pleasantly on having my case and myself discussed before the Seanad as this case has been discussed here this evening.  I would prefer the ordinary law.  I think that Dr. MacCarvill could very well have taken this action in connection with Dr. Ward in the courts instead of delaying us in doing our business here this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Patrick O'Reilly Mr. Patrick O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Patrick O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to delay this House very long.  I think it is a grand thing that this matter has been discussed with such restraint.  I do not know in what way it was discussed in the other House.  Some Senators appear to be worried as to whether this matter should be disposed of by action in the courts or under the tribunal it is proposed to set up.  This matter has been brought to light by the correspondence which the Taoiseach read here this evening.  It seems to me <Col N="1968" /> that if it were to be dealt with in the courts that the principal witness would be the Taoiseach.  I do not think that could be regarded as a happy state of affairs&mdash;that a position would arise in which the Taoiseach would have to go into court as a witness in a case of this sort.  I do not agree with Senator McGee that charges of this sort are not of such importance as to warrant a discussion in this House.</P>
      <P>It is because of the fact that the Parliamentary Secretary is a Parliamentary Secretary that these matters were brought to the notice of the Taoiseach.  In consequence of that he has come to the Dáil and the Seanad to ask the two Houses to set up this inquiry.  I think it is a healthy thing that an inquiry of this kind should take place to establish how far there is any substance in those charges.  Suppose the Taoiseach had to take the view that this was a very disquieting matter, that it was not a matter he would like to go before the public and suppose then, as he would have the right to do, I think, he asked the Parliamentary Secretary to relinquish his office, and then probably asked him not to stand as a Fianna Fáil candidate, a position would be created in which that unfortunate man would find that he had no redress.  That would give an opportunity to people to start a whispering campaign which is the most dangerous form of destruction that one could think of.  For these reasons, I think it is proper that an inquiry should be held, and that this thing should be gone into as far as it is humanly possible to go into it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Hayes suggested that judges are probably the worst people to hold this inquiry.  I cannot take that view. Suppose you do not get judges, who are you going to get?  I do not think it would be desirable to have this matter inquired into by a Joint Committee of the Dáil and Seanad.  I would not regard that as satisfactory.  After all judges, apart from the suggestion that has been made that they are guided by precedent, and by the arguments put before them by lawyers in coming to their decisions, are, we must admit, men of commonsense, and that in a matter of this kind, when they come <Col N="1969" /> to examine fact after fact, they will use their commonsense.  Because of their training, they will know how to get the material evidence that they will need to enable them to make up their minds.  In any case, I agree with Senator Sweetman that the members of the tribunal should be judges of the Supreme Court, the High Court and the Circuit Court.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator wish to say that the judges are going to be prosecutors?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Patrick O'Reilly Mr. Patrick O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Patrick O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesTunney" hpid="Mr. Tunney Mr. Tunney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Tunney</NameTxt>
      <P>Then what you have been saying is nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Patrick O'Reilly Mr. Patrick O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Patrick O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>The members of this tribunal will have all the power they require to call evidence on the matters that they are to inquire into. They will have brought before them all the facts that they consider relevant to the charges that are being made.  I think that should satisfy Senator Tunney.  In my opinion, the members of the tribunal should be judges of the Supreme Court and of the High Court if it is possible to get them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I face with very considerable displeasure the fact that I am called upon to consider this matter here.  Perhaps the fact that I dislike at any time being brought into my neighbours' quarrels and especially family quarrels, may be a consideration that I find it difficult to eliminate from my mind at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The experience of the Taoiseach in connection with this proposition will be such as to cause him to regret that he adopted this procedure.  He will discover that what Senator Hayes has indicated will turn out to be perfectly true.  So far as anybody can judge from the material placed before the House this afternoon, we shall have two long-drawn-out trials.  There is no use in pretending that, after this fact-finding body has sat and made a report to the Government, anybody will be satisfied, if further proceedings are initiated in the courts.  Until they hear the end of the story, judgment will remain in abeyance.  I think that it would have been much better if the courts of justice had been accepted as the medium by which this matter would be examined <Col N="1970" /> and judgment passed upon it. There are, it is true, various methods of arriving at the truth.  There is this tribunal method.  That is a court to find facts.  Then, there are the law courts.  But there is another way, too.</P>
    <P>I am some what puzzled to know the considerations which weighed with the Taoiseach in asking the Oireachtas to take the decision which he now seeks. Only a few weeks ago in the other House&mdash;I am not referring to last week &mdash;a motion was introduced concerning the conduct of a member of the House. The matter was one on which a number of members of the House seemed to have considerable misgiving.  It had relation to statements sworn in court. A demand was made to the Taoiseach to set up a body to inquire into certain things and the Taoiseach decided that there was no necessity to do so.  He told the House that he himself had inquired into the matter and had taken a decision.  That was a matter which the public had communicated to them through the Press.  This matter is entirely different.  The public and the Oireachtas heard of this matter for the first time from the lips of the Taoiseach himself this afternoon.  I see no reason whatever for the procedure adopted by the Taoiseach, nor am I prepared to accept the contention that, because certain charges were made against the Parliamentary Secretary, rendering it impossible for him to discharge the duties of his office, the urgency of the work to be done there demanded that the matter be settled quickly.  I see no difficulty whatever in a certain reorganisation within the Department which would have made it possible for the work to go on.  Only quite recently a Parliamentary Secretary had been added to that Department, and the country would have survived and its health services would not have appreciably deteriorated if certain problems had stood in abeyance until this matter was settled.  I do not agree that there was the least urgency.</P>
    <P>From the point of view of the people involved in this grave and serious matter, from the point of view of the credit and honour of every member of the Oireachtas&mdash;and these happenings give countenance to the things bandied about here and there&mdash;<Col N="1971" /> I think it would have been much better to proceed by way of the ordinary courts which every citizen has open to him if charges are made against him which he regards as unfair or unjust. I am quite satisfied that this fact-finding tribunal will settle very little.  The Taoiseach will find, even in so far as he is concerned, that the matter will not have ended when the facts are submitted to him by this tribunal.  There will be two long and expensive trials. It would be much better, from the standpoint of justice and truth, to have the matter dealt with in the courts.  If it were possible for this tribunal to assign counsel to the people who would be regarded as prosecutors and pay their fees, that would, at least, convince everybody that opportunities were afforded by the tribunal to hear both sides.  Of course, facilities would also be afforded to the other parties concerned to have all the facts fully and completely examined.</P>
    <P>When this investigation ends, it may be alleged, as was alleged against another tribunal this afternoon by a member of the House, that it collapsed because all the facts could not be adduced or because, as many people have said, there was no prosecuting counsel to bring out the many points which a tribunal should have illustrated for it in order to fact-find truly. I am rather in the position of Senator Sir John Keane in connection with this matter.  I think that the procedure is wrong.  Whether it be a case of a Deputy, a Senator, a Parliamentary Secretary, or a Minister, it would be far better to let the ordinary courts adjudicate.  Criminal allegations have been made in this case.  The tribunal cannot punish, so that the problem is still unsolved.  When you have such a position as that, I am convinced that the Taoiseach would serve the ends he is endeavouring to serve in a much more satisfactory way and in a way which would be more to the credit of the members of the Oireachtas and of our parliamentary institutions, by making it possible for men to solve their difficulties through the courts rather than by the employment of tribunals which have very limited powers and no <Col N="1972" /> power of punishment.  I should like to know from the Taoiseach if the members of this tribunal can decide that the proceedings, or portion of the proceedings, may be held in secret.  I think that that did take place in the case of the tribunal which dealt with the railway shares.  Whatever other members of the House may feel, I have no doubt that this is a very unsatisfactory way to proceed to do what the Taoiseach says he wants to achieve.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickSummerfield" hpid="Mr. Summerfield Mr. Summerfield">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Summerfield</NameTxt>
      <P>In the speeches we have heard for the last two hours and 20 minutes, I feel that Senators have really shirked the two main points. Surely more emphasis should have been placed on the thing that is concerning the Taoiseach and that should concern anybody who has got any feelings at all.  The honour and the integrity of a public representative are at stake and the sooner the charges that are made against that honour and integrity are either proved or disproved the better for everybody concerned. How much emphasis has been placed on that aspect?  Instead of that we have had a variety of speeches that have gone round the subject and dealt with a number of extraneous matters &mdash;dealt with things that have nothing at all to do with the matter which we are called upon to consider.  Speakers have not adverted to the honour of the man impugned and the fact that he is a junior member of the Government. That in itself provides a reason why the Government should ask us to adopt the procedure the Taoiseach has suggested to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government is concerned, as we heard and rightly heard, from Senator Douglas with this matter.  It is only proper that we also should be concerned with any charge of this kind whether it be a definite charge of the type we are dealing with or the more malicious slanderous whisper which the country is all too ready to listen to, when public men are concerned. If we have got any respect for our public men and our public institutions, we must at once take the readiest means available to investigate these charges.  The Taoiseach has said that considering the various means that are available, in his judgment and the <Col N="1973" /> judgment of his Government, this procedure of an inquiry by a tribunal is the readiest and the quickest method of getting this foul thing dealt with. It is foul whichever way it goes.  If the charges are proved they are foul; if they are disproved they are doubly foul.  I am not going to make a long speech at this hour of the evening but I have been very much concerned at the trend of the speeches to which we have listened.  Why other tribunals should have been brought in, I do not know.  If there was any apparent failure in the tribunal to which we have heard so much reference&mdash;the Córas Iompair Éireann Tribunal&mdash;was it not due to lack of moral courage on the part of certain people?  When they were asked to prove the charges they ran away from their responsibility. Let us have nothing of that kind in this case.  It is said again that this tribunal has no power to punish.  Its most important function is to investigate the truth or falsity of these terribly serious charges which are contained in the letters which have been read to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. Foran Mr. Foran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Foran</NameTxt>
      <P>There does not seem to be any desire to hear other speakers in the House and I hope we shall conclude the debate now.  We have wasted a whole evening.  My conclusion, after listening to all the speeches, is that the correspondence was sent to the wrong man.  It should have fallen into the hands of the Opposition to the Government; they could have made a good deal more capital of it if it went that way.  That is the impression created on me after listening the whole evening to the speeches.  Comparisons have been made between the railways investigation and the tribunal proposed in this case.  There is no analogy whatever between them.  In this case the charges are very definite, in writing. In the railways case they were allegations by word of mouth and no one was responsible for them.  A responsible citizen has made an allegation here containing very definite and serious charges.  These charges were sent to the Taoiseach.  Supposing he were to shelve his responsibility and put the matter on the long finger, the Dáil would not be so ready to debate <Col N="1974" /> the motion which it adopted to-day nor would certain people in this House.  The Dáil has adopted this motion and we are not going to alter it.  Therefore, what is the point in carrying on this discussion at such great length?</P>
      <P>I have every confidence that this tribunal will sift this matter because their job is very simple.  It does not require a lot of eloquent and very able lawyers; the charges are set out there definitely.  The prosecutor will have to produce his evidence to prove them. That is a simple job and he knows all about it.  The defendant will have his opportunity of refuting the evidence brought before the tribunal.  That is a simple procedure.  The report of the tribunal will be available for the whole community.  Some people are very concerned about the expense and the cost. I do not think it need be very costly. I do not think the investigation need occupy, as Senator Baxter said, months and months.  I do not think it will take very long to inquire into the matter. We shall have their findings in a very short time.  All I want to do is to appeal to the House to cut the cackle and get on with the work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJohnOReilly" hpid="Mr. P.J. O'Reilly Mr. P.J. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say, in the first place, that I think the House admires the courage of the Taoiseach in bringing the correspondence before us.  Personally, if I were in his position, I would have taken a somewhat different course.  The Taoiseach is concerned mainly with the reputation of the Parliamentary Secretary as such and the allegations that affect him as Parliamentary Secretary. They seem to be concerned with two charges.  One is the alleged evasion of income-tax and the other is the manner in which he discharged his functions as deputy for the Minister for Local Government in connection with the appointment held by himself.  These, I think, are the only two allegations that the Taoiseach might be concerned with. I personally would have investigated these things privately without saying one word to anybody.  I would say to Dr. Ward: &ldquo;We have evidence that you appear to be guilty of certain acts&rdquo; and I would give Dr. Ward an opportunity privately, either of admitting the fact that he was guilty, or of <Col N="1975" /> producing counter-evidence to show that he was not guilty.  I think that that investigation could have been completed in a couple of hours with the Departmental resources available.  If the Taoiseach was satisfied that Dr. Ward was not guilty he could have stood publicly and privately over the Parliamentary Secretary and let things rip&mdash;in other words, let such proceedings as might take place go ahead. The Taoiseach, if satisfied that he was not guilty, would feel that in the end things would come right and his policy would have been vindicated.</P>
      <P>I am concerned with one difficulty that arises.  Reference has been made to the absence of a prosecutor in connection with the inquiry in reference to Córas Iompair Éireann, and some preceding inquiries.  Supposing this consideration is taken into account.  It seems to be assumed that no matter which way the inquiry goes, legal proceedings will result.  Supposing Dr. MacCarvill or his brother is advised that it would be dangerous for him to take part in this inquiry, and that he proposes to initiate other proceedings, who decides that he would have to appear at this inquiry?  Perhaps the lawyers present or the Taoiseach in his reply would inform the House what will then be the position.  There would definitely be no prosecutor in that case. If Dr. MacCarvill or his brother decides to take part in the inquiry, he is incurring a certain amount of danger.</P>
      <P>He is also likely to incur a double set of expenses.  We are told there is no provision for the payment of expenses and the lawyers present have assured us that there is nothing to prevent legal proceedings going ahead concurrently with this inquiry.  In that case, then, it does seem a risk for Dr. MacCarvill to appear there at all.  Can Dr. MacCarvill be compelled to give evidence and if he is going to give evidence at the inquiry may not that prejudice him when he appears before an ordinary court afterwards?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These are matters which the Taoiseach might deal with when he comes to reply.  I would again like to say that I admire sincerely the great courage <Col N="1976" /> displayed by the Taoiseach in bringing this matter forward.  It was a most courageous act on his part particularly when it concerns two members of his own Party.  We should all admire that no matter what may be our opinion of the wisdom or prudence of his action.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HelenaConcannon" hpid="Mrs. Concannon Mrs. Concannon">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Concannon</NameTxt>
      <P>My own reaction to the speeches which have been made is that it seems the action of Dr. MacCarvill in bringing this matter before an interior forum necessitated the setting up of a tribunal before which the charges may be brought.  Therefore, they have a certain thing to investigate. You could not investigate this matter unless you had the facts and what better means is there of getting at these facts than by setting up a tribunal which will go into the matter and which, we are confident, will get the facts.</P>
      <P>On those facts the Taoiseach and the Government must take action, and that is another very important thing&mdash; the action to be taken.  I do not see that there is any other way of getting at the facts from which they must arrive at their decision except through the investigation of the tribunal.  There is no question of prosecution; it is a question of getting the facts.  That is what the Government wants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Unlike some of the members of the Seanad, I am sorry that this debate did not last a little longer now that it has lasted so long because as we were going ahead, the important points were beginning to emerge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As has been pointed out, it is the public character of this matter that concerns me immediately.  I, and members of the Government, got this letter containing certain allegations. Why was it sent to me?  Why was it sent to members of the Government? Clearly, because it concerned a person who was engaged in the Administration. He was a person of public importance, and when I got it my first concern naturally was the integrity of public life&mdash;so that there might be full confidence in it.  I, therefore, had to approach it, in the first instance, from that point of view.  Other aspects of it, what you might call the personal <Col N="1977" /> and private aspects of it from the point of view of allegations of a criminal character, were all present to my mind, too.  But if anybody pursues any of the other lines of conduct, they will see at once that these lines were not open to me.</P>
    <P>There has been talk here about ousting the courts.  The courts are not ousted; the ordinary courts are not ousted.  These will come into play and the nearest approach there has been to what is going to happen is that instead of having a small court in the first instance, a fact-finding court, we are going to have a court of a very high character.  The first thing that would be wrong would be that the public should get any impression here that the ordinary courts are being ousted.  They are not.  They are not going to be the first resorted to.  There is going to be a court of first instance as was suggested, I think, by Senator Hayes.</P>
    <P>Why is it that we are adopting this course?  The reason why we do that is this: if there were to be proceedings by way of libel action by Dr. Ward against Dr. MacCarvill, we would have a number of things coming out&mdash;side issues&mdash;which might be reflecting upon the character of the Parliamentary Secretary as a public man. Was he to continue in office while that was happening, or was I, on the other hand, to say to him: &ldquo;You had better resign&rdquo;?  If I were to do that, would he not be able to say to me: &ldquo;Any resignation on my part would be an indication that I accept these things as true.  These will have to be examined home, each one of them in particular; all these things coming out as side issues in this particular case, will all have to be examined before you can reasonably and justly suggest that I should resign.&rdquo;  Now, that would be the case if we were to have proceedings by way of libel action first.</P>
    <P>It is suggested by Senator Keane, and by somebody else, I think, that there is some sort of shielding in this thing, in not proceeding by way of criminal action, and handing the whole matter over to the Attorney-General. Suppose that was done and, as a result of it there was a finding that Dr. Ward <Col N="1978" /> was not guilty, then it would be suggested that because he was in the Administration there was some interference with the ordinary procedure.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir John Keane Sir John Keane">
      <NameTxt>Sir John Keane</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, no.  Does the Taoiseach say&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I say, definitely, that it would, knowing enough, as I do, about all the rumours and suggestions that are made.  I say that and I believe that would be said.  It would be said that either the Attorney-General or the Gárda did not proceed against a person who was in an administrative position with the same determination they would have used in proceeding against a person who was an ordinary citizen. And we must remember that he is not an ordinary citizen as long as he remains a Parliamentary Secretary. There is no use in pretending that he is.  If he has to be proceeded against as an ordinary citizen and the proceedings are to have the full confidence of the people, then he cannot remain as Parliamentary Secretary, and if criminal proceedings were to be taken against him at the same time it would be necessary for him to resign his position.</P>
      <P>Am I then to ask him to resign?  If I ask him to resign, I am in the position that he could say to me: &ldquo;It is not just.  I must be in a position of innocence until I am proved guilty.&rdquo; Surely anyone put in my position, in the Government's position, will say: &ldquo;The other two courses are not open to you.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I quite admit that people want to look into it and examine it from the point of view of the integrity of public life and they can easily be influenced by promptings and suggestions that some special privilege is being given Dr. Ward, because he is a Parliamentary Secretary, that there is going to be one law for the rich and another law for the poor, as Senator Sir John Keane suggested would be said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In other countries that Senator Keane knows, this procedure is often adopted where there are charges against people in administrative positions.  It is not an unusual thing.  That question was raised in the Dáil to-day&mdash;I do not know if it is proper to refer to what was <Col N="1979" /> said in the other House&mdash;this question of the prejudice there would be against Dr. Ward in this matter and that if a libel action came after this a jury might be influenced by it.</P>
    <P>Those who think that this is an unfair mode of procedure against Dr. Ward have one set of objections and those who think it would be too fair to him have another set.  I am attacked from both sides.  I knew that no matter what course I took, I would be attacked by some people; but I have to put up with that.  All I know is that this course has been suggested by me, after full deliberation and with full advertence to the various aspects of it that have come up for consideration in the Dáil to-day and in the Seanad now. The more I have listened to the arguments against it, the more I am convinced that I am taking the only course appropriate in the circumstances.</P>
    <P>There is no overriding of the ordinary courts, which will have full opportunity to consider this, once this tribunal has brought in its findings.  I will then be in the position, in regard to the public life of the country, that I will know whether there is to be a criminal action, in which case I could, for example, ask Dr. Ward to resign, without any compunction.  On the other hand, if there is to be no such action, then there will be no such question in my mind of any difficulty as far as that is concerned.  I would have resolved my difficulty, which is to know what the Government's attitude should be. It is the Government that is responsible, as the Parliamentary Secretary is appointed by the Government, on the nomination of the Taoiseach.  I have full confidence, unless and until something is proved to the contrary, that these charges are not true.  That must be my approach.  If the investigation should show that I am wrong, I will be able to take action.</P>
    <P>I do not think that the Seanad here ought to feel itself coerced by the fact that a decision has been taken in the other House.  The two Houses must concur before the tribunal can be set up.  It is true that the person concerned is a member of the other House and <Col N="1980" /> that the Government is responsible from day to day to that House.  That gives special importance to it, and no doubt it will be kept in the minds of Senators in deciding this matter. However, the Seanad has its own independent responsibility and I do not want it to attempt to shirk that responsibility by saying: &ldquo;The other House has decided and there is no use in our making up our minds on it at all.&rdquo;  Believing that this is the right course, I appeal to the Seanad to pass this Resolution, but I ask them to do it on their own independent and individual judgement, so that we will feel that this tribunal is being set up not by one House but by both.</P>
    <P>This procedure is done under an Act of Parliament.  I am very grateful to Senator Ryan for doing something which, perhaps, I should have done myself in introducing this particular matter.  Perhaps I assumed too much. I assumed that this procedure was known, on account of the fact that it has been used not once but a number of times.  It is an Act of Parliament designed to set up tribunals for investigations of this sort.  As someone has suggested, there is a medley of charges involved in this and they were intertangled in such a way that if you proceed in one way or the other you have charges of a particular kind coming out as a side wind, instead of being directed definitely to the points at issue.  These judges are investigators and I do not agree with those who say that judges are not fit and proper persons, or at least that they are not particularly fitted for investigations. They may not be fitted for certain types of investigation, but for the evaluation of evidence, to decide whether certain statements represent real facts based on sound evidence, surely you could not get any people with as much experience and training as judges have?  Surely they have experience enough to know whether a particular piece of investigation should be carried on in order to bring out a certain fact?</P>
    <P>I was asked about the Attorney-General. I think I said already that what was done in a previous case was that the Attorney-General sent counsel <Col N="1981" /> to the tribunal to inform the tribunal that the Attorney-General was prepared to give any assistance in his power, that he was at their disposal. I know the difficulty of any ordinary person, whether a Deputy or a Senator, in making up his mind on this particular matter.  I fully appreciate the difficulties Senators may have in trying to make up their own minds.  I had all those difficulties myself for a rather lengthy and rather anxious time.  It was with the full knowledge that the various aspects of this matter had a right to consideration that I decided upon this particular method.  I think it will be satisfactory and will be more speedy than waiting for some time to have a libel action come before the courts in the ordinary way.  Some steps would have to be taken to try to bring such an action forward.  I do not know the procedure followed in the law courts to determine what pushes forward a case, but I know that cases may be a very long time pending.  We cannot afford to have this question in suspense for a long period.</P>
    <P>I pointed out the difficulty of proceeding by way of handing the papers over to the Attorney-General.  It is only right that Senators should know that he is not the initiator in proceedings like that.  What happens is that the particular Department, the Gárda or someone else, takes the initiative. The papers come to the Attorney-General's Office from an initiating department and he decides whether or not a prosecution should ensue.  He himself does not initiate the investigation. That is done by the inspectors of the Department, and so on.</P>
    <P>Perhaps I should also say that, in the case of the Revenue Commissioners, I am not an expert, but I do not think that they bring criminal proceedings in ordinary cases.  They put on a new assessment, if information comes to them about income-tax not being paid.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right, but not if there was falsification of accounts, which would be very different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to confess that I am one less knowledgable on these things.  But, at any rate, in this case, I do not know what would be the <Col N="1982" /> procedure of the Revenue Commissioners, and, naturally, we are not going to interfere with them in any way in the exercise of their functions, but, again, I suggest that it would be doubtful if the Minister for Agriculture or the Minister for Finance were concerned that they would not be represented.  The Minister for Finance would be represented by the Revenue Commissioners, who would act for him if he took action against any person. In this case a particular man was occupying a position as administrator. That is the difficulty I would like to press home to those people who think we should let the ordinary law take its course.</P>
      <P>I do hope I have convinced Senators. Perhaps some of them may not agree with me and will regard this as an exceptional and strange procedure.  I want to point out in the circumstances it is not.  My own belief is that it is the most appropriate, or as I stated earlier, the least unsatisfactory.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is now ten minutes to ten.  I presume the Seanad will now adjourn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the Tourist Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>At this hour?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree that it is not worth taking now but the House made a decision that it should be taken immediately this motion was disposed of and it is not yet agreed that it should not be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The House agreed the debate should be adjourned till later to-day.  If the House wishes to resume it now, the Chair has no objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="Liam Ó Buachalla Liam Ó Buachalla">
      <NameTxt>Liam Ó Buachalla</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose that the House adjourn until 3 o'clock tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisODea" hpid="Mr. O'Dea Mr. O'Dea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dea</NameTxt>
      <P>I second, if necessary. Motion put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 9.50 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Thursday, June 6th, 1946.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>