<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="21" Month="May" Year="1975" Vol="81" No="2" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 21 Bealtaine 1975" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 21 May 1975" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="103">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="103" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take No. 1 only today.  We are in a little bit of difficulty as regards sittings for the remainder of the week. There is a Social Welfare (Pay-Related Benefit) Bill in the Dáil.  We had hoped it would come here tomorrow to be taken by us.  If that does not happen, it looks as though we must sit on Friday and we will not be sitting tomorrow.  I understand it might be possible by co-operation on both sides in the other House to arrange that the Bill might come to us tomorrow.  I am simply mentioning that in general terms.  If my friends opposite like to interpret it as an invitation to do what they can to get it for tomorrow's business we would be very glad.  As things stand at the moment, we will not be sitting tomorrow but will be sitting on Friday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I object to this.  I will endeavour to help decisions taken in the Dáil today.  I can only speak to my Whip about that and see if he would agree to take this business today. Maybe it is not possible.  Their programme is already drawn up.  If it is not taken today, it will not be taken in the Dáil until late tomorrow.  That means we will not have it until Friday. It is most unfair to expect country Senators to wait here, or to go home, if they like, and come back again on Friday.  In the other House they know every Saturday how many days and the hours they will sit the next week. We never know.  I am not blaming the Leader of the House or Senator <Col N="104" /> Sanfey for this.  It is not their fault; it is the fault of the people in the other House.</P>
      <P>It has been said today that it is our fault this time, because our people held up the Bill in the other House, a Bill which should be with us tonight at 7.30.  That may be so, but I cannot see the urgency to sit on Friday.  We could take that Bill on Tuesday or Wednesday next week.  I would imagine it would be completed in this House within a few hours.  When I mentioned that I was told this would not suit the Parliamentary Secretary, because he would be available only on Friday.  It looks as if 60 people here have to accommodate one man.  That is most unfair.  I, for one, object to sitting on Friday of this week.  Firstly, we were not informed of this in time, and, secondly, it is not that urgent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>There is not before the House a proposal to sit on Friday.  I was merely mentioning that as a matter of courtesy and in the hope that it might be possible to get co-operation.  I am not making any proposal at this stage.  That will come later today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>What time on Friday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>10.30 a.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>We on this side of the House are limited in number.  Many of us are committed to Friday's work at home as members of other bodies. We have no objection to sitting on Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, that is, three days every week for as many weeks as the House needs us. But sitting on Friday is a completely new situation.  Fianna Fáil Senators especially will find it practically impossible to meet on Friday because we are already committed to doing work at home.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>All bodies are important bodies and this body is as important as others but, as I have already intimated, we do not feel the pressures so much if we sit on Tuesdays, Wednesdays and Thursdays.  Today we will probably finish one Bill and we have to linger around the city all day Thursday <Col N="105" /> doing private work and then sit here on Friday at 10.30.  That is not fair to Senators.  We may have been accused of not doing enough in the past but we have certainly been working very hard for the last five or six weeks.  The extra sitting on Friday is not necessary.</P>
    <P>The Leader of the House mentioned that he was seeking co-operation. I do not think there is co-operation on either side of the House to work in the Seanad on a Friday.  I suggest we sit on Tuesday to take this Bill, if it is co-operation the Leader of the House wants.</P>
    <P>If we want to occupy the time of this House tomorrow&mdash;as it is the intention to sit on Friday&mdash;we might take motion No. 34 which deals with the White Paper on the National Agricultural Advisory, Education and Research Authority.  This document, which was circulated last week and is being discussed throughout the country, should be discussed in this House, too.  Perhaps the Leader of the House could arrange it for tomorrow? I would like an assurance that no further steps will be taken until such time as it is discussed in this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that the Leader of the House is being courteous at this stage in indicating that the House may sit on Friday, and not tomorrow.  In return, perhaps we should be courteous to him.  If the House is not sitting tomorrow but Friday, I will go home this evening and return Friday morning.  I will be quite content to sit here Friday, Saturday and Sunday and I would suggest to the Leader of the House that perhaps he should make arrangements along those lines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator suggest I book accommodation for him?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I have nothing to add to what I said.  I am not suggesting that there has been any degree of lack of co-operation from Senator W. Ryan or his colleagues as regards <Col N="106" /> business here.  I do not know sufficient about the business arrangements in the other House to be dogmatic about it.  My only suggestion was that, as far as I know, with co-operation on both sides in the other House it would be possible to have the Social Welfare Bill with us tomorrow.  I was merely throwing out the hint to those on the far side who would have greater influence with the Opposition in the Dáil than I.  If they can use their influence it might assist us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>When will we know if we are sitting on Friday?  If this is to be decided at 10 o'clock tonight when the Wildlife Bill is concluded here, some people might not be here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>We will take a decision when we finish today's business. If we have a firm intimation earlier, naturally we will let Senator W. Ryan know.  If we get the Social Welfare Bill from the Dáil today we will sit tomorrow.  If we do not, we will sit on Friday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>This is typical Government policy, living today and not thinking of tomorrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Leader of the House took into account what I have said.  Many of us have commitments on Friday.  It is not fair to expect us to go home and come back up on Friday morning.  Could we not leave the Bill over until Tuesday, and do our three-day stint next week? This is very unfair and ridiculous, to say the least of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Killilea will appreciate that it is not so long since we were told that we were ridiculous because we were not sitting more often.  Now we are told we are ridiculous because we are sitting too much.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair cannot allow this to develop into a debate, particularly a disorderly debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="107" />
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to know if the Leader of the House could facilitate us by saying that, if we cannot get the Social Welfare Bill tomorrow, we will have it on Tuesday.  That is all we ask.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That matter would be more appropriately discussed outside the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>He should bear in mind that it is not just Fianna Fáil Senators he would be facilitating; the vast majority of the people sitting behind him in their hearts agree with us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I am conscious of the fact that it does not facilitate me to sit on Friday, but we have to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the urgency? Do we have to take the Bill on Friday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHalligan" hpid="Mr. Halligan Mr. Halligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Halligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators should address their remarks to their own party in the other House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The proposal is &ldquo;That the Order of Business&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is endeavouring to put a question to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Halligan would agree that everything he does is perfect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHalligan" hpid="Mr. Halligan Mr. Halligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Halligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Stop trying to block business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>And let you off the hook.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senators do not respect one another, they should respect the Chair who is endeavouring to put the question.</P>
      <P>Order of business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Wildlife Bill, 1975:" RHead="Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Wildlife Bill, 1975: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="108" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Last night I had commented upon the context in which this legislation had to be considered and, indeed, welcomed.  I spoke yesterday of the delicate balance that regulates life in our species world, in our environment, and of our imposition of crude practices on that relationship, the devastation brought about by the subjugation of social values to an economic system primed by a seemingly infinite greed.  I asserted too that the environmental crisis was not a simple creation of technology but rather the consequence of the use of technology in a particular way, in a way that is historically specific.  What I said last night is better summarised in a Newsletter distributed on 6th June, 1972, by the International Fellowship of Reconciliation.  This is what that document said:</P>
      <P>Human beings live as a part of a complex natural system with aspects of interdependence which have only recently become dramatically evident.  They are also a part of complex social, economic and political systems which they themselves have created, usually without an appreciation of the unpredictable and sometimes disastrous effects of such systems on the life-giving capabilities of nature.  These systems contain such faults and imbalances that they do not respond equally to the needs of all people, but provide a minority with a surfeit of goods, while leaving the greater part of the world's people in poverty and despair.</P>
      <P>Later in that document reference was made to the atmosphere in which legislation on the environment and on wildlife must be considered.  The same document had this to say:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The interaction between the social and natural systems on this planet has in our time resulted in an environmental crisis which although it has been produced largely by the economic practices of the industrial nations, affects every person on earth.  The awareness of the environmental crisis has come upon us suddenly and it has come at <Col N="109" /> a time when the deprived nations and the poor and the deprived people in all nations are struggling for power to control their own destinies and asserting their right to full participation in national and world affairs.</P>
    <P>It is imperative for the well-being and even the survival of humanity that the condition of the natural environment and the needs of human beings be considered as interrelated parts of the same problem. This will require the introduction of profound changes into both our political, economic and social structures and our individual lifestyles, with the aim not only one of survival, but of survival with maximum possibility of human fulfilment.</P>
    <P>Those two quotations summarise what I had to say last night.  Those principles were adverted to in the Minister's opening speech to a lesser extent. The foundation which distributed that newsletter suggested a number of principles which, they suggested, essentially precede adequate legislation on the environment and in the area of wildlife.  These principles, at least five of them are relevant, are contained in the same Newsletter of 6th June, 1972. I quote:</P>
    <P>Human beings inhabit the earth but not they alone.  Human survival depends upon the life activities of uncounted thousands of species of plants, animals and micro-organisms, and upon intricate physical and chemical reactions in the atmosphere, oceans, fresh water, and on the land.</P>
    <P>They go on to comment on the vastness and complexity of this interdependence. The first principle is that human beings inhabit the earth but not they alone and human survival depends, again as I mentioned in my opening remarks, on the delicate balance between different forms of life.</P>
    <P>The second principle is important.  I do not expect people to agree with me about this because they have not agreed when I mentioned it before. The Newsletter continued:</P>
    <P>There is a fundamental conflict between traditional concepts of <Col N="110" /> economic growth and the preservation of the environment.  During the last century, uncontrolled continuous industrial growth and the production of environmentally harmful substances and products in some regions of the world, has produced dangerous amounts of pollution and has been responsible for an inordinate waste of resources.</P>
    <P>The third principle was to some extent adverted to in the Minister's opening speech.  I noticed he sought to put a restraint on indiscriminate road building.  That is a correct emphasis. Also in his speech he asks the farming community for their co-operation in introducing these measures.  My view on this is that he should have asked for not only the co-operation of the farming community, but for the co-operation of the Industrial Development Authority, because it should be a requirement of all new industrialisation projects that they assure us they will have no harmful effects on wildlife and on the environment.  The Minister, of course, could add the Industrial Development Authority when he comes to develop that section.  As I said last evening, the Minister is a most sensitive man and has presented this Bill in a sensitive way.</P>
    <P>I doubt if the Minister will have much control over the exploitation of national and regional resources by foreign corporations with a consequent outflow of profits from the exploited regions which has in other areas resulted in a vast and growing economic disparity among nations and a monopoly of industrialised countries over production, energy, technology, information and political power.  Complementary to this is the flooding of developing countries with surplus goods and capital, with the resultant distortion of their economies and the deformation of their environments into monocultures in the interests of further enriching the industrial states.</P>
    <P>It is this kind of interference with the environment over which we have such little control and we should seek to have control in this area.  I referred last night to the crude, bullying tactics of the oil barons when they suggest&mdash;&ldquo;Let us get the oil and gas out as fast <Col N="111" /> as we can, under any conditions.&rdquo;  It is to control the activity of these companies that we will have to devise new legislation.  We are in difficulty here because at the present time the political checks on multi-national corporations in industrialisation projects, the ability to exact from them care for the environment, care for wildlife, has not been successful.</P>
    <P>There is a fifth point which we will have to realise.  I want, by the way, to assure everybody that I am not some kind of neo-Luddite.  I am not against machines and technology.  Economic development of any kind will require technology.  But, some products proliferated by conventional technology have been extremely harmful ecologically. I am not rejecting technology <i>per se,</i> but I am suggesting that it must be restructured and reoriented.</P>
    <P>It is a principle that in the future the culture of any industrial nation will reflect its ideology.  We will need a technology which will stress the solution of humanity's problems rather than the exploitation of humanity's apparently endless greed as a basic principle, or starting point for legislation.</P>
    <P>The Minister's speech is a reflection of a very late response in the world generally to the problems with which we find ourselves environmentally. The January, 1972, issue of <i>The Ecologist,</i> volume 2, No. 1, published their commentary entitled &ldquo;Blueprint for Survival&rdquo;.  A number of eminent scholars put their names to that document, among them economists, suggesting that scholarships could no longer be value free, that it was a time for scientists in the human sciences and in the physical sciences to take a stand on the side of or against life.  I quote one paragraph from that document:</P>
    <P>The principal defect of the industrial way of life with its ethos of expansion is that it is not sustainable. Its termination within the lifetime of someone born today is inevitable&mdash;unless it continues to be sustained for a while longer by an entrenched minority at the cost of <Col N="112" /> imposing great suffering on the rest of mankind.  We can be certain, however, that sooner or later it will end (only the precise time and circumstances are in doubt), and that it will do so in one of two ways: either against our will, in a succession of famines, epidemics, social crises and wars; or because we want it to&mdash;because we wish to create a society which will not impose hardship and cruelty upon our children &mdash;in a succession of thoughtful, humane and measured changes.</P>
    <P>They, like the Minister in his opening speech, made an optimistic observation that it was not too late to change. I said last night that I was not so convinced of this, and that I was probably more pessimistic.  One of the reasons for that pessimism is that I am aware not only of the present consequences of economic activity, which I have so consistently attacked recently, but also of past and future developments.  I also referred last night to the forced human migrations from areas and the threat in the future from the unthoughtful development of the oil and gas resources.</P>
    <P>Senators will remember my reference to the scholar who wrote about the experience of Scotland.  When I complimented the Minister on his emphasis on the necessity of creating adequate wildlife values, I referred to the tragic division of the classroom from life which had become in modern times the necessary accompaniment to the economics of elite greed.  I referred too to the technologically contradictory nature of our actions, as evidenced in the destructure of nature, by for example, trees being destroyed and, at the same time, the replacement of the birds who lived in those trees by inefficient garbage collection innovations.  I referred too to the presence of wildlife species in the art forms of different civilisations, and indeed of our own civilisation in a different period.  I now summarise all of this in a sentence.  What I have been speaking about so far in this debate has been the destruction of the quality of wonderment.  I repeat that phrase&mdash;the quality of wonderment <Col N="113" />&mdash;and that is what this Bill is, but a very small beginning towards possibly restoring, or even recreating the possibility of it being restored, in a future generation.</P>
    <P>I am grateful to so many Senators who have shown an interest in this Bill, particularly when someone like myself who cannot guarantee that he will sit down in two minutes is speaking. When I use the phrase the destruction of the quality of wonderment, I would ask the Senators to bear this in mind.  Create the image in your own minds of the manner in which a child will marvel at the magnificent subtlety of life.  If one has seen a child hold a little animal or plant in its hand, one will be immediately struck by the magnificent wonderment of the child, the appreciation of the magnificence of life.  This child is condemned in our society to become the educated adult who must destroy life.  That is part of our contribution to civilisation.</P>
    <P>Not in anger but with a certain amount of sadness I referred yesterday to the reports of the <i>Roscommon Herald</i> of 13th August, 1971, when 1,574 birds and animals were reported as having been killed.  I refrained from naming the chairman of the organisation responsible.  I said then I was not angry with these people but, as I explained at length last night, it was the reaction I feared.  I hope that the Minister's careful introduction of this Bill will help in some small way to change the attitudes which generated that awful assault on nature, for example, the belief that all the varieties of life need to be destroyed&mdash;this includes cranes, foxes, badgers and so forth&mdash;in order to sustain economic existence.  The chairman of the gun club in question suggested that two farmers had been socially irresponsible because they had not allowed this savagery to take place.  I must insist, however, that it is only when clear social objectives and their political expression take precedence over consumer activity that the saving of the environment may be available to usher in a new and more dignified way of life.</P>
    <P>I would like to refer in more detail to parts of the Bill.  I agree with what Senator Horgan has said.  I would have <Col N="114" /> liked this legislation to have contained measures for the control of our lakes and fish.  I think they might have appropriately come within the responsibility of the Minister.  I feel that the Minister could sort out the complex legal questions.  For example&mdash;I will refer to it when I go through the text of the Bill&mdash;he has sorted out the question of acquiring commonages for the development of afforestation. Everybody knows that there are difficult legal questions involved in the taking over of fish life.  For example, a salmon on its way to the sea becomes the property of nearly 1,000 people as it passes through a river flowing through people's land.  There is a legal problem involved but not an insuperable one.  What I would have regarded previously as an insuperable legal problem has been solved in this Bill with regard to certain kinds of land.  I feel that the Minister should have moved towards establishing that the richness of our lakes and rivers is the property of the community.</P>
    <P>I would like to pay tribute to the people who work in the Wildlife Section of the Forestry Division and so forth.  The public in general have got tremendous benefits from the openup of the forests for recreational use. This model of the community restoring itself by having access to the natural resources is an appropriate one for rivers and lakes.  We need legislation in this area too.  We also need it for wildlife for many other reasons.  When the most successful person is exercising greed, and in the private enterprise economy that is a requirement to be a success, he cannot be trusted to use resources in the interests of the community. It would be inconceivable to expect him to do so.  Why should we expect it in the case of rivers and lakes?  It is our duty to defend our resources.</P>
    <P>Information kindly made available to me by the Salmon and Trout Conservation Council of Ireland some years ago suggested that salmon and trout are in trouble.  We all know why they are in trouble&mdash;because people have regarded fish as something that is economic, an object for making profits. We know, too, that in fisheries people <Col N="115" /> have made small fortunes.  This should of course be one of the life assets of the nation.  I look forward to legislation in this area soon to stop all this absurdity.  Nets and weirs killed 255,406 pounds of salmon.  When a salmon is expressed in pounds, society has reached another level of development and purpose.  I wish legislation in this area had been included in the Bill.</P>
    <P>I want to extend to the Senators and the Parliamentary Secretary the courtesy of some details as to what the Minister has proposed.  Senator Horgan last night referred to Humanity Dick Martin, a most interesting man who was born in and lived in Galway.  He was referring to his work in initiating legislation to prevent the infliction of cruelty on domesticated animals.  What Senator Horgan forgot, of course, was the interesting philosophical significance of Humanity Dick's success.  There are many lawyers in this House.  Part of my education has been to listen to them, and I have learned a great deal from them.  What strikes me is how good they are at law and how reluctant or shy they are on principles of jurisprudence. I wished that they would discuss with me the social context in which legislative instruments emerge. Why did Humanity Dick succeed in preventing cruelty to domesticated animals?  Yet in 1975 we are protecting deer that run free, that are rare, for the first time by the legislation before us.  We legislated so that we could not be cruel in private but we could be indiscriminately cruel in public.</P>
    <P>The truth is that laws at that time were reflecting the privatisation of experience; the idea that the outside world, the great economic and social forces that affected mankind, were outside our control.  Drama reflects the same thing.  Passion and emotion become a matter of tension between characters in a drawingroom rather than being played out against a wider background.  Similarly, as the scenes of the drama withdrew to the sitting room, the lawyers withdrew their legislative intent indoors as well.  A <Col N="116" /> 100 years afterwards they have gone out for a walk again.  Seeing that they have all taken the air and searched with such wonderful benefit, I suppose that these small measures are a beginning.</P>
    <P>I do not want to appear not to appreciate the great amount of good that is in this Bill.  I would like my remarks of last night, complimenting those involved in developing our forests as a great amenity, to be noted. I will come to compliment the draftsman of this Bill for solving this problem of commonages which I know of because of my own proximity to Connemara.  That is the way the legal advisers to an imaginative Department should always work.  It should not be the exception.  It should be a regular procedure.</P>
    <P>I should like to make a comment on the use of an interesting term in the Minister's speech and that is the term &ldquo;habitat&rdquo;.  I will examine it more closely when I comment on Senator Cowen's contribution on the activities of the Irish Coursing Club. We all know what happens to hares; even the coursing club admits that.  I shall be providing some scientific evidence about what happens to hares when they are removed from their habitat.  Not only are they removed but they are brought to a certain stage of feeding.  Even if they survive this cruel kind of activity, coursing, they are then supposed to be released and are expected to return to their habitat.</P>
    <P>Parliamentarians will be glad to know that Winston Churchill used this phrase about Parliamentarians themselves in 1943 when they were discussing the architecture which was best suited for the new chambers of the House of Commons in England.  I am quoting from <i>The Ecologist</i> of October, 1970.</P>
    <P>The old building had been badly damaged by German bombardment and was uncomfortable and impractical.</P>
    <P>
      <i>The Ecologist</i> refrains from saying &ldquo;irrelevant.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Yet Mr. Churchill urged that it be rebuilt exactly as it was before <Col N="117" /> the war instead of being replaced by one equipped for greater comfort and with better means of communication. He argued that the style of parliamentary debates in England had been conditioned by the physical characteristics of the old House and that changing its architecture would affect not only the manner of debates but also as a result the structure of English democracy.  In his words, we shape our buildings and afterwards our buildings shape us.</P>
    <P>I have been thinking about Churchill's remarks a great deal recently, as I have seen the buildings that have appeared in recent times and examined the contributions of the people who happen to live and supposedly work in them, legal and illegal.</P>
    <P>The Minister in his speech stressed Part II which, he suggests, will contain the power in relation to wildlife in the future.  I welcome most of the sections.  I shall dwell a little on section 23 which deals with practices which another parliamentarian, whom I do not admire very much, referred to on another occasion as degrading anachronism. I am referring to coursing.  In section 11 the Minister has rightly stressed the importance of being able to give assistance and aid development to different schemes in connection with wildlife.  There is something that bothers me in that section and that is whether the necessity for research is sufficiently adverted to.  We know so little about so many of the species for which we are expected to legislate. Section 11 (1) says:</P>
    <P>It shall be a function of the Minister to secure the conservation of wildlife.</P>
    <P>Even though we might have a public awareness of our attitude of destruction it is doubtful whether we have a sufficient number of experts to enable the Minister to do that adequately.  I am glad that the Minister noted in section 15 the importance of the North Slob in Wexford, and the way in which he adverted generally to the importance of nature reserves.  We all know of the importance of the North Slob particularly for migratory birds from Greenland. Part of our obligation becomes <Col N="118" /> clear to us here.  Positioned as we are, we have an international responsibility. In fairness, we have shown ourselves to be more sensitive in areas of ornithological interest than in any other areas, and the contrast is to our shame that our laws should be so disgraceful in relation to the animals that are running free.</P>
    <P>Section 17 refers to the wildlife habitat of animals and the importance of their being protected.  Later on I will ask the Minister to accept some amendment to the use of the word &ldquo;habitat&rdquo; and probably to extend some sections where the destruction of the habitat of wildlife is not protected in the Bill.  By that I mean the rooting of wildlife out of its natural lair.</P>
    <P>Section 21 deals with the protection of flora.  As pointed out by Senator Alexis FitzGerald, the protection of flora has received a relatively small mention in the Bill.  I am reminded in that section of the tremendous value that attaches to areas of North Clare.  It is appalling the manner in which insensitive people&mdash;who could blame them, removed from the experience of regular exposure to nature &mdash;decided to practically destroy very important areas in that part of Clare. That kind of protection, of course, will not come in a Bill.  It will come only in a society through education to believe generously in life.</P>
    <P>Section 25 is a historic one.  Here the dear little emerald isle enters the modern world to protect deer.</P>
    <P>I am anxious to come to section 26. I ask the Minister to consider the deletion of this section altogether from the Bill.  It refers to hunting. Last night I reminded the Seanad of the omissions from Somerville and Ross's accounts of <i>The Experiences of an Irish R.M.</i>&mdash;lawyers defending law sporadically, hunting most of the time, and generally entertaining themselves, never killing anything.</P>
    <P>I suggest that the idea in modern times of a defenceless animal, the fox, being chased by a pack of hounds, followed by a group of people mounted on horseback, is ludicrous. If I may digress for a moment, it can be <Col N="119" /> extremely difficult I am told on occasions to distinguish the sound of the hounds from the sound of the people on horseback.  Something which always puzzled me as a child why should such a traditional activity be so highly disorganised.  I think it is because of the variation in the sounds emitting from such people that they take off in different directions.  While we should show tolerance towards such people and realise that they may need to get out in the air regularly&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;The unspeakable in pursuit of the uneatable&rdquo;.  The Senator remembers Oscar Wilde.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to Dr. Browne for reminding me of Wilde's remark.  He described it well &ldquo;the unspeakable in pursuit of the uneatable&rdquo;. I ask the Minister not to feel that he has to make any concession to the hunting lobby.  The hunt is an extremely interesting phenomenon as it is dealt with in literature.  As someone who is interested in social history, I have found it one of the sad experiences of a socially aspiring peasant society that part of one's social advancement was getting up on a horse.  One really had made it if one got to ride to the hunt.  I remember too an occasional curate joining the ranks indicating the liberalisation that was to follow as Popes came and went.  I ask the Minister to make no concession to the group of people involved and to delete that section and terminate the issue of hunting licences.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A number of people have suggested that the elimination of the fox is an advantage to the farmer.  The only research carried out on this subject is that done by Dr. J.S. Fairley, when he was at Queen's University, Belfast. From examining the eating habits of a number of foxes he calculates that only a tiny number of foxes kill animals. The majority of foxes eat the afterbirths of ewes and minor harmful forms of life on farms.  This is not widely known.  It is unfortunate that Dr. Fairley's research is not adverted to by a wider audience, and the great excesses which I described as taking place <Col N="120" /> in Roscommon might not have occurred.</P>
    <P>I appeal to the Minister to delete the granting of licences for hunting and on Committee Stage I shall put down an amendment to section 26.  A changed use of the concept of habitat could be inserted here.  I would ask the Minister to consider rather than licensing hunts to make it an offence to dig for foxes&mdash;they are not a protected animal&mdash;in any earth or habitat either temporary or permanent with any implement or tool to drive the animal from that earth or habitat for the purpose of a hunt.  I hope I shall be of some assistance to the Minister when that Stage is reached.</P>
    <P>In section 26 (5) there is a reference to hunting licences for badgers and otters.  Hunting these animals should be terminated.  I appeal to Senators to be sensible in this regard.  Legislation in other countries has a respect for animal life.  I ask the Minister to make it an offence to interfere with the habitat, either temporary or permanent, of these forms of life for the purpose of driving them from their habitat.</P>
    <P>I overlooked the section for which I have the greatest abhorrence, that is, section 23, which allows coursing. Would the Minister reconsider the concession he has made here?  Coursing has been referred to as part of the Irish way of life.  Senator Horgan put it into a broader context.  He spoke about coursing in the general context of the relationship between man the hunter and the caged animal released for pursuit.</P>
    <P>I do not want to enter into the controversy concerning the quality of evidence, but the Irish Coursing Club's own members have admitted that the conditions in which coursing takes place are appalling.  They have admitted that the hare population is in danger of extinction.  They have refused to allow systematic evidence to be collected at their meets.  They have not yielded, to my knowledge, to any pressure from Bord na gCon. I am not so sure that any pressure came from that source.  I would willingly be enlightened on that matter. They have admitted that they are unable <Col N="121" /> to control the conditions in which coursing takes place.</P>
    <P>I want to balance a proposition against the suggestion that coursing is part of the Irish tradition.  The proposition is that if you have a species of life which is becoming rarer then it is our duty as legislators to preserve life rather than the dangerous habit or practice of a small group of people.  I do not wish to offend anybody, particularly those involved in the rearing of greyhounds, but contrast this principle of life with all of the conditions shown to be inoperable.  They have said they are unable to assert controlled conditions: they have said that the hare is becoming rare; they have said the cost of buying hares is too much; they have said all of these things, and yet the people who kill hares in the most horrible conditions are those who will be charged to exercise control.  One of them last night suggested that these are the most suitable people to defend the species.  That is just a simple absurdity.</P>
    <P>If the Minister will not delete section 23 from the Bill, if he feels he cannot do this, I ask him to accept some rewording of section 26 (3) so as to eliminate the words in brackets</P>
    <P>(being a day or days which are not specified in a hares order)</P>
    <P>which would make the Minister directly responsible for regulated coursing matches which are defined as those held in accordance with the rules of the Irish Coursing Club. Even if the Minister will not agree with the deletion of the other section, if, he will withdraw some of the powers which we know are not being put into practice by this group of people to himself.</P>
    <P>It is extremely important that the Minister under section 25 (2), if he is confident that he can ensure the sustenance of the species, will allow conditions to be inserted which will enable the number of animals killed to be published, recorded, broadcast, photographed, televised and reported. This would help a number of people. I will come to wording amendments in some of the other sections when <Col N="122" /> it is appropriate in the discussion on this Bill.</P>
    <P>When the small farmers in Roscommon decided to do what I described last night they did so because their economic future was threatened. We know the source of that threat and it was not from those forms of wildlife that they slaughtered.  Lest I be considered to be misleading people on that point I want to put on the records of the House the truth about the fox.  I have said that the only accurate information on the fox as a pest comes from the research of Dr. Fairley.  I should also like to put on the records of the House my gratitude to Dr. Fairley for supplying me with this information.  In an issue of the <i>Irish Naturalists Journal,</i> pages 215 to 219, entitled &ldquo;The Fox as a Pest in Agriculture&rdquo;, he concludes from an examination of the eating habits of foxes that it is a minority of foxes which are responsible for the killing of poultry and lambs.  He mentions the other sources of food.  The figure given from a representative sample of the destruction of farm produce is slight.</P>
    <P>Reports from Scotland and Wales are similar.  Therefore, the general manner in which the fox became the whipping boy for the farmers who lose lambs is scientifically not true. If it is not true of the fox it is even less so of the badger which is a much more slow-moving animal.  From a study of the badger's habits we know that he inflicts even less damage on farmers' property.  The otter, which I should like to see defended&mdash;and I spoke about the importance of doing this&mdash;provides a great service by eliminating a number of dangerous sources of vermin.  The badger, for example, is an extremely clean animal in his habits and the study of badgers' lairs reveals the most elaborate and intricate procedures for the disposal of waste.  They should be protected. Dr. Fairley's work is available in <i>The Irish Naturalists Journal,</i> January 1974, and in a series of issues following and preceding that date.</P>
    <P>I want to reply to another technical point which is also important in relation to coursing.  It is sometimes said that if coursing is outlawed the greybound <Col N="123" /> industry in general will be affected; that the greyhound industry, in turn, is an important source of income for people, particularly in the southern counties.  In relation to coursing and tracking, no conclusive evidence is available to suggest that coursing is necessary to produce a good tracking greyhound.  It is my habit in this House to give sources when I make statements like that.</P>
    <P>The statement that you need to sustain and allow coursing so as to defend the greyhound industry was made, for example, in <i>The Kerryman</i> of 10th January, 1975, in an article by John Barry&mdash;&ldquo;Coursing in the Future in Danger?&rdquo;  In the middle of it he mentions, among other things:</P>
    <P>Coursing cannot be allowed die. Apart from anything else it provides a means of livelihood for many people and it is also essential for track racing which as we all know is a very important industry indeed.</P>
    <P>I agree that track racing is an important element in the greyhound industry. But I turn to the statement, which has no support whatsoever, that coursing is essential for track racing.  I refer Senators to a journal aimed at people who practise these kinds of sport&mdash;to the editorial in <i>The Sporting Press,</i> of 8th September, 1966.  In that editorial discussed the hypothesis that the two are connected is examined: &ldquo;Is it necessary for the dog to kill to train?&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This is the point.  We are asked a question in that editorial because of the nature of coursing and hunting, because we are so used to the sight of animals chasing live game that it is the kill alone and not the excitement of the chase that makes them run.  In a very long editorial the editor of <i>The Sporting Press</i> suggests that in the absence of evidence that the instinct to chase may be a separate instinct altogether from the instinct to kill.  As I said, there is no evidence to suggest that the two are inextricably linked.</P>
    <P>There immediately Senator Cowen's suggestion falls down.  But even if it were true it would be objectionable, given all of the photographs we have <Col N="124" /> had, showing the conditions in which the hares are acquired.  Then in the <i>Irish Naturalists Journal</i> of January, 1974, in a footnote, Dr. Fairley gives a detailed account of the bodies of 51 hares which had been sent to him from a number of areas in the southwest. It shows that the hares had been fed additional food, they had been kept for some meeting in an enclosed paddock for some weeks.  Where is the concept of natural habitat there? They were moved from their natural habitat, fed abnormal amounts of food and then released.  Even if they succeeded&mdash;they were probably killed&mdash; in the context of 1975 are not these, to all of us, objectionable conditions? In view of all of this evidence, I must object to sections 23 and 26.</P>
    <P>I have been commenting on many sections in the Bill.  As I said, I do not want the impression to go out from my speech that I do not welcome this Bill or do not welcome the Minister's attitude to it.  I have indeed paid tribute to both.  In section 32 the Minister, I think, is referring to the necessity to have expert opinion in the case of the ringing of birds, in the possession of cannon-nets and so on.  He pointed out in his opening speech that one would need experts, but I would make this point to the Minister concerning that section.  I wholeheartedly agree with him that one does, but if one needs an expert in the ringing of wild birds why not then in section 23 which states:</P>
    <P>While constructing a road or while carrying on an archaeological operation, building operation or work of engineering construction, or while constructing or carrying on such other operation or work as may be prescribed, to kill or injure such an animal or to destroy or injure the breeding place of such an animal.</P>
    <P>If in the case of bird life why not require here a zoologist or botanist to advise on the interference with plant life and wildlife where a road may be proposed?  In other words, if you acknowledge the principle of the necessity for expertise in the one area, is it not well to acknowledge it in the other?</P>
    <P>In section 34, dealing with the use <Col N="125" /> of traps and snares, I agree with much of what the Minister is attempting.  But I wonder would it not be possible to make it an offence with severe penalty to expose for sale or invite purchase of the dreadful instruments which are described.  In Galway, for example, traps are freely available over the counter which should be available only under permit.  I should like that section amended.</P>
    <P>Section 39 refers to the burning of vegetation and the portion of the Minister's speech where he addressed his remarks to the agricultural community could be well repeated.  I have suggested including with the agricultural community in another context sections of industry, particularly new industry, and the IDA in particular.  But here the practice of burning vegetation is widespread.  We all know of indiscriminate burning of bogs and the inadequate procedures to prohibit it.</P>
    <P>In the case of section 42, which deals with damage being caused by protected wild birds, I would suggest to the Minister that there is a very great deal of difficulty here in establishing proof.  I have just quoted Dr. Fairley's articles on the subject of the fox which suggest that the fox is not as irresponsible as has been represented.  It is acknowledged, as I said, that a proportion do damage.  This is borne out by others, lest people might think Dr. Fairley's research might have been selective.  Dr. Fairley is the only man who has carried out research on this subject, to my knowledge, in the North or South.</P>
    <P>I am aware also of a remarkable survey carried out by the Natural Sciences Department of Doncaster Museum which set out to study Yorkshire mammals and which showed that the fox was not always the rogue of popular imagination.  That survey was in two localities, the Spurn Peninsula and the Thorne Moors&mdash;a vast lowland of raised peat bog between Thorne and Goole and the home of a colony of foxes.  Mr. David Lane reporting in the <i>Sheffield Morning Telegraph</i> said that investigators found remains of brown rats and rabbits, both pests to farmers, as well as mice, voles, shrews and moles.  Their findings <Col N="126" /> also revealed remains of birds, beatles and eggs, barley grains and pond weed.  Given Dr. Fairley's evidence as reported in the <i>Irish Naturalists Journal,</i> which has not been contradicted, and the evidence which is available from England, where is there difficulty in establishing the truth?</P>
    <P>I want to conclude by making reference to Part IV of the Bill.  It is a credit to the Minister.  I have paid tribute to the people who worked on this section of the Bill.  On a number of occasions in both Houses the problem of dealing with, as it is referred to in section 55, land held in commonage&mdash;that is, land held by two or more persons in common and undivided shares, joint tenants and so on&mdash;has presented a number of difficulties. Here the Minister has evolved a formula which is an extremely good one.  I am glad that he and his assistants were able to succeed so well in this area.  As I said earlier in my speech, given the same difficulties as we know exist in the area of inland waterways concerning fish, I would have liked that aspect of life to be under the jurisdiction of the present Minister for Lands as well.  I could hope he would succeed in bringing in good, accurate legislation.  I have gone on a long time and I thank my fellow Senators for their indulgence in listening to what has been a very long speech.  I justify it only on the grounds that very often we discuss legislation here that either restrains, restricts and sometimes creates the conditions for the expansion of human freedom, the exercise of social experience of different kinds.  Very rarely was I presented with an opportunity of examining the relationship of our own life with the lives of the eco-system generally.  That is what we have been doing in this Bill and I want to end by paying tribute to the Minister for allowing Seanad Éireann to discuss this very important Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá áthas orm fáilte a chur roimh an mBille seo.  Is Bille anthábhachtach é agus ba mhaith an mhaise don Aire é a thúirt isteach. Tuigim go ndearna an Teachta Seán Ó Flanagáin, nuair a bhí sé ina Aire <Col N="127" /> Stáit san Roinn seo, iniúchadh agus mion-staidéar ar an mBille seo.  Rinne siad obair mhaith agus sna blianta atá rómhainn beidh muintir na hÉireann an-bhuíoch dínn.  Molaimid na daoine a rinne an iarracht seo.</P>
      <P>I was intrigued by and benefited very much from the last speaker, Senator Higgins.  He explained a tremendous amount and has obviously done great research into this whole subject.  It is good that we have people of that calibre in the Seanad who will not deal lightly with a Bill like this.</P>
      <P>This is a very important Bill and, like other Members of my party, I want to welcome it.  Before the present Minister took office a part of this Bill was already in course of preparation; the Department officials and the previous Minister had been working on it.  Between them and the present Minister they have come to the Seanad with a very comprehensive document, one that embraces an enormous amount of detail and reflects not alone weeks but years of research, and probably a great deal of interdepartmental consultation and study. The Bill is intended to repeal old statutes, some of them relating to a period that is long past.</P>
      <P>This Bill provides new means whereby the State can help and assist in the matter of natural conservation. That is a term that has been used widely, particularly since World War II.  It is true to say that in that period scientific knowledge advanced so rapidly and industrial growth has so mushroomed that people have begun to drift from the rural areas towards the larger centres of population.  Because of that many of the things that were valued in life have been endangered and it was necessary that some steps should be taken to try and protect them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As far as the history of our country is concerned it is a well-known fact that when the English were here they cut down most of our forests, the old ancient forests that had covered our country for thousands of years.  The good commercial timber was taken <Col N="128" /> away and transported overseas and our forests were left bare.  Nothing was planted in their place.  That has been adverted to very often in our Irish poetry by many Irish poets who were concerned and who lamented the clearing away of our native forests. It was only when the State was founded that people adverted to the fact that forestry was important and was good for the national economy. For that reason various Governments have pusued a policy of trying to plant much of the waste land and indeed other land in this country has also been planted.  That has helped to delay the disappearance of many species referred to in the Bill.  I am not sure of the title because I am wondering in what way one would differentiate between wildlife and vermin.  I suppose these are terms that have been examined by those who drafted the Bill and I accept them.</P>
    <P>In the past the British Government in their time assisted in the wiping out of many of our native species of animals, in particular the wolf.  They actually gave a headage grant of £5 and minted gold coins to ensure that people would be rewarded.</P>
    <P>It is true, too, that at present many committees of agriculture pay money to those people who assist in tracking down foxes.  While Senator Higgins was speaking I was thinking of that and indeed it has been widely availed of and, irrespective of what many people may say regarding the fox, it was true in the past that he was more or less a destructive animal so far as the farmer was concerned because he raided poultry houses and at that time poultry on small farms were a very important part of the economy.  We all know that the same situation does not exist now in that regard because much poultry has gone from rural Ireland and is concentrated in large henhouses. Indeed, I think that County Monaghan has practically the largest percentage of fowl in the country.  From that point of view, the fox may no now be looked upon as the great rogue that he was in the past.</P>
    <P>At the same time forestry people in the past have had traps on the plantations to catch foxes and badge <Col N="129" /> and other wild animals.  Perhaps the Department itself in the past has been helping to wipe out some of these species that we now are trying in this Bill to preserve.  I am not sure if it is still the practice of the Department to use these traps.  I know from personal observation that they have been used in the past.</P>
    <P>When new towns are built up and when new industries arrive there is great rejoicing in the beginning and very often many of these industries get grants.  Indeed, in the past grants were made without much consideration being given to the effect of pollution from such industries on fishlife in the surrounding waters and on the local animal life and on the water used by a farmer for his stock.  That has been a great problem in my own county and in the constituencies the Minister represents because we have a very large concentration of lakes. Many of our rivers and lakes have suffered from pollution during the last couple of years.  We fully realise that in some cases it was not easy for the farmer to prevent this because many of them were engaged in pig production and a great deal of slurry resulted. Some research should have been done already by the responsible Department, so as to try to solve this problem and perhaps have this slurry evaporated and made into some kind of solid.  It could be sold back to the farmer in the form of artificial manure because it has a very high fertiliser content.</P>
    <P>Many of our traditional industries, such as co-operative societies, have a great responsibility in this matter of pollution and have completely shirked it.  I have seen lakes in my county actually white because waste milk and milk products were dumped there and killed the fish.  Down along the whole River Erne thousands of fish were killed.  This can happen once or twice probably by accident but there should be more strict legislation to ensure that the deliberate pollution of rivers and lakes will not be tolerated especially by big concerns who may be free from paying income tax and who may think that they have a right to do this with little regard for the farmers <Col N="130" /> who live along the river, whose cattle drink this polluted water or for the effects on the fish in these rivers, particularly in a county such as Cavan or Monaghan where many English tourists like to fish.</P>
    <P>Very often when lakes are polluted it gives a bad name to an area, which is certainly detrimental to the economy of the people living there.  In regard to pollution arising from the disposal of waste oil, there is no law or regulation informing a garage proprietor where he may dump any waste oil products he may have.  Despite the oil scarcity there is still plenty of it available and it is very harmful to rivers.  Animal and plant is destroyed by it.  That has a bearing on what we are trying to do in this Bill.</P>
    <P>The Minister has referred to the control of firearms in regard to helping to preserve wildlife.  Certainly, something is needed in this regard.  In the past it was very often the people who had no licence at all who did the greatest harm.  In some way people are still able to get cartridges from licensed gun dealers or by some other method and they kill the pheasants in a particular area long before the date specified on the licence.  The same applies to duck and partridges, which have almost completely vanished. Anything that could be done to ensure that people would have some regard for the preservation of pheasants would be welcome.  Some of these people would like to be termed sportsmen but certainly they are not: in my part of the country they are called pot hunters, a very appropriate name for them.  The Minister would be wise to ensure that there would be tighter controls in this respect.</P>
    <P>I do not want to reflect on people who come into the country but I have known people to come up Lough Erne near where I live&mdash;it is a fairly big lake&mdash;in motor boats, armed with shotguns.  They shoot whatever they see anywhere within reach.  They have a terrifying effect on wild duck.  They do not mind what season of the year it is when they make these onslaughts. If foreigners are doing this, there should be some means of controlling them because this is wrong.  Probably <Col N="131" /> in some hotels in some parts of this country hotel proprietors take it upon themselves to advertise free shooting without consulting the owners of the land.  It is a despicable performance by people who might have little regard for natives as guests in their hotels but who like to be very generous with other people's property so far as foreigners are concerned.  I would not countenance anybody granting these people leave to trespass on land owned by somebody else for amusement. I know that they shot anything they saw, robins, crows, pheasants, wild duck, and so on.  Something should be done about this and I am glad there is some reference to it in the Bill.</P>
    <P>It is wrong at any time, in any legislation, for anybody to assume that they can trespass on other people's land. The land belongs to the farmer.  Most farmers are decent people and provided they are consulted they are prepared to be generous.  But it is a bit much to expect a farmer to see tourists or others crossing his land and indiscriminately throwing lemonade bottles and various other bottles anywhere they wish on his farm, when this may eventually lead to some of his animals being injured.  Indeed I know of one case where a man lost one of the finest bullocks on his farm because somebody had put down a rabbit trap and the animal got his tongue caught in it and subsequently died.  The person who did that did not suspect the harm which he was doing.  In matters such as this the farmers would be very co-operative if gates were closed after use and if some respect was shown for what the farmer owned.</P>
    <P>The same would apply to those people who fish and those who plough through meadows and throw bottles into the middle of a field.  These things cannot lead to good relations between tourists or fishermen and farmers. I have known many English fishermen and I found them very decent.  Very often it is not foreign people who do most harm in this respect.</P>
    <P>How the Minister will be able to enforce this legislation in regard to <Col N="132" /> firearms and control of cartridges, is a matter he will have to work out himself. In the Six Counties as far as I know nobody has a licence to do any type of shooting in pursuit of game or otherwise on a Sunday.  This is one way of conserving.  We have a five-day week now and many people have at least two days off.  That is a lot of leisure especially for people who go shooting on both days.  If they go out in large numbers they can kill a great deal of game, especially if there is no limit to the amount they can shoot.</P>
    <P>There is reference in the Bill to control of inland waters.  Could the Minister say what this entails?  Many people have been asking me what the position regarding people who travel up a river and branch into a lake.  And what rights do they have to land on the shore along the lake and to light fires and so on?</P>
    <P>There is concern in some parts of the country regarding the big stretches of water and fishing grounds that are owned by people who live outside the State.  There was a time in our history when English people came to Ireland and granted themselves large areas of land with shooting rights and other amenities for themselves and their families at the expense of the Irish people.  Eventually, when the land was bought out under the various Land Acts the tenant farmers bought back their land but very often found that they did not own anything either underneath or over it.  They just had the top of the land and the foreign owner had ruthlessly retained everything else. Consequently, there are many areas where the game on the land does not belong to the farmer and somebody from outside the State can shoot on his land.  I think that in 1975 we should be able to remedy this.  I fully appreciate that to do so would require money.  I am not saying that irrespective of how these people got the land in the past we should get them out of it.  I believe that anybody with property, especially if it has been in the family for four or five generations, irrespective of how they got it in the past, they should have a right to it now. All of us would jealosuly guard that right but the time has come when we <Col N="133" /> will have to ensure that fishing rights, which are a valuable part of economy, will be under our own control.  It is necessary as soon as possible to take the steps that will ensure this.</P>
    <P>It may be said that some of these people who come to Ireland from abroad, and are giving employment are very nice people.  I do not disagree with that.  But it is very frustrating for people in their own country to find that they have to buy a stretch of a river if they want to fish or get into the good graces of somebody before they are allowed to fish.  That is wrong and the position should have been examined long ago.</P>
    <P>I would also ask the Minister to deal with inland waters and the rights of the people who own the land around lakes.  May they have landing facilities, and for how long?  How long may they camp?  May they light fires?  There is also the matter of pollution and throwing empty bottles and cans into the water.</P>
    <P>It has been said that the Department of Lands and the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries should have been merged into one Department.  I am not saying that because the Minister for Lands happens to be from my own constituency. Irrespective of what I may say about him at home, I am certainly not going to say anything against him here.  I think he is all right and I am sure he would be able to manage any Department entrusted to him.  Somebody has suggested a new Department called the Department of the Environment. Most of its functions would relate to land and agriculture.  A solution on those lines should be sought rather than try to create another new Department which would still have to consult the Department of Lands and the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries.</P>
    <P>I am not sure how the Bill defines game.  I remember, from the old gun licence I had that a hare was game. In my county we never shoot hares. As a matter of fact it is considered very unlucky and perhaps that was the reason why hares were preserved for so long in many parts of the <Col N="134" /> country.  When I was young I remember reading in <i>Our Boys</i> about &ldquo;Kitty the Hare&rdquo;.  It brought home to me that in the South of Ireland they had more or less the same situation as in the North&mdash;they regarded the hare with some superstition, an animal to be left alone.  We have had stories of people appearing on May morning in the shape of a hare and so on.  I think that superstition was better than any law that could be enacted.</P>
    <P>As the electric light banished the fairies so too did modern thinking banish the hare.  People are not as superstitious as they used to be. People whose fathers and grandfathers would not touch a historic building or attempt to remove a fort from their land or assist their neighbour in doing so now have little regard for these traditions.  It is a pity, because I can foresee the time when with modern land reclamation schemes and so on there will be very little sanctuary for any type of bird on any type of land.</P>
    <P>I was merely posing the question to what game is and the subtle distinction between game and vermin. The whole question of preservation is tied up in the food chain.  The Creator decreed that one animal should eat another.</P>
    <P>There was an old couplet which said: &ldquo;Big fleas have little fleas upon their backs to bite' em.  And little fleas have lesser fleas and so <i>ad infinitum.</i>&rdquo; Irrespective of what we may try to do nature will take its own course.  There are ways whereby nature will try to preserve the species.</P>
    <P>Land reclamation, especially with modern techniques, is very important to the farmer.  It is very much tied in with what we are discussing because it will be necessary in future for the Minister to ensure that sanctuaries are reserved in some parts of the country so that many of the animals and birds to which we refer may be preserved.  If not, they will certainly become extinct.  At this juncture I should like to pay tribute to the game clubs that sprang up in the last ten or 15 years when people clubbed together and formed a local voluntary <Col N="135" /> organisation to attempt, without any compulsion from the State or any fear of the Garda asking them to enforce regulations, to preserve various types of game.  Such an attitude is very welcome.</P>
    <P>So far as this whole exercise is concerned, one of the most important ingredients in it is education, which should begin very early in the home. Of course, it is being provided in the national schools at present.  There is a greater attention to environmental studies and more time is allotted to them.  People are more interested. Every citizen should take a keen interest in his own locality and everything pertaining to it.  When people learn the names and habits of various animals, and birds, they are not half so anxious to have them destroyed. Years ago I read nature articles by the late Ashton Freeman.  These were very informative and created love in the individual for the animal.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to salmon and trout.  It is true that they are in trouble in many parts of the country. We had great trouble in Lough Sheelin, one of the finest fishing lakes in Ireland, because of pollution.  I am glad to say that that has passed away. There have been instances of salmon dying of some mysterious disease due to pollution or otherwise.  These will have to be investigated immediately because salmon have been in this country for a long time and are very important to the economy.  As Senator Higgins said, the salmon has to pass through many counties and countries during his life cycle.  We know from recent developments, especially in fishing in the open seas, that many people do not use any bait or nets but just suck in the fish and have them processed straight away.  Consequently, it would appear that it will not take too long to wipe out the whole species and that would have detrimental effects on our own fishing which is very important to our economy.</P>
    <P>Senator Higgins mentioned also that we had an international responsibility regarding the preservation of some animals.  I fully agree with him.  In the winter we get many birds from the <Col N="136" /> Arctic Circle, in particular the Greenland goose.  In many areas they are wide open to indiscriminate slaughter. I am glad to notice a section in the Bill referring to seasonal killing or adverse weather conditions.  When there is very heavy frost, there are large concentrations of wild duck, widgeon and various other birds which concentrate where there is a break in the ice.  The place can actually be thick with them.  In situations like that, where one shot could kill 30 or 40, it is pure slaughter.  I am glad this has been recognised.  Also, in severe storms birds cannot protect themselves and some effort should be made to protect them.</P>
    <P>On some occasions the Forestry Service let the game rights of their forests, presumably for the game season.  Forestry, in recent years, has become very important.  The Forestry Service with the consent of the Minister, have opened forest parks in this country, as in other countries, notably the Black Forest in Germany.  This is a welcome development.  It is good that people can go into these forest parks and enjoy themselves.  They can walk around and learn the names of various trees.  The important thing to remember here is that this is a State investment. There must be civic education in this matter, so that people will respect property and guard against fires.  One disastrous fire could wipe out the fruit of 20 or 30 years.  Although the majority of people realise the risks involved this is not sufficient; it is the odd individual who does the harm. Everything possible should be done at all levels, in the school and in the home, to ensure that people are warned against the dangers of forest fires.  The farmer who lives adjacent to the forest is not often responsible for fires because he is very conscious of the proximity of the forest.  I have known in my own county, and in other counties, that at certain times of the year, notably in the spring, hundreds of acres of mountain land are set on fire.  Sometimes the turf in the area is wiped out.</P>
    <P>In the past, it was traditional, especially for sheep farmers, to burn off a small part of the growth on a dangerous <Col N="137" /> rock where they were losing lambs and sheep.  This was to clear the frontage so that the sheep themselves would realise the danger.  Then, this was done in an uncontrolled fashion and the fire was allowed to spread and burn for days without any attempt being made to put it out.  There is no use in talking about preserving wildlife if they are caught in these fires also.  Much of the grouse in my part of the county have often been wiped out because of senseless fires such as these which burned the whole surface completely.</P>
    <P>Education in that respect is very important.  It should be in everybody's interest to ensure that when we are allowed to use our forests, which are a great amenity, they would be treated with care and respect.  They are a great amenity. People should realise that a Minister has the responsibility to administer his Department. He should be generous enough to allow people enjoy these forests. Warning notices are often not sufficient. Radio and television could play a big part in this.  The media could be used to ensure that this would not happen.  Irrespective of what we may say here, one animal will kill another. We have the old Irish proverb: &ldquo;Cad a dheanfadh mac an chait ach luch a mharu?&rdquo;  At the same time, there is much we can do to preserve and prevent pollution.</P>
    <P>Coursing and greyhound racing are very big industries.  The main reason why people bred greyhounds was to hunt hares, whether they were artificial or of some other type.  I do not think the greyhound would be as anxious to follow anything else as the hare.  In our anxiety to ensure that we kill nothing, we have a difficult assignment so far as this world is concerned. One animal eats another. There are people who talk a lot about the cruelties inflicted on hares during coursing.  It is cruelty to a certain extent, but there are cruelties inflicted when animals are slaughtered and birds are shot.  I am sure anything alive feels the pain of dying.</P>
    <P>There are times when the farmer &mdash;and he is not the worst offender&mdash; finds that the badger has torn the <Col N="138" /> plastic off a silage pit and dug down right into it.  It is hard to blame him for being angry.  How was the badger to know there was silage underneath the plastic covering?  He was looking for worms for his breakfast.  This happened to be a very profitable source.  Instinct told him that they were there in abundance.  The farmer was losing the feeding stuff for his winter stock.  Consequently they were at loggerheads.</P>
    <P>There are various opinions held by every political party on blood sports. I know from reading the papers that the Taoiseach is very found of following the hunt.  In my part of the country traditionally people have been following the beagles and hunting with beagles on foot.  They could be called the native huntsmen.  They traditionally follow the hare and foxes at certain times of the year.  Very little objection is raised by farmers.  That practice has been there from the time of Fionn MacCumhail.  It cannot be wiped out overnight.  We have to be careful.  There is an old story of the boy throwing stones into the pond.  A little frog put up his head and asked him what he was doing.  He said he was having fun.  The frog said, &ldquo;It may be fun for you, but it is certainly not fun for us.&rdquo;  Most people want some type of relaxation.  Those who follow the beagles enjoy the conviviality afterwards.  They have their own point of view.  I have always enjoyed the old tune, &ldquo;The Fox Chase&rdquo; by Leo Rowsome.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Dolan would agree that that is when the fox escapes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to see the fox escaping.  I am not sure if we could get over that by having slower horses, slower hounds, or by breeding some type that would not catch up with them.  Very often&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Minister for Lands (Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick, Cavan) Thomas J. (Cavan) Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands (Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick,</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Cavan</i>): The huntsmen think some of the hounds are too slow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>That can happen.  The old proverb says &ldquo;Very often a slow hound caught a hare&rdquo;.  We know <Col N="139" /> the cow actually killed a hare by lying down on it.  Irrespective of what we do there will be slight accidents.  Those who object to hunting have a right to their point of view.  I am non-committed so far as hunting is concerned. I do not indulge in it.</P>
      <P>Very often there can be cruelty to human beings.  That occurs when there is discrimination.  There are other methods&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKilbride" hpid="Mr. Kilbride Mr. Kilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>Wildlife.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, probably.  A painstaking effort has been put into this Bill and an attempt made to cover every eventuality.</P>
      <P>I was interested in Senator Higgins's reference to research carried out by a Dr. Fairlie regarding the fox.  We often accept many of the old traditions without question.  When research has been carried out we often find that the old traditions were at variance with the facts.</P>
      <P>This is a good Bill.  We will have a better opportunity at Committee Stage of dealing with it in detail.  I thought Senator Higgins's contribution excellent.  He carried out more research and reading on the subject than I had time to do.  He brought various points to my mind for which I am thankful.  He also brought a sense of humour to the chamber which has been sadly lacking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKilbride" hpid="Mr. Kilbride Mr. Kilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is both timely and appropriate at this time for the preservation of wildlife. Senator Higgins and others mentioned the various species of mammals which were the marauders and the innocent, and, in that regard, reference was made to the fox and the hare.  Nature as it existed before we had civilisation or before the application of science to our way of life had provided wildlife with the appropriate safeguards for the continuation of the various species.  The elimination, to some extent, of certain species took place. We know from animal fossils in various parts of the world that there were animals on earth of 130 ft or 140 ft high.  It was not modern ways of life that caused these species to <Col N="140" /> become extinct.  Many species have become extinct in the course of time.</P>
      <P>We have to protect wildlife against man's science and commercialisation. I believe the Minister's effort in that direction is appropriate.  From experience, I flatly contradict some of the observations made about the fox by Senator Higgins.  I assure Senator Higgins that if he was the owner of a large number of hens and saw an old vixen go away every morning with one of them, and at the end of a month or six weeks, if there were only three or four left of the original 50 or 60 hens, the arguments of the various authorities quoted by Senator Higgins would very soon become questionable, even to him.  Such are the experiences of many farmers, and it has been my own experience too.  Any farmer will vouch for the fact that the fox kills young lambs.  It has been stated that the fox lives on animals and bird life that were a pest to farmers.  Over the last 30 years huge sums of money have been paid out by county committees of agriculture as bounties on foxes' heads, tails or tongues.  Yet the fox is as plentiful today as ever he has been.  I make these observations to show that the fox was meant to be hunted.  He was endowed by nature to protect himself by his wiles and cunning.  Somebody may say it is cruel to see hounds pull him apart, but that is part of the exercise of allowing the fox to pursue the role for which he was created by nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the time of the British rule here foxes were protected in areas where large landowners had forest rangers and nobody was allowed to hunt them. Consequently, the foxes eliminated themselves by in-breeding, the manage and other skin diseases, attacking the older ones and wiping out many of their numbers in these forests and plantations. Since then the fox has not been so plentiful.  He is a most virile animal and his breeding capacity has increased, and his ranging over the country has become more widespread. Since the high walls and protected plantations of the gentlemen or the landlords of old have to a great extent disappeared, the fox has gone to the rest of the country and he has become <Col N="141" /> the evil one of the housewives' poultry flock.  He has become the marauder of the young pheasants and other wildlife species which are suffering and to some extent, disappearing.</P>
    <P>No ill has befallen the fox.  We heard in support of wildlife such distinguished names as the Rev. Ian Paisley and Sir Winston Churchill quoted.  We read of John Peel, &ldquo;D'ye ken John Peel at the break of day, with his hounds and his horn in the morning, the peals of the horn would awaken the dead, or the fox from his lair in the morning.&rdquo;  These are the writings of a famous Scottish poet, whose acquaintance with the environment and with the people was equal to if not greater than either of the two distinguished gentlemen quoted.</P>
    <P>In regard to bird life one of the things that has happened in consequence of the increased application of science to food production has been that the dressing of cereals, wheat in particular, has caused numerous coveys of partridge to be poisoned. Partridge are to be found today in very few places.  If the Minister had scientific proof of a means to protect the partridge, it would be too late to do it now because the partridge is nearly extinct.  About ten, 12 or 20 years ago if one went out in the early morning one could hear the cuckoo and the corncrake.  One does not hear them so often now because they are very scarce.  It is true that the cuckoo is a migratory bird.  It is also true that she has a host bird into whose nest she lays her egg and that bird is of the lark species.  Since the advent of silage making on the very wide and extended scope that is practised now, these birds in their laying or hatching time are caught up in the sward, are pulverised and eliminated.  This is a section of wildlife that modern methods of living have a bad effect on, and I fear will have the effect of eliminating these species of bird entirely in this country.</P>
    <P>We heard the characteristics of national life associated with birds and animals in this and other countries. The golden eagle was characteristic of the south of Ireland.  That species is now extinct.  No such bird comes here, <Col N="142" /> unless one comes from Scotland occasionally.</P>
    <P>The Minister should consider how best he can protect the species of wildlife which are in danger of extinction, because of the modern science applied for the catching, trapping, killing or hunting of these birds or animals.  He has to consider how he can protect them from the consequences of modern methods of farming, air transport and all the other things that go with the pollution of the haunts and the food on which these animals live. It would be wrong to say that the Minister must re-enact nature and to put the clock back 50 years, so far as these birds are concerned.  There are certain things the Minister cannot and should not be expected to do. What he is proposing to do is something to be commended.  To do that he has to be very careful indeed.</P>
    <P>The application of this Bill when it is enacted will require the co-operation of the local, rural population 100 per cent.  That co-operation will have to extend to the point where the people will virtually be the custodians of the wildlife in every part of this country. That creates a dangerous situation for the people involved and for everybody associated with the use of guns and other both commercial and sporting equipment used in and, sometimes, out of season.  If a very enthusiastic set of people in or near a town or in the rural areas undertake the setting up of bird sanctuaries, the care and protection in season of various species of wildlife, and that having gone so far with enthusiasm and interest the idea comes into their mind that their interest is near-ownership, then they start drawing the line and saying: &ldquo;This is my area.  I have got so and so's name.  I have so much and only we 20, or 30 may shoot here.&rdquo;  I know of one man who said: &ldquo;Only I will shoot on these four townlands.&rdquo;  He did not have to be a landlord or a landlord's agent.  He did not have the authority of a former landlord when he passed on his lands to the Land Commission or, as Senator Dolan said, to the tenants.  He can be as dogmatic in exercising these rights as anybody could imagine.  The structuring, <Col N="143" /> therefore, of the game councils and committees for the protection of wildlife will have to be well specified, and their rights, duties and authority well defined.  I am sure the Minister will take steps to see that that arrangement will apply.</P>
    <P>Somebody said something about the protection of wildlife in forests.  These animals, generally hares, are mostly hunted either for sport or for what Senator Dolan referred to as pot hunting. It is true that the hare is getting scarce because of indiscriminate hunting and killing out of season as well as in-season.  The Minister has to apply a system in regard to afforestation that militates against the hare. The Minister cannot allow a hare into a forest and the Minister is paying forest rangers or whatever he calls them to shoot hares they see in the forest.  They will completely clear a young forest of them in the first two, three, four, or maybe five years when the bark of the young trees are at an early stage and easily removed. For that reason it is hard to see to what extent the Minister can protect hares within the confines or the territory for which he has responsibility.</P>
    <P>One important aspect of rural life that we could put before our youth in the schools is the protection of wildlife. In rural Ireland, where wildlife is very much a local affair to every young boy and girl, it would be appropriate that there should be at least once a week a half hour devoted to teaching the children about wildlife.  In the schooldays of most people in rural Ireland we had the fellow who said to us: &ldquo;There are so many rabbits in such a place.&rdquo;  There was the other fellow who said: &ldquo;There are so many birds' nests in such a place.  We will go a rob them.&rdquo;  or: &ldquo;There is a big pheasant and we will go and catch him.&rdquo;  The catching usually ended up in killing. The reverse picture should be put before children.  A day will come for the men and women in the generation to come when the fortunes of wildlife will lie with them in regard to tolerance and the application of organised protection.</P>
    <P>We often look at what are the ill-effects <Col N="144" /> on wildlife species and the consequences of the activities of the game licence holders, but we have all forgotten about the rabbit.  The rabbit is a species of wildlife which in the past provided a lucrative income for people who were then wage-earners who worked on certain estates and by payment of a certain sum undertook trapping, the preparing, selling and exporting of rabbits or selling them to exporters. After the war or towards the end of the war we imported that terrible scourge of the rabbit species of the man-made disease of myxomatosis. We heard a lot of crying about hounds pulling foxes apart or greyhounds pulling hares apart, but who in their wildest imagination could anyone think of anything so cruel and create such terrible suffering and death as was meted out to the unfortunate rabbit through the scourge of myxomatosis.  Myxomatosis was discovered by a French scientist for the purpose of killing the rabbit.  The rabbit had been a far greater source of income in this country than the hare.  The hare is an incidental factor in the management and production of greyhounds for greyhound racing and for export and coursing.  That may be seen to be cruel, but that cruelty cannot be compared to what was done to the unfortunate rabbit that was killed, poisoned and got a slow and terrible death&mdash;the rabbit that was a source of income, and a dainty morsel to get in an hotel on any occasion when one would care for a variety of food.</P>
    <P>The Minister should look closely at the question of whether or not myxomatosis should be permitted to be perpetuated here.  The fact that rabbits have survived myxomatosis and that there are now rabbits in the country is an indication that nature preserves every species to the greatest possible extent.  This is mankind producing a deadly weapon for the purpose of killing a form of wildlife which not alone was advantageous to man himself but was no real problem as regards doing extensive damage.</P>
    <P>I have looked positively at this matter of wildlife.  I hope the Minister will also look at it in the light of the circumstances associated with our time <Col N="145" /> in the world, with what we owe to society, and what we owe to the wildlife that God gave us in this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KitAhern" hpid="Cáit Bean Uí Eachthéirn Cáit Bean Uí Eachthéirn">
      <NameTxt>Cáit Bean Uí Eachthéirn</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, welcome any legislation that endeavours to conserve our natural flora and fauna.  What Goldsmith once said about the bold peasantry may also be said about our flora and fauna because, if once destroyed, I fear it can never be supplied.</P>
      <P>Whilst this legislation was being drawn up I wonder did the drafters study what a very farseeing woman had to say about nature conservation that is, what is contained in <i>The Silent Spring</i> by Rachal Carson.  She foretold that if we kept using pesticides, insecticides and artificial manures and kept overshooting wild animals, the day would very fast come when even the sound of a bird would not be heard.  It deals in great detail with the balance of nature.  This is a very mysterious balance and delicate balance.  It was designed by the great Architect of the Universe to keep a balance between birds and animals, and vegetables and the human being. It proves that every section of nature is interdependent on the other.</P>
      <P>There is also very deep reference to this in the works of Teilhand de Chardin.  He also traces the evolution of the human race and the spiritual dimension that we have even in matter. As Senator Martin said, the disappearance of wildlife has its root cause in pollution, pollution of land, sea and air.  If pollution gets out of hand any more than is happening at the present day, we are certainly facing a silent spring.  We are also facing great problems in the field of human genetics, because between the food that we are now eating, which is destroyed and contaminated by all these artificial manures, pesticides and insecticides, we will not be able to keep the balance or take over control.  From that point of view we all of us very much welcome the Minister's interest in this field.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Dolan and Senator McGlinchey referred to the good old days.  The poets of the 18th and 19th century were indeed very farseeing as well, because we have many of our poems bemoaning the felling of our <Col N="146" /> woods and trees.  It is beautifully expressed in Cill Chais when the poet says&mdash;</P>
    <P>Cad a dhéanfaimid feasta gan adhmad</P>
    <P>Tá deireadh na gcoilte ar lár.</P>
    <P>Then he goes on to say:</P>
    <P>Ní chluinim fuaim lachan ná gé ann</P>
    <P>Ná fiolar ag éigheamh cois chuain.</P>
    <P>Ná fuaim na mbeacha chun saothair</P>
    <P>Thabharfadh mil agus céir don tsluagh.</P>
    <P>Again in <i>Seán Ó Duibhir a' Ghleanna,</i> you discover the appreciation there was for all birds:</P>
    <P>Ar m'eirigh dhom ar maidin</P>
    <P>Grian an tsamhraidh a' taitneamh.</P>
    <P>Chuala an uaill dá casadh</P>
    <P>Is ceol binn na n-éan.</P>
    <P>Bric is miolta gearra</P>
    <P>Creabhair na ngoba fada</P>
    <P>Fuaim ag an mac alla</P>
    <P>Is bás ins an spéir.</P>
    <P>Later on he says:</P>
    <P>Sé sin m'uaigneas fada</P>
    <P>Scáth mo chluas dá gearradh.</P>
    <P>An ghaoth aduaidh um leathadh</P>
    <P>Is bás in an shéir.</P>
    <P>Then he regrets that he has to go back to Galway and the days of the sport and game are over:</P>
    <P>Is a Shéain Uí Dhuibhir a' Ghleanna</P>
    <P>Tá tú gan géim.</P>
    <P>These poets lamented the passing of our trees, the passing of our woods, and with the passing of our woods and our trees so also passed a great section of our flora and fauna.</P>
    <P>I was surprised to hear somebody say that when Fianna Fáil were in office very little interest was taken in this subject.  I was not involved in politics at the time myself but I was very interested in rural life, in gun clubs and in the regional game boards. At that time Fianna Fáil did make a serious attempt to tackle this very complex problem.  As Senator Dolan said, I am sure some of this is already in some form in the Department.  It took 40 pages of an introductory statement by the Minister not to mind 50 or 60 sections.  A good consensus <Col N="147" /> had to be developed and agreements had to be reached by all the interested parties.  There are very many interested parties&mdash;you have the sportsmen themselves, the owners of the land, the gun clubs, and many other interests. It was legislation which could not be brought into being overnight.</P>
    <P>In 1958 also the Government gave financial assistance to the interested organisations and asked at that time for recommendations and suggestions which would be helpful in updating the antiquated legislation which was in existence since 1930.  But I feel that in this field we are paying very little attention to these groups.  While we were dallying about the legislation, they in their areas were preserving our game and drawing up rules and regulations and keeping bounds. A very loud voice should be given in this legislation to these sportsmen, to the gun clubs and to the regional game authorities.  I hope the Minister will look into it, because this legislation is something that cannot be run by the Civil Service.  You must have co-operation at the grass roots.  The amount of gamekeepers or bailiffs will rectify the situation.  It must come voluntarily and it must have the co-operation of all these bodies, especially the rural organisations and the farmers.</P>
    <P>Section 16 provides for the setting up of an advisory council.  I am greatly afraid that those who have the big estates will have far more of a say than the smaller people.  I do not like the idea of taking powers of authority over our commonages and small parcels of land because these are the only areas that our landless sportsmen call their own.  At least leave that part of our country open to these men, who, as I say, over these years have done so much for the flora and fauna of our country.</P>
    <P>Under section 12, there is an obligation on the Department and other bodies towards nature reserves and refuges.  If you speak to sporting people they will tell you that some of our greatest culprits are those in our own State forests, that before the State make laws about vermin for <Col N="148" /> other lands, they should put their own house in order.  The sporting bodies with whom I have spoken would prefer that we would go in for more game sanctuaries rather than have too many rules about the amount of your catch and so on.  As regards this part of the Bill which refers to our foreshore, they believe that we are heading for taking all the sport out of sport with too many regulations.</P>
    <P>Then there is a section on research. I do not think there is any need for setting up a further structure for research because in An Foras Taluntais we have a natural place for research. Different kinds of farming activities are dealt with by them and they are quite capable of doing any research which we need as regards game and wildlife.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Minister to consider in what way the universities could be brought into the field of research.  I remember during the early days of the gun clubs and the regional game councils the Fianna Fáil Government did quite a lot of research into the Irish red grouse.  During the last few years this research has come to a standstill.  I am told that the research on this one indigenous bird we have should go hand in hand with the study of our sheep.  That is another reason why An Foras Taluntais is a very appropriate body to undertake whatever research is needed.</P>
    <P>There are two licences spoken of. I do not believe it is necessary to have two licences.  A stamp could be put on one which is a game licence.  It is only asking for more revenue from our sportsmen.  Indeed sporting today is costly enough for an ordinary person. Like golf, it is going beyond their means altogether.  If we clamp any more taxes or extra licences on them we are just ruling the poor and the small men out of the sporting world.</P>
    <P>I spoke before about extending this legislation to the foreshore.  It would be much better if the Minister looked after some of the sloblands and wetlands that we have rather than extend the legislation to this other area.  It is only fair that we should in this debate congratulate the game councils <Col N="149" /> and the gun clubs and all these bodies who have been working in this field before any legislation was drawn up. I know some areas where they can have a season of three months for shooting and have voluntarily cut it down to one month themselves.  They are all very concerned and they are the greatest game-keepers there can be in any area because they see that the men and women who are breaking the law will have an eye kept on them and that they will not go beyond the limits.  I hope that they were consulted when this legislation was being drawn up.  I also hope that they will be given a major role in whatever boards or bodies are set up in the future.</P>
    <P>Many people referred to the necessity for further education.  One of the greatest educational programmes we have had over the past number of years was that of Eamon de Buitléar with <i>Amuigh Faoin Spéir.</i>  If the Minister could get more of those programmes on Telefís Éireann it would be much better than tying it up with the schools.  As Senator Dolan said, we have environmental studies already in our schools, but at the same time it could be supplemented by programmes such as that of Eamon de Buitléar.</P>
    <P>Someone referred to the burning of our mountains and bogs.  The ordinary person does not realise the great damage that is being wrought by this burning.  There should be a scientific way of burning one section this year and another section the next year so that some cover will be left for the birds, and so there would be sufficient grit for the grouse especially and, indeed, for all other birds.  That would be a programme that could be put on television.  There is much that can be improved in our programmes.  Here is a ready-made programme, if some of these people could be got in who have all the knowledge and put them on a show instead of some of the stupid subjects that are being presented to the people.</P>
    <P>A question was asked of me, why, if we are collecting about £1 million from the gun men in gun licences, do we not plough back that £1 million or <Col N="150" /> more into preservation.  The least we might do is to return it to the game councils and the gun clubs.  As I said before, it is a sport that is becoming very expensive.  Cartridges are very costly now, and some people believe they could reload cartridges if only they could get the shot and the gun powder.  That is also something that could be looked into.  Like everything else it will soon be beyond the reach of the poorer sections of the community. Down through the years hunting, fishing and shooting had been the sport of people of limited means.  I hope it will always be kept within the means of the poorer sections of our community, and will not be just some other sport and recreation for the élite.</P>
    <P>Once again I would like to ask the Minister to make sure that the bodies that have put years of education and research into this will have a major role to play when the boards are being set up.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at</i> 6 <i>p.m. and resumed at</i> 7.30 <i>p.m.</i></P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we resume consideration of the Bill, when we agreed to the Order of Business earlier today it was understood that a statement would be made on what the position would be when we returned after the tea adjournment.  In view of the fact that it has already been suggested by the Leader of the House that we are to meet on Friday, I want to point out again that many Members are committed to county councils, vocational education committees, or agricultural committees or urban councils and Friday is not suitable.  If we knew beforehand it would be all right but no previous notice has been given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I was about to say before resuming on the Bill that during an informal discussion while the Minister was absent Senator Killilea drew my attention to the fact that&mdash;I ask him to accept that it was inadvertently&mdash;I may have misled Members on the Order of Business with regard to the reasons why we did not <Col N="151" /> get the Social Welfare (Pay-Related Benefit) Bill today.  I was under the impression that it might have been possible by agreement for the Dáil to have altered their Order of Business to take that.</P>
      <P>The hint I was trying to give was that the approach might be made and that that might be done.  I now understand that that probably would not have been possible.  The reason for our failure to get the Bill today is because of delay in getting it out of the Dáil last night.  That is the reason we will not get it until Friday.  I should like to take the opportunity of clearing the record.  I am obliged to Senator Killilea&mdash;although it was informally &mdash;and to Senator Dolan now for having given me the opportunity of saying that.  The position remains unaltered. We will not get the Bill until Friday and consequently we will be sitting on Friday to take it.</P>
      <P>It seems clear now that in any event the Wildlife Bill, Second Stage, is unlikely to conclude tonight, in which event we will also be sitting tomorrow for the purpose of concluding the Second Stage of that Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>On a further point of information, seeing that the Leader of the House has now definitely said we will now be sitting on Friday, would he concede to one request? Seeing that he has refused the suggestion of not sitting on a Friday&mdash; I oppose that principle because we sat Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday and there are a thousand different reasons why we should not sit on Friday, both financial and others&mdash; could he arrange to have the Seanad sit on Friday at 3 o'clock in preference to 10.30 a.m. as suggested?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid it will not be possible.  There is a function on Friday evening which a number of Members will be attending.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry to delay the House but the point arising from all this is that it is obvious that the Government are unable to pass even a simple little Bill such as the Pay Related Bill which should only take a moment.  I would request that this <Col N="152" /> be the last occasion that the Seanad be asked to sit on a Friday if it has sat on a Tuesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not have any objection as to when we sit provided we know some time beforehand.  Is there that great urgency about the Bill now in the Dáil?  Could it not have been postponed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>All I am in a position to say is that it is desired to have it taken on Friday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>Today when I was on the Order of Business I was about to ask about a motion.  The Leader of the House has now apologised for the situation that occured but he overlooked my request to have the last motion on the agenda taken.  He did not answer me as to what he intended to do about it.  Has he considered it since&mdash;may it be possible to take it tomorrow when the Wildlife Bill finishes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator gave himself the answer when he raised it.  It would be impossible to arrange at short notice for the taking of the last motion tabled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked for another assurance that we would seek from the Government that no vote be taken on the relevant White Paper until such time as it was debated in this House. That question is still unanswered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot give any assurance about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>A matter of such major importance should go through the process of debate in this House and in the other House.  Before any further moves have been made on that White Paper it is important that it be debated in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Wildlife Bill, 1975:" RHead="Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Wildlife Bill, 1975: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is in many ways a monumental piece of legislation in the field of preservation <Col N="153" /> and conservation of wildlife.  It is clearly a Bill&mdash;and this has been acknowledged by many speakers already &mdash;for which there is a need and also for which there has been a demand. I believe the Minister is quite right when he said in his opening statement that the success of the Bill depends on the volume of public sympathy and support which it can attract.</P>
      <P>This Bill is a courageous Bill.  I say that because as a person who is interested to some extent personally in game shooting, having read this Bill and heard the Minister's speech, I think there are provisions in the Bill which are nearly bound to cause resentment&mdash;I was about to say &ldquo;ruffle the feathers of some shooters&rdquo; but I would be accused of a pun if I said that.  The Minister and his Department have shown responsiveness to the needs that exist in this field and they have shown considerable courage in the manner in which they propose tackling the problems as indicated in the provisions of this Bill.</P>
      <P>The Minister has made it clear in his opening statement that the general approach has been on the basis that there is no such thing, as he put it, as free shooting.  While I would hesitate to adopt that as a general principle, I understand what the Minister means and it is particularly in this context that I admire his courage in the manner in which he is tackling the problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister went on to indicate his view that anyone who shoots for game over somebody else's land without permission is a poacher and I think very few will disagree with that.  Taking the poacher in that sense, although most people who take part in the activity of shooting game regard a poacher in a somewhat different sense&mdash;they regard a poacher as a person who seeks to take or capture game by unfair or unlawful methods&mdash;the person who goes out shooting with a gun on somebody else's land without actually taking permission may be regarded as a tresspasser but from the point of view of the ordinary games man I do not think he is regarded as a poacher in the other sense.  I understand and sympathise <Col N="154" /> with the point of view of the Minister in this connection.  It might be said that it is no concern of the Government, the Department or the Minister whether an individual is trespassing on another individual's land and that whatever remedies are sought or should be sought for that situation should be sought by the owner of the land.</P>
    <P>That is a fairly valid point but the machinery which the Minister is establishing is not primarily designed, as I see it, for the purpose of protecting any one against trespassers.  It is for the purpose of tightening the law in the interest of game and wildlife preservation. That is the Minister's interest in the particular machinery which is being established.  It still will remain the right of a person whose land has been trespassed against by someone shooting over it without permission to take whatever action he may see fit.</P>
    <P>It is at this point that I can see the possibility of some misunderstanding and resentment being caused.  Most of us who are interested in game shooting will be familiar with areas in the country where there have been what might be regarded as traditional rights of free shooting, where traditionally over the years it has been the practice to allow all and sundry to go in and shoot without objection.  Most of us who go around the country on holidays, duck shooting or pheasant shooting, no matter what area we go into there will always be local people, perhaps someone in charge of the hotel, who will be able to say: &ldquo;Of course you can shoot on such and such a mountain.  You can shoot on such and such a bog.  No one has any objection.&rdquo;  I can see that people who have been accustomed to getting that kind of hospitable reception in local areas may feel aggrieved at the steps the Minister is taking in the Bill to put a curb on what he has described as poaching.  At the same time, while I understand that resentment, I find it difficult to be convinced that the steps the Minister is taking are not the correct ones.  They are the only steps open to him and he is not taking them in the interests of trying to <Col N="155" /> curb people's freedom or trying to prevent people from trespassing as such; he is taking these steps in the interests of protection and conservation of wildfowl.</P>
    <P>There are various other measures set out in the Bill towards achieving the same objective&mdash;the possibility, for example, of a bag limit; the possibility in certain circumstances of curtailing the open season or extending the closed season; various sections which deal with unfair methods of taking game, hunting at night, and so on.  All these are steps which are open to the Minister and he is taking them.  Some of these steps will be bound to create a certain amount of criticism and cause a certain amount of concern among people who have been accustomed to a much more free-and-easy approach to the question of game shooting.</P>
    <P>The provisions which are contained in the Bill and which the Minister obviously hopes will assist in the cause of preservation and the protection of game life are principally those contained in sections 28 and 29.  My only doubt about the provisions of these sections is as to whether or not they will be entirely workable without a very great increase in the staff of the Minister's Department or activity by the Garda.  The provision in section 28 is to impose a prohibition on game shooting except by qualified persons. The qualifications required are, first, that the person must be 16 years of age or more, secondly, he must have sporting rights or be a guest or invitee of someone with sporting rights or shooting with the written authority of the owner with sporting rights; or, thirdly, he must be a member of a body, presumably a body such as a gun club which has sporting rights; or fourthly, he must belong to a category which is declared as qualified by the Minister.</P>
    <P>Senator Cáit Uí Eachthéirn, referring to this question, spoke of two gun licences, the ordinary gun licence and the game licence.  I think the Minister spelled out in his introductory speech that the question of two gun licences for the ordinary game shooter would <Col N="156" /> not arise; that there would be an endorsement placed on the ordinary gun licence which would enable the person to use his gun for game.  In order to get that the applicant must be in a position to make a declaration to show that he is eligible under the category of qualified persons.</P>
    <P>My doubt as regards the workabilty of this section relates to the question: how does one prevent a person who has a gun licence from using it for game?  I know that in section 74 there are fairly stiff financial penalties for offences committed under the Bill, but it would take an army of gardaí to enforce the section.  That fact emphasises the correctness of the Minister both in his approach to and reading of the situation, when in his opening statement he referred to the success of the Bill depending on the volume of sympathy and support which it might attract.</P>
    <P>When the Minister referred to poachers&mdash;the person I call the trespasser-poacher&mdash;it occurred to me, and I am sure to anyone else who is interested in game shooting, that there is another type of poacher who is much more objectionable and more of a danger to conservation and preservation of game birds: that is the person who goes out a week or a couple of weeks before the shooting season opens, gets the first run-through a shoot and kills off, say, pheasants before the season opens.  I regard a person who deliberately acts in that way as a cheat.  To the extent that the provisions of this Bill may stamp that kind of action out, it will be a more valuable step towards preservation and protection than the prohibition which might be put on the person who is technically a trespasser. Very often people who trespass know that the area on which they are shooting is one where there is no objection by the owner or group of owners to visitors or others going in to shoot.  However the person who deliberately goes out before the season opens and tries to cheat his own colleagues, who have shotgun licences in a particular area, is, in my opinion, much more a poacher of the objectionable sort.</P>
    <P>I mentioned the trespasser-poacher, <Col N="157" /> and many of these may feel aggrieved by this legislation, but there is another side to the picture, somewhat different from the general question of conservation, looking at it from the point of view of individuals who have gone to the trouble of restocking gun clubs under the supervision or encouragement of regional game councils.  Very often people invest quite an amount of money and a good deal of time and expertise in restocking areas.  It is only right and fair that people who involve themselves in that trouble and undertake that kind of expense should be entitled to expect that others will not simply go in and reap the harvest of their labours.  That side of the picture should not be overlooked.</P>
    <P>Senator Kilbride, I think, was right in talking as he did with regard to the scourge of myxomatosis in rabbits. Senator McGlinchey and some others referred to the days when there were large estates which were well stocked and well preserved.  That situation obtained here.  The reduction in game stock generally&mdash;I am talking of the most common types of game birds like partridge, which used be common, grouse and pheasant&mdash;was due to a number of factors, one being the breakup of the large estates.  I think valuable work, such as work in bogs, drainage and land reclamation, also had its effect but the breaking-up of the big estates had a very definite effect.  The second most serious effect was the introduction of myxomatosis into the country some decades ago.</P>
    <P>I hold no brief for rabbits as such. I used enjoy eating a rabbit occasionally. I agree with Senator Kilbride's description of it.  Many people regarded it as a delicacy.  Many others regarded it and relied on it as what used be referred to as the poor man's chicken.  I appreciate the point of view of a farmer who found that his corn crop, in particular, was being badly damaged by rabbits and that rabbits were increasing.  I understand all that. At the same time when myxomatosis was introduced it had a savage effect. Most Senators from rural areas have seen rabbits afflicted by myxomatosis, seen the blindness occurring and seen them reeling around with sores on their <Col N="158" /> heads&mdash;a disgusting sight, quite apart from the feeling of pity one had for the obvious suffering of the animals.</P>
    <P>It had a secondary affect on game birds in this way, that up to the time of the introduction of myxomatosis, when there was a large rabbit population in the country, by and large the fox population fed on the rabbits. When myxomatosis wiped out the rabbits foxes turned their attention from fur to feather and the result was a fairly dramatic reduction in the stock of game birds in the country. That is still continuing.  Where there are foxes in large numbers&mdash;and obviously there are foxes in large numbers throughout the country&mdash;they are forced to prey on birds rather than rabbits.  My personal view is that they probably acquired a taste for birds and that, even if rabbits were back as they were before, possibly foxes would continue to prey on young birds.</P>
    <P>A further effect followed the introduction of myxomatosis and the wiping out of the rabbit population.  When rabbits were plentiful it was comparatively easy and comparatively cheap for either a landowner or a gun club or a syndicate that got together for purposes of taking care of a shoot and enjoying it to make proper arrangements for a gamekeeper to look after the shoot or the land.  In addition to being paid what would probably have been quite an insignificant cash wage the gamekeeper was only too glad to be given trapping rights for rabbits in which he was primarily interested.  He was able to make quite a good living out of trapping rabbits and selling them and their furs.  When the rabbits went, that particular occupation also went.  Many people just were not able to afford what it would then have taken to pay and maintain a full-time steward or gamekeeper to look after the shoot, as regards preservation, restocking and so on. Therefore, the introduction of myxomatosis, I think, had a very drastic affect on bird numbers in the country. That seems to be recurring.  In many areas, certainly in my own area, rabbits are back in good numbers, but I understand that even when they are young and up to the time they are <Col N="159" /> graziers they still become afflicted with myxomatosis.  Whether it could ever be eradicated once it is introduced, I do not know.</P>
    <P>I know that a not inconsiderable number of people are against all types of hunting, whether it be what is normally referred to as a blood sport or shooting.  While I do not necessarily share it I can certainly appreciate that point of view.  A personal friend of mine is a crackshot with a shotgun but he will not shoot birds or rabbits or hares.  He contents himself as long as I have known him, with clay pigeon shooting.  He simply would not use his gun to kill a live animal or a live bird.  There are people who feel like that and I respect their point of view, their feelings and their principles.  At the same time, it is absolutely true to say that hunting has been there from time immemorial, hunting of one type or another, and certainly hunting for the pot.  Essentially, even though people who go out with a shot gun might not admit it, that is game shooting: they are shooting for the pot: they are not shooting simply to kill a bird and leave it there to rot. They are shooting in the same way as the angler goes out with his rod and his creel, to bring back something for the pot.  I can see a distinction, of course, between hunting of that sort and what might be called hunting for entertainment.  But in one shape or another hunting has been there from time immemorial.</P>
    <P>There is just one other thought I want to leave with Senators, particularly those who feel strongly about fox hunting.  I am going to leave myself open to a broadside from someone when I say this.  I have not particularly strong views about this.  That is probably my own fault; I never really got down to thinking about it. I am not a hunting man in the sense of hunting a fox from horseback. Last time I was on a horse was some years ago; we parted company and I have not been on horseback since. I would not really be fit to partake in the exercise of fox hunting.  I understand that it is exhilarating.  But leaving all that aside, the thought <Col N="160" /> which I would like to leave with people is this.  Particularly in the west of the country I could say&mdash;Senator Michael D. Higgins will correct me if I am wrong in this&mdash;a considerable asset to our economy has developed in the breeding of hunters or halfbreeds. They contribute greatly to the economy of a number of farmers. They are not big breeders but small or medium-sized farmers who have a good mare and produce the goodclass of half-breed that is used for hunting.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Or as a showjumper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  Very often the showjumper starts as a hunter.  But if fox hunting as we know it were to be eliminated it is worth considering what effect that would have on the breeding of hunters here. There might be a limited number who would still continue in the game in the hope that they might get a world beater in the showjumping class, but certainly the kind of ready cash that can be got from the rearing of good half breeds for hunting purposes would be gone.</P>
      <P>Those are the only thoughts I have on this Bill.  The Minister has shown not merely considerable awareness of the problems that exist but he has shown considerable courage in his approach to this.  I wish him every success so far as this legislation goes. By and large people interested, either as I am, as an individual, in game-shooting or interested from an emotional point of view in the preservation of wild fowl in the country will wish the Minister success in his efforts in this field.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a pretentious Bill which is notable for the fact that it has missed opportunities and for its remarkable comprehensiveness in achieving so very little and, worse still, for drawing attention to an extraordinary, inexplicable lacuna in our legislation in regard to protection.  Because it omits protection for particular forms of wildlife that I will deal with later on, it is a Bill which will contribute to making us the rather unfortunate claimants to yet another seedy and obscene record in failure to <Col N="161" /> civilise our laws in a particular aspect of our society.  It is a very frustrating activity of my public life to go through Bill after Bill introduced in this House and in the other House and time after time, no matter what aspect of the life of our society is concerned to find the same stark, materialist considerations: The inevitability of cruelty, punitive, repressive, suppressing violence and completely barbarous practices which seem to pass over the majority of Senators, and indeed Deputies, without their knowing of the extraordinary philistinism or barbarity of the practices which they pass into law.</P>
      <P>Over the years I have had the job of drawing attention to our curiously sadistic behaviour in relation to, say, the punishment of children, penology, criminology or criminality.  In all these aspects where one could or should expect some element of humanitarianism, one never finds it, we seem to have this extraordinarily sadistic, sado-masochistic element in the Irish ethos which is inexplicable. It runs right across the whole culture. This is not a special Catholic thing, or a special Protestant thing.  It is special to us Irish; it is exceptional in Europe.  It is becoming exceptional in the one-time Third World people. Now, instead of cruelty to animals by hunting and killing painfully, which all hunting necessarily is, people now go on safari with Leica cameras.  They are leaving behind the great guns for killing elephants, lions and tigers. Senator O'Higgins was right when he said that there was an element of hunting for the pot in primitive times. The only way a man knew how to survive was to hunt for the pot.  Those times are long past.</P>
      <P>Some European and African countries have attempted to preserve their wonderful wildlife game, irrespective of the fact that peculiar barbarians with money, go on safaries to kill these wonderful animals&mdash;lions, tigers, elephants and so on.  They now go to look at them, see their beauty and try to derive the aesthetic satisfaction that civilised human beings should get from seeing the beautiful products of nature they used to kill in other African countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="162" /> This is a rather pretentious Bill. One of the points made by Senator O'Higgins is particularly valid in establishing its pretentiousness.  It would require an enormous reinforcement in the warden/gamekeeper personnel in the Department to implement it.  I do not think we are likely to get that.  For that reason many of the provisions in the Bill will not be operative.  Even if one looks at the schedule of animals referred to in the various sections, it will be seen that this is complete stable door legislation. The horse has long bolted in relation to most of these wild animals we are going to protect&mdash;buzzards, eagles, falcons, harriers, hawks, kites and owls.  There are very few of these.</P>
    <P>This is very formidable legislation which seeks to protect these species of wildlife.  There are also the pine martin, red deer, seals and whales.  The Minister will have to agree that there is a certain element of unrealism in the suggestion that he is going to bring any significant protection to these wild animals.  Because this legislation has been delayed for so long, and because we have been so totally irresponsible in regard to the marvellous heritage of animal and bird life and the countryside, it is quite likely that this legislation is too late.</P>
    <P>In the Fifth Schedule a number of animals are mentioned&mdash;badger, bat, deer, hare, hedgehog, otter, pine martin, red squirrel and stoat.  Legislation will permit killing deer, hare, otter and badger.  This means that the list of animals which one is going to protect is either non-existent, or, by the time the hunting people are finished, there will not be any of these left.  This is a give it with one hand and a take it with the other Bill. It is very difficult to know why the Minister took the trouble to introduce it.</P>
    <P>This Bill was promised by his predecessor, Deputy Seán Flanagan, as far back as 1970.  It was to be a model-for-Europe Bill.  That is quite untrue.  Maybe Deputy S. Flanagan meant it to be so but he is no longer there and so cannot be blamed for it. The Minister must know that it is not <Col N="163" /> true.  In Strasbourg in 1974 an informal discussion took place and it was decided that a telegram should be sent about the &ldquo;model Bill&rdquo; to Deputy Fitzpatrick.  The following advice was given: forget it, advised the Dutch delegates, the whole messy business of hunting and chasing and the industry which supports them will quickly come to an end as a result of their beastly excesses.  The 5 or 10 per cent of the remaining wild animals will then have a chance or die out in peace.  As for their laws being a model for Europe, enjoined the Swiss, that has not been true for a long time.  They are an example of the worst in Western Europe, at least as far as wildlife is concerned. Only Italy is as bad and Spain is nearly 100 years ahead of the Irish Republic&mdash;and Spain has bull fighting, another form of barbarism.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the source of the quotation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>The Wildlife Protection Association meeting held in Strasbourg in 1974.  This is the kind of insulation from the reality of the concept which the world has about the ancient and historic Irish people which is so confusing.  We give the impression that we believe we are a very gentle race.  We are the only people who think that; we are the only people who believe that.  An extremely good case can be made for showing that we have no right to that opinion whatsoever.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The origin of that would be a most interesting activity to wonder about, from the psychological point of view. I have my own opinions, but I will not go into them now.  It is a fascinating and horrifying thought that we have this preoccupation with cruelty, violence and the savagery of killing little animals who are not attacking us, but who are running away from us as fast as they can.  We are hunting them as fast as we can on horses, with the yells and shouts Senator M.D. Higgins talked about, not unlike the hounds baying.  Hounds can be forgiven for behaving like hounds.  This is the extraordinary practice in relation <Col N="164" /> to many of the beautiful little animals which do very little harm compared to what is said about them.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Higgins mentioned one point in relation to the killing by shooting and so on and Senator Dolan also talked about this: we kill animals anyway to eat.  I happen to be a vegetarian because I would not kill an animal myself and, therefore, I would not care to ask anybody else to kill an animal for me.  I am not asking people to be vegetarians.  We have a method of killing humanely.  There is a great difference there.  Senator Dolan said we have to kill animals for those people who eat meat.  That is understandable. I want to emphasise that we kill them humanely.  Nobody could say that when one takes a double-barrelled shotgun, a .22 or a .303 rifle, and shoots at a bird in a tree or an animal 50 or 100 yards away&mdash;a very high percentage of the animals hit are hurt and will die very painfully&mdash;that that is not cruelty.  There is all the difference between that kind of killing with a gun or a hound and killing with the very blunt instrument of long distance pellets and slugs or the hunt to kill by hunters.</P>
    <P>It is not necessary to hunt for the pot because we have many laws to make sure the butchers and abattoirs use humane killers.  We have inspectors who make sure that animals are killed in a humane way, but not in respect of hunting or of this sport of following little animals until they are exhausted, fall at our feet, and the dogs tear them to pieces.  How anybody can take one of the most beautiful birds in the world &mdash;the cock pheasant, with its glorious colourful feathers&mdash;and pour shot into that lovely body and destroy and bring it down in blood and broken bones and feathers, I cannot understand.  How anybody can do that defies my comprehension. If it is done in the name of sport, that is an obscene misuse of that word.</P>
    <P>There are Senators who do not share my views.  Possibly, as time goes on and they think a little about what I am saying, they may come to share these views.  I have not had these views all my life.  This is one of the grievances I had against my upbringing and my <Col N="165" /> education.  I did not see the enormity of the cruelty of an adult taking a little animal in this very cruel way and killing it.  This is one of the reasons why I take an interest in discussing this measure.  I hope, as time goes on, that Senators will begin to, possibly not change their minds, but to understand the changing mind of young people. This is one of the hopeful developments in our society practically at all levels, that young people are becoming less involved in this display of violence which appealed to our generation and our forefathers.  Remember bull-baiting, bear-baiting, cock-fighting and dog-fighting and all the brutalising, dehumanising, cruel and savage sports. They are now unthinkable to most of us.  There is cock-fighting possibly in the Border counties still.  They have passed into history.  They are no longer acceptable to any Senators here.  They would not think it funny to catch a bear or have bulldogs tearing at the noses of bulls and fighting to the death, or those other terrible displays of cruelty of, say, 50 or 100 years ago&mdash; bare-knuckle fighting among men.  They are all unthinkable now.  So we have progressed to some extent in the world, but it is limited here.</P>
    <P>I am hoping young people will not follow in the pattern set for them by our generation.  There is hope that they are not doing this.  I find it reassuring that football matches are finding it very hard to get crowds.  The essential warlike display at these football matches is violence of one kind or another. These are being supported by less and less.  Even bullfighting in Spain is finding it quite difficult to get spectators. I am hopeful that the next generation will begin to see the unthinkable cruelty of these activities.  The Minister could have taken this opportunity to deal with this question of cruelty to animals in the name of sport or of hunting.</P>
    <P>The main animals in which I am interested are the otter, the badger, the fox and the hare.  These are still to be fair game for hunters in the years ahead.  Surely this is an extraordinary omission on the part of the Minister? He will not take the responsibility of eliminating the killing of these animals <Col N="166" /> in the form of sporting activity.  Even Britain, which had this inhumane attitude to animals among the ruling classes for centuries, has got to the stage where they are outlawing open coursing.  We will be the last outpost of barbarity in all Europe in relation to killing, hunting and torturing animals. This is a scandalous reputation. Are we ashamed of this?</P>
    <P>Senator O'Higgins talked about the money side of the hunting business. There is the question of whether cruelty should be permitted because there is money to be made from it. There must be some limit to the gross materialism of our standards in this allegedly Christian society.  There must be some levels which we will not permit simply because there are a few pounds in it.  Even if this consideration did not exist, is it not a fact that one can have drag hunts?  If people must indulge in hunting, can they not have drag hunts?</P>
    <P>The South County Dublin Hunt Club, to which the Taoiseach is attached, have a drag hunt.  This is an utterly painless activity for the animals, apart from the horses.  It is exciting, presumably; it is enjoyable and trains the hunters Senator O'Higgins was worried about.  One could continue to have one's trade in hunters and, at the same time, not do it at the expense of the unfortunate fox.</P>
    <P>I am particularly sorry that the otter will not be protected.  Otter hunting is an extraordinary sport.  These are gentle, delightful, clever, ingenious, brave, courageous little animals.  Yet, hoards of young people go out with poles, sticks and hounds to follow this unfortunate animal on both banks of a river.  The animal jumps into the water and tries to keep swimming under the water.  When he comes onto the bank he is hunted back by these dreadful people with sticks in their hands.  This tiny little animal is the target.  They hunt him back into the water until eventually he is too exhausted&mdash;a hunt can go on for anything up to four hours&mdash;and is dug out with picks and shovels if he goes to ground.  He is then beaten to death or the hounds tear him apart.  He fights for his life, but the hounds are <Col N="167" /> much too strong for him.  If the hounds are not able for him, there are always the ring of bully boys with their big sticks to protect themselves from the poor little exhausted animal.</P>
    <P>How could anybody call this a sport?  It is extraordinary that there are young boys and girls throughout Ireland who have been brought up to believe that they are participating in a sport when they go otter hunting. Otters are said to kill fish.  I do not see why animals should not have the right to live.  Why must they be killed simply because they interfere with our way of life, but not in a meaningful way?  If they get into spawning beds and kill the spawn, that can be prevented. The fish they kill, according to very close observation, are sick fish.  It has been ascertained that they kill eels.  Eels eat trout and salmon. The intelligent owners of riparian rights in these rivers are beginning to understand that otters are an advantage in a river.  Very occasionally the otter kills salmon and trout.  Otters are now encouraged in rivers in order to protect the river, the salmon and the trout.</P>
    <P>The British magazine <i>The Field</i> contains records of these sports.  In 1967, in an editorial they stated:</P>
    <P>The truth is that the otter does little or no harm to fishing interests.</P>
    <P>It is very difficult to understand why we allow this delightful little creature to be hunted by dogs and by people with sticks in this very cruel and unfeeling way.  Perhaps some Senators can give a rationale for this kind of thing.  I have never heard one which convinced me.</P>
    <P>Senator Michael D. Higgins talked about Dr. Fairlie's work on foxes.  He made it clear that much fallacy existed about hunting the fox.  Incidentally, having listened to Senator Kilbride telling about the fox being bred to be killed and being a treacherous and cunning animal, I do not want to be disrespectful to the Senator, but the truth of the matter is that the behaviour pattern of an animal, and particularly the fox, is an extraordinarily complicated <Col N="168" /> and abstruse subject.  It is much easier to have the kind of piseog we heard from the Senator than to have factual information.</P>
    <P>Dr. Fairley who has done between ten and 20 years study on the life and activity of foxes, now says that he could write a book about the fox and its activities, but what he does not know, the questions which have arisen since he started studying the fox, would fill volumes in a large library because, apparently, it is such a complicated creature.  Dr. Fairley of Galway University, is the greatest authority on foxes in Europe.  It is wrong to say they kill the lambs. There is quite an amount of evidence to establish that foxes cannot kill them so long as the ewe is present. The only time foxes will kill lambs is when the ewe is having a second lamb, where there are twin lambs.</P>
    <P>We can understand the farmer's viewpoint because of the folklore about foxes over the years, and when he sees a fox then every dead lamb or chicken is the work of the fox.  This is not true. There are other animals, including roaming dogs and hungry dogs, such a distressing sight in rural Ireland, which can cause the trouble.  The fox is frequently blamed but in Dr. Fairley's assessment&mdash;this is a scientific assessment&mdash;something like 50 per cent of the cases attributed to the foxes are attributable to other causes.</P>
    <P>The fox serves a very useful function, to use civil service jargon, because they kill rats, mice and various animals.  To destroy the fox would probably upset the balance of nature which other Senators spoke about and in that way, rather like the complaints of so many about myxomatosis, it would probably do more harm than good if the fox were eliminated.  Of course the truth is the fox is not being eliminated, that the people on horses kill very few foxes.  When these people talk about keeping down the foxes they are not really doing that, they are simply enjoying themselves in this bizaare pastime; but the excuse given is that they are keeping down the foxes.  Neither, apparently, does the bounty system keep down foxes.  The population of <Col N="169" /> foxes is unchanged even though there has been the bounty system in Northern Ireland for many years; 7,000 to 9,000 foxes were killed but the same number of foxes still exists.</P>
    <P>Why does fox hunting continue to be tolerated?  Why does the Minister allow this sport to continue?  Surely there are good reasons for its elimination, even from the agricultural point of view.  The farmer does not want horseriders jumping through his fences, riding across his land and bringing these foxhounds, many of which are diseased. Indeed the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries make that point when they tell farmers, in order to protect their herds from brucellosis, to keep dogs off their land.  Yet these kinds of hounds, in the form of hunts, could be the source of brucellosis.</P>
    <P>Cub hunting is another extraordinarily cruel kind of foxhunting, whereby they bring the young hounds down, collect a few young fox cubs and after ten or 15 minutes they are caught and torn to bits by the young hounds.  This is the process of blooding&mdash;surely, again, a totally barbaric practice.  How can anybody defend taking these small animals, which are about the size of kittens, and throwing them to dogs to be torn to bits in order to blood the dogs?  Meanwhile the poor unfortunate vixen will dodge around in the covert to the last minute trying to divert the hunt from her family&mdash; the wonderful courage of these animals in the face of this barbaric human behaviour.  There is the blooding of children at foxhunts.  Surely this is the most primitive tribal kind of behaviour by allegedly civilised human beings, taking the blood of the dead animal and smearing it over the child's face.  These are the kind of things that we do and will continue to do under this new Bill.  The Minister knows this goes on and he is doing nothing about it.  It is extraordinary, but very few of the Senators seem to be unduly concerned about it.</P>
    <P>There is one other fact which I should like to convey to Senator Dolan so that he would know the good that a fox does rather than the damage he causes.  The fox kills, on average, 15 mice and six rats per day, that is <Col N="170" /> 21,000 mice and 9,000 rats a year.  So that could be a case, that if foxes were killed, the rats and mice would be allowed to proliferate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>(<i>Cavan</i>): Has the Senator no sympathy for the poor mice and rats?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I can understand a fox behaving like a fox but a human being behaving like a fox is a different matter altogether.  This is the kind of way in which the balance of nature is upset.  The fox has a very positive function.  I appreciate the difficulties of farmers.  I have seen my own lambs killed by something or other.  I do not know what killed them but I did not necessarily blame the fox.  There are ways in which foxes can be controlled, by gassing them in the setts.  In some cases they have to be killed, but it is a reasonably humane way of killing them.  To block their holes, making them go out into the open without any refuge or protection against dogs is completely unforgiveable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The other animal I should like to talk about is the badger.  Again, the badger is a beautiful and aesthetically a delightful animal.  He lives on rats, mice, slugs, snails, worms, grubs, roots, berries, wasps, insects and young rabbits. Again in the balance of nature he serves a very useful purpose.  He is a very important and valuable asset. In relation to the killing of poultry and the going into a silage pit that Senator Dolan talked about, these kinds of things can happen, but surely nowadays we have a responsibility. Senator Kilbride talked about the killing of hens, but if one keeps hens in insecure surrounds or if one has farm buildings which are not properly protected, surely one can hardly blame an animal if, being hungry, he decides to take advantage of the fact that you have left the door open.  Most of us close the doors of our houses at night time, and if we have a shop or a petrol pump we do not leave it there for anybody to come along and take what they want.  These are things that we observe in relation to our behaviour to one another.  Why can we not take the same precautions and see that these animals are safely lodged and protected <Col N="171" /> for the night?  Most of the deep litter kind of poultry that is in use in rural areas is highly protected.</P>
    <P>However, badgers are very shy creatures and badger-baiting, fortunately, is no longer permissible.  I think most of us would shudder at the thought of the awful business of capturing a badger and then killing it with dogs.  But there was a time when it was commonplace and accepted and its cruelty obviously not appreciated. Badger digging, however, is still legal. The terrier is sent down into the sett, the poor badger fights back.  The diggers find out where the badger is and then they start digging down.  Dog after dog is sent down into the sett to drag the badger out and then it may be killed when it is brought to the surface, but quite frequently, unfortunately, the people who have dug it out tend to indulge in the sport of losing it to the terriers and letting the terriers kill it or putting it in a sack and taking is somewhere else to kill it, again an extraordinarily cruel pastime.  There were a few sequences shown on Telefís Éireann of a film taken in Northern Ireland in 1966 in which an unconscious badger was revived and brought back to life in order to fight on.</P>
    <P>There is no justification for killing badgers in this way at all.  Nobody has seriously made a case for it at all, and this is a wild animal like the otter and the hare that should have been protected in the Minister's Bill.  There was a newspaper report here in 1966 of a badger killing:</P>
    <P>The one I saw killed had put up a three-hour fight, but in the end the fighting spirit with which he had defended his life, his family and his home was exhausted.  Its sleek black and white coat was covered in blood from the dog bites and slashes from two sharp tongs.  Even then it took four blows with a crowbar to split open its skull and end its misery.</P>
    <P>This is another process, incidentally, in badger hunting&mdash;the use of a badger tongs which is a very small weapon with very sharp edges, which is pushed down into the hole as soon as the badger is dug out.  The badger is pulled out with this appalling <Col N="172" /> weapon and then thrown to the dogs in order for the dogs to destroy him.  That goes on in our society among Irishmen and women, presumably, too occasionally, but we are going to go on defending that kind of behaviour in rural Ireland, this cruelty to tiny little animals by civilised men.</P>
    <P>Finally, I should like to talk about the other extraordinary pastime in our society, that is, hare coursing.  Coursing clubs are operated by the Irish Coursing Club and Bord na gCon between them.  There is no doubt at all&mdash;and the Minister must know this&mdash;that the rules of the coursing club are very frequently broken.  This again lovely wild animal, the hare, is becoming increasingly scarce, and even the blood sport people themselves recognise that it is becoming increasingly scarce.  They hold about 90 meetings a year, about 140 days coursing, and the process is even more calculatedly cruel than the other ones I have recounted involving the badger, the otter and the fox, because this is a particularly gentle animal.  I suppose the badger, the fox and the otter could all bite you.  That might be used as a justification for smashing their brains in by some of these hunting men, but the hare is a particularly beautiful gentle animal. The coursing process is a particularly shocking one because the agony, the cruelty and the torture is so prolonged. It goes on and on and on.</P>
    <P>The animal is collected in the first instance.  They have drives and nets. They drive the poor hares into these nets and what is particularly offensive to me is that youngsters are brought out into these drives.  These lovely animals are driven into the nets and when they are caught in the nets they are frequently screaming, struggling, terrified, and they are taken out of the nets, put in cases and then sent off to the coursing meeting. Then the farce of training goes on.  Imagine training a wild animal in three or four days.  What a misuse of the word &ldquo;training&rdquo;.  How could it happen?  Anyway, they wire in the place where they have the meeting, and the theory is that six or seven days before the meeting these animals are hunted up and down by people <Col N="173" /> shouting at them so that they learn to know the track between the slipper and the escape.  Even if this did take place it would be an appallingly cruel process, but it does not take place; in fact in most cases the hares are not trained and the result of this is that when the hare gets into the arena&mdash; like the gladiators of old&mdash;it does not know where the escape hatch is. Which of us would in similar circumstances if we were to be hunted like that?  Which of us would remember, in the appalling panic of the dogs behind you, where the escape was? So it zig-zags here and there and, of course, is quickly killed.  The killing rate is very high and on some occasions hares have been known and have been shown to have been coursed when they were sick from pneumonia, when they could not run properly. Yet the coursing has taken place and a very high percentage of the unfortunate animals have been killed.</P>
    <P>This process of so-called training the hares goes on.  Then the poor little devils are hunted by these greyhounds who cannot be blamed for their behaviour because they are only animals. If some of them are not killed&mdash;and many of them are killed immediately &mdash;they then get to the escape.  This is where the offensive misuse of the word &ldquo;sport&rdquo; comes into it.  Instead of congratulating the gallant and brave little animal for getting away from the greyhounds, the animal is captured again and sent back into the enclosure to await possibly another course that day, and if not that day, another course the following day.  If he survives all that, he will be encased again and be sold to another coursing club and be coursed until he is killed.</P>
    <P>Is that not a remarkably extravagant exercise in calculated cruelty? Surely the kind of mind that does this is capable of doing all these things like Auschwitz and Buchenwald and justifying it?  These are utterly helpless animals; they cannot even talk back or defend themselves.  Most of them cannot even bite you.  And they are about three feet high off the ground.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyMcAuliffe" hpid="Mr. McAuliffe Mr. McAuliffe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAuliffe</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator never <Col N="174" /> caught them, or he would know about bites.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry, I hope the Senator was not badly hurt, was he?  He survived anyway.  That was a good thing.  If he were to do to me the things that are done with the hare, I would bite him, too.  However, the slipper is the man who lets the dogs off after the little hare.  He is the brave man that stands behind the dogs.  He has the decision whether to give the hare a fair run for his money or whether to have sport&mdash;kill the hare quickly and blood the young dogs, because the dogs have to be blooded apparently.</P>
      <P>This is the kind of crude, simplistic thinking about animal behavour which could only be the product of extraordinarily ignorant minds.  I just quoted there Dr. Fairley who spent between ten and 20 years exclusively working on the history and lifestyle of a fox and says he could write a book possibly on what he has found, and there would be a volume of questions to be asked about the behaviour of a fox after that. This of course is true of all animals, including ourselves.  There is no absolute proof that an animal must be blooded before he will hunt no more than there is that a youngster who is blooded in this horrible way by the blood of a dead animal is going to hop up on a horse at the first possible opportunity and look for some unfortunate animal in order to hunt him and kill him.</P>
      <P>Coursing is a disgusting practice. There is no doubt that there is a very big vested interest involved in the hunting of hares, but, as I said in relation to the fox, it is possible to have this kind of sport with mechanical animals. In Harolds Cross, Ringsend, and these other dog tracks all over the world there is no reason why one could not have this sport.  I am not opposed to people enjoying themselves, but there is no reason in the world why we should feel that it is sporting to hunt an animal.  We must be the only species in the world that kill one another because we are angry with one another. But we are the only species of animal which hunts for sport and gets fun out of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="175" /> There is a terribly primitive implication in the sickness of the kind of human being that can see nothing wrong in this kind of thing.</P>
    <P>The coursing club is not supervising this sport as it should supervise it.  It is condoning the cruelty of this whole process of coursing.  It is concealing it where it can.  There is documented evidence to show that by the Irish Council Against Bloodsports.  They have gone to the trouble of going to these disgusting meetings&mdash;and a revolting experience most of them must find it&mdash; in order to document the evidence and to show the various failures on the part of coursing clubs.  I should like to quote, if I may, a couple of paragraphs from a committee meeting of the council after the conclusion of the annual general meeting trials of the South County Dublin Coursing Club on the 19th, 21st and 22nd October:</P>
    <P>The bestiality of coursing was emphasised on Sunday last when one hare was caught by two dogs, pulled and tugged, but eventually got away and was again caught by one dog. The dog carried it round for a time by one leg when it again escaped but this time was once more caught by the two dogs.  It was put out of its suffering when eventually the stewards reached the hare and killed it.</P>
    <P>Another example:</P>
    <P>Coursing's mercilessness was emphasized last Sunday when a small young hare released for coursing ran frantically to the wire at the side of a field in an attempt to get out.  It was chased away by the onlookers&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>brave onlookers behind the wire,</P>
    <P>&mdash;&mdash;and then headed for the entrance gate and the real escape.  Just at the gate and freedom it was blocked and it was chased back to the hare paddock for further coursing.  For officials to reach the hounds in order to release the caught hares took from 15 seconds to two minutes and five seconds.  To put the maimed animal out of pain and suffering took anything from one to five blows at the <Col N="176" /> back of its neck with the edge of the hand.</P>
    <P>The last quote:</P>
    <P>Children were brought into the meeting and trials to be taught the lesson that cruelty of the strong to the weak was acceptable.</P>
    <P>Youngsters are encouraged to take the maimed animals and kill them, put them out of their misery.  What an extraordinary way in which to train a child in kindness.  I would ask the Minister to reconsider the provisions of this Bill, if not from a humanitarian point of view, then from the point of view of the good name of the country.  We are the last country in Europe doing this kind of thing.  We are the last barbarians in Europe.  They have all gone through this like us.  They have all gone through the savage era and they have become more civilised.  We are the last among them.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to amend section 23, to delete subsection (7) permitting the taking and killing of hares by coursing and so on, to delete section 26 allowing masters of hounds to hunt and kill otters and stags, badgers and such animals.  This is one omission which would not cost too much.  The case could be made for showing that it will not hurt materially.  There was always a defence of all these other things, bull baiting, bear baiting, bare knuckle fighting, cock fighting, dog fighting, slavery&mdash;all this horrible inhuman behaviour by human beings either to one another or to animals. There is always this materialistic defence of them, but in the end finer qualities in human beings, which exist probably in us too although there is very little sign of it, still persists.  In the final analysis if we do not do it for any of these reasons could we not do it because the rest of Europe has done it?</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryWalsh" hpid="Miss Walsh Miss Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Miss Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Unlike the previous speaker I should like to add my voice to the many Senators who have extended a welcome to this long overdue legislation.  In doing so I should like to pay my compliment to the Minister for a most comprehensive and detailed statement of introduction.  There is no doubt that he has been in consultation <Col N="177" /> with the various sporting and conservation bodies who are interested in the preservation of wildlife, both at national and at local level.</P>
      <P>As a Wicklow woman, I should like to say that Wicklow is one of the prime sporting counties in this country and has a special and very particular interest in this legislation and will continue to demonstrate that interest when the Bill is passed, as I presume it will be, by ensuring the day to day implementation of the new legislation.  Unfortunately or fortunately, the close proximity of Wicklow to the capital has presented us with many advantages, but on the other side with very many problems, not the least is the heavy pressure on our wildlife population.</P>
      <P>Wicklow has often been described as the &ldquo;Garden of Ireland&rdquo; but to a certain section of the community it is regarded more as the &ldquo;back garden of Dublin&rdquo; rather than the &ldquo;Garden of Ireland&rdquo;.  Having said that, I should like to place on record, firstly, the appreciation of the many people in Wicklow who are interested in tourism, of the traffic generated by reason of our close proximity to the capital.  Certainly we appreciate the business that it generates in view of the close proximity to Dublin Airport and the sea terminal of Dún Laoghaire and the many visits that are paid to our beautiful county by the many tourists who come from all over the world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Unfortunately, however, there is one type of visitor which we could well do without.  I refer to the many vandals who come out in droves as day trippers and weekend trippers and who ravage and rape the natural beauty of our scenic county.  I refer not alone to the destruction of our trees and bird life but to the killing of some of our domestic animals.  There is a new cult in vogue at the moment where young boys come out with bows and arrows and go so far as to kill sheep which are the property of the sheepowners of the county.  They kill sheep in our fields and I suppose skin them and refurbish their deepfreezes here in Dublin with them.  I do not know whether one would call this a <Col N="178" /> blood sport or a type of larceny but it is certainly something which no Wicklow person could condone and more particularly no person who would like to be regarded as a sportsman.</P>
    <P>There is another element to which I would refer here.  It is probably irrelevant to the Bill.  That is the incidence of indiscriminate dumping in our county.  Many would-be tourists and trippers who come out from the capital practise it because of the lack of scavenging services and refuse depots in the Dublin area: they literally strew their garbage over our beautiful county.  This is something which we resent.  Particularly as a member of a Wicklow local authority I resent it in no uncertain manner.</P>
    <P>I have referred to the cult of the use of the bow and arrow.  It may sound rather far-fetched and exaggerated to many Senators but it is nonetheless factual.  If anybody doubts my word I can produce the facts to prove it.  I have concrete evidence of it.</P>
    <P>In section 74 of the Bill heavy penalties are envisaged which, if strictly enforced, should combat the ever-growing menace of the poacher. But, taking into account the everincreasing value of game as a source of food, one wonders if the penalties are severe enough.  I would have grave reservations about this.  It is something which I imagine will be dealt with on Committee Stage.  I know that for many years associations like the National Association of Regional Game Councils, the Irish Wildlife Conservancy, the Irish Field and Country Sports Society and the Irish Deer Society have made representations to successive Ministers regarding the preservation of wildlife in Ireland.  It is my belief that the keystone of this legislation will be establishment of the advisory council that has been referred to by the Minister.  I respectfully suggest to him that he would recruit the personnel for this advisory council from representatives at national level of the various sporting organisations to which I have referred.  I think that in that way we will be assured of the specialised knowledge, expertise and <Col N="179" /> practical experience of the men most closely concerned with the conservation of wildlife.  The smooth and efficient working of this Bill would really depend for success on the character and personnel of the proposed Wildlife Advisory Council to be set up under section 13.</P>
    <P>In my opinion if there is anything wrong with this Bill it is that it is so long overdue.  We remember that it is almost half a century since the Game Preservation Act, 1930, was introduced. The Wildlife Bill is a milestone in the conservation of game and the protection of our national heritage.</P>
    <P>As a Wicklow person I should like to deal specifically with deer, which are a source of pride and pleasure in Wicklow.  At last under the terms of this Bill they have got the status which they rightly deserve.  They are no longer regarded as pests but are to be protected under this Bill.  Our red deer, which are becoming extinct, are now included in the list of protected animals under section 23 and the Fourth Schedule.  Other members of the deer family are similarly protected under the Fifth Schedule.  It is worthy of note that Ireland is the only civilised country in the world without laws to protect native deer. Legislation to control deer hunting and deer preservation is urgently required.</P>
    <P>For the first time close seasons will be established.  Under section 33 the Minister will have power to make regulations specifying the type and calibre of weapons used to hunt deer. Our main cause for concern is that there should be a prohibition of weapons which are totally inadequate to control deer.  Their use has been the cause of untold misery and suffering to the deer which are hunted by them.  I refer specifically to the use of the .22 rifle and shotgun.  It has been suggested to me by people who know more about this sport than I do that nothing less than .240 is effective.</P>
    <P>I submit, with respect, that it should not be necessary to obtain a licence to hunt hare or deer with hounds in <Col N="180" /> an open season.  I would not oppose the licensing of packs of hounds to hunt the otter.  With regard to section 44, I feel that the entering of lands while hunting protected wild animals should be allowed without having to obtain the prior permission of the land owner.</P>
    <P>On sections 22 and 29, I consider the Minister should not be obliged to impose the same conditions on residential and non-residential sportsmen when granting licences.  It would be desirable that licences granted to nonresidents should be for specific periods only and not for a full year at a time.</P>
    <P>With regard to section 74, which deals with penalties, I think minimum penalties as well as maximum fines should be laid down and procedures devised to ensure that the rates of fines may be adjusted to keep in line with the real value of money.  The minimum fine for killing a red deer should be much larger than for killing a more common mammal.  It is a well-known fact that poachers who shoot deer have a lucrative market in this city for the animals they kill. For that reason I think the fines for this poaching should be much greater than for other poaching offences.</P>
    <P>Mandatory confiscation of firearms and other articles used in connection with such offences should be stipulated and persons so convicted should automatically lose their licences to hunt.</P>
    <P>Section 34 deals with the netting of hares, which is permissible.  No provision has been made for the netting of hares for the purpose of coursing them.  This omission will require to be rectified.</P>
    <P>Sections 11, 15, 18 and 55 deal with land acquisition and compensation for land acquired.  Accordingly, land may be acquired for reserves and refuges for wildlife through established orders, recognition orders or designation orders.  The procedures for obtaining the agreement of private land owners to the acquisition of land and the conditions for obtaining proper compensation when such land has been acquired is very unsatisfactory and not according to established custom.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="181" /> At this juncture I should like to pay tribute to the many private game preserves that are in existence throughout the country and particularly in my own county, Wicklow.  Firstly, there is one game preserve at Broadlough near Wicklow.  Secondly, we have on the Grangecarne Estate perhaps the only herd of white deer to be had in Ireland. I am open to contradiction on that point.  I do not think that people who keep such game preserves and who give their land for this purpose are amply complimented and compensated.</P>
    <P>Of particular interest to County Wicklow are sections 55 and 56, dealing with the compulsory acquisition of land for nature reserves.  Senators may recall the uproar which was created when a former Dublin County Councillor, Councillor Niall Andrews, proposed the creation of a national park in part of the Wicklow mountains.</P>
    <P>I have no hesitation in announcing that I was one of the shocked groups, so to speak, because of the sad experience we have had of the trippers.  I have referred to the people who devastate our country at weekends.  I fail to see how such a national park could be policed without being a heavy burden on the finances of the State.  Perhaps the Minister has other ideas about this and perhaps there are other people who could demonstrate to me and to many of the members of the Wicklow County Council, particularly to the farmers of the county, that such a park could not only be established but could be controlled and maintained.  I doubt that.  The idea has met with much opposition from the members of the Irish Farmers' Association in the county and it has been under serious consideration for quite some time.  The idea of a national park with free access to vandals and despoilers of all descriptions was something to which the sheepfarmers and the ratepayers of Wicklow did not take kindly.</P>
    <P>While on the question of the preservation of deer, I think the Minister has a problem on his hands.  I would be very loath to see the extinction of the deer population but I think it is on the way.  I also feel that the Department <Col N="182" /> of Lands have another obligation. Wicklow is also famous for afforestation, as the Minister knows well.  If my information is correct, much damage has been done to the young trees by some of these deer.  I do not blame the deer.  They have got to live. Young conifers or the bark of whatever they go for is a sweet bite.  If we are to preserve the deer and preserve the vegetation there must be a systematic fencing programme initiated by the Department.  The two of them do not go hand in hand.</P>
    <P>I am strictly opposed to poaching in all its forms, but there is one poacher in respect of whom I would lean slightly in the other direction and that is the farmer who is being beseiged by deer which comes down from the mountains and eat his crops, particularly root crops.  This happens within three miles of where I live.  In these times it costs so much to plant a crop, to buy seed and fertilisers, that no farmer can afford to lose a crop whether it be through vandalism or through pests.  I would give a certain <i>carte blanche</i> to a poacher such as that. I would be the first to make representations to the Minister on behalf of a farmer who was being pestered in such a manner.</P>
    <P>I referred to the fencing policy I should like to see initiated by the Department of Lands, and this brings me to the question of sheep.  As a former member of Wicklow County Committee of Agriculture the question of sheep scab in Wicklow often arose. One excuse which was often presented to the agricultural instructor and the various inspectors, of Departments and otherwise, was that sheep found refuge within the State afforestation plantations and that they could not be rounded up at sheep-dipping time.  I could not stress too forcibly the point that our young plantations must be fenced properly.</P>
    <P>I was disappointed that most of the Senators spoke of the gory details of &ldquo;this horrible blood sport business&rdquo;. They painted very grim pictures.  But very few saw fit to speak of the flora end of this legislation.  They dealt mainly with fauna.  I should like to <Col N="183" /> recite a little poem I learned when I was a child:</P>
    <P>A garden is a lovesome thing, God wot.</P>
    <P>Rose pool, ferned grott&mdash;</P>
    <P>The veriest school of peace.</P>
    <P>And yet the fool contends that</P>
    <P>God is not.</P>
    <P>Not God</P>
    <P>In gardens where the eve is cool?</P>
    <P>Nay, but I have a sign&mdash;</P>
    <P>`Tis very sure</P>
    <P>God walks in mine.</P>
    <P>Having said that, I will go back to the Garden of Ireland, Wicklow.  We have many beautiful plants that are almost extinct.  We have a very famous oak wood in Shillelagh which is certainly in need of preservation.  Timbers from that wood have gone to the construction of Liverpool Cathedral and many famous buildings on the Continent.  I regard it as part of our national heritage in Wicklow and I should like to see it preserved.  The Burren in Clare is the only place in the world where wild orchids grow in abundance and where there are many tropical plants which are not found in many parts of the Continent.</P>
    <P>In conclusion I should like to say that the various interested organisations <Col N="184" /> with whom I have had consultation since this Bill was first furnished to us, have unreservedly welcomed it. I have had two of them in the House with me since the Bill was introduced. I have no doubt that they will have suggestions to make to me and other Senators on the Committee Stage. There are many amendments that can be made on that Stage.  I commend the Minister for introducing it and I hope the Bill will have a smooth passage through the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>What is it proposed to take tomorrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesSanfey" hpid="Comdt. Sanfey Comdt. Sanfey">
      <NameTxt>Comdt. Sanfey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to continue with the Wildlife Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>What about Friday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesSanfey" hpid="Comdt. Sanfey Comdt. Sanfey">
      <NameTxt>Comdt. Sanfey</NameTxt>
      <P>The situation is unchanged. We are hoping to have the Social Welfare (Pay-Related Benefit) Bill by Friday.  It is proposed to sit at 10.30 a.m. on Friday.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 22nd May, 1975.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>