<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="20" Month="Jun" Year="1924" Vol="7" No="28" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 20 Meitheamh 1924" DateEnglish="Friday, 20 June 1924" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="2759">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2759" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar a 12 a clog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- DEPUTIES AS PARLIAMENTARY SECRETARIES">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - DEPUTIES AS PARLIAMENTARY SECRETARIES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the President if it is proposed to appoint any Deputies as Parliamentary Secretaries in accordance with the provisions of the Ministers and Secretaries Act, 1924, and if it is his intention to submit names in that connection for the approval of this Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the intention of the Executive Council to appoint Parliamentary Secretaries.  These appointments are not subject to approval by the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the President state if such appointments have been made, who filled the appointments and what the appointments are?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Notice of any appointments made will appear in <i>Iris Oifigiúil</i> in due course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I to understand from that that these appointments will not be announced through the Dáil at all, though they are appointments in the Dáil?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>No; they will not be announced except in <i>Iris Oifigiúil.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - DELAY IN PAYMENT OF PENSION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - DELAY IN PAYMENT OF PENSION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="TOMÁS Mac ARTÚIR TOMÁS Mac ARTÚIR">
      <NameTxt>TOMÁS Mac ARTÚIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state what is the cause of the delay in the payment of pension to Mr. J.T. Healy, ex. R.I.C., of High Street, Ballinamore, whose name appears on the list of awards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have had to institute certain <Col N="2760" /> inquiries into this case in order to satisfy myself that Mr. Healy's resignation was really caused by his national sympathies.  As soon as my inquiries have been completed Mr. Healy will be notified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasCarter1921" hpid="Mr. CARTER Mr. CARTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CARTER</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister let me have the result of the inquiries next week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I will communicate with the Deputy as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - KILRUSH COMPENSATION CLAIM">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - KILRUSH COMPENSATION CLAIM.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár) PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)">
      <NameTxt>PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he has received from Anthony Dunleavy of Kilrush, Co. Clare, a claim for compensation in respect of his car, and if he will expedite the consideration of this claim with a view to early payment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed that this claim was investigated by the Minister for Defence, who considered £100 a reasonable sum to pay by way of compensation.  A Paying Order for this amount was sent to Mr. Dunleavy's solicitor on the 24th March, but was returned by him.  No further action has been taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- DAMAGE TO DUNMANWAY PROTESTANT HALL">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - DAMAGE TO DUNMANWAY PROTESTANT HALL.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (for Tadhg O Murchadha) PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (for Tadhg O Murchadha)">
      <NameTxt>PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (for Tadhg O Murchadha)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether a claim for compensation in respect of the occupation of and damage to the Protestant Hall, Dunmanway, Co. Cork, by National Troops has been received from Rev. Canon Wilson, Dunmanway, and whether a settlement of the claim will now be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>A partial claim has been received by the Commissioners of Public Works from the Rev. Canon Wilson in respect of loss of profits and damage to and loss of furniture and effects following on the military occupation of the Cox Memorial Hall, Dunmanway, and the Commissioners are awaiting a further claim in respect of structural damage before proceeding with the investigation of the entire claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - SKERRIES-DUBLIN ROAD">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - SKERRIES-DUBLIN ROAD.</Title>
    <Col N="2761" />
    <Speaker pid="BartOConnor" hpid="PARTHOLAN O CONCHUBHAIR PARTHOLAN O CONCHUBHAIR">
      <NameTxt>PARTHOLAN O CONCHUBHAIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government and Public Health whether he has any power to order the County Dublin County Council to keep the road from Skerries to Dublin in better repair than at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT and PUBLIC HEALTH (Mr. Burke) Seamus Aloysius Bourke">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT and PUBLIC HEALTH (Mr. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer is in the affirmative. A new county surveyor has just been appointed.</P>
      <P>The Chief Roads Engineer of the Department is at present engaged on a special inspection of the roads in Co. Dublin in connection with the trunk road scheme completely received from the County Council on the 18th inst. It is expected that under this scheme portions of the road from Dublin to Skerries will receive attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- LETTERKENNY MENTAL HOSPITAL AFFAIRS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - LETTERKENNY MENTAL HOSPITAL AFFAIRS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár) PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)">
      <NameTxt>PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government and Public Health if he is aware that it is alleged that Michael Blake, the Head Attendant in Letterkenny Mental Hospital, who was absent from his work as stonemason in the hospital for seven days last October, received full pay from the Management Committee, who granted him sick leave for that period; that it is further alleged that during such absence he was setting gas retorts, the property of the Letterkenny Urban District Council, and for which he was paid £6 by the Council, and if, in view of these allegations, he will cause enquiries to be made into the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that any complaint has been made to the Committee of Management of the Letterkenny Mental Hospital with regard to the absence of the Head Attendant from duty without sufficient cause.  The Committee would presumably consider any well-founded complaint against an officer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not appear to have any functions in the matter which will, no <Col N="2762" /> doubt, be considered by the auditor at the audit of the accounts.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- MAYNOOTH MERCHANT'S APPLICATION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - MAYNOOTH MERCHANT'S APPLICATION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN (for Seoirse de Bhulbh) Mr. EGAN (for Seoirse de Bhulbh)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN (for Seoirse de Bhulbh)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Justice if he is aware that Messrs. M. and J. Dawson, of Maynooth, have applied for a licence to sell cartridges, etc., which up to date has not been granted, and whether, in view of the fact that the firm in question is of high standing, he will enquire into the matter, and if satisfied order a licence to be issued.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>An application for registration as dealers in firearms and ammunition was received last January from Messrs. M. and J. Dawson, Maynooth, but no additions have been made to the number of such dealers since the 18th of December last.  On the 25th April, in reply to an inquiry, Messrs. Dawson were informed that if it was decided to appoint additional dealers their application would receive careful consideration.</P>
      <P>I intend shortly, slightly to increase the number of registered firearm dealers, and I shall consider this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - FINEA (WESTMEATH) ARRESTS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - FINEA (WESTMEATH) ARRESTS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEÁN O LAIDHIN SEÁN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Justice if he is aware that Peter Harten and John Arkins, both residing at Finea, Westmeath, were arrested by the Gárda Síochána on May 10th, 1924; and whether, seeing that no charge has been preferred against them, he will order their release.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware that Peter Harten and John Arkins, both of Finea, County Westmeath, were arrested on the 10th ultimo, and detained under the Public Safety (Powers of Arrest and Detention) Temporary Act, 1924, on very strong suspicion of having been engaged in an attempt to overthrow by violence the established form of Government of the Saorstát. It is not proposed to release them for the present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say when it is likely that he will charge them?  When does he intend to bring <Col N="2763" /> them into court and have the charges proved against them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of that question, will the Minister say whether these two men are Irish or English, or where did they come from?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>For the information of Deputy Gorey, I may tell him they are two farm labourers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>They have very queer names.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.  -" RHead="LAUSANNE TREATY.&mdash;PUBLICATION OF DOCUMENTS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - LAUSANNE TREATY.&mdash;PUBLICATION OF DOCUMENTS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for External Affairs if his attention has been drawn to the fact that the Canadian Government has published its correspondence with the British Government respecting the Lausanne Treaty and if he will publish and circulate to Deputies any correspondence between the Executive Council and the British Government respecting the same Treaty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="MINISTER for EXTERNAL AFFAIRS (Mr. Fitzgerald) Desmond FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for EXTERNAL AFFAIRS (Mr. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware that owing to apparently conflicting statements made by the British and Canadian Governments relative to this matter, it was agreed that the correspondence between them should be published. The same circumstances do not obtain with regard to the Irish Free State, and it is not proposed to publish the correspondence between this Government and the British Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister consider that the example of Canada is only to be praised when it is embodied in a Constitution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister propose to make any statement in regard to this question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, this matter will come before the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.  -" RHead="OCCUPATION OF PETTIGO HOUSE BY NATIONAL TROOPS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - OCCUPATION OF PETTIGO HOUSE BY NATIONAL TROOPS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesSprouleMyles" hpid="Major JAMES S. MYLES Major JAMES S. MYLES">
      <NameTxt>Major JAMES S. MYLES</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether National Troops are still in occupation of the private house of Sir John Leslie at <Col N="2764" /> Pettigo; whether Sir John Leslie has offered alternative accommodation, which has not been availed of, and if he will state when he may expect to regain possession of this house, which has been occupied by three different armies during the past three years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President (Minister for Defence) The PRESIDENT (Minister for Defence)">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT (Minister for Defence)</NameTxt>
      <P>Troops still occupy Sir John Leslie's house.  I am not aware that he has offered to provide alternative accommodation for them, but I am having the matter investigated and will communicate the result to the Deputy as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - LIFFORD ARMY ACCOUNT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - LIFFORD ARMY ACCOUNT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesSprouleMyles" hpid="Major MYLES Major MYLES">
      <NameTxt>Major MYLES</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he has received an account for the sum of £16 12s., due to Mrs. Argue, of Lifford, and if he will state when payment may be expected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Accounts amounting to £11 12s. and £5 have been received from Mrs. Argue, the former in respect of billeting an officer subsequent to 31st December last, and the latter for cartage of rubbish during period August to December, 1923.</P>
      <P>In the former case, enquiries are being made with a view to establishing the identity of the officer concerned and the necessity for billeting him.  In the latter case the account is under local investigation.  The necessary enquiries in both cases will be completed as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - GORTAHORK (TIRCONAILL) CLAIM">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - GORTAHORK (TIRCONAILL) CLAIM.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesSprouleMyles" hpid="Major MYLES Major MYLES">
      <NameTxt>Major MYLES</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he has received an account on various occasions from Mr. Hugh O'Duffy, of Gortahork, Tirconaill, for the sum of £15; whether this account is long outstanding, and if he will state when payment may be expected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>An account has been received from Mr. O'Duffy for professional fees in respect of valuation of furniture.  It will be considered by the Office of Public Works, which Department is responsible for the settlement of claims arising out of military occupation of premises.  Settlement of the account will be expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - BALLINAMORE EX-CAPTAIN'S PAY">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - BALLINAMORE EX-CAPTAIN'S PAY.</Title>
    <Col N="2765" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="TOMÁS MacARTÚIR TOMÁS MacARTÚIR">
      <NameTxt>TOMÁS MacARTÚIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state when it is intended to pay Mr. Michael Martin, of High Street, Ballinamore, Co. Leitrim, an ex-Captain of the National Army, his rank pay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Mr. Martin is not entitled to rank pay, as his promotion was unauthorised and irregular, and cannot be approved.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- MOHILL (CO. LEITRIM) SHOOTINGS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - MOHILL (CO. LEITRIM) SHOOTINGS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="TOMÁS MacARTÚIR TOMÁS MacARTÚIR">
      <NameTxt>TOMÁS MacARTÚIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state what awards have been made in the cases of Mr. Francis O'Reilly, Miscawn, Aughnasheelin, Ballinamore, Co. Leitrim; Mr. Geo. O'Reilly, Derrinkeher, Ballinamore, Co. Leitrim; Mr. Michael Wrynn, Tarmon, Ballinamore; Mr. John Connolly, France, Ballinalee, Co. Longford; Mrs. Byrne, Currycramp, Dromod, Co. Leitrim, and Mrs. Baxter, Kildough, Bawnboy, Co. Cavan, in respect of the loss of their sons, who were shot at Selton, Mohill, Co. Leitrim, by British forces, in March, 1920.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not appear to have received claims from Mr. Francis O'Reilly or Mrs. Byrne.  Forms of application have now been sent to them.  The claims made by Mr. George O'Reilly, Mr. Michael Wrynn, Mr. John Connolly and Mrs. Baxter are on the point of being assessed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - DRUMSHAMBO BARRACKS RAID">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - DRUMSHAMBO BARRACKS RAID.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="TOMÁS MacARTÚIR TOMÁS MacARTÚIR">
      <NameTxt>TOMÁS MacARTÚIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state what award has been granted to Mrs. Ellen Dolan, of Derrada, Ballinamore, Co. Leitrim, in respect of her son, James Dolan, of the National Army, who was shot in Drumshambo Barracks during a raid by Irregulars.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>A gratuity of £25 was paid to Mrs. Mary Dolan on the 11th instant in respect of the death of her son, James Dolan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasCarter1921" hpid="Mr. CARTER Mr. CARTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CARTER</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the President reconsider that and see if something more could not be given, as she is a very poor woman?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2766" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I am informed that Mrs. Dolan, not having been wholly dependent on her son, a pension does not issue.  The gratuity was assessed owing to the necessitous circumstances of the case.  I should say that the method of assessment is on a basis of dependency, or partial dependency, and to that extent it is limited by reason of the maximum which is granted.  I will undertake to look into the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- ENNIS APPLICATION FOR WOUND PENSION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - ENNIS APPLICATION FOR WOUND PENSION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár) PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)">
      <NameTxt>PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will expedite the consideration of the case of Patrick Mahony, Old Mill Street, Ennis, for a pension in respect of wounds received by him in action at Tralee, and in consequence of which he was discharged from the National Army as totally incapacitated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would refer the Deputy to the reply given to a question asked by Mr. Connor Hogan regarding the case on the 22nd February last.  Mr. Mahony has not yet returned the form of application.  Another has now been sent to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - DRIMOLEAGUE BILLETING ACCOUNT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - DRIMOLEAGUE BILLETING ACCOUNT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="TADHG O MURCHADHA TADHG O MURCHADHA">
      <NameTxt>TADHG O MURCHADHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that a sum of £94 5s. 6d. is due to Mrs. Mary Crowley, East End, Drimoleague, Co. Cork, in respect of a revised billeting account, for meals supplied to prisoners and drinks supplied to troops as per orders of Dr. Fuller, Drimoleague, and whether seeing that the above accounts are certified, he will arrange for a settlement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The amount mentioned by the Deputy is the balance of an account in respect of which Mrs. Crowley has been paid £204 16s. 9d. The account is very involved and careful investigation will be necessary before a settlement in regard to this balance can be reached.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- CARRICK-ON-SHANNON TRADER'S ARMY ACCOUNT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - CARRICK-ON-SHANNON TRADER'S ARMY ACCOUNT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="TOMÁS MacARTÚIR TOMÁS MacARTÚIR">
      <NameTxt>TOMÁS MacARTÚIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister <Col N="2767" /> for Defence if he will state what is the delay in the payment to Mr. Thomas Carthy, Carrick-on-Shannon. Leitrim, for cars and food supplied by him to the National Army.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Accounts amounting to £20 2s. Od. contracted by Volunteers prior to the formation of the National Army on the 1st February, 1922, in respect of motor hire and accessories have been received.  They are not a charge on Army Funds, but they will be considered when the Indemnity Bill. 1924, which is at present before this House, becomes law.</P>
      <P>Similar accounts amounting to £54 1s. 9d., contracted by the Army, have been assessed at £43 14s. 2d., and this amount was paid on the 23rd ultimo.</P>
      <P>No claim in respect of food supplied appears to have been received at Headquarters. If a detailed statement of the amount alleged to be due is forwarded by Mr. Carthy to the Cashier. Army Finance Office.  Portobello Barracks, Dublin, it will receive due attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- WOUNDED EX-CAPTAIN'S ARMY PENSION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - WOUNDED EX-CAPTAIN'S ARMY PENSION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEÁN O LAIDHIN SEÁN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that several applications for a pension have been made by ex-Captain Naughton, c/o William Kennedy, Monksland. Athlone; that this Officer, who attested on March 3rd, 1922. and who was demobilised on November 27th 1923, was wounded on July 24th, 1922, and whether a decision in this case will be expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret the delay in disposing of Mr. Naughton's claim. It has been due to the difficulty of providing for the medical examination. necessarily a slow matter, of a large number of applicants for wound pensions. Mr. Naughton will be examined by a Medical Board on the 25th instant. A decision will be arrived at shortly afterwards.  There was only one Medical Board dealing with the work, and we have made arrangements within the past week or fortnight to have three Medical Boards sitting.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.  -" RHead="THE RETURN OF SURRENDERED GUN TO KINNEGAD MAN">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - THE RETURN OF SURRENDERED GUN TO KINNEGAD MAN.</Title>
    <Col N="2768" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWalterShaw" hpid="Mr. PATRICK. W. SHAW Mr. PATRICK. W. SHAW">
      <NameTxt>Mr. PATRICK. W. SHAW</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that Mr. C. Glennon, of Kinnegad, Co. Westmeath, has been notified from Beresford Barracks, the Curragh, that he will require to call personally for the return of his gun to the above barracks, and whether, as this course would entail considerable trouble and expense, he will arrange that in this case, and in similar cases, the guns will be sent to the nearest Gárda Síochána or Military Barracks in the district where the owners reside.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the practice when arranging for the return of surrendered arms to send them to the military post nearest to the owner's address.</P>
      <P>Mr. Glennon's gun is being sent to the Mullingar Military Barracks and may be obtained there on application by the owner.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- THE ENLISTMENT OF CONTRACTED LABOURERS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - THE ENLISTMENT OF CONTRACTED LABOURERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKHogan" hpid="PADRAIG K. O hOGAIN PADRAIG K. O hOGAIN">
      <NameTxt>PADRAIG K. O hOGAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that men are being enlisted in the National Army who had made contracts for the year with farmers, and without getting references from their last employers to see that they were free to enlist; and whether he is aware of the inconvenience caused to farmers by men being taken away from them in the middle of the season.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of those matters, and I feel certain that no men are being induced by recruiters to break contracts of employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE LEGISLATIVE" RHead="PROGRAMME">
    <Title>THE LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Before proceeding with the Orders of the Day, I would like to ask the President if he is in a position now to say anything about his proposal regarding the Legislative programme for the remainder of the Session?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope to have the programme ready for the Deputies before the adjournment this evening. And I propose to move to take public business until 3 o'clock so as to dispose of the items on the Orders for the Day; that would leave one hour for the resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it intended to take No. 7 (The Local Elections Postponement (Amendment) Bill, 1924), to-day?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2770" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to stop at 3 o'clock in any event in order to take Private Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, we are getting the matter typed or roneoed, and I expect to have it before the adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we to go straight down the Orders of the Day?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, sir; as straight as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It is suggested that the Ministerial business be not interrupted until 3 o'clock for the purpose of taking up private business on the Orders of the Day.  Is that agreed to?</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="TELEPHONE CAPITAL BILL," RHead="1924&mdash;FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>TELEPHONE CAPITAL BILL, 1924&mdash;FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask the leave of the Dáil to introduce this Bill, which is one to enable money to be advanced from the Exchequer to the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs for the purpose of telephonic extension.  The money will be charged to a special account, and will be repayable by means of terminable annuities over a period not exceeding twenty years.  The title of the Bill is&mdash;&ldquo;A Bill to grant money for the development of the telephonic system of Saorstát Eireann, and for other purposes connected therewith.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That leave be granted to introduce the Telephone Capital Bill, 1924&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill read a first time.</P>
      <P>Second Stage fixed for Wednesday, 25th June.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="TRADE LOANS (GUARANTEE) BILL," RHead="1924.&mdash;FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>TRADE LOANS (GUARANTEE) BILL, 1924.&mdash;FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Minister for Industry and Commerce I am moving for leave to introduce this Bill, the purpose of which is as follows:&mdash; A Bill to enable the Minister for Industry and Commerce to guarantee certain classes of loans the application of which is calculated to promote employment in Saorstát Eireann, and to grant <Col N="2771" /> or guarantee certain classes of loans the application of which is calculated to promote a reduction in the retail prices in Saorstát Eireann of essential commodities, and to make provision for the application of public monies in or towards the fulfilling of such guarantees and the granting of such loans.</P>
      <P>The Government feel that controlling prices is not the way to reduce prices, and the most effective way is to guarantee loans to consumers or purchasers, or a combination of both, who will agree to sell the essential articles at reasonable prices.  Hence the last paragraph.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister in a position to say that this is the Bill that the Minister for Industry and Commerce has mentioned is the equivalent of the British Trade Facilities Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it ready for distribution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It is ready for printing, but not yet ready for distribution.</P>
      <P>Question: &ldquo;That leave be granted to introduce the Bill&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill read a first time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is very urgent, and I would suggest that the Second Stage be taken on Tuesday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I protest against this.  It is a very important and a very urgent Bill, and a Bill which I hope we shall be able to pass before many weeks are over.  I think, however, it is too much to expect us to take the Second Stage on Tuesday.  The period is too short.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is, I agree, a very urgent and a very important one. We are all very anxious to have it passed before the end of the Session. The fact is that the Minister for Industry and Commerce will be in the Seanad in connection with the Railway Bill, and on that account there is a special reason why we should have the Second Stage on Tuesday.  Full consideration could be given to the Bill on <Col N="2772" /> the Committee Stage.  The Bill is a very short one, and it will be printed and circulated to-morrow evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That explains the reason why there should be further delay.  The Bill will not be in the hands of Deputies until Monday, and possibly, in many cases, Tuesday.  It is quite unreasonable to expect us to be able to deal even with the principle of the Bill at Tuesday's sitting.  Much as I would like to facilitate the measure. I protest against this kind of rushing.  We rather relaxed our vigilance because of the hope of an early adjournment, but now we must abandon that attitude, and we must resume our vigilance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>There are already eight Bills on the Order Paper for Tuesday, and would this Bill suffer very much by being put back to Wednesday? If it takes its place at the bottom of the Order Paper for Tuesday, it may not have a chance of coming on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am only too well aware of the number of Bills down for Tuesday.  In view of what Deputies have said I suppose I cannot press for Tuesday.  Will Deputies agree to Wednesday?</P>
      <P>Second Stage ordered for Wednesday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="FISHERIES (ELECTION OF CONSERVATORS" RHead="POSTPONEMENT) BILL, 1924 (FIRST STAGE)">
    <Title>FISHERIES (ELECTION OF CONSERVATORS POSTPONEMENT) BILL, 1924 (FIRST STAGE).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="FIONAN O LOINSIGH FIONAN O LOINSIGH">
      <NameTxt>FIONAN O LOINSIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>Sé an fáth atáim ag iarraidh cead ó'n Dáil an Bille seo a thabhairt isteach, go bhfuil se riachtanach togha a se' reachtula bheith ann roimh deire an Fhoghmhair. Tá Bille ar an gceist seo ullamh agus chuireas chun oifig an Dli é seachtmain o shoin.  Ach mar gheall ar an obair atá acu annsin, ni bheadh se ullamh an tseisiún seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In asking leave to introduce this Bill I may say that the reason is that the Fisheries Bill which I had prepared, and which I sent to the draftsman a few weeks ago.  I find has been crushed out and cannot be introduced this session. The draftsman has so many Bills <Col N="2773" /> in his office that he has informed me to that effect.  That Bill proposes to change to a certain extent the existing constitution of Boards of Conservators and I am anxious that the statutory elections, which fall due in October next should be postponed until they are held under the new conditions. Elections are triennial, and if I have not leave to postpone them, those elected under the existing conditions hold office for three years.  There are only two sections in the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister propose that these elections be held immediately after the passing of the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. LYNCH Mr. LYNCH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYNCH</NameTxt>
      <P>As soon as possible. Certain formalities have to be gone through in the way of notices, etc.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that there is general complaint as to the composition of these Boards?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="Mr. LYNCH Mr. LYNCH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYNCH</NameTxt>
      <P>That is exactly what I want the elections postponed for, so that the constitution of these Boards may be altered according to the provisions of the new Bill.</P>
      <P>Leave given to introduce the Bill.</P>
      <P>Bill read a First Time; Second Stage ordered for Wednesday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MILITARY SERVICE PENSIONS" RHead="BILL, 1924.&mdash;FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>MILITARY SERVICE PENSIONS BILL, 1924.&mdash;FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move for leave to introduce a Bill to provide for the payment of military service pensions to certain members and former members of the National Forces and the Defence Forces of Saorstát Eireann. This Bill, with one which was introduced yesterday, will, I hope, remedy some of the omissions of the last year and provide compensation and allowances for persons who have rendered good service.</P>
      <P>Leave given to introduce the Bill.</P>
      <P>Bill read a First Time; Second Stage ordered for Wednesday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="AGRICULTURAL PRODUCE (EGGS)" RHead="BILL, 1924&mdash;FOURTH STAGE">
    <Title>AGRICULTURAL PRODUCE (EGGS) BILL, 1924&mdash;FOURTH STAGE.</Title>
    <P>SECTION 3.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2774" /> In Section 3 (1) (e), page 3, line 9, to insert after the word &ldquo;exported&rdquo; the words &ldquo;by the registered proprietor.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This is purely a drafting amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I have again to draw attention to the fact that these amendments have not been given due notice of.  We knew that the Report Stage was to be taken to-day, but we did not know what the amendments were. This is too short a notice, and I just want to register a formal protest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan) MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not think of inserting any amendments on the Report Stage, except a purely drafting amendment and amendments which have been debated on the Committee Stage and which we agreed to leave over to the Report Stage.  However, I see the force of the Deputy's protest.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In Section 9 (4), page 6, line 22, to delete the words &ldquo;on or.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the debate on the Intoxicating Liquor Bill, it was perfectly obvious that we had to take out the words &ldquo;on or&rdquo; to make it quite clear that accounts should be rendered before the 17th March.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In Section 9 (7), page 6, line 46, to delete the words &ldquo;on or&rdquo; and to delete the word &ldquo;on&rdquo; after the word &ldquo;March&rdquo; in the same line and substitute therefor the words &ldquo;in the year in respect of&rdquo; and in line 48 after the word &ldquo;as&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;on and.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is consequential on amendment No. 2.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In Section 18 (1) page 10, to delete all words after the word &ldquo;shall,&rdquo; line 48, to the end of the sub-section and to substitute therefor the words &ldquo;be punishable accordingly.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2775" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>With reference to this and other amendments to Section 18, Deputy Johnson pointed out in the Committee Stage that the section could perhaps be differently drafted so as to arrive at the same result.  The effect of this amendment will be to make Section 18 read as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Any person who sells, exchanges or barters or offers or exposes for sale, exchange or barter any eggs which are externally dirty or which are unfit for human consumption, shall be guilty of an offence under this section and shall be punishable accordingly.</P>
      <P>Deputy Johnson drew attention to the fact that the latter part of that section was repeated a few times in the section and that perhaps it could be differently drafted.  For that reason we put in &ldquo;shall be punishable accordingly.&rdquo; Later on there will appear an amendment which will set out the offences and fines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I do not understand this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>We debated an amendment to this section in Committee and the amendment which I suggested on that occasion was accepted.  But Deputy Johnson pointed out that possibly we might draft the section differently, with a view to preventing repetition of the offences set out.  The section will then go on:&mdash;</P>
      <P>With a view to preventing the sale, exchange or barter, and the offering or exposing for sale, exchange or barter of eggs which are externally dirty or are unfit for human consumption the Minister may by order make regulations in regard to all or any of the following matters, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)the packages and packing materials used for packing eggs;</P>
      <P>(b)the method and manner in all or any respects of protecting eggs from wet, damp, dirt, or contamination of any sort while stored or in course of packing or transport;</P>
      <P>(c)the marking for identification purposes of eggs or the packages containing eggs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2776" /> (3)  Any person who contravenes in any respect any regulation made under this section shall be guilty of an offence against this section and shall be punishable accordingly.</P>
    <P>Then at the end of sub-section (3) comes in the new sub-section referred to as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(4)  Any person guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable on summary conviction thereo in the case of a first offence to a fine not exceeding ten pounds, and in the case of a second or any subsequent offence to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for any term not exceeding six months or to both such imprisonment and fine.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>This is another example of the effect of this kind of hurry.  I have not had an opportunity of seeing the Bill as amended in Committee, and there has not been time to examine it.  I see that the Bill I am looking at is the original Bill.  Consequently I am acting in ignorance, but I will take the Minister's word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate the point generally, but this matter was debated in Committee, and the amendment gives effect to the suggestion that was made.  It was agreed that we might change the drafting on the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not finding fault with that at all.  I am pointing out that it is practically impossible for Deputies to do their duty properly when asked to legislate in this fashion. We have to trust the Minister to do it, and I have not the slightest doubt that we may do so.  But, at least, we ought to have an opportunity of being able to find out if the promises that were made are being embodied in the amendments. The Minister circulated the Bill to-day, and these are the amendments. No doubt they are satisfactory, but we have to act by faith.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Supposing we had six months to put the Bill through, and that there was a drafting amendment agreed to on Committee for insertion <Col N="2777" /> on the Report Stage, would the Deputy in any circumstances get that drafting amendment except on the Orders of the Day, or would it be considered necessary that we should get it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.  If it is merely a drafting amendment we can only take the Minister's word for that. We should be in a position to check it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I have read the whole Section, as amended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The idea of this section is to reach, not only exporters, but people who do a wholesale trade internally, so that they should be compelled to mark their eggs, and to collect and pack them under proper conditions. It was agreed that we should take power in this Bill to make regulations compelling them to do that.  This is the new section for that purpose.  I will insert the amendments in the proper places.</P>
      <P>(1)  Any person who sells, exchanges, or barters or offers or exposes for sale, exchange or barter any eggs which are externally dirty or which are unfit for human consumption shall be guilty of an offence under this section, and shall be punishable accordingly.</P>
      <P>Sub-section 2 goes on:&mdash;</P>
      <P>With a view to preventing the sale, exchange, or barter, and the offering or exposing for sale, exchange or barter of eggs which are externally dirty or are unfit for human consumption, the Minister may by order make regulations in regard to all or any of the following matters, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  the packages and packing materials used for packing eggs;</P>
      <P>(b)  the method and manner in all or any respects of protecting eggs from wet, damp, dirt, or contamination of any sort while stored or in course of packing or transport;</P>
      <P>(c)  the marking for identification purposes of eggs or the packages containing eggs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2778" /> That gives us all the powers we want as against the wholesaler, producer or dealer.  It gives us power to make regulations with regard to packages and packing materials, and power to make regulations as to the collection of the eggs, and protecting them from &ldquo;wet, damp or dirt.&rdquo;  It also gives power to compel the wholesaler or producer or anyone else, to mark the eggs.  The next sub-section prescribes penalties.</P>
    <P>Any person who contravenes in any respect any regulation made under this section shall be guilty of an offence against this section and shall be punishable accordingly.</P>
    <P>There are three sections, therefore, that provide for punishment, fines and imprisonment, and we see in the next section what the punishment, fines or imprisonment shall be.  Instead of leaving it as it was when Deputy Johnson objected putting the fines in in each sub-section, the new section will read:</P>
    <P>Any person guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable on summary conviction thereof, in the case of a first offence to a fine not exceeding ten pounds, and in the case of a second or any subsequent offence to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for any term not exceeding six months, or to both such imprisonment and fine.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;In Section 18 (2) (b), page 10, line 63, to delete the word &lsquo;and&rsquo; substitute therefor the word &lsquo;or&rsquo;.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In Section 18 (3), page 11, to delete all words after the words &ldquo;shall be&rdquo; in line 5 to the end of the sub-section and substitute therefor the words &ldquo;punishable accordingly.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add at the end of Section 18 (3) a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(4)  Any person guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable on summary conviction thereof in the case of a first offence to a fine not exceeding ten <Col N="2779" /> pounds, and in the case of a second or any subsequent offence to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds, or, at the discretion of the court, to imprisonment for any term not exceeding six months, or to both such imprisonment and fine.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 20.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add at the end of Section 20 a new sub-section as follows:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(4) Regulations made by the Minister under this Act shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after they are made, and if a resolution is passed by either House of the Oireachtas within the next subsequent twenty-one days on which that House has sat annulling such regulations shall be annulled accordingly, but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under such regulations.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Committee Stage Deputy Baxter suggested an amendment providing that any regulations made under the Bill should be laid on the Table of each House.  I agreed to the principle and suggested that I should be allowed to draft what, in my idea, would be a proper section to give effect to that.  This is the section. I think that Deputy Baxter's amendment suggested ten days, but I say &ldquo;as soon as may be after they are made.&rdquo;  There is a common form for a section like this.  This section is drafted in accordance with that form, and gives the Dáil ample time to control, check and alter the regulations. It gives 21 days to do so.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 21.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In section 21, page 11, line 30, to delete the word &ldquo;annually.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>With the consent of the Dáil, and I hope there will not be any disagreement over it, I would suggest <Col N="2780" /> to insert there the words &ldquo;from time to time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment reads &ldquo;to delete the word &lsquo;annually&rsquo; and to insert from &lsquo;time to time.&rsquo;&rdquo;  The section would then read:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;All expenses of carrying this Act into effect shall, to such extent as shall be sanctioned by the Minister for Finance, be paid out of moneys to be provided from time to time by the Oireachtas.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill, as amended, be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Fifth Stage ordered for next Tuesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE DAIRY PRODUCE BILL. -" RHead="REFERRED TO SPECIAL COMMITTEE">
    <Title>THE DAIRY PRODUCE BILL. - REFERRED TO SPECIAL COMMITTEE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps at his stage I might refer to the question that was raised yesterday as to whether the Dairy Produce Bill should not be referred to a Special Committee.  Deputy Johnson suggested that, and I asked for time to consider it.  On consideration I think that it would be better to refer the Bill to a Special Committee, and I take it that it is the Committee of Selection that nominates a Special Committee.  When the selections have been made we can settle the date of the first sitting and the date of the final sitting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The date on which the Committee would report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That could come before the Dáil when the Committee of Selection had met, and the first and final sittings could be decided.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We can make an order now that the Bill be referred to a Special Committee to be nominated by the Committee of Selection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>You will want to state the number, will you not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2781" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, otherwise the Committee of Selection could not select them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Not more than nine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Then we can order that the Dairy Produce Bill be referred to a Special Committee of nine Deputies to be nominated by the Committee of Selection, five, say, to be the quorum.  When we get the names the Minister suggests that we could fix the date on which the Committee will hold its first meeting and the date for reporting back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Would not the Minister consider that the Farmers' Party ought to get special representation on the Committee?  Would he make a special representation to the Committee of Selection to keep that viewpoint before them when the are making the selection?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee of Selection would keep that before them in the light of what the Deputy says.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it suggested that the whole Committee should be composed of farmers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be better for the Deputies representing the farmers to make the point raised by Deputy Wilson when the Committee is making the selection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Certain lines have been followed by the Committee of Selection, and in this case we would like a departure from them.  They have always followed the line of giving representation to parties according to their strength in the Dáil.  We want to depart from that line now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be better not to give such instructions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Wilson is a member of the Committee, and he can bring that matter before them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>And in any case the Committee reports to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>In any case that suggestion is obvious and is reasonable. I propose: &ldquo;That the Dairy Produce <Col N="2782" /> Bill be referred to a Special Committee of nine Deputies to be nominated by the Committee of Selection, and that the quorum of the Committee be five.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion. Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="INTOXICATING LIQUOR BILL." RHead="- SECOND STAGE (RESUMED)">
    <Title>INTOXICATING LIQUOR BILL. - SECOND STAGE (RESUMED).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to add my voice to what Deputy Johnson has said in saying that a Bill of this complicated nature really cannot receive that care and detailed attention it ought to have in the very short time that is at the disposal of this Dáil, the short time, whenever it be, that we are to adjourn for the summer holidays.  In saying that I also want to make it perfectly clear that it is not because I do not think that this Bill is a necessary Bill, and a Bill that ought to receive support and attention at the earliest possible moment.  It unquestionably is all that.  But because it ought to receive not only attention but detailed attention I am very doubtful whether that can justly be given in the short time that is available. That consideration has been impressed upon my mind particularly because in reading the Bill one criticism instantly suggested itself to my mind and I recorded it at the time in the note of a certain word, and I was glad to notice that the word was used yesterday by Deputy Bryan Cooper, and that is the word &ldquo;rigidity.&rdquo;  The Bill is a rigid Bill.  The circumstances with which it has to deal, and the evils and abuses which it purports to correct are all of a very complex kind, and I do suggest that it cannot be said that the hard and fast lines upon which the Bill has been laid out can possibly deal with conditions so complex as the conditions that do prevail in regard to this matter. There is another reason, and that is that the greatest problem, as has already been indicated, is the reduction of licences, and that is not dealt with at all in this present Bill.  While we are at the matter, that matter ought to be gone into with some degree of fullness, and the course ought not to be adopted of leaving certain matters over on the chance that these trimmings round about the central question would be dealt with later.  I am inclined <Col N="2783" /> to think that by the time this Bill has become law, in whatever form it becomes law, there will not be much chance of a Commission being appointed to deal with the other and smaller matters that are left over, and they are very important matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely not the smaller matters?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>The other matters that will be left over after this Bill has been disposed of.  Certain Deputies have suggested that a reduction of licences will lead to a smaller consumption of intoxicating liquor.  I do not think that the facts as known in different countries substantiate that. But in any case licences are too many, and the number ought to be reduced. But the chief objection that I see to this Bill, and I state that I intend to support it, because I think the general lines upon which it is framed are lines that ought to receive support&mdash;is the question of rigidity.  I suggest that to lay down exactly the same time of closing for a hotel in Dublin&mdash;the Shelbourne has been mentioned&mdash;and a publichouse in a remote country district is not, I think, to recognise the essential difference that there is between the two, because if drunkenness is to be diminished it can best be diminished by the system that has been adopted through the Continent of Europe, and that is by making any intoxicating liquors that are to be served only to be served where non-intoxicating liquors and foodstuffs are available; that is, to break up the general bar system.  Now, obviously in the case of a hotel that has no bar, it is not a question of social distinction; it is a distinction of kind, and in the case of the hotel that has no bar, and where drinking, if it has to be conducted, has to be conducted in public, the circumstances are quite different from a house in the country that has nothing except its bar, or where after a certain hour no purchases whatever are made, and the only people to be found there are there for drinking and drinking only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Yet in this Bill the same hour is adopted for one as for the other.  The same principles that are made to apply <Col N="2784" /> to one are made to apply to the other; or, take another case the Minister yesterday mentioned a certain club I think we are all very familiar with, although not with its interior, I hope, but we know the club to which he referred when he made reference to the large amount of liquor that was consumed there.  If I got his reference aright, I believe one can obtain membership of that company of men for sixpence a year, and you can sign for two guests. It is very little other than a disguised publichouse, and the smallest amount of disguise that can be rendered is rendered.  There is a great difference between a club of that kind and a social club that is not obviously intended primarily for drinking purposes, and where, I suggest, the limitation of hours, instead of achieving the purpose the Minister has in mind, and which the Bill purports to achieve, will actually do the very reverse, because I think one of the matters where the rigidity of the Bill is neglecting the essential factors of the case, as these factors do exist, is the neglect of the psychological element in the matter. The Minister knows, I am sure, that the very fact that there is a closing time means whoever is attending at the club is sent round to advertise the fact that closing time is approaching, and the temptation is set up and acted upon when that notice has been received to see that enough drinks are available for a considerable length of time, for another two hours.  A number of drinks are actually ordered in those circumstances which none of the persons there would consider had he had that extra time within which to order whatever he liked.</P>
    <P>It is a fact that in a city like Paris, where you can get a drink at any time of the day or night you wish, there is less drunkenness than there is in a city that has a rigid closing time.  I agree where you have the bar system, where people go in for no other purpose but to stand and drink at the bar, that there is a case to be made out for such places having a rigid closing time.  But to enforce the same closing time for other places where drinking is not the primary purpose of the establishment is rather inclined, I suggest, to cause <Col N="2785" /> that purpose to become primary in the minds of those who would visit&mdash;that they would visit it because closing time is approaching, instead of using it as they might be otherwise inclined to do, mainly if not wholly, for ordinary purposes of social communion.  That is the main fault to which I wish to draw attention, because I think it is a very glaring fault.  I think that if that line is to be adopted you will get the very purpose of the Bill, as I have said, turned against itself.  The case has been mentioned of golf clubs.  At the present time golf is played in full daylight a half hour after closing time, and what will happen?  Men, before they go out will take good care to order enough drinks to be available for them, put them in their lockers against their return, and they will see that a good ample margin is left, so that instead of men going in as they do now, at ten minutes to ten and taking what is quite sufficient for them, not drinking to excess, because you cannot purchase that small quantity long in advance a large quantity will be ordered in advance. The effect of the earlier closing time in cases of that kind will lead to what I have described, and which is not the intention of this Bill, or the intention of the Minister, and I take it the intention of the majority of the Deputies. I am mentioning these things not because there is any essential difference, at least I would imagine there is very little difference, between the purpose the Minister desires to achieve and the purpose that I for one will support fully, and I am willing to support this Bill because I think that after changes and amendments in Committee, it can better achieve its purpose than it can do, or hope to do, in its present form. I say that for myself, I would not find it difficult to come into alignment as far as its purposes are meant.  The question is how far the provisions of this Bill help these purposes.  I suggest to the Minister that anything that is of that rigid kind that neglects the psychological factors of the case, and that acts in defiance of the very great difference there is in the kind of establishments throughout the country where drinks are available is bound to prove irritating, and anything that proves unduly <Col N="2786" /> irritating is a legislative provision which will not achieve the purpose it is intended to achieve.  The two main parts of the Bill that are matters of pressing necessity are, of course, the two last sections.  Very grave evils have occurred, and they must be stamped out as strongly as possible.</P>
    <P>The next gravest evil of this kind in the country, and this is a matter the Minister says he is going to leave entirely open to the House, is in regard to establishments where we have all seen on a fair day a shop with a bar attached with a number of men in it, some of whom are very much the worse for liquor, and yet women and children going into that shop for ordinary purchases.  It is one of the worst sights of the countryside.  I am sorry the Minister has left that matter open in the way he has indicated.  I think there ought to be a very sharp distinction made and, as Deputy Johnson said, and I entirely agree with every word he said, that the owner of a shop in the country ought to make up his mind whether he is going to run it as a public house or run it as a shop, and having made up his mind, stick to his decision.  I have said that one of the gravest matters that this Bill neglected from its consideration was the reduction of licences, which was to be left over for some subsequent Commission to determine.  There are indications to show that when this Bill leaves the Dáil this question of the dual shop in the country will also be left undetermined, and I am sorry for it.  The Minister in doing that has said that he will bow to the will of the Dáil, because he recognises that the case can be made out on purely economic grounds for that. Even if a case could be made on purely economic grounds, I think the social grounds and the decent grounds are the higher grounds to take.  But if he is willing to bend in that matter, then I ask him to indicate in closing this debate how far he is willing to meet reasonable objections that might be argued in Committee, and reasonable amendments that might be put forward to make the Bill a little more flexible than it is&mdash;that the conditions I have indicated, that the public houses where people attend for the purpose of taking intoxicating liquor, and primarily <Col N="2787" /> for that purpose, shall not be treated in exactly the same way as the club, where that is not the primary intention, and not treated in the same way as a hotel, where that is not the primary intention. The fact remains that people who attend a public house attend it for one acknowledged purpose, and they drink the kind of liquor that will achieve that purpose.</P>
    <P>A friend of mine in the country a short time ago had occasion to employ a man cutting his turf, and entertaining him at lunch thought he would try him with a bottle of claret to see how the taste would agree with him. The man drank his bottle of claret and he drank a second bottle of claret, and when he was asked how he savoured that for a drink he replied: &ldquo;Well, it is not too bad a drink, but you know, sir, it is very tedious.&rdquo;  There are a good many drinks that are drunk in places till late hours at night that I am afraid would be described by persons who are in the habit of frequenting public houses as being very tedious. This Bill treats all purposes as being primary purposes within the meaning of this Bill, and while supporting the Bill I do so in the hope that in Committee the Minister will be able to meet amendments in order to make its provisions turn more ways than one and recognise more conditions than one, and render it less rigid and somewhat more flexible.</P>
    <P>
      <b>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</b> took the Chair.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielVaughan" hpid="Mr. VAUGHAN Mr. VAUGHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. VAUGHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The proposed Bill is in many points good and to a great extent the reforms suggested in it are long overdue.  I was glad to hear the Minister for Justice say yesterday evening that he was going to leave clause 12 to an open vote of the Dáil, as it would be placing too great a hardship on rural areas.  In villages and towns the vast majority of licensed holders carry on the retail of all commodities necessary for the rural population, and these holdings are barely, if at all, economic.  Ninety-five per cent. of those licensed holders could not, if this section was enforced, carry out the structural arrangements.  If this section became law it would mean people <Col N="2788" /> would have to build an extra department, and it would mean that an extra person would have to be employed in that department to carry on the business and the volume of business carried on in that department would not allow that, as one part of the trade would not pay.  The result would be that traders would have to give up business and find some other means of livelihood.</P>
      <P>Summer Time is not an accepted fact in practice, as far as the greater part of the agricultural community is concerned, so that 10 p.m. closing would be a great hardship in the rural areas, not so much to the licensed holders as the workers, whose toil is only completed at that hour.</P>
      <P>It is suggested in the Bill that licensed houses are to be closed every, where on Good Friday and St. Patrick's Day.  On Good Friday and St. Patrick's Day fairs and markets have been held in towns throughout the country, and it would be causing great hardship to people who travel long distances to fairs and markets held on those days if the licensed houses are closed.  They are at the fair at six o'clock in the morning, and if they have to wait until 9 o'clock to get refreshments it is unfair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>God help them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielVaughan" hpid="Mr. VAUGHAN Mr. VAUGHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. VAUGHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I say that 9 o'clock opening in the morning would be causing a great injustice to the people in the rural areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy tell us, from his experience, how did they manage to wait in the South of Ireland when they started at 4 or 5 o'clock in the morning?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDaly" hpid="Mr. DALY Mr. DALY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DALY</NameTxt>
      <P>Exemptions were granted for fairs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielVaughan" hpid="Mr. VAUGHAN Mr. VAUGHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. VAUGHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I consider that 9 o'clock for the opening hour would be rather late in country places.  I think the Minister should look into this in the Committee Stage and see if he could carry out the existing statutory hours of sale, say from 7 a.m. to 11 p.m.  I think it would suit people who live in rural areas.  I think the want of consideration for the parties aggrieved by the sections I have referred to is ample reason why I cannot support the <Col N="2789" /> Bill, if the Minister does not see his way to delete these sections I have referred to in the Committee Stage of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is right that I should rise and indicate that the Minister may count on my full support for the Bill so far as principles are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>What about Government interference?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course Deputy Wilson must have his little joke.  I am not going to take up the time of the House after the very full debate that has taken place on the Bill but I think it is right and proper that I should indicate to the House that so far as I and my Party are concerned we support the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There has been a good deal of opposition to this Licensing Bill from various quarters of the country, and, judging by a great deal of the correspondence which I got in connection with the opposition to it, it chiefly came from people who had not read or studied the whole of the Bill, and who knew very little about it. The Minister in his statement yesterday has said that so far as Clause 12, which deals with structural alterations, is concerned, he proposes to leave it to a free vote of the House.  That, of course, is the one really contentious clause in the Bill so far as three-fourths of the licensed houses in the South, West, and Midlands of Ireland are concerned. For my part I am in perfect agreement with the principle in that clause.  That is to say, I think it eminently desirable that drink and other classes of goods should be sold in separate apartments if possible, but, then, the Minister in introducing the Bill, stated that compensation was not being provided for.  The reason that I am opposed to Clause 12 in its present form is not, as I have said, on a matter of principle, but because it is not architecturally possible to carry out the provisions of that particular clause.  A great many houses are so situated that, leaving out the question of expense, it would not in practice be possible or feasible to give effect to the alterations referred to in Clause 12. <Col N="2790" /> This Bill has a great many valuable clauses in it, and it deals with some very distinct, definite, and pressing evils, and I think that probably the greatest evils with which it deals are the drinking of methylated spirits and, to a very much greater extent, of what is known as poteen.  I think that people do not always realise how widespread the evil of poteen drinking is in the country.  Apart from the fact that it defrauds the revenue, the great majority of the stuff manufactured is of a most poisonous nature, and is full of high ethers and of all kinds of objectional poisons, and its effect on the human health is most lamentable.  I am quite certain that the drinking of poteen has a great deal to do with the filling of our lunatic asylums, and the provisions which deal with that have my cordial approval and welcome. Incidentally I might say that I am sorry that the Minister for Finance is not here, as I think that the growth of poteen manufacture is largely due to the very high spirit tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Of course the Minister for Finance must raise his revenue, but I hope that he will consider, when introducing his next Budget, the desirability of making some reduction in the present spirit tax, if for no other reason than for the reason that it would discourage the manufacture of this vile spirit which is playing havoc with the health of the people.  Some years ago the spirit duty was ten shillings a gallon, and at present it is £3 12s., and of course, naturally, it is a very much more prosperous industry now to manufacture illict spirit and dispose of it than when the duty was ten shillings a gallon.  That is a matter which I would commend to the consideration of the Minister for Finance when preparing his next Budget.  Deputy Figgis has referred to the reduction of licences.  I think that there is general agreement that the reduction of licences would be necessary but, as the Minister for Justice has indicated, the reduction of licences is such a very big problem and requires such very careful and searching inquiry, it would need to have a special commission set up to examine into every possible phase of this question. The question of the reduction of <Col N="2791" /> licences cannot be fairly considered without considering at the same moment, the question of compensation to those people who have had their licences taken from them.  There have been a good many suggestions in connection with the reduction of licences, and personally I think as a general principle there should not be any great objection to reducing the number of licences, and having the people whose licences were taken away compensated by those licence holders who were left.  I think that is a perfectly fair and reasonable suggestion.  However, the carrying out of that would require very careful machinery and when we look into the practical details of compensation by the licensed holders who are left it is not as easy as it looks, but I still believe that it could be got over and that that difficulty is to my mind a very excellent reason why the Minister in this Bill did not deal with the question of the reduction of licences.  It is too big a matter and will require very careful going into.  For my part I have no hesitation in saying that I sincerely hope it will be gone into.  I think it will be for the benefit of the community at large that the number of licences should be reduced.  Another important matter touched on in the Bill is the question of clubs.  I have no fault whatever to find with clubs which are properly conducted, clubs which provide food and, possibly, lodging accommodation and so on.  But there is no question of doubt that there is a good deal of damage done by those clubs which can sell drinks at all hours of the day and night right through the country.  From the point of view of the licensed trader it must be remembered that they are paying very heavy licence duty, which is based on valuation, and that they have a lot of other expenses which clubs have not got, whereas clubs pay practically no licence duty except, I think, a nominal one of £1 a year, and they are liberty to sell what they like at any hour of the day or night.  That does not seem to be fair.  I see no reason why clubs should receive special treatment, and I think it reasonable that the hours regulating the sale of intoxicating liquor <Col N="2792" /> in clubs should be the same as the hours regulating its sale in public houses.  There are a good many other matters in the Bill to which at this stage I do not wish to refer.  I suppose they will be coming up on the Committee Stage.  There is, for instance, the very thorny question of the added areas.  I do not profess to have any great firsthand knowledge about the merits of the case put up by the added areas, but I must say that at first sight it does seem rather hard on licensed traders in those areas, that they should not have the same terms regarding hours and so forth as the other licensed traders in the city.  There may, however, be some strong case against it of which I, at the moment, am not aware, but I hope to hear the Minister explain that and various other matters in detail on the Committee Stage.  Taking the Bill as a whole I have no hesitation in giving it my cordial support.  I think it is a definite advance in dealing with a very serious problem and I commend the Bill to the favourable consideration of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN (Clare) Mr. HOGAN (Clare)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN (Clare)</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I may confess that we can never hear the Minister for Justice too often.  In introducing this Bill and listening to his speeches, I was forcibly reminded of what I may call the heroic period in Irish history.  One would recall very properly, in listening to the Minister's speech, the return of Ossian from Tir na n-Og.  We know that that hero, mounted on a white horse, left the land under a charge by his spouse not to touch earth lest he should become a mere mortal, but coming through the Glen of the Thrushes in Wicklow he saw a body of workmen endeavouring to raise a slab of stone or marble, and taking compassion on these poor mortals he leaned forward and, taking the slab of stone or marble, he slung it seven perches away.  The Minister for Justice, or may I call him Ossian O hUigín riding the milk-white steed of the Liquor Bill&mdash;I was tempted to call it the white elephant of the Liquor Bill&mdash;and seeing poor depraved humanity in such a state, rushes forward to lift this slab of moral depravity upwards, but he takes great care that the girth of his saddle is such that he <Col N="2793" /> will not fall amongst men or wrangling clerics like Ossian of history.  He leaves Section 12 in the Bill open to the free vote of his Party.  He faces this issue on a high moral plane, and he asks us to assume and believe that this will help the cause of temperance. That is the basis upon which the Bill is placed, and it is very well worthy of analysis.  Does anybody really suppose that the number of public-houses, or the ease by which drink can be obtained, is the cause of intemperance. Does the Minister believe that?  Does anybody who knows the question thoroughly believe it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Some seven or eight years ago it was common comment that Ireland was more temperate than ever it was; that the young men of Ireland were more temperate than ever they were.  Was there any rigid legislation at that time to force them to become temperate?  There was not, but there was then the result of what one may call the Irish-Ireland movement and the Gaelic League.  This influence raised the people above the low moral standard which we are told we have today. It raised them above that, and it gave them something better to live for, something nobler to strive for than mere satisfaction of desires at the moment. If we want to tackle the temperance question properly we must tackle it as an educational problem. We must have education well sustained and well protected.  Acts of Parliament will never do that, and they have never succeeded in doing that so far as I know.  The publichouse is but a manifestation of the disease, and removing the publichouse is on a par with the doctor who endeavours to treat jaundice by applying a skin lotion instead of treating the blood and the liver of the patient.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Take alone Section 6 of this Bill. What is the need of introducing this section?  Does not the present position of the law in that respect, meet all the requirements?  Does not the Minister know that debts contracted across the counter for drink cannot be recovered as shop debts, and what, I ask, is the need of going any further, I am not pleading for <Col N="2794" /> getting &ldquo;tick&rdquo; in public houses.  I am merely putting the proposition to the Minister that there is a sufficient guarantee at the present time to prevent drink being got in this fashion.  I also put it to him that there is also opportunity for a good deal of abuse in the section.  There is the possibility of involving people whom the publican cannot possibly refuse, and there is the possibility of blackmail under the section on the publican afterwards.  I think the Minister himself will acknowledge that, if he seriously considers the section.  We have heard a lot about section 12, and we have also heard a lot about Clause 12, and Article 12, during the past month or so.  I am aware of the conditions governing the sale of drink in some cities, and in a good many country towns.  There is a possible inference to be drawn from that.  There is an obvious inference, but if you draw that obvious inference it is wrong.  I do agree that there is certainly a need for a separation of the licensing business from that of the other business conducted in city houses, but I do not agree that the same thing applies in any proportion at all to the sale of drink in country districts, or in country towns.  There is no need.  I say for this absolute separation in country public houses.  There is no need in these houses to cut off all internal communication.  That is what is making the matter difficult.  If this provision were to apply, in the case of country public houses, a man would have to go out on the street if he wanted to get from one part of his house to the other.  If such a provision as that is made it will cause a lot of unemployment, because a good many people will have to go out of business as a result of it.  I know hundreds of houses that will not lend themselves to these structural alterations internally. These people, before they got their present licences, had to satisfy the local police authorities at that period that their houses were fitted structurally for the granting of the licences. Now we come along and we tell them that all that is wrong, that there must be another reconstruction, and that they must spend some more money on their premises.  If you have hundreds of houses that do not lend themselves <Col N="2795" /> to reconstruction, as I know you have, and if this provision is to be insisted on, it will mean that the people who have these houses will have to go out of trade altogether.  Their assistants will be dismissed and will be thrown on the unemployment labour market, causing a lot of hardship to great numbers of people.  The Minister has changed what we used to know as the sweet seventeen period in the girlhood scale, and has raised it to impressionable eighteen.  He has told us that you must not put a girl of eighteen behind the bar, even though her father and mother are managing the public house. The father and the mother may become ill, but their daughter, if she is under 18, must not go behind the bar to serve a drink to anybody who comes in. Really, that is stressing the matter too far.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Deputy has read the section.  The section says that &ldquo;any licensed holder who employs any female person,&rdquo; and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That, of course, will raise a very nice point.  Does the father or the mother employ a girl of 18, and will she not at a future period expect recompense for it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>She will get it, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>No doubt the Minister is very much interested, and so should all of us be, in seeing that nothing is done that would be calculated to lower the womanhood of Ireland from the high standard which it enjoys at present. I suggest to the Minister that there are other directions and other channels in which his energies should be directed.  There is nothing to prevent girls of lesser ages than 18 or even 16 from going to theatres and picture houses where the atmosphere is much more morally depraved than in the country public houses.  I suggest that that would be the place for his energies and not places where, if this legislation was carried, three or four people coming into a public house cannot get served because there is nobody there but a girl under 18 years of age.  Again, take the case of trying to advance the cause of temperance in the improved arrangements at theatres.  The Minister <Col N="2796" /> tells us that unless people have seats booked they cannot get a drink before the theatre starts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Deputy read the section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am open to correction, but the point I want to make is that if you want to get a drink in a theatre there is nothing to prevent you booking one seat.  There are two conclusions, to my mind, that emerge from this Bill, and one is that the Government Party that drafted this Bill is hopelessly out of touch with the ideas and thoughts that prevail in the country.  Secondly, and perhaps it is a good thing, the second conclusion that emerges from this Bill, and it is the only matter that I can congratulate the Minister on, is that he seems himself to be entirely without knowledge of the conditions that govern the sale of drink in country towns.  I am in agreement that some remedy is necessary in order to provide for the separation of two sets of business in cities, but in country districts that does not hold.  I suggest to him, as it comes to my mind, that you cannot induce or inculcate temperance, if that is the idea of the Bill, through rigid Acts of Parliament.  An educational programme is one to bring that about, and if he would attack that programme and start it, and carry it through, and utilise the power that is in his hands of setting up counter attractions in these places, perhaps he might find the public house would not be such a source of evil, and perhaps he might find the standard of morality and temperance that was in the country some seven years or eight years ago would be revived and increased, and that a good many publicans would have to get out of business for want of people coming to them.  It is by creating these counter attractions you will achieve anything.  I believe the Bill is inadequate for the purpose for which it is brought in, and, therefore, I believe that the cast iron regulations in it should not be supported.  I believe that the Bill in its present form is useless and not worthy of support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel we are suffering somewhat at present, no doubt due to pressure of Bills, from the <Col N="2797" /> fact that the Second Reading of Bills becomes simply a stage in which reference is made to what is contained in this or that particular section of the Bill, and we do not get the opportunity of seeing the Bill as a whole referred to, and its relations to the general matters of social and economic life in the country.  I feel that the Minister would get over some of his difficulties in connection with this Bill if he had been able to give us an impression, in introducing the Bill, of what he would consider an ideal Intoxicating Liquor Bill or an ideal Temperance Bill.  A number of conferences have taken place with different parties interested in it both from the social and commercial point of view, and I am sure very many aspects of temperance were discussed at these meetings.  I am sure that an explanation of what would be the ideal thing to have, though it could not be had at the moment for particular reasons, would be very useful and instructive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Take even Clause 12, where the division of premises for the sale of intoxicating liquor, from business of another kind, is being insisted on.  I think it would be very much easier to get that clause through in the light of an exposition of what the Minister or the Government think the publichouse and such institutions should become in the social life of the country.  These institutions are there, and are bound to stay in some form or another, but it is desirable they should not stay in the particular form in which they exist now. I do not know very much about it, but it seems to me that the point to be aimed at in the Bill as it stands at present could as easily be arrived at in an alternative way.  I would like to see what the effect would be of bringing in a regulation that a person could not take a drink standing, and what I would like to press for now is that the Commission that the Minister spoke of would be set up at the earliest possible moment.  There are restrictions in this Bill which will give rise to a big volume of complaint&mdash;real complaint or complaint simply made for one purpose or another.  At the time that these complaints are arising, and I realise there are a good number of different details <Col N="2798" /> to settle in connection with the liquor or drink traffic in this country, it would be very advisable if the Commission would actually be set up with terms of reference at a time when people perhaps with curious grievances are coming along, so that you would have a pretty definite machine examining what the complaints were.  A Commission such as this should, I consider, get twelve or eighteen months in which to make its report, and to take into consideration a very wide number of things.</P>
    <P>There is restriction, but control of the drink traffic must be looked at purely from the point of view of the requirements and the benefits of temperance in the country, and temperance in the country will cover a very large number of matters, one item of which will be the control of the sale of intoxicating liquors.  It is a matter in which the education of our people has to be considered as well as housing and conditions generally.  There are some people who are very much interested in temperance as affected by education, and who now see a very strict and stringent Bill being brought forward at a time when the very moderate demands of the secondary teachers are being given a deaf ear by the Government.  I do realise that this Bill is intended to be a Bill for the reduction of licences and for the crushing out of a certain number of the licensed houses.  Now you will get much more support for a Bill like that in the light of a policy of temperance fully set out with activities on the part of the Government in different directions that would show that they knew how temperance was really to be arrived at, and what temperance was really to be aimed at.  I therefore press that the Minister, if he has not already done it, should arrange that the commission which has been suggested be set up at once.  I take an interest in the added area districts in Dublin where some of of the owners of the seven-day licensed premises are suffering under an injustice that was not meant to be an injustice. I propose to bring forward an amendment to the Bill dealing with that particular point.</P>
    <Col N="2799" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMcGarry" hpid="Mr. McGARRY Mr. McGARRY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGARRY</NameTxt>
      <P>I intended to reserve what I had to say for the Committee Stage, but I would like to say a word or two now on the general principles. For 11 or 12 years we have been, very assiduously and energetically cultivating disrespect for law and order in this country.  We have taught our people they were doing the right thing when they broke the law, and you are giving them another law to break now.  In general I think if you want to arrive at temperance you cannot do it by legislation.  You cannot legislate our people into it.  I do not think I need stress that.  Everyone knows people will go out of their way to get a drink when they ought not to get it.  On the Continent, for instance, where cafés are open until four or five o`clock in the morning, you never see anyone under the influence of drink simply because a man on his way home has no need surreptitiously to go in by a back way for a drink.  He knows he can get a drink on his way home.  I say, if this legislation is intended to make people temperate, it is going on the contrary to do the other thing.  I am afraid I will have to say something that struck me when Deputy Hogan was speaking.  He said, &ldquo;You want counter-attractions.&rdquo;  It is the counterattractions that bring people into the public houses.  I will say anything I have to say abou the details of the Bill in Committee.  With regard to the question of added areas, and those houses in the city whose seven day licences lapsed because the owners did not apply for them, the Minister gave an undertaking to Deputy Byrne in August last that the question of the added areas houses and those which had seven day licences, but which could not open on Sunday could be considered.  Whether he has considered and decided against the seven-day licences since I do not know, but he gave a definite undertaking, and so far as the members of the Association in those areas who have houses for which they are paying seven-day licence duty are concerned, they are not satisfied that he did consider it.  However I would like to know that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Secondly, there is another class, the men who have the six-day houses in the city.  In some cases the licence <Col N="2800" /> lapsed because somebody was not particular about opening on a Sunday and did not apply for a Sunday licence. The house was sold, and the argument will now be put forward by the Minister that people who bought houses in the added areas, or who bought these six-day houses in the city, bought them knowing that they could not open on a Sunday.  That is so, but they bought them in the hope that they would be allowed to open on Sunday in time, and the hope was always on the horizon. With regard to the added areas, the Clancy Act allowed them to open for, I think, ten months.  Then someone discovered a flaw in the Act and they had to close.  Subsequently a new Bill was prepared&mdash;I may be corrected in this&mdash; but I think a time was allotted in the British House of Commons for the introduction of the new Bill in the Private Members' time.  Owing to the war, the Bill was never presented.  I think that if the Minister wants to reduce the number of houses, let him reduce them, but until he does so I think those two classes of licence holders will be labouring under a disadvantage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe that I can approach the consideration of this Bill without any regard to Party obligations, and certainly without any regard to the numerous appeals, letters and wires that I have received on the subject. When any legislation is being dealt with in this House for the revision of the existing licensing laws, I think we should take into consideration the conditions under which we have been living for hundreds of years in this country.  Any revision of the existing licensing laws should be more by gradual than by revolutionary methods. I want to say right away that while I am opposed to one or two clauses of the Bill as it stands now, I propose to give my vote in favour of the Second Reading, because I believe a case has been made for the revision of the existing laws.  I want to say this much, that in all cases of this kind I am not influenced in any way by the eloquent advocates of the temperance cause.  I have discussed the question many a time with eloquent advocates of the cause of temperance, but many of those advocates are, in my opinion, only reformed <Col N="2801" /> drunkards.  I dare say it is very useful for people to learn in the school of experience, and any lessons that can be taught by people of this kind or by people who advocate temperance as a result of their own experience should be listened to, but I am not influenced in this matter by that particular class of people.  Section 12 of this Bill has been referred to by everybody here to such an extent that I do not think there is anything for me to say.  What is in the mind of the Minister, so far as I am concerned, would get my support, but not in the way it stands in the section at the moment.  I believe it is impossible to put that clause as it stands into operation without doing an injustice, especially in the case of country traders.  I might be prepared to give support to the idea which is in the mind of the Minister if a longer period is substituted.  I think the hardship is too great to impose it in the very short period laid down in the Bill.  With regard to the question of hours, I believe that the Minister is right in the hours he laid down for opening and closing on week-days.  I believe it is quite right that the opening hour of public houses in cities and towns should be in or about 9 a.m.  I am not speaking as a prohibitionist or a temperance advocate, but I believe that the working man or any other class of individual who works or renders service to the State should not be in a position to be able to go into a public house before he starts his day's work.  I am opposed to the clause which lays it down that the public houses should be closed on St. Patrick's Day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the question of <i>bona fide</i> traffic and Sunday opening, I would find it very difficult to justify the uses and abuses of that traffic on the lines on which it is conducted at present.  My own idea&mdash;I have no commission from anybody, and I am not going to be rushed by anybody&mdash;is that if publichouses are allowed to be open anywhere on Sunday, they should be allowed to open everywhere&mdash;that they should be open in all the cities, towns and villages during certain hours all over the country.  You will find, for instance, that if a man in Dublin cannot get a drink at 6 o'clock on Sunday <Col N="2802" /> evening he will go down to Westland Row and take a train to Bray, and perhaps, owing to the liberty allowed him by the licensing laws down there, he will miss his last train home.  I think any legislation which would prevent happenings like that&mdash;to my own knowledge it happens in a great many cases, particularly around the cities&mdash;should be supported as far as possible.  The only solution of that question that I see is to allow every publican everywhere at given times on Sunday, to open and close his house.  Many men who are anxious to obtain intoxicating liquor on Sundays will perhaps, spend 2s. 6d. to get to a place where they can get it, while they will not have, perhaps, another half-crown to spend on drink.</P>
    <P>Regarding the question of clubs, some of the Deputies who have spoken here on the hours of opening are, I think, only looking at this matter from the point of view of the higher-class clubs.  I would not draw a distinction between the hours laid down in a Bill of this kind for any club.  I believe that if the Stephen's Green Club is allowed to be open until 11 o'clock at night, the Workmen's Club on the quays should have the same privilege. I believe that such consideration over and above that given to publichouses in the matter of hours should be given to clubs.  I believe in encouraging competition. The extension of the hours for clubs is the only method I see that is likely to provide the licensed trade in the city with any kind of effective competition.  The licensed trade in the city&mdash;I say this quite frankly&mdash;have not been playing the game.  They did not think fit even to recognise the Commission that was set up by the Government in order that they might convince the Government and its Commission that the prices they were charging were just and fair.  That is the only distance I am prepared to go in the case of clubs.  If the extension of an hour in the case of clubs would create an effective competition against the monopoly that exists in the City of Dublin and in other places, I would be prepared to support that concession for that reason.  I know many workmen who are well conducted and who belong to workmen's clubs, and they <Col N="2803" /> hardly ever visit licensed premises.  I do not think they should be debarred, if they care to get a drink in a club, from that right.  I do think that any man, whether he be a workman or be engaged in any other sort of occupation, should leave his club at eleven o'clock at night if he wants to be fit for his work next morning.  With regard to penalties for abuses of the existing licensing laws, I will go to any extent the Minister may think fit in that direction. I will also support him, particularly, to any extent he may think fit to go, in penalising people who are disgracing this country and demoralising its citizens by taking part in the sale of or encouraging the distribution of poteen.  I have heard some very sad tales told about areas where poteen drinking has been resorted to, and I think any Deputy, or any man charged with responsibility in the public life of this country, should assist those who are endeavouring to put down that traffic.</P>
    <P>With regard to the sale of drink and the employment in licensed houses of persons under the age of 18 years, if it is right to refuse to supply people under the age of 18, it is equally right and equally fair to say that young people, especially girls, should not be employed in those houses.  With regard to the question of structural alterations, I hope the Minister does not mean by the clause as it stands something in the nature of an attempt to wipe out a number of licensed houses. I believe, as other members have said, and quite truly said, that the number of licensed houses in Ireland, and especially in the cities and towns, is excessive.  I think the Minister might compromise on this question.  If he deems it advisable, as I think he says he does, to set up a Commission to deal with that aspect of the case, I think he might agree as a compromise that the question of the injustice or otherwise of putting Clause 12 into operation might be left to the Commission to deal with.  It is not right to insist upon insertion of that clause in its present form, because whether it appears in that light to the Minister or not, it certainly appears to me to be confiscation on a small scale.  To my own knowledge, <Col N="2804" /> in certain parts of the country, in the case of certain old houses, it is impossible to put that clause as it stands at present into operation.  I am prepared in regard to the Bill to listen to the arguments for and against, but in respect of the contentious clauses I shall use my own judgment in voting &mdash;that is, such clauses as Clause 12 and the clause dealing with the hours.</P>
    <P>On the question of the sale of drink, I have often noticed by reports of the Police Courts&mdash;I have myself witnessed the occurrences sometimes&mdash;that individuals were fired out of licensed houses under the influence of drink.  After being fired out, they were arrested by the police, brought into court, charged and fined.  I have very seldom noticed that in these cases the licensed trader suffered in any degree whatever. The licensed trader in a case like that is a party to the crime&mdash;if a crime be committed&mdash;and in such cases he should be prosecuted as well as the individual concerned.  I hope the Minister will give fair consideration to that aspect of the case and bring home to the people associated with occurrences of that kind their responsibility in the most effective way.  There is a clause with regard to the forfeiture of licences for three consecutive convictions.  On that I am quite in agreement with the Minister.  We had, as far as I can see from a considerable experience in travelling, a great amount of liberty over and above that which they had in England, France and other countries. We have abused that to a great extent. When we come to deal with the extent of the abuse of the existing licensing laws, it is not so much a matter for legislation here as it is for the administration of the existing laws by the servants of the Government.  That is the most effective method of dealing with people who are abusing the laws that exist at present or who may abuse the laws that come into operation as a result of the passage of this Bill.</P>
    <P>On the question of the application of the suggested hours in country districts on fair days, I think Deputy McGoldrick suggested yesterday that that matter should be submitted by the trader to the District Justice, with an application to open at an earlier hour than the hours laid down in the Bill, <Col N="2805" /> on the occasion of fair days.  That is the only way out of the matter, and I think the Minister should give very serious consideration to that very useful suggestion.  As I have already indicated, I have no commission in this matter from anybody.  I do not regard myself as being responsible to anyone, or any section, of my constituents in giving my vote.  I have no prejudice against the Bill, because I am not a prohibitionist.  I do believe, however, if we are to get back to our normal position&mdash;the pre-European war position which this country occupied&mdash;we can only do so by useful legislation of this kind.  While I reserve the right in Committee to use my own judgment upon any amendments that may be brought forward to one or two clauses in the Bill, at the same time I have great pleasure, for the reasons I have stated, in voting for the Second Reading of the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnThomasNolan" hpid="Mr. NOLAN Mr. NOLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NOLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>A good many Deputies have already spoken on this Bill, and many have dealt with the interests of a certain class who allege that they have a grievance.  I will just deal with Clause 12, which refers to structural alterations.  I will deal with it from a different point of view than it has already been dealt with.  I have had a little experience of the licensing trade in Dublin.  Instead of putting up a partition in any business premises, I would be in favour of abolishing the snugs, private bars and the screens in publichouses, and I would also be in favour of doing away with the upstairs rooms.  I would leave the place perfectly open, so that any man who comes in to have his drink may be seen by others who may go in there for the purpose of doing other business.  There is an old saying that everything bad is done in the dark.  Any person going for a drink into a place so altered as I have suggested may remain as long as he likes, just the same as he would in a snug.  If the bar forms part of the shop, a person can go in for groceries or meal, and if he feels like it he can have a drink as well.  By leaving the place perfectly open it will be in the interests of temperance.  If anybody has an objection to go into a bar for the purpose of purchasing tea, <Col N="2806" /> sugar, or meal, there are other places in town, with no bar attached, where he could get those things.  Take restaurants as an example.  Drink is sold there, yet there is very little drunkenness. I will vote against that particular clause, not in the interests of the grocers who are victimised by it, but in the interests of temperance.</P>
      <P>There is one matter that is not mentioned in the Bill, and it has reference to occasional licences.  In the old days the resident magistrate or the justices of the peace had power to grant occasional licences to any persons who desired to have a tent at race meetings or gatherings of that sort.  Especially in country towns, race meetings are very often got up for the sake of some local person having a tent for the purpose of selling drink.  I know&mdash;not of personal knowledge, thank God&mdash;that the stuff sold there is anything but right.  I remember a year or two ago a publican got a licence for a tent at a race meeting and the manager of the bar in the tent said that two of the bottles, of what was supposed to be whiskey burst.  You can judge the nature of the stuff in those circumstances. I would like if the Minister would include something in the Bill dealing with this matter.  As regards the sale of wine, it is proposed in the Bill to give permission for the sale of wine to grocery houses.  I do not think that is fair or right.  Some concession ought to be made with regard to hours of opening on fair days.  Some provision could be made by which a man travelling a distance of 12 or 14 miles in the wet perhaps should have a chance of getting a cup of tea or a drink of some sort.  If he cannot get that, he will find some means of getting into a public house, through the back door if necessary, and that is not a state of affairs that should be encouraged. I hope the Minister will take those matters into consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. P. HUGHES Mr. P. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to make one or two remarks in connection with this Bill.  First and foremost, I am going to vote for the Second Reading of it because I believe all legitimate traders will welcome a Bill of this class, which is not of the drastic nature that some people anticipated it would be.  Legitimate traders are anxious to <Col N="2807" /> conduct their business in the best interests of the trade, and I believe that this measure, with very few alterations on the Committee Stage, will be acceptable to the licensed trade both in the city and in the country.  I admit there are objectionable clauses in the Bill. I am not going to refer to Clause 12, because it has been flogged enough already.  There are clauses that could do with slight amendments in Committee, and I am sure that these amendments will be forthcoming.  If they are reasonable ones, I hope the Minister will give them due consideration. There is one thing that the Minister should make provision for in the Bill. At the present time any person who has a valuation of £10 can go to the Excise Authorities and get a wine licence without making any application elsewhere.  I do not think that that is fair to people who have to pay licences to carry on business. Where people pay licences for the sale of wine, as well as other spirits, they should be protected from the person who has a little shop and who gets a licence in the way I state.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this in the interests of temperance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. HUGHES Mr. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>If a man has a £10 valuation he can get the licence from the Excise authorities.  A clause, I think, should be inserted in the Bill debarring people from getting those privileges.  Questions have been raised in regard to the ages of barmaids. These are things that I do not want to go into.  I think a bar is not the place for a little girl of tender age.  To put a girl of tender age behind a counter is not quite right.  At the same time, I believe that members of the licensed traders' family should be allowed to serve people under certain circumstances. With very few amendments I think the Bill is one that will be acceptable to the trade, and I therefore will vote for the Second Reading of it. There are one or two clauses that, with slight amendments, can be made to meet with the general approval of the trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I cannot do better than follow the loyal example of Deputy Hewat, and I will convey to <Col N="2808" /> the Minister what the intentions of my Party in regard to the Bill are.  I may say, however, that they are quite the opposite to Deputy Hewat's.  A great many Deputies have been prophesying what they intend to do on the Committee Stage.  I will endeavour to prevent the possibility of those prophecies ever materialising by voting against the Second Reading of this Bill.  There are undoubtedly some meritorious features in the Bill.  Probably they are more exactly in the memorandum which precedes the Bill, and which is, I think, a very desirable addition in the direction of supplying Deputies with information. I think that suggests a step which might be of great advantage to the discussions here and should, for the information of Deputies, be followed in the presentation of all future Bills.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Follow a good example.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>I also consider that the last two parts of the Bill are of vital importance and of urgent necessity, but I think they are irrelevant in this instance.  They aim at a distinct purpose from the main purpose of this Bill, which is for the regulation of certain beverages, and this is for the entire prohibition of certain things.  I think the combining of the two in the one Bill prejudices the speedy passing into law of that part which I consider important and urgent, and at the same time it gives a fictitious value to the other portion of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The question arises, what is the purpose of this Bill?  Is it merely the regulation of the sale of certain drinks or is it aiming at temperance?  Is it directed to trying to convey the impression that those who are engaged in this business are engaged in an illegitimate traffic?  If that is so, then why these professions of non-prohibition proclivities on the part of the Minister and certain other Deputies?  If it is a legitimate trade, then why have flung at it, by practically everyone who speaks who has never known the joy or the delight of partaking of refreshments which the trade gives, those statements that have been uttered?  Why, if it is a legitimate trade, can the matter not be discussed in the same calm, tranquil and business-like way in which every <Col N="2809" /> other business is discussed&mdash;in which, for instance, the business which Deputy Gorey's colleagues raised yesterday in regard to dairy produce, was discussed?</P>
    <P>I do not know whether I ought to be afraid to suggest that this was the production of minds conscious of the necessity of making up for the sins of mis-spent youth.  I do not see why humanity in the Saorstát should have to pay the penalty for those sins of omission or commission.  We are told that the reduction of hours is going to produce a certain very material reform. The reduction of hours is not very serious or material in extent of time.  There is still quite sufficient time left, both on week-days and on Sundays for anyone whose main or sole purpose is to become inebriated, to accomplish that rather doubtful question of achievement.</P>
    <P>We are told by two or three speakers who gave us the advantage of their experience on the Continent. that they had not had an opportunity of getting drunk over there.  I think it is only fair to say that it is not so much the hours during which these establishments on the Continent are open, as the nature of the beverages that are dispensed.  When Deputy Hughes complains of people who can get a licence for the sale of wines without an application to any authority, I believe that it is a step in the right direction, because to popularise wines instead of whiskey or brandy or stout would be a very good thing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. HUGHES Mr. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>It would increase facilities for drinking in every house in the city and country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>If it produces temperance, why not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. HUGHES Mr. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>If I may interrupt again, I think the Deputy is well aware of the fact that wherever there is a wine licence, you always have another bottle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not a wine licence and therefore I have not another bottle.  I was going to suggest that instead of concentrating upon these artificial and generally unsuccessful expedients, such as rigid regulations, endeavours directed towards temperance with the object of popularising <Col N="2810" /> a particular make of light wine as a beverage for those requiring it, would be very much more likely to secure that desired result.  I think the Minister for Justice could do a great deal in that direction if, in the shops that dispense the beverage, he would authorise advertisements to be hung up indicating that the wines sold there were the same as supplied to the Minister for Justice.  I am sure the example he would set would very speedily be followed by the greater portion of the population.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>There are other classes of advertisements that would require no words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Gorey generally advertises the art of being irrelevant and impertinent.  The question of structural alterations is something which it will be impossible to put into operation, and though it would be interesting to discuss what would be the effect if that were practicable, still it is simply sheer waste of time to prolong a discussion on that matter, because it is absolutely physically impossible to carry this into operation in the greater proportion of the establishments in different parts of the country.  Many of them would have to tear down practically the whole interior of their shops, and reconstruct, and unless the Minister for Finance is willing to subsidise those places, to enforce such a clause in the Bill, or to persist in its enforcement, simply means sending that class of trader out of business. That clause in the Bill cannot stand.  We would be simply legislating for something that we know in advance cannot be carried into effect, and that is simply deluding ourselves and irritating the people of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the question of the reduction of hours, the point has already been made that it will cause serious inconvenience to the people who come into fairs and markets.  That is an undoubted fact. It cannot be pleaded that this provision is intended to be aimed at the prevention of drunkenness or over-indulgence in liquor to any extent.  I challenge any Deputy to recall to his mind any occasion when he saw a man under the influence of drink at 7 o'clock in the morning on a fair day.  If there is <Col N="2811" /> a time when there are reasonable grounds for the reduction of hours, surely it is in the evening and not in the morning.  I commend to the consideration of the Minister, if this Bill does reach the Committee Stage, the suggestion of Deputy Davin, that on application to a District Justice, or some other authority, some arrangement could be made to meet the convenience of the people concerned.</P>
    <P>Another point as to the reduction of hours is that the licence fee that has been paid by those who own these establishments has been based on a certain numbers of hours' trading.  If you are going to reduce the number of hours of trading upon which that fee was based, then I think it is only fair and equitable to the traders that the fee should be reduced.  I am thoroughly in agreement with the idea that on Sundays there should be certain hours, in town and country, when refreshments could be obtained in reasonable quantities.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Is quantity in the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume there is a certain degree of reasonableness in the quantity which a man could or should consume.  Does the Deputy suggest that I should have said an unreasonable quantity?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the Deputy might for the Committee Stage produce a scale of quantities according to personalities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>If every Deputy, including the Deputy who has made the suggestion, will furnish me with particulars of the quantity they consume of every kind of beverage, whether soda, milk or other more vivacious beverages, if this Bill reaches the Committee Stage&mdash;which I firmly hope it will not; I hope it will meet the same fate as the Sweepstakes Bill&mdash;I will try to comply with the suggestion of Deputy Johnson.  In furnishing the particulars, Deputies should state not only the quantity they consume now but the quantity they consumed in the days of their unrepentant youth.  That should give us a fair idea of what is the all-round beverage amount that is reasonable for a Christian and a statesman or a politician to consume.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2812" /> I also want to support the idea that the sub-section which deals with the non-employment of any female person under the age of 18 years, should be amended on the lines suggested, I think by Deputy Hughes and other Deputies, with regard to the employment of a person in the trade of a member of his own family.  It is quite possible, I believe, to amend this Bill, but its amendment will have to be considered on common sense lines and not on the lines of partisan feeling.  If the underlying idea is that this trade is not a legitimate trade and should be stamped out, then we ought to have it frankly and candidly stated.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the Deputy mean by &ldquo;legitimate?&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it a trade which has a moral right to existence within the State?  Is it a trade which serves nothing but a reprehensible purpose? Is it a trade which has any functions to serve within the State, which are of advantage to the community?  I hope I have made my interrogations sufficiently explicit for the Minister to understand.  If the answer to these questions is &ldquo;No,&rdquo; then let us have a Bill suppressing it.  If the answer is &ldquo;Yes,&rdquo; then let us have a Bill regulating this trade, if you like, but regulating it on business lines and not in the direction of hampering, irritating and destroying it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>resumed the Chair at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no questioning the fact that there are too many licensed houses in the country.  In the small town of Cavan there are fifty-four licensed premises.  Half the number would be quite sufficient. If that number could be reduced, I believe the remaining traders would be willing&mdash;and I think this would apply generally&mdash;to contribute half the equitable compensation to those whose licences were extinguished.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Why not the whole?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter for investigation.  It may be that the whole would not be too much.  It may be that the whole would be too great. I cannot say.  But I believe that there is, even amongst the members of the trade themselves, a perfect willingness <Col N="2813" /> to have the number of licences reduced.  But the number will have to be reduced on the principle of fair dealing and fair compensation to those who have, up to the present, been obtaining a livelihood out of the licensed premises which are to be discontinued.  I believe, too, that the complaint against the proposed legislation with regard to clubs is well founded and that as they stand the provisions in this respect will meet with very justifiable criticism and opposition. A differentiation must be made in all fairness between clubs which are mere drinking clubs, constituted solely for the sale and consumption of drink, and those which are social clubs, frequented for an entirely different purpose, and which serve a very useful link in the chain of social life in this country.  I omitted to draw attention to one point, and that is sub-section 6 of Section 12.  I would not allude to it save that nobody else has done so. If the section becomes effective it would reduce the premises considerably, but make no reduction in the valuation.  Revision of the valuation of the premises is precluded by this particular section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On that point Deputy Figgis drew a very heartrending picture of women and children going into these places, which were, in the main, filled with men the worse of drink.  I wonder where did Deputy Figgis discover these particular associations?  Has he penetrated into these dens of infamy, and, if so, to what extent?  I could as easily have drawn on my imagination and said that if women and children go in and see men taking a casual drink the desire on the part of these men for over-indulgence is restrained, because they see these women and these children pass through.  Probably the one would be as true as the other. There is no use, no sense, and no public service rendered by people drawing upon their imagination, by putting forward pictures of things which there are no real grounds to substantiate.  I think I have covered all the points that interested me.  I had hoped to have spoken until three o'clock, but, as I have exhausted my resources, I hope sufficient speakers will follow to talk this Bill out, or, at least, cause it <Col N="2814" /> to be adjourned until some day in the far-distant future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is like life: a mixture of good and evil. I will not say that as in life, the evil is predominant.  I hardly think so.  At the same time it cannot be denied that there are some bad regulations prescribed in the Bill which will have a very detrimental effect on the country. The Bill has been very exhaustively criticised.  I do not propose to go over all the provisions of the measure.  At the outset, I may say that I do not propose to vote against the Bill.  There are many good points in the Bill, particularly those dealing with illicit distillation, and the sale of methylated spirits.  I am sorry to see that the provisions dealing with these have been put at the end of the Bill, when they they should be in the front.  There is no doubt whatever that the drinking of methylated spirits is increasing to a very large extent in this country.  I am strongly of opinion that methylated spirits imported into or manufactured in this country, should be denatured before it is passed on for industrial purposes.</P>
      <P>As to illicit distillation, I do not think any law you could pass could be too stringent or too severe in order to put down that demoralising traffic.  It is essentially wicked.  Unfortunately, in the poorer parts of the country its victims are those who, owing to physical privation, have not the moral strength to resist the temptation.  In order to stamp out that traffic I think every person who is found in possession of poteen, whether a licensed trader, a man engaged in its manufacture, or some poor dupe who got possession of it, should be sent to prison, without the option of a fine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 12 of the Bill has been adequately debated, but there are one or two things that strike me in connection with the arguments used for and against this section.  I am somewhat interested in the psychic theory of contagion by visual contact.  We had a Deputy standing up here this afternoon with very melodramatic concern for the morals, if I may so express myself, of ladies who have to enter the licensed grocers' premises to make purchases. <Col N="2815" /> Deputy Milroy has anticipated me largely on that question.  I am afraid the Deputy who spoke like that was drawing very much on his imagination. We have idealists, unfortunately, in this country.  They are indigenous to the soil.  If Deputies can only pick out and emphasise that as an argument in favour of structural alterations, are they not acting the part of valetudinarian moralists?  Is it right or just that outsiders, foreigners, should regard the normal people of this country as neurotics who cannot resist these things?  I see no temptation to any person in going into these places where such a division does not exist. There is not the slightest temptation to indulge in drink.  If these alterations that the Bill provides for have to be made, I am afraid one of the results will be that shrewd shopkeepers, seeing that conditions in the licensed trade will not be very profitable in the future, will retire from the licensed trade altogether, and seek other means of livelihood. Then what happens?  The licensed trade will fall into the hands of undesirables, which is the last thing that Deputies want to occur.  There is very great danger of that.</P>
    <P>The result will be that the depravity of the publichouse, as it has been described, will be very much increased. Everyone agrees whole-heartedly that publichouses should not open on Christmas Day or on Good Friday.  St. Patrick's Day should, at least, be regarded as Sunday.  On that day we have many political and social reunions, that even Ministers have not hesitated to attend.  I think I will be only speaking the truth when I say that Ministers have a penchant for dining out on this day.  What will be the effect of closing on St. Patrick's Day?  Could the plain man get a drink in a publichouse or a club on that day? Can drinks be supplied in restaurants after dinner?  That is one of the questions, and it is scarcely fair.  After all, there is no use in throwing a Puritanical gloom over St. Patrick's Day; it would not be desirable, even in the best interests of the country, to restrict whatever gaieties take place on that day.  Deputy Corish considered <Col N="2816" /> that with regard to clubs the Bill was scarcely drastic enough.  I think that the right of the police to enter and search a club can be exaggerated.  We all want temperance, but, at the same time, even to ensure temperance, we cannot have private places&mdash;and, after all, a club is a private place&mdash;invaded at unusual hours by the police.  It is wrong.  Again, I am doubtful of the effect of the section which prohibits any person under the age of eighteen from serving behind a bar.  The Minister was rather doubtful as to whether the publican's daughter could do so, but at the same time, I think that the age limit could with advantage be lowered a year or two&mdash;certainly not more than two.  I do not think that there is any great danger to morals for a girl to go inside a bar when she is sixteen.</P>
    <P>There is one aspect with regard to the structural alteration section that I have overlooked.  Amongst those who may retain their business premises, it may mean uneconomic labour, that is, that they will require two people to serve, where one served before.  That would be uneconomic, and I say it would hardly be fair to a struggling country that is endeavouring to get on to its feet that any business man should be forced to employ persons for whom he has no work.  In conclusion, I think I should pay a tribute to the Minister for bringing into the one chamber, and for going in with them, the advocates of prohibition and the representatives of the licensed trade.  His courage was extraordinary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="Mr. T. MURPHY Mr. T. MURPHY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. MURPHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I intend to vote against the Second Reading of this Bill, and as the debate has dragged on so long and as arguments for and against the Bill have been so elaborately dealt with, I do not intend to weary the Dáil by going into them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the main the objections I have to the Bill are the objections that were outlined by Deputy Hogan, and I am looking at the Bill as it will effect the rural districts and the small country towns.  I think the effect of it, as far as a good many people I know who are in the trade are concerned, will be to drive them out of business altogether, and I think that would be an <Col N="2817" /> undesirable thing, if the State is not willing to compensate them.  During the debate on the Town Tenants Bill, the Minister for Justice used a good many arguments that I think could be used against this Bill.  He spoke about confiscation, and so far as I know of what the effects of this Bill would be in rural districts, I think the argument of confiscation, or something like it, would apply, because the result will be that people will be forced out of business, and will get no compensation, and that would be a position to which the argument of confiscation or something like it, could be very properly applied. I do not intend to deal with the question of structural alteration.  That has been dealt with very fully, and there is certainly nothing else to be said on the point.  In regard to fines and the powers which are to be given to the District Justices and the Superintendents of the Gárda Síochána, I think they are rather drastic.  Deputy Lyons, last night, referred to the powers that will be given to Superintendents of the Gárda Síochána to ask a District Justice to close down a particular town or village at a certain time.  It may be necessary that something like that should be done at times, but I think it is not a very good precedent to give too much power to the District Justices or the Gárda Síochána.  I know cases where very heavy fines have been inflicted on publicans, and where the decisions of District Justices have been reversed, or the fines considerably reduced, and I do not think that it would be well to do anything in the direction of giving the District Justices too great powers in connection with this matter.</P>
    <P>Deputy Hogan also referred to the clause that prohibits the giving of credit.  I believe that that clause is unnecessary, and that it could be very easily evaded.  And a person who wishes to give credit will find a good many ways of evading it, and I think it will do no good and serve no purpose whatever.  I believe this Bill will press very heavily on the small traders in country towns and rural districts. They are very much penalised as it is; their business on account of the taxation on liquor, is very small, and a good many of them are in a very struggling position.  I do not think it is <Col N="2818" /> reasonable or just to penalise them any further, and I submit the effect of this Bill will be to penalise them unduly and to make their position impossible. I think the Bill is being put up to the Dáil at an inopportune moment.  If the Minister for Justice believes that certain vital matters in connection with the licensed trade are to be referred to a Commission, I think that the whole matter might be deferred until that Commission has reported, and for the reasons that the Bill is, as far as I know, unnecessary in the rural districts, and that it will penalise traders, I shall vote against it.  As has been indicated by Deputy Hogan, there is no great drunkenness in the small towns or rural districts at present.  Some of us may remember the time when St. Patrick's Day was the occasion of a drunken orgy in a good many places. That time has passed away, and the influences that Deputy Hogan and other Deputies mentioned have contributed to that, and I do not think that there is any serious drunkenness or any serious illegal drinking at present.  On the contrary, I submit that if the Bill is passed the effect of it will be to encourage illegal drinking, because when the restrictions make it harder for people to get drink there will be more of an effort made to evade the law, and consequently there will be more illegal drinking.  I believe the Bill is harsh, unnecessary, and unjust, and I shall vote against the Second Reading.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>I also intend to vote against the Second Reading.  Deputy McCarthy, last night, said that he was going to vote for it because 95 per cent. of it was bad and 5 per cent. good. For the same reason I am going to vote against it, and if I had any doubts in my mind before I came here to-day as to whether I would be doing right or not in taking that course, they would have been removed by the speeches I have listened to&mdash;not alone by the speeches, but by the speakers, because it seems to me to be more than a coincidence that a large number of Deputies who, I know personally, are rather partial to a little drop, are in favour of the Bill, and a big number of the Pioneers are against the Bill.  I cannot understand that reasoning, and I <Col N="2819" /> am beginning to think that there must be something in the Bill which will not do any good for temperance, but will give more opportunities to the people who want an opportunity of going into a publichouse.  I do not intend to try to argue against the different clauses of the Bill; I think that has been done sufficiently already; but I agree with what Deputy Murphy has said, that the Bill is harsh.  I think it would be an injustice to a number of country traders to pass it at the moment, and I believe that a number of its sections are really absurd, particularly Section 12. With regard to the hours I do not quarrel. I agree with other Deputies that there are too many publichouses.  There are far too many.  I am sorry that the Minister has thought it right to include in the Bill the question of the putting down of the traffic in poteen and methylated spirits.  I think that if he really desired to do that at once he should have brought in a separate Bill to deal with it, and I am sure that he would have got such a Bill through the Dáil with the consent of every Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>As there is private business to be taken at 3 o'clock, I move the adjournment of the debate until Tuesday.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned till Tuesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE BOUNDARY QUESTION." RHead="- DEBATE RESUMED">
    <Title>THE BOUNDARY QUESTION. - DEBATE RESUMED.</Title>
    <P>Motion by Mr. Milroy; amendment by Mr. Johnson.  Debate resumed on the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Sir, we are all conscious that when the President spoke the interest in this question died.  That does not necessarily suggest that the interest was killed, but that the expectations with which we all looked to the President's utterance were satisfied. There is, therefore, to that exent, no justification for my prolonging the debate. On the other hand, the problem which Deputy Johnson raised for the second time in his amendment, and the attitude developed towards the Boundary Question by Deputy Milroy, do constitute items of sufficient importance to <Col N="2820" /> make it worth while to prolong the consideration of the question.  Deputy Milroy was careful to disclaim any intention on his part to cast blame upon the present Executive Council, either for the delay or for whatever consequences have arisen that might be attributed to delay.  That is, he professedly declared, that while his motion expressed dissatisfaction with what had occurred in connection with the Boundary, it was not to be taken as a vote of censure.  Deputy Johnson's amendment repeats most of the language of Deputy Milroy's original motion, but the first sentence which is common to both, is interpreted differently by the two Deputies, unquestionably.  Deputy Johnson lays the blame explicitly and avowedly upon the present Executive Ministry, and announces that his purpose is to have a vote of no confidence in so far as regards the handling of the Boundary problem.  Now, Deputy Johnson's discussion of the matter exhibits the usual vigour and the devotion to detail that characterises all his utterances in this House, and I feel that to follow him, as, of necessity, I must, if my purpose be to refute the position that he takes up &mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>May I draw your attention to the fact that there is no House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>There is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>One Deputy has just come in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson asked the Dáil to listen with some patience and care to what he had to say, and I not only listened with care, but with the patience that is not so much patience as profound interest, and have studied in the Official Report his speech at a later date.  Now, there are more than two theses in his speech. Broadly speaking, he holds that the contribution of the Attorney-General to the debate on the Railways Bill on May 28th was an extraordinary pronouncement. These are his words:&mdash;&ldquo;And that it constitutes a confession of a lapse of duty on the part of the Executive Council, whose Attorney-General made the confession.&rdquo;  He holds also that the Provisional Government made an agreement with respect <Col N="2821" /> to postponement of powers in connection with the National Council, that it acted <i>ultra vires</i> in doing so, and that the Provisional Government had no power to do what he declares the Provisional Government did.  He also maintained that the function which was ascribed to the Council of Ireland in the Act of 1920, was handed over after the Treaty.  These are mainly the points which I propose to traverse.  He says: &ldquo;What I have to say in the main is censure upon the Executive Council, because the Executive Council appears from the evidence tendered in this House by the late Attorney-General, to have failed to see that Article 12 of the Treaty is made obligatory.&rdquo;  Now, that is a very serious indictment of the Executive Council.  If there be anything in the indictment, however, the consideration of dates will show that the criminal in the matter is the late Provisional Government, and not the present Executive.  It is a question of dates.  This alleged confession of the Attorney-General is in column 1498 of the Official Report of the 28th May, 1924.  He says:&mdash;&ldquo;The operations of the Council of Ireland provisions were by agreement postponed for a period of five years.... It was given effect to in a statute I will mention in a moment.&rdquo;  He mentions the statute. It is an Act called the Irish Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act.  The date of that Act and the date of the Irish Free State Constitution Act are identical&mdash;5th December, 1922.  Consequently, what was done in the Irish Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act was done by the Provisional Government. Deputy Johnson's case is that the Irish Provisional Government of the Free State could not do anything which he alleges to have been done on the confession of the Attorney-General. I read from Deputy Johnson once more: &ldquo;I deny that the Provisional Government had any right, power or authority to enter into any agreement to vary the Provisions of the Treaty.&rdquo; Of course, that is common case with us all.  The Provisional Government had no right, power or authority to enter into any agreement to vary the provisions of the Treaty.  He argues here very elaborately, as he argued on <Col N="2822" /> a former occasion in connection with the Railways Bill, that for the Provisional Government to operate, the members of that Government should have been constituted Privy Councillors of Southern Ireland, and have taken the Oath.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputy is rather mistaken.  The powers were given to the Parliament of Southern Ireland.  If the Provisional Government claims to have been the Parliament of Southern Ireland, then these qualifications were required.  My contention is that the Provisional Government were not the Parliament of Southern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>All right.  I was about to read that statement of Deputy Johnson.  Deputy Johnson presents it in a more accurate form as a dilemma, that either they were the Executive of Southern Ireland, or they were not.  If they were not the Executive of Southern Ireland, then they could not operate as if they were.  On the other hand, if they purported to be the Executive Government of Southern Ireland they did not satisfy all the conditions of the Act of 1920, and therefore they were acting irregularly.  I think that is a fair paraphrase of the argument.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>All I want to say is that the Provisional Government were given certain definite powers.  It was not an Executive answerable to Parliament as defined in the Government of Ireland Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I had better read it instead of paraphrasing it, although I claim that on consideration Deputy Johnson will see that I do him no injustice in my paraphrase. &ldquo;I stated also that the Provisional Government had no authority to enter into such an agreement for the variation of the Treaty.  The only authority that could be claimed for it lies in the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, which says that the Executives of the two Parliaments under that Act could come to an agreement for postponing the transfer of powers.  Now, it is for the members of the Provisional Government who may be present, to say whether they claimed that the Provisional Government <Col N="2823" /> was, in fact, the Parliament of Southern Ireland under the 1920 Act, and had they conformed or not to the requirements of the Ministry to be set up under that 1920 Act.  If they did not so conform, they were not empowered to act by agreement with the Northern Government.&rdquo;  These are the exact words of Deputy Johnson. Either the Provisional Government was or was not the Executive Government of Southern Ireland under the Act of 1920.  He points out that it could not so operate because it did not conform to the conditions of one section, and therefore it had not the power.  That is the Deputy's case.  He has argued wholly in forgetfulness of a very important fact.  Article 17 of the Treaty declares that for the purposes of the transition period following the Treaty, an Executive Government shall be set up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>For administration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, for administration. Article 18, which Deputy Johnson has completely forgotten and therefore ignores the consequences of, goes on to announce that the Articles of Agreement for a Treaty are to be ratified in Great Britain and Ireland.  They were so ratified by the Irish Free State Agreement Act, and Deputy Johnson seems at any rate to have left that out of his calculations when he says in column 2379: &ldquo;The only authority that could be claimed for it lies in the Government of Ireland Act, of 1920.&rdquo;  It was under the provisions of Article 17 of the Treaty, together with the Irish Free State Agreement Act, that it became a Government, and the Deputy will remember, perhaps, that in the judgment in the English Courts with regard to the Irish deportees, it was declared there judicially that the Irish Free State had come into being in April 1922, and the Acts about which we are talking are December, 1922, several months later.  I quoted the other day, and I quote again, the Irish Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act, and strange to say, Deputy Johnson, who has been so very accurate in the framing of his amendment, did not make a speech on his amendment.  The words <Col N="2824" /> there are &ldquo;Council of Ireland&rdquo; as regards Northern Ireland.  Now, these two concurrent Acts, both dated 5th December, 1922, both emanating from the same Legislature deal, the one with the Irish Free State Constitution and the other with &ldquo;such provisions as are consequential on or incidental to the establishment of the Irish Free State.&rdquo; And the express declaration of Section 1 of the Irish Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act, is that:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Subject to the provisions of the First Schedule of this Act the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, shall cease to apply to any part of Ireland other than Northern Ireland.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This Irish Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act deals with the modification of the Act of 1920, as for what is called for convenience Northern Ireland, in consequence of the Irish Free State Agreement Act and the Irish Free State Constitution Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy arguing that the authority of the Saorstát is derived from the British Parliament?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not, sir, arguing anything of the kind.  I propose to show that the Deputy has been misled by passages which he himself quoted from two members of the Northern Government&mdash;Mr. Moles and Sir James Craig, the Premier.  I am not at all arguing that any authority whatsoever in Ireland is derived from a British Act of Parliament; and no one knows better than Deputy Johnson that I am not likely to take up that attitude, even for the purpose of victory in a small argument.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I cannot follow you otherwise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I was trying to make myself clear.  The difficulty is due to the intricacies of the question itself, and I am trying to follow Deputy Johnson.  There are here two Acts of the date 5th December, 1922.  One of them is really a ratification of the Irish Constitution.  I will read the important clause&mdash;Clause 5:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Act may be cited as the Irish Free State Constitution Act, 1922 (Section 2), and shall be deemed to be the Act of Parliament for the ratification <Col N="2825" /> of the said Articles of Agreement as from the passing whereof the month mentioned in Article Eleven of the said Articles is to run.</P>
    <P>This other Act&mdash;the Irish Free State Constitution (Consequential Provisions) Act sets out the modifications necessary in the Act of 1920, with regard to Northern Ireland; and everything in the First Schedule, which is the operative part of the Act, refers exclusively to Northern Ireland.  The actual heading of the First Schedule is &ldquo;Modification of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920,&rdquo; etc.  And then it deals with the &ldquo;Governor of Northern Ireland,&rdquo;&ldquo;Privy Council and Great Seal of Northern Ireland.&rdquo;&ldquo;Council of Ireland,&rdquo; and &ldquo;Financial Provisions.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Those were not referred to in the Treaty, but the other part, the Council of Ireland, was referred to in the Treaty so far as concerns Northern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am coming to that.  I am dealing with the Deputy's speech as it goes on in its own sequence, but I want to clear the ground for the moment.  The Council of Ireland is mentioned in the Irish Free State Constitution (Consequential Provisions) Act, Section 3.  Section 3 of the First Schedule says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The Constitution of the Council of Ireland, shall, if identical Acts for the purpose are passed by the Parliament of the Irish Free State, and the Parliament of Northern Ireland, be altered in accordance with those Acts.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The appointed day for the transfer in relation to Northern Ireland of the powers, which by the principal Act, are made powers of the Council of Ireland, shall be such day as may hereafter be fixed by Order in Council not being earlier than the day on which any such identical Acts as aforesaid come into operation or the expiration of the period of five years from the passing of this Act, whichever may first happen.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now, that is a reference to the Council of Ireland and its appointed day and its Constitution.  There are two things to be remembered in this connection&mdash;the Constitution of the Council <Col N="2826" /> of Ireland and the powers to be transferred to it.  The Constitution of the Council of Ireland is set out in the Act of 1920, Section 2:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;With a view to the eventual establishment of a Parliament for the whole of Ireland, and to bringing about harmonious action between the Parliaments and Governments of Southern Ireland and Northern Ireland, and to the promotion of mutual intercourse and uniformity in relation to matters affecting the whole of Ireland, and to providing for the administration of services which the two Parliaments mutually agree should be administered uniformly throughout the whole of Ireland, or which by virtue of this Act are to be so administered, there shall be constituted, as soon as may be after the appointed day a Council to be called the Council of Ireland.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Subject, as hereinafter provided, the Council of Ireland shall consist of a person nominated by the LordLieutenant acting in accordance with instructions from his Majesty, who shall be President, and forty other persons, of whom seven shall be members of the Senate of Southern Ireland, thirteen shall be members of the House of Commons of Southern Ireland, and seven shall be members of the Senate of Northern Ireland, and thirteen shall be members of the House of Commons of Northern Ireland.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is the Constitution of the Council of Ireland.  That is how it is set up, and that is the composition of it as a Council or Board.  Then, under the heading &ldquo;Legislative Powers.&rdquo; Section 7, it is given powers with regard to private Bill legislation.  And under the heading &ldquo;Executive Authority,&rdquo; by Section 10, its powers over railways, fisheries and contagious diseases of animals, for example, are given.  But these are not transferred.  There never was &ldquo;An Appointed Day,&rdquo; and they were never transferred.  That is one of the mistakes I intend to read from Deputy Johnson's speech.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>No mistakes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Now, I will return to the point at which I was interrupted. <Col N="2827" /> Deputy Johnson says that the only authority that could be claimed for it lies in the Government of Ireland Act of 1920.  The Provisional Government was not the Executive of Southern Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputy is misreading.  It is quite subject, I see, to that interpretation&mdash;that in the sentence: &ldquo;The only authority that could be claimed for it,&rdquo; the word &ldquo;it&rdquo; referred to the Provisional Government. What is obvious to me, but what is not perhaps obvious to everybody, is that the &ldquo;it&rdquo; refers to authority in reference to the agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you mean the agreement to postpone?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, to that agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I misread it.  In that case, as we are in agreement, I need not argue that further.  Now, the whole thing at issue between Deputy Johnson and me is: What was the reason for this Council existing?  Whether correctly or not, the authors of the 1920 Act claimed that it was intended to be an instrument of ultimate unification through the joint exercise of powers over fisheries, railways and such other matters as from time to time might be delegated to it by the votes of both Houses of the two Parliaments.  It is said under Section 4 that that was ultimately to bring about Irish union, and on the day of Irish union there was to be a Parliament of all Ireland.  Deputy Johnson says &ldquo;Hear, hear,&rdquo; in approval of that, and I think that is what his misled him to some extent, because he says here, referring to Article 12: &ldquo;Many of us knew that there was contained in that provision an instrument would would ensure the essential unity of this country at some future time, that would ensure immediately the essential unity of the country and the predominance of unified Government over the whole country in respect of certain functions.&rdquo;  Now, the fallacy that is here, and in the passages quoted from Captain Craig and Mr. Moles is this: The provisions that are made for the Constitution of the Council of Ireland <Col N="2828" /> in the Act of 1920, contemplated two subordinate Parliaments, two provincial Parliaments with concurrent power of legislation remaining in the Supreme Parliament at Westminster. Once the Treaty was passed, and more particularly when the Irish Free State Agreement Act was passed, the Irish Free State came into being, and under Section 1 of the Treaty Ireland had Dominion status.  The Parliament of Ireland was no longer a Subordinate Provincial Parliament, but a Sovereign Legislature.  It is interesting to note, once again, that for the first month following the 5th December, 1922, Ireland and the Free State was historically and geographically the same, that is to say, the term Ireland was declared to be identical with the Free State, and the Free State was Ireland, but the powers of exercising jurisdiction were in abeyance for that month.  At the end of the month, when the Six County people exercised the option given them under Article 12 of the Treaty, it was no longer in abeyance, and the jurisdiction was withdrawn.  That is an important fact to remember.  The arrangements which were made to allow of a delegation of authority for certain matters from two subordinate provincial Parliaments could not work.  In the nature of things, it was impossible that they could work as between a subordinate provincial legislature of Great Britain in the province of the Six Counties and a Parliament that was sovereign.  Now, that was not lost sight of by those who framed the Treaty, although by those who read the Treaty it has since been forgotten.  Article 12 of the Treaty reads: &ldquo;If before the expiration of the said month an address is presented to his Majesty by both Houses of the Parliament of Northern Ireland to that effect, the powers of the Parliament and Government of the Irish Free State shall no longer extend to Northern Ireland.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>By implication that is a declaration that it did extend, but after the exercise of its option this power was no longer extended.  The provisions of the Government of Ireland Act, so far as they related to Northern Ireland, continued to be &ldquo;of full force and <Col N="2829" /> effect.&rdquo;  That is the provision in the Government of Ireland Act.  The provisions of the Act were to remain in full force and effect, and not as Deputy Johnson says in his speech, the powers of the Council of Ireland.  The Article reads on: &ldquo;The provisions of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920 (including those relating to the Council of Ireland) shall so far as they relate to Northern Ireland continue to be of full force and effect, and this instrument shall have effect subject to the necessary modifications.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Article 12 expressly declares that there are necessary modifications, and the Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act makes the necessary modifications, but because Mr. Ormsby Gore, in November, in the debate upon that as a Bill, used the unhappy language of &ldquo;variation of the Treaty,&rdquo; there are some people in Ireland who ask us to believe that the Provisional Government assented to something being done in the Westminster legislature which varied the Treaty.  It did not vary the Treaty, but it adjusted, as was necessary, the provision for the Council of Ireland to meet the new circumstances that had arisen, to wit, that instead of being a Council constituted by members elected by two subordinate Parliaments, it was now to be a Council, if ever it was brought into being, which would be constituted by the co-operation of a Sovereign Parliament and a subordinate Parliament.  That is why the word &ldquo;variation&rdquo; of the Treaty is used.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>And would continue to have full force and effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>The provisions were to continue to be of full force and effect, but what is not being noticed is this: that in the Government of Ireland Act of 1920, where the constitution of the Council of Ireland is provided for, Sub-section 3 declares:&mdash;&ldquo;The constitution of the Council of Ireland may from time to time be varied by identical Acts passed by the Parliament of Southern Ireland and the Parliament of Northern Ireland, and the Acts may provide for all or any of the members of the Council of Ireland <Col N="2830" /> being elected by Parliamentary electors.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>So that even in the Act of 1920, before the Treaty, by no prevision or divination, arrangements were made to vary the mode of composing or of selecting the membership of the Council of Ireland, namely, by identical legislation. The Article of the Treaty which decrees the power of the Supreme Parliament in Westminster with regard to its subordinate Parliament in NorthEast Ulster, is followed up by a declaration under Article 13 of the Treaty, which says: &ldquo;For the purpose of the last foregoing article the powers of the Parliament of Southern Ireland under the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, to elect members of the Council of Ireland shall, after the Parliament of the Irish Free State is constituted, be exercised by that Parliament.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Now, that is an interesting point on which I stop to dwell for a moment.  It seems as if, notwithstanding that the Irish Free State is to be a co-equal member of the Commonwealth of free Nations, that here is power being given to it which requires confirmation or ratification in Westminster, but really the fact is that you have identical legislation. We adopted the Treaty and the Constitution, and the British Parliament, also, in the Free State Constitution Act, ratified the Treaty and the Constitution.  Now, the whole point, therefore, in this argument of Deputy Johnson disappears, because he fancies that the powers of the Council of Ireland were handed over.  They were not.  There has been no &ldquo;appointed day&rdquo;; there never was an &ldquo;appointed day.&rdquo;  As he himself mentioned there is power given under a later section of the Act of 1920 to postpone the &ldquo;appointed day.&rdquo;  That being so, it was postponed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>By whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>It was postponed as regards the Northern Ireland Parliament by the British Government, that is by the Supreme Parliament.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>It is only to be done under the 1920 Act by agreement between the two Governments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2831" />
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly. There is the whole fallacy.  I may tell Deputy Johnson a very ancient story of a Greek logician.  A Professor of Law accepted a distinguished pupil to learn from him all he knew of law, on condition that when the pupil won his first case he was to pay an enormous fee.  The pupil absorbed all that the Professor knew, but, instead of going into the courts to practise, he set up a rival school of law and took away pupils from his master.  The master then, in a foolish moment, sued him on the contract for the fee, and the pupil's reply illustrates exactly what is in Deputy Johnson's mind, and what was in Captain Craig's mind.  He said: &ldquo;You are bound to lose in any case, because if you take me into court, then by the decision of the court, if you win, I have lost my first case, and under the contract, as I have lost my first case, I pay you nothing.  On the other hand, if I win, then by the decision of the court, you have lost.&rdquo;  That is a very ancient illustration of a fallacy which turns up in modern times: that is to think of the Act of 1920 operating as in the Act as set out, and to think of its operating for somewhat similar services under specifically new conditions not contemplated in the Act of 1920.  They cannot have it both ways.  Arrangements for the Council of Ireland that would suit the two subordinate Parliaments, could not possibly be made without adjustment to suit a Sovereign Parliament. That is the whole situation.  We now come to the section of the Act of 1920, in which the supremacy of the West-minister Parliament, in point of legislation over Ireland, is declared It is practically the last section of the Act&mdash; Section 75.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>We claim the Treaty renounced it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>The section is: &ldquo;Notwithstanding the establishment of the Parliaments of Northern and Southern Ireland or anything contained in this Act,&rdquo; this may answer Deputy Johnson when he says provision is in the Act&mdash;&ldquo;the supreme authority of the Parliament of the United Kingdom shall remain unaffected and undiminished over all persons, matters, <Col N="2832" /> and things in Ireland, and every part thereof.&rdquo;  And in an earlier section it is expressly laid down that the legislative authority of the subordinate Parliaments is exclusively with matters that lie within their domain, and there are reserved services.</P>
      <P>Now, I think I have laboured that long enough.  There is no confession on the part of the Attorney - General that the present Executive Council were remiss in any of these matters. There is, as one would expect, a legally correct statement by the Attorney-General that we had nothing to do with that strictly speaking.  &ldquo;The Provisional Government,&rdquo; he says, &ldquo;gave nothing away.  They could not ... it was their business, not ours.&rdquo;  Now, I come to another question: that is the contribution of Deputy Milroy.  He has, as I have already said expressly renounced any desire, although he had but lately joined the national group, to indict the Executive Council in this matter.  But he complains of delays, and he spoke of quibbles.  The President has already, by giving a minute diary of the proceedings in regard to this matter, proved conclusively that though there were delays they were unavoidable, and in so far as they existed at all, were wholly beyond the control of the Executive Council.  But I desire to associate myself, absolutely, with what Deputy Milroy has said in respect of the consequences of those delays. Sir James Craig boasted that they were &ldquo;digging themselves in.&rdquo;  These are the exact words.  Deputy Milroy said &ldquo;every move of the game has been directed to our disadvantage.  There are over 4,000 special constables transferred to North Fermanagh.  Unless we revert to the situation in 1918 we shall be dealing with a new situation which has been deliberately contrived in the intervals of these delays.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I will read from a letter written to the &ldquo;The Times&rdquo; (London), but refused publication by it, by Mr. C.J. O'Donnell, an ex-member of the Liberal Party.  He is an Ulsterman, and speaks with intimate knowledge. He says:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;For many years West Belfast was worthily represented by Mr. Joseph Devlin in the Imperial Parliament&mdash;a <Col N="2833" /> serious offence to Orange intolerance. By the inclusion of two Protestant Wards, Shankhill and Woodvale, in the constituency, Catholic representation has been effectively wiped out in Belfast. Although 34 per cent. of the total population of the Six Counties are Catholics, they are represented in the House of Commons at the present hour by only two out of seventeen members.  The Catholics of Tyrone have decided to take no part in the Local Government Elections this month (May) and this decision has been held up as another example of Irish cussedness.  There is a more natural explanation.  They know it would be waste of time to go to the polls because the electoral areas have been so jerrymandered by the Belfast Government that success is hopeless.  By segregating and combining districts, by twisting internal boundaries, it has made sure that in the County Council of Tyrone the present Nationalist majority of six will infallibly be changed into an Orange majority of fifteen.  In Fermanagh the reduction is from a majority of three to a minority of sixteen. In 1920, before gerrymandering in the two counties of Tyrone and Fermanagh, in which there is a total Catholic majority of 23,009 in the joint population, the Local Government representation gave 84 seats to the Catholics and 65 to the Protestants.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This writer, by the way, always says &ldquo;Catholic&rdquo; and &ldquo;Protestant,&rdquo; when he ought to speak in political terms of &ldquo;Nationalist&rdquo; and &ldquo;Unionist&rdquo;&mdash;or &ldquo;Loyalist,&rdquo; as such a person would describe himself.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;So gerrymandering was resorted to, with the exhilirating result that the figures were twisted right round. At the most the Catholics can now secure 63 seats to 85 for the Reformed Faiths, in spite of their large majority in voters.  In all unions, six in number, their representatives are now in a minority, whilst since 1920 they had majorities in four.  In Omagh 463 votes are needed to secure the election of a Catholic, whilst 228 Protestants suffice for a <Col N="2834" /> Protestant victory.  In Protestant Lurgan there was a Catholic minority of six.  Not one can now be elected.  The Ulster Catholics are manifestly right in refusing to take any part in such a malevolent travesty of representative institutions. Can one wonder that Catholics in Southern Ireland have resolved to strain every nerve in order to rescue as many as possible of their co-religionists from a Government that, openly and without subterfuge, loads the dice so as to exclude its Catholic subjects from their legitimate influence in even municipal administration?&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Deputy Milroy and Deputy McCabe, who seconded this amendment, both stressed these points.  It does not matter how the delay has come about, whether it was by malignant influence of the stars, or whether it was by some upheaval of the ocean.  At any rate, the delay has scored against us, and very naturally we view with dismay further postponements of coming to deal seriously with the question.  I was very glad to notice that both these Deputies observed, as one would expect them to do, the strictest decorum in regard to their references to the consultation on the part of the British Government with the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council.  In that they showed a marked contrast with Lord Carson.  If I may say, in passing, apropos of that, there is a very interesting comment in the &ldquo;London Star,&rdquo; in which the high standing of the South African Judge, Mr. Feetham, who has been selected by the British to act as Chairman of the Boundary Commission, was dealt with.  In the &ldquo;Star&rdquo; the fact that he was one of a brilliant band of Oxford graduates whom Lord Milner had brought with him to South Africa, was mentioned. The brilliant success and high achievements of Mr. Feetham in South Africa were dwelt upon, and several of his colleagues in that band were mentioned. It struck me as especially interesting that one of them went unnamed.  Mr. Lionel Curtis, who also achieved distinction in South Africa, who is a noted writer upon Commonwealth matters, the author of the &ldquo;Problems of the Commonwealth,&rdquo;<Col N="2835" /> and who is in the very high position of Adviser on Irish Affairs to the Colonial Government, was not mentioned. I think it is a fair deduction that it was he who contributed this interesting paragraph.</P>
    <P>In that connection, it occurs to me to dot the i's and cross the t's of one remark in Deputy Milroy's excellent speech&mdash;I mean excellent as regards those parts with which I heartily agree. He says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It&rdquo; (that is the application of Article 12) &ldquo;will have to be settled in accordance with the spirit of the Treaty, and with the spirit of those who signed the Treaty.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Now, I regard that as the most important contribution of Deputy Milroy to this discussion.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It will have to be settled in accordance with the spirit of the Treaty, and with the spirit of those who signed the Treaty, or it will never be settled rightly. We are told it simply means rearrangement of the line of the frontier, taking in a little here and there to make the boundary more symmetrical.  It means nothing of the kind,&rdquo; so Deputy Milroy insists.</P>
    <P>We have almost forgotten in 1924 what was the spirit of the time when that Treaty was framed, and that language employed. 1918 is so far away that it might be just as well centuries removed, so much has the interval of years been filled with incidents, events, struggles and contests that have preoccupied our souls.  The language of the Treaty was dictated by a spirit, then everywhere prevalent.  That spirit was incarnate, more particularly in President Wilson than in any other statesman of the time.  When the language of that Treaty was used, we were all not only intimately acquainted with the utterances of President Wilson, Mr. Lloyd George and the others who were engaged in settling Europe and bringing about what they claimed would be a lasting peace, but we knew these utterances off by heart.  There were very few who did not know them.  Even Macaulay's Schoolboy could be outdone in this matter.  There were very few <Col N="2836" /> who did not know President Wilson's fourteen points, and most people knew President Wilson's four points.  The thirteenth of the fourteen points was a declaration with regard to Poland, and everyone of us interpreted it to refer equally to Ireland, though with diplomatic delicacy, President Wilson was understood not to refer to the doings and the practices of the Governmental and Constitutional advocates of an Associated Power.  Article 13 of the Fourteen Points declared that an independent Polish State should be erected to include the territories that were inhabited by exclusively Polish populations, and under specific covenants, their political, economic and territorial integrity was to be guaranteed.  The League of Nations was declared to be a necessity for this lasting peace in Point 14, and it was to be an association of nations to give those mutual guarantees to States, both small and great&mdash;guarantees of political and economic independence, and territorial integrity.</P>
    <P>Territorial integrity was the dominating demand with regard to nationalities whose autonomy and whose aspirations to statehood had long been suppressed by greater Powers.  Those who framed the Treaty and those who subscribed to it on our behalf were animated by that spirit and contemplated no other meaning for those words in Article 12 of the Treaty, so that those of us who are now inclined to read it with the conceptions of today make a historical blunder.  Anyone who confuses rectification of boundary with securing for the Irish Nation such a share of territorial integrity as is consistent with the agreement to provide certain safeguards for a minority of settlers and their decendants in the North-Eastern corner are thinking of something else than mere rectification of boundaries.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>resumed the chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>It is almost 4 o'clock or I should inflict upon the House some remarks regarding a matter which has passed from our memories. This whole conception of the rights of nations&mdash;whether small or great&mdash;to be free to determine their <Col N="2837" /> own laws and way of life, to set up for themselves institutions that would be expressive of the civilisations which they value&mdash;that was declared to be the purpose with which the great war was fought.  Those who met at the Paris Conferences to re-settle the map of Europe declared that they were carrying out, as part of the public law of Europe, the principle of nationality. The incorporation of the principle of nationality in the public law of Europe was their professed design.  It had been the tendency, as everyone knows &mdash;it had been preached as a doctrine by Massini, it had been the sub-conscious tendency in Europe in the 19th century&mdash;for nationalities to struggle to make political States that would be co-incident also with geographical boundaries.  When that discussion was going on at the Peace Conference with regard to the determination of what peoples should be allowed plebiscites to determine their mode of government and the rest, I recalled the famous speech of a Dublin lawyer at the time of the formation of the Irish Volunteers. In a golden outburst of what some people might describe as rhetoric he said:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The Almighty has stamped upon our island in indelible characters her charter as a nation.  The God that made our land an island never meant that she should be a province and, by God, she never shall.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>We had all the claims for identification of political and geographical statehood, but Mr. Lloyd George, Earl Balfour and the rest took upon themselves the character in the American satire:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I do believe in Freedom's cause,</P>
      <P>As far away as Paris is.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>They determined to make not an enclave, as was done in Europe, but to set up a province with a provincial legislature and, in the expectation of eventual unity, to give it certain powers.  The reason I referred incidentally to Mr. Lionel Curtis is because has name occurs to me in this connection. Deputy Johnson, in the passage I read from his speech in the beginning, spoke of an instrument of &ldquo;final unification.&rdquo;  Those who advocate federal union between portions of a divided land in which there are racial <Col N="2838" /> differences believe profoundly in waiting for time to bring about a union of hearts through a consciousness of mutual interests.  They look to solutions of problems such as confront us in dealing with our Northern neighbours for inter-provincial union, so that it is not important really as Deputy Johnson put it&mdash;though I do not at all suggest he had the same intention&mdash;it does not really matter how you draw the boundaries now, the boundaries are of very slight moment in comparison with setting up that machinery that shall be as little as possible machinery with friction and that shall bring about ultimate unification.  That is not our conception.  We still adhere to what we have never abandoned&mdash;the claim that Ireland shall one day be a unit State. We have undoubtedly no objection whatsoever, as our signatories to the Treaty indicated, to granting to a Province, a legislature, or local administration, or for that matter, to creating it, but that that Federal Government, instead of being brought about by slow degrees, should be brought about now with the defeat of our national aspirations&mdash;that I agree with Deputy Milroy is not to be tolerated.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephMcGoldr" hpid="Mr. McGOLDRICK Mr. McGOLDRICK">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGOLDRICK</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the debate until Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The President has a statement to make as to the business of the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not got roneo copies of the programme, but I am in a position to give it as I hope it will work out.  The revised programme contains 31 Bills.  Of these seven are in the Seanad, having passed through all stages in the Dáil.  The Third Stage of the Local Government Bill has been postponed until October, and the Pilotage Orders (Confirmation) Bill, and possibly the State Harbours Bill will be treated as private business and introduced in the Seanad.  Of the remaining 21 Bills, five have passed their Third Reading, and should occupy little further time.  That leaves 16 Bills, of which seven have passed Second Reading, and eight have yet to be introduced.  I query the last statement <Col N="2839" /> on the sheet before me, because I think nearly all the Bills have been introduced. We estimate that by sitting up to 11 o'clock on Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday evenings, something like 40 hours can be given to Estimates by Friday, 11th July.  By taking the First Stage of the Appropriation Bill on that date and the Second Stage on Tuesday, the 15th, we can finish out the programme with possibly two Bills that may not get through their final stages.  We could get through those if some facilities were given regarding one of them&mdash;the Dairy Stock Breeding Scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that one of the Bills not yet introduced?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not introduced yet.  We would take the Fourth and Fifth Stages on the 16th July. There are two Bills which may be introduced, but I do not see much possible chance of getting time&mdash;the Industrial and Commercial Property Protection Bill and the School Attendance Bill.</P>
      <P>I will now give the programme for next week.</P>
      <P>Tuesday, June 24th&mdash;1.  Damage to Property (Compensation) (Amendment) Bill, 2nd Stage; 2.  Defence Forces (Temporary Provisions) Continuation Bill, 3rd Stage; 3.  Criminal Justice (Administration) Bill, 3rd Stage; 4.  Finance Bill, 4th, Stage; 5. Local Government, (Rates on Agric. Land) Bill, 3rd, 4th, and 5th Stages; 6.  Criminal Justice (Evidence) Bill, 3rd Stage; 7.  Unemployment Insurance (Extension) Bill, 4th and 5th Stages; 8.  National Health Insurance Bill, 5th Stage; 9.  Local Elections (Postponement) Amendment, 4th and 5th Stages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Wednesday, June 25th&mdash;1.  Telephone Capital Bill, 2nd Stage; 2.  Fisheries (Election of Conservators) Postponement Bill, 2nd Stage; 3. Agricultural Produce (Eggs) Bill, 5th Stage; 4. Report <Col N="2840" /> on Temporary Accommodation of Oireachtas; 5.  Estimates. 4 hours. Sit to 11 p.m.</P>
    <P>Thursday, June 26th&mdash;1.  Indemnity Bill, 3rd Stage; 2. Military Service Pensions Bill, 2nd Stage; 3.  Trade (Loans Guarantee) Bill, 2nd Stage; 4.  Land Bonds (Guarantee) Bill, 1st Stage; 5.  Estimates. 2 hours.  Sit to 11 p.m.</P>
    <P>Friday, June 27th&mdash;1.  Damage to Property (Compensation) Amendment Bill, 3rd Stage; 2. Finance Bill, 5th Stage; 3. Estimates. 3 hours.</P>
    <P>There is no necessity to read out the arrangements for the following week. According to that, the date of rising will be altered to July 16th.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I can only say this, that the Minister is inviting a strike, and I do not want to strike.  I am prepared to carry on until September if necessary, if the Minister wants these Bills, but unless he is prepared to carry on much longer than the 16th July he will not get these Bills and the Estimates. I think the Minister is trying this machine too much.  He must take into account not only the Dáil, but the Seanad.  He may make up his mind for certain he is not going to get these Bills through.  He ought to say which Bills are absolutely necessary in addition to the Estimates.  He cannot do this work, and it is well that he should face the matter immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the President say whether amongst the eight Bills to be introduced is included the Control of Prices Bill, which he promised to introduce before Easter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It will not be under that title, but it will come under the Trade (Loans Guarantee) Bill on Thursday.  The beneficial effects which were anticipated to flow from the other measure will be found in that.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 4.10 p.m. until Tuesday, June 24th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - EDGEWORTHSTOWN" RHead="DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - EDGEWORTHSTOWN DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEÁN O LAIDHIN SEÁN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he can state why dependent's allowance has not been paid to Mrs. Hogan, Clonwheelan, Edgeworthstown, in respect of her son, Bernard, No. 22759, who attested on the 4th March, 1922, and was discharged <Col N="2769" /> on the 24th February, 1924; whether, as he was her chief support, he will have this case reinvestigated, with a view to having the allowance granted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Dependent's allowance was paid to the soldier in respect of Mrs. Mary Anne Hogan. of Clonwheelan, Edgeworthstown, from the 4th March, 1922, up to the 29th July, 1922, and subsequently direct to Mrs. Hogan.  The rate was 28/- per week up to the 22nd January last and 14/- per week afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - BALLYMAHON" RHead="TRADER'S ARMY ACCOUNT">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - BALLYMAHON TRADER'S ARMY ACCOUNT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEÁN O LAIDHIN SEÁN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that a sum of £104 10s. is due to Mr. M. Whelan, merchant, Ballymahon, Co. Longford, in respect of goods supplied to the military stationed at Ballymahon; and whether, seeing that the applicant has made several applications for payment without result, he will expedite settlement of this account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the Office of Public Works will settle Mr. Whelan's account at a very early date.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>