<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="24" Month="Jul" Year="1924" Vol="8" No="19" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 24 Iúil 1924" DateEnglish="Thursday, 24 July 1924" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="2071">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2071" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar a 3 a clog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - DEVELOPMENT OF GALWAY PORT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - DEVELOPMENT OF GALWAY PORT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCosgrave" hpid="SÉAMUS MacCOSGAIR SÉAMUS MacCOSGAIR">
      <NameTxt>SÉAMUS MacCOSGAIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the President whether the Government have yet considered the demands for the opening of Galway as a port of call for ocean-going steamers, and if he will consult the shipping authorities on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government have given consideration to this subject on more than one occasion; it has, also, been carefully explored by the Ministry of Industry and Commerce. As the Deputy is aware, a scheme of this kind cannot be undertaken, with any prospect of success, except in cooperation with the British, United States, and Canadian authorities.  The subject was raised by the Saorstát representative at the recent Imperial Economic Conference, and the present position, from the British point of view, was explained by the then First Lord of the Admiralty.  If the Deputy will refer to pages 323, 328, and 329 of the Official Record of Proceedings of the Conference he will realise the impossibility of successfully pursuing the project at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - WAR COMPENSATION COURT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - WAR COMPENSATION COURT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Mr. OSMOND GRATTAN ESMONDE Mr. OSMOND GRATTAN ESMONDE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. OSMOND GRATTAN ESMONDE</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the President whether he will state what progress, if any, has been made towards setting up the War Compensation Court, since the statement of the Minister for Finance on November 22nd, 1923, that negotiations on this subject had then reached an advanced stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Negotiations on this subject have been unduly protracted <Col N="2072" /> owing to the fact that the question has been complicated by a number of other issues arising directly and indirectly out of the proposed Terms of Reference.  The matter has, however, occupied the constant attention of the Government, and the Minister for Justice is proceeding to-night to London to endeavour to reach an agreement on outstanding points, so that some equitable settlement of their claims may be assured to Irish claimants.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- PUBLICATION OF POST-TRUCE DEBATES">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - PUBLICATION OF POST-TRUCE DEBATES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the President if, and when, it is intended to print and publish the Official Debates of Dáil Eireann for the session that followed the Truce of June, 1921.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The publication of the public debates during the session referred to will be put in hands as soon as it is found possible for the Clerk of the Dáil to have the material prepared for publication.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- PAYMENT OF ARMY ACCOUNT (LONGFORD)">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - PAYMENT OF ARMY ACCOUNT (LONGFORD).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that the balance of an account, amounting to £30, is due to Mrs. E.T. Wort, baker and confectioner, Queen Street, Athlone, and formerly of 13 Wards Terrace, Longford, for bread and confectionery supplied to the Longford Barracks from March, 1922, and whether payment will be expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="MINISTER for DEFENCE (The President) William T. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for DEFENCE (The President)</NameTxt>
      <P>The balance of Mrs. Wort's account amounted to £28 8s. 8d.  A cheque in full payment was issued on the 9th instant.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - RE-OPENING COMPENSATION CLAIM">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - RE-OPENING COMPENSATION CLAIM.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that a gratuity of £15 has been awarded to John Deehan, Main Street, Moate, in respect of his son, Patrick, who was shot at Fry Place Barracks, Athlone, on July 30th, 1922; whether, in view of the fact that the deceased Volunteer was but fourteen and a half years old, <Col N="2073" /> he will have the case re-opened with a view to increasing the award.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The award of gratuity made to Mr. Deehan is being reconsidered.  I will communicate the result to the Deputy in due course.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- COMPENSATION OF OFFICERS' DEPENDENTS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - COMPENSATION OF OFFICERS' DEPENDENTS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY (for Pádraig Mac Fhlannchadha) Mr. MORRISSEY (for Pádraig Mac Fhlannchadha)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY (for Pádraig Mac Fhlannchadha)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that Lieutenant Hanrahan, 2nd Battalion, Limerick City Brigade, was mortally wounded in action on October 17th, 1922, and whether any compensation has been paid to his parents, who were entirely dependent upon him for support, and if he will reconsider the case with a view to compensating adequately his parents for their great loss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware of the circumstances in which Lieutenant Hanrahan met his death.  He was not mortally wounded in action, but was mortally wounded by being fired at whilst walking along Roxborough Road, Limerick, in the company of a lady friend.  As his parents had not been wholly dependent on him, they are not entitled to a pension under the Military Service Pensions Act.  Dependents' allowance at the rate of 14/- a week was, however, paid to them up to the 23rd February pending an award under the Army Pensions Act.  The award was £20.  As suggested by the Deputy, I will review the case as favourably as possible with a view to increasing that award.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - CONDITION OF CO. CORK ROADS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - CONDITION OF CO. CORK ROADS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephHenness" hpid="MICHEAL O hAONGHUSA MICHEAL O hAONGHUSA">
      <NameTxt>MICHEAL O hAONGHUSA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government and Public Health whether he has read the report of proceedings of a meeting of Motor Owners' Associations and users of roads in Cork county, held in Cork on the 15th instant, at which members generally commented strongly on the scandalous condition of the main roads in Cork County; whether he can state the contributory causes to this condition of the roads in this county, whether it is from lack of funds, incompetence or inefficiency on the part of the supervising staff, or want of sense <Col N="2074" /> of civic responsibility on the part of the local authorities; further, whether he will instruct an Inspector from his department to hold an inquiry at an early date into these matters and fix responsibility, and whether such Inspector's report will be placed on the Table of the Dáil; and, also, whether he will state the amount of moneys annually contributed by taxpayers for the maintenance of roads in that county.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN (for Minister for Local Government and Public Health) Mr. McGILLIGAN (for Minister for Local Government and Public Health)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN (for Minister for Local Government and Public Health)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have read the report referred to.  No doubt the unsatisfactory conditions obtaining are largely due to impaired administration and slackness in work during the lengthy period of disordered conditions which prevailed in the county.  The Chief Roads Engineer will undertake local inspection; he will be asked to submit a full report which, as requested, will be placed on the Table of the Dáil.  The amount contributed by the ratepayers for road maintenance in the county, excluding the County Borough of Cork, is about £180,000 per annum.  Since September last the grants allocated for road improvement in the county, excluding the city, amounted to £110,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephHenness" hpid="Mr. HENNESSY Mr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of that answer, may I ask the Minister if his attention has been called to correspondence in the Press under yesterdays' date in which a traveller writes, after having seen the Cork roads: &ldquo;I have seen better roads made in Central Africa by barefooted natives with home-made wooden mallets&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not believe that the Minister for Local Government has seen that recent correspondence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister tell us, in view of the fact that the upkeep of roads at present in the Cork county costs £180,000, what these roads would cost if they were kept in proper repair and maintained in proper order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That again is a question based on hypothesis.  I cannot answer it at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister, in calculating that £180,000, taken into <Col N="2075" /> account the 6d. in the £ on the rateable value of property under the Compensation for Damages Act, 1923?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that would be excluded by the particular sentence in the question that I have read, &ldquo;the amount contributed by the ratepayers for road maintenance.&rdquo;  It is very general, but I think the 6d. under the Property Compensation Act would be excluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Therefore, the rates are very much greater than what is represented by the figure £180,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is my impression, but I do not put that forward as the impression of the Minister for Local Government, who knows more about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephHenness" hpid="Mr. HENNESSY Mr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that in the Northern Counties of the Saorstát and in Leinster, where the rates are not so high, that the roads are in excellent order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That may well be, but it could be explained by the fact that &ldquo;the unsatisfactory conditions are largely due to impaired administration and slackness in work during the lengthy period of disordered conditions which prevailed in County Cork.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say whether the cry, &ldquo;Up, Cork,&rdquo; means &ldquo;Up the Cork roads?&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - ATHLONE OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - ATHLONE OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEÁN O LAIDHIN SEÁN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government and Public Health if he is aware that an old age pension, which was granted by the Athlone Sub-Committee in June, 1924, to John Early, The Pigeons, Athlone, has been rejected by the Pensions Officer; whether, as the applicant is over seventy years of age, and is in very poor circumstances, he will have the case re-investigated with a view to having pension granted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN (for Minister for Local Government and Public Health) Mr. McGILLIGAN (for Minister for Local Government and Public Health)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN (for Minister for Local Government and Public Health)</NameTxt>
      <P>A claim by a Mr. John Early, Tubberclair, <Col N="2076" /> Glass, Athlone, was disallowed on appeal on 9th August, 1923, on the ground of means, and the case has not come before me since.  I have no information regarding a more recent claim, as mentioned by the Deputy.</P>
      <P>I have no functions in the matter unless a claim comes before me on appeal. If it does I will give full consideration to all the facts, and make such inquiries as may seem called for.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- CONVEYANCE OF TIRCONAILL PRISONERS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - CONVEYANCE OF TIRCONAILL PRISONERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephMcGoldr" hpid="PÁDRAIG MagUALGHAIRG PÁDRAIG MagUALGHAIRG">
      <NameTxt>PÁDRAIG MagUALGHAIRG</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Justice if he will state what has been the cost of the conveyance of prisoners from County Tirconaill to gaols outside the county for the year ending 31st December, 1923, and also for the half-year ending 30th June, 1924; why there is not a bridewell in Letterkenny, in which town there is a disused workhouse; whether the equipment of a bridewell there for prisoners on remand or summary conviction would not be central for the county, as well as more economic and convenient, and whether he will have the necessary steps taken to arrange for the establishment of same in Letterkenny.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>The cost of conveying prisoners from Tirconaill for the six months ended 30th June, 1924, was approximately £700.  I have not at present before me the figures for 1923, as the accounts for that year are now with the Comptroller and Auditor-General.</P>
      <P>I have considered the advisability of establishing a bridewell or separate prison at Letterkenny, which, of course, would be more convenient than Sligo Prison, but I am not satisfied that this course would be justified, in view of the heavy expenditure which would be involved in the erection, upkeep and consequent establishment charges of a new prison.  To transform the old workhouse at Letterkenny into a temporary prison would entail a capital expenditure estimated at about £2,000, and a prison staff would of course, require to be allocated and maintained there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I propose, however to review the <Col N="2077" /> matter next October, when more complete material will be available upon which to form a decision.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.  -" RHead="REPRESENTATION AT INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCES">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - REPRESENTATION AT INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for External Affairs if he will state what arrangements, if any, have been agreed to by him respecting the representation of Saorstát Eireann at any International Conferences or Conventions in which it may be committed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Before putting this question, I would like to say that the question was put down prior to the Minister's answer to Deputy Johnson's question on the day before yesterday, but I still put it to him in case the negotiations referred to by him referred to a wider matter with regard to general representation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="MINISTER for EXTERNAL AFFAIRS (Mr. D. Fitzgerald) Desmond FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for EXTERNAL AFFAIRS (Mr. D. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>The position at present is generally decided by the precedents of Versailles and Washington and the resolutions of the Imperial Conference.  In this connection I would refer the Deputy to a statement in my speech on External Affairs Estimates, 9th July, column 4040, lines 8-17 of the Official Report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>A most judicious reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- TELEPHONE FACILITIES (CO. LOUTH)">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - TELEPHONE FACILITIES (CO. LOUTH).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="PEADAR O hAODHA PEADAR O hAODHA">
      <NameTxt>PEADAR O hAODHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs whether, in the public interest, he will consider the installation of a telephone box in the sub-offices at Blackrock and Annagasson, in the County Louth, and whether he is aware that there is an insistent demand for such facilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="MINISTER for POSTS and TELEGRAPHS (Mr. Walsh) MINISTER for POSTS and TELEGRAPHS (Mr. Walsh)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for POSTS and TELEGRAPHS (Mr. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of providing telephone call office facilities at Blackrock and Annagasson, Co. Louth, is at present under consideration, and when the necessary enquiries have been completed, I will communicate the result to the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - REPORT ON INDUSTRIAL INSURANCE">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - REPORT ON INDUSTRIAL INSURANCE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCosgrave" hpid="SEAMUS MAC COSGAIR SEAMUS MAC COSGAIR">
      <NameTxt>SEAMUS MAC COSGAIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce <Col N="2078" /> if he will announce to the Dáil the recommendations of the Committee appointed to report on the question of industrial insurance in the Saorstát, and if this report will be circulated to Deputies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The report of the Committee and the legislation which their recommendations would involve are now being considered. It appears better to defer the question of publishing the report until a decision is arrived at on these matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - TRADE LOANS ADVISORY COMMITTEE">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - TRADE LOANS ADVISORY COMMITTEE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he can state before the recess what persons he proposes to appoint to act on the Advisory Committee to be set up under the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Bill, when enacted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer to this question depends on:&mdash;1. The date on which the Trade Loans (Guarantee) Bill becomes law.  2. The date on which the Dáil rises for the Summer Recess.  3. The decision as to whether one committee or two committees will be practicable, or, if practicable, necessary. 4. The favourable or unfavourable replies returned by those who may be invited to act.  As it is not possible for me to forecast the future, I am not in a position to answer the question in the affirmative.  I hesitate, however, to give a definitely negative reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister arrange for that reply to be printed and circulated in red ink?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>With the humorous parts underlined.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- REDUCTION OF CROSS-CHANNEL SERVICES">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - REDUCTION OF CROSS-CHANNEL SERVICES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="PEADAR O hAODHA PEADAR O hAODHA">
      <NameTxt>PEADAR O hAODHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether he is aware that it is contemplated by the London, Midland, and Scottish Railway to reduce the steamship service between Greenore and Holyhead to three sailings per week <Col N="2079" /> for goods traffic, and to discontinue entirely the passenger service, and whether having regard to the serious unemployment this would cause in the district and the inconvenience to traders, he will have enquiries made, and, if necessary, make representations with a view to the continuance of the present service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of the proposed reduction in the steamship service between Greenore and Holyhead, but I am making enquiries, and will communicate later with the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="QUESTION ON" RHead="ADJOURNMENT">
    <Title>QUESTION ON ADJOURNMENT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>On the motion for the adjournment I intend to raise the <Col N="2080" /> question of the condition of the cells in Mountjoy in which prisoners condemned to death are being kept.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. Kevin O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. Kevin O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>It will not be possible for me to be present at the adjournment this evening.  I have to leave for London to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I take that as a suggestion that the matter might be taken on at once?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister for Justice agree to take it on at 6 o'clock for half an hour?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="SITTINGS OF" RHead="THE DAIL">
    <Title>SITTINGS OF THE DAIL.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that we sit later than 8.30 to-night and that we take the adjournment not later than 10.30.  While on that subject, I should say that I propose to move on the adjournment to-night that we re-assemble at 10.30 a.m. to-morrow and sit until the business is finished, allowing for adjournments for lunch or any other dietary arrangements that may be required. I think that proposal would meet with the approval of members generally.  It would then be my intention to move when that sitting would conclude, which would start at 10.30 a.m., to re-assemble on the 1st August to receive any recommendations or amendments that would be sent to the Dáil from the Seanad.  On the 1st August I would move that we re-assemble on the 21st October.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to oppose this motion, but I should like to point out to the President that we cannot have a very satisfactory discussion of the estimates under these conditions. There are two estimates of importance to be considered&mdash;the estimate for the Ministry of Justice and the estimate for the Ministry of Industry and Commerce. They raise very important and far-reaching questions.  If these votes are allowed to go through now with only discussion of comparatively minor details, will the President give us a day or two days for their discussion on a motion after the re-assembly in October? We shall then, so far as the estimate for Industry and Commerce is <Col N="2081" /> concerned, be able to discuss it with the trade figures for six months instead of four months before us.  We must talk about the trade of the country some time, and it would be really better to get a day after the re-assembly when the Dáil will be less tired and the Minister will have a longer time to acquaint himself with the work of his Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would propose to afford a day for the discussion of any particular Department or Ministry, but I take it that that does not involve not passing the Estimates now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  We must pass the Estimates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I would propose to afford that facility to Deputies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion I had in mind was something like Deputy Corish's motion about Local Government, only reversed.  I thought that some Deputy on the Government Benches would move: &ldquo;That the Dáil approve of the policy of the Minister for Industry and Commerce as expressed in his Department.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a request to take Estimate No. 14, and I undertook to provide that we would take it now.  I take it there will be no objection to that course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Before you take up the Estimates, A Chinn Comhairle, what am I to understand by the President's statement that we are to adjourn until 10.30 to-morrow, and continue on until <Col N="2082" /> we are finished?  When might that be, I would like to ask?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope, not later than sunset to-morrow evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be sunset on Saturday evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not expect that, and I have been afforded some indications that it is the general desire of Deputies to facilitate the dispatch of business before sunset to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Then the only thing they have got to do is to go asleep on the Benches, which they probably will do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the President's intention as regards legislation as apart from the Estimates and the Appropriation Bill?  Does he propose to go on with the State Lands Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot say that until to-morrow morning.  After No. 14 I propose to take the Estimates which concern the Minister for Justice, as he has to go on important Government business to-night to London.  I take it that he will be afforded facilities to get his Estimates passed before he goes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Mr. ESMONDE Mr. ESMONDE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ESMONDE</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the President consider the inviting over of British Ministers to discuss these matters here instead of forcing our Ministers over to London on all occasions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to get notice of that.  It suits our convenience and purpose for the Minister to visit London to have this matter settled.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DÚN LAOGHAIRE," RHead="BLACKROCK, DALKEY CORPORATION BILL, 1924">
    <Title>PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DÚN LAOGHAIRE, BLACKROCK, DALKEY CORPORATION BILL, 1924.</Title>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
Tuarasgabháil ó Chó-Choiste na mBuan-Orduithe (Gnó-Príbháideach) dar dáta 8 Iúl, 1924, ná fuarthas laistigh den aimsir orduithe aon fhógra athchomhaire i gcoinnibh Tuarasgabháil Scrúdóir na mBillí Príobháideacha i gcás Bille Bhárdas Dhún Laoghaire, na Carraige Duibhe agus Dheilginse, 1924, agus dá réir sin go dtuigtar<Col N="2083" />an chéad léigheamh do bheith déanta sa tSeanad ar an mBille sin, eadhon, Bille Bhárdas Dhún Laoghaire, na Carriage Duibhe agus Dheilginse, 1924.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
Report of the Joint Committee on Standing Orders (Private Business). dated the 8th July, 1924, that no notice of appeal from the Report of the Examiner of Private Bills in the case of the Dún Laoghaire, Blackrock,<Col N="2084" />Dalkey Corporation Bill, 1924, has been received within the prescribed time, and that the said Dún Laoghaire, Black-rock, Dalkey Corporation Bill, 1924, is accordingly deemed to have been read a first time in the Seanad.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Report ordered to lie upon the Table.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - DRAINAGE MAINTENANCE" RHead="BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - DRAINAGE MAINTENANCE BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - STATE HARBOURS" RHead="BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - STATE HARBOURS BILL, 1924&mdash;FIFTH STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I notice that the President, when this Bill was last discussed in the Dáil, stated that the upkeep of Dún Laoghaire Harbour was about £24,000 per year.  That statement is somewhat misleading, because I believe that sum represents the charge for the upkeep of the East and the West Piers, as well as Carlisle Pier.  I assume that the powers which the State have secured under this Bill, in addition to the powers already possessed, will enable the authorities to put the Pier in proper condition, so as to make it suitable for passenger traffic.  I speak on this matter purely from the point of view of the disastrous effect which the unsuitable condition of the Pier has upon the development of tourist traffic. Owing to the work of voluntary organisations, passengers at the rate of one thousand to fifteen hundred per day come to this country <i>via</i> Dún Laoghaire during the tourist season. The present condition of the Pier and the confusion that is caused owing to lack of accommodation will have a very disastrous effect upon the development of tourist traffic.</P>
      <P>In pre-war days a sum of five or six million pounds yearly was spent in this country by tourists, and Deputies can realise what the loss of that traffic would mean to the people of the Free State.  Hotel keepers and others who had direct association with the tourists have suffered to a considerable extent during the four or five years of trouble in this country.  As the State controls this Harbour and is responsible for its upkeep the State should see that it uses its powers in the development of that tourist traffic.  The President I think will agree that it is very desirable that that should be done.</P>
      <P>As to the question of dues, in exercising the powers which they rightly obtain under Section 7, the Government should take into consideration the likely effect that any dues imposed will have upon the increase of passenger fares.  I merely mention that in passing.  But anybody who has had any experience of the conditions at this Pier and the effect which these conditions have had upon the development of tourist traffic will realise that it is the duty of the Government to exercise their powers to make some improvements at the Pier.  The President, I believe unintentionally did allow people to infer from his statement on the last occasion that the £24,000 mentioned was solely for the upkeep of Carlisle Pier.  That is not the case, as that amount represents the charge for the upkeep of the three piers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Owing to the hasty manner in which legislation is being passed at the present time, some matters do not get full consideration. Section 7 of this Bill provides that the Government shall have power to charge whatever dues they wish at Kingstown Harbour.  In no part of the Bill is any reference made to the relative positions occupied by the commercial port of Dublin and the State-owned Harbour of Kingstown.  When this Bill was before the Committee, counsel for the Government recognised in words the obligation on the part of a State-owned harbour not to do anything that would injure or prejudice the port of Dublin, but the Committee did not agree to an amendment to that effect being inserted in the Bill.  I would have liked to have had an opportunity of inserting an amendment <Col N="2085" /> which would embody in the Bill some recognition of the principle that a State harbour is not to be used to the detriment of the commercial harbour of Dublin, which has to do all its own maintenance out of funds secured from the trade entering the port.  I would refer the Dáil to the fact that in previous Acts of Parliament which gave the necessary powers to the Dublin Port and Docks Board to levy dues, etc., there was a clause of this sort.  In the 1902 Bill there was such a clause. That was sought to be extended in other Bills subsequently promoted in the British Parliament, but in no case has the right of Dublin Port to some protective clause been disputed.  In this Bill which is now brought forward there is no reference whatever to the relationship that should and must exist as between Kingstown harbour and the port of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Dun Laoghaire harbour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no use worrying about that now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not know that this Bill was coming on at this stage, and I think nobody else did.  I would like to suggest that it is not an equitable thing for this Dáil to pass a Bill of this sort without some recognition of the relationship between the two harbours.  It is quite true that there is less likelihood now of the unfair competition which the Dublin Port and Docks Board feared in the past, but there must always be a tendency for passenger boats, and sometimes cargo boats, to run into a comparatively free harbour in preference to a harbour that is charging dues for its upkeep and maintenance.  I submit it is not fair that this Bill should go through without some reasonable section being inserted safeguarding the interests of the port of Dublin.  I do not know whether the President will accept that, but, without having any official knowledge of it, I think that if a milder section had been suggested than that put forward by counsel on behalf of the Dublin Port and Docks Board before the Committee, it would have been accepted on behalf of the Government.  I do not know whether that is so or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2086" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand I did state that it was Dun Laoghaire Harbour, or, to speak according to the Statute, Kingstown Harbour, which cost £23,000 or £24,000 per year for upkeep. As soon as this Bill passes the name of that harbour will be changed to what it was previously.  It was changed to Kingstown, I believe, in the year 1836 by some Statute.  It will now revert to what it was before 1836, and for many years previously, that is, Dun Laoghaire.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Including the spelling of 1836.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  With regard to the question raised by Deputy Hewat, the present revenue we derive in respect of an expenditure of £23,000 or £24,000 is something amounting to £1,000 or £1,500 yearly.  I anticipate that the revenue derived will be increased fifteen times that sum, or twice fifteen times that sum.  That is a pretty considerable increase.  I do not think it would be fair to fix the price in Dublin as the figure at which the mail steamers should be charged.  After all, there is a difference between mail steamers and ordinary cargo steamers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>We accept that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I anticipate that the revenue will come to about £18,000 yearly as a result of the passing of this Bill.  This is an extraordinary expense upon the State at present.  While we are very anxious to develop tourist traffic, attract people to the country, see that they are treated with the greatest courtesy, and that their stay at the ports or harbours is not unnecessarily delayed, nevertheless, the expenditure on this harbour must of necessity be very economically spent.  While some expenditure may be necessary within the next couple of years, I do not anticipate that the pier will be made really up-to-date for some years to come.  Of the £24,000 spent on the harbour, a revenue of one-eighteenth or one-seventeenth is derived.  The Bill seeks to remedy that.  But for the introduction of this Bill, hasty as this legislation is, no change could be made in the revenue derived from the harbour, and no change, except for the worse, would take place so far as expenditure <Col N="2087" /> is concerned.  However hasty this legislation is, it certainly does bring in a very considerable increase in revenue compared with that of the last few years.  As it stands, the Bill is certainly an improvement on existing conditions.  Even if there were more time to spend in considering the Bill, I do not know that any improvement in the section would have been made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not taking exception to anything in the Bill except that it is the first Bill of the kind that has not recognised the relative positions of Dublin and Dun Laoghaire harbours. All I was asking the President to do was to see if he could insert some section putting the two harbours on some relative basis.  I agree that the object of the Bill is to enable the Government to get more revenue out of Kingstown or Dun Laoghaire harbour.  I wanted only to have a recognition of the Dublin position so far as future developments are concerned.  There is very little risk to-day, but when you are legislating you do not know how far ahead you are legislating for.  I think it is not the intention of the Government to injure Dublin at all. All I was pleading for was recognition of the old principle that competition should not set in as between the two harbours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the President aware that consultations have been going on for some time between the engineers of the railway companies and the Board of Works, and that improvements of a temporary nature have been recommended at the Pier?  In view of the altered situation that is created by the passing of this Bill, does the President not see the urgent necessity for going ahead with the improvements?  Will the Minister for Finance authorise the Board of Works to carry out the improvements without further delay?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I should prefer to await the return of the Minister for Finance before answering that question affirmatively.  In a large matter of that kind I think it would be only fair that the Minister directly responsible <Col N="2088" /> for a service, in which the Board of Works is concerned, should be consulted about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Bill passes from the Dáil, might I ask the President, seeing that there is no schedule attached to the Bill, whether a schedule of the proposed charges will come up for approval or be laid on the Table of the Dáil when decided upon?  If so, possibly that would give an opportunity of raising the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I believe it will not come before the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the President will agree that it would be unfortunate in the case of goods traffic if steamers were allowed to go into Dun Laoghaire harbour at a lower rate than Dublin. I agree with him so far as passengers are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is certainly not intended to do that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. -" RHead="ORDER OF BUSINESS">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - ORDER OF BUSINESS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the estimates, a number has been omitted from the Order Paper. After 54, which is Marine Services, there should be 52, Ministry of Industry and Commerce.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES." RHead="VOTE 14.&mdash;PROPERTY LOSSES COMPENSATION">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES.  VOTE 14.&mdash;PROPERTY LOSSES COMPENSATION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That a sum not exceeding £4,833,000 be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the Charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1924, for payments in respect of destruction of, or injuries to, property within the period 21st January, 1919, to 12th May, 1923, inclusive, under the Damage to Property (Compensation) Act, 1923, as amended and otherwise.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There have been some complaints with regard to this particular service, <Col N="2089" /> that delays have taken place in hearing the cases, in dealing with the cases and in the payment of awards when made. I have investigated a number of these cases personally, and I find that in very few instances have all the requirements been complied with by persons who put forward claims under the Damage to Property Act.  In cases where claims have been made, sometimes plans have not been furnished and particulars not given.  In other cases which have been heard, it has been brought to my notice that solicitors engaged have not presented the decrees to be signed by the judges or have not lodged the necessary particulars.  If it should occur that Deputies are informed of cases in which delay has occurred, I should be very pleased to institute inquiries, in order to see that the utmost possible expedition, as far as the Government is concerned, will be used to get these cases out of the way.</P>
    <P>I have been informed that in certain counties a number of people are very willing to start, directly the cases are heard, re-building.  In any of the cases that have been brought to my notice I have not been able to find that the Government itself, or any Department of the Government, is responsible for the delays that have been occasioned. Only this morning I had a case, and I am informed that the Board of Works has not had the necessary information submitted to it to enable it to deal with that case expeditiously.  I mention that case because some Deputies have spoken to me on it, and I have had many letters upon it, and some outsiders approached me on the same subject. That deals with &ldquo;C.&rdquo; As regards &ldquo;A&rdquo; we are not concerned with that except to this extent, that a representative from the Saorstát is on the Wood Renton Commission, formerly called the Shaw Commission, and it is possible that some question may arise in that connection, and I should be glad to give any information that is available to Deputies.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The question I want to raise on this matter is in regard to a matter about which I gather from the newspapers there has been some contention as to the payment of the compensation. I think it was generally felt <Col N="2090" /> that there was an understanding arrived at between the British and the Irish Governments respecting damage done on the one hand by the British troops and police, and on the other hand by Irish troops and police and others, and that each side was to bear the cost of the compensation according to the category in which the owners of the property lay, whether they were supporters of the British Government or supporters of the Irish Government. I understood that it has been found impossible to get awards paid to owners of property whose property was destroyed or damaged by British troops or British Auxiliaries or Black and Tans.  The contention was that they were not bound to pay that damage, and that such damage was done by troops or police, or soldiers under orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not know whether I am stating the position correctly, but I think there are very few Deputies in the House but know that much of the damage was done by people acting under orders and that if they were not acting under orders it was a very easy thing to say they were.  I think it is necessary to have the thing explained and find out from the Government how far they have given away their position, and whether these people are to be compensated equally with the others, no matter whether their property was damaged by troops or police acting under orders or not, or whether it was nominally or legally malicious or otherwise. I draw attention to the position of persons whose property was in the Six Counties, who themselves lived in the Six Counties, and whose property was damaged by officials, police or otherwise of the British Government, and who are not receiving any compensation. It seems to me that there is a great lapse here that such persons who have equally suffered or at least have suffered greatly should not be entitled or not be receiving&mdash;they certainly are entitled&mdash;any compensation for the damage done by persons acting under orders of police or military.  I heard it stated, with what correctness I cannot say, that it is only damage that was done maliciously that would be compensated for in the technical sense; it cannot be malicious if done <Col N="2091" /> in the name of the Crown.  I do not know whether that is the correct legal position or not.  It is an immoral position and an inequitable position, and I think our Government should contest it to the full.  I am quite sure there were many cases of damage to property by individuals which could quite legitimately be repudiated by the Irish authorities if they so wished, and possibly in such cases the Irish Treasury would be saved a very considerable sum.</P>
    <P>I would like to know whether it is a fact or is not a fact that the Irish Government has not repudiated responsibility for damage done to private property during the pre-Truce period, even though they are satisfied that such damage was not done under orders.  If the position taken up is correct in the one case, surely it is correct to take it in the other.  Very few people in this country who have any interest in this Property Losses Compensation but thought the whole matter was clear and well understood between the two Governments, and that the full compensation was to be paid and shares borne by the respective Governments according to a common understanding.</P>
    <P>I want to know from the Minister what is the position in regard to compensation for damage done by persons admittedly acting under orders of the British authority and persons who should have been acting under these authorities, but who acted upon their own account.  Secondly, what is the position in regard to sufferers from damage at the hands of the British or Northern authorities, as the case may be in the northern counties.  Are they being compensated, and if not, why not?  I hope the Minister will be able to give us a satisfactory answer as to the line taken by the Government, and that he will assure us that the full rights of Irish citizens are being demanded in this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. THOMAS O'CONNELL Mr. THOMAS O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOMAS O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>There is another aspect of the case in connection with this matter of property compensation that I think it would be well again to draw attention to, and in this connection my impression was rather the opposite to that of Deputy Johnson, <Col N="2092" /> because in these particular cases I thought the plea was that because they were not done under orders that compensation was not paid.  I referred to the cases familiarly known as looting cases, where merchants and a variety of other people had their property damaged and taken by force at night undoubtedly by the agents of the Crown Forces.  There have been many of these cases, and I think when these matters were under discussion before the Minister for Justice told us that it was a matter that was still in dispute between the British Government and the Irish Government as to where the responsibility should lie.</P>
      <P>There have been very many cases of the kind.  I have a particular case in mind that happened in a small town in Mayo.  The owner of the business was a general trader, publican, grocer and egg dealer, and because earlier in the day the Black and Tans were refused free supplies of drink, they came back at night and smashed the windows, took away all bottles of wine and whiskey they could lay hands on, and in addition smashed up several pounds worth of eggs ready for shipment.  The Minister knows there were many such cases, that many of those people had their business destroyed, and suffered very great loss.  They got no compensation.  I would like to know what really is the position now with regard to those cases; whether any decision has been come to?  Has any arrangement been come to with the British Government as to the acceptance of their responsibility?  and, if not, is it the intention of the Irish Government to compensate those people who undoubtedly have suffered loss and who ought to get compensation from somebody or other?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>In the early months of 1922, shortly after the Treaty was approved by the Dáil, certain supplementary negotiations took place between the British Government and representatives of the Provisional Government. Amongst other matters which formed the subject of these supplementary negotiations, this question of compensation figured largely.  I was backwards and forwards a good deal in connection <Col N="2093" /> with those supplementary negotiations, and I have a very clear recollection of the understanding that was come to with the British Government of the day&mdash;the agreement that was come to with regard to compensation for damage to property.  It was different from the agreement come to with regard to personal injuries.  In the case of personal injuries the agreement was a back-to-back arrangement, each side dealing with its own supporters, so to speak.  In the case of damage to property, the understanding clearly come to, without any modification or qualification whatsoever, was that each Government would pay for the destruction committed by its own troops and adherents, and it was well understood that there would be very little difficulty in finding out in a particular case by whom the damage was done.  I have, as I say, a very clear recollection of that, and a very clear recollection of a jest which I happened to make at the time when it was remarked that there would really be no bother in finding out by whom the destruction was done: that everyone knew in a particular case by whom the destruction was done, and that it would appear there was more definite information on the matter then than when questions were being answered in the House of Commons.  I got the reply that when the time came when I was answering questions in our own House of Commons they would see how much information I would have about points.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>They were good judges.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>It is certainly beyond any doubt that that was the arrangement arrived at in 1922.  Since then people with, apparently, short memories have been attempting to put a different construction upon the agreement, and to suggest that in certain classes of cases the principle of each side paying for the damage committed by its own troops and adherents should not be maintained and acted upon.  It is in connection with that matter which has arisen that I am crossing to London this evening.  Many despatches have passed between both Governments on the subject.  Sometime ago the Minister <Col N="2094" /> for Finance himself crossed to London and had a conference there with some British Ministers.  The most that perhaps I can say on the subject at the moment is that that principle is being maintained, the principle embodied in the agreement arrived at in January or February, 1922.  That principle is being strictly maintained by the Executive Council, and will be maintained.</P>
      <P>Now, there are certain classes of damage which do not come within the scope of the Wood Renton Commission or the Shaw Commission, as it was known, and which are none the less a very real grievance to the people concerned&mdash;damage occasioned by commandeering, damage occasioned by deterioration through neglect or otherwise of property that was commandeered, inconvenience and loss occasioned by the occupation of houses and so on.  Damage of that kind does not come within the scope of the Commission which is now sitting, or within the scope of any claim that could properly be laid before the courts.  Generally it may be taken that claims which would not come within the scope of the Malicious Injury Acts could not be brought before the existing Commission, that is which would not come within the scope of the Malicious Injury Acts had the damage in every case been committed, say, by a civilian or a body of civilians.</P>
      <P>It is a hardship that as yet there is no recognised compensation for loot.  It is a hardship that whereas if a man's goods were brought out to his backyard and burned, as did occasionally happen in these good old days, there would be compensation.  But if they were thrown in a lorry and driven away there would be none.  That is an anomaly, and it is something that would require treatment in the future. But Deputies will appreciate the difficulties in dealing with cases of loot or of alleged loot.  The law in the past, or the existing law, makes no provision for cases of common robbery or theft or loot.  The taking away of property is not covered, but injury or destruction to property is covered by the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I take it that the guiding principle there was simply the practical difficulty of proof.  It is not impossible that you <Col N="2095" /> would have stories of masked men coming in and taking £500 in notes out of a teapot.  You do not know whether they did or not, and your belief, or disbelief, in the story will depend very much on what you think of the narrator. As I say, the law did not make provision in the past for the mere removal of property as distinct from its destruction.  There have been rather prolonged negotiations on the subject. There should be established here by agreement some kind of court, tribunal, or committee which would deal with those, undoubtedly, genuine and pressing cases which are not covered by the existing Commissions&mdash;cases of property taken and not returned, or returned in a very deteriorated condition, cases of houses commandeered and occupied for a long time without compensation, and cases of loss to traders owing to restrictions imposed by the powers of the military under regulations which prevailed here at the time.  The members of the motor trade suffered very considerable losses.  Certain other establishments, such as printing places, were closed down and cases of that kind are not covered by the existing Commission which is dealing only with injury to, or destruction of, property. The expression has been used that we were hoping to have established here a branch of the War Compensation Court.  That might easily create a false impression, and it is not a set of words that ought to be adhered to in this connection.  The War Compensation Court has a very definite meaning. It is a tribunal established in England to meet cases of loss inflicted on civilians in England, due to the action taken by the military authorities there, in the conditions which prevailed in the course of the European war.  The military, as of course happens in every country in time of war, were given very arbitrary and comprehensive powers which they had to use in disregard of the rights of the civilian population.  That Court was established to meet cases of that kind.  It had its own terms of reference, which would not be at all applicable to the conditions which I have been touching on, the conditions of this country, and the kind of cases that remain to be <Col N="2096" /> dealt with arising out of the conditions that existed here.  Therefore, I think, neither by the members of the Executive Council nor by other members of the Dáil, ought the phrase become stereotyped that we want to establish here a branch of the War Compensation Court.</P>
    <P>We want to establish by agreement some court, committee or tribunal which will deal with cases of loss and injury that are not covered by the terms of reference of the existing Commission. That might be done by an extension, by agreement, of the terms of reference of the existing Commission, or it may be done otherwise, but it is certainly a matter which ought to be done, and done in the near future, having regard to the considerable number of cases of genuine loss and hardship that still remain and have not yet been adequately dealt with.  The main thing I want to make clear is this, that no principle has been, or will be, recognised by the Executive Council other than this, that throughout the years in which there was conflict arising out of the fact that there was one administration here based on force, and endeavouring to maintain itself by force, and another administration here based on the results of the election of 1918, based on the popular will, injuries accruing, damage to property accruing, as the result of the conflict of these two administrations, and whatever forces they could muster, have to be met; there is no fairer principle by which that could be met and no fairer principle which we would be willing to consider other than this, that the damage committed by the adherents of a particular side must be met by that Government.  That is the principle on which we stood in the early months of 1922, and that is the principle on which we still stand.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is to say, whether or not these people professed to be acting under orders or otherwise?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Utterly regardless of the fact, which it would be difficult, if not impossible, to establish, whether they professed to be acting under orders or otherwise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of that <Col N="2097" /> statement, that it is on that business that the Minister is crossing to London, I do not think that it would be wise or judicious for me to go into detail.  I content myself with having raised the matter in the form I have done, insisting, or shall I say supporting, the Minister in his contention, and insisting, so far as one Deputy can, that that is and must be the principle on which this whole arrangement shall be completed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to raise the question of the procedure adopted by the Wood Renton Commission in dealing with cases in which the British Government would be liable.  It appears that the policy in many cases is to go down and see the property which has been damaged, and, I understand, the inspectors also go, one representing the Irish Government, I think, and one certainly representing the British Government.  I am speaking now with reference to my own constituency, where very considerable damage was done during 1920 and 1921. Those men do not make a detailed investigation of the property.  They do not examine it in anything like a technical sense, and very often they do not even ask, for instance, in the case of shops, for returns as to the trade done. I am informed that they only take a casual stroll around the place and make a report on which the Commission bases its award.  In many cases they interview the owners of destroyed property, and sometimes they come to a settlement.  Very often this settlement is not agreed to by the Wood Renton Commission.  It appears that the owners of property have whittled down their claims as far as they can.  They are put in an unfavourable position when they come to a settlement with the inspectors, but when that settlement comes before the Commission it is turned down and the Commissioners proceed to base their award on the report of the inspector.  I am afraid that Irish nationals have not been adequately protected under the policy I have outlined.  These property owners have been very badly hit.  Not alone have they lost considerable sums of money through looting, but they have been out of their capital for years, and <Col N="2098" /> that is a very serious loss in itself.  The whole position is quite unsatisfactory. There should be something in the nature of a careful examination of destroyed property, and instead of making those pretended agreements, the cases should be heard and determined by the Commission, and the parties, the injured property holders, should get, as I am informed they do not get, every opportunity of putting their cases before them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to mention one case in which I have been interested, and which apparently cannot be settled in such a way.  It is the case of an old lady who owned a house next door to the police barracks.  The military authorities notified this old lady that by a certain time on a certain night she was to remove all her furniture and go out of the house, as it was to be destroyed.  It was a menace to the constables in the barracks next door.  The solicitor for the old lady took up the case.  There is no court yet established to deal with such cases. The only way the British authorities can deal with it is to send over an official from the British War Office.  After an offer was made some other person in higher authority came over and repudiated the original offer.  I want to know from the Minister is that case to come before the Wood Renton Commission, or if he would bear a case like that in his mind, realising that there was more than one concerned with such a case?  It is a case in which many people interested themselves.  The house was in a seaside place, and the old lady relied on the revenue from this particular house as the only means of upkeep during the holiday season. No satisfaction up to the present time has been obtained, although the solicitor acting for the old lady took all the steps desirable to make a satisfactory settlement.  I would like to know, in a case of that kind, who is to be the authority that will decide the amount of damage or compensation that is to be given, and whether the Irish Government will have a representative, or will they insist on their point of view being heard in regard to any unfair amount that may be offered, or in regard to the delay that has taken place in bringing <Col N="2099" /> such a case to a satisfactory settlement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephMcGoldr" hpid="Mr. McGOLDRICK Mr. McGOLDRICK">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGOLDRICK</NameTxt>
      <P>This vote involves a sum for compensation for pre-Truce damage amounting to three million, five hundred thousand pounds. I think the Commission that was agreed to to assess pre-Truce damages must be proceeding very slowly.  After some three years we have awards for damage withheld from several parties.  It is due to the delay on the part of this Commission who have those awards assessed and returned for discharge.  A great deal of capital is being made on behalf of persons who had property damaged or destroyed during the British regime and who are said to be without compensation. That can only be due to the delay on the part of this Commission. It is militating against our claim here which is that no one has suffered injury through our part in this matter. We should have a great deal less responsibility under this head than is our share.  We have had heavy responsibilities placed on us through this Commission, and here we are delayed in reconstruction owing to the awards not being made.  Allegations exist that the delays are wilful.  We should know if this is true, and if so what course it is proposed to take.  I suppose these are some of the instances the Minister will be concerned with in his proposed interview across the Channel. The terms of reference of this Commission have been clear.  I do not think there is any room for trifling with those things.</P>
      <P>As to the items on this list, all those are capable, within the terms of reference of being decided by this Commission. I do not see the necessity for setting up a separate Commission to consider those cases that are set up outside the scope of the terms of reference. If such a Commission is to be set up, when are we to expect any result from its deliberations?  Is this to continue indefinitely, and is the nation to remain in bad odour over those unsettled claims?  It is necessary to have all those things adjusted in order that the agreements we have entered into may be honourably carried out?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephHenness" hpid="Mr. HENNESSY Mr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the <Col N="2100" /> remarks of Deputy McGoldrick and the others who have spoken on this subject, and I am glad to hear that the Minister for Justice is proceeding to London to hold a conference with the British authorities to clear up the matters that are in dispute.  That is why I rise to see whether we can get some points cleared up in connection with this whole matter.  We know that there are many people who have had genuine claims placed before the Commission, and whose awards were made six months ago, but payments, however, have not been forthcoming.  In County Cork a large amount of destruction was carried out by the British forces. I have some constituents who have placed their genuine claims before this Commission.  They have been investigated, and the awards were made as far back as six months ago, but no payment is forthcoming.  It is a delicate matter to touch on at the moment.  We are dealing with an International Commission, but, at the same time, when one hears rumours of interference with the members of this Commission one is entitled to ask is there any such interference with the members by any outside authority?  We have non-decree cases, and the terms of reference state specifically:&mdash;&ldquo;Sub-head A: In cases where no proceedings have been instituted, or if instituted, have not resulted in a final decree being given.&rdquo;  We have numbers of non-decree cases over which there has been some quibbling. I do not say it is being done by the members of the Commission.  As far as I am aware, those gentlemen have always done their very utmost to satisfy me.  I have no complaints and no reasons to grumble, but there are a certain number of non-decree cases hung up, and we want to know why those cases are hung up and who is responsible for the hanging up.  When we hear rumours outside that certain branches of the British Government are attempting to dictate the meaning of the agreements reached between the Saorstát and the British Government, we want to know from the Minister for Justice if he has heard anything like that and if there is any foundation for those rumours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We also want to know whether the <Col N="2101" /> members of the Commission take into account the political views of certain people whose claims go before them. And if they do, why do they do it, if the cases are genuine cases?  We understand that this is a Commission set up by both countries under a panel arrangement.  There are English and Irish representatives and English and Irish investigators.  Those investigators representing both parties go into the country and they investigate those cases and place their reports before the Commission.  Under these circumstances what right have any British authorities to interfere with this Commission? We have the same right. There are 30,000 claims paid up to date.  The majority of those were very large claims, and no one on our side attempted to interfere with the Commission in apportioning the awards. We did not care what the political views of those parties were so long as their claims were genuine.  Now we have five or six thousand claims hung up.  I hope the Minister will be able to relieve the minds of Deputies in the Dáil like myself who are being worried over those matters.  I have put down questions for to-morrow on this matter, and I am glad that an opportunity is given to the Dáil this evening of raising these particular points before the Minister proceeds to London.</P>
    <P>With regard to the War Compensation Committee, I do agree with the Minister that it is time that some such Commission should be appointed here to deal with the large number of claims, claims for looting and things of that nature, which do not come within the terms of reference of the Shaw Commission.  Very large losses have been suffered and very large claims have been made by traders and others under that particular heading.  I hope that after this conference settles down to work within the next couple of days in London our Ministers will be able to return and tell us that payment of those claims, which are now hung up and have been hung up for the last six months, will be very largely expedited and that there will be no further worry to Deputies about them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="Mr. P. HOGAN (Clare) Mr. P. HOGAN (Clare)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. HOGAN (Clare)</NameTxt>
      <P>There was <Col N="2102" /> an old recipe for dealing with Ireland's troubles under British rule, and it was to refer them to a Commission.  I hope the Minister for Justice has not accepted that principle with a view to postponing claims for compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Deputy any suggestions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I was glad to hear him say that there was a new Commission to be set up to deal with the cases that did not come within the terms of reference of the Shaw Commission, because there are very many such cases. I hope that the Minister will not take a headline in speed and in efficiency from the Shaw Commission, and that his Commission will work better and give quicker results.  In awarding compensation the Shaw Commission has adopted what we may call a very bad principle.  I will mention three towns in my own constituency&mdash;Miltown Malbay, Lahinch and Ennistymon&mdash;where property was destroyed on a more or less wholesale scale by the forces of the Crown, and where awards were made in a very parsimonious fashion. Representatives of the Commission went down to these districts, and they calculated according to their own ideas what the destroyed premises would be worth.  They endeavoured to reconstruct these premises in their own minds on something like a fairy estimate, and they did not reconstruct them on the basis of what these premises would be surely worth in these districts.  They reconstructed them from the point of view of no solid fabric whatever.  They reconstructed them from some buildings that were allowed to stand, and never gave consideration to the fact that the destroyed buildings had been singled out by the forces of the Crown, because they were of a better class than those which they left standing.</P>
      <P>There is another aspect of the matter, and Deputy Hennessy referred to it, and it is, that compensation is withheld because of political views.  I think that is a mistaken way of dealing with the matter, and I am sure Deputy Hennessy would know whether that is what the Government are doing in some cases or not&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2103" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephHenness" hpid="Mr. HENNESSY Mr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not insinuate anything against our Government on that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Some Government is holding it up.  There are so many Governments in this country that it is impossible to know what Government is doing it.  I will refer the Minister to a particular case I have in mind.  In that case a motor car was taken away by the Auxiliaries and destroyed; and the plea was put up that the motor car was destroyed by these forces not under orders, and that, therefore, there was no compensation to be awarded notwithstanding the fact that it was vouched for by a major in the English army that he saw these forces destroying the car.  That is one side of the matter.  Then these Auxiliaries went back into the garage and they took away the tools that that man might sometimes employ to make a living. What was alleged in that instance? That the tools were stolen, and that he was, therefore, not entitled to compensation. So that in both cases he was cut out of compensation.  These are cases that should certainly get compensation, and they should be included in any terms of reference provided for the new Commission; and it should be a suggestion to the Commission from this Government that they should expedite their findings and consider the cases before them much more expeditiously than has been done.  I could give scores of cases of a similar character, but I think the one I have given is sufficient.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>In considering this Estimate we are dealing with various classes of compensation claims under five separate heads.  The whole question of compensation for destruction or injury or damage done in this country is almost bewildering at the present time, because the court to which the claimant has to make application depends, in the first place, upon the nature of the claim, and in the second place, depends largely upon the period during which the damage was done.  We have what is known, or what was known, as the Shaw Commission, which deals with and has dealt with pre-Truce claims.  As far as my personal experience is concerned, I think <Col N="2104" /> that the Shaw Commission, and the members of it, are to be commended for the manner in which they have dealt with these claims.  I think they have not been over dilatory in the immense amount of work that they had to get through, but I think, taking them as a whole, they have so far given satisfaction all round, and that is saying a great deal for any Commission, especially for a Commission dealing with compensation.  I would particularly like to know, in regard to all these items which are set out in this vote, what is the meaning of the figures which we see under the head of 1923-24 as against the figures under the head 1924-25.  Do these first set of figures mean not only that the money has been voted but that it has been paid?</P>
      <P>I think that would be a very interesting reply if the Minister is in a position to give it, because the complaint that is brought, and I think very justly brought, and which is brought home to every Deputy, I am sure, every day for the last twelve months, is not so much that claims have not been considered, not so much that awards have not been made, but rather that payments have not been made of the awards that have been determined by these various courts.  It is especially in regard to item C, which comprises the cases that come under the Damage to Property Act, 1923 I make these few remarks. Last year £4,000,000, it appears, was voted towards the payment of these awards.  What I want to know is, has that £4,000,000 been paid?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, and £2,000,000 more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamArcherRedmond" hpid="Captain REDMOND Captain REDMOND">
      <NameTxt>Captain REDMOND</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I am very pleased to hear it.  That being so, I cannot understand if this £6,000,000, as the Minister now says has been already paid, why the Estimate for the coming year is only to be £3,500,000, because I certainly would venture to say that nothing like 50 per cent. of the amount of claims that have come before the various County Courts under the Damage to Property Act, and the awards made thereon, have been paid.  Therefore, I cannot understand why the Estimate for the coming year should <Col N="2105" /> show a reduction and not an increase upon the Estimate for the year that has passed.  The Damage to Property Act is in existence barely only a year, and I cannot understand how the amount to be paid during the coming year is estimated to be less than the amount that was paid during the past year. The complaints that are received are so numerous, and so widely scattered, that I must confess that I think the amount to be paid in the coming year must be considerably more than the amount that has been paid up to this. I would also like to ask the Minister whether these awards&mdash;award is a term that perhaps we may be allowed to use to cover what are known both as Decrees and Reports&mdash;have been paid both in Decrees and Reports, and if not, when it is intended that what are known as the Report cases shall be paid, and when it is determined that they shall be paid, whether the Report cases are to be paid entirely in securities or cash, or partly in securities and partly in cash.  There is a distinct difference, I admit, between what are known as Reports and Decrees, but what I think would be of great use to the community generally is to make it clear that there is also to be a distinction between the method of payment in regard to these two classes of awards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The difficulty that I have been up against, mostly, has been this, that claims have been made, and that the claimants have been successful in Court, and they have walked out of Court almost on the tips of their toes, feeling at long last that they are to be compensated, but I am sorry to say in the great majority of cases which I have had anything to do with they have not been paid.  I do not think that is an exaggerated statement, and that is the almost universal experience of the members of the Dáil.  I think it would be well, therefore, if the Ministry of Finance could follow the example that they have already shown in the case of the Shaw Commission in regard to the claims made and the awards made under the Damage to Property Act.  I think the general feeling throughout the country is &ldquo;Oh, you would have been all right <Col N="2106" /> if your claim had come before the Shaw Commission, because the Shaw Commission would have made your award, and above all you would have been paid, but you are in a different position now, because your claim came before the County Courts under the Damage to Property Act.  It is true the award has been made, but your claim has not been paid.&rdquo;  I, therefore, sincerely trust that the Ministry of Finance, which of course is the Department primarily concerned in this matter, will expedite the payment of these sums which have already been awarded.  I admit that in the matter of Reports they are up against considerable difficulty, for personally, I think that the whole system of Reports is a bad one, but that is neither here nor there, for it is in the Act.  The fact is that a judge is sent down to the country, and he sits judicially and hears a case, and then his decision is to be further subject to the ruling of the Minister for Finance and that is not, I think, at all a proper or wise proposal.  But there it is, and the Minister for Finance has now the burden thrown upon him of going into all these Report cases, and deciding whether in his opinion the judge who sat upon them was right in the decision he had come to.  I think it is an exceedingly cumbersome and irksome procedure, and one that is prone to bring delay, but even that being so, I think that there has been unfortunate, and indeed, perhaps unnecessary delay in this regard.  I do think that it is only right that the Ministry should be told that it is time that these cases, numbering as they must, thousands upon thousands, which have not yet been dealt with, finally decided and paid, should from this on be expedited.</P>
    <P>I see that there is also an item regarding expenses in connection with investigations of these claims.  These expenses are confined, I see, to the period covered by the Damage to Property Act, and I think that probably the amount is none too large.  But I took occasion on a previous Vote in connection with the Personal Injuries Committee, which is another separate court to which applicants have to go for another class of injury, to impress upon the Ministry that they should <Col N="2107" /> provide for the Personal Injuries Committee in the same way as they have provided in this case for the damage under the Damage to Property Act, and I hope that that suggestion will be considered by the Ministry of Finance. I would also like to know whether this £6,000,000 which is down beside item A for the period 1923-24 has actually been paid.  I think it is well that people should recognise that these sums have been paid, because they do not know that they have been paid. I think it worth while, therefore, calling attention to these various items, hoping that the Ministry will do everything possible to expedite the further payment of the sums already due on foot of awards that have been made under the various heads in this Vote.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMcGarry" hpid="Mr. McGARRY Mr. McGARRY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGARRY</NameTxt>
      <P>I merely want to ask a question; I am not going to make a speech.  I would like to know whether it is a fact that people who are claiming compensation for damage to property understood that a report was the same as a decree.  I would also like to know whether it was a fact, and I think I am right in stating that it was, that there is no power under the Act giving any Judge, District Justice, or President of any Court power to issue a decree under this Act.  I may be corrected; I suppose it would be a matter for the Attorney-General to correct me, but he is not here.  I take it that I am quite right in stating that there is no power in the Act to make a decree; there was only power to report, and that all decrees made under this Act were not in accordance with the law. I would like to have an expression of opinion as to whether that is correct or not.  I am advised that it is so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>Under heading C, I would like to bring forward a couple of cases of utterly inadequate compensation awarded, and practically under compulsion accepted by certain individuals in respect of damage done during the Irregular movement in July, 1922, under which this heading comes. In 1922 Ballymore-Eustace, County Kildare, was occupied by the Irregulars, and the Government considered it necessary to have them removed.  They sent a certain number of soldiers there, <Col N="2108" /> and they occupied the Central Hotel and other houses there at random.  The consequence was that very extensive damage was done to this hotel, which is owned by Mrs. Julia Lawlor.  The doors were all smashed to atoms; the woodwork of the windows was smashed and practically all the furniture was made into matchwood.  Great injury and damage was done to the roof and walls, and also to the out-offices, and a great deal of injury was done to the shops connected with this hotel.  This lady is an old person and a very nervous woman, and she was reduced almost to poverty as a result of this. She claimed £600.  It was too much, of course, but the amount that was offered to her and that she accepted&mdash;for she was told that if she did not accept it she would get nothing&mdash;was £120 or £125.  Anybody, even a novice, who looked at the damage done could see&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Was this case before a court?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>The arbitrators gave £120, and she was told that if she did not take it she would get nothing.  It was obviously unjust.  Anybody could see that at least £350 would be a very low computation, and would only partly pay for the damage that was done.  She took this money because she was absolutely poverty-stricken.  I think that that was a most unfair advantage to take of this woman.  I brought the case several times before the Ministry, and the last time the President said he would go into the matter. That was some months ago.  These things naturally give rise to great discontent, and you can hardly wonder at that when a person's house is taken from them for defence purposes, everything in it destroyed, and nothing adequate given as compensation.  There was another case in the same village where a large quantity of wood work was damaged, windows and floors broken, and only £10 was given&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy sure that this is under the Damage to Property Act, or is it under the Public Works Vote for compensation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>It comes within these dates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2109" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a question of dates; it is a question of machinery.  Did these people take action under the Damage to Property Act?  There is another Vote for premises commandeered by the Army under which these things have been discussed for a long time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately I was away&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has no right to raise that at the wrong time because he was away when we carried the other Vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>I wished to bring these cases to the attention of the Government, because they are manifestly unjust.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I forgot to ask the Minister if he took note of the class of cases which I referred to in the Six Northern Counties, where people suffered damage to their property at the instance of Crown Forces, but have not been paid&mdash;and apparently are not to be paid unless something is done&mdash;compensation for any damage, and whether these are amongst the cases, or the class of cases, which are the subject of negotiations between the two Governments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I might as well deal with that point now.  Residents in the Six County area who suffered damage to property can proceed in the courts under the Malicious Injury Acts which are in force there, and I understand that procedure has been adopted by many with sufficiently good results and that decrees were given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Many of them were obeying the general instructions of the Government of the Republic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Up to a date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry Deputy Hogan (Clare) has left; he asked certain questions and made certain comments which I wish to deal with.  A Deputy should not get up here and make a general sweeping indictment of delay and inefficiency with regard to <Col N="2110" /> anybody or any institution, without having made some reasonable investigation of the facts. The Wood Renton Commission has not been dilatory or inefficient and I think it is a very definite proof of that that £6,000,000 has been paid out in respect of pre-Truce damage. The Wood Renton Commission is not a very long time in existence.  It is not quite two years in existence, and the task which it had to shoulder was not a light one.  The fact that £6,000,000 has been paid out on foot of awards of that Commission in respect of pre-Truce damage is in itself some evidence that Deputy Hogan was just a little sweeping in his indictment of the work of that body.  Delay, where there has been delay, is rather in respect of post-Truce damage and in respect of payment on foot of decrees given in the courts.</P>
      <P>So far as I can ascertain the factors making for delay have been rather mixed.  There has in many cases been delay, because of delay on the part of the applicants' own solicitor in complying with the necessary formalities of preparing the decree and reporting.  Then there has been necessary delay occasioned by the making of inquiries as to whether a successful plaintiff has any arrears in respect of income tax rates, rates, or land annuities. If it is found that there are any such arrears the Government may deduct the amount of such arrears from the amount given by the decree. Finally, it has to be remembered that 27,000 of these cases had to be handled and the staff resources and man power in the handling of them were limited. The limitations have been the limitations simply of a human machine, but I think if the Deputies&mdash;I have no doubt that complaints are very numerous and widespread&mdash;independently made some inquiries they would find that in many cases the delay is due to factors that are within the control or should be within the control of the applicants themselves.  When these cases have been traced by Government Departments, it has been discovered that in a great many of them, if not in the majority of them, the delay has been in the offices of the applicants' own solicitor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2111" /> Deputy Redmond asked me about the Estimate of £3,500,000.  He thinks it small though in fact £6,000,000 approximately has already been paid out, and he has expressed the belief that at least as much would need to be paid in the future, but the £3,500,000 which is down as the Estimate for the current financial year does not take stock of the amount of securities that will be issued and it is anticipated they will be considerable.  The awards actually made by the Wood Renton Commission as distinct from the decrees given by the courts appear in the next issue of <i>Iris Oifigiúil</i> after they are made and are paid for the most part within 10 days or a fortnight.</P>
    <P>In the matter of meeting awards made by the Wood Renton Commission, it is well that Deputies and the public generally should know we are up-to-date and intend to keep up-to-date and awards are being paid as quickly as they are made by the Commission. There has been a great deal of ill-informed criticism on this question of compensation.  A good deal of the criticism comes from the fact that certain classes of damage are not covered by the terms of reference of this Commission at all.  That is not the fault of the Commission.  The Commission must act within its terms of reference and there is no use blaming the Commission because a particular case which is not within its scope is not dealt with. The cases that are within its scope have been dealt with and dealt with I submit very expeditiously and very efficiently indeed.</P>
    <P>Both Deputies Hogan waxed eloquent about the way in which this Commission gets about its work, that people go down, simply take the air of the locality, come back and present a report. Now, that is drawing the long bow, and I submit there is another side to the picture, a very different side. The Deputy knows the physical ailments which is contrary to shortsightedness, the ailment of long-sightedness, that where you are near a thing it scarcely exists at all, and the further you go away from it the more clearly you see it, and it becomes quite large.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2112" /> It is very often the case in damage to property that the further you get away from it the more clearly you begin to see the damage, the more clearly you realise it, and the full extent of it, until after the lapse of a couple of years it is a very big matter, indeed, and anyone who attempts to make light of it is your sworn enemy.  As between the extreme of the picture that the Deputy attempted to paint, and the other extreme probably the truth lies midway. The fact is that it is a very big task, indeed; that it is almost well nigh impossible to get accurate evidence, and that you have to send down some man to make a fair appreciation, or what he believes is a fair appreciation and to make an offer.  This offer is not a &ldquo;take it or leave it&rdquo; offer.  It is an offer to settle the matter out of hand, or to await the ordinary process of the Commission, and people who agree to settle the matter out of hand cannot, in addition, come along and ventilate their grievances.  They are free agents in the matter.  They are told our estimate of the damage which they suffered is &mdash;&mdash;pounds.  &ldquo;We have made rather a thorough examination; we believe that the damage you suffered is £&mdash;&mdash;; if you wish to contest that and to go into the case at full length and produce witnesses and account books, showing that your stock-in-trade was so much, very good, but that will occasion some months' delay.&rdquo;  Now, a person who agrees to settle in conditions like that should not, after agreement, come along to Deputy Connor Hogan and so rouse his feelings and emotions as to make him address the Dáil at length on the subject.  Deputy Wolfe gives the case of a constituent of his, a very nervous lady, who only claims £660, which Deputy Wolfe says &ldquo;was, of course, too much&rdquo; for damage occasioned by the troops when they were in occupation of her premises.  That is a difficult case.  Deputy Wolfe says that £600 was, &ldquo;of course, too much.&rdquo;  I do not know why he says &ldquo;of course.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say that it has been the universal practice, knowing that you would get very much less than what you ought to get, to ask far too much.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2113" />
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not mind admitting that it has been the universal practice on the part of Government officials to recognise the universal practice of applicants claiming too much, so that it just works out in this way, that as between the figure of £600&mdash; which &ldquo;was, of course, too much&rdquo;&mdash; that she claimed and the figure of £120 that was offered, we are not in a position to decide.  We have only Deputy Wolfe's evidence before us that £600 &ldquo;was, of course, too much.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>But not as much as £120 was too little.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Of course.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN LEAS CHEANN COMHAIRLE AN LEAS CHEANN COMHAIRLE">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>took the chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact is that there was no claim in law for the commandeering. There was a claim for the damage.  If Deputy Wolfe's constituent thinks that the amount offered to her in compensation for actual damage done to the premises was too small it would be open to her to press her claim in court.  That is not, of course, a question of acceptance or non-acceptance at all.  It was open to the lady in question to refuse the offer, which was not her conception of the damage done, and she could go to the courts and press her claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>In reference to that, I wish to say the woman was told that if she did not accept £120 she would get nothing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The question did not arise on this Vote at all, and the Ceann Comhairle told us that some time ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The lady's solicitor could have told her otherwise.  Now, as to report cases from the court&mdash; these are cases where there is no claim in law, but where a recommendation from a judge in any particular case that he had satisfied himself as to the circumstances, would be considered on the basis of making an <i>ex-gratia</i> grant. These cases will be paid when the Damage to Property (Amendment) Bill becomes law.  They will be dealt with in general in the same way as regards cash and securities.  But in the special cases of loot, only securities will be <Col N="2114" /> issued.  I think that is the intention of the Ministry of Finance.  I do not know what Deputy McGarry's point was in asking whether &ldquo;only reports could be made under the Act and no decrees could be given.&rdquo;  So far as I know, that is utterly inaccurate, but it is perhaps the kind of point that the Deputy should put in writing to the Minister. I am not sure that I have covered all the points of importance that were raised.  I am not quite sure whether Deputy Hennessy was here when I was speaking first or not, but it did seem to me that he was re-opening a matter which I had dealt with and regarding which I made a rather definite statement to the Dáil.  I do not propose to go back on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say if any assistance can be given in cases of the claims which I mentioned, or if the individual concerned who is a citizen is to be left to the mercy of the British authorities?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not like pronouncing on a particular case after just a hurried and superficial statement of the circumstances.  My own view would be that in the circumstances set out by Deputy Davin it would be a case for such a committee or tribunal as may in the future be established and not for the existing Wood Renton Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister was good enough to say that Deputy Patrick Hogan and I were drawing the long bow.  I will give him a concrete instance where one of the Wood Renton inspectors went out to examine the remains or ashes of a rick of hay that had been burned something like three years previously.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>He could not see the rick of hay then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not say he could.  His sight might penetrate to the fourth dimension.  That is the very point I wanted to bring out.</P>
      <P>Vote put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE" RHead="34&mdash;GENERAL PRISONS BOARD">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE 34&mdash;GENERAL PRISONS BOARD.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That a sum not exceeding £122,885 <Col N="2115" /> be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the expenses and charges which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1925, to defray the expenses of the General Prisons Board and of the establishment under their control, the registration of habitual criminals and the maintenance of criminal lunatics confined in district mental hospitals (17 and 18 Vict., c. 76; 34 and 35 Vict., c. 112, s. 6; 40 and 41 Vict., c. 49; 47 and 48 Vict., c. 36; 61 and 62 Vict., c. 60; 1 Edw. VII, c. 17, s. 3; 8 Edw. VII, c. 59; and 4 and 5 Geo. V, c. 58.)</P>
    <P>Deputies will note that the Estimate represents a decrease of £40,746 on last year's Estimate.</P>
    <P>Sub-head A&mdash;Salaries, Wages and Allowances.&mdash;The estimated expenditure under this sub-head shows an increase of £1,024, compared with the Estimate for the year 1923-24. The increase is due, in the first instance, to the appointment of a member of the Board at a salary of £740 a year and increased provision for bonus rendered necessary by the increased cost-of-living figure on which the bonus for the year is based.  The expenditure on this sub-head has been falling owing to the fall in the cost-of-living figure and the non-filling of the post of Inspector (£500 to £600) and the agent for discharged prisoners (£75).  The number of established employees on the 1st April was 13, and the number of unestablished employees 9, as compared with 12 established and 13 unestablished on the 1st April, 1922 &mdash;an increase of 1 in the established ranks and a decrease of 4 in the unestablished ranks.</P>
    <P>Sub-head B&mdash;Travelling.&mdash;There is a reduction of £100 on this sub-head. Although the Estimate for the past few years was below the figure in the present Estimate, that is explained by the fact that the normal inspection of prisons was not possible within the last three or four years, and that normal inspection has now been re-started.  Each prison is now inspected and reported upon at least once every two months.  The incidental expenses <Col N="2116" /> which are provided for under this sub-head include a supply of newspapers, photo chemicals, carriage on parcels and matters of that kind.</P>
    <P>Sub-head C&mdash;Pay and Allowances of Officers, including Uniform.&mdash; This sub-head shows a decrease of £11,120.  The number of permanent warders provided for is 152, an increase of 3, as compared with the figure of last year.  The explanation of that is that vacancies in the post of farm steward and engineers had not been filled.  The sum provided for uniforms shows a reduction of £580, due to reduction in cost of uniform material and to the manufacture of uniforms by prison labour.  Reductions of £720 and £250 have been made under the provision for allowance to officers in lieu of quarters.</P>
    <P>Sub-head D &mdash; Victualling.&mdash;These figures are based on an estimated prison population of 1,600. They are based also on the approximate cost per head of each civil prisoner for the previous year.  It is felt that a smaller sum than the sum mentioned in the Estimate would not be sufficient.  The excess over last year's Estimate and the Estimate for 1922-23 is due to the cost of maintaining prisoners classed as &ldquo;military prisoners,&rdquo; in receipt of special diet in civil prisons.  It is hoped that the necessity for maintaining such prisoners will not arise during the current year, and that we will be able to defray the cost of maintenance of civil prisoners within the limits of the provisions that have been made.</P>
    <P>Sub-head E&mdash;Clothing, Bedding, Furniture, etc.&mdash;This sub-head shows a reduction of £500 on that of previous years.  The expenditure is necessitated by reason of damage and destruction of prison property by persons confined in civil prisons under military control and classed as &ldquo;military prisoners.&rdquo; The expenditure under this sub-head was high while conditions of that kind prevailed, but it is hoped that during the year 1924-25 the destruction will have been made good and complete renewals supplied to all the prisons within the amount provided.</P>
    <P>Sub-head F&mdash;Medicines, Surgical Instruments, etc.&mdash;Under this sub-head <Col N="2117" /> there is a decrease of £100, which is based on the requisitions of the medical officers of the various prisons, and it is considered that the amount asked will be adequate.</P>
    <P>Sub-head G&mdash;Fuel, Light, Water, Cleaning Articles, etc.&mdash;This is the same as last year's estimate.  It is felt that the provisions made will suffice, if none of the prisoners classed as &ldquo;military prisoners&rdquo; are committed to civil prisons and if the prisons are entirely under civil control.</P>
    <P>Sub-head H&mdash;Rent, etc.&mdash;The Prisons Board pay rent for various properties on which prisons are built, and it has been arranged that in cases of prisons like Clonmel, taken over by the military, the Board of Works will repay the rent, in which case the sub-head will be credited with any receipts. But provision has been made for all rents that are properly payable.</P>
    <P>Sub-head I&mdash;Escort and Conveyance. &mdash;There is a reduction of £2,000 for escort and conveyance of prisoners.  It is probably due to the normal functioning of the courts and the activities of the Gárda Síochána.  The estimate is the lowest that could be arrived at on that sub-head.  It can only be an approximation.</P>
    <P>Sub-head J&mdash;Ordinary Repairs.&mdash; There is a decrease of £1,500 under the provision made last year.  Owing to the conditions prevailing in the prisons during 1923-24, a very small portion only of the necessary maintenance work is carried out.  It is to be remembered that since the outbreak of the European War normal maintenance of prisons was not carried out.  Only unavoidable works were entered upon, with the result that expenditure under this sub-head must for a few years be above previous figures, in order to bring the prisons up to the standard that is properly required.</P>
    <P>Sub-head K.&mdash;This is a new sub-head under which provision is made for cost of wilful destruction of public property, which took place in practically all the prisons where prisoners classed as &ldquo;military prisoners&rdquo; were confined. The expenditure for 1923-24 exceeded the estimate by approximately £2,000, due to the fact that when the estimate was framed a certain <Col N="2118" /> amount of destruction had taken place and was provided for.  Subsequently, still more destruction took place, and but for the fact that the Clerk of Works was able to arrange for restoration work being carried out, in the main, by prison labour, the cost in this estimate would have been even heavier than it was.</P>
    <P>Sub-head L&mdash;Fine Fund, seems to be purely nominal.</P>
    <P>Sub-head M&mdash;Travelling and Incidental Expenses show a reduction on last year of £450.  The expenditure includes travelling, removal for temporary duty, and separation allowances to prison officers, burial of deceased prisoners, and expenses which are not provided for under other sub-heads.</P>
    <P>Sub-head M.M&mdash;Telegrams and Telephones, is a new sub-head, and the expenditure estimated for indicates a probable reduction of £50 on last year.</P>
    <P>Sub-head N&mdash;Maintenance of Children of Female Prisoners.&mdash;There was no child maintained during the year 1923-24; provision has been made for the maintenance of one child for the current year.  Of course, it can only be an estimate.</P>
    <P>Sub-head O&mdash;Maintenance of Criminal Lunatics in District Mental Hospitals.&mdash;With regard to this sub-head, the expenditure really does not come within the control of the Prisons Board and is placed on the Prisons Vote in consequence of an error in the drafting of an Act passed in 1901&mdash;the Lunacy Act.  The Board have repeatedly made representations that this is not a proper charge to place on the Prisons Vote and at one time a Bill was actually introduced to effect the change, but was not put through to its conclusion. It is a matter that might, perhaps, be looked into administratively in future. What I want to stress is that the estimate under this sub-head is not within the control of the Prisons Board.</P>
    <P>Sub-head P&mdash;Gratuities to Prisoners. &mdash;Expenditure under that sub-head is affected by the numbers discharged each year.  Since the outbreak of the European war committals were fewer; consequently discharges were limited, and the expenditure figure was somewhat smaller.</P>
    <P>Sub-head Q&mdash;Contributions to Discharged <Col N="2119" /> Prisoners' Aid Societies, is a small estimate of £150.  It is, I think the same amount each year.  Certainly it is the same as last year's amount. It is an expenditure for a grant of £50 to the Discharged Female Prisoners Aid Society, Henrietta Street, and a grant to the Borstal Association in respect of inmates discharged from Borstal Institutes.</P>
    <P>Sub-head R&mdash;Appropriations in Aid. &mdash;These Appropriations represent receipts from the sale of old stores, rents of cottages, excess of receipts over payments in the manufacturing department. The large amount of Appropriations in Aid realised for 1923-24 is due to the fact that sums amounting to £4,099 were received from the Government of the Northern Area in respect of the maintenance of Borstal inmates from that area maintained in the Borstal institutions, and also to the fact that the activity of the Governor of Mountjoy Prison resulted in an unprecedented output in the manufacturing department of that prison. Mats, prisoners' clothing, cell furniture, and so on, were made there.</P>
    <P>Deputy Johnson proposes to raise, I think, on this Estimate rather than on the adjournment the question of the condition of cells where prisoners sentenced to death are detained in Mountjoy. Perhaps it would be a more proper course if I let the Deputy make his point before giving such information as I have at my disposal with regard to it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter I wished to raise on the adjournment is better taken now while the Minister is present. Information came into my hands this morning dealing with men who, unfortunately, are under sentence of death, and it is necessary that if the matter is to be raised it should be raised at once.  I understand that in the past there have been special regulations enforced in respect of prisoners condemned to death.  A special large airy and bright cell was allocated, equal in size to three ordinary cells. There was also a prison officer in the cell with the prisoner.  Consequently it is necessary, in addition to the special brightness and airiness of the <Col N="2120" /> cell, to have a larger cell for two persons to occupy instead of one.  Two officials were in charge&mdash;one by night and one by day.  The officials were allowed to rest four and a half hours alternately.  A change has taken place under the new regime, presumably in the interests of economy.  Possibly it may be said that it is because of the fact that there are more persons under sentence of death than has been known before, and that no preparation for such large numbers&mdash;excessive numbers, unfortunately&mdash;have been made.</P>
      <P>The information I have is that these condemned prisoners are placed in a small ordinary cell, with an officer in charge night and day.  The cells have only sufficient cubic space for one person, and all the regulations of the prison&mdash;medical and otherwise&mdash;are against more than one person occupying such a cell.  Two persons have to occupy it now, and that practically means that an official is confined in the cell with the prisoner ten hours consecutively. If I gather the information aright that is the position.  If it is so. I think it is bad for the official and bad for the prisoner.  It is irritating and certainly, as I would think, inhuman to place any official, on the one hand, in charge of a prisoner under sentence of death for so long a time.  And, even worse, perhaps, to place the condemned person in such a position as to be in view of the same officer for so long a time.  It seems to me that the conditions of the past were probably the result of very long experience, and had at least, improved in the direction of humanising the last days or hours of a condemned man.  We ought not to lower that standard, and I would ask that some attention be paid to this matter immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To come to the general Vote, there are two or three matters I would like to draw attention to.  The first is to ask a question.  Is it intended that there should be an appointment of a chairman of the Prisons Board?  For the vice-chairman £1,000 yearly is estimated, but there is a blank space against the name of the chairman, whose normal pay would be £1,200 a year, presumably with bonus.  For a considerable time there has not been a <Col N="2121" /> chairman, and I would like to have an assurance from the Minister that there is no need and no necessity, and that it is not the intention to fill this office.</P>
    <P>Under sub-head (d) the Minister pointed out that there was an estimated population of 1,600.  Taking into account £31,000 for victualling, I calculate that comes to 7s. 6d. per week per person.  I hope the Minister will consult with the Minister for Local Government and other Ministers and compare the 7s. 6d. per week per person for rations purchased at wholesale prices with the cost of living outside. I recognise that a family outside is assumed to consist of two adults and three children.  At 7s. 6d. per week for a prisoner on prison fare find out what is the cost for the ordinary civilian and hence what ought to be paid, under the Local Government Department and other Departments, in wages? I will assume it is not the expectation of the Ministry that the civilian living outside would live on the same low standard that is allocated for prisoners living on ordinary prison fare.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Minister to consider the position, or rather, shall I say, to take some pains to find out the relations of the officers of the Prisons Board to Governors and the establishment generally, and how those relations compare with the relations of the officers to the Board hitherto.  From correspondence that I received I gather that there is a very keen sense of dissatisfaction with the way in which the work has been administered, particularly in regard to the little irritants, which the officers have been made to suffer.  I would like to know what number or what proportion, of the officers who were entitled to retire have retired, and does the Minister take into account the possibility of very many more retirements on pension unless the general irritation which, I understand, the officers feel they are now obliged to submit to is eased somewhat?</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Since Deputy Johnson gave notice, I made inquiries about the condition of the cells in Mountjoy that were used for men under sentence of death, and the position is, roughly, as described by the <Col N="2122" /> Deputy.  The dimensions of the ordinary cells in Mountjoy are 13 ft. long, 7 ft. wide, and 8½ft. high.  Certain special large cells, differing from the ordinary cells in that they are three times as wide, were used for the custody of men under sentence of death. There are at present in Mountjoy Prison four men condemned to death. There were two large cells, which are really constructed of three ordinary cells knocked into one.  One of these cells was destroyed by military prisoners, and is not at the moment available. There is, therefore, only one of these large cells available in the prison. That means that two of the men will have to be kept in ordinary cells.  It is true, as the Deputy says, that the humane practice prevailed in the past of endeavouring to make the conditions as tolerable as possible for men awaiting execution, but you are limited by your realities, and by your resources. When two large cells are not available, and when there are four men under sentence of death, then it becomes a question of simply doing what you reasonably can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In fact, what has happened is that one of these men is occupying the large cell and the other three are occupying three ordinary cells.  The cell that was destroyed, and that was in course of repair, will, I understand, be available to-night.  That will mean that two men will have the special large cell which was usual, and only two will be in the ordinary-sized cells. We tried to meet the situation by placing only one warder in charge, whereas in the case of the large cell with one man under sentence, two warders were with him constantly day and night.  In the smaller-sized cell, which at present, of necessity, has to be used, only one warder is engaged on that duty.  The medical report is to the effect that the prisoners, who were seen by the medical member of the Prisons Board on Tuesday, stated that they had everything they wanted and had no complaints to make, that they were in good health and satisfied and even pleased with the treatment they were receiving.  That is the official information at my disposal.  With regard to the point the Deputy has <Col N="2123" /> raised about the position of Chairman it will not be filled.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Minister passes from that will he say whether it is not possible to shorten the number of hours which the official has to remain in charge of the condemned men?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to be clear as to whether that representation is put forward on behalf of the official or on behalf of the men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>It is put forward from my own belief that a long time in company with a condemned man is bad both for the condemned man and the official.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter that I would undertake to inquire into &mdash;the notice has been short.  I understand the limitation is because permanent officers have to be engaged in that particular duty, and the number of permanent officers available is somewhat limited.  I will undertake that if it is possible to do anything in the direction suggested by the Deputy it will be done.</P>
      <P>Now it is not proposed to fill the position of Chairman of the Board and generally the future administration of the prison service is a matter that, at leisure, and when the pressure on the Department eases off, would need to be looked into and overhauled.  The Board is scarcely functioning now as a Board; it is simply acting as headquarters of the prison service, answering for the Department on all major matters, and seeking instruction upon any important matters that arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it admitted that the attendant is kept for ten hours in the cell with the condemned man?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>No, not ten hours. Eight or nine hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>The statement by Deputy Johnson is ten hours, and I was going to suggest that ten hours was too long for any warder or attendant to be confined in a cell with a condemned man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Deputy say that eight or nine hours is too long?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2124" />
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>Even so, I think it is necessary that a change should be made in that direction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I pass from that I would make it clear that the eight or nine hours' spell is only at night.  Prisoners under sentence of death get as much open air and exercise as is reasonably practicable to give them, and are allowed many other ameliorations denied to ordinary prisoners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the attendant at night be asleep or is he bound to keep awake?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>He would not be asleep.</P>
      <P>Vote put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE" RHead="31&mdash;MINISTRY OF JUSTICE">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE 31&mdash;MINISTRY OF JUSTICE.</Title>
    <P>Motion made and question proposed &mdash;&ldquo;That a sum not exceeding £24,238 be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1925, for the salaries and expenses of the Ministry of Justice.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a vote for my own Department, the Department of Justice, formerly Home Affairs.  The net estimate shows an increase of £7,738 over the estimate for last year. The principal increases are under sub-head A&mdash;Salaries, Wages and Allowances&mdash;£8,516, and sub-head AA, which is new, for the cost of Film Censorship, and which appears for the first time on the Estimate, £3,382.  Sub-head E is in connection with expenses of winding up the affairs of the late Dáil Eireann Courts, and that shows a decrease of £4,500.  Under sub-head A the increase is largely accounted for by reason of the transfer from the Vote of the Gárda Síochána of the expenses of the staff engaged on the keeping of the accounts and payments to that Force.  Formerly the greater part of the accountancy work of the Gárda Síochána was done in the Depôt and the Vote for the Gárda Síochána bore that expense.  Since then we simply improved and tightened the administration, so that the staff has <Col N="2125" /> been transferred to, and is in closer connection with the Ministry, and the expense of the staff is now borne on the Ministry's Vote.  The staff consists of one clerk-in-charge of accounts, at a salary of £550 to £700 per annum; four junior executive officers, from £100 to £400 per annum; six lower clerical officers, at from £60 to £250; eight temporary clerks, from £2 15s. a week to £4, and one typist.  This is a civilian staff, and the Gárda Síochána Vote is accounted for by the Ministry of Justice.  It was considered that the accounting work should be done under the direct supervision of the Ministry, and accordingly the transfer was made.  In fact, administratively, the executive head of the Department of Justice is the Accounting Officer for the Vote of the Gárda Síochána.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is an item of £470 for the administration of the Aliens Restrictions Act which may require some explanation. It is made up as follows:&mdash;There is a sum of £370 for an Immigration Inspector (salary and allowances) and a provision of £100 for the payment of a deputy for the above officer for extra assistance during the Summer months, and for repayments to the Customs and Excise Authorities of any expenses incurred in administering the Aliens Restrictions Act at Moville.  All aliens coming from abroad, that is from outside Saorstát Eireann or Great Britain or Northern Ireland, wishing to land in the Saorstát, must receive permission to do so from an Immigration Officer. On the Immigration Officer rests the full responsibility for seeing that no undesirable alien is permitted to land, and to that effect each alien landing has to be carefully examined.  The routine for the landing and examination of aliens is as follows:&mdash;The Immigration Officer boards the arriving vessel before anyone has left it and is supplied with the passenger manifest.  All passengers desiring to land&mdash;Irish, British, and aliens&mdash;are then examined by him.  He has nothing to do as regards passengers listed as Irish and British, but to see that their nationality is genuine, and that they are not aliens in possession of forged passports. Aliens must be in possession of passports duly vised when necessary. A visa is not required in <Col N="2126" /> the case of many foreign countries. The Immigration Officer is empowered to refuse leave to land to any alien who</P>
    <P>(a) is not in a position to support himself and his dependents.</P>
    <P>(b) if coming to take up employment has not a permit from the Ministry of Industry and Commerce;</P>
    <P>(c) if a lunatic, idiot or mentally deficient;</P>
    <P>(d) has been certified for medical reasons to be unfit to land;</P>
    <P>(e) has been sentenced in a foreign country for any crime within the meaning of the Extradition Acts 1870-1906;</P>
    <P>(f) is the subject of a deportation or an expulsion order in force;</P>
    <P>(g) has been prohibited from landing by the Minister for Home Affairs.</P>
    <P>On the Immigration Officer rests the responsibility of deciding, in doubtful cases, whether a person is of Irish or British nationality, or is an alien.  Exhaustive instructions have been issued on this point for the guidance of Immigration Officers.</P>
    <P>There is an allowance of £50 for inspection under the Cruelty to Animals Act, 1876, which represents the salary of the Vivisection Inspector.</P>
    <P>The figure of £868 for messenger and Protective Force Services represents the proportion of the total cost of these services at Government Buildings, which is attributable to the Ministry of Home Affairs.  There are certain services common to all Departments, and a simple apportionment appears on the Vote of each Ministry. The sum of £300 provided for overtime is to meet the cost of the extra duty performed by the Gárda Síochána Accounts Branch in the first week of each month, during which period the whole Force throughout the country is paid. These periodical payments involve a great pressure of work on that particular staff, and necessitates overtime by them.  It was, therefore, necessary to insert a provision of £300 to that end.</P>
    <P>It has been found necessary to provide a sum of £2,000 for contemplated additional staff.  The constantly increasing scope of the duties of the <Col N="2127" /> Ministry have rendered very difficult the fixing of a definite establishment, and in view of the quantity of legislation recently passed, and still pending, which directly affects the scope of the Ministry's duty, it is considered advisable to make provision to this extent for extra staff.  There are two posts for which provision was made last year, and which do not appear this year, the post of Adviser on Police Organisation and the post of Civil Commissioner at Pettigo.  These disappear from this year's Estimate.</P>
    <P>With regard to the Film Censorship (sub-head AA), I made in March last a rather detailed statement regarding the financial arrangements of the Film Censorship.  Payment is made to the Irish Bonded Film Store, Limited, at the rate of 10s. per thousand feet of film shown, and this represents the only payment made by the Ministry to the firm in question.  It is not anticipated that more than 65,000 feet or 70,000 feet of film will be shown per week, but it is, nevertheless, thought advisable, in view of the lack of practical experience, to make ample provision for the cost of this service.  Accordingly, the sum of £2,652 under the heading, &ldquo;cost of showing films,&rdquo; is set down, and this would include the reshowing of films.  The sum of £300 &ldquo;provision for additional staff,&rdquo; is intended to meet the expenses of any extra clerical assistance the Censor may require, and to pay for the services of a deputy should the Censor himself, for any reason, be unable to act or be absent.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that sum of £2,652 set aside for the benefit of a private trading concern?  Is that the idea of making provision for this large amount?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what the Deputy means by the phrase &ldquo;set aside for a private trading concern.&rdquo; It is set aside as an estimate of liabilities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it intended that it will eventually find its way into the pockets of the Irish Bonded Film Store Company?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  As I stated, it is not anticipated that more than <Col N="2128" /> 65,000 feet or 70,000 feet of film will be shown per week.  As a matter of fact, that figure is there to meet the largest possible average footage which is considered to be in or about 100,000 feet per week.  The anticipation of the Department is that the average footage will prove to be 65,000 or 70,000 feet per week, and consequently that figure of 100,000 feet is unlikely to be reached.  This entails no loss to the public.  It is not in any real sense a charge on the State.  The Censorship of Films Act provides that the fees shall be fixed in such a manner as to meet the expense of censoring, and no more.  If it is found that more than an average of a hundred thousand feet per week is dealt with, it will be possible to reduce the present fees of one-fifth of a penny per foot for ordinary films and one-tenth of a penny for topical films.  The scale of fees under the Act must be arranged to ensure that this particular service is self-supporting. It is not meant to be a charge on the State, or to be a revenue-producing service, but the fees must be fixed to meet the expenses of the censor's staff and any expenses incidental. There is an item of £500 under sub-head B for travelling and subsistence, an allowance which is intended to meet expenses incurred by officers who have to travel.  The Immigration Inspector at Cobh, for instance, has to make weekly journeys to Cork, and has occasionally to come to Dublin for consultations at the Ministry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards sub-head C, incidental expenses £500, the chief charge against that would likely be the issuing of public notices and advertisements of a statutory nature, for instance, notices, such as the notices of the commencement and termination of summer-time. Provision is made for the purchase of newspapers and postage of letters and so forth.  Telegrams and telephones, £520.  Last year the amount was found to be inadequate in practice, and the amount now is based on our experience of last year, and on the increased scope of the work of the Department.  Expenses in regard to the winding-up of the affairs of the late Dáil Eireann Courts are estimated at £1,500.  That is a reduction of £4,500 as compared <Col N="2129" /> with last year.  Considerable progress has been made in clearing off debts in connection with the late Dáil Courts, and but for the fact that members of the staff who are dealing with these claims were also engaged in the work of the Winding-up Commission, the probability is that we would not have to ask for any vote in connection with this particular service this year.  The debts that had been outstanding in connection with the Dáil Courts system may be classified as costs due to solicitors who conducted prosecutions, arrears in the remuneration of registrars and clerks, the cost of escorts for prisoners and their maintenance, minor expenses, such as lighting, stationery, and so on.  There are also sums paid by way of deposit for the hearing of cases which were not, in fact, heard.  We have been making every effort to settle outstanding claims.  That settlement has not been quite completed.  There has been delay owing to the fact that some of the staff were engaged on work in connection with the Winding-up Commission.  I think that covers all I wish to say, but if there is any information which any Deputy requires I shall be glad to give it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Although the Minister's statement is very exhaustive, he did not explain the reason for the very large increase in bonus.  The bonus has increased from £3,760 to over £7,000. In part that is, no doubt, due to the transfer of clerks from the Gárda Síochána, but as eight are temporary clerks who do not get a bonus, it seems to me to be a large increase.  Is the Minister satisfied that the Film Censor gets an adequate salary for the important duties he has to perform?  It must be tiring work, and he only gets £250 without bonus.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy may be glad to know that his salary has been increased recently to £400.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Is he a permanent or a temporary officer?  I know he is a statutory officer.  To give him £400 a year without bonus is to place him in an anomalous position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to raise the question of the partial failure of the <Col N="2130" /> Minister to make proper provision for establishing machinery for the effective checking of weights and measures. Attention has been drawn to this matter here by questions on three or four occasions, and the answer on every occasion was to the effect that so far as the district concerned was affected, an examination was being held for the purpose of appointing members of the Gárda Síochaná to carry out the work.  When members realise that there has been no effective check on weights and measures for the last four or five years, they will realise the importance of this matter, especially as we have to face the fact that profiteering of an unscrupulous kind has been going on.  I am informed by people who have experience in this work that there has been failure on the part of the Government to check weights and measures, and that when weights get rusty there is a reduction of the standard weight.  I have been told in my own town that a person who has standard weights and measures has been supplied with goods whose weight was below that of the quantity demanded. No unnecessary delay should be tolerated by the Minister in his department in bringing into operation machinery which will mean an effective check on the weights and measures which are in operation.  The fact that there has been no check for four or five years makes it rather imperative on the Minister to have steps more than of a normal kind taken to see that this state of affairs is remedied.  The Minister must have noticed, in the newspapers, controversies over this matter.  I drew attention to it before on the Estimates, but so far as I know there appears to have been no great advance made in regard to the machinery which was in operation twelve months ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister might give the Dáil some information as to the advance made on this question.  On the question of the film censorship I will say nothing beyond this, that if I did attempt to say anything on this matter, the Minister might say I was trying to pull his leg now, inasmuch as he said the last time that my leg was being pulled by someone else.  The Minister has provided an Estimate which means <Col N="2131" /> the showing of 100,000 feet of film. That was disputed by the Minister as being an average figure.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Experience points to the figure of 70,000 being the average.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it the Minister in his wisdom&mdash;and the Minister is a wise man&mdash;considers that it is fairly reasonable to assume that that amount of film would be shown in the picture houses.  Does the provision for additional staff mean the staff employed by a private trade film company, or is it the staff to be provided by the Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>By the Censor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>We will leave it to time and to the anticipations of the Minister to prove at the end of the period now being provided for, whether or not his Estimate is a fair and correct one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Minister what is the intention of his Department in connection with assistants to what were formerly known as Clerks of the Crown and Peace.  These people have been treated badly.  They have been Government servants, practically speaking, but have never been recognised either by the British or the Irish Governments.  They are doing very valuable work, but they have no lease of their job.  I would like to know the intention of the Minister in connection with the question of their establishment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to assure Deputy Davin that we appreciate the necessity of getting out inspectors as early as possible to deal with weights and measures, but I would ask him, on his side, to consider that you do not get those men readymade, that you have to select men and put them through a very careful course at the Depot, and put them through an examination at the end of that course, before you can feel satisfied that you have men competent for the work.  It would not be just, either to traders or the public, to send out men if you had any doubt whatever of their competence. One batch of men who had been trained <Col N="2132" /> at the work sat for an examination set by the Civil Service Commission, and, I am glad to say, did remarkably well at the examination.  Those men are at work through the country.  More men are being trained to the work, but it needs training and a testing examination at the conclusion of the training, before you can turn men loose on that particular class of duty.  I will under take to do everything possible to speed up the process, but I cannot say that any speeding up is possible.  I do not think it is.  We realised, before questions were set down at all, the importance of getting men out on that work, and I do not believe anything has been left undone to ensure a speedy supply to meet the demand that was undoubtedly there.  There is no use in fighting old battles over again about the film censorship.  I have nothing to add to what I said in March, April, May, and June of the present year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>On what page and what column?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder would Deputy O'Connell care to raise on this Vote the matter of which he spoke this evening?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter I brought to the notice of the Minister this evening was what had been conveyed to me to-day with regard to some eighteen or twenty prisoners arrested and detained on the 9th instant.  As has been represented to me, they have been detained without trial or charge since that date.  I gave the Minister all the information I had with regard to the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>My information on the matter is rather detailed.  The history of the case in connection with those eighteen men who were arrested is as follows:&mdash;In May, 1922, cattle were driven from the lands of Messrs. Arthur and Robert Gentleman at Mount Cole, County Kerry, and since that date persistent interference has gone on.  In December, 1923, a seizure order was made under the Public Safety (Emergency Powers) Act, and seventeen trespassing cattle were seized and sold.  Despite that, cattle were again put on the land, and, on the 18th <Col N="2133" /> March, 1924, a house situated, on the lands which was in the course of repair to accommodate workmen, was maliciously damaged to prevent occupation. On the 11th of May, 1924, shots were fired at the owners by masked men, and they narrowly escaped injury.  At that stage the Gárda Síochána and responsible officials decided that if the individuals, who were well known to be connected with this series of outrages, were allowed to continue at large, there might very easily be fatal consequences, and instructions were issued to the Gárda Síochána to effect the arrest of the men concerned.  On the 14th instant orders were issued directing their continued detention under the Public Safety (Powers of Arrest and Detention) Act, 1924.  The persons now in prison are well known locally as being concerned with the outrage from the beginning, that is, since May of 1922, and it seems undesirable to release them at the moment.  Their arrest, therefore, and their detention were carried out under the Public Safety Act and are legal.  With regard to certain additional complaints which have been made as to their conditions of custody for the first week, I have not detailed information of that, but I am prepared to look further into it.  The main fact is that these men were properly arrested and have been in legal custody from the day of their arrest. They are suspected very strongly of being the chief perpetrators in a series of outrages which date back almost three years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I to understand that it is not proposed to make a formal charge against those men?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a question that will be looked into.  It is doubtful whether evidence to support a formal charge will be forthcoming.  It is that kind of a case to which I have referred again and again in the Dáil, where you find something that falls very short of knowledge, and yet you have not a case which might be substantiated by evidence in the court.  You have a situation where a district is so terrorised that whilst almost every man, woman and child in the area knows who is responsible <Col N="2134" /> for particular outrages, you would not get evidence that would ensure a conviction.  Deputy Corish asked about the position of Clerks of the Crown and Peace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>Their assistants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister may also take advantage of the opportunity of stating what is to be the future position of Clerks of the Crown and Peace or their successors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>That scarcely arises on this Vote at all.  The Deputy is rather premature.  That is a matter that will be very carefully considered when Part II. of the Courts of Justice Act comes into operation.  I do not think that it is properly raised on this Vote at all.  I could only say at the moment that the question of the Courts Staffs is receiving very close attention from the Ministry&mdash;as close attention as the many other calls upon the Ministry's staff permits, and that we see ahead a time when it must receive very detailed examination under the Courts of Justice Act, when the new courts and the new Circuit Courts come into operation.  The proposal simply is that we are to have one chief establishment officer answering to the Ministry for all matters connected with the courts' staffs from top to bottom&mdash;the staffs of the Supreme Court, the High Court, and the Circuit Courts.  But I am not in a position to give detailed information, because we ourselves have not come to definite decisions in connection with that matter.</P>
      <P>Vote put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sitting suspended at 6.35 p.m., and resumed at 7.30 p.m., An Ceann Comhairle in the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE" RHead="35 (DISTRICT JUSTICES)">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE 35 (DISTRICT JUSTICES).</Title>
    <P>Motion made:</P>
    <P>That a sum, not exceeding £27,675, be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1925, for the salaries and expenses of District Justices.</P>
    <P>Vote agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE" RHead="38.&mdash;(PUBLIC RECORD OFFICE)">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE 38.&mdash;(PUBLIC RECORD OFFICE).</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2135" /> Motion made:</P>
    <P>That a sum not exceeding £4,676, be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the Charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1925, for the salaries and expenses of the Public Record Office and of the Keeper of State Papers, Dublin.  (30 and 31 Vict., c. 70: 38 and 39 Vict., c. 59, and 39 and 40 Vict., c. 58).</P>
    <P>Vote agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE" RHead="47.&mdash;(IRISH LAND COMMISSION)">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE 47.&mdash;(IRISH LAND COMMISSION).</Title>
    <P>Motion made:</P>
    <P>That a sum not exceeding £396,604 be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the Charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1925, to pay the Salaries and Expenses of the Office of the Irish Land Commission (44 and 45 Vict., c. 49, s. 45, and c. 71, s. 4; 48 and 49 Vict., c. 73, s.s. 17 and 18 and 20; 53 and 54 Vict., c. 49, s. 2; 54 and 55 Vict., c. 48; 3 Edw. 7, c. 37; 7 Edw. 7, c. 38 and c. 56, 9 Edw. 7, c. 42; the Land Law (Commission) Act, 1923, and the Land Act, 1923.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan) MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputies will notice that there is an increase of £160,085 this year as against last year's estimate, but they must remember that the figures shown here for 1924-25 are the figures for the Land Commission plus the Congested Districts Board. The Congested Districts Board is, of course, absorbed in the Land Commission, and both are called the Land Commission now; and this estimate covers what used to be called the Congested Districts Board Services.  The figures for 1923-24 are really the figures for the Land Commission for that period, and the figures for the Congested Districts Board for eight months of the year.  The Land Law Commission Act which transferred the Congested Districts Board to the Land Commission was passed in July, and for the months April, May, June and July&mdash;four <Col N="2136" /> months&mdash;the Congested Districts Board was financed from its own funds, so that when you are comparing the estimates for those two years you must remember that you are comparing the Land Commission for a year and the Congested Districts Board for a year, as against the Land Commission for a year and the Congested Districts Board for eight months.  That explains the increase to some extent.</P>
      <P>It will be noticed that there is an increase of £57,490 under Sub-head A&mdash; Salaries, Wages and Allowances.  Part of that increase, of course, is due to the fact that for the four months I have mentioned the Congested Districts Board staff were not on the estimates; and part of it is due to an item on page 166, £21,890 for extra inspection and survey staff.  For the last month there have been employed 11 additional inspectors and 10 surveyors&mdash;it may be the other way about.  Their salaries and travelling expenses, etc., will, I think, absorb half that amount&mdash;about £11,000 and the £21,890 is to cover a possible necessity for employing more inspectors and surveyors in the course of the year in the event of the work increasing to such an extent as to justify their employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are also two items on the Estimates this year that have not appeared before either on the Land Commission Estimates or on the Congested Districts Board Estimates.  One is Sub-head G, and the other Sub-head H. Sub-head G reads: &ldquo;Contributions towards charge for excess stock, £160,000.&rdquo;  I take it that most of the Deputies know what that charge is.  It is a charge which we have, so to speak, inherited. It is a relic of the time when there used to be cash sales.  An estate was bought for £10,000 cash.  It was necessary to issue £11,000 worth of stock to find £10,000 cash; and the tenant purchasers were asked to pay interest on sinking fund of the £10,000, so that there was £1,000 over of stock, the interest on sinking fund of which the State had to find&mdash;interest on sinking fund of what was called excess stock and bonus stock under the 1903 Act.  On that we are paying £160,000 this year.  In former years that used to be on the Development Fund Vote.  It now appears <Col N="2137" /> on the Land Commission Vote for the first time in its entirety.  Last year £106,667 in respect of that appeared in the Land Commission Vote.  Deputies will remember that there was a Supplementary Vote for the Land Commission and the Congested Districts Board.</P>
    <P>Under Sub-head H there is an Estimate of £25,000 &ldquo;Payment under Section 11 (7) of the Land Act, 1923.&rdquo;  It is not very likely that very much of that will be required this year, but in the event of considerable sales being effected during the year, possibly £25,000 will be required as a contribution to price.  These are the only comments I wish to make on the Estimates. I ask Deputies to remember, when they are comparing the Estimates for 1923-24 with the Estimates for 1924-25, that they are comparing, so far as the Congested Districts Board is concerned, an Estimate for eight months as regards the first-mentioned period, with an Estimate of one year in the other period.  It may save a certain amount of time if I explain what the Land Commission has done since the beginning of the last financial year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought you were to deal with Sub-head I.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not intend to deal with Sub-head I.  It speaks for itself. There is an increase of £40,793, as shown by the Estimate.  In addition, there is a sum of £40,000 from the Unemployment Fund being spent on the Improvement of Estates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To come to the work of the Land Commission for the last year, when the Land Commission and the Congested Districts Board were amalgamated there were £4,000,000 worth of pending sales in the Land Commission, and £5,000,000 worth of pending sales in the Congested Districts Board.  The £5,000,000 worth of pending sales in the Congested Districts Board had been accumulating for years.  One of the complaints against the Congested Districts Board was that they were accumulating estates and not dividing them.  That was not their fault.  They had not sufficient powers under the Act to acquire lands compulsorily to meet the peculiar and difficult needs of the congested districts.  They bought <Col N="2138" /> lands and they kept them on hands with a view to acquiring more land, so as to have sufficient land to deal with the problems in that area.  However, we have far more drastic powers under the Act of 1923.  There is no occasion for the Land Commission to keep lands on hands.  As I have said, there were £5,000,000 worth of pending sales under the Congested Districts Board, and there were £4,000,000 in the Land Commission.</P>
    <P>The Land Commission and the Congested Districts Board amalgamated, and now there are £2,000,000 worth of sales, that is to say half the Land Commission sales are being dealt with still, and in addition out of 21,000 acres of untenanted arable land which the Congested Districts Board had in their possession when the amalgamation took place, 11,000 acres has been divided, and the balance will be divided before the end of this year, so that all that untenanted arable land will be divided before next Spring and in time for next year's sowings.  That 21,000 acres represents the total area of arable land which the Board had at the time when the two services, the Land Commission and the Congested Districts Board, were amalgamated, that is to say last September.  Within the year the Land Commission have divided half of it, and before the end of the year will have divided the balance.  I may say that the average rate of division of land during the year 1922 was £2,000,000, so that in respect of the old sales sales of lands purchased under previous Acts, the Land Commission in the last year have dealt with £2,000,000 worth of the land which they had before the amalgamation, and at least half the arable land which the Congested Districts Board had in their possession at the time of the amalgamation.  That is in addition to dealing with extraordinary arrears, and dealing with all the huge preliminary work that had to be done in connection with the Land Act of 1923.</P>
    <P>With regard to the arrears of annuities problem, this is a sore subject, and I wish to put before the Deputies the position in regard to arrears of Land Commission annuities.  In 1922-23 about £1,000,000 worth of arrears of <Col N="2139" /> annuities began to become due.  The total collection of annuities amounted to £2,900,000.  The gale days are June and December, and in January, 1923, there would be about £800,000 worth of arrears, and that would be reduced down to £400,000 by the following May, that is, a month before the next gale.  What did that show?  It showed that the annuitants were trying to establish something in the nature of a hanging gale, by paying the December gale of annuity about a month before the next annuity was due.  The same thing happened in regard to the June gale of annuity; arrears again showed up to £1,000,000, and began to fall gradually to £300,000 or £400,000, say, in November or October.  Everybody knows that unless Land Commission annuities are paid, the money must be found from the Guarantee Fund. Everybody knows that the Land Commission annuities are the interest on the Sinking Fund of stock that was issued for the purchase of the lands.  The draw on the Guarantee Fund takes place in the month of February in respect of the December gale.  Any arrears in December carry on to the beginning of August, and any arrears in respect of June carry on to December, so that what was happening was this, in those months, February and August of each year, there was a draw of £500,000 or £600,000 on the Guarantee Fund, and a draw on the Agricultural Grant.  The Agricultural Grant is the first item that has to bear the loss.  What was the result?  The result was that the rates on agricultural land were considerably higher than they should be, and that the men who were paying the arrears of annuities were paying an increased agricultural rate. You had people complaining about the increased rates and the size of the rates all over the country.  It was inevitable that the rates should be much bigger if this tendency to increase the arrears was allowed to grow.  We were faced with the problem either of collecting Land Commission annuities punctually or allowing the rate on agricultural land to be inflated to a far greater degree than it should be.  There was no question of what we should do in the matter.  There is not a farmers' organisation <Col N="2140" /> in the country that does not admit that the Land Commission annuities must be paid.</P>
    <P>I will go further.  There is not a responsible farmer in the country who does not admit that Land Commission annuities should be paid.  But while these admissions are made, while no one makes a case that they should not be paid, nevertheless there was the problem that one-third of the annuities were going into arrears, and so far as about 40 per cent. of the annuitants were concerned, the receivable orders might as well not have been issued. In at least 40 per cent. of these cases they waited until they got the six days' notice to pay, and in some counties in at least 80 per cent. of cases the annuitants waited, wherever they paid at all, until they got the six days' notice to pay.  So that these six-day notices which were used in normal times to remind three, or four, or five per cent. of annuitants who were in arrears that they had not paid their annuities were becoming in fact another receivable order, and it was practically evident that the expense&mdash; practically evident that the money&mdash; orders was money thrown away; that the six-day notices were taking the place for 50 per cent. of the annuitants of the receivable orders.  In that state of affairs, and in view of the necessity of collecting these arrears of annuities promptly, which everybody admits should be paid, the Land Commission ceased issuing the notices, and in the month of January of this year they published in all the daily and provincial papers notices to the effect that they would not in future issue these notices, that the annuitants who were in arrear would be processed without the usual six-day notices.  It is alleged that annuitants in some cases have been processed after they had paid their annuities. I have never got a single case authenticated where this has occurred, and I am anxious to get these cases. Deputy White raised it by asking a question some time ago.  He asked was it a fact that a couple of hundred processes were issued in Donegal, and was it a fact that some of these processes were served on annuitants who had already paid.  What are the facts? The facts are that a couple of hundred <Col N="2141" /> processes were issued in Donegal against people who were a year in arrear, and for whom the ratepayers of the County Donegal were paying. Only in five cases were processes served on tenants who had already paid their annuities, and in these five cases the annuities came in after the processes had been handed to the process-servers, and before service.</P>
    <P>I know exactly how that sort of thing happens.  The solicitor writes for the payment to the tenant-purchaser. He asks him to pay his annuity. He probably gets no reply. This annuity is a year in arrear.  The tenant knows that it is due in the month of June or the month of December, as the case may be.  He does not pay it.  He does not pay the solicitor. He waits for two or three months, when the processes are issued and are in the hands of the process server.  It is not absolutely unknown that the fact that the processes are in the hands of the process-server gets out, and he hops in and pays his annuity.  As I say, in five instances in this particular case, which I have investigated carefully, out of the few hundred, where the annuities have been paid they were paid after the processes were handed to the process-server, and before he had succeeded in serving them.  I would not make the slightest excuse if that were the case in the whole two hundred and not in the five instances, because I know how these things happen.</P>
    <P>With regard to the work of the Land Commission in connection with the new Act there are about a hundred thousand tenants unpurchased, and for the purpose of collecting both the compounded arrears of rent and the payments in lieu of rent it was necessary to get the correct particulars of each of these and of their rents.  For the purpose of vesting their holdings in the Land Commission it was necessary to get not only the name and address and the correct rent of each of these tenants, but also particulars as regards their holdings, the area, a map of each holding, whether the holding was judicial or non-judicial, and whether the rent was first, second or third term. That was all required for the purpose of fixing a price.  That is to say, if you <Col N="2142" /> joined the two necessities, namely, the necessity for getting particulars for the collection of payment in lieu of rent, and the fixing of the price of each holding, it was necessary to get in respect of each tenant unpurchased his name and address, his exact rent to a penny, the map of his holding, his area, and whether his holding was judicial or non-judicial, first, second or third term. That is to say the Land Commission had to establish what was a land agent's office for every tenant left unpurchased, and had to get particulars not approximately correct, but particulars with regard to each tenant's holding absolutely accurately.</P>
    <P>Otherwise any sale based on that figure could be afterwards upset by the Courts.  They proceeded to do that by writing to each landlord asking him to return the rents of his tenants with these particulars.  That was obviously the right course.  There is about one landlord for every 20 tenants, and there would be about 4,500 landlords against 100,000 tenants.  The landlords within a certain time returned these particulars, and in 40 per cent. of cases these particulars were found to be incorrect. They were materially incorrect in regard to the rents because as a rule the tenants did not get credit for abatements.  You all know what abatements are.  Abatements may not appear on the face of the receipt; they may appear on the fly-leaf or something like that; but you all know that in a great many cases the rent receipt does not show the exact rent.  In any event, in 40 per cent. of cases the particulars were not accurate.  That meant that the Land Commission had to interview every tenant or every landlord, or had to settle the question by correspondence.  Possibly Deputies have some idea of the difficulty of settling a question of that sort.  These questions had to be settled, and in over 2,000 cases they had to go before the Land Judge.  For the last ten months Judge Wylie has tried about 2,000 cases which will rule, I suppose, a large number of others.  That work has all been completed within about eight months, and in my opinion it was a very considerable feat for the Land Commission in all the circumstances, in view of the <Col N="2143" /> difficulty of dealing with people on a question like this by correspondence, and getting all these particulars accurately within a period of eight months.  And remember all these particulars are necessary for the automatic working of the Land Act.</P>
    <P>Deputies should also remember that the Land Act in a great many of its more important provisions works automatically once the basis is laid down, and this preliminary work is of primary importance in view of the fact that it is the basis on which any question in the course of the administration of the Act might be brought before the Judicial Commissioner. Any sale might be interfered with if the preliminary particulars were not accurately ascertained.  All these preliminary particulars have been ascertained within the last eight months, and practically the first year's compounded arrears of rent have been collected with very little difficulty in the circumstances.  The payment in lieu of rent is being collected, and between payment in lieu of rent, compounded arrears of rent, and between the annuity and interest in lieu of rent the Land Commission has collected £5,000,000 per annum.  In addition to that the Land Commission have now inspected about 350,000 acres of untenanted land. After inspection and before the land can be acquired compulsorily a three months period must intervene.  When the Land Commission decide that they intend to acquire a certain area of land they gazette it in the Official Gazette, and a period of three months intervenes between the date when this notice is inserted and the date when the lands are actually acquired.  The same applies with regard to vesting a tenant's holding.  Before any tenant's holding can be vested it must be three months gazetted, for the reason that a great many people may have a right to object to the vesting.  It is quite possible that a tenant would not have a legal claim to the land, and there are other reasons of that sort.</P>
    <P>To make a long story short, within the last year the Land Commission dealt with almost as much land, purchased under the 1903 Act and the 1909 Act, as the Land Commission in previous years when they had nothing else <Col N="2144" /> to administer but these Acts.  That is to say, they dealt with £2,000,000 worth of pending sales as against an average of £2,500,000.  In addition they have divided half the arable land which accumulated under the Congested Districts Board, which came over with the Congested Districts Board and which represented years of arrears and will have completed the division by the end of this year.  In addition, they have reduced the abnormal arrears problem which developed during 1922 and 1923 to practically normal proportions.  They have done practically all the preliminaries, the important difficult preliminary work in connection with the Land Act of 1923, and they have inspected at least 350,000 acres of untenanted land. They have done that with practically no additional staff.  They have some additional officials on the outdoor staff, but it is only within the last two months that an additional outdoor staff has been employed and a further additional staff will be employed as they are required.  It is often suggested that the land should be divided here and there without any general plan on the part of the Land Commission, and I just wish Deputies to get an idea of what that would mean.  These figures will have to be taken as approximate. There are about 5,000,000 acres, available for the Land Commission under the new Act.  That is a very generous figure, and that is taking as much land as they possibly could, in my opinion, take.  There are 100,000 tenants.  Most of these tenants are in the congested districts.  Most of them live on very small, miserable holdings.  They are the problem that was not solved in the past.  They are the problem that was never faced in the past owing to the difficulties of solving the problem.  Taking a line from the 1903 Act, it takes about 3,000,000 acres to deal with 100,000 tenants.  I cannot give accurate figures, but this figure is a deduction.  Taking a line from previous Acts, it took on an average about 3,000,000 acres to deal with 100,000 tenants.</P>
    <P>It will take at least 3,000,000 acres to deal with the 100,000 tenants we have. Most of them live in Connaught, on the western seaboard, in Cavan, in all the counties where the congests are and <Col N="2145" /> most of them have small miserable holdings, smaller holdings than were dealt with under the 1903 Act, and, in my opinion, the amount of land you require will be nearer 4,000,000 acres. We have to make up our minds whether we will deal with the congests now regardless of the difficulties or the attraction of leaving them there and dealing with other classes, or whether we will set out to solve the biggest problem left in the country&mdash;the terrible poverty that you find in places like Mayo, Sligo and Donegal.  I have no doubt myself that whatever the difficulties are that the Land Act of 1923 will have failed unless we deal with the problem that these counties present, and that any other policy in the way of giving land to the landless, no matter how attractive, at the expense of these congests, is unsound.  If we carry on that policy to a successful conclusion it will mean that we will have to be under the necessity of migrating a very large number of small tenants from Connemara, Mayo, Donegal, Kerry and other counties which I need not mention and which are not included in what is rather technically known as the &ldquo;congested areas.&rdquo;  In addition, we will have to migrate&mdash;and this will be the more difficult problem&mdash;fairly large tenants with 100, 120, and up to 150 acres in order to make room for the congests in the holdings which they leave after them.  There is no question about it, the larger tenant is the more suitable migrant.  He is better educated, he knows his way about better, he knows conditions better and, as a rule, he will prefer to go because the large tenant with 120 to 140 acres surrounded by twenty or forty miserable congests has not got all the security of tenure he would desire, and it will be an advantage to him and to the congests to migrate him.  The real danger will be in his reception in the other districts by the tenants, say, in the counties of Kilkenny, Tipperary, Meath or Dublin.</P>
    <P>This problem cannot be solved unless every party co-operates.  They must co-operate and resist the temptation of making cheap capital out of migration and out of getting land divided round their own districts.  We have to face the thing now.  We are at the parting <Col N="2146" /> of the ways.  The preliminary work is being done, and we must make up our minds as to what our policy is going to be.  I know the country well enough to know that it will be extremely difficult to carry out.  There is no question as to the right policy, and that it cannot be done until Deputies remember that each in his own area must get up and say even the unpopular thing when they know it is the right thing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what we always did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps we would be on the other side of the House if we did not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the annuities the Minister finds great fault with the tenants for not meeting annuities up to date, and not coming in with the receivable orders and tendering them with an accompanying cheque. We heard the same thing the last time we were on this Vote.  I would ask the Minister this: Is it not a fact that while the English were here in connection with the operation of this Act, that fourteen days' notice was always sent out?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>And after that, the solicitor's notice was sent out?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>The notice stated that the annuity was to be paid on or before but not later than a certain day.  That has been done away with.  The average farmer of the country is not an accountant. He has not a clerical mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The result is that he forgets all about it and the next thing he has is something he does not want.  The withdrawal of that notice to my mind has been the cause of considerable trouble.  I know the sending out of these notices would mean expense but considering that it is a Government matter they could be sent out with no great expense, except the expense of printing the notice.  Their not being sent out at present is the cause of considerable trouble.  If the people got <Col N="2147" /> those notices there would be no excuse for them.  As it is they get no notice and consequently trouble has arisen.</P>
    <P>With regard to the operations of the 1923 Act, as the Minister has said, considerable difficulty has arisen.  I do not think I am exaggerating when I put it this way that the landlords have not given a proper or honest return in 40 or 50 per cent. of the cases.  Where-ever they have given an abatement for the past ten, twenty, or thirty years, they have when asked for a return ignored all mention of this abatement, and they return the full amount of the old rent.  The provisions of the Act required that they should give a true return, otherwise they are subject to a penalty.  All the cause of friction in the country at the moment has been caused by this question of their not giving a proper return.  Case after case I have had to deal with and a number of them I had to bring to the notice of the Minister.  I have had to deal with any amount of such cases where the landlord deliberately did not give a proper return.  I should say that they sent the old rent in the hope that the tenant was fool enough not to notice what happened.  In some cases the demand for arrears of rents was more than the tenant would have actually to pay if the Act had not been passed.  In one case the nett arrears to which the tenant was entitled under this demand was only 25 per cent., whereas he was actually entitled to 30 and 35 per cent.  In the demand made on him he was actually called on to pay more than he had been paying for the past thirty or thirty-five years.  I believe that the landlords were deliberately doing the wrong thing and they are the cause of all the confusion we have had over these questions.  I do not think the Minister has told us, or if he has, I do not remember his saying so, whether they have got in all those arrears of rents.  He said he had got practically all now.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>One year's rent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>What percentage of it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>£700,000 out of £800,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>That is very satisfactory.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2148" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>took the chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it was fair of the Minister to steal all my thunder.  I cannot close my eyes to the fact that I am up against a subtle and able solicitor, as well as a Minister for Lands and Agriculture.  However, there are two or three matters that I wish to draw the attention of the Minister to.  One is the flooding of lands on both sides of rivers, and the consequential blocking and obstructions of main drains flowing into those rivers.  None of these lands is situated in Drainage Board areas.  Unfortunately they are subject to these periodic floodings, and sometimes these floodings render them practically derelict. But the people have to pay the Land Commission annuities notwithstanding. In some instances the flooding was brought to the notice of the Land Commission.  The reply was in the most courteous terms possible, and to the effect that they had no money or that no money was available for this purpose.  I hold that property has its duties as well as its rights, and when land has become derelict and unproductive through flooding, the Land Commission is not entitled to annuities that the land is not able to produce.  There is an estate down in my area known as the Young Estate, in the Innishowen Rural District.  It was sold in 1906 under the 1903 Act, and the tenants are still paying interest in lieu of rent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to this question of taking proceedings and issuing processes for Land Commission annuities, payment in lieu of rent and compounded arrears, I would say that it has been, of course, open to a good deal of criticism. I do not get up here in the Dáil for the purpose of encouraging tenants not to pay their annuities.  My object is to save them law costs, if it is at all possible.  But I think myself that the Land Commission officials should treat these people with a little more sympathy and consideration than they are doing.  I know of cases where processes were issued for rent that had been forwarded three weeks or a month previous to the issue of the processes. I know of a case where there were two sets of processes issued for one amount and communications were sent to the <Col N="2149" /> State Solicitor and he did not answer them.</P>
    <P>The procedure seems to be that a list is sent from the Land Commission offices to the State Solicitor, and that from the time he receives that list, or from the time that list is sent out from the Land Commission to the State Solicitor, payments are remitted to the Land Commission and the money is sent on by bank drafts and post office orders. Those bank drafts and post office orders are received at the Land Commission office in Dublin.  No communication seems to pass between the Land Commission and the State Solicitors advising the receipt of these monies, and the result is that many of these people are let in for costs for the recovery of annuities for which payments have already been made.  The whole thing is that once this list of defaulters from the Land Commission gets into the grip of the State Solicitor, he must have costs whether payments are made or not.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is to pay them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>The tenant has no right to pay law costs for proceedings taken against him for payments already made.  I do not suppose for a moment that the Minister would advocate that. The Land Commission's methods of collecting annuities notwithstanding that they have a huge staff, does not appear to be as highly organised as would be expected from a great State Department.  The Land Commission should be more reasonable in their methods.  The past year has been one of the worst years we have had in this country since 1879.  Under the present bad conditions which prevail, farmers have to pay high rates, annuities, payments in lieu of rent, and compounded arrears, and they have to pay this in November and also in May.  That is a pretty big order inside one year for poor men who had practically no potatoes or oats last year.  I would assert that some more consideration should be given to the condition of those unfortunate people before processes are sent out against them for the recovery of annuities.  With regard to these matters of processes, I will read you this from the &ldquo;Derry Journal.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is outside the area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2150" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not read the &ldquo;Derry Journal&rdquo; to us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, this is a report of the Lifford Quarter Sessions, and the paper is dated 30/4/'24.  Here is the extract:</P>
      <P>Michael Bonner, Cooly, was the defendant in a Civil Bill at the suit of the Land Commission for a half-year's instalment of an annuity.  Mr. John A. Hamilton, who appeared for the defendant, said the money had been actually paid five days before the process had been issued, and it would have been paid sooner had the defendant been able to obtain a receivable order in his own name from the Land Commission.  It was ridiculous for the Land Commission to issue a process for money which had been paid, and it showed very unbusiness-like methods.  They surely did not expect to get a decree for money which had been paid.  Mr. McMenamin, for the Land Commission, said it was probable he had received instructions in the case before the money was received.  The Land Commission then would not accept payment until the matter of costs was settled.  Mr. Hamilton: If they did not accept payment, why did not they send us back our money?  His Honor nilled the process.</P>
      <P>Then take the case of John and Samuel Boggs, of Bree, Ballygorman. There are two sets of processes issued for one amount.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>He must have been a pretty bad case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope I am not detaining the Dáil.  I think this is a good entertainment.  Take the case of John McLaughlin, of Carbodoey, Strathobridge, Carndonagh.  Processes were issued on the 15th May.  The money was sent from Carndonagh on the 5th May, 1924, that is ten days previously.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>To whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>John Andrew MacLaughlin sent the money to the Land Commission.  And ten days after the money was remitted by Post Office Order he is processed.  We do not want to go into Euclid to prove that ten and <Col N="2151" /> five are fifteen.  Now, here is a case that was handed to me the other evening, and it had reference to a man named James Connor, of Cashel, who sent a Post Office Order for £2 2s. 3d. from Carndonagh on the 14th May, 1924.  He got the following acknowledgment on the 4th July:&mdash;&ldquo;I beg to acknowledge receipt of your remittance for £2 2s. 3d. on account of the debt due in respect of above case.  As Mr. W.T. McMenamin, State Solicitor, Ballybofey, has already been instructed to take proceedings for the recovery of this amount prior to its receipt by the Land Commission, you must now settle with him for his costs. The amount of your remittance has been credited to your account without prejudice to the recovery of costs.&mdash; John T. Drennan, Secretary.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Does not that look like manufacturing costs?  I have several other cases here if you are desirous that I should proceed with them, but I believe myself that I have to a certain extent met the challenge that the Minister threw out.  As I have already stated, I do not want, nor, I am sure, does any other Deputy, or reputable man in the country want, to start an agitation to prevent men from paying their annuities, but I should mention that these are only a few of the several cases that have happened down in my area, and I believe the same thing is happening in other areas.  Other Deputies can speak for those.  I do not want to encourage people who are not paying their rent, as I am as anxious that they should pay their annuities and interest in lieu of rent as anybody else, because I am a large ratepayer myself, and in the event of their falling into arrears I know what happens.  But I would appeal to the Minister and to the officials of the Land Commission that they should be more considerate to the unfortunate people, especially in view of the circumstances of this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>If the statement that was made here by the Minister this evening in regard to the necessity for collection of arrears of annuities could be made by the Minister, assisted by Deputy Gorey, to a general meeting of the farmers of the Free State area, I am sure every Deputy would agree that <Col N="2152" /> it would save many of us a good many communications and also receiving a good many deputations.  They would not be necessary if farmers fully realised the import of the statement made by the Minister.  The Minister has, in his detailed statement, given figures and facts which I presume will mean that Deputies will not have to ask the questions which have really been answered in his statement.  With regard to Deputy White's complaint, which he has fairly well justified, it may be due to the fact that there is a border-line between Donegal and the Land Commission and that the delay involved is due to the fact that there is a hold-up somewhere or other between the point of forwarding and the point of receiving those communications. When that border-line disappears, through the activities of Deputy White and his colleagues in the North, the delay may not seem so great as he complains of to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What I really rose to complain of to-night is a matter which I have already brought to the notice of the Minister and which I am even yet receiving a great number of communications about. Landlords are at present advertising for sale, either by private treaty or by public auction, lands that are likely to be acquired by the Land Commission under the Land Act of 1923.  I do not say that there is any great cause for complaint in a case where land is being changed from one owner to another. But the trouble arises in many cases that have come under my notice, where Landowners have split up their land and have advertised it for sale and sold it in many cases by private treaty, the divisions into which it was split constituting small and uneconomic holdings. I say that should not be allowed to go on by the Land Commission if there is any method by which the Commission can prevent such a thing taking place.  The Minister has referred to this matter before and answered questions in connection with it where questions have been asked. The Minister, in his statement, told us that inspections have taken place in regard to 350,000 out of a possible 5,000,000 acres likely to be acquired by the Land Commission.  If landowners are to be allowed between now and the <Col N="2153" /> time the 5,000,000 acres are likely to be acquired, to split up their land in small uneconomic lots and sell it by private treaty or public auction, when such land is likely to be acquired, it will not alone create confusion and misunderstanding in the localities affected but it will cause considerable confusion to the Land Commission when at a later stage they come along to acquire these lands.  In the cases that have come under my notice I know that this has caused a good deal of irritation locally and there is a feeling amongst the local uneconomic holders, which is justified to a great extent, that this land should be inspected, valued and an effort made to acquire it now before the auction takes place or the lands are handed over to some other person.  I have brought this matter to the notice of the Minister for Agriculture and may I say that at all times and in all matters concerning questions of land, he is approachable and gives fair consideration to any claim put up.  The only ground of dissatisfaction, I think, is that in cases where lands have been advertised by public auction or private treaty and split into small lots adequate steps have not been taken to counteract the activities of the landowners.  In my opinion in these cases the landowners are trying to forestall the activities of the Land Commission.  At present this matter presents a problem and creates confusion in the districts concerned.  It will present a very serious problem at a later stage if the Land Commission come to acquire these lands.</P>
    <P>If land is advertised for sale, especially land that has been split up into small uneconomic holdings&mdash;and this particularly applies in the constituency of Leix and Offaly, although I understand other constituencies are affected &mdash;I see no difficulty in the way of the Land Commission sending down Inspectors to value the land and make an offer to the owner.  I realise that, if the landowner wishes to put an obstacle in the way of the Land Commission acquiring land compulsorily, it may take time to acquire it.  Personally, if the Land Commission is not prepared to take some effective steps to deal with this particular situation, which is a serious and critical one in <Col N="2154" /> one of the counties in my constituency, I am prepared to take all the constitutional means at my disposal to prevent any other people from securing these lands.  I would only do that as a last resort.  But I would take steps, of a constitutional nature at any rate, to see that it would not be profitable for any people to come in and buy lands that I hope in the near future will be acquired by the Land Commission under the Land Act.  I hope the Minister will make the position quite clear with regard to the attitude of his Department on that matter, particularly concerning landowners who split up large estates into uneconomic holdings which they know in time will be acquired by the Land Commission.</P>
    <P>There is another question that I want to get some information upon.  I am not quite sure if I understood the Minister rightly.  That is why I press for a definite understanding.  Is it the intention of the Ministry, in respect to this 5,000,000 acres which is to be acquired, to inspect and value all acquired lands before they proceed to divide the lands amongst the people in any area.  That is a point that should be made quite clear.  So far as Deputies representing rural areas are concerned, great difficulty is experienced by them when they receive a large number of communications in regard to the attitude of the Commission on this and other questions which they are unable to answer.  If the Minister would make the position a little more clear in regard to that and other matters, it would relieve Deputies who are not in a position to reply right away to questions which they are asked without transferring these communications to the Land Commission.</P>
    <P>With regard to what seems to be new appointments of inspectors, I would like to ask the Minister from what class these land inspectors have been recruited; what, if any, are the qualifications necessary for the appointments, and if any of these inspectors are sent to inspect or value land in the districts from which they come?  I think it would be very undesirable that an inspector, say, from Leix should be sent down there to do this work.  I would rather see a man from Donegal, Galway <Col N="2155" /> or somewhere else sent to the district. In that way one would expect that an inspector would be more impartial than he would be if sent to the district from which he came originally.  At any rate, I would like to have some information as to the method of recruiting these fifty-two land inspectors who have been appointed this year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Only twelve inspectors and eleven surveyors have been appointed. It may be the other way about&mdash;eleven inspectors and twelve surveyors&mdash;but, at any rate, only twenty-two have been appointed between inspectors and surveyors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going by the estimates, page 166, which says thirty-four inspectors, five assistant inspectors, and thirteen re-sale valuers&mdash;that is fiftytwo. There were no such appointments last year.  That is why I say there were fifty-two appointed this year.  I merely want information as to the qualifications of the individuals and the intention of the Ministry as to the districts to which the inspectors will be sent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another matter which has come under my notice.  Inspectors have gone down to districts, and, for some reason unknown to me, and perhaps without the authority or without instructions from the Ministry, have called a meeting of the uneconomic holders and landless men within a three-mile radius.  I think it is undesirable for inspectors or anyone appointed by the Commission to do that.  There seems to be a foolish idea in the minds of people when an inspector arrives in a district to inspect land, that that land has already been acquired by the Commission.  I think that inspectors should make inquiries of that kind in a more judicious manner than they have done in some parts of the constituency I represent.  It creates a great deal of irritation locally if three or four people are left out while one hundred are sent for.  There is no necessity for inspectors to call a meeting of the inhabitants of a particular parish in order to explain to them why he has arrived in the district, or his reasons for picking out this, that or the other man who may be entitled to land.  In one particular area this has led to a revolution <Col N="2156" /> on a small scale.  I am sure that is not the intention of the Minister.  But some general direction might be given to inspectors in regard to matters of that kind.  I hope the Minister will declare quite definitely and frankly the policy of his Department with regard to landowners who are selling their lands, either by auction or private treaty, with the intention, as far as I can see, of evading the terms of the Land Act.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the policy to be pursued in dealing with the division of land, as foreshadowed by the Minister, I feel sure that every Deputy will be glad to see the great problem of the congested areas in the west and north-west of Ireland dealt with and solved.  At the same time, I would like to remind the Minister that there are congested districts in the Leinster counties.  Anybody who travels through counties such as Meath, Westmeath, Kildare, etc., must know that here and there you run into a track of inferior land, bogland, and so on, and find that that tract is studded with the little houses of people who are living there under very miserable conditions, indeed.  I know of one estate in County Kildare, surrounded by a rich district, in which there are 180 tenants with valuations of £5 and under. Before bringing migrants from distant places, I think that these people should be placed in possession of economic holdings.  If that is not done, I am sure it will create a great deal of dissatisfaction, and the state of the country, to use a moderate term, will not improve.  On the contrary, I think it will be making confusion worse confounded. I could refer to another estate&mdash;the Verschoyle Estate&mdash;in another part of the county, in which similar conditions prevail.  Indeed, things there are worse, because the landlord has denied the tenants access even to the bogs, and they have to go without their fuel this year.  I bring these points forward in order to show that the Minister ought to bear in mind that his first duty is to relieve congestion in a particular district before introducing migrants from distant counties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWalterShaw" hpid="Mr. SHAW Mr. SHAW">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SHAW</NameTxt>
      <P>I know that the question of migratory tenants will be a very <Col N="2157" /> difficult and possibly a very controversial one, but I do not want any remarks I make to be taken either by the Minister or by anyone else as selfish.  I know that it is a necessity for people in the West, and in other parts, who are very probably worse off than the people I represent to obtain land in other parts of the country.  The suggestion I make is that where there are tracts of land under 400 acres, of which at least six persons are entitled to obtain a portion, and where only one person will be successful, such land should then be exempted.  On the other hand, in the County Westmeath and County Longford I am aware of tracts of land where one person has got two or three thousand acres.  I would like to see such lands divided amongst persons who may be described as migratory tenants from other localities.  In those two counties there are thousands of small farmers with 8 or 10 acres of land who by working very hard are able to live and rear their families.  I know what it would mean to such people to be able to get 8 or 10 acres in addition.  I would appeal very strongly to the Minister to see that where there are tracts of land of 150, 200, 300 and possibly up to 400 acres they should be exempt, and that the land selected for transfer to migratory tenants should be the larger tracts.</P>
      <P>Another suggestion that I would like to make, and one that I think would be of very considerable benefit to the community at large, is that, where possible, 30 or 40 acres of land should be secured in the vicinity of towns for use as a cow park.  If that could be done it would enable poor people who are now unable to obtain milk, or to pay for it, to keep a cow.  I strongly urge that some scheme of that kind should be devised and that land could be acquired for that purpose.  At present thousands of people, and especially children, suffer from lack of milk. Nothing I think would be of more substantial benefit to the people than such a scheme.  There is a want of that particularly nourishing food, milk, which many poor people are debarred from getting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I direct the attention of Deputies to sub-head (G).  This is one of the items supposed to be spent <Col N="2158" /> for the development of agriculture.  It is part of the £600,000 that was spoken of the other night and is the remains of an inheritance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to explain, in order to save the Deputy a certain amount of oratory, that this is not part of the £600,000.  It has nothing good, bad or indifferent to do with the agricultural grant.  It was never mixed up with the agricultural grant and comes from a totally different source.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>It is part of the £600,000 which we were told the other night was portion of the £1,000,000 spent on agriculture.  I was directed to look at Vote 47, which includes the £600,000 and is an inheritance from past legislation.  I want to ask the Minister why we should be saddled with £160,000 for excess stock?  It is a debt which in all reason should be payable by those who issued this stock and should be placed in a contra-account against the British Exchequer, instead of against the vote for the development of agriculture in Ireland. Under the Land Acts previous to the Hogan Act the sinking fund would be invested at £2 15s. per cent.  At the moment it is being invested at 5 per cent., where it is not used for further advances, and the rate of interest on that sinking fund is a couple of pounds more than the previous Acts provided for.  I contend in respect of that sinking fund that there is more than sufficient to blot out the £160,000 for excess stock.  The Minister can contradict that if he likes.  I want to ask the Minister, after the Land Commission has dealt with two millions remaining &mdash;because of pending sales&mdash;there were four millions at the beginning of the year&mdash;are we finished with all the previous Land Acts, and will the sinking fund then be directed towards the annihilation of the old debt and this £160,000, which is an incubus on our backs every year?</P>
      <P>As to arrears, it must be remembered that the Minister has stated the landlords in 40 per cent. of the cases returned wrong rents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Incorrect, I think would be more like it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2159" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The Land Act was passed last year, and by reason of the landlords sending in incorrect accounts confusion arose.  Up to recent months these accounts have not been rectified. The position of a tenant who had to pay a year's arrears&mdash;arrears due previous to May, 1923&mdash;can be understood. A half-year was due in May, 1924. That was payable under the pink order of the Land Commission.  In view of all this confusion, is it not a great testimony to the honesty of the farmers that there is only one-eighth of the arrears outstanding at the moment? On the question of costs, I see that they have collected £1,100 in law costs from defaulting annuitants. The fact of not issuing that particular notice, which the Minister says would cost a lot of money, but which any merchant would issue for the collection of accounts&mdash;and he would be very glad if he could get in his accounts by sending out bills&mdash;means that £1,100 came from poor tenants by whom the money would otherwise be paid regularly every year.  You cannot break a custom like that with impunity.</P>
      <P>With regard to the question of migration, as far as I can gather the Minister is going to meet that question by migrating the larger farmers in the congested areas who have purchased under the Act of 1903 and previous Acts.  Under the Land Act these men must be brought away from their present farms and put in better farms in Meath or Kildare or Wicklow or somewhere else.  I contend that a great case was made by Deputy Conlan. Where in an area there are 180 tenants with a valuation of less than £5 it would be unjust to bring in men from another part of the country and leave these men where they are unprovided for.  I quite agree that if 100,000 tenants were withdrawn from the Western seaboard they must be migrated and provided for, but they could get the land of those tenants in the West and these larger tenants in the West could be brought on to the ranches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The 100,000 includes all tenants unpurchased.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand it would take 3,000,000 acres to settle 100,000 congests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2160" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I had better explain.  There are 100,000 tenants to be purchased at the present moment. They have all to purchase, and where they have uneconomic holdings, they have to get economic holdings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I dare say, but, judging by previous Land Acts, it has taken about 3,000,000 acres to deal with 100,000 tenant purchasers.  It takes 30 acres to one tenant, and as there are 100,000 tenants to be provided for, under the new Act, it will take another 3,000,000 acres to do that.  The policy advocated by the Minister is a sound one.  I agree that provision should be made for the congests in the Western areas, but I would like to settle these men upon the Western areas, on the local land, and migrate the larger men and give them better farms, because the Land Act has made provision for them.  At the same time, the Minister must not forget the claims of the local landless men spoken of by Deputies Conlan and Davin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephMcGoldr" hpid="Mr. McGOLDRICK Mr. McGOLDRICK">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGOLDRICK</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to refer to a point or two in connection with this discussion.  There are landlords, so far as I understand, who have not made any return at all.  Now, this is a vexed question.  The onus is to be laid upon the tenant to take the necessary steps to ensure that he comes within the Land Act of 1923, and I consider that in such cases the onus of establishing his right to come in under the Act of 1923 should not rest upon the tenant. I know myself instances in which no returns have been made, and tenants feel, unquestionably, that it is a great grievance, so far as they they are concerned, that the responsibility and onus should rest upon them to take steps to compel the landlords to make returns, and to allow them to be included, as they should be, within the Land Purchase Act of 1923.  Some of the landlords may, in these cases, believe that they have some technical ground for not making a return.  I do not believe, in the cases that came before me, that they have any legal ground.  However, this is a question for the Commissioners to decide, and it appears that the onus of getting the Commissioners to take steps falls upon the tenant.  I do not think that that is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2161" /> I think a great deal could be said with regard to the grievance that exists in respect to notices referred to from the Farmers' Benches.  Undoubtedly, the tenants were confused.  I think the situation was one in which anyone might reasonably have been confused. There was a question of arrears, and there was 25 per cent. reduction, and then compounded arrears and the half-year's annuity, coming together, and all these things confused the tenants, with the result that they did not know what they were expected to pay.  Even the banks were confused.  They did not know where they stood, or what they should take, and when they should take it.  All this confusion combined to leave them in a very difficult position, and was responsible to a very large extent for whatever delay ensued in the payment of the annuities.  Undoubtedly, the tenants were anxious, and ready, as far as possible, to meet their obligations, and these obligations were severe enough upon them.  One would think in the stress that existed that it would be the duty of the establishment at headquarters to take steps to make it perfectly clear to them what their obligations were, and not to leave them in the confused condition, no matter what little cost it might entail in clerical work.</P>
    <P>The next question is the question raised by Deputy Davin with regard to holdings being divided up.  I have reason to know that that policy has been adopted to a certain extent.  I do not know how extensive it has been, but I know instances in which it has happened. I know of two holdings, fairly large ones, to be divided into three. Without the consent of anybody these holdings were sold, each of them, to three tenants and two of the tenants were made to pay rent for the third one.  That was done in order to evade the necessity of having a proper division made at headquarters.  That still is the position in regard to these holdings. That will entail a lot of difficulty. It is up to the Land Commission to see that these people who really bought <i>bona fide</i>, and believed that they were buying under conditions that would leave them in the same boat as everybody else, are not disadvantaged because of some ruse or trick of lawyers <Col N="2162" /> or legal authorities that put them into that position and left them a legacy which it may be difficult to get out of unless they have the assistance of the Land Commission.</P>
    <P>Another matter referred to here is this: An estate is before my mind, bought out since 1908 on a purchase agreement, although not vested.  The valuation of the holdings on that estate would not be more than £5 on an average.  There is a demesne on the estate.  This demesne consists of an uninhabited house, fairly large, and a considerable quantity of land, the best on the estate undoubtedly.  Now, this land has been untilled for two years and is grazed by everybody.  The rates are unpaid, but the animals are well watched against seizure and the county council has taken steps to see if it is possible to recover the rates on the land.  The rates are fairly considerable and their non-collection means a considerable loss.  When is this land to be dealt with?  It stands here in the centre of this congested community of small holders who bought out their holdings under an agreement and who are all in need of more land.  When is it to be dealt with?  And how are the rates to be collected?  I would like that the Land Commission would keep these problems before them, because they are serious, and of importance to the community.  It is too bad to have a big demesne like this lying idle and people all around in need of land and all anxious to till every perch they have.  But they have not sufficient land to sustain themselves and their families. I think it is the duty of the Land Commission to see that these things are attended to.  They are very serious to the community and they are a very great trouble to the Deputies on all occasions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamSears" hpid="Mr. SEARS Mr. SEARS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SEARS</NameTxt>
      <P>I was very glad to listen to the statement of the Minister regarding the preliminary work done under the Land Act of 1923, particularly because that statement will explain to the people why the division of the land has not yet commenced.  When this Act of 1923 was passed it was regarded all through the West of Ireland as a great Act of emancipation.  It was going to do for the congested districts of the <Col N="2163" /> West what the British Government had failed to do, even though it had inquired into that problem by means of setting up Royal Commissions.  For over half a century the British Government came up against that problem in various ways, but it did not do anything, and we looked forward to this Act to do for the congested districts what the British Government had failed to do.  Thirty or forty years ago the British Government inquired into this problem.  They appointed a Royal Commission to investigate it, and the finding of that Commission was that the only way to remedy the evils of the land problem in the West was to increase the size of the holdings in that part of Ireland.  The British Government, however, did not do that.  A way to a settlement of the problem was pointed out to them, but they went another way.  Therefore, the people in the West looked with great hope to the Land Act of 1923, and as there has been considerable delay in administering the provisions of that Act the people are now becoming impatient.  Anyone who knows the situation of these poor people or who is intimate with the terrible conditions under which they live, can understand that impatience and can forgive it.  After hearing the explanation of the delay the Minister says we are now up against the problem as to how this terrible evil is to be remedied, and he says there is a right way and there is a wrong way of settling it.  It cannot be settled in a parish or in a provincial way.  It is an evil that can only be settled in a national way.  It is quite true, of course, that it is a provincial problem, but I suggest that there is a terrible disgrace attached to this problem.  First and foremost, it is misunderstood, it is even misunderstood amongst our own people.  Often I have heard in the city of Dublin, and even in this Dáil, people say: &ldquo;Oh, here is the cry of distress again from the West.&rdquo;  We hear it said, too: &ldquo;Have we not heard that cry a hundred times, and how often have they got relief.&rdquo;  How did they get relief, I ask?  They never got any addition to their land and their distress was caused fifty, thirty or twenty years ago from lack of suitable land. <Col N="2164" /> Their little farms were not increased in size, and when a bad year came destitution followed in its wake.  It was no wonder it did, and why should people wonder.  If they understood the problem they would not wonder.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>at this stage took the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamSears" hpid="Mr. SEARS Mr. SEARS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SEARS</NameTxt>
      <P>How, as the Minister asked, is this problem to be settled? It can be settled either in a right way or in a wrong way.  Some Deputies mentioned about congested districts in the County Kildare or in the County Wicklow.  I say that a congested district, that is, where you have small farms, is as big a problem and as great an evil in Kildare or Wicklow as it is in any other part of Ireland.  In every part of Ireland we want small farms increased, so that they will be capable of sustaining and giving the occupier an opportunity to make a decent living for his family.  Whether such a congested district is in Connaught or out of Connaught that should be done, only I hope it will be done in Connaught first, and in Mayo before any place else.  It would be a great wrong to bring congests from Galway or Mayo and plant them down in some other county until you had first increased the size of the uneconomic holdings in that county.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another problem, and that is the landless men.  I have as much sympathy with the landless man who was brought up on a farm, either as a labourer or as a farmer's son, as any other Deputy, but when you have not enough of land for them, are you going to continue the system of small holdings? I think that the nature of the situation suggests that the first thing to be done with any available land you have for distribution is to increase the size of the holdings already held. Make them economic first, and then if there is any other land create economic holdings for the landless men.  But before you increase the size of the uneconomic holdings, if you commence to divide the ranches into holdings for landless men, you will simply be perpetuating the present evil and doing a terrible wrong to everyone concerned. Anyone that knows Connaught and sees year after year the battalions of <Col N="2165" /> young men and girls leaving their country to seek a living in another country, going over to Scotland to be herded in sheds and treated with contempt and insult at a time when there is plenty of land in Ireland for them, must admit that the problem in the West is very bad indeed.  In size the holdings are only a third or a quarter of a decent farm.  Not alone are the holdings small, but the land is bad. We all know the history of the conditions under which these people exist at present.  They were driven back on the mountains and into the bogs, and both they and their ancestors have been tilling this miserable land for generations. No human labour could make this land profitable.</P>
    <P>These people must be brought out of the bogs and off the mountain sides and put on good decent land.  I agree with some Deputies who stated here that those who have large holdings in Connaught should be encouraged to go into the Midlands and take holdings there of an equivalent size to their own, leaving their own holdings to be divided up afterwards.  I understand that that is the policy of the Land Commission and that is the line on which they are working.  I agree it is a sensible line.  If this problem is not taken up on national lines it will continue to be a sore in the future as well as it has been in the past.  I was glad to see that Deputies from other counties have approved of the suggestion made by the Minister, and that they are prepared to approach this problem in a good spirit.  It can be settled without causing friction anywhere.  An experiment in the matter of transplanting and emigration has been made already by the Land Commission.  I know of whole parishes and of half parishes that were taken and transplanted. They were taken to other districts and given good land, and I know that in their new homes these tenants have been successful in ninety-nine cases out of a hundred.  Their new farms and holdings are a credit to them.  Wherever they go they prove to be good citizens and add to the wealth of the nation.  Is it not better, I ask, to have them on good land making a decent living instead of allowing them to remain under the miserable conditions in <Col N="2166" /> which they existed years ago?  Is it not better, I ask, to have these people on good land in other counties rather than to have the bullocks on it?  Their labour on this good land will be more productive than it can be on the bogs on which they live at present.  The Minister himself has no excuse for not settling this problem.  There is no Minister of Agriculture in any country who has such drastic powers as he has now. He can take possession of land, not alone in the congested districts, but in any part of the Saorstát for the purpose of relieving congestion.  Deputy Conlan referred to a bog held by the landlord.  That cannot be, as the Minister can take possession of any bog, no matter who has it, and divide it up among the neighbouring tenants.  The Minister has complete powers to settle this question which has troubled Ireland for a long time.  He has asked for the support of the Dáil, and I believe that the Dáil will give it to him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy who has just sat down stated that the bog to which I referred could be taken by the Minister.  The Minister in fact tried his best and could not get it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. BAXTER Mr. BAXTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAXTER</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that there will be general agreement with the Minister's statement that the Land Commission is working very hard.  I am as critical of its work as anybody but I can agree with the Minister's statement, and I also agree with the principles which he has enunciated in regard to untenanted land.  The problem cannot be dealt with by counties or districts but from the point of view that congestion exists and that the greatest congestion must first be relieved and so on down the whole line until the State, which Deputy Sears wishes, has been created.  There has been a good deal of discussion as to the attitude of the Land Commission in prosecuting tenants for arrears.  Deputy White has been inclined to blame the Land Commission; I am not going to blame the Land Commission but the Minister himself.  He is responsible as the Land Act, and the arrears that were tacked on to it, have created the state by which the tenants had to pay arrears on annuities in twelve months. It is because they were honest enough <Col N="2167" /> to pay where they had not got the money that there has been a great deal of contention as well as actions in the courts, and very considerable dissatisfaction throughout the country.  The Minister may as well accept it and realise that it is the Land Act and not his Department that is responsible for that.  It is not owing to the administration of his Department but to the fact that the Act provides that tenants have to pay arrears which they have not paid off yet.  I presume that we are debarred from discussing that part of the Land Act which deals with arrears. I would like to hear the Minister say, as I heard him say some time ago, that in the distribution of land, account is not going to be taken of the political point of view of claimants for land. There is what I believe to be a very false impression created throughout the country, that only the adherents of a certain political party will have any claim or right to get any land that will be distributed.  Very good care has been taken to disseminate that point of view in many counties, but I believe it is not correct.  It would be a very false standard on which to base a man's claim for land.  I believe that many of them would be found to be very unworthy and, in some cases, incapable of managing the land if they got it, taking into account the use they have made of the little land already in their possession. That ought to be the standard by which a man's fitness should be judged and not his adherence to this or that political party.  I think it would be a good thing if the Minister would state that, irrespective of what political party a man may belong to, whether he belongs to the political party in this House or to that outside it, his claim, will be recognised.  I would also like the Minister to state what position we are in with regard to the vesting of land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I believe that in a considerable number of cases the arrears have been paid off, and that the tenants are in a position on some estates to have the land vested and thus to enjoy the full benefits of the Land Act.  When does the Minister expect that this land will be vested, and why have steps not been taken before now to put the Minister <Col N="2168" /> in a position to pay for this land in order that it may be vested in the tenants?  I would also like to know if the Minister has reconsidered his attitude with regard to the payment of arrears to facilitate the vesting of land, and whether arrears still outstanding shall be added to the purchase money. I also want to suggest to the Minister, in regard to the allusion made by Deputy Sears to the bogs, that in some counties this question of taking over bogs is causing very serious trouble, and has cost life in some cases.  On many estates that will be vested in tenants under the 1923 Act there is a considerable portion of bog adjoining, but up to the present this bog is still in the possession of the landlord.  In many cases the tenants do not know whether the bog is in the possession of the landlord or the Land Commission, and do not know whether the landlord has a right to set it or not.  There is a large portion of bog not used by tenants, although a considerable number of them are in need of bog.  The landlord may, perhaps, permit tenants on the estate to use it, but he will not permit outsiders to do so.  I would urge the Minister that in the period that will elapse before next season's turf-making, steps should be taken as far as possible by the Land Commission to acquire and distribute bogs on estates that will be vested in tenants under the 1923 Act.  I am not speaking of bogs in areas that may be termed untenanted, but where the tenants will have land vested in them.  I would urge this point strongly on the Minister because not only is it an economic necessity in some districts, but it is also a matter that is causing very serious dissatisfaction and grave trouble.  I recognise, of course, that the distribution of untenanted land is the first work to be done, but the distribution of untenanted land will go on in some districts to the benefit of some people, whereas in other districts very little will be done and very little benefit will accrue under the Land Act.  Exorbitant rents are being paid for bogs, while the Minister has it in his power to reduce such rents.  The holders are required in some districts to pay £1 a perch in order to have a fire in the winter.  The Minister has power to <Col N="2169" /> reduce those rents, and I urge him, along with the work in connection with the distribution of untenanted land, to do what he can in this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'CONNELL Mr. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there will be general agreement with the statement made by Deputy Baxter that the general outline which the Minister has given us of the work of the Land Commission is, on the whole, satisfactory. I would press him specially to say what is his attitude towards the point raised by Deputy Davin, that is, the sale of lands by public auction or treaty in order to evade the working of the Land Act.  With regard to the question of migration.  I think we must all agree with the general principle stated by the Minister as to the way in which this problem is to be tackled.  Where there is a big man in the congested area he will be found a more suitable man to migrate.  There are many areas where there is not a big land owner.  It would be well in dealing with the problem to note what Deputy Shaw has said, that is, to use bigger ranches for the purpose of migration rather than smaller ones in order that whole colonies may be migrated.  Many people strongly object to migration, because they feel they will be strangers in a strange land.  If they are migrated in colonies, and if their friends and neighbours are sent with them to a new land, they will have less reluctance in migrating.  I think, having migrated those people, the Commission should not forget that it will be necessary for some time to take care of them, as it were, and to educate them into the new methods of agriculture prevalent in the district. Many of those men will come from districts where work is almost entirely manual.  They will have no knowledge whatsoever of the use of machinery, or of the improved methods of agriculture, and special provision ought to be made to take care, as it were, of the migrants for a few years in their new and strange surroundings.  With regard to the question of bogs, most of those migrants from the western areas live very near a bog, and I think they are inclined to put too much value on bogs for the purpose of fuel.  They think nothing of a farm unless, as Deputy White would say, &ldquo;there is a <Col N="2170" /> turf bank intil it.&rdquo;  I know districts in Roscommon where bogs are scarce. People have a bog anything from four to-eight miles away from their farm. I maintain that the bog at that distance is more of an incumbrance than anything else.  Those people start out in the morning early and come back at night with one load of turf in the day. Fuel at that price is not an economic proposition, and I would suggest to the Land Commission the possibility of examining such districts in the future, and seeing whether it would not be better, when they are putting up houses on those tracts of land, to fit them with anges for coal-burning.  Coal, certainly in those districts, would be cheaper than turf, as a good deal of the valuable time of the migrant is spent in the bog.</P>
      <P>The Minister spoke of one hundred thousand unpurchased tenants.  I am sure he will realise that there were many purchased tenancies which are still uneconomic ones.  Many of those in the buying of land, when it was divided in piecemeal fashion, would have patches of five or six acres, or even smaller patches, and would get an extra few acres.  Those people, though they are purchased, have an equal claim with the uneconomic holders, who may be having their lands purchased now, and should not be forgotten when the land is being distributed.  I agree with the general principles enunciated by the Minister, that the first claimant to the land is the uneconomic holder.  When the operations of the late Congested Districts Board were suspended, very many men who had given long service to the Congested Districts Board were dismissed, and I would like the Minister to give an assurance now that when the new works are being begun, those men would get first preference when he is employing them, not the general labourers, but the gangers and supervisors and those who lost their positions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinMNally" hpid="Mr. NALLY Mr. NALLY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NALLY</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to ask the Minister when it is intended that the Land Commission should divide the six or seven thousand acres of land they own in County Mayo and which they are letting out for grazing at a huge profit? That applies to the Ross. Clifford and <Col N="2171" /> Sligo estates, and other parts of the County Mayo, and is causing considerable unrest in those parts of the county. I think the first thing the Land Commission should do is to settle this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be well within the recollection of Deputies that when we were discussing the Vote of the Ministry of Agriculture the Minister stated that the Vote did not include all that was given to agriculture, and instanced that there was £600,000 in addition to the sums voted.  The next morning one of the papers had in broad headlines: &ldquo;A million for agriculture.&rdquo; I deny that agriculture is receiving anything like a million, and I deny that this sum of £672,000 is really devoted to agricultural purposes. I maintain that it falls into the same category as National Health Insurance, Unemployment Insurance, and the Poor Law system.  In other words, it is a measure of social amelioration, and by no stretch of the imagination could it be regarded as an aid for agriculture, because it could not be demonstrated that agriculture will benefit as a scientific resultant from it.  I am afraid that through the length and breadth of this country to-morrow, when people read the statement of the Minister for Lands and Agriculture with reference to his plan for redistributing land, it will come as something of the nature of a thunderclap.  If I interpret the Minister correctly, he said that they had available something like five million acres of land, or, roughly, a quarter of the Free State, for distribution to relieve 100,000 congests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Something like five million acres of land at least are required to relieve 100,000 congests.  I am at a loss to know whether these figures include families in the congested areas alone or do they include all the uneconomic holders throughout the length and breadth of the Saorstát.  The Minister laid down as a great cardinal factor that the main idea would be mass transportation. I have a little knowledge of history.  I do not suppose&mdash;I exclude Cromwell's policy of &ldquo;to hell or Connaught&rdquo;&mdash;that we had anything in the world's history to approach the scheme that the Minister <Col N="2172" /> outlined to-night since Nebuchadnezzar transported the Israelites from the Jordan to the Euphrates, from Jerusalem to Babylon.  The Minister's plan of mass transportation is on the same scale as the mass transportation of 2,500 years ago.  There is one difference&mdash;the Israelites trekked in large bodies; the Irish will trek singly now. If we remove 100,000 congests it roughly will mean about 600,000 per sons, because the people in the congested areas are said to be prolific.  I am just wondering what the cost will be to this State.  What will the effect be on production?  What will the whole effect be on security?  The principle appears to be to shift men who are not congests in themselves and perhaps have a sufficiency of land or perhaps something approaching a sufficiency of land.  They are to be shifted to other neighbourhoods.  They are displaced to make way for others.  So that as a result of any such measure of amelioration we shall have internal convulsion and social revolution.</P>
    <P>Deputies in this House seem to appreciate very fully what the Minister said.  Unfortunately I am a realist.  I do not possess that faculty of ingenious fancy that men call romanticism, and I ask: what can be the effect on the social and economic life of the nation of the transplantation of six or seven hundred thousand persons?  As Deputy O'Connell put it, they themselves in their new surroundings would be strangers in a strange land.  I quite agree.  And I might amplify his statement by saying that as far as we can predict with any degree of certainly in human affairs they will be strangers in an unfriendly and perhaps in an actively hostile land.  And even if the Powers of Arrest and Detention Act were to be passed in perpetuity, one wonders whether even all the resources of the State could save some of these people from falling victims to local jealousy in the areas to which they have migrated.  I believe if you transport the ordinary, decent man he will succumb and he and his family will be helpless victims.  If, on the other hand, you transport some of the hard &ldquo;chaws,&rdquo; some of the toughs, will you not create a condition of unceasing strife?</P>
    <Col N="2173" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I know what he wants. He wants to get rid of the toughs of Clare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It appears to me that this problem should be approached very cautiously.  Families who have no concern with the congested areas, who are not directly congests themselves, have to be transported apparently to make way for others.  These people will be shifted from their homes and transported to other districts, where the conditions of farming are unknown to them, and they will not readily adapt themselves to the new conditions.  In addition, why, I ask, should those people, even the congests, be severed from their home ties and from their associations in the localities in which they heretofore resided?  It appears to me that, so far from embarking in that dangerous revolutionary policy of mass transportation, we ought to endeavour to relieve the lot of the congests without making anything like a violent distribution of land.</P>
      <P>Certainly by all means divide the land where land is available, but not in the wholesale manner propounded by the Minister for Agriculture.  I think that if in certain areas the lands were retained in the hands of the State and if the congests were allowed to graze cattle, young stock&mdash;we are endeavouring to introduce dairy schemes into the country and improve the dairy herd for instance&mdash;and if the congests were allowed to send heifers from their best milch cows to these lands at a reasonable fee that in itself would very materially help them in the battle for life.  It would not be everything but it would be something.  The State is laying up trouble for itself by this proposed wholesale distribution of land. We are relieving congestion in this generation by dividing all the available lands, but we forget that we are intensifying congestion and that there will be no land then to go round.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A DEPUTY A DEPUTY">
      <NameTxt>A DEPUTY</NameTxt>
      <P>Why, sir?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Where are you going to get it?  Are you going to have another confiscation?  Men with a sense of insecurity will not go in for improvements on a large scale.  And as regards the cost, I wonder do we <Col N="2174" /> realise what the cost of this scheme of mass transportation will be?  Will the congests be able to get on without State Aid?  I doubt it.  In many places they will have to build houses and walls and those things are very costly and they will perhaps have to drain the land.  I ask the Minister to bear this in mind and to ask himself the question whether the State can meet the extraordinary expenditure of this scheme, or does he expect that the congests can do it.  I believe that the cost of transporting 100,000 families of congests would be nothing less than £20,000,000, which would entail on this State a charge of £1,000,000 a year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Deputy suggest coffins instead?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="Mr. P. HOGAN (Clare) Mr. P. HOGAN (Clare)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. HOGAN (Clare)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Hogans seem to be very much in evidence in this debate.  I have a little to add to what was said by the different Deputies with regard to the distribution of land. It is the distribution of the untenanted land that I am mainly concerned with, and I am afraid that the Land Act is not operating as well as many would wish in that direction.  There is some tardiness about its operations which both the uneconomic holders and the landless men do not seem to fancy.  I have put several questions to the Minister, and the most information I could draw from him is this, that these lands would be vested in the Land Commission as soon as practicable.  That might mean anything.  I do not know how soon it would be practicable, and I would like to know this evening, or get some idea, as to how soon these lands may be vested in the Commission and distributed.  There is some ferment and dissatisfaction in the country amongst the uneconomic holders and landless men in this connection.  If I understood the Minister rightly, he indicated that it would be a wiser policy to deal with the congested districts first and then to come gradually into districts that are not congested.  I do not know whether he understood the implication of the question or not, but it amounted to this, that they expect the policy of the Department would be to concentrate on the congested districts first.  In Clare there <Col N="2175" /> are two districts which are not congested, and the reason these two districts are not congested is because of the action of a noble lord in another place.  I will not mention the name of the noble lord, but possibly the Minister will recognise him when I tell him that an ancestor of his was engaged in a quarrel with the Danes somewhere up in Dorset Street in Easter Week in the 11th century.  If we are going to concentrate on congested districts, are we going to distribute the other four or five districts in this county, and leave out these two districts there where there is most land available for distribution, and where there are a good many uneconomic owners and landless men?  That would create a good deal of confusion, and I would like some information from the Minister in that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is also, of course, the point Deputy Davin raised.  I should also like to say that when I brought the matter under the notice of the Minister he did try to take some steps to discover whether this land could be acquired under the Act of 1923.  In this case I did try to show how the matter worked out.  The person who owns the land realises that he cannot get a person, perhaps, to buy the entire property, and he puts it up to be sold in eight, nine, or ten lots, as the case may be.  I pointed out to the Minister that it would be eight times easier to realise that estate if it was in the possession of one man, rather than in the possession of eight people.  The Minister said that was not a difficult matter, and he gave me to understand that it would be just as easy to take over that land, though it was vested in 100 people. There is another thing, how soon may we expect that the Congested Districts will be dealt with?  If we know that we may have some idea as to how soon we may concentrate on the other districts that are not congested.  I do not know that I have anything else to say, except that I was very much interested in the transportation, or whatever you call it, of colonies from one district to another. I would like to make a suggestion to the Minister in that connection.  It is quite possible you will be transferring <Col N="2176" /> colonies from different districts, and I would suggest to the Minister that he would give some consideration to the possibility of transferring colonies of Irish speakers from Irish-speaking districts into districts that are not Irish-speaking, and putting the colony together so that it would be self-supporting, and that instead of the Pale invading the Gaeltacht, we will have the Gaeltacht invading the Pale, and spreading the light there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there is some slight misunderstanding, at least in some quarters, as to what I meant to convey when I gave figures of the numbers of tenants unpurchased, and of the amount of land available to deal with them.  There are 100,000 tenants in the country.  A tenant purchaser holds his land in fee simple, and is not, properly speaking, a tenant.  There are 100,000 agricultural tenants who pay rents to landlords.  The figure is slightly less, but it is not worth speaking about. The figures include congests, uneconomic holders, big farmers and small farmers&mdash;100,000 judicial and non-judicial tenants, present and future.  I hope that is clear.  They include everybody inside and outside the congested districts, congests and non-congests, big farmers and small farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I said that the amount of land available for the Land Commission on a very generous estimate&mdash;I am taking into account probably all the land that the Land Commission can be reasonably expected to acquire&mdash;is about 5,000,000 acres.  By a little analysis of previous operations of the Land Commission I have found that 100,000 tenant-purchasers were planted on between 2,500,000 acres and 3,000,000 acres of land.  These figures are rough, but you can make some deductions from them, and one fairly safe deduction is that it will require 3,000,000 acres of land to deal with the existing tenants, and this will include in a great many instances part of their own holdings. It is certain that it will require 3,000,000 acres to deal with the existing tenants, but I think the amount required is nearer to 4,000,000 acres.  Deputy O'Connell pointed out that a very great many tenant-purchasers who had already purchased their land under <Col N="2177" /> previous Acts, and who are paying their annuities, are still uneconomic, and have to be dealt with.  I am afraid the fact is that we cannot expect, even with ideal conditions and even with the co-operation of everybody, to deal with congests under this Act, or any Act, so as to solve the problem finally, but rather our aim should be to go as far as we can to solve it, and at least to make sure that difficulties encountered can be got over, and should not be allowed to stand in the way of a solution of that particular problem.  I do not mean to suggest for one moment that we were to concentrate on the congested districts, and I never meant to suggest that congests outside what are technically known as congested districts were not to be dealt with.  I did not deal at any length with congests outside congested districts, for they present no problem as a rule, except in a county like Cavan, and in certain small areas outside Cavan, where they do present difficulties, but as a general rule, taking the country as a whole, present no problem, for there is land.  They can be dealt with quite simply.  I took it for granted that no one could possibly so misconstrue what I said as to think it was our intention to make holdings within the congested districts economic, and leave congests outside the congested districts out of the settlement.</P>
    <P>I referred to congests especially because they are, roughly speaking, the most difficult problem.  There are, as I said, small areas outside the congested districts that are also a difficult problem because of the absence of untenanted land in the neighbourhood, but speaking generally the congests present the really difficult problem. That was the reason that I referred to them and concentrated on them for the moment.  All I intended to convey was that when the Land Commission was acquiring untenanted land in the congested districts they have to keep well in mind the fact that they are to deal with every uneconomic tenant left unpurchased, and in addition with a very large number of uneconomic tenant purchasers who have purchased their holdings under the previous Land Acts.  When dividing untenanted land, either inside or outside a congested <Col N="2178" /> district, they must keep the fact well in mind that if they are to deal with all the congests, or with a reasonable number of them, if they are to make a reasonable number of uneconomic holdings economic they must be careful not to divide the land indiscriminately and choose a few congests who happen to be in the neighbourhood, and so far as the remainder of the land is concerned to divide it among landless men.  They must be careful to follow some general scheme.  They must have in their minds the fact that even though there may be very few congests in this particular district, there may be a very large number of congests in other districts who will have to be migrated. When Deputies asked me why could not land be bought here, there and everywhere, and divided with an eye to the immediate needs, that is the reason that that cannot be done.  Deputies should realise that though it may be a very effective proposition to talk of taking different estates in this county or the other county to advertise the work of the Land Commission, by doing that, and dividing these estates amongst landless men of particular districts we would be pursuing a policy which, if continued, would leave us in the end with, I should say, three-quarters of the congests of the Western seaboard, and of other places like Cork and Cavan, where there are a very large number of congests concentrated. That is as far as I wish to go under that heading.</P>
    <P>I do not want to hold out the hope that the Land Commission will be able to deal with all congests.  They will not.  The problem is too big.  There will be a residue of congests who will not be migrated, I am afraid.  There will be, apart altogether from the fact that there may not be enough land, even if they could be migrated, a large number of congests left who will not migrate in the end.  The exigencies of the case will be such, perhaps, that landless men will be dealt with even to a greater extent than would be absolutely correct if one were in a position to put through an ideal solution. Between one thing and another, between the difficulty of migrating congests, between the difficulty of finding <Col N="2179" /> suitable areas to which to migrate them, between the expense, between the demand of landless men for land in areas where there are no congests&mdash; taking all the circmustances into account, it will surprise me if in the end all the congests are dealt with.  But certainly the policy of the Land Commission should be, so far as possible, to aim at dealing with all congests, and it should be the aim of every responsible party in the State to co-operate in that, and to forego, each and every one of them, the undoubted political advantages to be gained in advocating land purchase for this area and that area.  Without the co-operation of every party and of every responsible Deputy, every responsible public man, with a general consciousness that it is necessary to examine, first, the claims of people who may be living at the other end of the country before you can divide land among people who would be in other circumstances entitled to the land, and who live in the particular neighbourhood, you will not be able to deal with the problem.  With that consciousness, with that policy clearly defined, and with the goodwill and co-operation of every party behind that policy, you can go very near to the solving of this problem.</P>
    <P>I want to clear up one point.  I stated that 40 per cent. of returns made by landlords were incorrect.  That statement in itself is not quite correct. What I should have said was that 40 per cent. of returns made by landlords were challenged by tenants, and that is not exactly the same thing as saying that 40 per cent. of the returns were incorrect.  They were challenged by the tenants largely on the ground that abatements of rent were not allowed, and in some cases the tenants' contention was upheld; in other cases the landlord's contention.  I could not say what the proportion was.  I should say that it was about half-and-half of the 40 per cent.  But I was not correct in stating that 40 per cent. of the returns made by landlords were incorrect. The exact fact is that 40 per cent. of returns made by landlords were challenged by tenants, and in some cases the landlords were vindicated, while in others the tenants were.  As <Col N="2180" /> a result of these disputes the Judicial Commissioner had to try at least two thousand cases.  Deputy White instanced cases where processes were served after the bank drafts had been sent to the Land Commission.  I am quite sure that that is so.  What occurs is this.  Tenant purchasers owed a year's arrears, and after they had sent their annuities direct to the Land Commission they received processes. That occurred, of course, every day. Tenant purchasers let the 1st June pass without paying their annuities.  They waited until the end of June, knowing that they were a month in arrears. They wait for the first notice, for the second notice, for the third notice, for the fourth notice.  They wait until they get a solicitor's letter&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation. Let us be right about this.  Is there a first, second, third, and fourth notice, and-then a solicitor's letter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no first notice now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the use of saying that there is a first, second, third and fourth, if there is not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no first notice now.  I am speaking of the general cases.  Tenants know perfectly well that the gale days are due in December. There is not a single tenant purchaser who does not know that.  Really I do not think it is expecting too much civic sense from the farmers, if they do admit that they have to pay their Land Commission annuities, that they should not take advantage of unsettled conditions of one kind or another in order to get out of doing so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that, as a rule, tenant purchasers who have received money which the State borrowed, for which the State pledged its credit, this money being used in order to make them the owners of their land at reasonable rates of interest, at very reasonable prices, and who admit that they should pay their annuities, should pay the annuities when they are able, at least when they are due.  We can leave out of account for the moment people who for one reason or another are actually not able to meet this charge, and <Col N="2181" /> they are a very small proportion of the people in arrears.  The point of view should not be that they will not pay this debt, which they admit they owe, which they would not dare to say is not a liability due from every point of view. They should not wait until the bailiff or process-server calls around.  I think it is not expecting too much civic spirit in the farmers to pay that debt when it becomes due, whenever they are able.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I interrupt the Minister to ask if he has seen the decision that Judge Cooke gave in Lifford in April last?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know anything about that decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>According to his judgment the Land Commission acted illegally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>When they went through these lists they found that nearly always it is the same people who owed these arrears; that they are often big farmers, as often big farmers as small farmers.  The same people always lose their Receivable Orders; the same people, half-year after half-year, do not receive their Receivable Orders from the Land Commission.  The same people do not receive letters from the Land Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Beat the drum now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>They are always the same.  It is in the interests of the farmers themselves that these annuities should be paid promptly, because if they are not they fall on the rates, and every farmer and every responsible farmer Deputy, should make it clear that there is no excuse for waiting for a notice from the Land Commission, or a letter from a solicitor.  It would be the duty of every farmer who has borrowed money from the State to pay the interest on the annual debt and not to wait on these notices.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>If he has the money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>As a rule it is not the farmers who are badly off who withhold these payments.  The commonest thing in the world, as Deputy White knows, is for tenant purchasers to wait, say two or three months after the annuity is due, until they know <Col N="2182" /> that processes are out, and then to send on the amount of the annuity to the Land Commission.  That is quite common. That is a procedure which is not peculiar to a debt due to the Land Commission.  Every solicitor knows that the commonest thing in the world is to find people who owe money and who refuse to pay, waiting until the process is out and then sending the money along.  The Land Commission, after two or three months dealing with people who are in arrears, instruct the solicitor to proceed.  He issues his processes and the annuity is paid.  Who is to pay the solicitor's costs?  Is it the State?  Sharp practice of that sort goes on every year, and when I get complaints that processes have been served after payments have been made I find in practically every case on investigation that the annuity was owed for half a year, or for a year; generally the last gale day had passed for three or four months, and generally the case had reached the hands of the solicitor, and the process was actually issued before the money arrived in the Land Commission.  I can assure Deputy White that the very day on which the Land Commission receives instalments by post they immediately communicate with the local solicitor, who is absolutely entitled to get his decrees for his costs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>Judge Cooke did not give a decree in the Bonner case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be better if the Deputy heard the Minister, and then asked any questions he wished afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>After the process is issued before payment has been made it is the duty of the tenant to go to the Court and prove that he had paid before it was issued.  Then the boot would be on the other foot.  I do not know of any case where tenants, who know the law in this respect as well as any solicitor, have succeeded in getting costs against the Land Commission. With regard to Deputy Davin's point, as everybody knows, we have no power under the Land Act to prevent owners from selling their lands, and I think everybody knows the reason.  We could <Col N="2183" /> not announce generally that the owners of landed property, who for the greater part are tenant purchasers, are not entitled to sell their lands.  We took certain powers over the lands in the Land Act.  These powers are, as some Deputy said, very drastic.  We can go no further.  I need not point out the effect of such powers.  It would mean that the value of all property of that class would immediately fall to a figure considerably lower than the market value of the property before such a notice was issued.  I think no responsible Deputy would advocate for a moment that we should by statute take power to prevent any class from selling the property which they possess at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I advocated that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not saying the Deputy did.  I am just going into the reasons.  On the other hand there is ample power under the Land Act to acquire lands that have been recently disposed of.  The fact that A is the owner and that B was the owner yesterday makes no difference to the powers which the Land Commission have under the Act.  I do agree that when lands are sold and divided, say, into small holdings which are now the property of seven or eight persons instead of one, each of them owning perhaps only an economic holding, it makes it more difficult for the Land Commission to re-acquire these lands. It is easier as a practical matter to acquire 200 or 300 acres from one owner than to go in and evict five or six small purchasers to get possession. The powers are there, if necessary, to use them and the only thing that is to be said on that particular question, the question of owners dividing their lands and then selling them, is that it only occurs in very few cases.  That of course is a form of land purchase without State aid.  Wherever the circumstances justify it the Land Commission will exercise their powers of acquisition of these lands even if they are divided, just the same as they are exercising their powers against any other land owned by anybody else in the neighbourhood. <Col N="2184" /> Where the circumstances justify it they will do that and that is the only thing that can be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not possible for the Land Commission where they knew land was advertised for sale to have arrangements immediately made for the inspection of these lands?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is possible, the Deputy is quite correct, and so far as is possible when lands are being sold in that way the Land Commission do take cognisance of it, and they will inspect these lands as quickly as possible. Owners who, in the normal way come under the Land Act, have ample notice that the lands will be acquired, and any purchasers buying land in these circumstances, do so at their own risk. Deputy Davin also wanted to know how we appointed inspectors.  The appointments made were thirty-four inspectors, five assistant inspectors, and thirteen valuers&mdash;the C.D.B. staff transferred. We have only appointed twenty-two new officials between inspectors and surveyors.  These were appointed by the Selection Board set up by the Civil Service Commission.  I need not say that there were a great many applicants for these appointments.  The Selection Board had first of all to analyse the various applications, go into the qualifications of the applicants as stated by themselves in their applications, and they did not find much difficulty in selecting men whose applications were such that they were entitled to further investigation.  Then out of the very large number of the applicants, a certain proportion were summoned to Dublin, interviewed and examined as to their experience and their qualifications. The Selection Board after this examination selected the most suitable candidates, with a special eye to the work that had to be done, and after making quite sure, as far as it could be made, that the qualifications of the men selected were such as to be likely to make them efficient inspectors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I raised a point with regard to the districts to which those people were likely to be sent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to that point, I do not think an inspector is <Col N="2185" /> usually sent to his own district.  I do not think you could lay down a general rule that he should not.  From experience such a rule is, I think, not necessary. As I say, inspectors are not, as a rule, sent to their own districts.  Deputy Shaw pointed out that it would be well, when tenants are being migrated, to migrate them in colonies or migrate them in large numbers, and he suggested the purchase of large estates rather than small estates so that they could be kept together, so that it would not be necessary to dot them here and there, one man by himself without a friend near or a neighbour from his own district.  He pointed out that perhaps the right way to do it would be to acquire large areas of land and to put in seven or eight or a dozen migrants from one particular district, so that the break with the home associations would not be too great.  That is obviously the best policy and what the Land Commission will, so far as possible, adopt. Deputy Baxter wants to know is the land to be divided on political lines, if you like.  I do not think it is necessary to answer that question.  Of course, it is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>resumed the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister making sure that no means are being adopted at present to give that impression?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am.  I am aware that organisers of all parties are announcing that &ldquo;If you give your name we will get the land for you.&rdquo;  I know that is going on.  I know that is occurring with regard to organisers and persons connected with all parties.  I have heard it is occurring with regard to persons connected with the Farmers' Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Name.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Let the Minister conclude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I have heard it stated on reliable authority in connection with men supposed to be connected with the Farmers' Party.  It is inevitable that that sort of thing should occur.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2186" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>It is inevitable that lies should be told!  Give the names.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Let the Minister say what he has to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not give the names nor the information I have.  But I want to say that I have most reliable information that organisers and men connected with all parties in the Dáil have been stating: &ldquo;Give us your name and we will get you the land. We are the only people who can.&rdquo;  I will give the Deputy in confidence the names of such as have done so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be delighted to have them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that that takes in anybody.  But if it is any consolation to Deputies I can assure them that the Land Commission will do what they have always done in the matter.  They will divide the land on the merits of each case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCosgrave" hpid="Mr. JAMES COSGRAVE Mr. JAMES COSGRAVE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMES COSGRAVE</NameTxt>
      <P>Who are the organisers concerned on behalf of the Independent Party?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I could answer that question also.  Deputy Baxter put forward an extraordinary explanation for the large arrears of Land Commission annuities that are outstanding. He stated that it was because they had to pay arrears of Land Commission annuities and arrears of rent together.  Well, I have heard a great many explanations for the large amount of arrears, but that is the most naive.  The arrears of annuities in 1922 before the Land Act was passed were far bigger than since the Land Act was passed.  As a general rule, people who owe arrears of rent are people who have not purchased their holdings.  The people who owe arrears of annuities are one class of people; people who owe arrears of rent are another, with a very small number of exceptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. BAXTER Mr. BAXTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAXTER</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister misunderstood what I said.  What I did refer to was the confusion that had been created over the collection of annuities.  I stand by my statement that the compounded arrears of rent that had to be paid prevented the annuitants <Col N="2187" /> paying their interest in lieu of rent, and many of those tenants have been proceeded against.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what the Deputy means.  If the Deputy agrees with me in the statement I have just made, that is an end of it, but the arrears of rent have absolutely nothing whatever to do with the arrears of annuity. If that is clear I am satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. BAXTER Mr. BAXTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAXTER</NameTxt>
      <P>Has it to do with interest in lieu of rent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Compounded arrears of rent have nothing whatever to do with interest in lieu of rent or with annuities.  As a rule, with very few exceptions, annuitants are people who have purchased their holdings.  Tenants who pay interest in lieu of rent are tenants who have purchased their holdings, but whose holdings have not yet been vested. I was referring to the £2,900,000 of annuities, and I was explaining that there was about £1,000,000 of arrears in the year 1922-23.  I want to make it quite clear that that was not caused by reason of the fact that people had to pay compounded arrears of rent.  As a rule, the people who were paying compounded arrears of rent, with very few exceptions, are not annuitants. Deputy Nally asked me when did we intend to divide the 5,000 acres purchased in Mayo, which is let for grazing. I presume he refers to the land purchased by the Congested Districts Board, and taken over by the Land Commission on the absorption of the Congested Districts Board.  I pointed out there were 21,000 acres of such land, of which 10,000 acres have been divided within the past year, and the balance will be divided before the end of this year, and in good time for next year's cropping.  I think these are the only points requiring reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the Minister to reply to my question with regard to the two million acres of land under previous Acts&mdash;when they are disposed of will that complete the operations under the old Acts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. BAXTER Mr. BAXTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAXTER</NameTxt>
      <P>I would also ask for a reply to my questions as to the <Col N="2188" /> taking over of bogs, and the putting of arrears into purchase money, the vesting of the lands, and the floating of stock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to remind the Minister of the decision come to by the County Court Judge at the Lifford Quarter Sessions.  Judge Cooke nilled cases there, where it was proved the rent had been received before the process was served.  Will the Minister have any objection to giving the Dáil a report of the names of inspectors appointed, their previous calling and experience, and the districts they are appointed to?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephMcGoldr" hpid="Mr. McGOLDRICK Mr. McGOLDRICK">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGOLDRICK</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister might say on whom the onus rests in regard to estates in respect of which the landlord has not made a return&mdash; whether it is for the tenant to prove that he is within the Purchase Act, or the landlord to prove that he is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the assertion made about the members of the various parties promising land, I promised a fellow twenty acres down in Clare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like if the Minister would give me privately or publicly the name of any organiser who promised land on behalf of the Labour Party.  So far as I am concerned&mdash;and I think it is the general attitude adopted by our party&mdash;we know we have no power to promise land because the power is in the hands of the people to whom the Minister is responsible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is now getting into a new and most offensive point.  The Minister is responsible to the Dáil.  The power is in the hands of the Dáil.  If the Deputy means anything else he is wrong and he is getting into a new and more offensive point than ever.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to be offensive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy mean that the Minister is responsible to the Dáil or otherwise?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the Minister&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Does Deputy <Col N="2189" /> Davin mean that the Minister is responsible to the Dáil and that the Dáil has the power of giving the land? Is that what he means?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Neither do I.  That settles that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>May I remind the Dáil that there are some thirty Votes yet to be discussed, and that we have got to get all the stages of the Appropriation Bill finished to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWalterShaw" hpid="Mr. SHAW Mr. SHAW">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SHAW</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Minister replies, might I ask what is his intention with regard to vesting lands as far as possible in trustees living near towns so that they may keep cows on these lands?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to smile at the innocence of Deputies.  I do not know of any politicians who do not say to their supporters &ldquo;Vote for me and we will get land.&rdquo;  I know it occurs in every party and I state that here definitely. There is no Deputy here in any party who does not know that what I am stating is quite true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>We know it is true on behalf of the Ministerial party.  We know their organiser said so and we can prove it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do state definitely that the lands will be divided on the merits, and that no political considerations of any kind will enter into it. Deputy Baxter asked me will bogs be divided as well as untenanted land and at the same time?  They will, of course. I could not promise that there will be an appropriate amount of bog provided with a certain amount of untenanted land, but the Land Commission is well aware that it is very little use giving tenant-purchasers holdings except they have an appropriate amount of bog as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy McGoldrick asked me will the onus be on tenants of supplying particulars in the event of the landlord refusing.  The onus is on the Land Commission to get the particulars, and if they do not get them from the landlord <Col N="2190" /> they will get them from the tenant, and if they do not get them from either they will have to send an inspector to make inquiries.</P>
    <P>Deputy Shaw pointed out the advantages of vesting lands as far as possible in trustees near towns to enable the poor people and the people generally, who wish to do so, to keep cows on these lands.  I agree with him that that was a great advantage.  It has been done under the 1903 Act, and it will be done, and there is ample power to do it, under the 1923 Act.</P>
    <P>Deputy Wilson wants to know whether the operations under previous Land Acts will be concluded when we have dealt with the two million acres of land in the hands of the Land Commission. When we have dealt with the two million acres in the hands of the Land Commission, and also with whatever amount of land has been acquired by the Land Commission that was formerly held by the old Congested Districts Board, then all operations under previous Acts will be finished.  The Land Commission at present cannot buy land under any previous Acts. They must buy under the 1923 Act, and when pending sales have been dealt with, the operations under previous Land Acts will have been finished.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="Mr. P. HOGAN (Clare) Mr. P. HOGAN (Clare)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. HOGAN (Clare)</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister say what is the position of tenants in small villages close by an estate which has been divided and who are tenants of that estate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is whether they are agricultural tenants or not. If they are agricultural tenants they must be dealt with under the Act.  If they are not agricultural tenants they are not dealt with under the Act.  If the Deputy asks me what is an agricultural tenant, I prefer to say I do not know.  I could not define an elephant, but I would know what agricultural land was if I saw it.  If he gave me a specific example I would probably be able to say whether it was an agricultural holding or not.  But to ask me for a definition of an agricultural holding or an agricultural tenant, would be to ask me something I could not answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2191" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>You have adroitly avoided Deputy White's point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I to understand that the Minister is definitely abandoning the idea of sending out notices which the Land Commission used send out, and is it his idea that annuitants throughout the country must be like a lot of athletes on the mark, ready to start when the pistol is fired?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The Land Commission do not intend to revert to the six day notice.  There is not a tenant purchaser throughout the country who purchased under these two Acts who does not know that his gale days are the first of June and the first of December. He has his receivable order; yet he wants another notice and he wants a thousand pounds of public money spent on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>How did the Land Commission arrive at £1,100 as a grant in aid of costs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an appropriation in aid of costs which they had to pay for legal proceedings instituted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>But they succeeded in the proceedings?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it appropriation in aid of costs which are received afterwards.  If they employ a solicitor they must pay him costs.  If he recovers the costs it comes in in aid of the Vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister explain why, in view of the precarious <Col N="2192" /> position of agriculture and the uncertain position of the future, there is such eagerness on the part of farmers to take upon themselves a greater burden of land?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is hardly a question which affects the Minister's department.</P>
      <P>Vote put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE" RHead="No. 45&mdash;ORDNANCE SURVEY">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE No. 45&mdash;ORDNANCE SURVEY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That a sum, not exceeding £36,201, be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1925, to defray the salaries and expenses of the Ordnance Survey and of Minor Services connected therewith.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think this Vote should not be allowed to pass through without an opportunity of examining it.  I would ask leave to move that Progress be reported.</P>
      <P>Progress ordered to be reported.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE." RHead="- DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>Progress reported, Committee to sit again to-morrow.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the Dáil until 10.30 a.m. to-morrow.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 10.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="DRIVER'S RATION ALLOWANCE">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DRIVER'S RATION ALLOWANCE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he has received a claim from Mr. J.T. Stafford, late No. 43611, Mechanical Transport, for ration allowance while acting as driver to the Command Claims Officer in Kerry, and, if so, when this claim will be dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret that there appears to be no trace of the receipt of any claim from Mr. Stafford. A form has now been sent to him, and on its return, duly completed, the claim will be considered as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - VISIT" RHead="OF MR. JOHN DEVOY">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - VISIT OF MR. JOHN DEVOY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the President if he has received any notification, or is aware, of the intended arrival on a visit from the United States of Mr. John Devoy, on Saturday next, 26th July, and whether in view of Mr. Devoy's great and special services in the cause of our country's independence, official cognisance will be taken of his visit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received notification of Mr. Devoy's visit, and have sent him a message of welcome by wireless.  I have also invited him to be the guest of the State during his stay. I feel that this is the least tribute which we could pay to Mr. Devoy, whose life has been spent in the country's service.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>