<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="18" Month="Jan" Year="1924" Vol="6" No="6" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 18 Eanáir 1924" DateEnglish="Friday, 18 January 1924" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="371">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="371" /> Do chuaidh an Leas-Cheann Comhairle i gceannas ar a 12 a chlog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - THE BOUNDARY COMMISSION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - THE BOUNDARY COMMISSION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="PADRAIG F. BAXTER PADRAIG F. BAXTER">
      <NameTxt>PADRAIG F. BAXTER</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the President if he will state what further steps have been taken by the Executive Council since the matter was last discussed by the Dáil to have the Boundary Commission set up; if he will say if any discussions are in progress with a view to having a conference, as reported in the English Press, if he will state how soon it is likely a definite step will be taken by the Government of the Saorstát in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>There is little to add to my previous statement on this matter.  Progress has been necessarily delayed by the recent General Election in England.  No discussions are taking place at the moment on the subject of the conference to which the Deputy alludes.  Invitations to a conference were issued by the present British Government and accepted by us, but no date has so far been fixed.  It is obviously impracticable to take further action until we know whether a change of Government will take place in England.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS. - MOTOR" RHead="HIRAGE&mdash;PRE-TRUCE CLAIMS AGAINST BRITISH GOVERNMENT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - MOTOR HIRAGE&mdash;PRE-TRUCE CLAIMS AGAINST BRITISH GOVERNMENT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="TADHG O MURCHADHA TADHG O MURCHADHA">
      <NameTxt>TADHG O MURCHADHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the President if he will state whether there is any machinery by which accounts amounting to £67 odd for motor hirage and damage to motor-cars incurred by British Auxiliary forces and due to Mr. Henry Smith, of Dunmanway, Co. Cork, who, without result, made several applications for payment to the British <Col N="372" /> authorities before their evacuation of the country, can be recovered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>In the absence of more detailed particulars of the account referred to, I am unable to give a satisfactory reply to the Deputy's question.  If he will arrange to have supplied to me a copy of the account, together with copies of any correspondence which passed between Mr. Smith and the British Authorities, I will take the matter up with a view of ascertaining whether anything can be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. MURPHY Mr. MURPHY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MURPHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be very glad to give the President the information.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS. -" RHead="EMPLOYMENT FOR WOUNDED EUROPEAN WAR SOLDIERS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - EMPLOYMENT FOR WOUNDED EUROPEAN WAR SOLDIERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major BRYAN COOPER Major BRYAN COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major BRYAN COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the President whether, in view of the fact that posts in Government employment are now being reserved for men who served in the National Army, he will give consideration to the claims of those men who were unable to join the National Army on account of wounds received in the European War and hold them eligible for employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The temporary reservation of posts in Government Departments for men who have given service with the National Forces is a necessary contribution towards relieving the unemployment immediately consequent on demobilisation, and I fear it would not be practicable to except any particular class of persons from the operations of the regulation. I do not think there are many cases of the type alluded to by the Deputy affected by it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>As there are very few cases, perhaps the President might see his way to do something in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnThomasNolan" hpid="Mr. NOLAN Mr. NOLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NOLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of that answer, are there not I.R.A. Volunteers who fought in the Anglo-Irish War? Have they not the first claim?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I should say before demobilisation started we concentrated upon those people referred to by the Deputy.  The services of one Deputy Minister were almost entirely <Col N="373" /> taken up with seeing that I.R.A. Volunteers got any positions vacant at the time.  Of course, it must be remembered that we have not got the dispensation of many posts, and that it is impossible to provide for all of these cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnThomasNolan" hpid="Mr. NOLAN Mr. NOLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NOLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite agree with you.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - MOTOR TAXES IN CO. GALWAY">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - MOTOR TAXES IN CO. GALWAY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCosgrave" hpid="SEAMUS MAC COSGAIR SEAMUS MAC COSGAIR">
      <NameTxt>SEAMUS MAC COSGAIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether he can state the amounts received from the County Galway in Motor Taxes during the past two financial years, and the amounts which have been remitted to the Galway County Council in respect of same for the purpose of road repairs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. Burke) MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. Burke)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>This question should have been addressed to me.  Inquiries are being made as to the amount collected and paid to the British Ministry of Transport in the financial year ended the 31st March, 1922.  The amount received in the year ended the 31st March, 1923, was £2,852 15s. 6d. The share paid to County Galway of the preliminary total advance of £100,000 was £4,540.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- DISTRESS IN HARE ISLAND, SKIBBEREEN">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - DISTRESS IN HARE ISLAND, SKIBBEREEN.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="TADHG O MURCHADHA TADHG O MURCHADHA">
      <NameTxt>TADHG O MURCHADHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether his attention has been drawn to the acute distress bordering on starvation in Hare Island, Skibbereen, Co. Cork, due to the failure of the fishing industry and other causes, and whether it is proposed to allocate any money for the relief of such distress, and, if so, whether he will favourably consider the project of giving a grant for the making of a new road between Whitehall and Cunmanore Point, in Hare Island, which would be of much convenience to the inhabitants and consequently alleviate the existing distress?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>In this case it does not appear that the Skibbereen Guardians have invoked the special powers of the County Council concerning exceptional <Col N="374" /> distress contained in Section 13 of the Local Government (Ireland) Act, 1898. There are no funds at my disposal which would enable a grant to be made for the new road proposed.  Further inquiries as to the position will be made through my Inspector locally.  It is not clear that in this matter any effort has been made to avail of the existing powers of the local Guardians or of the County Council.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- DISTRESS IN NORTH-WEST DONEGAL">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - DISTRESS IN NORTH-WEST DONEGAL.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EugeneDoherty" hpid="EOGHAN O DOCHARTAIGH EOGHAN O DOCHARTAIGH">
      <NameTxt>EOGHAN O DOCHARTAIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he has had a number of memorials from Parish Committees in North-West Donegal respecting the distress which exists in these districts, and if he would make a statement to the Dáil setting out the arrangements which his Department have in hand: (1) To meet the distress existing; (2) To provide grain and seed potatoes for these districts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>The representations referred to have been received.  A Roads Inspector has been specially detailed to visit the areas referred to in conjunction with the local Inspector, who has been keeping the Ministry informed as to the general position in Tirconaill.</P>
      <P>I am in communication with the Minister for Finance on the question of the sums available for the relief of distress as distinct from grants for road improvement and bridge schemes.  The Deputy may be assured that everything possible is being done, and that so soon as I am in a position to do so, very careful consideration will be given to his representations.  As to the provision of grain and seed potatoes, I am in correspondence with the Minister for Agriculture on the general question of reported shortages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMacBride" hpid="Mr. McBRIDE Mr. McBRIDE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McBRIDE</NameTxt>
      <P>As a supplementary question, I would like to ask the Minister for Local Government, if like distress prevails in West Galway and Mayo, whether the provisions intended to apply to Donegal in the carrying out of necessary works should also apply to Mayo and Galway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I have heard conflicting <Col N="375" /> reports on these various areas.  The whole matter will have my consideration at an early date.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - RATHNEW (WICKLOW) BRICK WORKS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - RATHNEW (WICKLOW) BRICK WORKS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="SÉAMUS EABHRÓID SÉAMUS EABHRÓID">
      <NameTxt>SÉAMUS EABHRÓID</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he is aware that a Brick Works at Rathnew, Co. Wicklow, has been closed for some time, and that the expense of erecting houses in Co. Wicklow is thereby much increased owing to cost of transport of bricks from Dublin, and if he is prepared to take steps with a view to having the works re-opened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMcGrath" hpid="MINISTER FOR INDUSTRY AND COMMERCE (Mr. J. McGrath) Joseph McGrath">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER FOR INDUSTRY AND COMMERCE (Mr. J. McGrath)</NameTxt>
      <P>At the present time, nearly all brick works in An Saorstát are closed down, owing, I am informed, to the higher cost of using brick for building purposes as compared with the cost of cement work. One works in Dublin has over 5,000,000 bricks in stock at the moment.</P>
      <P>The proprietors of the Rathnew Brick Works are, I understand, prepared to re-open their works, provided an assurance is given them that local labour will accept a wage which will permit of the industry being conducted on economic lines, and that a sufficient demand can be obtained for bricks produced at these works.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>And that sufficient profit can be made out of the industries. Is that it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>As one connected with that industry, may I point out that at the present moment the company owns three cement works, and that two of them are closed down.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - CIVIC GUARD SHOT AT BELTURBET">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - CIVIC GUARD SHOT AT BELTURBET.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCosgrave" hpid="SÉAMUS MAC COSGAIR SÉAMUS MAC COSGAIR">
      <NameTxt>SÉAMUS MAC COSGAIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state whether the soldier who fired the shot which killed the Civic Guard, Michael Lyons, at Belturbet, Co. Cavan, on the night of the 15th August, 1923, has yet been tried, and, if so, with what result, and, if not, when he will be tried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>The soldier has not yet been <Col N="376" /> tried.  As regards the last part of the question I would refer the Deputy to the Minister for Home Affairs for information.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- ARREST AT BALLYNACALLY (CLARE)">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - ARREST AT BALLYNACALLY (CLARE).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár) PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)">
      <NameTxt>PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that Patrick O'Shea, Ballynacally, Co. Clare, was arrested on the morning of the 23rd November, 1923, by the Military in connection with an alleged attack on a soldier of the National Army, and that he was detained for a fortnight before he was handed over to the Gárda Síochána, to ask whether the case came up for hearing before the District Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The detention of Mr. O'Shea was authorised by a warrant given by me under the Public Safety Act.  The case against him was heard before the District Court on the 20th December.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="Mr. PATRICK HOGAN (Clare) Mr. PATRICK HOGAN (Clare)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. PATRICK HOGAN (Clare)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that the State produced no evidence at the District Court, and that the District Judge refused informations?</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS. -" RHead="BALTINGLASS SHOOTING&mdash;QUESTION OF COMPENSATION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - BALTINGLASS SHOOTING&mdash;QUESTION OF COMPENSATION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="AODH O CÚLACHÁIN AODH O CÚLACHÁIN">
      <NameTxt>AODH O CÚLACHÁIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that Joseph Allison, Brannockstown, Harristown, Co. Kildare, has not yet received compensation in respect of the death of his son, Patrick Allison, shot dead at Graney Cross, Baltinglass, on the 24th October, 1922, and whether payment will be expedited, as previously promised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The necessary formalities are not yet completed. They are being expedited as much as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- HORSE INJURED BY MILITARY TENDER">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - HORSE INJURED BY MILITARY TENDER.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="TADHG O MURCHADHA TADHG O MURCHADHA">
      <NameTxt>TADHG O MURCHADHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that a horse, the property of Jeremiah O'Leary, Dunbeacon, Dorrus, was injured in a collision with a military tender driven by Sergeant <Col N="377" /> Duffy, of the National Army, at Abbey Road, Bantry, Co. Cork, on 19th May, 1923; whether an inquiry was subsequently held, at which O'Leary was present and where he was informed that the findings were being forwarded to Cork; whether he will state what the findings were, and when O'Leary, who is a poor man, will be compensated for the loss he has sustained?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>A Court of Enquiry exonerated the driver of the military car from all blame.  The question of compensating Mr. O'Leary is under consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - CO. ROSCOMMON SHOOTING">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - CO. ROSCOMMON SHOOTING.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCosgrave" hpid="SEAMUS MAC COSGAIR SEAMUS MAC COSGAIR">
      <NameTxt>SEAMUS MAC COSGAIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state whether the soldier who fired the shot which killed Peter Barrett, at Coolgarvey, Co. Roscommon, on the 28th September, 1923, has yet been tried, and, if so, with what result, and, if not, when he will be tried?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The soldier has not yet been tried.  As regards the last part of the question I would refer the Deputy to the Minister for Home Affairs for information.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS. -" RHead="MILITARY ENGINEER'S DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - MILITARY ENGINEER'S DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether any claim for dependent's allowance has now been received from Volunteer Michael Sherlock, No. 48992, Engineering Corps, and whether any decision has been reached in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Volunteer Sherlock's claim for Dependent's Allowance was rejected on the grounds that there is no evidence to show that he contributed towards the maintenance of his home for some years before enlistment.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS. - TALLAGHT" RHead="MINE EXPLOSION. COMPENSATION OF INJURED SOLDIER">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - TALLAGHT MINE EXPLOSION.   COMPENSATION OF INJURED SOLDIER.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether an application has been received from Mr. T. Green, Convent road, Dalkey, for a disability pension in respect of injuries received <Col N="378" /> when blown up by a mine at Tallaght, when Assistant Quartermaster, 24th Infantry Battalion, and whether he can state what decision has been arrived at in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The receipt of a claim for pension from Mr. Green cannot be traced.  He was found medically fit prior to being discharged from the Army as &ldquo;time expired.&rdquo;  In view of this a claim can scarcely be entertained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of that answer, is the Minister aware that Private Green was in hospital for four months and subsequently employed on light duty until his discharge, and might the finding of medical fitness be reviewed in view of these facts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>If a claim for pension is made those facts will be reviewed. My information is that it cannot be traced.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - CAHIR ARMY ACCOUNT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA.&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - CAHIR ARMY ACCOUNT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="MICHEAL O hIFEARNAIN MICHEAL O hIFEARNAIN">
      <NameTxt>MICHEAL O hIFEARNAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state what is the cause of the delay in connection with the payment of an account furnished by Mr. Patrick Franklin, Cahir, Co. Tipperary, amounting to £24 15s. 6d., for hire of motors by the Military and sundry purchases by the Military in connection with motor transport; whether he is aware that this account was furnished last May and is still unpaid, to ask when payment will be made?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no record at Headquarters of the receipt of Mr. Franklin's claim.  If it is sent with full details to the Chief Claims Officer, Portobello Barracks, it will have due attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="QUESTION ON ADJOURNMENT. - DISTRESS IN" RHead="TIRCONAILL AND FLOODING IN TIPPERARY">
    <Title>QUESTION ON ADJOURNMENT. - DISTRESS IN TIRCONAILL AND FLOODING IN TIPPERARY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to give notice that, on the adjournment, I will call the attention of the responsible Minister to the present deplorable state of distress prevailing in Tirconaill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to give notice that I would raise, on the adjournment, the important question of the flooding of certain towns in Tipperary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a more important matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that the Minister for Local Government has already given an assurance that the distress in Donegal is having <Col N="383" /> his serious attention, I think that matter should be taken as having been disposed of.  This matter of the flooding in Tipperary, and elsewhere, of the Barrow and the Suir, is of very great importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>May I suggest that Deputy White would add to his motion for the distress in Tirconaill the words, &ldquo;and other places.&rdquo;  That would cover both.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWhite" hpid="Mr. WHITE Mr. WHITE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WHITE</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="QUESTION ON ADJOURNMENT. - HOUSING (BUILDING" RHead="FACILITIES) BILL, 1924.&mdash;FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>QUESTION ON ADJOURNMENT. - HOUSING (BUILDING FACILITIES) BILL, 1924.&mdash;FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am moving for permission to introduce a Bill to facilitate the provision of dwelling houses, to deal with the question of providing suitable dwelling accommodation in various urban and rural districts throughout the country, to provide for a Government subsidy in connection with such provision, and for associating local authorities generally with this project.  The general lines have been indicated on a former occasion, so I will just run through them rather briefly.  It is proposed to provide a sum of £300,000 for this Bill.  The Minister for Finance has agreed, after very careful consideration, to make that sum available.  It is a very considerable sum having regard to the many claims and services which have to be provided for out of the revenue of the State.  The general proposal is, with a view to alleviating unemployment in so far as that is possible, to provide houses for the working classes at prices which, it is hoped, they will be able to pay, and, generally, to give some help towards business.  We have already indicated, on more than one occasion, that this problem is one which will require help from every section of the community.  Help is required, if this particular Bill is to be made a success, from those who come under the term &ldquo;employers&rdquo; and those embraced in the term &ldquo;employees.&rdquo;  We would say that if there be a real effort made by the two bodies embraced in those two particular terms, there ought to be a very considerable improvement in the provision of houses in every part of the country.  Unfortunately, there <Col N="384" /> is scarcely a bigger problem affecting the whole country than this question of the provision of suitable accommodation for the working classes.  It is, perhaps, the one particular service which has become most costly since the war.  In the pre-war period, the question of the provision of houses at an economic price, was very nearly a line ball.  The difference which ought to be made up, either by the Government or local authorities, between the cost of the house and the price that the person who gets it is able to pay, was very small, but since the war an enormous difference has occurred between the cost of the house and the price the person is able to pay for it.  That, to some extent, is the object of this Bill&mdash; to seek to bridge that difference and to bring home to everybody concerned the necessity for arriving, sooner if possible, later certainly, at a point at which the bridge will not be necessary, and at which the provision of houses will be the same as any service or business. Then it will be done at a price which people can afford to pay.  It is, as I said, proposed to associate local authorities with this great work.  In the first place, a very big effort will have to be contributed by every local authority where these houses are built. In the first year, the houses will get a remission of 95 per cent. of the rates, that is to say, that the house, having been built, will only bear one-twentieth of the rates struck in that area for the first year.  And in the second year 90 per cent. of a remission will be allowed, so that only one-tenth of the rates will require to be paid.  That process will be continued until the twentieth year, when the house will have to bear the full rates and be in the same position as any other house not built under this Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is also provided that local authorities are empowered to provide sites, and in certain cases to provide loans to the amount necessary.  It is possible, after the Bill is passed, that a case may be made that builders have not got the capital necessary to go on with this work.  I think it will be possible to arrange that local authorities can advance money, and that it can be paid on the architect's certificate.  In that <Col N="385" /> way capital should not be a hindrance if the money be not available, and so far as the private builders are concerned, the local authorities will be able to help them.  It must be remembered that that is going a long distance, because from the returns which have been furnished to me by the Minister for Local Government, it would appear that a large sum is due by local authorities to banks on overdrafts. They have not got in the rates and, generally speaking, their financial position is far from satisfactory.  A real and determined effort ought to be made to reduce the very heavy burdens which the rates are imposing, and have imposed, within the last couple of years on business generally throughout the country.</P>
    <P>The number of houses which, it is hoped, may be constructed through this Bill will be something in the neighbourhood of three thousand, and it is proposed to make available from the sum of £300,000 varying sums according to the size of the house and according to the provision of sewers and water mains.  There will be set out in the schedule the various subsidies in each case, and they vary from £50 for a three-roomed house to £100 for a five-roomed house.  It is also provided that a fixed sum will be put on the price that the house must be sold for.  In other words, it is really intended by the operation of this Bill that the houses will be sold to the persons for whom they are intended.  A case is occasionally made&mdash;I do not know whether there is a great deal of exaggeration in it&mdash;that the houses provided by local authorities for the working classes are not let to or sold to the working classes, and during my own experience with one local authority I should say that in the main there was very little truth in it.  They were, in the vast majority of cases, let to the people for whom they were intended, and in a great number of cases very much higher prices could have been got in the open market if the houses had been sold in a free market.  During the period in which I had some experience with the Housing Committee of the Dublin Corporation, the policy was to let houses to the families which <Col N="386" /> had the largest number in them.  There was a list made out, and a very large family was practically certain of getting one of those houses.  This problem of housing is, as I have said, one of the most complicated we have to face, and one for which there is no real solution. I mean that there are many methods of solving it or of approaching its solution, but to say that in a few sentences it is possible to say &ldquo;this is the way in which it can be done&rdquo; will be admitted by any persons who have had anything to do with it to be impossible.  If we take the position at the present time, where some people say that there is little use in putting up a proposal of this sort, because the working classes cannot afford to pay three hundred or four hundred or four hundred and fifty pounds for a house, a popular public speaker could make a great play upon that, but the fact is that if one only deals with the class unable to pay the sum of £300 or £400 or £450, and that houses are provided for that class, a very serious burden falls on the shoulders of the ratepayers and taxpayers of this country, which they are not at the moment ready to bear.  I would suggest that in these lean years there are numbers of people comprising the term &ldquo;working class&rdquo; capable of paying these particular sums, who do not require such assistance to the same extent as some of their less fortunate brethren.  You must come in now and provide for them when the prices are high, getting out of them the maximum they can afford to pay, getting out of the State the maximum it can afford to pay and out of the local authorities the maximum they can afford to pay, and having provided for all, getting more towards an economic position in the construction of those houses.  The burden on the State, on the local authorities, and on the persons who are not able to pay this big price will be relatively less according as the market becomes normal and conditions improve. It is unnecessary to say anything more, except that, in considering this and other questions which are particularly complex, there has always been a danger of taking one order in the community, stretching their point of view, and criticising any other and vice versa. <Col N="387" /> This problem will not be solved if we confine ourselves to what might be called a sectional discussion of it.  It is too big, too complex, too varied, and will require the help of every order in the community and every citizen to make it possible to solve it.</P>
    <P>During something like 50 years, I think, the total number of houses provided in urban districts throughout the country numbered only 10,000.  Since the Treaty was passed, something like 2,000 or 3,000 houses have been provided. That is a very considerable contribution during the period, at a time when prices were absolutely prohibitive. The State is unable to contribute the amount which it was thought wise after the Treaty to make available for this particular service.  It will, I think, be admitted on all sides that it was a prohibitive and impossible amount.</P>
    <P>We are now approaching the subject from another angle.  We are endeavouring to get private enterprise to give some assistance towards the solving of the problem.  Local authorities, from their very nature, must bear expenses and charges which house-building cannot bear and which, as far as the people are concerned, simply postpones the day when a man can have his own house, and get it at a rent that he can possibly meet out of his wages.  From an examination of the problem as far as the City of Dublin is concerned it was my impression, when rents were in the neighbourhood of 6/- or 7/- per week, that while owned by private individuals these houses might have been let at 1/6, or possibly 2/- per week lower rent.  The main consideration in this problem is the vast number of people who have to be provided with houses.  It is a very great work.  Very great discontent arises from the fact that people are housed in unsanitary areas, and there is very little attractiveness in the home where conditions are so dismal and so forbidding.  The State, in making this large sum of money available for this service, believes that there will be a return in better citizenship and in appreciation by the people who will get these houses that the State is not unmindful of its obligations towards its citizens.  I formally <Col N="388" /> move the First Reading of the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Dáil will welcome the evidence which the introduction of this Bill gives that the Government is taking serious notice of the need for making provision for houses.  I think the Dáil, too, will acknowledge the difficulties in the treatment of the question, the varied views, the varied principles at work, in arriving at some satisfactory conclusion as to, at least, one of the methods whereby the problem may be solved.  The President has suggested that there are innumerable proposals, and that it may not be possible to solve it on one line alone.  I think the difficulty will be apparent to anybody who has heard what the President has said, in view of the contradictions that are contained in his statement&mdash;the apparent desire to ride two horses going in different directions at the same time, namely, the attempt generally to drive down wages and, at the same time, arrive at a conclusion which means that houses can be built and let at economic rents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that the President, and the Dáil, if they study this matter closely, will arrive at the conclusion that most students have arrived at, that the housing of the people is one of the services which will not henceforth be economic, in the usually accepted sense, unless in the remote possibility that wages will always be considered irrespective of rentals, and that whatever the ruling rent in a district may be, it will be added to the normal rate of wages.  We cannot drive down wages and, at the same time, maintain or raise rents. However, this is only one aspect.  The other apparent contradiction in the President's statement is where he put forward, I think, as an example of what should be followed, that large families should get the preference in the selection of tenants for such houses, or as purchasers of such houses, and, at the same time, suggested that there should be a bounty of the kind for houses of three rooms.  A large family in a three-roomed house is not a prospect which we should contemplate with pleasure.  I am not saying this because I want to <Col N="389" /> throw cold water upon a scheme which has not yet been placed before us, but just to remind the Dáil of the difficulty in the way of treating this problem as though it were one that could be treated as an ordinary commercial proposition, which is the ideal that the President seems to have in mind.  I welcome the evidence of the intention of the Government to deal seriously with this problem, and shall be glad to examine the Bill when it is printed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. JOHN GOOD Mr. JOHN GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHN GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>One was glad to hear from the President that it is the intention to deal with this difficult question in the near future.  I think we all agree that the lines he has forecasted are those that should be tried in dealing with the problem.  Deputy Johnson has pointed out some of the difficulties that lie in the path of those anxious to deal with a problem of this character, but while he objects on the one hand to a reduction of wages or to a desire to get a reduction of wages, in dealing with this problem he has not expressed any opinion at all on the question of wages as they stand at the moment in the building industry.  I have already expressed views on more than one occasion in the Dáil on this important matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>So have I.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>And I think it is generally accepted that the wages in the building industry at the moment in Dublin and in Ireland generally are at a very much higher figure than they should be.  I have also gone so far as to say that as this possibly stands as one of the difficulties in the way of housing that, as far as I was concerned, any interest I could use in connection with the industry would be used towards effecting a reduction in a reasonable way.  I asked Deputy Johnson, as he has a considerable influence with those engaged in the industry, that he would use that influence in the same direction.  I am sure that a combination of that character would do very useful work in connection with the reduction of the costs and rents of houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Apart from that problem, he referred to another interesting aspect.  It is one <Col N="390" /> that I think should have some attention&mdash;the question of the size of the houses.  Possibly there is something to be said for his argument that it might be desirable to build larger houses than those with three rooms, but seeing that the problem at the moment is, to some extent, uneconomic, and that rents, even as a result of dealing with housing, are possibly higher than we would like to see them, yet, in view of these facts, it is necessary, in order to keep the figures within reasonable bounds, that the size of a house should be reduced as far as possible.  I think if the Government would, as far as it possibly can, confine itself to the building of smaller houses until conditions would be improved, they would thereby help the larger number.  While it is undesirable to house large families in three-roomed houses, I think Deputy Johnson and all the other members of the Dáil will agree that it is infinitely more desirable to put such families in three-roomed modern comfortable houses than to see them housed as they are now in too many cases in single rooms in tenements.  I would urge that that should be very largely the policy of the Government, to build the largest number of three-roomed houses possible.</P>
    <P>Another argument that might be adduced, and I do not want to deal with this subject at any length now, is in connection with the building of the smaller-sized houses.  As one who has had something to do and who has had some experience of housing under a local authority, we find that even where agreements have been made with tenants that there is to be no subletting in a very large number of the larger houses&mdash;with more than three rooms&mdash;there is subletting.  In fact, subletting has gone so far as to become profiteering.  Tenants who get these houses confine themselves and their families to one or two of the five rooms and set the other rooms at exorbitant rents, and practically live on the income they receive in that way.  That is a matter that ought to be borne in mind in connection with housing.  A deputation that attended from the tenants under a local authority that I happen to be connected with urged very <Col N="391" /> strongly on that local authority that they should confine their efforts to the building of three-roomed houses.  As a result of that I attended with a deputation before the Ministry some months ago, and I urged instead of limiting the smaller type of house that they should do all in their power to encourage the building of that type of house, rather than the larger one.  I hope those particular aspects of the problem will have the attention of the Ministry.  In connection with the necessary reduction of wages, if Deputy Johnson is still willing to do what he can towards effecting that necessary reduction, as far as I am concerned I will do anything I can to assist in that direction.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of personal explanation, may I say in reply to Deputy Good, that he asked me the question before and I gave him a distinct answer which repeated what I had formerly offered in the Dáil, to use every possible influence with every workman in the country to facilitate the production of houses, and every other commodity, to the utmost extent, I the Government and the employers would come down with a proposition that they were willing to use their offices, their ability, and their organising capacity, on the basis of payment for services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. J. CONLAN Mr. J. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to impress upon the President the urgent necessity for inserting a provision in the Bill that contractors would be bound to use Irish materials as far as would be possible.  In the Athy district of my constituency several brick works were in operation up to a comparatively short time ago, and indeed I believe one of them is still in operation.  These works turned out the very best class of brick, in fact most of the old squares in Dublin were built of Athy brick, and that will go to show their durability. There is the precedent of a Government taking action in this direction in the fact that the British Government, while building the Curragh Camp, took over land in the vicinity, and started the making of bricks there, and there was not a single brick used in the construction of the Curragh Camp but was <Col N="392" /> manufactured in the district.  That was due, in a great measure, to the action of the then Irish Party in Westminster, who urged upon the Government that, in fairness, they should give the local industries a chance in that way.  I would like to bring this matter under the attention of the President in order that provision may be made to give these local industries a chance of reviving.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. P. HUGHES Mr. P. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know if this is the proper time to discuss matters that may, or may not, be in the Bill, as we have not seen it yet, but there is one aspect of the case put forward, I think by Deputy Good, with which I cannot agree.  I chance to have some little knowledge of house-building in urban areas, and, for my part, I would not favour the building of a large number of three-roomed houses.  I think that the smallest house that should be built for a family should be a four-roomed house.  Perhaps you might have a moderate number, I should say a very small number, if any, of three-roomed houses to accommodate people with families.  I know it is true, despite the terms put into the letting agreements of these houses, that people have let a room, or perhaps two rooms in houses.  But what are the facts?  The reason for that is the shortage of houses and people were obliged, in order to get shelter for themselves, to pay exorbitant prices.  If there were a number of houses which people could go into, they would not have to pay these rents, and it would not be profitable for people to let these rooms, and would keep them for themselves.  I believe that if houses are built under the Government scheme a condition should be made that people should not be allowed to sub-let, as they have done during the past few years in the abnormal conditions that prevailed.  As far as the statement about Irish manufactures is concerned, I believe that the Government would be wise in seeing that as far as possible all materials put into any house for which they give a subsidy should be of Irish manufacture, thereby relieving unemployment in the Saorstát.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>There is only one question I would like to ask <Col N="393" /> the President with regard to the Bill at this stage, and it refers to the third section of the Motion before the House. It is with regard to the phrase, &ldquo;to ensure a supply of building material at reasonable prices.&rdquo;  I do not know whether the President might not consider, seeing that he has gone somewhat fully into the provisions of the Bill in other respects, indicating what would be the general provisions of the Bill in that very important respect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know whether I said that in dealing with the housing problem there is scarcely any theory that any person will put forward that cannot be disproved.  In other words, one's experience in connection with housing is varied.  What Deputy Good said is quite correct; what Deputy Hughes said is perfectly correct, but the two things are absolutely different.  The truth is that one thing happens in one part of the country and the other in another part.  One may happen under one housing scheme, and an entirely different thing may happen under another, and that is why I mentioned that the problem was very complex, and it is a problem which lends itself to oratory on public platforms where one may claim that every man must have a six-roomed house, a bathroom, and the appurtenances which make for easy living and comfort. I recollect some time ago, when we were dealing with this problem in Local Government, and I was the Minister for Local Government, some local authorities denounced us in all the moods and tenses as a reactionary Government, because we would not allow them to put in bathrooms.  I suggest that people who get houses may put in bathrooms if they like, but I am against giving bathrooms for one-hundredth of the community, while the other ninety-nine hundredths are without housing accommodation.  Housing reformers will tell you that whatever you do, do it perfectly, but a very strange thing is that they have been talking for 20 or 30 years and they have not given us any example of the perfect thing yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One can only deal with this subject gradually and, I should say, constructively, benefiting by any mistakes made, <Col N="394" /> trying to improve on them, and gradually reducing, year by year, the number of persons who require houses by the provision of other houses.  I do know that what Deputy Good has said is perfectly correct.  I have known and heard of cases where four-roomed houses were provided, and were sub-let to people who were paying more than the rent. I know of other cases.  I have seen applications from persons having very small incomes during the peak wages period.  I saw one case in which I think a family with £3 a week coming in to them offered to put down the whole of the money to buy a house, and I saw a return of a family having £17 5s. 0d. coming in and offering £2 for the key, and then expecting to get the house for one-third the cost price. I am sure nobody would stand for that. I do not know that Deputy Johnson meant to do me an injustice when he said I made two rather mixed statements. I thought I had made it perfectly clear that I had admitted the force of one, and could not deny the force of the other.  In other words, that large families ought to be provided with houses.  If you concentrate on that you will do nothing, and the number of these that you will be able to build would be so small and costly that very little work would be done.  What is being aimed at in this Bill is, in the first place, an endeavour to provide employment, and, in the second place, to get houses at the least cost to the State, the Local Authority, and the individual getting the house.  If people with large families can possibly take or buy a house, they should and will get the preference, and every possible facility would be afforded them to get houses.  But that method of dealing with it by which one goes in for providing economic housing accommodation is not possible when prices are highest, as far as my examination of the problem goes, and I have not been able to find anyone who can show how that particular method could be made successful.  The Deputy said that I was attempting to ride two horses, and that there was an attempt to drive down wages, and arrive at a conclusion that houses could be built at an economic price.  What is the fact?</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="395" /> On this question of wages and housing very great stress has been laid by practically everyone, but that, to my mind, is not really the question at all, but the value received.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.  Organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no use in saying that we insist on a man getting £3 or £5 a week for doing no work. Organisation is not confined to the one side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.  We are trying to improve ours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Precisely, but the real point in this question of the provision of houses is not wages so much as the other question, that of output.  There is an opportunity at any rate as far as this Bill is concerned afforded the orders I have mentioned of showing the best that is in them, for this particular service.  It is not a business proposition in the ordinary sense.  There is too much of the better side of humanity called on to settle this question than in an ordinary business transaction. There is a real crying need on the part of the majority of the working classes for these houses.  I believe that is admitted both on the employer's and the employee's side, and I am satisfied that while the employees have a good deal to say for their side of the case, that the real, serious effort should come from them, because they are to get the maximum benefit out of the success of a scheme of this sort.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>May I explain that when I was referring to wages I was not referring merely to wages in the building trade, but to the attempt to drive down wages in general.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The only attitude I have taken up on the general question of wages is that there ought to be value for value received, and that there is no use in trying to keep a standard which does not give value to anybody, and which, in the long run, costs the people affected very much more than if we were to arrive at a time when we were getting value for <Col N="396" /> whatever sum was paid, no matter what it was.  I calculate that something like 12,000,000 bricks would be required to construct the houses which we have in contemplation under this Bill.  I think that would, to some extent, meet one point of the case made by Deputy Conlan, and I think would help to some extent to reduce the over-stock that there is in one of the building concerns in Dublin.  There is also, of course, the ordinary reconstruction which it is hoped will begin with the spring of this year, that is, the reconstruction of the houses that have been destroyed.  It is proposed, in the Bill, to take power to purchase or manufacture building materials.  I do not expect that there would be any activity with regard to the manufacture, but there may be with regard to the other. There is, I understand&mdash;I have only heard it in the last couple of weeks&mdash; considerable activity in the slate quarries in the Saorstát, and I should say in that, and in the provision of bricks or other building material in the country, efforts will be made to ensure that Irish manufactured materials will get a fair show under the operations of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the President to explain, when he said &ldquo;powers will be taken to purchase,&rdquo; whether it will be by the Local Government Department or the Local Authorities or by whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not remember the details of that, but I will be able to answer the Deputy on the Second Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we are all very gratified to find that the time has come when the Government is prepared to move in this very important question of providing houses.  There is one aspect of the case that I would like to put before the Dáil.  It is that in connection with the administration and development of this it would be very desirable if the Government would pay due attention to the need for enlisting the sympathy of companies, and of the commercial community generally, in this very urgent matter. I know myself that the business concerns have recognised their responsibilities in this matter, which they have <Col N="397" /> not been able to fulfil owing to the uneconomic conditions in which they were called upon to contribute in connection with this housing question. Recently the Minister for Finance came before the country requiring a loan of money, and very sensibly, I think, one of the first things he did was to enlist the enthusiastic support of the business community as a whole. I suggest to the President and the Executive that the precedent established by the Minister for Finance might be very profitably employed in connection with the housing question, now that we have arrived at a point when the Government recognises the necessity of contributing.  May we hope that Labour has arrived at the point when they also&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be better for the Deputy not to raise controversial matters at this moment.  The President should, properly speaking, have wound up the debate, but I did not like to prevent the Deputy from saying a few words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall bow to your ruling, and will not continue, because anything further I might have to say would be ruled out under that ruling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>If I might intervene, I would suggest that a little latitude might be allowed on this subject. It is one of much complexity, involving in its treatment the kind of thing that the Deputy has in his mind without arousing any bitterness.  I think Deputies opposite would not take any objection to having the subject discussed in the manner in which the Deputy was discussing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that Deputy Johnson would want to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Really what I was trying to develop was not an argumentative side of the question at all; I was really putting forward the need for the co-operation of all parties in connection with this matter as one of great importance, and as being a matter of great urgent public national importance.  That was all I wanted to say.  I did not want to commit Deputy Johnson to reply in an argumentative <Col N="398" /> sense, and I was only asking for the co-operation of all parties, which I think is apparent, as a necessity.  That was really what I was urging the Dáil to take into consideration in the initial stages of this Bill.</P>
      <P>Question: &ldquo;That leave be given to bring in the Bill&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the Second Reading, I expect the Bill will be circulated by Tuesday, and I propose to put it down for its second stage on Thursday.  If that is not sufficient time we can extend it to Friday, but in the hope that it will be ready for circulation on Tuesday, I will ask leave to take the second stage on Thursday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask that the regular procedure be followed and that whatever notice is required should be given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Four days, as far as I know, is what is required, and I am giving five.</P>
      <P>Ordered that the second stage be taken on Thursday, the 24th January.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="QUESTION ON ADJOURNMENT. - FISCAL INQUIRY" RHead="COMMITTEE'S REPORT&mdash;ADJOURNED DEBATE RESUMED">
    <Title>QUESTION ON ADJOURNMENT. - FISCAL INQUIRY COMMITTEE'S REPORT&mdash;ADJOURNED DEBATE RESUMED.</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That the Dáil is of opinion that the Government in considering the fiscal problem should have regard not merely to the admittedly restricted view of the matter taken by the Fiscal Inquiry Committee as indicated in their final Report, but should examine the problem in the broadest possible aspect&mdash;due regard being taken of all the factors affecting the general well-being of the Saorstát.&mdash; (Mr. Seán Milroy).</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>In dealing with this motion of Deputy Milroy's, I desire, first of all, to pay my tribute of admiration to the very great industry, hard work and research which he has shown in preparing his statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeNicolls" hpid="Mr. GEORGE NICHOLLS Mr. GEORGE NICHOLLS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GEORGE NICHOLLS</NameTxt>
      <P>took the Chair at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="399" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I might say that Deputy Milroy has undoubtedly treated the matter in the broadest possible aspect. He has travelled about 4,000 miles in his effort to give effect to his proposal, and I think it rather a pity that he found it necessary to call forth his powers of invective, when speaking about the members of the Committee, all of whom were elected by the Government, in the strong terms which he employed.  He refers to their report as being &ldquo;malignantly misleading.&rdquo; He talks about their having put industrial representatives in the dock, and appears to have a very strong objection to the fact that certain people are professors. Personally, I do not hold any brief for the members of the Committee, but, in all fairness to them, I think it must be admitted that, at any rate, they have no vested interests to serve, and that by the very nature of their calling they would, in the ordinary course, present a fair and judicial report of their proceedings.  They had nothing to gain by doing otherwise that I can see.  If you had this Committee constituted by prominent business men, industrial people associated with industry in general, there would always be the danger that you would have a certain amount of bias in approaching the various problems.  Another matter in this connection is that whilst Deputy Milroy indulged in very eloquent generalities&mdash;he reviewed the fiscal problems from every conceivable corner of the globe&mdash;these gentlemen had before them witnesses taken from Ireland who had every opportunity of representing the Irish point of view, and that whatever we may think of international economics and the fiscal problems of other countries, the particular matter that concerns us is the Irish outlook. Of course, this controversy of Free Trade and Protection is a very old one, and it is a matter about which a great deal can be said on both sides.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A great many people hold that, by the mere application of tariffs, Ireland will be straight away converted into an agricultural and commercial paradise. For my part I have given a good deal of study to the matter, and I am not one of these people.  I have, while preserving a fairly open mind, been always <Col N="400" /> willing to hear concrete arguments as opposed to generalities, and I must say that I have a very strong inclination towards a Free Trade policy for this country, at any rate for a little while. One of the usual arguments used in connection with this controversy by the Protectionist protagonists is the analogy of other countries, and the country most often referred to as being a country which has developed its industries to a very great extent under Protection, is America.  But it ought to be remembered, first of all, in comparing Ireland with America, that Ireland is a relatively microscopic geographical unit, whereas America is a mighty continent. The State of Texas alone, in America, is bigger than England and Ireland put together, and America is really a conglomeration of countries. America, within its own territory, possesses the biggest Free Trade area in the world, with an immense population to buy its own products.  America possesses within its own shores every conceivable type of climate, soil, mineral wealth, and every natural advantage. America is a country that can afford to adopt any fiscal system it pleases, and still it can become a great country. Deputy Sears, and I think also Deputy Milroy, tried to establish the case that the great growth of commercial America, and of America generally, was owing to the fact that it had imposed tariffs on the products from other countries which go into it.</P>
    <P>In my view that is a big question.  I think the development of America was due to a great many other causes. First of all, America is a new country. Only a generation ago millions of acres of virgin soil were being ploughed up there, and that is going on still.  They have enormous resources of oil, which supply half the world.  They have enormous resources of coal and enormous resources of iron, and they possess gold and many other natural advantages, which Ireland does not possess.  Consequently, I maintain that the analogy with America cannot be sustained.  Now, people who refer to other countries where tariffs are prevalent; very conveniently overlook the great free trade country of England; and, after all.  England, in proportion to its size and population, with all its <Col N="401" /> faults, and I suppose they are many, still remains the greatest commercial country in the world, in proportion to its size and population.  Yet, that is a prosperity which grew up directly under a free trade system.  The greatest era of commercial activity in the history of commercial England corresponded with the repeal of the Corn Laws from the time of Cobden on. That is certainly a fact which must be taken note of.  Of course, the greatest industry which England has is the shipping industry, and one of the things that America lost by her policy of tariffs was her shipping industry. I do not say that she lost it, but it was never developed to anything like the same extent that the English mercantile marine developed.  In pre-war days, at all events&mdash;I am not in a position to state the figures now&mdash;nearly all American coast traffic was carried in English ships, because owing to the very high price of the necessary materials that had to come in for the building of the ships, America was not able to compete with England in the manufacture of ships.</P>
    <P>Deputy Milroy considers that the imposition of tariffs would be a first-class cure for unemployment.  I might remind Deputy Milroy that many and many a time the great country of America, upon which he depends for an illustration of his policy of protection, had very great epidemics of unemployment and very great trade depression.  They had Bank and Stock Exchange failures and general commercial decadence at different times in America.  At the moment it is true that American trade is booming, but I do not at all agree that it is due to the policy of tariffs.  Then, to get away from other countries, and to come back to our own country of Ireland, I must say that the first thing we have to do is to define protection and what precisely protection means. I think, in a very few words, protection means the keeping away of competition. The keeping away of competition means, of course, that those who are left get better prices for the goods.  If, as is sometimes argued, the imposition of tariffs will not increase the price of an article, where does <Col N="402" /> protection come in?  I fail to see it, and in this connection, further, we have this to decide when you are discussing a question of protection&mdash;are you going to propose to protect the individual manufacturer or trader, or do you propose to protect the whole community?  My conception of my duty, as a member of the Dáil, is that rather than advance the views of any one trade or industry, it is my duty, as far as lies in my power, to look after the interests of the whole community. It is quite easy, we will say for the sake of argument, for a man who makes bottles, or bricks, or anything else, to put on such a tariff as will exclude all external competition.  That would be a very excellent thing, if you regard it purely from the point of view of putting money in the pocket of an individual brickmaker, or bottlemaker, or bootmaker, as the case might be.</P>
    <P>Then, there is a great deal said about what is called the incidence of taxation. Volumes have been written by people, who call themselves political economists, on this matter, and I do not propose to weary the Dáil with a long dissertation on this subject.  If you have to put on a tariff you have to consider who pays it.  The advocates of tariff say it is paid by the person who imports the stuff.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>resumed the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>However, it is rather too big a question to decide how much of the tariff is paid, first of all, by the importer from the other side; secondly, by the Shipping Company who carries the goods; thirdly, by the wholesale merchant on this side; fourthly, by the wholesale trader; and, finally, by the retail trader.  My own view is a very clear one on this matter.  I have a certain amount of knowledge of commercial methods.  There are such things as rings in commercial communities, and I am afraid the general tendency, if a tariff is put on, will be to pass it along to the consumer; and I do believe that in the long run the nation at large will have to pay the tariff.  One of the great difficulties with which we are confronted in discussing a tariff policy for Ireland is that, first of all, Ireland <Col N="403" /> is mainly an agricultural country.  The difficulty is how to devise a tariff system which will do good to the agricultural community&mdash;which, after all, is the chief community&mdash;as well as benefiting the industrial community.</P>
      <P>When one examines that problem one immediately sees how, from the Irish point of view, the whole question of tariffs bristles with trouble.  In the case of the farmer, if you put a tariff on agricultural machinery, such as ploughs and harrows and threshing machines, manures, seeds, and various other things which the farmer uses, you are going to put up the cost of living, and the cost of production of these articles on the men who represent the most important part of the community. True, you may do a certain amount of benefit to the people who manufacture those goods, but you are doing it at the expense of the community; in other words, at the expense of the farmer.  I would like just to consider a little further the question of protection, as it affects the agricultural industry.  The farmer naturally would want some protection on some of his products.  That would increase the cost of living to other members of the community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Generally speaking, it is quite clear, on reading this Report of the Fiscal Committee, that there was a great deal of difference of opinion, even amongst the commercial community, as to the desirability of tariffs.  They are not by any means all agreed.  I will just take the industry with which I am associated most personally&mdash;the Malting Industry&mdash;and, in expressing the views on that industry I am expressing now, I am giving not only my own views but the considered views of the Maltsters' Association of Ireland, who handle annually three-quarters of a million barrels of Irish barley approximately.  As you will see by the Report issued by the Fiscal Committee, the Irish Maltsters' Association gave evidence to the effect that a tariff on barley would be bad for the country, bad not only for them, but bad for the agricultural community more particularly; because it has to be remembered that barley is largely the raw material for our biggest export industry.  If you put a tax on <Col N="404" /> anything that is used in connection with the manufacture of Dublin Stout, you immediately penalise the Dublin stout brewer when he tries to compete with the English brewer in England where, by far and away, the biggest end of his trade lies.  That is a fact which, I am afraid, is not very often appreciated by people who call for a tax on barley&mdash;that probably two-thirds of the produce of their barley is exported across the water.  It is true that a certain amount of foreign barley does come into Ireland in connection with the manufacture of stout.  For various technical reasons, which I need not go into, this amount is necessary, and even with a tariff on that amount of barley coming in, it would still come in, and would have to come in, for not only is it necessary for technical reasons, but Ireland does not, at the moment, grow sufficient barley for our large export trade in stout.  If you put a tax on that small amount of foreign barley coming in, of course you would undoubtedly get a certain amount of revenue, and from that point of view I dare say it might bring a certain amount of delight to the mind of the Minister for Finance; but as a purely protective measure, I cannot say it would do very much good.</P>
    <P>In this connection, I would like to refer to the fact that Deputy Milroy told us that there was practically no export of tillage products from Ireland. I have already instanced the case of barley.  I should say there is probably anything from £500,000 to £600,000 worth of barley exported in the form of stout and whiskey.  There is also a very large proportion of oats exported, but I have not the figures.  In dealing with this question I suppose it would be quite right that one should take the whole of Ireland as a fiscal unit, including Northern Ireland, as of course Northern Ireland exports a considerable amount of linen, which is made from flax grown in Ireland.  Therefore, I think he is rather over-stating the case when he tells us there is practically no export of tillage products from Ireland.  Furthermore, in that connection, the stock-raising and the tillage industry are so intimately interwoven they really, to a great extent, may be said to be part of each other.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="405" /> In the winter of course roots, mangolds, turnips, rape and other products of tillage have to be utilised for the feeding of stock, which afterwards are exported, either as stores or fat cattle, to England, and other countries.</P>
    <P>Then, again, you have to consider that the farmer would naturally say we should have a tax on wheat coming in.  Someone else would say there should be a tax on flour.  You cannot tax either one or the other of those articles without putting up the cost of living on the general consuming community, and that is another difficulty I see.  Deputy Milroy also referred to tobacco.  Tobacco is, to a certain extent, grown in Ireland under a Government scheme of protection, and, to my mind, public money was never more ill-spent than in trying to cultivate the growth of tobacco in Ireland.  The real reason is that, even when you have got your Irish-grown tobacco, the Irish manufacturers can only use from five to six per cent. of it in their products, and the amount that can be used is not worth talking about.  Further, it can only be grown, and has only been grown, with the definite aid of a Government subsidy for which the rest of the country have to pay.  My own view is that neither the soil nor the climate of Ireland is fit to grow tobacco that will compete with the sun-grown and sun-dried tobacco of other countries.  It is really a waste of money trying to bolster up an industry of that sort for which the country is naturally unfitted.</P>
    <P>We had a discussion on building.  Is it proposed to put a tax on building materials, on slates and cement, and on the various timber goods used in connection with building?  If you do, what is the result?  Is it not going to make the President's task, in dealing with the housing problem, more difficult?  Will it not increase the cost of housing?  I cannot see that the country as a whole would gain anything by a tariff on these articles.  Deputy Sears, in seconding the motion of Deputy Milroy, referred to the beet industry, and he told us a certain amount of what had been done in Norfolk.  I have always held the view that the beet industry is a particularly suitable one for Ireland; but there are many difficulties in the way.  The first is where <Col N="406" /> are you going to get your beet?  There would have to be a very appreciable increase in the area under tillage.</P>
    <P>Of course, you could not grow beet as an isolated crop.  It has to be part and parcel of some definite rotation of crops.  It would necessitate more land under the plough and a greater supply of barley and oats or other cereals, and it would require rather a revolution in our existing tillage rotation.  In the tillage rotation systems which work in our different districts, it would mean a change.  It certainly could not be done in a hurry.  It is one of those industries that could scarcely be taken up as a matter of private enterprise.  It would not only require a great deal of capital to start the factories, but also a tremendous amount of co-operation on the part of farmers, in order to enable the factory to be supplied with beet and to have extended the area under tillage.</P>
    <P>There was one remarkable omission in the course of Deputy Milroy's speech.  He made no reference whatever to the possibility of action being taken by other countries in response to our tariff policy.  In other words, he made no reference to the policy of retaliation.  I am aware, of course, that England is our chief market, and it may be argued that the Englishman is not likely to tax his food; that is to say, he would hardly tax our cattle or agricultural produce going in.  There are, however, a great many forms of retaliation other than a direct tariff on imports. They might, for instance, in England give greater facilities for the importation of Canadian cattle, or produce from the Colonies, if we started a policy of taxing English manufactured goods that come in here.  While I have, as may be gathered, fairly strong ideas in favour of free trade, I am quite willing to keep an open mind and to listen to any convincing arguments that may be advanced in favour of protection.  I say, however, that in a debate of this sort you cannot reach any finality.  In discussing this problem you must have definite, concrete cases put before you.  Each individual industry must be taken on its merits and the effects of tariffs examined <Col N="407" /> from their source to their logical conclusion. It is only by taking each individual industry separately that a really true decision can be arrived at as to what is best for the country.  I think it is a very good thing that this discussion did arise, and I hope that Deputies later on, instead of indulging in generalities in connection with it, will try and develop details and make some proposals in a concrete form.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to add my tribute to that already given by the Deputy who spoke before me to the diligence and detail with which Deputy Milroy made his case.  With a great deal of what he said I am in agreement, and with some of it I am not in agreement.  It is admitted that a public service has been rendered by bringing forward this case.  Deputy Egan is correct in saying that the debate is more or less of the nature of a pious debate.  It is preliminary to the conclusions that the Ministry are considering and which they will put forward before the Dáil, and the time to criticise will be when they come forward in concrete form.  I do not suppose that any Deputy is prepared to explode his shell before the occasion arises when it will, if it ever will, be necessary to do so.  The report of the Fiscal Committee is, I think, a very unsatisfactory one.  I am not going to charge the members of that Committee, as Deputy Milroy did, with malignancy, but the form of the report is unfortunate.  It is scrappy, it is incomplete, and the first portions of it are entirely contradictory to the latter portion, and several arguments advanced in various parts, when brought face to face with one another, will be found to be mutually destructive.  I think that possibly the cause of this is to be found in the early section of the report, where the Committee state that they regarded a speech delivered in this Dáil by President Cosgrave as imposing certain limitations upon them in which he stated that it was facts, and not policy, which the Committee was intended to determine.  I remember that sentence at the time, and I remember wondering exactly what it meant.  The Committee have not furnished <Col N="408" /> facts, nor have they furnished a policy, but have indulged in the use of words that I think do not apply to the needs of this country at all.  I say so with every deference, because all the preceding speakers in this debate have also adverted to these phrases.  They spoke about free trade and about protection.  I contest the use of those words in relation to this country, and I say that they have no application to us at all, that the policies which are meant to be included in those phrases have no application to this country, and that free trade and protection as alternative fiscal policies have only relation to a country that has an organised system, a system which this country has yet to have.  I suggest that it is only common sense to consider that all the various arguments used from time to time over this much-vexed question as to whether free trade or protection is the correct form of policy, are arguments that leave us entirely cold.  I suggest that common sense points to that conclusion, but not common-sense alone.  Those who turn to the text-books on these matters and those who argue in terms of one or other of the two fiscal theories, will find that the text-books bear out the contention which I am making.  Adam Smith, John Stuart Mill, and modern writers like Hopson have all said that the protection of industries that are merely in a state of youth and that have not yet learned to walk is not protection in the economic sense in which that phrase is generally used.  It is as though people were to argue, as the members of the Fiscal Committee have argued, protesting against protection as an economic policy; it is just as though some other Committee were to state exactly what is the best method of tending forests when we have not yet got the woods that are to be tended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The first point I wish to make is, that it is not until a country has got its industries that it can afford to consider whether the ordinary methods of protection or free trade are applicable in their terms to such a country at all.  The United States has been cited as a great protectionist country.  If I were a citizen of the United States I should be a protectionist, because it is a policy clearly devised for the needs of that <Col N="409" /> country.  If I were a citizen of the United States I would agree with the policy of that country, irrespective of what economists might call that policy. If I were a citizen of Great Britain I would agree with the policy that Great Britain has adopted, and it would be a matter quite immaterial to me if I were told that that policy was free trade, because it is devised for the needs of that country and meant for the betterment of its quite peculiar circumstances. Deputy Egan has already mentioned this matter, and stated that the United States covers a very large area of territory, and covers within the limits of that territory enormous resources of raw material.  Great Britain has nothing of the kind, and must depend on her shipping to bring her those raw materials.</P>
    <P>Therefore, the policy of permitting those raw materials to enter the country without any preliminary taxation is a right policy for one of those countries and not for the other.  I have never yet seen any assessment as to the proportion between what the economists call the invisible imports and the total imports and exports of Great Britain.  I wonder would it be possible to assess it?  Attempts, hitherto unsuccessful, have been made. It is notorious that England is a country, the invisible imports of which form a very large portion of her total prosperity. Obviously, England is a country which cannot afford taxation on industries or manufactured products. The point I am desiring to make is this: I am not regarding the fiscal policy of Great Britain as a free trade policy, nor am I regarding the fiscal policy of the United States as a protectionist one.  What I am saying is that each of those two States has drawn up its policy in direct relation to its own needs.  If, then, at some later stage, the theorist comes along and has his own labels for the two forms of policy those countries have adopted, I suggest that is a matter of no moment to this country.  What we have to consider is the same problem that they have had to consider, and not whether we are going to be a free trade or protectionist country in the ordinary connotation of those terms, <Col N="410" /> but rather what is the policy best adapted by our own special and peculiar needs.  I remember in the years 1903, 1904, and 1905, a great Englishman, Joseph Chamberlain, advocating a new policy that started a very remarkable period of public debate in England.  I remember reading&mdash;I confess it with no particular pride&mdash;every one of the speeches delivered by the two great protagonists on either side.  I remember encumbering my shelves with the very great number of works produced at the time and&mdash;a tribute rather to my industry than intelligence&mdash;mastering those works, and finding as a result that the argument very largely was not an argument as to facts, but as to party moves.  Why I referred to it now is that I think the memories of that great debate have thrown their shadow across our present times and have obscured our application to practical problems because of the reference that those practical problems bring to the terms, conditions, and, if I may say so, the general terminology of that argument.  I remember one of the catch phrases of the time, and we have heard that catch phrase here actually from a speaker who through the general part of his speech kept himself free from it.  The phrase was: &ldquo;Your food will cost you more.&rdquo;  He did not use the phrase, but there were certain references to that very question.  I put this very practical question to the Dáil. The protectionist argues for a certain form.  I remember a protectionist arguing the case for his party, and in the recent English election his opponents rose and stated &ldquo;Your food will cost you more.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Deputy Milroy dealt with this matter, and pointed to a fact which is unquestionably true and which we all admit. We can admit the fact, and proceed from the basis of the fact, that there are two commodities more used in this country than any other commodities, namely, sugar and tea.  There is not a single house that does not use those two articles of food.  We know, if we turn to the last nine months' statement of the monies received in this country because of the dues it levies at the ports, that a very considerable <Col N="411" /> portion of the income of this country is derived from the duties on sugar and tea.  If there were to be any proposal that wheat or flour were to be taxed, or that meat was to be taxed, I imagine there would be a number of people in this country who would rise and say, &ldquo;There you are, this is Protection, your food will cost you more.&rdquo;  Deputy Egan said that the consumer will have to pay for it. There is one part of that argument which is well worth considering, and that is that our present scale of taxation does yield to this country the income it requires within a little margin. It is intended to yield the income this country requires.  Therefore, if there were to be other taxes levied, those taxes would have to take the place of some of the present taxes.  I take the case at its extremest.  I take those two fundamental commodities&mdash;flour and wheat.  If those two commodities were to be taxed it would be quite possible to release taxation on sugar and tea, so that the general price of food would not cost more.  I know it would at once be said, &ldquo;this is Protection.&rdquo;  I have for the last seventeen years, since that great debate was conducted, asked a number of people what is the meaning of the two words, Protection and Free Trade?  In some cases people, unfortunately stricken with frankness, admit that they themselves cannot give a definition, and in other cases they smile credulously at the question.  I repeat, what is Free Trade and what is Protection?  I shall be told that if bread and meat were to be taxed, rather than tea and sugar, that is Protection. I shall be told that if tea and sugar were to be taxed, rather than bread and meat, that is Free Trade.  I refuse to accept any category so artificial as this.  I say there is no justification for the taxation of two such items common to the consumption to every household in Ireland as sugar and tea, because they are articles of absolute need.  One is an essential food, and the other is not a luxury, but an essential need.</P>
    <P>I might even go further and ask with regard to porter and stout, and if anybody <Col N="412" /> says to me that porter and stout are not food, I shall refute any such critic with the complaint of an old lady in the Coombe, who asked how it was possible to continue these times with the price of food at 8d. per pint.  I am not urging a particular form or that any particular commodities should be taxed. What I am urging is that we should consider, not merely accept the fact, that tea and sugar, because they have been received into our hands from another nation's need, were each of them taxed at a time when these commodities were considered to be luxuries, although they have long since passed out of that category; that we should free ourselves from these acceptations of previous arguments and apply ourselves anew to our own special needs and circumstances.</P>
    <P>Deputy Milroy, in his speech, referred to a great number of authorities for whom I have a certain degree of veneration, and I have heard the complaint made that some of the authorities he has referred to are now somewhat out of date.  I do not believe that these essential arguments do become postdated quite in that manner but, even if that be accepted, I would refer the Dáil to what I consider to be the latest work on the subject and, probably, the finest.  That is a book that I have been studying for some weeks now, called &ldquo;The Fundamental Principles of Taxation in The Light of Modern Development,&rdquo; by Josiah Stamp.  He states in regard to all taxes that they must be regarded from three points of view: (1) from the individual point of view; (2) from the State point of view; (3) from the point of view of the community. To return for a moment to the instances that I gave, that if the taxes on sugar and tea&mdash;and I put it quite hypothetically&mdash;were to be remitted completely, and the same revenue was to be sought from other forms of taxation, quite apart from whether the words &ldquo;protection&rdquo; and &ldquo;free trade&rdquo; would apply, or would not apply to such a change, it is quite clear that the individual would gain. If these other sources of taxation were wisely sought so that they did yield the same revenue, the State would not lose. If they were so wisely sought that industries <Col N="413" /> could be promoted in this country, that do not exist at present, the community would gain also.  That is the argument that I am putting forward.</P>
    <P>I say that we have received and were acting upon taxes levied upon certain commodities, all those taxes being entirely obsolete in their own country, and never yet have considered whether they suit the conditions and circumstances of this country.  I do urge that it would be a profitable exercise if we took into our hands a list of commodities on which taxation is levied in the Free State, and asked ourselves whether they were necessary from the point of view of the individual, whether they could not be given a like benefit from the point of view of the State, and whether changes could not be effected in them of very much greater benefit from the point of view of the community.  In other words, I am urging, if I might put it in a humorous way, that our Minister for Finance should levy a very high tax upon any Deputy who rises in this Dáil and uses either the phrase &ldquo;free trade&rdquo; or the phrase &ldquo;protection.&rdquo;  Let us drop the use of these words altogether.  They are no indexes to realities; they are merely indexes to outworn controversies.  We should not seek to devise some policy that would theoretically be conformable with either of these doctrines, but should seek to devise a policy that should be a real policy as opposed to a theoretic policy.  To put it in another way, it should be a scientific policy drawn from our own separate Irish needs without references to old controversies and without any reference to the special needs of the country that first devised the taxes under which we are labouring and which we have taken over from that country.</P>
    <P>Supposing we were to do so.  Supposing we ceased to think of protection, to think of free trade, and only thought of the utmost gain that we could get from the best system of taxation that we could devise, the best form in which our duties could be raised. Deputy Egan says that that might involve us in some retaliation from other countries.  I think he hardly remembered that the British Dominions <Col N="414" /> are themselves what are generally spoken of as protectionist countries, and I have yet to learn that where it suited the needs of Great Britain to receive their commodities that Great Britain brought any retaliation into effect in respect to such Dominions.  I do not think we need fear the question of retaliation.  Countries always consider their own special needs.  Without prejudging the real question that will come forward when the Budget proposals of the Ministry are framed, without going any further into an argument that at present is rather in the nature of being a pious argument, all I am urging is that we should not follow the example of the Fiscal Inquiry Committee, and let our minds be beclouded with old controversies, old labels, old terminologies that have no application whatever to this country; that we should cease to think about protection and free trade and come down to the actual concrete problem of devising some means that will give help to the industries of this country without bringing any greater injury to the individual taxpayer; giving the same result to the State, but giving a greater result to the community than the community can hope for under the present system.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it will be evident that this is a subject upon which those who have been in the habit of acting together in the past will find themselves divided, and there may be curious combinations when we come to <i>real politik</i> in this country.  I do not know what kind of exhibition it would make if the &ldquo;flure&rdquo; were taken by Deputy Milroy, Deputy Figgis and myself against &ldquo;all who may.&rdquo;  I will say that I regret that the motion of Deputy Milroy did not ask that a statement of Government policy on this matter should be made.  It is nearly a year ago since the first suggestions were made that the question of fiscal freedom, and the use which was to be made of it, must be referred to a Committee of Inquiry before the Government would be justified in launching upon any change of policy.  Inquiry was made and a Report was handed to the Ministry. We are within a month or two of a new Budget, and a decision will have <Col N="415" /> to be made as to future fiscal policy. I think it would be well if we could have had from the Ministry&mdash;it is possible we may still have it before this debate closes; but I do not think there is evidence of any great interest in the matter from the Ministerial ranks&mdash;a statement of policy, but I think it is unlikely.  I would like to have had a vote of the Dáil declaring its wish and belief that the time had arrived when a definite statement of Government policy on this matter should be made. Bear in mind that there are many people waiting anxious to know what the policy is to be before embarking upon enterprises, before extending their present enterprises, or before deciding whether to close down their present operations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major BRYAN COOPER Major BRYAN COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major BRYAN COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>took the Chair at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The persistent delay in declaring yea or nay, whether there is to be any departure from past policy, is retarding any potential development of industry to a greater degree&mdash;I ask Ministers to take a note of that&mdash;than any question of the rate of wages that are to be paid in the ensuing months.  I agree with a great deal of what Deputy Milroy said in criticism of the Fiscal Committee's Report.  It may sound strange for me to say that I am not sure yet, having read the Report carefully, whether it is intended to decry protective tariffs, whether it is intended to advise or suggest to the Ministry that tariffs for protective purposes should not be imposed.  Judging by the public comments, particularly the newspaper comments, and may I say particularly the comments in British financial newspapers, the Report of this Committee has given very widespread satisfaction to those established interests which are prosperous and do not require any assistance.  From other comments which one has read, one would imagine that the conclusions that are assumed to have been arrived at by the Committee have been generally accepted as satisfactory because there has been no widespread agitation, and no very keen criticism, or dissent from the Report as presented.  I think the conclusion is a <Col N="416" /> false one, and I think as a matter of fact that there has been a great deal of dissent and criticism of the Report. Whether there has or has not been, there ought to have been.  I said I was not quite sure what the conclusions were that the Committee desired the Government to take out of the Report. As has been pointed out by more than one Deputy, the Committee has taken particular note of the direction which was given it by the President when it was set up in June last.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;It is facts, and not policy, which the Committee is intended to determine. Every proposition that is advanced will be examined, solely with a view to ascertain and inform the community as to all the facts.  The Committee is not expected to advocate a policy.  That will be a matter for the people and the Government when they have the facts before them.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That quotation from the President's statement is repeated in the Report, and it is evident that it governed the proceedings of the Committee.  But when we read the Report we find an extraordinary absence of statements of fact.  We find page after page of precis of evidence.  This witness said that and another witness said something else, but we have no facts.  A little later we have paragraph after paragraph of conclusions and economic theories which one might have imagined had been taken from certain economic text-books.  They are not statements of fact.  They are not figures of fact which the public can lay hold upon to determine policy from.  It is facts which are to be elucidated, and the intention was that the Report should inform the community as to all the facts.  I looked through the Report in vain to see what are the facts relating to, say, the glass bottle industry, the boot-making industry, the textile industry, the wholesale clothing or any other industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What is the capacity for production in this country of those various industries to-day?  What is the market in this country that those establishments may be expected to supply?  What are the costs of production in this country as compared with the costs of production in other countries?  What amount of assistance would be required&mdash;or <Col N="417" /> shall I put it the other way&mdash;what amount of handicap should be placed on competing industries to enable Irish industries to meet the competition? We have none of the facts.  We have a presentation of theory, a presentation of suggestion, but none of the facts upon which the community was and is asked to draw conclusions.  It may be, of course, that facts have been placed before the Ministry.  It may be that weeks and weeks were spent in intimate inquiries as to the facts relating to the various industries, and that these facts have, in reality, been placed at the disposal of the Ministry.  We as a Dáil did not appoint this Committee, and, therefore, we have no right to call upon the Committee to give us its Report.  I will assume that the facts which were called for have been collected and have been placed at the disposal of the Ministry which appointed the Committee.  I will assume further, that the facts have been examined and digested, and, as a consequence, the Ministry will be able to say to the Dáil, before the debate concludes, that they have arrived at general lines of policy and will indicate them to the country, that in due time the working-out of the policy will be announced, and that advantage will be taken of the introduction of the Budget to indicate the policy in its application in detail.  But the Committee has not presumed to suggest, or to forecast, that fiscal policy for the country.  &ldquo;It has taken its task to be rather that of collecting and analysing facts and presenting them to the best of its ability.&rdquo;  If there are Deputies present who have the Report in hand, I would ask them to refer to paragraphs 117, 119, 124, 125, 126, and ask themselves whether these paragraphs are really presentations of facts relating to Irish industries.  Deputy Milroy has, of course, pointed out that it is suggested as a reason against tariffs in certain industries that the effect would be to increase the wages in those industries, and it is suggested, if not to the Ministry and the Dáil, to the companies or the business men who were making proposals regarding tariffs in those industries, that that was a warning which should be taken <Col N="418" /> into account, and even that it is a sufficient inducement to prevent them continuing to advocate tariffs for the protection of their industries.</P>
    <P>I said, of course, that I was not quite sure what was really the intention of the Committee in making the Report&mdash;what they desired to suggest to the Ministry in regard to the effect of proposals for tariffs upon the country as a whole, and upon the particular industries concerned. Let me draw attention to the second Interim Report, in which they referred to the duty upon motor cars.  They point out that the existing duty does not fall upon motor vehicles engaged in industry, or husbandry, or upon manufactures or ambulances, and, as a matter of fact, the existing duties apply to private cars for pleasure and luxury.  &ldquo;The duty cannot, therefore, be regarded as one that seriously interferes with any important industry or agricultural interest, and in view of the present importance of the revenue and the proceeds of this duty,&rdquo; the Committee did not see its way to make any recommendations for its removal.  But there is a proviso: &ldquo;Having regard to certain evidence, the Committee reserves for its Final Report the discussion of a change in the apportionment of the duty between the chassis and the body of the completed car.&rdquo;  But in that Report it recommends the withdrawal of the duty upon accessories and component parts.  That is to say, it recommends the withdrawal of the duty upon the raw material for an assembling or a repairing industry.  But in the third paragraph of the Final Report it comes down definitely with a recommendation for protection for the body-building industry, and recommends that the present tax on completed cars should be maintained, but that a much lower rate of duty should be levied upon the chassis when imported without the body.  Now, there is the fact.  There is a definite proposition there, because having regard to the industry and to the effect of a tariff upon employment in that industry, they recommend that there should be a change in the duties affecting motor cars, and in effect to protect by a tariff the body-building part of <Col N="419" /> the motor car industry.  Put that recommendation against the theories in the paragraphs which are named, from 116 onwards, and I ask the Dáil and the Ministry to note that this Report is not, in fact, a Report against the imposition of duties on imports for protective purposes.  That is a definite conclusion which I ask the Ministry and the Dáil to come to.</P>
    <P>I think that possibly the most interesting, possibly even the most valuable, portion of this Report is the Appendix marked A.  It gives a comparative table of the nominal and real wages in certain industries in the Saorstát, Northern Ireland, and Great Britain, respectively. I will not quote further from this Report, but I ask the Deputies to take it home, read it carefully, study it thoroughly, take notes, and sleep on it, and then let them come back and tell us whether they want to see a change in the rate of wages in Ireland as will approximate them to those in Great Britain. And note a very important fact in connection with these industries, that pre-war in the industries named the wages were generally considerably below the rates ruling in Great Britain. Perhaps Deputy Milroy will report this to those whom he may come in contact with, who are interested in these suggestions, and are advocating preferential tariffs as the only means of saving their industry.  They had, as a matter of fact, a protective tariff in the rates of wages pre-war&mdash;considerable protection&mdash;and the industries were not eminently successful, and there were not such widespread organizations as we would like to have seen. They had a protective tariff, in effect, by the fact that they had lower rates of wages in Ireland than in the competing industries in England, but they were not able to succeed and develop to the extent that they and we all would have liked.  The conclusion I ask the Dáil to draw from that is, that protective tariffs are not the only factor to be taken into account.  You may have a protective tariff and no improvement in your capacity to produce, no improvement in your market, no improvement in your business organisation which will enable you to supply that market, or as the word goes, &ldquo;capture&rdquo; it.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="420" /> The evidence supplied to the Commission came from representatives of separate industries, which separate industries were asked to report upon their own industries, to give information about those industries, and to make proposals regarding the assistance, encouragement, or protection of those industries.  I presume that they confined their evidence to that which they might be presumed to know most of, and while they were asked to do that, and while their evidence was confined to matters within their own knowledge, a complaint is made during the course of this Report, to the effect that &ldquo;none of the witnesses gave them very much assistance regarding the effects of a tariff on industry generally.&rdquo;  That seems to me to be another point of criticism which is valid against the Report, in the conclusions which it has arrived at regarding the effects of a tariff policy upon the country as a whole.</P>
    <P>I want to get away from the Report a little with these final words, that the evidence which was adduced quite clearly produced an impression upon the Commission that there is something wrong in the state of industry in Ireland from the point of organisation, management, and marketing ability, and I think it clearly points to this conclusion, that tariffs or no tariffs, protection, or no protection, free trade or no free trade, there is not much hope for industrial development in the country until there is a very great improvement on the capitalists', employing, <i>entrepreneur</i>, side of industry. But the fact remains that we are living in Ireland, and we have to deal with the population we have to-day, their character, ability, training, and knowledge, and with facts as they are.  The ability may be great or small, but such as it is that is what we have to deal with.  The problems before statement &mdash;shall I say before politicians&mdash;were stated a good many years ago in a popular work in words something like this: &ldquo;Given a country and a people, find how to make the most of that country and that people.&rdquo;  That is the problem we have before us now.  We have a country and a people, and it is our business to make the most of this country and this people, and notwithstanding the defects, the failures, the <Col N="421" /> inabilities, lack of education and training, whether of employers or workmen, it is this country at this stage of its development that we are to deal with.  But we cannot come to any satisfactory conclusions unless we take into account the situation in countries outside our own.  What are the facts regarding those countries in relation to this?  One of the facts, a very important one in my opinion, is the industrial development in England and Continental countries.  Let us take England.  The power to produce cheaply commodities for ordinary consumption has been tremendously advanced within the last ten years; advantage was taken of the war period to improve productive facilities, organisation methods and equipment, and consequently the handicap which existed pre-war against Irish manufacturers compared with British manufacturers is doubled, or trebled, or quadrupled to-day because of the fact that the productive ability in competing countries has increased greatly in proportion to the productive abilities in this country.</P>
    <P>If we were to accept the doctrine that cheapness to the consumer should be the determining factor in the fixation of prices, and in determining economic policy, let us ask ourselves where we shall be leading to?  A manufacturer in Birmingham or Sheffield or Leeds can to-day, undoubtedly, produce commodities for domestic consumption and raw materials for other industries &mdash;that is, partly manufactured goods&mdash; and place them in any part of Ireland more cheaply than competing manufacturers, such as we have within Ireland, can, because of improved organisation, cheaper power, more convenient coal, better management, and longer training on the operative side.  Are we to say that it should be the considered policy of this country to feed and to satisfy the desire for cheapness on the part of the consumer to this extent, that because British or German manufactured articles can be placed in Athlone or Mullingar or Cork cheaper than an Irish manufacturer can place them there, it must follow, as a matter of public policy, that the consumer in Cork or Athlone or Mullingar, must be <Col N="422" /> free to purchase that article cheaply, because it is cheap, even though it is manufactured under specially advantageous circumstances in England?  If that is to be the determinant, then I predict continuance of the tendencies as between the two countries that have existed for 70 or 80 years.  It is the logical conclusion, and the businesslike conclusion, of the acceptance of the principle that the consumer's interest must predominate, and the consumer's interest must determine the economic policy of the country.</P>
    <P>What is the article that we can produce most efficiently, most satisfactorily, most cheaply, in comparison with similar articles from any other country?  The history of the country supplies the answer&mdash;store cattle, grass-fed beef; therefore, the conclusion is that our energies should be directed as a nation to producing, in increasing quantities, that which we can produce most cheaply, most efficiently&mdash;store cattle and grass-fed beef&mdash;because we can put that into the English market, and get a higher monetary return for it to the proprietor than by any other line of production that we know of.  Is that to be the policy?  And if so, what will be the result?  One of two things.  Either the human population will still follow production and exchange cattle for boots, and the potential bootmakers will go to where the boots are made, and we will send cattle in exchange for boots; or, alternatively, that for the export of cattle which have not consumed labour in their production we shall receive wealth which will be expended by the recipients in employing men in ordinary personal services. We may continue the present tendency and so export those articles which embody a small amount of human labour, and import those articles which embody a large amount of human labour because it is more profitable to the exporter, to the producer, to the proprietor, and let the proprietor then expend his receipts in employing what one might, without offence, call the parasites of the land.</P>
    <P>It has been quite seriously put forward that the real development of this country should be to make it a <Col N="423" /> pleasure ground for the rich, or as somebody paraphrased it, to make a circus of Ireland.  And one would imagine, reading the newspapers lately, that that was going to be the accepted intention.  We shall receive high prices for cattle because the most profitable, or in deference to the farmers we will say, because of higher profits than we can get from any other export, and we shall expend these profits in employing men to run races or to groom horses, or to entertain us in theatres, or to plead for us in the law courts, or to lecture us in our Universities, or to pay politicians in the Dáil&mdash;that, in fact, the population of this country will not be engaged in production.</P>
    <P>Is that a prospect that commends itself to the Dáil, is it a prospect that commends itself to the Ministry?  It is not, I am sure.  Everyone has spoken about the necessity for developing industry and of encouraging industry. What steps then are we going to take towards that development, or to make that development possible?  I have come to this conclusion, after examining this subject as carefully and as honestly as I could, coming to it with prejudices definitely in favour of free imports, I have come to the conclusion that to make that development possible there will need to be a change in the apportionment of import duty, and that to give an opportunity to those who desire to develop industries at home there will need to be some handicap placed upon the fundamental urge of humanity to buy in the cheapest market.  We all desire to get goods, when purchasing, in the greatest quantity for the least expenditure.  It is a natural attribute of humanity, and the Free Trade economist, the Free Trade philosopher succeeded in England, particularly because he was adjusting an economic policy to a natural attribute in allowing free play to human nature, forgetful of the fact that civilisation is, in reality, a curbing of the natural appetites.</P>
    <P>I am following a good deal on the lines that Deputy Figgis indicated when he was speaking as to the unwisdom to say the least of it, of laying overstress upon the experience of other countries.  If I were in England, I still <Col N="424" /> think I would be in favour of a limitation of the principle of import duties upon manufactured goods, and I do not think for a moment that the facts which were adduced by Deputy Egan that Free Trade had assisted in making England commercially and industrially prosperous, and that Protection in America had not prevented America from becoming industrially or commercially prosperous, were matters of very great moment to us.  They proved this, though, that neither one system nor the other is the essential condition to prosperity. I believe it is desirable, if we are to make the most of this country, that we should have some alternative to the pastoral industry, and that there should be an encouragement given to the production of as many of the essential commodities as can be produced at home, even though there may be, as I said earlier, some handicap placed upon the desire of the people to buy in the cheapest market.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Agriculture and the Minister for Home Affairs have said on two or three occasions lately what has been said in other countries, and what will be said more and more, I think, in this country: that the costs of distribution and transport weigh disproportionately heavy upon the productive industries of the various countries which have the same complaint to make.  The Minister for Agriculture gave some figures or estimates which have not been checked, but which may be taken as roughly indicative of the true position, to show that the costs of transport and distribution were unduly heavy, and that there was a disproportionate number, to the population, engaged in transport and distribution.  I ask the Dáil to consider how is that going to be remedied.  Let us take it that you all agree with the complaint, that you all agree with the diagnosis, and that it indicates economic sickness.  Supposing you tried to redress the balance and reduce the number of redundant people engaged in distribution, what, I ask, are you going to do with them? Do you suggest that there is room for them in agriculture?  We are told that they are leaving agriculture because it is not prosperous, and is it suggested that the redundant men and women <Col N="425" /> should transfer their attentions to America, England or Scotland?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>at this stage resumed the chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Every public man is urging against a policy which would lead to emigration.  Is it suggested that instead of engaging in distribution they should engage in performing cartwheels before passing vehicles, and call out for pennies, or that they should engage in any other form of amusement catering.  That is a possibility, but is it going to make a great nation? Then what other alternative do you put before us?  The only alternative that I can see is to make it possible for them to find a way to produce wealth in the course of their application of labour to industrial production.  If that is essential, then you have got to ask yourselves how are we going to find a way to ensure that there should be a redistribution of the occupations of the people, so that a larger number shall be engaged in productive work?  I submit that we have got to find a way to employ that idle labour, or wasted labour, or misapplied labour power, to new industries, or to the development of existing industries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Having arrived at that, what are we to do with it?  If I were thinking of the distant future, if I were thinking of ten or fifteen years hence, I would press upon the Dáil policies which I think will ultimately be found acceptable in regard to the way that improvement in the industrial situation can be arrived at.  But I am not going to look ahead ten or fifteen years.  I see the position in the year 1924 as being a very serious one and a very difficult one.  We are, in fact, at the parting of the ways, and I see that we have to confirm, in the economic sphere, a decision that was made in the political sphere.  I will come to that in a moment.  I cannot afford to look ahead ten years and propose policies which it would take ten years to attune the public mind to receive. I am driven to this conclusion, reluctantly, I admit, that there must be tariffs upon imports of such a kind as are capable of being produced and developed with a reasonable expectation <Col N="426" /> of success in this country, and that economic enquiry should be directed to finding out which of those industries are best fitted for development, are most suitable for the conditions of the country, and are most likely to make the economic basis of future development secure and stable.</P>
    <P>I said that we were, in my opinion, at the parting of the ways economically, and that we are compelled to make a decision in the economic sphere which will either confirm or deny the decision which was made by the country two or three years ago in respect to its political future.  We decided that the country should be politically an independent entity.  Many of us knew that that would mean very little indeed unless it were going to result in a change economically, socially and culturally. An independent political community is one thing.  Can you conceive it as a desirable thing that we should have political freedom to conduct our political affairs affecting matters of administration and matters of internal communication and education, while at the same time allowing a continuation of the economic subordination of the country to more powerful neighbours? Are we wise in thinking of these islands, known as the British Islands, as the economic unit upon which we are to base our considerations, or are we to attune our minds to thinking of Ireland as the economic unit?  If the former, then this Report in the main is quite understandable.  If Great Britain and Ireland are to be considered an economic unit, then the policy suggested in the main part of this Report is sound, just as it would be sound for Devonshire in relation to Sheffield, or as it would be sound for any agricultural portion of England in relation to any industrial portion.  Any of us who may have studied, even to a slight degree, the industrial history of the last 120 years, knows that the shifting of the population followed changes in the power of production and the necessity for the use of coal.</P>
    <P>If Great Britain and Ireland are to be considered an economic unit, and if it is sound and sensible that what is potentially an industrial population should go where the industries are and leave the pastoral population to remain <Col N="427" /> where the herds are, and that the aggregate amount of profit earned will be greater&mdash;if that policy is accepted and followed&mdash;certainly the aggregate amount of immediate profit will be greater.  But I am asking the Dáil to agree that is not the intention of this country and that we do, as a matter of fact, desire that as far as it is reasonably possible Ireland should be an economic unit with such international trade as is necessary and desirable, always bearing in mind the necessity for making Ireland within reasonable limits an economic unit, and bearing in mind the necessity for keeping her within those limits.</P>
    <P>I say that conclusion, that presupposition, is a consideration which should determine the economic policy of the country.  It is not good enough to put questions to people, and say what is best for us industrially, and then when you have an aggregate of answers from a variety of people to say that we will follow that.  This Dáil, at any rate, ought to be able to think in terms of the nation; not only as a political unit but as an economic unit. And why is it desirable that there should be an industrial population to supplement the agricultural population, and that that industrial population should have access to the material for production and plenty of opportunity to exercise their abilities?  It is that notwithstanding the dearness, notwithstanding the possibility, that we may have to pay more, and that even we may all possibly have to live upon a lower standard than has been set up by a more highly organised industrial country across the water, we shall get a greater variety of development, a greater variety of culture, and a greater variety of experience, and, cumulatively, a greater ability to make the most of this country.  Now, I am afraid I am going too far in what might be called the higher policy. Having said what I have said in that respect, convinced as I am, and possibly disagreeing with a great many of my colleagues, in saying that the future of the country depends upon at least securing, within the next few years, the foundations upon which the <Col N="428" /> industrial future may be built, and that that basis probably can only be secured by something in the nature of protective tariffs; let me add that after protection is given, then will come the necessity for using the opportunities, and seeing that the opportunities are used; then will come the necessity for encouragement of technical education, and improved methods of production, and improved methods of organisation and of marketing.  But if I may be allowed, if I am not wearying the Dáil, I want to deal with what might be called the more practical side of this question.</P>
    <P>I want to deal with it now, because of the likelihood that the Finance Department is considering its taxation proposals for the coming year.  If one takes in hand the report of the Cost of Living Committee of the Department, you will find, on page 13, an analysis of the proportionate expenditure on a large number of the wage-earning households. And without arguing, or even without concluding that these are absolutely reliable, and without going to draw any conclusions from them, they will be accepted, to say the least, as indicative of the way the average working class household expends its income on the ordinary commodities requisite to keep the family.  Deputy Milroy, in the course of his speech, several times referred to the possibility of the transference of duties, and it is from that aspect that I want to speak.  Deputy Figgis also touched upon that question of the transference of duties from tea and sugar to beef and flour.</P>
    <P>I am asking the Dáil, and more particularly the Minister for Finance, to consider whether the possibilities of revenue may not be in harmony with or run parallel with the possibilities of encouraging Irish industry.  Now, from the revenue point of view, there have been taxes imposed on tea and sugar, tobacco and spirits, beer, etc.  From this analysis I find that out of 100 shillings expended by the average working class household, the sum which is paid for the taxes on tea and sugar&mdash;which, by the way, and I ask this to be noticed, is levied as import duties and not upon the retail selling price, a very <Col N="429" /> different thing&mdash;the proportion of taxes which is paid by the average working class household in the town on tea and sugar amounts to 1.84 per cent., and the revenue from the tax on tea and sugar was estimated to be round about £2,800,000.  Now, just as an illustration, and without urging this specifically, although I propose to put it forward as subject to the examination which the Minister for Finance can give to it, an examination which I am not able to give by virtue of the absence of statistics under the new Government&mdash;suppose that we re-adjusted the incidence of taxation, and wiped out entirely the duties upon tea and sugar, it would be reckoned to be a considerable relief to the average householder, and especially to the householder with a big family. That relief would be felt also by the farming community, especially the farming community which is living near the ground and has not much to spend, and spends proportionately more upon tea and sugar than the townsman does, that is to say, that of the total cash expended a greater proportion goes on articles of that kind than in the case of the townsman.</P>
    <P>Suppose it were decided that the incidence of taxation for the purpose of realising £2,800,000 was placed upon manufactured textile goods, wearing apparel, leather goods and the like.  By the way, let me say here that the revenue derived from the import duties on clothing and textiles in New Zealand amounts to rather more than a quarter of the total revenue derived from imports.  The rate of duty is from 25 to 45 per cent. ad valorem. Now, with the best information at my disposal, again in the absence of reliable statistics from the Statistical Department, which I am sorry I do not see much sign of, to the great loss of the community, I have endeavoured to extract from the Department's report on imports in 1921&mdash;which include northern ports as well as southern and western ports&mdash;I attempted to make a classification of the various groups of commodities which are imported and sold within the Saorstát.  From that classification and analysis I arrived at the conclusion that for that year there were about eleven million pounds' worth of goods imported for use in the <Col N="430" /> Saorstát which might be described as wearing apparel or, in the wider sense, textile goods.  If this 25 per cent. duty on an average was imposed on that wearing apparel, we should have a revenue practically equal to the revenue estimated to be derived on sugar and tea in the present year.  What would be the effect on the cost of living of that change in the incidence of taxation? If it were a flat rate of taxation on wearing apparel and textiles the effect would be to increase the cost of living to the extent of one per cent. on the average expenditure of the working class family as defined in this report.  As against that you will have a very much greater increase in the amount of employment given, because the greater proportion of the eleven million pounds' worth of produce would have been produced in this country&mdash;that is to say, that the wealth addition in the making up of goods is very much greater than the value of the raw material.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>What about revenue?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The revenue, I pointed out, is, up to this stage, equal to the revenue on 25 per cent. provided there was no manufacture in Ireland. The revenue from the point of view of no change would be equal.  Bear in mind that I said a flat rate on 25 per cent. of all wearing apparel.  I think no one would suggest a flat rate.  I think it would be found that the articles of consumption for Jamesie or Pádraig going to school and for the ballet girl and dancing master would be different.  Jamesie's boots would not bear as heavy a tax as the pumps of the dancing master, and the incidence of the tax on wearing apparel would be so varied as to ensure that purely luxury articles would be much more highly taxed than the necessary articles which would be in constant regular use by the sons and daughters of farmers, and the sons and daughters of working men, and also that, in fact, assuming no change in the internal productive industries, the change in the tariff from sugar and tea to wearing apparel would add not one penny to the cost of living of the average family working in the country.  Deputy Wilson reminds me&mdash;it is quite sound and right&mdash;that the revenue would lose <Col N="431" /> if this eleven million pounds' worth of goods, instead of being imported in a complete stage, were brought in raw, and manufactured here to the extent that home manufacture replaces imported manufacture.  Perfectly true, but no one is suggesting that you were going within one year to produce eleven million pounds' worth of manufactured goods to replace importation.</P>
      <P>There will be a very gradual process and the incidence of duties would necessarily vary with the requirements of succeeding years, as they do in every other country which has the same problem to solve.  I put that forward as an illustration that it is quite possible from a revenue point of view to readjust your taxation in such a way as will gradually improve the productive capacity of this country, and that as you are improving the productive capacity you are at the same time creating new sources of taxation.  I would like to have said a word or two about the possibility, even within the new budget that may come forward, of raising revenue by tariffs on a minor scale, not primarily and solely as protection but the creating of development funds for the assistance of industries within the country by other means than protection.  I again draw attention to the fact that in New Zealand they raised anything from half a million to six hundred thousand pounds a year for a number of years past by a one per cent. primage duty and a duty of that kind; even one per cent. ad valorem, might well create a fund in this country, if imposed upon commodities which are not already dutiable, of not less than five hundred thousand pounds a year, which will be a considerable sum if wisely expended for improving and developing technical education and industrial research, and, perhaps, even the organisation of marketing facilities and the advertising of well made Irish products.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Your Committee, though it had a duty to examine into all such projects, failed to say anything of value about such schemes or such proposals as may have been put forward.  There were to my knowledge, suggested, diminishing tariffs for the purpose of assisting the technical equipment of factories, industrial <Col N="432" /> research and technical development.  That was surely within the scope of the enquiry but it is dismissed with a sentence.  I hope, therefore, that other factors outside the purely and narrowly economic considerations which were considered by the Committee will be taken into account by the Government itself.  We cannot think in terms of commercial economics alone.  We must think in terms of the nation, and those who compose the nation and their future.  I submit that it is necessary not only that full consideration should be given to all those factors, but that the public should be made aware, without any unnecessary delay, of what the intentions of the Government are in respect to future fiscal policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Much of what Deputy Johnson said is of great force and weight, and I do not at present propose to comment on it, because I should like to think over it more carefully.  I would suggest that there are factors which he has overlooked, that modern science, for example, is continually bringing every part and unit of the world closer, and that no such thing as a self-contained community can exist. Self-interest is still the guiding rule of mankind, and it would be very hard by any system of commercial tariff whatever, to neutralise the advantage of accessibility to minerals and so on. However you may try to alter the course of nature, you will find it difficult to do so.  With regard to his definite constructive proposal of a tax on wearing apparel, I think there is a point which must be taken into consideration, and that is the question of how the tax is to be collected.  Tea and sugar come in wholesale in bulk, and it is easy to collect the taxes on them.  Wearing apparel would, I presume, include partly worn apparel and new apparel. I hope he will include the new and the old, otherwise what would happen would be that the slop suit manufacturers would shake a suit out, three or four times, put stains on it, and so escape the tax.  New Zealand has not passenger steamers arriving two or three times a day.  If Deputy Johnson were to go to Westminster on Monday to see the triumph of Labour, when he <Col N="433" /> came back to Dún Laoghaire, he would find a difficulty if the Customs Officer were to take out all his suits and closely examine them.  His clothes would be classified, some as luxurious suits, and others less luxurious&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>How do they do it in other countries?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>They do it in New Zealand, for instance, where only one ship arrives in the week, or in the United States, where boats arrive two or three times a week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Did you ever hear of a place called Canada?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I have heard of Canada.  The position is much the same there.  Surely Deputy Johnson does not suggest that there is a mail boat running from Montreal twice a day to Holyhead.  It is difficult to do this in this country.  I put a concrete point to Deputy Johnson.  Every week there comes to this country theatrical companies. Are their costumes to be taxed in Dún Laoghaire, and again when they go to Belfast?  Will the kimono of &ldquo;Madam Butterfly&rdquo; and robes of &ldquo;Iolanthe&rdquo; pay a tax here?  There are difficulties that Deputy Johnson has not yet considered.  Before the Minister for Finance accepts the suggestion, he would do well to give a certain amount of consideration to it, and to study the situation in Canada, as Deputy Johnson suggests.  As regards Deputy Milroy's motion, I do not disagree with it. I should have supported it had it not been for the speech he made.  The motion itself is a pious expression which I think members of the Fiscal Commission could agree to.  They said in their report that they did not deal with the question fully.  I am not going to oppose it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are a great many facts in the situation to be considered, and, like everyone else, I am not a doctrinaire in this matter.  I am not setting up Free Trade as a fetish, and on one or two points I am myself disposed to criticise some of the actions of the Commission. I am not a Cobdenite.  Cobden was a very great man, but a bad prophet. Very few of his prophecies as to what <Col N="434" /> would be done under Free Trade were justified by the event.  When we examine what we might call the minority report of the Commission we begin to realise some of the difficulties with which the Commissioners were confronted. In one or two cases Deputy Milroy made statements which, in my experience, are almost wholly the reverse of the facts.  I take one case.  He said it was notorious that the cost of living was lower in the protected countries of Western Europe than it is in England under Free Trade.  That, as far as my experience goes, is not the case.  So, I listened carefully for Deputy Milroy's evidence.  His notes were voluminous, and it is possible he may have got them mixed.  The evidence he gave that the cost of living was lower in the protected countries of Western Europe, was the statement of a gentleman called Coughlan, speaking in 1903 about New South Wales and Victoria, which are not precisely in Western Europe.  If you are going to prove things by statements of that kind the procedure is akin to that of the Juror in &ldquo;Alice in Wonderland,&rdquo; who wrote down all the dates on slates, added them up, and reduced the answer to pounds, shillings and pence.  Then Deputy Milroy produces another witness from Western Europe, Sir John Bowring, a most remarkable man, of whom an Irish historian, Mr. Justin McCarthy, said he was &ldquo;almost invariably in the wrong and when in the right managed to assert it in a manner at once untimely, imprudent and indecent.&rdquo; That is Deputy Milroy's witness.  I certainly did not gather from Deputy Milroy's speech, though I knew it already, that this witness died in the year 1872 and that the Report to which Deputy Milroy alluded and quoted as showing how Prussia had advanced and improved her conditions under a protective system, was written in 1839. That is Deputy Milroy's idea of &ldquo;stoppress&rdquo; news.</P>
    <P>As a matter of fact, those years from 1839 to 1875 approximately were years of great prosperity not only in protectionist Europe, but in free trade England.  During those years Gladstone reduced the income tax to 4d. in the £, and talked of abolishing it altogether. These years are not parallel <Col N="435" /> years by which we can judge the state of things in which we find ourselves now, when half the wealth of the world has been blown away by war.  So, I am afraid, I am not persuaded of that happening by Deputy Milroy's statement.</P>
    <P>It is hard to compare the cost of living in any Continental country with the cost of living in Ireland, because the conditions are different; the currency is different.  Last spring I was in Italy and France.  It is very hard to compare the cost of macaroni in, for instance, Rome and in Ringsend, because in Rome macaroni is a necessity of life; in Ringsend it is more or less an ornament. There are things you can compare the prices of, such as eggs, which are the same everywhere, or should be.  I found that eggs in Rome cost very much the same, or perhaps a halfpenny less than eggs in Ireland, and that the workman who bought the eggs was getting something like 75 per cent. lower wages. Some things are cheap on the Continent, but they are generally things which depend on human labour.  You can take a cab in Rome and drive a distance for 2½d. that a Dublin jarvey would charge you 2/6 for.  It depends on the labour.  You cannot only take into account the cost of living in Continental countries; you must also take into account the cost of living.  I think Deputy Milroy will find in all these countries of Continental Europe, whose example he urged us to adopt, that the standard of living at present is far lower than in Ireland.</P>
    <P>I have a word to say as to the Report of the Committee.  Deputy Milroy said that its conclusions were inaccurate and sometimes malignantly misleading.  As far as the personnel of the Committee is concerned, there is only one of them I should know if I met him in the street.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy's quotation was not exact.  I said &ldquo;Its survey was incomplete, its premises inaccurate, and its conclusions misleading, sometimes malignantly misleading.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the correction, but really I have not the time that Deputy Milroy had, and consequently I have condensed some of his remarks. As I said, I am not personally known to <Col N="436" /> any of the Committee except one, and, therefore, there is no animus in my remarks, and I am not disposed to take up the cudgels on personal grounds.  I know nothing of the Chairman beyond the fact that the Government selected him to fill a responsible post, and that, at any rate, he has experience of living in a protected country.  Two of the others I know very little about, except that I have read a book of Professor Henry's, which seems to be a good work.  I gather that Professor Smith must have some ability, because it is not at all easy for an Irishman to rescue a position from English competition. There are two others.  Deputy Milroy complained the Committee had ignored the economic history of Ireland.  When Deputy Milroy wants to study the economic history of Ireland, what book does he take down if he wants it in a ready and convenient form?  I do not know, but if I wanted to do it, I would take down the works of a member of the Commission.  Dr. George O'Brien's are the standard works on the economic history of Ireland, and presumably that history was in his mind when he helped to prepare and sign the report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>He had forgotten about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I come to the last name&mdash;Professor Bastable.  It is ridiculous to say that Professor Bastable knows nothing about economics. In any discussion on economics anywhere you go Professor Bastable is quoted as one of the highest authorities on the subject.  If you need any proof you have the fact that he has been appointed Examiner in Universities all over the world, from Cambridge to New Zealand.  New Zealand takes its economics from a member of this Committee. It is not the custom of Universities to select as their Examiners persons who are inaccurate in their premises and misleading, and sometimes malignantly misleading.  I cannot help thinking that Deputy Milroy exaggerated the case.  It is very small encouragement to men of distinction to put their time at the service of the State&mdash;and I say this seriously&mdash;if they are to be stigmatised in those terms. Criticisms such as Deputy Johnson has <Col N="437" /> made no one takes exception to. Everyone is prepared to have their doings criticised on the merits, but I think that epithets such as Deputy Milroy used are not conducive to the public benefit.</P>
      <P>It seems to me that a motion of this kind is inseparable from the legislative independence of Ireland, because our predecessors in Grattan's Parliament had to listen to very much the same kind of speeches and hear very much the same kind of debate in the year 1783.  I turned to Lecky the other day for a description of the conditions in these times, and I find this in the sixth volume, chapter 24:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Irish letters continually speak of food risen almost to famine prices: of great multitudes of workmen unemployed: illegal combinations of workmen (I am afraid that is what they called Trades Unions in those days): industry in all its forms lamentably depressed.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The spokesman of the protectionist interest in those days was a gentleman called Luke Gardiner, after whom Gardiner's Row and Gardiner's Place are called.  He was one of the representatives of County Dublin, but his motive for intervening in the debate was not the same as Deputy Johnson's. He was annoyed with the Government because they had refused to give him a Peerage.  I acquit Deputy Johnson of that.  I hope Deputy Milroy, if he has not read Mr. Gardiner's speeches will do so, because he will find them very familiar.  In one of them he said: &ldquo;I wish to call attention to the poor distressed manufacturers.&rdquo;  I heard something like that here the other day. Finally, he worked up to his conclusion:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The only way to serve the manufacturers of Ireland was to lay such duties on imports as might counterbalance the great capital of the English, the low price of their wool and their great exactness in furnishing goods.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That was very much Deputy Johnson's argument now.  What was the result?  Those measures were debated in 1783 by the Irish Parliament <Col N="438" /> and they were rejected by overwhelming majorities.  That is what Deputy Milroy calls the wise protective policy of Grattan's Parliament.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. MILROY Mr. MILROY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MILROY</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what Deputy Milroy calls any such thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>At any rate, these are the facts.  That was Grattan's Parliament, and they rejected protective duties.  They adopted one protective duty which I did not hear recommended by Deputy Milroy, the one on the import of grain.  The then Chancellor of the Exchequer, Sir John Foster, also adopted a system of bounties to assist both manufacturers and tillage. To what extent the Minister for Finance will be able to follow in the footsteps of his predecessor I do not know.  I believe there is good in that. All historians declare that Foster's Act was the keynote of the prosperity that afterwards came to Ireland.  Newenham, writing 25 years later, said it was the primary cause of the unprecedented increase in wages in the last 25 years, so that not only did the farmer and the grocer benefit, but the labourer and the wage earner also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have done with the past.  I come to the present.  I think it is common ground that there are three evils at the moment in this State.  One is the depressed condition of agriculture. Deputy Milroy says that will be remedied when he has flourishing manufactures in every country town, when Mullingar becomes another Manchester, and when a new Sheffield arises in Skibbereen; that then the farmer will have a good market at his own door and will prosper.  That seems to be like the old proverb, &ldquo;Live horse and you'll get grass.&rdquo;  I think some immediate relief, whether on the lines of Sir John Foster or on other lines, is needed by agriculture.  The second thing, which is generally admitted as an evil&mdash;I do not know whether Deputy Johnson accepts it&mdash;is the high cost of living.  On going out of the Dáil to the street the first man you meet will say: &ldquo;Are not things a terrible price?&rdquo;  Deputy Milroy's remedy was a transfer of taxation. He wanted to take the tax off tea, sugar and jam, and put it on clothing. I do not know why Deputy Milroy <Col N="439" /> should be so unkind to jam.  Perhaps he does not like jam.  Jam, after all, is a manufactured product which we ought to be able to manufacture in Ireland. It is made from fruit, or it is supposed to be made from fruit.  At any rate, it is made from something the farmer can grow, even if he grows turnips.  I can see no reason why Deputy Milroy should extend protection to the clothing manufacturer and refuse it to the jam manufacturer.  If you are going to adopt protection, surely every industry has a right to claim it alike?  I think Deputy Milroy, however, is of opinion that protective duties are not likely to raise prices.  I can give him tangible proof.  Here is a hat that I bought in Paris nine months ago.  It is not a bad hat, but it cost approximately 8/- more than it would have cost either in London or Dublin.  It is a French made hat, and being French made, there was no import duty upon it, but the manufacturer put up the price because he was selling in a protected market.  He, therefore, could afford to put up the price without fearing foreign competition. All my experience goes to show that if you put on a duty, the customer, the consumer, whatever you wish to call him, has to pay it.</P>
    <P>I now come to the third point.  It is a point I am glad to say on which I may be able to meet Deputy Milroy. To a certain extent there is in every industry unemployment.  I do think that on that particular point the report of the Committee might have been fuller and more carefully studied. Deputy Sears spoke with great eloquency yesterday in support of a bounty, and said we were sending young men and women abroad to labour in other countries for our own market.  That is an evil that ought to be remedied.  I have felt that deeply. If possible, further consideration should be given to unemployment and emigration, in view of the fact that we are exporting our surplus manhood. The Committee do not seem to have realised that fact.  They do not seem to have realised that at present we are producing more people, and probably in the future will produce even more, than we can find employment for.  I <Col N="440" /> do think that further examination of the problem on these lines is necessary and desirable.  As I said I approach this question not from the point of view that Free Trade is a great principle. It is solely a matter of expediency.  I would prefer before making the great revolutionary change that Deputy Johnson suggests&mdash;transforming the whole basis of taxation&mdash;that he should ask the Minister for Finance to see what is possible within the limits of our present fiscal system. Deputy Sears, I think, referred to beet sugar.  Within the limits of our present fiscal system the Minister can give a rebate to beet sugar produced in Ireland.  I think that would be a perfectly sound thing to do, economically. If anyone is prepared to put up a factory for beet sugar, and put up the necessary capital, he might well promise that for 10 years he would be exempt from Excise duties.  The policy foreshadowed by the President on the subject of housing is right, that a preference, where possible, should be given to Irish slates and cement.  In all these ways we could encourage industries without going into this vista of protection.  One reason why it would be injudicious to do so is that we have very little promise from those who gave evidence before the Commission that they would be able to give increased employment, and that of large established firms that give big employment, the majority of them were either indifferent or hostile.  I think that if we are urged to act now without further information, and without further knowledge, we shall be in the position of people who sink their ship in the hope that they will be able to make a very satisfactory raft out of what remains.</P>
    <P>Deputy Milroy said that countries can prosper under protective systems. Countries can also prosper under Free Trade.  It is the transition period that is the trouble.  I feel that this country has had so much unsettlement and disturbance in the last eight or ten years that it is scarcely wise to add economic disturbance and unsettlement. You can sail a boat above Niagara, you can sail a boat below Niagara, but sailing a boat down Niagara is a different affair.  I therefore hope that <Col N="441" /> while the Government will not cease to interest themselves in this question they will hesitate before they take a leap in the dark.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>As it is now practically 4 o'clock, I beg to move the adjournment of the debate.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned until Wednesday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ADJOURNMENT. -" RHead="FLOODS IN TIPPERARY">
    <Title>ADJOURNMENT. - FLOODS IN TIPPERARY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the Dáil until 3 o'clock on Wednesday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that Deputy White, of the Farmers' Party, has withdrawn the notice of his intention to raise the question of distress in Tirconaill.  I just want to bring to the notice of the Government the position that has been created in many parts of the South of Ireland, particularly in Tipperary, by floods.  I am sure that every member of the Dáil is conversant, through the newspapers, with the hardship that has been created during the last few days.  The following appeared in yesterday's issue of the &ldquo;Freeman's Journal&rdquo; in connection with the town of Clonmel:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Those living in cottages in the Old Bridge district are in a pitiable plight.  Dozens of workers' families were flooded out, and had to climb into lofts, etc., to escape the water, and were imprisoned there.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is a terrible state of affairs, and I want to suggest that the cause of it is bad drainage.  I want to suggest to the Government that it is about time for them to try to get some scheme on foot for proper drainage.  This is not confined to urban district.  For many years very serious damage has been done in agricultural districts by the continual flooding of rivers.  I do not intend to delay the Dáil on this matter, but I suggest to the Government that they ought to take steps to prevent a recurrence of such floods, which do such tremendous damage to the agricultural community, and, in this case, to people <Col N="442" /> living in urban districts, and I suggest that in this case also the Government should do something to relieve the distress caused to the people whose houses have been flooded.  Their property, such as bedding and other articles, has been destroyed, and at present most of the poor people of Clonmel and Carrick-on-Suir in particular are housed in the convents and in the workhouses.  We read in this morning's papers of water five feet deep rushing through houses in Carrick-on-Suir, washing away all the furniture and bedding belonging to the poor people.  That is all I have to say on the matter, but I would like to impress on the Government that proper schemes of drainage should be undertaken immediately in order to prevent a recurrence of this.  I am sure Deputies on the Farmers' Benches will agree with me, because they have been labouring the fact that serious damage has been done in agricultural districts for a long number of years, owing to the flooding of the rivers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I may say that a very disastrous state of affairs exists over a very wide area in the County Kildare, computed at 100,000 acres, at present flooded by the river Barrow.  A gentleman, who is known to many members of the Dáil, Mr. Cobb, of Portarlington, who lives in the middle of the district, was here yesterday and told me that in some parts the roads are flooded to the extent of five or six feet.  This has entailed a great deal of misery and privation upon the people of the district. I think it would be a very good time for some members of the Government, who like a little diversion and holiday, to go to Monasterevan and charter a schooner.  They would have some nice experiences.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise to support Deputy Morrissey in his suggestion that strong steps should be taken by the Government to relieve the distress caused by the flooding in the towns of Clonmel, Carrick-on-Suir and Tipperary, and also that some steps should be taken to remove the causes of this periodic flooding in these districts.  I am aware, from my knowledge of the towns in question, that there are a great many low-lying streets, mostly <Col N="443" /> inhabited by the poorer classes, and I understand, from the accounts in the papers, that these streets have been flooded, and that a great number of the poorer people have been obliged to leave their homes, and have been taken away in boats.  I know that where flooding takes place, dirty water and all that kind of thing gets into the houses, injures the little furniture, and all the household belongings of the people, and that in many cases these houses become uninhabitable and become insanitary, owing to dampness. I do not think the local authorities have any power or any money for the relief of distress caused by this, and I think it would be rather a matter for the Government.  In particular, I would like to emphasise the necessity for removing the cause of this periodic flooding, and it applies not only to the urban, but to the rural areas.  There are large areas in Tipperary drained by the Suir and the Anner, which are periodically flooded, and I believe that this flooding could, in a measure at least, be relieved if steps were taken by the Government.  It is an engineering matter to a large extent, and I am not competent to deal with the methods which could be used, but I understand that considerable relief could be given with a comparatively low expenditure.  In North Tipperary, a great deal of damage is done to agricultural lands by the flooding of rivers.  I understand that the rivers are silted up, and this has been caused, to a large extent, by trees and other obstructions, which have been allowed to accumulate.  I would suggest that the Government ought really seriously to consider the advisability of segregating portions of the unemployment money for purposes of this kind.  This is the kind of constructive work we want to see given, and I would suggest that money would be much better expended on this sort of work, and that the morale and the self-respect of the workers would be kept up to a much higher standard by being thus employed than by hanging round and going periodically to draw this demoralising dole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Deputy Morrissey in drawing attention to this matter. <Col N="444" /> Commissions have been sitting continually, and the ablest engineers in the country for the last 50 or 60 years have made recommendations on the question of drainage.  I think it is about time that the Government, who are anxious to find employment for demobilised soldiers and to relieve unemployment generally, should consider the question of the drainage of the rivers. In the constituency I represent a body of men have formed themselves into a Committee for the purpose of promoting a Private Bill dealing with the drainage of the Barrow.  That is not a matter that should be left to a few individuals in a particular area.  It is a national duty for the Government to deal with the question as a whole to prevent the recurrence of such things as have occurred at present.  I think the Government should seriously consider the question of the drainage of the rivers in the months of April and May next, and they should not leave questions of such national importance to a few individuals to spend private money in bringing in a Bill such as I have referred to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I also support the representations made by Deputy Morrissey in this connection.  I think the time has arrived when the Government should seriously consider the question of drainage in the Saorstát.  I have just received information that a good deal of land is under water in Co. Wexford. I know a good part of the railway line between Enniscorthy and Wexford is under water.  These matters should receive the serious consideration of the Government, and I urge on them the necessity of taking action on this very important matter as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that two questions have been raised, one the relief of immediate distress occasioned by flooding, and the other the general question of drainage.  If these be the two points put forward, with regard to the first it is a matter for the local authorities, and I think it would be well that people in such localities should make some effort to look after themselves. It is not a good policy to be always looking to the Government for every possible form of assistance or <Col N="445" /> initiative in everything that is to be done.  It is a local liability, so far as I know, and the Government spends a considerable amount of money in making grants to local authorities of one sort or other during the year.  It is really contributing as much to these grants as it can possibly afford.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards the second question, that has been under consideration, but it is not in an advanced state, and the general impression is that there is no immediate chance of doing anything during this year, and that at this particular time when the floods are high is not the time, even if one had the money, when it could be profitably spent.  Suggestions have been made by Deputies, and it has been urged that we should take them into serious consideration. We have had them under consideration for some time past.  It is a very big subject, and it may cost a <Col N="446" /> good deal of money to deal with the drainage question in the immediate future.  For the next two or three years any expenditure on foot of improvements, or expenditure of any kind, must be very carefully planned, very carefully considered, and the proposals must be cut down to the lowest possible sum that would be in keeping with efficiency, but I can assure the Deputies who have spoken that we are seriously considering the question, and I do not think it is at all likely that we will be in a position to make any further pronouncement on the matter within the next two or three months. We do not anticipate we will be in a position to say anything on the subject sooner than May or possibly June.</P>
    <P>The Dáil adjourned at 4.12 p.m. until 3 p.m. Wednesday, 23rd January, 1924.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DEPENDENT'S" RHead="ALLOWANCE (PALLASGREEN)">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE (PALLASGREEN).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA">
      <NameTxt>DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received repeated applications from Mrs. Susan Ryan, Farranfina, Pallasgreen, Co. Limerick, for dependent's allowance in respect of her son, <Col N="379" /> Michael Ryan, No. 44601, 63rd Battalion, and if he will take steps to have payment of this claim expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Necessary local investigations of Mrs. Ryan's claim have been delayed owing to changes of her address.  Steps are being taken to have them completed at the earliest possible date.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="LISDOONVARNA (CLARE) INTERNEE">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - LISDOONVARNA (CLARE) INTERNEE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár) PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)">
      <NameTxt>PÁDRAIG O hOGÁIN (An Clár)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if it is proposed to detain Patrick O'Connor, Ballytigue, Lisdoonvarna, Co. Clare, as an internee, considering the fact that his father, now helpless, is without any one to care him at home.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Arrangements are being made for the release of Mr. Patrick O'Connor.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - ARMY" RHead="FUEL ACCOUNT (WESTMEATH)">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - ARMY FUEL ACCOUNT (WESTMEATH).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEÁN O LAIDHIN SEÁN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that Hugh Brennan, Tyrrellspass, Westmeath, has made numerous applications for payment of the amount of £5 for the supplying of fuel to the National Army stationed in Tyrrellspass from May to August, 1922; whether payment will be expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mr. Brennan's account as furnished was paid.  He states that there is a balance due to him, but no account for this can be traced.  The matter is under investigation.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DEPENDENT'S" RHead="ALLOWANCE (KILCOCK)">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE (KILCOCK).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. DAVID HALL Mr. DAVID HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVID HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether the claim of Mrs. Jane Balfe, Garradice, Kilcock, for dependent's allowance in respect of her son's service&mdash;Private Philip Balfe, No. 25792&mdash;in the National Army has been considered, and whether payment of allowance will be expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mrs. Balfe's claim was disallowed after due investigation on the ground that the amount normally contributed by her son to his <Col N="380" /> home for a reasonable period prior to his enlistment was less than the minimum required by the regulations, 12/- per week, before an allowance might be issued.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - CO. MEATH" RHead="DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - CO. MEATH DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. D. HALL Mr. D. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether a claim for dependent's allowance has been received from Mrs. A. Nevin, Loughan, Kells, Co. Meath, in respect of the service of her son, Private Thomas Nevin, No. 20201, C. Company, 48th Battalion, Mullingar Barracks; whether he is aware that prior to joining the National Army Private Nevin contributed £2 per week to the support of his home; whether the claim of Mrs. Nevin will receive immediate consideration with a view to expediting payment of dependent's allowance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mrs. Nevin's claim was disallowed.  In view of information contained in the question, it is being reinvestigated, and the necessary enquiries will be completed as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - BALLYMAHON" RHead="(LONGFORD) OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - BALLYMAHON (LONGFORD) OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether he is aware that Catherine Clyne, Ballymahon, Co. Longford, was granted 4s. per week old age pension in 1921, her husband being in receipt of a salary of 35s. per week; whether this amount is now reduced to 2s. per week, and whether the Minister will consider this case with a view to increasing this allowance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no record of an appeal having been received in this case, and, consequently, the Ministry have no information as to the yearly means of the claimant.</P>
      <P>If, as stated, the husband has a salary of 35s a week, and if there are no other means, the wife's moiety for calculation purposes would be at least £45 10s. a year, and the old age pension allowable thereon under Statute would be 2s. a week, and that rate could not be increased.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DRIMOLEAGUE" RHead="ACCOUNT FOR MILITARY BILLETING">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DRIMOLEAGUE ACCOUNT FOR MILITARY BILLETING.</Title>
    <Col N="381" />
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="TADHG O MURCHADHA TADHG O MURCHADHA">
      <NameTxt>TADHG O MURCHADHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state when a balance of an account amounting to £59 14s. 4d. due to Jeremiah Collins, Drimoleague, in respect of billeting of troops will be paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The portion of this account outstanding is under investigation, and will be paid within the next few days.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - CORK CLAIM" RHead="FOR DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - CORK CLAIM FOR DEPENDENT'S ALLOWANCE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="TADHG O MURCHADHA TADHG O MURCHADHA">
      <NameTxt>TADHG O MURCHADHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether a claim for dependent's allowance lodged by Mrs. Kate Hurley, Nedineagh, Dunmanway, Co. Cork, in respect of the service of her son, Volunteer John Hurley, No. 25474, Pay Book No. 20972, C. Company, Drimoleague, who joined the National Army in Dunmanway on 23rd August, 1922, was disallowed; whether he is aware that Volunteer Hurley was, prior to enlisting, a permanent road labourer in receipt of £2 5s. 0d. a week from Cork Council, and whether Mrs. Hurley's claim will be reconsidered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The claim of Mrs. Hurley was disallowed after due investigation, on the ground that the extent of dependence, that is to say, the amount normally contributed by her son to his home over and above the cost of his own maintenance therein for a reasonable period prior to his enlistment, was less than the minimum required by the regulations, 12/- per week, before an allowance might be issued.  It was ascertained that John Hurley had not been in regular employment prior to enlistment, that his average earnings were 24/- per week, and that the extent of dependence was about 8/- per week.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - ATHLONE" RHead="CLAIM FOR PERSONAL INJURIES">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - ATHLONE CLAIM FOR PERSONAL INJURIES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEÁN O LAIDHIN SEÁN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he is aware that a claim has been lodged by Mr. Chas. Donlon, Bastion Street, Athlone, for compensation for bodily injuries inflicted by members of the British <Col N="382" /> forces, on March 12th, 1921; whether, as Mr. Donlon is unable to follow his former occupation as harness maker, owing to the injuries received, settlement of this claim will be expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="MINISTER FOR FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER FOR FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>Mr. Donlon's claim is at present receiving attention, and there will be no avoidable delay in disposing of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - PAYMENT TO" RHead="CARBURY (KILDARE) SOLDIER">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - PAYMENT TO CARBURY (KILDARE) SOLDIER.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="AODH O CULACHAIN AODH O CULACHAIN">
      <NameTxt>AODH O CULACHAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that Thomas Gorman, of Coonagh, Carbury, Co. Kildare, Army No. 2234, Engineers Corps, attested 1st July, 1922; that he has not been paid corps proficiency pay of 3/- per day due to him for time worked as a carpenter from the 7th September, 1922, to the 27th March, 1923, in Edenderry Barracks, the officers in charge during that time being Commandant Flanagan, Lieutenant Dowling, Captain Hamilton, Captain Kenny, and Commandant Kelly; and whether instructions will be given to have payment expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Thomas Gorman served in the 45th Infantry Battalion, and not in the Engineers Corps. He was not employed as a tradesman, and he is not, therefore, entitled to proficiency pay.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>