<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="5" Month="Jun" Year="1924" Vol="7" No="20" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 5 Meitheamh 1924" DateEnglish="Thursday, 5 June 1924" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1907">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1907" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar a 3 a clog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - CIVIL SERVICE SALARIES">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - CIVIL SERVICE SALARIES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="TOMAS DE NOGLA TOMAS DE NOGLA">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS DE NOGLA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether he is now in a position to announce a decision in regard to the salaries of the &ldquo;Lytton entrants&rdquo; to the Clerical Grade of the Saorstát Civil Service, having regard to the fact that the salary scale for ex-National Army candidates to the same grade has been fixed in the recent announcement for an examination.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER FOR FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER FOR FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>A decision on this matter will be given in the course of a few days.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - BOUND VOLUMES OF STATUTES">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - BOUND VOLUMES OF STATUTES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="MAOLMHUIRE MAC EOCHADHA MAOLMHUIRE MAC EOCHADHA">
      <NameTxt>MAOLMHUIRE MAC EOCHADHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether he is aware that complaints are made by the members of the legal profession of the inconvenience arising from the failure of the Stationery Office to publish bound volumes of the Statutes passed in each session of the Oireachtas; and whether he will at once have arrangements made to remove the inconvenience in question by having such bound volumes published in respect of the past sessions and all future sessions as soon as conveniently can be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>Arrangements were made some time ago for the publication in bound volumes of the enactments of Dáil Eireann and of the Oireachtas (commencing from the opening of the first Dáil Eireann), to be continued by the publication of an annual volume of the legislation of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If there is any blame in the matter mentioned it cannot be laid at the door of the Stationery Office as, when the volumes are published, it has been decided that indexes to the statutes will be included.  The work on these indexes <Col N="1908" /> has been put in hand and it is hoped that the material will be handed over to the Stationery Office shortly.  It is confidently anticipated that any delay which has occurred in connection with the volumes of the Dáil and other statutes will not recur.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister be in a position to tell us, when we are dealing with the Stationery Office Estimates, what kind of policy they are adopting with regard to the prices of these publications?</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BENEFIT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BENEFIT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="PADRAIG O hOGAIN (An Clár) PADRAIG O hOGAIN (An Clár)">
      <NameTxt>PADRAIG O hOGAIN (An Clár)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he is aware of the delay in paying unemployment insurance benefit to Patrick McNamara, Upper Drumbiggle, Ennis, and if he will expedite a decision on the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Patrick McNamara of Upper Drumbiggle, Ennis, claimed benefit on the 2nd January, 1924, but his claim could not be allowed because he failed to satisfy the first statutory condition for the receipt of benefit, having had only nine contributions paid for him at any time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="PADRAIG O hOGAIN (An Clár) PADRAIG O hOGAIN (An Clár)">
      <NameTxt>PADRAIG O hOGAIN (An Clár)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state the reason of the delay in paying unemployment insurance benefit to Martin Casey, Tiermaclane, Ennis, Co. Clare, notwithstanding the fact that the claimant complied with the regulations governing the payment of these benefits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Martin Casey was prosecuted and convicted in November, 1923, for claiming and obtaining unemployment benefit in respect of days on which he was employed. Some delay necessarily occurred in the payment of a subsequent claim because of the complications resulting from the irregular receipt of benefit by him on the previous claims and the benefit wrongfully obtained had to be recovered from him.  This matter has now been adjusted and a further payment of six days' benefit was made to Mr. Casey on Friday, the 30th May, 1924.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1909" /> Payment on the claim lodged by Mr. Casey last March was suspended pending adjustment of the question arising on his previous claims.  Instructions are being issued to the branch manager at Ennis which will enable him to pay all outstanding benefit due to Mr. Casey within the next few days.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - KILDARE TRADER'S ACCOUNT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - KILDARE TRADER'S ACCOUNT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="AODH O CULACHAIN AODH O CULACHAIN">
      <NameTxt>AODH O CULACHAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that a sum of £19 19s. 6d. is still due to Mr. William Ryan, saddler and harness maker, of Claregate Street, Kildare, on account of saddles, etc., commandeered by Commandant McGreel, 1st Cavalry Reserve, on the 1st July, 1922, who gave an official order for same and told Mr. Ryan that he would be paid in due course, whether Captain O'Donoghue some time afterwards asked for and was given the official order, so that the claim might be verified; further, whether more than ten applications for payment have been sent in without result, and whether he will have enquiries made with a view to immediate payment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="MINISTER for DEFENCE (The President) William T. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for DEFENCE (The President)</NameTxt>
      <P>A payable order for £19 19s. 6d. in settlement of his claim has been forwarded to Mr. Ryan.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- EX-SOLDIER'S CLAIM FOR PENSION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - EX-SOLDIER'S CLAIM FOR PENSION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="AODH O CULACHAIN AODH O CULACHAIN">
      <NameTxt>AODH O CULACHAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that Thomas Hughes, of Fair Green, Naas, Army No. 44196, or 12329, 16th Infantry Battalion, Keogh Barracks, Dublin, who attested on the 12th July, 1922, and was discharged as medically unfit on the 20th October, 1923, is unable to work, as the result of a bullet wound received in the left hand when the Anglo-American Oil Company's premises at the East Wall was attacked by Irregular forces on the 7th February, 1923; further, whether three applications for pension were sent in without result, and whether, as this young man is one of a large family, whose father is also disabled, he will expedite consideration of this claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>One application <Col N="1910" /> only appears to have been received from Mr. Hughes.  The usual form was sent to him for completion on the 11th December last, but, it appears, has not been returned.  A further form has now been sent, and on its return, duly completed, the case will be considered with the least possible delay.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- CLAIM BY DUBLIN HACKNEY CAR DRIVER">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - CLAIM BY DUBLIN HACKNEY CAR DRIVER.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. ALFRED BYRNE Mr. ALFRED BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ALFRED BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will take steps to have the claim of Mr. William Brown, 65 Ballybough Road, Fairview, reconsidered; if he is aware that Mr. Brown, hackney car driver, was seriously injured and his car wrecked by a military motor car on 9th July, 1922, and that after nearly two years waiting has been informed that as the car was being irregularly used, and the officer using it was not on military duty at the time, the claim cannot be entertained as a charge against Army Funds, and if he will see that funds are provided for compensating the claimant in this and other cases of a similar kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been decided to reconsider Mr. Brown's claim with a view to ascertaining whether an <i>ex gratia</i> payment might be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- CASTLEREA CLAIM FOR COMMANDEERED LORRY">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - CASTLEREA CLAIM FOR COMMANDEERED LORRY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="TOMAS MAC EOIN (for Tomás O Conaill) TOMAS MAC EOIN (for Tomás O Conaill)">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS MAC EOIN (for Tomás O Conaill)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received a claim from Mr. Thomas J. Caulfield, of Main Street, Castlerea, on account of a Garford 350cwt. lorry, commandeered by National troops on July 2nd, 1922; if he is in a position to say whether this claim has yet been settled, and, if not, whether he will see that the matter is expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>A cheque for £90 in favour of Mr. Caulfield was issued on the 18th March last to his solicitor, Mr. Staunton, Castlerea, in full settlement of the claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - RETURN OF SURRENDERED GUNS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - RETURN OF SURRENDERED GUNS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="SEOIRSE DE BHULBH SEOIRSE DE BHULBH">
      <NameTxt>SEOIRSE DE BHULBH</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that two guns surrendered by Mr. R. Woodburne, Hazelhatch, Co. Dublin, have <Col N="1911" /> been located, one at the Curragh and the other at Island Bridge, and whether he will give instructions to have them returned to their owner as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>One double-barrelled fowling piece and 48 rounds of sporting ammunition registered as the property of Mr. R. Woodburne have been traced.  The gun and ammunition will be returned to Mr. Woodburne on his furnishing to the Chief Ordnance Officer.  Island Bridge Barracks, Dublin, the original receipt of their surrender and a police permit authorising their possession now.  Notification accordingly was sent to Mr. Woodburne on the 14th December last at the address the Commons, Rathcoole. It has not been possible to trace a second gun belonging to Mr. Woodburne or an application for the return of same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of the President's answer, I would ask him is he aware that the first gun has not been returned to Mr. Woodburne?  Will the President, in view of the fact that great damage has been done by birds to crops in that part of the country, kindly see, if possible, that not only these guns are returned to this man, but that the guns will be returned to every man in that area in cases where the guns can be traced?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course application must be made in each instance and it depends upon the owners having a permit from the police&mdash;that is apart altogether from the difficulty of tracing these guns.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="Mr. WOLFE Mr. WOLFE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WOLFE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am speaking of cases where the authorities have the guns.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, yes, we will do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- COMPENSATION FOR RATHANGAN HOUSE">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - COMPENSATION FOR RATHANGAN HOUSE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeWolfe" hpid="SEOIRSE DE BHULBH SEOIRSE DE BHULBH">
      <NameTxt>SEOIRSE DE BHULBH</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that a house in Rathangan, Co. Kildare, was commandeered by the Military from Mr. James Hamilton, in July, 1922; <Col N="1912" /> that he was promised compensation at the time, but that no money has since been forthcoming, and whether he will see that this claim is investigated and discharged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware that a house in Rathangan in which a Mrs. Hamilton resided was occupied by troops, and that other accommodation was provided for her.  No claim in respect of the occupation of her residence has been received at Headquarters from either Mr. or Mrs. Hamilton.  If particulars of a claim are furnished to the Chief Claims Officer, Portobello Barracks, Dublin, it will be duly considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- DISUSED WORKHOUSE LAND AT SCARIFF">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - DISUSED WORKHOUSE LAND AT SCARIFF.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="PADRAIG O hOGAIN (An Clár) PADRAIG O hOGAIN (An Clár)">
      <NameTxt>PADRAIG O hOGAIN (An Clár)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government and Public Health if he will state whether the land attached to the disused workhouse at Scariff has been applied for by workers in the district; if he has considered favourably the application, and if, in consideration of the destitution in that district, he will have the land apportioned as early as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT and PUBLIC HEALTH (Mr. Burke) Seamus Aloysius Bourke">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT and PUBLIC HEALTH (Mr. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer to the first part of the question is in the affirmative.  On 28th March last a general order was made empowering county councils to make short lettings of workhouse buildings and lands on certain conditions. The applicants should now approach the county council on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>Have county councils in An Saorstát been circularised on that matter&mdash;are the county councils aware of that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not answer that question off-hand.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="EXTENDED" RHead="SITTING">
    <Title>EXTENDED SITTING.</Title>
    <P>Ordered: That the Dáil do sit until 10.30 p.m., with an interval from 6.30 p.m. to 7.15 p.m. (Minister for Finance.)</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="RESIGNATION OF" RHead="ATTORNEY-GENERAL">
    <Title>RESIGNATION OF ATTORNEY-GENERAL.</Title>
    <Col N="1913" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá leitir fachta agam ón Teachta Aodh O Cinnéidigh agtabhairt suas a shuidheacháin sa Dáil mar Theachta do Dháilcheanntar Chathair Bhaile Atha Cliath Theas.</P>
      <P>I have received a letter from Deputy Hugh Kennedy resigning his seat in the Dáil as Deputy for the Constituency of Dublin City South.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="STATE HARBOURS BILL," RHead="1924. FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>STATE HARBOURS BILL, 1924.  FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg leave of the Dáil to introduce a Bill to place certain harbours under the control of the Commissioners of Public Works in Ireland and to provide for the regulation of the amounts of the charges to be levied in such harbours under the control of the Commissioners aforesaid and for other purposes relating to the said harbours, and to change the name of Kingstown Harbour.</P>
      <P>This Bill deals with two harbours, Dun Laoghaire and Dunmore harbours. Each of these harbours is vested in Commissioners who were appointed by the Lord Lieutenant, but would in future be appointed by the Executive Council or the Governor-General.  In actual practice the same persons have been appointed Harbour Commissioners for Dun Laoghaire as have been Commissioners for Public Works.  But in their capacity as Harbour Commissioners for Dun Laoghaire they own and manage the harbour.  In their capacity of Commissioners for Public Works they maintain the harbour.  It is considered desirable that this duality should be ended and that the Commissioners of Public Works should maintain the harbours in one capacity.  It is also provided in the Bill that certain restrictions with regard to the power of the Harbour Commissioners to fix tolls and dues should be removed and that they should be able to fix such tolls and dues as seem to be suitable and appropriate.</P>
      <P>Leave to introduce Bill granted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a question under Standing Order 52 for Private Business which places <Col N="1914" /> on me an obligation if I consider this Bill a Bill which should be referred to the Examiner for Private Bills, to do so.  I would like, therefore, that the order for the Second Reading should not be fixed until Tuesday next if the Minister will agree.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="CRIMINAL JUSTICE (ADMINISTRATION)" RHead="BILL, 1924.&mdash;FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>CRIMINAL JUSTICE (ADMINISTRATION) BILL, 1924.&mdash;FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move for leave to introduce this Bill.  The object of it is to modernise certain forms of indictment which are statutory under the existing law and which are somewhat archaic and feudal in their phraseologies.  It is a rather urgent Bill, and in view of the setting up of the new courts we would be anxious to have it passed this Session.</P>
      <P>Agreed.  Second Stage ordered for Wednesday, 11th June.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="CRIMINAL JUSTICE" RHead="(EVIDENCE) BILL, 1924">
    <Title>CRIMINAL JUSTICE (EVIDENCE) BILL, 1924.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Bill which does not appear in the Orders of the Day, but I would ask the leave of the Dáil to introduce it.  The Bill is entitled Criminal Justice (Evidence) Bill, 1924.  It is a Bill to amend the law of evidence in criminal cases.  This is a Bill which the Attorney-General had prepared and worked on.  I really know very little about its contents myself. But I would ask the Deputies to give it its First Reading and enable it to be introduced and discussed next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that the Attorney-General is resigning his seat in the Dáil, I would like to ask are these Bills urgent?  I do think it is extremely desirable that we should have some professional guidance on a matter which is obviously a technical subject, and on which, as far as I know, Deputy Duggan is the only Minister with legal knowledge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I beg pardon of the Minister for Industry and Commerce, and the Local Government <Col N="1915" /> Minister, too, but I think they are not in very constant practice at the Bar, and I do feel that unless there is absolute urgency which could be proved and stated by the Government we ought not to proceed with these technical Bills just now.  I do not know whether the Attorney-General has resigned his office of Attorney-General as well as his membership of the Dáil, and whether it is the intention of the Government to bring in or appoint another Attorney-General who may or may not seek election to the Dáil. but I think, before proceeding with this Bill, that we ought to have some statement with regard to the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should not conclude because this Bill was not prepared in my department but was prepared in the department of the Attorney-General, that I would not be prepared at a later stage to meet all the technical points which he or other Deputies might wish to raise.  Naturally we will take immediate steps to fill the vacancy created by the resignation of the Attorney-General.  I do not anticipate that either of these Bills is of a nature that will call for the presence of the Attorney-General in the Dáil.  They are simply rather urgent administrative measures and they will not raise any very technical difficulties. We would be particularly anxious to get them through this session.  The Deputy may take it that with the crowded programme we have before us and with the number of other important measures that will have to be jettisoned if we are to have an adjournment in July these Bills are not lightly introduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Minister has promised that the vacancy created by the resignation of the Attorney-General will be filled immediately does he mean that he will move for the writ to be issued at once?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That does not arise at all.  It is a different question altogether.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree that that matter does not arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1916" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson will have another opportunity of asking that question.</P>
      <P>Leave granted.  Second Stage ordered for Thursday, June 12th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE" RHead="BILL, 1924. FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BILL, 1924.  FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask leave to introduce the Unemployment. Insurance Bill, 1924.  It is a Bill to amend the Unemployment Insurance Acts, 1920 to 1923, and for purposes connected therewith.  The main provisions of the Bill are to the following effect:&mdash;The first provision is to revive contributions which have been exhausted by the payment of benefit in the last year and to make this contribution again available to qualify for benefit. The second provision will be to make special arrangements for men demobilised from the Army who had been previously employed in insurable occupations. The method of doing that will be to credit them with an increased number of contributions in respect of the period of Army service.  The third provision will be the temporary suspension of certain disqualifications for benefits, due to insured contributors not having been able to obtain the necessary number of contributions.  I ask leave to introduce the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say whether it is the intention of the Executive Council to have this Bill passed through all its stages before the session ends?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The date from which I have arranged to work with this Bill, if it meets with the approval of the Dáil, is the 30th June. Consequently, it is my intention to impress on the Dáil the necessity of passing it before that date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. A. BYRNE Mr. A. BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say if the conditions will be made retrospective, or will they run from a certain date?  Will the Minister give credit to soldiers disbanded three or six months ago?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1917" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That matter will arise later.</P>
      <P>Leave granted.  Second Stage ordered for Wednesday, June 11th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="LOCAL ELECTIONS POSTPONEMENT (AMENDMENT)" RHead="BILL, 1924&mdash;FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>LOCAL ELECTIONS POSTPONEMENT (AMENDMENT) BILL, 1924&mdash;FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg leave to introduce the Local Elections Postponement (Amendment) Bill, 1924.  During the course of the debate on the Local Government Bill I explained that the date on which the local government elections will be held would to a great extent be regulated by the date at which I considered I could get the Local Government Bill, or the substance of it, passed through the Dáil and Seanad. I find now that it will be impossible to get that Bill through for some considerable time.  This places me in a rather awkward position.  At the present time under the Local Government Postponement (Amendment) Act of 1923 I have power to postpone elections till not later than the 30th September, 1924, and by an Order issued on the 22nd February last I postponed the elections till the 15th July.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If I do not get this Bill through before the 15th July it will be necessary to hold the elections on that date.  I am placed in a difficulty in this matter, as I believe all of us are most anxious to hold the local elections, or, at all events, the county council elections, as soon as possible, but there are difficulties in the way which make it practically impossible to do so.  In the ordinary course the election of rural district councillors should be held along with the county council elections.  If this Bill goes through in anything like its present form, there will be no necessity to hold the rural district council elections.  The rural district councils will cease to function after the Bill goes through.  For that reason it would be very foolish, I consider, on the part of the Dáil to hold those elections now. They would cost approximately £60,000&mdash;that is, the elections for rural district councils, and for that reason it is practically essential to postpone the district council elections.  With respect to the county councils, when the rural district councils cease to function <Col N="1918" /> the chairmen of the rural district councils will automatically cease to be members of the county council.  To remedy this, the Local Government Bill provides for an addition to the membership of the county council.  If the number of additional members necessary from this cause were generally small, there would be no very serious objection to allowing the county council to co-opt a few members, but in some counties the number of members to be co-opted will be more than the number of the elected members, and this would be contrary to every principle of democratic representation.  If we held the county council elections now we would, I am afraid, have to hold a further election on the passing of the Local Government Bill to fill these vacancies.  This would cost just as much as the election in July.  With regard to town elections, the cause for postponement is primarily one of cost. To quote from a letter I received from a certain local authority: &ldquo;The cost of the elections here on the last occasion was something about £104, and as the town rate only amounts to about £120, the cost of elections is out of all proportion to the revenue, and you are requested to recommend some means by which this cost can be at least considerably reduced.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I have already taken steps to remedy this so far as I can, but the real reduction can only be secured by holding county council and urban elections on the same day, the voters in urban districts voting both for the urban council and for the county council.  Whatever date is fixed for county council elections will be fixed also for urban elections.  It will further be seen that if two elections to county councils have to be held in the circumstances I have above referred to, the ratepayers, in the case of the unfortunate council whose letter I have quoted, will still be overtaxed.  Much as I dislike postponing elections, I feel that such postponement is imperative, and I ask the Dáil to agree to these elections being postponed to a date not later than the 31st March, 1925.  That will give us an opportunity to have the new councils elected before the striking of the rate, which is the main thing.  After all, <Col N="1919" /> county councils or local authorities elected at the present time cannot do very much, as the rate has already been struck, and with the Minister for Agriculture, I have made arrangements to relieve the agricultural population from the incidence of that rate. I know there will be a certain amount of opposition to this Bill, but I do not think any Deputy can suggest any way out of the difficulty other than what I have suggested here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I intend to oppose this Bill, and I ask the Dáil to refuse leave to have it introduced.  The obvious remedy for the grievances that are talked about is to have an election. After a series of postponements and concurrent complaints of the inability of local bodies to do their work efficiently and effectively, we are asked now to agree to a further postponement. No case of any kind is made for a further postponement, except that the Minister hopes that some day in the future the new Act will become law. He has no right to deprive the councils of their authority or the public of their right to elect councils pending the fulfilment of his hopes.  It should be apparent, I think, from the general expressions of opinion regarding the Bill which he relies upon, that it is opposed very seriously by representative people from all sides and in all quarters.  The chances of that Bill becoming law in its present form are very small indeed. There has been talk of a Commission to inquire into the general system of local government.  If such a Commission is to sit and examine the question thoroughly, it is not going to report in time to have an exhaustive Bill carried so that the elections may take place before the 31st March next, and then I suppose we will have another Bill asking for a further postponement.  I ask the Dáil to refuse to give permission to introduce this Bill, so that an indication will be given that the elections must be held, and then we can insert in the new Local Government Bill whatever provisions we like regarding the future conduct of councils.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to support Deputy Johnson in the statement he has made.  I think the action of the <Col N="1920" /> Government in regard to these local bodies is nothing short of a disgrace. We have had postponement after postponement, and now we are asked again to postpone the elections until March, 1925.  I need hardly tell the Minister that the people in all parts of the country are getting sick and tired of these postponements.  They have local councils that were put in, not by the votes of the people at all, but at the special request largely of the Ministers who are now in power.  All over the country we hear that these councils are guilty of maladministration, that they are not run in an economic fashion, or as they ought to be.  The rates are too high in every place, and everyone is displeased with the present position of local government.  Now we are asked by the Minister to pass a Bill which proposes to postpone the holding of these elections until March, 1925.  I certainly will refuse to give my assent to such a proposal as that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. HUGHES Mr. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what is the objection to this Bill which we have not yet seen.  I could understand objection being taken to the Second Reading of a Bill, but we are not being asked now to give this Bill a Second Reading.  We have not the Bill in our hands, and we do not know its details, and hence I do not think we should countenance the practice of refusing to give leave for the introduction of the measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is it not within the privilege of the Dáil and of Deputies to debate the principles of a measure on First Reading&mdash;not the actual details, but the principles of the measure?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. HUGHES Mr. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know how you can debate the principles of a measure that you have not seen or read.  If you were to do that it would be a new procedure, so far as I am concerned at least.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, have we not heard the principles of the Bill outlined by the Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN CEANN-COMHAIRLE AN CEANN-COMHAIRLE">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN-COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no point of order.  Deputy Hughes is quite in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1921" />
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. HUGHES Mr. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>I think this is the first time that the Dáil has been asked to refuse to give leave for the introduction of a Bill.  I do not want to have the municipal or the county council elections postponed indefinitely, but if a good case can be made in the circumstances I think the Minister is entitled to get leave to introduce his Bill and to make a case.  He cannot do that until the Bill comes up for Second Reading, and until we have an opportunity of reading the measure and discussing it on its merits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I would appeal to the Minister to consider this question very seriously before he forces this measure on the Dáil.  I ask him, is it more important to force this contemplated Bill of his on the Dáil than that the people of the country should be represented in the way they want to be represented? The Minister knows, better perhaps than anyone else, from representations that have been made to him and to previous Ministers with regard to the abolition of some of these councils, that the people of the country want to have these councils made thoroughly representative bodies.  I say it is more important that that should be done than that his new Bill should go through.  I am opposed to the introduction of this Bill.  In answer to the points raised by Deputy Hughes I may say that these points could not be made were it not for the speech of the Minister in introducing the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Mr. OSMOND GRATTAN ESMONDE Mr. OSMOND GRATTAN ESMONDE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. OSMOND GRATTAN ESMONDE</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the Minister in asking leave to introduce this Bill, which is.  I think, a most necessary Bill.  It would be a most preposterous idea to be forced to go to the trouble and expense of an election for the purpose of local government in view of the fact that a Bill is to be passed into law, possibly within six months' time, that will revolutionise the whole position of local government and of local government elections in this country.  I think it would be a preposterous thing and an abuse to have an election now in view of the fact that another election would follow on the passing of such a Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1922" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to ask the Deputy who has just spoken a question: Who is asking for this new Bill to revolutionise local government?  We are satisfied with the present system of local government.  We do not want a new-fangled Bill; we want the proper opportunity for electing people to represent us on our local bodies.  We are not in favour of changing the law every year.  Deputy Esmonde seems to attach more importance to allowing a new Bill to be brought in than that people should be properly represented. but I say that it is a more preposterous idea than what we suggest, for we only want fair play.  We only want to run the Government on the principle laid down and carried on for the past twenty years and which has not yet been improved upon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. HUGHES Mr. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy willing to throw away £120,000 upon a useless election?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>We are throwing away millions on maladministration.  That is what we are doing at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. HUGHES Mr. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HUGHES</NameTxt>
      <P>Then why not put it right?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in favour of the postponement of elections for a short time because I am aware that the register will not be ready by the 15th July.  It would be a great mistake to have an election in July because that would be conducted on the old register and would not give you a reflection of the opinion of the country.  But I do not agree with the Minister in the terms of his Bill that the elections should be postponed until March, 1925. I think that is certainly too far away. The date would have to be brought nearer than that.  I am not prepared to agree with the Farmer Deputies about maladministration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>You never do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be sorry to think that I agreed with you in everything. I say the uncertainty that prevails and the opinion that prevails in the different local bodies that there is not going to be an election are responsible for a good deal of the carelessness that is said to exist, and for <Col N="1923" /> the fact that a good many of the public boards have not given of their best. I would favour the postponement of the election until the autumn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>We have heard from the Minister on several occasions complaints about the iniquities of the public bodies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I have spoken very little about the iniquities of the public bodies.  I spoke about the system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>We have heard it, and if the Minister has not spoken of it he has given practical evidence of what he thinks of the local bodies. If they are as bad as they are supposed to be, why does he bring in a Bill to keep them in existence for a longer period?  If they are as bad as he says, why not get rid of them at once?  I suggest that the real object of this Bill is to give the Minister and his department an opportunity of going ahead with his present system, and sending commissioners all over the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>No Deputy is more anxious to get these elections on than I am.  From the start I have done everything in my power to get the elections proceeded with, and it is only owing to the fact that because of the considerable amount of time taken up last session on Broadcasting, and other matters, that my Bill was not further advanced.  I cannot really see that any argument has been put up against the <Col N="1924" /> argument put forward by Deputy Esmonde.  It is purely a question of avoiding the duplication of the elections. You are sure to have some kind of a Bill passed before very long, whether it is exactly as I have drafted it or not.  I believe it will be substantially the same, but that is beside the question at the moment.  You are certain to have some kind of recasting of local government administration between now and next January, and it would be a ridiculous thing to have an election just for the holiday months or summer months, and another again in the autumn for these new bodies.  It is absolutely essential to have another election when a Bill similar to the Local Government Bill of mine goes through the Dáil.  I cannot see how Deputies can justify the double expense of holding two elections, considering that the first representatives to be elected would be only four or five months at most in office before the second election would have to be held.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister explain how, or in what possible way the Broadcasting Inquiry prevented his getting on with this work?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>There was no opportunity of bringing in the Bill in that Session.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Was it ready?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>It was.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That leave be given to introduce the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1925" />
      <Col N="1926" /> The Dáil divided: Tá, 36; Níl, 23.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Richard H. Beamish.<br />Earnán de Blaghd.<br />Seoirse de Bhulbh.<br />Próinsias Bulfin.<br />Séamus de Búrca.<br />Bryan R. Cooper.<br />Máighréad Ní Choileáin Bean.<br />Uí Dhrisceóil.<br />Osmond Grattan Esmonde.<br />Darrell Figgis.<br />Henry J. Finlay.<br />John Good.<br />John Hennigan.<br />William Hewat.<br />Seosamh Mac Bhrighde.<br />Liam T. Mac Cosgair.<br />Pádraig Mac Giollagáin.<br />Seoirse Mac Niocaill.<br />Liam Mag Aonghusa.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Pádraig S. Mag Ualghairg.<br />Martin M. Nally.<br />Peadar O hAodha.<br />Mícheál O hAonghusa.<br />Criostóir O Broin.<br />Seán O Bruadair.<br />Eoghan O Dochartaigh.<br />Peadar S. O Dubhghaill.<br />Pádraig O Dubhthaigh.<br />Eamon S.O Dúgáin.<br />Aindriú O Láimhín.<br />Fionán O Loingsigh.<br />Pádraig O Máille.<br />Séamus O Murchadha.<br />Pádraig O hOgáin (Gaillimh).<br />Caoimhghín O hUigín.<br />Seán Príomhdhail.<br />Liam Thrift.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Pádraig F. Baxter.<br />Seán Buitléir.<br />John Conlan.<br />David Hall.<br />Connor Hogan.<br />Domhnall Mac Cárthaigh.<br />Séamus Mac Cosgair.<br />Maolmhuire Mac Eochadha.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Risteárd Mac Fheorais.<br />Risteárd Mac Liam.<br />Tomás de Nógla.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ailfrid O Broin.<br />Aodh O Cúlacháin.<br />Liam O Daimhín.<br />Tadhg S.O Donnabháin.<br />Eamon O Dubhghaill.<br />Seán O Duinnín.<br />Donchadh S.O Guaire.<br />Mícheál R.O hIfearnáin.<br />Domhnall O Muirgheasa.<br />Tadhg P.O Murchadha.<br />Pádraig O hOgáin (An Clár).<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Motion declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the Second Stage be taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Dáil has no objection I propose to take it to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>There is an objection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Then, on Wednesday.</P>
      <P>Second Stage ordered for Wednesday, June 11th, 1924.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="AGRICULTURAL PRODUCE (EGGS)" RHead="BILL, 1924. SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>AGRICULTURAL PRODUCE (EGGS) BILL, 1924.     SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan) MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LANDS and AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I dealt at some length with this particular Bill on the First Reading.  I stated what the problem was, and I do not intend to go into that side of the question now.  I just want to touch on one of the general principles that underlie this Bill, and that will underlie a number of Bills that will be introduced in this Session.  I stated on the First Reading that this Bill was prepared in consultation with the trade, and that so far as its main principles were concerned it was in general approved by the trade.  It is a Bill to regulate the trade, and it seems a little extraordinary in that state of affairs, in view of the fact that the trade itself, both producers and exporters, is in favour of it, that it would be necessary at all to introduce a Bill like this, that gives rather drastic powers to a Government department to regulate the business which these people are more nearly interested in than anybody else.  It looks rather like forcing people to make money.  Well up to a certain point it is. This particular Bill is, if I might use the expression, a sort of voluntary compulsion, and the point I wish to stress is, number one, that there would be no need for a Bill like this if both sides of the trade, that is, both the producers and exporters, were properly organised for the purposes of their own business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>And the second aspect of it that I <Col N="1927" /> want to stress is that in spite of this Bill, in spite of the fact that we are forcing the trade, so to speak, to organise itself, any of the possible good effects of the measure will be negatived unless all concerned realise that they have got to help themselves, that in anything that we can do for them we cannot really improve either the egg trade, or the butter trade, or any side of our agricultural business, unless the people themselves, the people who are really interested, the people whose business it is to look after it&mdash;unless they begin to improve it themselves, and unless they realise that they will be competing in the future with other countries that have had for a long time all the possible advantages that they can get out of this Bill, and that are, in addition, more wide-awake, more enterprising than we are unfortunately at the present moment in this country. That is the underlying consideration in connection with this Bill and in connection with a number of Bills of the same sort which are to be introduced in this Dáil, even in this Session.  These are the only points that I intend to deal with now, as I have dealt with the Bill at some length on the First Reading. I beg to move for Second Reading.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. BAXTER Mr. BAXTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAXTER</NameTxt>
      <P>Since I came into this Dáil no Bill has been introduced by any Minister on the Government Benches that I can so enthusiastictally support as this measure from the Minister for Agriculture.  And I have only one regret to express in connection with it, and that is, that it was not introduced more than six months ago, that it was not introduced as soon as possible, or in a very short time after the first interim Report of the Agricultural Commission.  I think it is regrettable that it is not the law of the land to-day.  It is regrettable that it is not the law, because, as I see things, a very large part of the trade in poultry for this season, at least a pretty fair share of the trade, will have passed over by the time this Bill is the law of the land.  I agree with the Minister for Agriculture that it is regrettable that such a measure has to be introduced <Col N="1928" /> at all to compel those engaged in the poultry industry in this country to manage that branch of our business as it ought to be managed.</P>
      <P>We have been waiting for years, and we must all agree that the conduct or the management of this branch of our industry is not improving.  That fact has been so persistently forcing itself on us for some time past that opinion is to-day very strong in favour of this measure.  It is to a certain extent revolutionary in character.  And that the State should feel it necessary that the State should possess the power that the Minister seeks in this Bill is a farreaching step indeed.  But I agree that it is the only course that can be adopted. Our mismanagement of this industry in the past may be attributable to the fact that perhaps we have had too many people engaged in the industry, with the result that the responsibility for mismanagement was distributed over a great number of heads or shoulders, each one inclined to shove the responsibility on to the other, and none of them realising its responsibility to the country's trade or to the good name of its products at all.  The Bill gives the Ministry authority to inspect the premises of exporters.  How the exporter is to deal with his customer is a matter that is left fairly open.  The Minister, I assume, believes that the exporter is capable of dealing with his customers or traders by refusing to deal with them unless they comply with certain regulations.  I am partly inclined to the view that it might be necessary to include in the Bill some power for the exporter to be in a position to penalise those who would come to him with an article which might seem to be up to the standard, but which later he might discover was not. It is a matter for debate whether the exporter would feel that he should ask some protection from the law in that way or not.  I welcome this step of the Minister for Lands and Agriculture and I believe I am expressing the opinion of the agricultural community generally when I say that they feel such a measure as this is necessary so as to enable all those engaged in this industry to do what is fair by the industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1929" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join in commending the Bill.  I agree with Deputy Baxter in his regret that the Bill was not brought in six months ago. The report which was called for hurriedly a year ago is dated the 22nd May, 1923, and it was generally expected that action would have been taken upon that report promptly.  No doubt the Minister had good reasons and has carefully thought out the position beforehand. Probably it will be charitable to assume that as a result of the delay he has frustrated possible opposition from the trade, and that as a consequence the chances of success in the working out of the Bill may be greater. I am glad Deputy Baxter has given such hearty approval to the Bill on behalf of the agricultural community.  I hope he is speaking confidently with regard to the backing that the measures required in this Bill will get from the wives of farmers who are primarily concerned in this matter.  I imagine that in the working out of the Bill exporters will find it necessary to impose conditions upon their purchase of eggs which will in turn require from the farmers' wives considerably more care in the handling of their part of the industry. I think that would be all to the good, directly and indirectly.  A great portion of our export of eggs is to England, which receives eggs from Denmark and will be receiving them in great quantities, I think from Russia and other countries in Europe.  The advantage that we have of being close to that market and enabled thereby to send eggs a day or two fresher than any other country is lost by the fact that we are not sending them in good order and well presented, quite apart from their quality.  Inherent quality is one thing, but the attractiveness of the packing is of equal importance.  The Bill, I think, will have good results as far as the export trade is concerned. It will also, I think, have good results in respect of the home trade.  Some people have thought that the effect of it will be to send all good eggs to England and leave the Irish consumer the choice only of bad eggs.  There may be something in that for the first two or three months, but very little.  It should be noted, I think, that the Bill does give power to the officers of the Ministry <Col N="1930" /> in regard to the inspection of eggs sold for home consumption.  The whole procedure will inevitably react in favour of a better and more regular collection of eggs, careful inspection, proper grading, and generally to tune up the productive side of the industry in a way which will be beneficial to the consumers, and I think inevitably very beneficial to the producers.  I think, too, with the Minister that one of the results will be to induce by a sort of gentle compulsion, a very much better organisation of the transportation and distribution of eggs.  That again will be all to the good.  I therefore welcome the Bill very heartily.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There has been con siderable delay in introducing the Bill, and Deputy Johnson has stated the reason that I had intended to give.  As I pointed out, this is a Bill that regulates possibly £6,000,000 worth of trade.  To regulate trade by legislation is an extremely difficult thing.  It is very easy to do more harm than good. It was absolutely essential to think out the Bill and the possible consequences of it a long way ahead.  For that purpose it was necessary to get in touch with all the associations, wherever there were associations&mdash;to get in touch with the people who were organised, and also with those who were unorganised, so as to prepare the Bill with all the relevant data in mind. It would be easy enough to produce a simple Bill.  Probably nine sections out of ten would be the same as in this Bill, but it is just the tenth that might make all the difference when the Bill was put into operation.  The very slight difference between the condition in the North and the conditions her has necessitated a Bill which is radically different.  I have been in consultation with people in the North and with people who approved of the Northern Bill for the North and the agreed that it was absolutely necessary to have a different sort of Bill in the North to this Bill.  As I pointed out, the main difference is that was register exporters only.  We do not attempt to deal with wholesalers, the reason being that there are far more wholesalers in the trade here than in the North, for the size of the trade even.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1931" /> That brings me to the other point which Deputy Baxter raised.  He suggests that it might have been necessary to put some power in the hands of the exporter to deal with the producer of eggs who sells bad eggs.  We considered that point very carefully and in fact, as the Bill was first drafted. Section 16 read: &ldquo;It shall not be lawful for any person to buy, sell, or offer or consign for sale.&rdquo;  That would have made the position worse from the point of view of the exporter, but would not have given him any powers as against the retailer.  It would have made his position more difficult for this reason.  If he bought eggs which were not up to standard it was an offence. If we put in the word &ldquo;buy&rdquo; as well as &ldquo;sell&rdquo; that would have made his position worse.  We realised that, and took out the word &ldquo;buy,&rdquo; but we could not go any further.  We could not put a positive weapon into his hand to deal with the retailer or the producer, and I do not think there is any necessity.</P>
    <P>He will, as far as he can, look after himself.  If he is buying eggs he must sell them graded, tested and fresh.  It is an offence if he does not.  He has no alternative, except to penalise a person who comes forward, and tries to sell him dirty eggs, by charging that person for cleaning them.  He will take into account, in buying the eggs, that he has to sell them as fresh eggs, properly graded, and will accordingly penalise anyone who comes forward to sell eggs, not up to the standard, by giving them a lower price.  He realises the fact that he will have to clean the eggs afterwards, before he can sell them.  With regard to the home trade I have pointed out that all the big exporters, in fact, all the exporters, were wholesalers as well.  Probably. most of the exporters who deal with the export trade are the people who do most of the wholesale trade at home.  That being the case, in view of the fact that there is a section in the Bill that prevents the exporter from even selling eggs internally, unless they are properly graded, tested and packed, the consumer at home has some guarantee that he will get the <Col N="1932" /> same terms as the English consumer would get from the exporter under other circumstances.  If one of our inspectors walks into an exporter's premises and finds there eggs graded, tested and packed, amongst which, on examination are some stale eggs, or cold storage eggs, when asked to account for them, it will not be enough for the exporter to say that the eggs were meant for home trade.  The exporters are registered and whether eggs are meant for home, or for foreign trade, the regulations are the same.  I think that covers the particular difficulty, and makes it almost certain that the exporters will be almost as careful in regard to the home trade as to the foreign trade.  When Deputies take into account that most of the exporters are the big home wholesalers as well, I think they will agree that the home trade is likely to be benefited by this. As Deputy Johnson pointed out there is likely to be some slight confusion at the start, but matters will right themselves.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="MR. JOHNSON MR. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>MR. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder could the Minister give us an idea of what is meant in regard to the regulations in Section 15 (1).  I think it might save time if we knew that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I had better read the section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1) The Minister may by order make regulations prescribing the marks to be placed on every package of eggs sold on or exported or consigned from any premises registered in the register of exporters for the purpose of indicating all or any of the matters following.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Eggs are graded according to weight, and outside on the package will be numbers, 1, 2, 3 or 4, according to the grade.  It will be shown on the outside of each package what grade of eggs it contains.  (b) &ldquo;The premises on which such eggs were packed.&rdquo;  Each registered premises will have a number or trade mark.  That will also be on the outside of the package.  (c) &ldquo;In the case of preserved eggs, that such eggs are preserved.&rdquo;  That speaks for itself. In the case of preserved eggs, if a case contains any such eggs, the word &ldquo;preserved&rdquo; must be on the outside of the package.  (d) &ldquo;That such <Col N="1933" /> eggs were produced in Saorstát Eireann.&rdquo;  We want to get a reputation for our eggs.  We want to bring about such a state of affairs that the word &ldquo;Irish&rdquo; on a package will be a guarantee of good quality.  We start off forcing them, after they grade the eggs, to put &ldquo;Irish&rdquo; on the package.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;And any other matter which in the opinion of the Minister should be indicated on such eggs.  The Minister may also by order make regulations prescribing the marks to be placed on every egg sold on or consigned by any premises, registered in the Register of Exporters, for the purpose of indicating all or any of the matters mentioned in the foregoing sub-section.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is, in view of the fact that there is contemplated in the British and other Parliaments legislation which will possibly necessitate some mark indicating the country of origin on each egg that goes into the British market. If that happens we are not going to give up the British market because we have to mark our eggs.  We want to be in a position to do it if necessary, without further legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister thinking of dating the eggs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That was not in contemplation as far as I know.  It is not one of the essentials that would be required under the contemplated legislation in England, as far as I know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I was in hopes that by power to make regulations regarding the marks to be placed on eggs, you had in mind the imposition of the duty on the part of the producer of indicating that the eggs were collected at a certain date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be open to us to do that.  That is rather a contentious question which perhaps I should not go into now.  It is a detail and is amply covered by Section 15.  I may say that one of the specific things I had in mind in putting in that sub-section was that a Bill might be brought in in the British Parliament next year saying that any eggs coming in must be marked. and we would have had the necessity <Col N="1934" /> of coming here to pass a formal Bill in order to do that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill read a Second Time; Committee Stage ordered for Thursday next.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES." RHead="ESTIMATE 39&mdash;MINISTRY OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES.  ESTIMATE 39&mdash;MINISTRY OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT.</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on amendment to reduce sub-head A by £800 (Mr. Johnson).</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. A. BYRNE Mr. A. BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>Last evening when the Minister was replying to the very able statement made by Deputy Johnson regarding the abolition of the Dublin Corporation I felt that it would be spoiling a good case to add very much to what Deputy Johnson and Deputy Hewat said.  But I wish briefly to refer to two points made by the Minister. One was the question of houses.  The Minister stated that the Corporation were slow in their methods of dealing with the housing problem.  I certainly am dissatisfied with the way the Dublin housing problem is being dealt with. but the fault is not due to the Dublin Corporation.  I have been speaking to one member of the Housing Committee to-day and he asked me if I could get the Minister for Local Government to produce the file of correspondence between the Housing Committee and his department, which he said would disclose the fact that the department held up the housing scheme at Marino for practically twelve months, in spite of the Corporation's protests, and further that the department reduced the number of houses to be built at Marino on one contract to half the number proposed. The Corporation's idea was to build 450 houses, but as a result, for some unknown reason of this interference, the scheme was reduced to 200 odd houses&mdash;a very few over 200.  I think that settles the question of housing. I can certainly say that the Housing Committee of the present Corporation did more within the past four years than any previous Committee in a period of ten years.  They dealt with the money speedily and the houses were built at the lowest possible price.  These <Col N="1935" /> houses were no deared&mdash;in fact, in some cases they were cheaper&mdash;than the houses that were built when the President was Chairman of the Corporation Housing Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Prices have fallen since then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. A. BYRNE Mr. A. BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Marino housing scheme is costing much less than the houses in Fairbrothers' Fields.  The Minister also referred to the question of wages.  The wages paid by the Dublin Corporation are largely affected by the rate of wages paid outside.  Certain classes of trades insisted on a higher wage in the case of the Corporation and other public boards than that paid by private contractors.  I understand that within the last few days an attempt has been made to reduce the wages of one class in the Corporation, and I hope that the Minister will not leave Dublin in the same plight as Derry is in to-day, when he starts attacking the wages of the Corporation workers.  I have answered the only two points made by the Minister when he was replying to Deputy Johnson.  I do wish to express this opinion, that on the whole the Corporation members who have been my colleagues for the past four years&mdash;a new Corporation, too, with whom I differed in many cases&mdash;under extraordinary difficulties, and hampered by the Government also, have done their best, and if the good points of the Corporation were probed and given the same publicity as their few little bad points it would be fairer. I hold that there are very few bad points, and that the only fault is that the Corporation has been used by the Government's own followers of four years ago as a political platform, using the same weapons as they used against the British and the old Irish Party; that the present members of the Corporation do not forget that these weapons succeeded then, and that it is possible that the same weapons of embarrassing the Government to-day may succeed and may bring about what they hope to see.  The Government will be doing a wise thing by stating that the reason for the abolition of the Corporation was that it was used as a political platform by their opponents, and <Col N="1936" /> that it was for the purpose of taking from them the publicity and the opportunities they had of exposing grievances which their followers suffered from.  The Corporation, as the public health authority, has continually drawn attention to the condition of the prisons, especially of the prisons in Dublin, which it thought it ought to control.  I think, candidly, as a corporator who is, should I say, almost glad to have a little rest from Corporation duties, that the faults of the Corporation are no worse than those of the Dáil.  I ask the Dáil to compare the report on the administration of the Corporation with the auditor's report concerning the army and see which comes out better.  I ask the Minister if he is not satisfied with the present Corporation to give the electors an opportunity of deciding who shall represent them.  There is no justification for abolishing an ancient body like the Dublin Corporation.  There may be justification for postponing the operations of the present members, but I say the way to do that is to have an election, and have it immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MylesKeogh" hpid="Dr. KEOGH Dr. KEOGH">
      <NameTxt>Dr. KEOGH</NameTxt>
      <P>I come to praise Caesar not to bury him.  I have been privileged to be a member of the Corporation for the last eleven years, representing, I may say, all types of people, from Trinity College to the slums in South Dock and Trinity Ward, and I have had opportunities during the last few weeks of meeting many electors, both of Trinity College and in the slums of the Grand Canal Street neigh-hourhood, and they, like myself. are not satisfied that the removal of the Corporation was justifiable.  Individual Deputies are representing private taxpayers, and for the four and a half years since the last election that I represented the ratepayers there was always an opportunity of asking them what they had to say, and I never heard of any grievances.  The trouble as far as I can see, is that four and a half years ago a very strong political body &mdash;53 out of 80&mdash;was elected who promised to revolutionise the Corporation. For two years they certainly worked hard, harder than in the case of those who were members for the six years previously.  They did wonderful things &mdash;put people in and put people out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1937" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Jobs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MylesKeogh" hpid="Dr. KEOGH Dr. KEOGH">
      <NameTxt>Dr. KEOGH</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know anything about jobs.  I do not know if there ever was a job in the Corporation. There are appointments to be filled as there are here.  This political body worked very hard for two years, but I read in the Press two years ago that there was a division in it; I understand it is not healed up yet.  From that time on no one seemed to take any interest in the business.  Everything was thrown in the air.  It was a case of going hammer and tongs at one another on some political division, and the Corporation business was neglected.  Many members resigned, and many as a protest would not sit with their fellow members.  We hoped that one and a half years ago a new body would be elected that would not go in on the political ticket.  It was not necessary to have politicians in civic life.</P>
      <P>I waited with feverish anxiety yesterday to hear the Minister reveal some shocking revelations as to what was going on in the Corporation.  I was disappointed; there was nothing revealed but the hardy old annual of the Stanley Street workshops.  I believe the Stanley Street workshops could have been regulated and put in order by the Government without putting the whole Corporation out of existence. The Corporation, as a whole, should be given credit for what they have already given us.  Deputy Johnson and Deputy Hewat spoke, as private members, of the Corporation, and I am sure members of the Corporation will thank them.  I do not think it is a place for members of the Corporation to speak at all because it is merely a case of whitewashing one another.  People may say: &ldquo;What else can you say but praise them?&rdquo;  I am sorry there were not strong reasons given why the Corporation was dissolved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure that Deputy Keogh was anxious to speak kindly of the dead when he referred to the good works of the late Corporation.  I am afraid those of us who have been ratepayers in the city for the last quarter of a century have very few kindly remembrances of the late Dublin Corporation. Deputy Byrne. another member of that auspicious body for some <Col N="1938" /> considerable time past, referred to the fact that the Dublin Corporation was always guided in the amounts it paid to its workmen by the figures paid by other bodies in the city.  The larger number of the workmen employed by the Dublin Corporation were unskilled workmen, and other bodies I happened to be connected with were very largely influenced if not governed in the amount they had to pay to unskilled labour by the Corporation.  We were being continually confronted by those alarming figures which the Corporation paid to their workmen.  I want to deal with the late Corporation very much in the same spirit as Deputy Myles Keogh.  I think the kindest thing one can say of them is that they left undone the things they ought to have done, and did the things they ought not to have done, but I think we ratepayers remember them not by the things they ought not to have done or the things they did, but by the heavy burden of rates that they cast on us year after year.  We business men came to the conclusion many years ago, long before this Government came into existence, that there was only one possible remedy for the Dublin Corporation, and that is exactly the course the present Government has taken.  I think it was a surprise to most of the citizens of Dublin to find that the new Government had the moral courage to take that stand and do what they did, and I think as a result of that action we have seen few tears in the eyes of the ratepayers of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarSeanDoyle" hpid="Mr. P.S. DOYLE Mr. P.S. DOYLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.S. DOYLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that some of the Deputies at any rate are anxious that those of us who are members of the Dáil and who are ex-members of the Corporation ought to express some opinion or other on the action of the Ministry in installing Commissioners and dealing with the Dublin Corporation.  I did not intend to offer any opinion, particularly on the action taken as regards the Commissioners, for one reason; I do not think, having regard to all the talk we have about the dignity that we are thought to have lost, that it is a dignified attitude for one of us, at any rate, to stand up and take sides on the matter. On the other hand, if the citizens <Col N="1939" /> feel that they are wronged in the matter and that their rights have been taken from them, it is their duty, more than ours, to take that action first. That is my opinion on that point.  I do not propose to criticise either the action of the Ministry or those who may have provoked or brought about the drastic course taken in this regard. I do say I gave no encouragement to it, and, as I have already stated, I did not approve of the installing of Commissioners. I am opposed to it, but I recognise that there are instances where such drastic courses are necessary if those public bodies are to function in the interests of the citizens.  I take exception to some particular actions of the majority of the Corporation.  I will only refer to one.  I do not stand for the reduction of wages, particularly for those of the working classes, but regarding the non-acceptance of the Government grant by the Corporation, while I appreciate to the full the action taken by the labour section in it&mdash;I feel they could do nothing else from the point of view they looked at it, namely, an attempt to reduce the standard rate of wages&mdash;yet I think that it was possible to accept that grant.  Having regard to the very abnormal state of unemployment at the moment, I think it was quite possible to have accepted that grant on conditions that would not interfere with the local standard rates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As to the Inspector's report, there are a couple of items to which I also take exception, and those are the references to Stanley Street.  The Stanley Street workshops were established for the purpose of assembling in one centre workmen who were employed by various committees.  It was with a view to carrying out that work in a more direct manner.  Each committee had its own section, and its number of workmen centralised into one shop. Prior to its being done, things went on all right, but immediately the workshop was set up it became a little industry, and could be made a thriving one, if what I might call the ring, which is usually formed where any little industry has to be killed, were not formed.  Some of our business men in the city are well aware of that.  It <Col N="1940" /> was not possible to get the work done as it ought to have been done.  I admit that, but the influences set to work starved Stanley Street, and the work which should have been done in the workshops was sent outside.  That is the kernel of the failure of the Stanley Street workshops.</P>
    <P>Regarding housing, I do think the Deputies who have already referred to this matter of the alleged delay of the Housing Committee in connection with the building of houses, will agree that that is not justified.  I say that, because I do know that a good deal of unnecessary delay took place in the transfer of the different communications between the Housing Committee and the Local Government Department. I think that if the same delay will take place now that the Commissioners are working the Corporation, it will be found that progress in the matter of housing will be just as it was when the business was conducted by the Housing Committee.  There is one particular matter to which I would like to refer. I noticed that in the propaganda that has been going on for a long time in connection with the suggested dissolution of the Corporation and the propaganda going on since the Corporation has been dissolved, it is those who clamoured the most to bring about that drastic dissolution of the Corporation who have latterly weakened off so very much and even gone so far as to protest against the action of the Government in that respect.  What is behind that I do not know.  At any rate, if anyone takes up the Dublin papers that have been agitating against the Corporation for so long, he will find that there is something behind it.  I do not propose to occupy the time of the Dáil any longer, except to say that in my mind the citizens have a right in feeling that they have been interfered with.  I believe it is their right to take whatever course they think proper to protest in this matter.  I will confine myself to that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="MR. DAVIN MR. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>MR. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one aspect, and perhaps an important aspect, of this whole question which I trust the Dáil has not overlooked.  That is that the Minister for Local Government, as an external Minister, has in my <Col N="1941" /> opinion, in taking this action treated the Dáil more or less in a contemptible way.  Perhaps I am wrong, but it is my view at any rate, that it would be his duty, having abolished a public body, first of all to provide the Deputies with a copy of the Inspector's report on which he acted, and which forced him to come to that conclusion. He should afterwards, in my opinion, have come along to the Dáil and justify to them the action he had taken. I have been listening to the debate that has taken place on that matter during the past day or two, and on a previous occasion, and I noticed that the Minister on one or two occasions used the word &ldquo;Government.&rdquo;  I had rather a peculiar idea that when the word &ldquo;Government&rdquo; was used, that the Minister, before taking this action, was in consultation with the Executive Council and had something in the nature more or less of their approval. If he has taken that step, I think that as an External Minister he has gone in the wrong direction.  He should have come down to the Dáil, after having provided us with a copy of the Inspector's report, and endeavoured to justify his action in taking such a serious decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister stated that the reasons which forced him to come to this conclusion and to take the decision for which he accepted full responsibility were, that he was not satisfied with the administration of the Dublin Corporation, and that consequently he thought that the best course to adopt would be to appoint Commissioners to take the place of the body that had been elected by the people to find out the things which he was anxious to find out, and to find out what was wrong, and where the Dublin Corporation had made mistakes, and that he was doing all this in the interests of the citizens.  Now I submit that he could have done that just as well by the holding of an Inquiry. Through that inquiry he could have found out everything that he was anxious to find out, without wiping out the whole body.  This is in my mind the whole cause of the trouble, and the whole explanation of the thing with which Deputy Good has dealt, that is, that the Dublin Corporation had accepted <Col N="1942" /> responsibility for the rates of wages and the salaries which are not pleasing to the Minister or to the officials that are in charge of the Ministry for Local Government.</P>
    <P>The Minister, and his colleagues who are on the Executive Council have, unfortunately, allowed themselves to be drawn into the hands of the capitalists or ruling classes.  They are endeavouring to use the position of unemployment in this country, and the position of the unfortunate people who have been thrown on the unemployment list because of their own action.  They are endeavouring to cut down lower the existing wages which the Dublin Corporation had accepted.  Now the £10,000, and it was only £10.000, would not employ very many men for one week only, even if the Corporation had accepted the conditions attached to that grant.  But I tell him that although the unemployed are faced with starvation, they still have got their organisation and leaders among them, and they will not allow themselves to be used as a lever to serve the purpose which the Minister has in mind.  You have a case of that in Derry at the present moment. You cannot use the position of the unemployed to bring down rates of wages, and therefore the Minister, if he thinks that the Commissioners who succeeded the Dublin Corporation will serve the purpose of reducing wages, and using unemployment to lower the standard of living of the ordinary workers outside, will find in a very short time that he is very much mistaken indeed.  I can see that Deputy Good's interest in the standard of living is such that he will welcome this action of the Minister.  He can see that the Minister is allowing himself to be used by the classes with which Deputy Good is so prominently associated.</P>
    <P>I contend that the Minister, when replying, should give good reason as to why he did not publish the report of the Inspector, and why he did not, as an external Minister, instead of going to the Executive Council&mdash;if he has gone to the Executive Council&mdash;come down to the Dáil and justify his action in wiping out a body elected by the citizens of Dublin.  The proper thing for him to do would be to order an <Col N="1943" /> election in the City of Dublin, and thus find, as he would find, a body of people elected to represent the citizens and taking responsibility for their action as representatives of the citizens.  Deputy Alfred Byrne has rightly pointed out that the body that was elected at the last election was composed of 53 members of one Party who were sent there for a purely political purpose, because they had a certain flag tied to their tail.  They were to stand up as representatives of a national organisation and carry out the mandate they received&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MylesKeogh" hpid="Dr. KEOGH Dr. KEOGH">
      <NameTxt>Dr. KEOGH</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I wish to say that the Deputy is wrong when he says that it was Deputy Byrne who said that that Party was composed of 53 members.  In justice to Deputy Byrne I wish to say that it was I said that, not he.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry, but I assumed that it is a fact.  I take it, at all events, as being a fact.  I contend that the fifty-three representatives of the Dublin Corporation who were sent there, not because they were men more capable than anybody else, to administer the affairs of the City, have done nothing in a very extraordinary way during the time they were there to justify this action.  I put it to him this way: that when positions became vacant in the service of the Corporation during the period when these fifty-three people were acting for and supporting the Government of Dáil Eireann at the time, they did not appoint officials to the Dublin Corporation because they had special qualifications for, say, the position of rate collector.  When the position of rate collector became vacant it was a political office, and the person appointed to the position was appointed, not through his qualifications, but for other reasons.  These are things that the Minister might explain.  I rise to take exception to the attitude of the Minister as an external Minister in not publishing the report of the Inspector, and not coming down to the Dáil before the question was raised, and endeavouring to justify the action he has taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1944" />
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Taking up Deputy Davin's challenge first of all, I may say that the Corporation was abolished in consultation with the Government. I have no apology to make for that. It would be absolutely ridiculous to think that external Ministers should work at a loose end without co-operating with the Government of the country. As long as I am a responsible Minister for Local Government I believe that I am entitled to take decisions in matters of this kind without coming before the Dáil.  As I remarked previously, it is necessary to do that, or otherwise you should abolish Ministers altogether, and rule the country through a Committee of the Dáil.  Deputy Byrne has dealt principally with the housing problem.  I believe that I have given sufficient reason for the abolition of this body in my reply to Deputy Johnson.  Deputy Byrne has complained of my strictures with regard to their conduct on the housing question and he has retorted with the <i>tu quoque</i> argument.</P>
      <P>It is true there was a considerable number of letters passing between our department and the Dublin Corporation on the question of housing.  I am quite willing to allow the Deputy to consult the files and make whatever use he likes of them.  The main reason for holding up building was that the Corporation raised ridiculous points, insisting on such things as having window sills of cut stone and having the stones cut on the site, and matters of that sort.  That would have added very considerably to the cost of those buildings. They can never be erected, unless under the most economic conditions at the present time.  I can inform Deputy Byrne that the Commissioners are already making considerable progress with building.  They have secured prices far more favourable than before for the building of the remaining houses and they are starting the erection of 197 houses on the Marino Site on Monday next.  Progress is also being made as regards other sites and developments which will entail the employment of a considerable amount of unskilled labour will be started at once.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1945" /> I can well understand the attitude of Deputies Byrne and Keogh in objecting to my action in this matter.  It is only reasonable.  I am sure they feel a certain grievance in the matter and I sympathise with them.  To use an old phrase, it hurts me more than them to have to take this action, but in the circumstances it could not be helped.</P>
    <P>I am not surprised at Deputy Johnson's attitude.  He has consistently played the role here of a champion of democracy, and he has played that rôle very successfully.  I have come in for a great deal of his battery, but I have got so used to it now that I really pay very little attention to it.  I was very surprised to see Deputy Hewat taking me to task over my action in this matter. He is, I believe, representing a section of the ratepaying community and they were very much to the fore in objecting to the conduct of the Corporation. I find it very difficult to understand his motive in quarrelling with our conduct in this matter, unless he has in mind the object of competing with Deputy Johnson for the position he holds as the great champion of democracy and constitutional Government in the Dáil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going to give a warning to Deputy Hewat at this stage.  I warn him that he has very little chance of competing with Deputy Johnson on that matter, because Deputy Johnson is certainly a past master in political strategy of that kind.  I thought I gave sufficient reason for obliterating, as Deputy Johnson said, the Dublin Corporation.  Very little stress has been laid on the fact that the Corporation has turned down the grant, and that, undoubtedly, had a great deal to do in influencing me in my decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Politics have been referred to.  I do not mind how much political tomfoolery the Corporation or any other local authority in Ireland carries on, so long as it does not interfere with efficiency; but when it interferes in matters of life and death, as was the case when the Corporation turned the grant down, I may say that I was justified in interfering. At present we have what may be described as an unparalleled situation <Col N="1946" /> in Dublin, or at least such a situation as has not arisen for a very considerable time.  There are thousands of unemployed in the city in a very serious state of destitution.  Anyone who has anything to do with charity in the city at present realises how badly off many people are in the poorer districts.  It is not an uncommon sight to see strong men having to go to charitable institutions to get food, men who in the ordinary course of events would earn a decent livelihood.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>They would get more than £2 10s. anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Better that than nothing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>In making this grant available we did what we thought was the best thing which would give relief in a terrible situation.  During the course of this discussion I have not hauled the Corporation over the coals for not reducing wages.  I believe the Corporation wages are too high, particularly when you take into consideration the fact that a great number of the employees get pensions and other perquisites which the ordinary workman has no chance of getting.  The great grievance, on the question of wages, against the Corporation was the fact that they refused even to consider the question of wages.  I considered that, at a time when the rates in the city were so high, notwithstanding the fact that the valuation was made only a few years ago, and when you take into consideration that we have so little money for the relief of unemployment, and for measures of that kind, the Corporation was certainly unjustified in every respect in turning down that grant, and insisting upon the payment of wages to the unemployed equal to the extravagant wages they are paying their own officials at the present time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That was one instance of the attitude of the Corporation towards our Government.  I do not mind what kind of political fraud they go on with there.  It is a good platform for those gentlemen who do not want to come into the Dáil, but when it comes to a matter of this kind it is going too far for them to allow their political bias to prevent them carrying out their duty to the citizens.  This is an instance <Col N="1947" /> of their whole attitude towards the Government on matters into which politics do not enter at all.  At the same time I had very good information that the Corporation did not intend to strike a rate for the police force, and that conduct was altogether unjustified; and also that they were going to refuse to pay anything towards the upkeep of the Dublin Union, because I had Commissioners there.  These are two points that indicate the attitude of the Corporation towards the Government, and, if you take these facts into consideration, with the arguments I advanced in favour of their abolition in reply to Deputy Johnson, I do not <Col N="1948" /> think anyone will say that I acted in a hasty or a too autocratic manner.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the publication of the Report, and circulating it to members of the Dáil?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>A copy of the Report was handed to the Press.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what I mean.  I contend a report of this kind should be circulated to members of the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has another method of having that done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a question for the Minister for Finance.  I have absolutely no objection to the publication of the Report.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Amendment put:</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 13; Níl, 48.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Seán Buitléir.<br />David Hall.<br />William Hewat.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Risteárd Mac Fheorais.<br />Tomás de Nógla.<br />Ailfrid O Broin.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aodh O Cúlacháin.<br />Liam O Daimhín.<br />Eamon O Dubhghaill.<br />Domhnall O Muirgheasa.<br />Tadhg O Murchadha.<br />Pádraig O hOgáin (An Clár).<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Pádraig F. Baxter.<br />Earnán de Blaghd.<br />Séamus Breathnach.<br />Seoirse de Bhulbh.<br />Próinsias Bulfin.<br />Séamus de Burca.<br />John Conlan.<br />Bryan R. Cooper.<br />Sir James Craig.<br />Máighréad Ní Choileáin Bean Uí<br />Dhrisceóil.<br />Darrell Figgis.<br />John Good.<br />John Hennigan.<br />Connor Hogan.<br />Seosamh Mac 'a Brighde.<br />Domhnall Mac Carthaigh.<br />Liam T. Mac Cosgair.<br />Patrick McGillígan.<br />Risteárd Mac Liam.<br />Eoin Mac Néill.<br />Seoirse Mac Niocaill.<br />Liam Mac Sioghaird.<br />Liam Mag Aonghusa.<br />Pádraig Mag Ualghairg.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">James Sproule Myles.<br />Martin M. Nally.<br />John T. Nolan.<br />Peadar O hAodha.<br />Mícheál O hAonghusa.<br />Criostóir O Broin.<br />Seán O Bruadair.<br />Próinsias O Cathail.<br />Partholán O Conchubhair.<br />Eoghan O Dochartaigh.<br />Tadhg O Donnabháin.<br />Peadar O Dubhghaill.<br />Pádraig O Dubhthaigh.<br />Eamon O Dúgáin.<br />Seán O Duinnín.<br />Donchadh O Guaire.<br />Mícheál O hIfearnáin.<br />Aindriú O Laimhín.<br />Fionán O Loingsigh.<br />Pádraic O Máille.<br />Séamus O Murchadha.<br />Padraig O hOgáin (Gaillimh).<br />Seán O Súilleabháin.<br />Liam Thrift.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that we are still discussing sub-head (a) of this Estimate.  The Minister for Finance keeps reiterating that he must balance his Budget, and keeps asserting that he can neither reduce the taxes upon sugar, nor the income tax, nor any of the other taxes that bear so heavily both upon the poor and the well-to-do.  I think it behoves the Minister that he should make very careful inquiry into Departmental expenditure. <Col N="1949" /> When one looks at this sub-head one is rather alarmed to find that in the present year there is no less than an increase of fifteen officials connected with the temporary staff, costing £2,800.  That does not reassure us that there is such a desire on the part of the Minister to see that reductions are made in this particular Department. With regard to the inspectorial staff, I should like to refer to the Directory of 1919, which I picked up recently, and in which I found this statement, that the Local Government Board in Scotland appoints four lay inspectors, three medical inspectors, and one veterinary inspector.</P>
      <P>The point I want to make is in connection with the four lay inspectors and the three medical inspectors.  One of the medical inspectors also acts as superintendent of the Central Vaccine Institution for Scotland.  As against the four lay inspectors in Scotland, we find that the lay inspectors in the Saorstát number seventeen, and that instead of three medical inspectors, we have here no less than ten.  I maintain that there is no necessity in the wide world for this excessive number of inspectors.  When I look further at the Estimate, I find that travelling expenses are put down at not less than £11,200.  That is the Estimate, but the actual expenditure may not amount to that figure.  I am going to make a very serious suggestion, and it is that it would be very much better to pay a number of these men their salaries and let them remain at home, rather than be paying them for running over the country when there is not sufficient work for them to do.  At the time I allude to, in 1919, there were in all Ireland four medical male inspectors and one female inspector, with two inspectors of lunacy.  Now in the Twenty-six Counties we have no less than ten of these inspectors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to ask, also, why the Medical Inspector, who is the Inspector of Lunacy, should receive a very much larger salary than the other inspectors. Is he more fully qualified, or better qualified, or is he a much more senior man than the men who are acting as ordinary medical inspectors?  I state quite seriously, too, that the <Col N="1950" /> salaries of these medical inspectors are very small.  I should like to see them very much better paid, but I should like to see their numbers very much reduced.  I can understand that there are difficulties, perhaps, in the way of reduction.  It may be impossible to find work for these men to do once they have been put on the list of inspectors. And I also feel that, probably, during the past year or two, there has been a good deal of work in organising the County Health Homes, and that that may have performed an excessive amount of work.</P>
    <P>With regard to an item lower down, I see that there are eighteen officials connected with the Irish Land Act of 1919.  The Estimate for the salaries of these officials amounts to £4,330.  I take it, however, that the statement below, that expenditure under this Act is a charge on British funds, means that it really does not matter to the Saorstát what is paid, or what number of officers are employed in this respect, and that it does not matter very much whether the item is increased or not. I want to finish, then, by saying that I should like to protest here against the employment of seventeen lay inspectors and ten medical inspectors who are running all over the country; and it is not only the question of their salaries, but the amount of travelling expenses that the increased number of inspectors entail.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that Deputy Sir James Craig should be rather more considerate for our position in this matter.  Any time he comes over to my office I would be willing to show him in detail the amount of work that those various medical inspectors are doing, and I think that he will afterwards agree that they are not by any means underworked.  During the last few years we have had practically a revolution in local government in Ireland; and. as a result of that, duties have been cast on the shoulders of inspectors that were never thrown on their shoulders before.  During the struggle with the British an inspector was a regular autocrat, I might say, down the country.  He had to undertake all the duties of county council, urban council, district council, and the <Col N="1951" /> Ministry of Local Government, and of everything else combined; and it has taken us some time to break away from that position.  We are at the present time only in the formative stage of local government under the new regime. As compared with last year, there is an actual reduction of twenty-seven in our inspectors' staff, mainly as a result of definitive transfers to other departments of staffs already on loan.  The Ministry's Vote for the present year contains provision for some members of the Local Government Board staff who were seconded for service in other Departments of the Government in 1922, and are still on loan, and also for certain staff on loan to the Soldiers and Sailors Department in connection with the provision of houses for British ex-servicemen. Excluding inspectors and auditors, the number of such staff provided for is 27.</P>
      <P>The total inspectorial staff comprises 46 members, but of this number 6 are on loan to other Departments, and 3 have been appointed to discharge the duties of the Dublin Guardians and the Dublin Corporation.  Five, including one Medical Inspector, are engaged on old age pensions work.  The number of appeals on claims and on questions raised in respect of existing pensions was very much higher than last year, and this meant throwing an additional burden of work on the shoulders of the inspectors.  On the whole, when the peculiar difficulties and circumstances of the present situation are taken into consideration, I think it will have to be admitted that our staff is not by any means excessive.  At the same time, I realise that at some future time we will be able to make considerable reductions in this Department, but this cannot be for some considerable time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. DAVID HALL Mr. DAVID HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVID HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister inform us of any hours between morning and night during which any of the lay inspectors is bound to give his service to the particular county or counties to which he is appointed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>The inspector is expected to carry out his duties during reasonable hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1952" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware, while he endeavours to justify himself in employing these inspectors, that many of them&mdash;I know one in particular who spends the greater portion of his time driving about in a motor car, not on any public business, but playing hockey, golf, and lawn tennis, and more particularly going to race meetings?  And the State is paying him for doing that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not got as much time as the Deputy to observe the different amusements and enjoyments that my staff engage in when they are off duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask you to make inquiries into this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy sends me information of the facts, I will be willing to make very careful inquiries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no check over them.  They can do what they like.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister inform us in connection with the provision for soldiers and sailors under the Irish Land Act, whether the Government has any longer any voice in the distribution of the land which takes place under this Act, or whether it is merely under the Trustee that that sort of control comes in?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>These lands are distributed through the Trustee appointed, and we have absolutely no control whatsoever over these lands at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to know if the Minister for Local Government has any control over the provision of houses for ex-soldiers and sailors, or is it the Trustee who also looks after them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Trustee only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to point out the extraordinary amount spent on travelling.  Roughly, I find it amounts for all Departments to £605,000, which means £2,000 every day is spent on travelling expenses.  I think this is an item that ought to be looked into a little more carefully.  It was in connection with the Inspectors that I thought the amount of £11,000 was very excessive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1953" />
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Owing to the large volume of work the Inspectors have to do, it is natural to expect that travelling expenses should be high, and until we are in a position to reduce our staff of Inspectors they will remain so. After all, if we have a staff at all it is necessary to keep them going around and performing their duties.  If there is anything in particular Deputy Sir J. Craig objects to, I will be willing to show him our accounts and go into the whole matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Does not the subsistence allowance of £1 per night seem excessive for the Inspectors?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Under Sub-head C I notice the salaries of auditors, who number 26, including stock-takers, as against 32 of the previous yéar.  Out of the 26, it appears that one first class Auditor and two second class Auditors are on loan to another Department.  I take it from that, that the condition of the accounts of the local authorities is so far in advance of what it was last year that the Minister can afford to loan to other Departments some of his staff.  It seems to indicate that the work has been got over, and the complaints that we have been hearing about are pretty well satisfactorily adjusted. But I want to draw attention to a specific instance where I think the Auditor has gone beyond his authority and acted&mdash;shall I say?&mdash;as an agent for the Government, for the Ministry, in their wage cutting propaganda.  We hear many times that Auditors are semi-judicial and have power outside the control of the Ministry, and if that is so they are entitled to audit accounts, but they are not entitled to direct policy.  I am referring to the position of the Monaghan Urban District Council, regarding which I raised a question some time ago, and to which I got an answer.  The question was:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;To ask the Minister for Local Government and Public Health whether his attention has been drawn to the report of the Auditor of the accounts of the Monaghan Urban District Council, dated the 21st February, 1924, in which the weekly wage of 47s. 6d. paid to the Council's employees is described as &ldquo;extravagant.&rdquo; and a surcharge is threatened <Col N="1954" /> if such payments are found at the next audit to have been continued; whether he is aware that workers employed by private persons in Monaghan town as railway labourers, builders' groundmen and hodsmen, etc., receive wages of 45s. 6d., 47s., 48s., and 50s. a week; and whether he considers that the fact that an Auditor differs from the local authority in his judgment as to what constitutes a normal, reasonable or expedient payment is sufficient to constitute a payment &ldquo;unfounded&rdquo; within the meaning of Section 12 of the Local Government (Ireland) Act, 1871.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The answer I received to that question was that the Minister had no information as to the rates of wages paid to the employees in the town outside the Urban Council employment, and that it was &ldquo;open to any interested party to bring any material information under the notice of the Auditor,&rdquo; and, further, that the Auditor was &ldquo;empowered to disallow and strike out all payments, charges and allowances which are made countrary to the law or which he deems to be unfounded.&rdquo; Now, here is a position where the Auditor has taken upon himself the duty of saying that the rate of £2 7s. 6d. is extravagant, and because it is extravagant in his view, he interprets his duty, which allows him to disallow a payment which he thinks unfounded, to cover his view of what is extravagant. The extravagance consists in a payment above what may be paid in some other services, but apparently there has been no question of considering the rate of pay in the town.  Of course, this action on the part of the Auditor appears to have been the result of a deputation, or rather of a communication sent by the local employers, and when the Auditor obeyed the instructions of the local employers, then, of course, came the local employers to say, &ldquo;You see what the Local Government Department says, and the local urban employers have now to reduce the wages to that paid to the local urban employees.  We have to come down upon you, and reduce the wages of the ordinary employees working in the town.&rdquo;  That is a perfect illustration <Col N="1955" /> of the policy, say, of the Local Government Ministry.  Then the Auditor's test of extravagance appears to be the rate of wages paid in other urban districts not connected with Monaghan, taking no account of the rate of wages paid in the town, and then listening to the local employers complaining of the rate of wages and making this report, with the obvious conclusion that local employers then come upon their non-municipal workmen and say &ldquo;We, too, must reduce the wages.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Then we will be told by the Minister that it is not his policy to interfere or to attempt to bring down the wages of the ordinary private employee; that he is not using his power in the municipal life of the country to try to degrade generally the standard of life of the working classes.  The auditors' authority under the 1871 Act, as has been stated, is that he shall disallow and strike out of every such account all payments, charges and allowances made by any authority and charged on any fund contrary to law which he deems to be unfounded, and shall surcharge the same upon the person making or authorising the making of the illegal payment.  I suggest to the Dáil that if the duties of the auditor are to be interpreted in the way that has been done in this case&mdash;that he should listen to the complaint of private employers and shall order, which is in effect what happened, the local council to reduce the wages from 47s. 6d. to something lower, on the ground that that wage is extravagant&mdash;we are simply getting into a state where the Minister is going to endeavour to rule the rate of wages in the country whether for municipal employment, national employment or private employment. The illustration that I am bringing before the Dáil is simply one other following many that have been already dealt with time after time, and is brought forward to show, by the accumulation of evidence, the course of policy which the Minister is following. I say that he is exceeding his authority, and not only exceeding his authority, but going outside the two lines of public policy.  I expect the Minister will <Col N="1956" /> say that he cannot be held responsible for the reports of the auditor, that the auditor is an independent authority, somewhat analogous to the Comptroller and Auditor-General in national accounts. I suggest that the Comptroller and Auditor-General, or any such person, ought not to attempt to dictate to a local council the rate of wages to be paid and has no right to order, which by inference he does, under threat of surcharge, that the rate of wages ruling in the town should be lowered, that the rate of wages paid by private employers should thereby be reduced and, as a consequence, that the general standard of living of the working classes in that town should be lowered and degraded.  I am sorry that the Minister for Finance, who represents the town, is not here to back me up in this protest.  I am sorry that the other Deputies from the County Monaghan are not here to back me up in this protest.  It so happens that I have been presented with the facts of the case as well as them, and in their absence I feel bound to raise this matter.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - CHAIRMANSHIP" RHead="OF BOUNDARY COMMISSION">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - CHAIRMANSHIP OF BOUNDARY COMMISSION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to ask permission to read a telegram which has just come.  His Excellency the Governor-General has received a telegram from Mr. Secretary of State Thomas, stating that the Prime Minister (Mr. Ramsay MacDonald) intended making the following statement in the House of Commons this evening in connection with the Chairmanship of the Boundary Commission.  I am reading the telegram as it came:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;With the approval of the Government of the Union of South Africa, His Majesty's Government have asked Mr. Justice Feetham, a member of the South African Supreme Court, to undertake this duty. I am very glad to be able to inform the House that Mr. Justice Feetham has accepted the appointment, and will leave South Africa for this country next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Perhaps I may be permitted to remind the House that Mr. Justice Feetham has already rendered valuable public service in connection with <Col N="1957" /> Indian reform.  Mr. Montague availed himself of his advice on Constitutional questions in discussions and the investigation of the preliminary drafting of Government of India Bill, 1919.  He served with distinction as Chairman of the important Committee then appointed by the Secretary of State for India to enquire into the question connected with the division of the functions in India between the Central and Provincial Governments and in Provincial Governments in that country between Executive Council and Ministers, a question the complexity and importance of which it would be difficult to overstate.  Consequent on the report of this Committee Mr. Justice Feetham gave evidence before the Joint Select Committee of both Houses which sat in the course of 1919 to consider Constitutional reform proposed in India.  It is a source of great satisfaction to His Majesty's Government to have secured for this appointment a distinguished member of the South African Judiciary.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The message came into my hands during the time that Deputy Johnson was speaking, and I took the earliest opportunity of affording the information to the Dáil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask, on that point, if the President would wish to say anything respecting the report in the morning papers regarding the reference to a committee&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a different matter.  I have been asked to allow a question on that already.  It is coming on to-morrow on the Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. -" RHead="DEBATE ON ESTIMATES RESUMED">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - DEBATE ON ESTIMATES RESUMED.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson has raised a great storm in a teacup with reference to this estimate.  If the only evidence he has on which to base his claim that I am falling foul of public policy, is the conduct of an auditor of my department in giving expression to an opinion that a certain wage was too high.  I think that he has established a very poor case.  This auditor has not even surcharged.  Even if he had surcharged in this particular case, and <Col N="1958" /> assuming that he had done an injustice in doing so&mdash;which has not been conclusively proved to me&mdash;I do not think it would be very much to go on, for I would have still the right to remit the surcharge, and there would be the same right of applying in the High Court.  On the whole, it is quite a hypothetical case to be making such a pother about.  I have never discussed policy with an auditor or influenced the decisions of auditors in matters of this kind in any way.  Like all other human beings they are liable to make mistakes, and I have no doubt that if this auditor has made a mistake in this particular case a wholesome public opinion will be brought to bear upon him, and will influence him to adopt better conduct in the future. Deputy Johnson has raised a point about two auditors who have been loaned from my department and, incidentally, he has, by innuendo, suggested that the auditors of my department are not all that is to be desired as regards the performance of their duties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>took the Chair at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want the Minister to be under a wrong impression. My suggestion was&mdash;if you like, my innuendo was&mdash;that the work was no longer so great as to call for the attention of such a staff, and that therefore the maladministration of local authorities was not evident, because the auditors could be spared for other departments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I might say that these auditors could be ill spared, and they were only loaned to the Exchequer and Audit department because the services of very experienced men were required. It is a new department and had no staff to deal with the important matters that came before it.  It was for that reason these auditors were lent. At the present time we are understaffed as regards auditors.  The position as regards the audit is that from the local elections of January and July, 1920, the activities of the then Local Government auditors ceased.  Early in 1921 the Dáil Ministry appointed a staff of four auditors to scrutinise the accounts <Col N="1959" /> of local authorities.  These auditors could not conduct a legal audit, and the difficulties of the time were such that it was impossible for them to make a stay of more than a day or two in one place.  The position at the date of the Truce was that there were all round arrears of two years in the accounts of local authorities, as well as very considerable arrears prior to that, in some areas.  After the Truce two of the four auditors employed by the Dáil Ministry resigned on political grounds and a new staff was recruited, which has since been dealing with the accounts of public authorities.  A great deal of extra work was thrown on the staff owing to the amalgamation schemes which necessitated the winding up of all the union accounts, and the transfer of assets and liabilities to the county councils, as well as the necessary adjustment as between one area and another comprised in the former union area.  The present position as regards audits is: Union accounts in the majority of the counties are finally closed; rural district councils are approximately two half years in arrear; urban councils are approximately 12 months in arrear; county councils are approximately 12 months in arrear.  It is anticipated that during the financial year all the accounts of local authorities will be brought up to date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to refer to (d) &ldquo;Travelling, etc., of Auditors,&rdquo; which, I am glad to say, as far as I have the expenditure before me, shows that it has been reduced by about £700. I was going to call attention to the fact that in the Report of the Comptroller and Auditor-General on Travelling and Subsistence Charges, he says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;My examination of the accounts disclosed an appreciable number of cases in which I was not satisfied that the claims made by public officers for travelling and subsistence expenses were reasonable and necessary.  In addition, many unvouched charges for travelling were included in the accounts, and claims for car hire were submitted without details of the actual journeys undertaken.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>He finishes up at the bottom by saying:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1960" />&ldquo;I have instructed my officers to scrutinise all claims for travelling and subsistence expenses appearing in the accounts for the financial year 1923-24, and I hope to be able to report more favourably next year.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I have already stated that, in my opinion, these accounts require to be more carefully looked into than in the past.  I am satisfied with regard to this, now that the Comptroller and Auditor-General, at all events, is going to see that there are vouchers for travelling. I maintain, however, that the travelling expenses are on far too high a level for the amount of work that is done.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>As to H (2), &ldquo;Telegrams and Telephones,&rdquo; there is a considerable expansion in this item, from £372 in 1923-24 to £560.  Is that owing to some extension of the telephone system?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a Post Office estimate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>This item of telegrams and telephones will be continually cropping up.  On looking over the accounts I was impressed by the enormous cost attributed to this service. As roughly as I could make it up, it comes to £26,000 for telegrams and telephones in the various Departments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we are entitled to a little more explanation than that given by the Minister.  There is an increase of nearly 80 per cent. on this item.  The tendency exists, and has always existed, in Government offices, to send a telegram when a letter could be written.  That must be checked by the responsible Minister, and unless the Dáil makes it plain that Ministers have got to check it, it will not be done.  It is all very well to say that it is putting the money from one pocket into another, and that the Postmaster-General gets it, but it means keeping up an unnecessary staff.  The Postmaster-General has to employ a staff that he would not otherwise require.  These telegrams are mostly sent from Dublin, and it means that in the Dublin offices more telegraphists have to be employed than would otherwise be needed.  We have an absolute right to an explanation from the Minister as to why there is an increase of 80 per cent. on this <Col N="1961" /> estimate, and why it is anticipated that there will be a still greater expenditure under this heading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Post Office estimate, and my Department is not responsible for it.  At the present time every possible check is being applied in my Department.  I think business men have found that in the long run it pays to communicate by telegraph rather than by letter.  We get a great many complaints from time to time about delay in answering correspondence and things of that kind.  Matters are continually cropping up which do not brook any delay, where we have to intervene at the earliest possible moment, such as the Letterkenny strike and other similar matters when certain emergencies arise, and where the telegraph or telephone must be used.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister tell us who are entitled to frank telegrams in his Department?  I am not referring now to telephones.  Do telegrams have to go to the Secretary, or how many officers have the right to send telegrams on their own initiative? That is rather an important point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that this privilege, or right, is confined to a limited number of heads of Departments. It is not a right that is given to every clerk.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Minister states that this is a Post Office charge, in answer to Deputy Hewat's complaint that there had been an increase, are we to infer that there may not have been actually an increase in the use of telephones and telegrams but that the Minister thinks that the Post Office is entering a charge in excess of what might have been the case, because Deputy Hewat has drawn attention to the fact that there has been a very considerable increase, and the answer to that was that this is a Post Office charge?  Is the Post Office charge commensurate with the increase, or is it not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an estimate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>What I meant to suggest is that it is for the Post Office to estimate what our expenditure will be <Col N="1962" /> in this matter, that we ourselves do not make this estimate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister accept the Post Office estimate without checking it?  That would seem to me rather unbusinesslike.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I assume we check it, but not for the purpose of making the estimate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with sub-head K, grants to voluntary hospitals in respect of duty on spirits, that was an item in the Estimates last year, and when I asked the Minister about it he promised to let me know, but I am still in ignorance about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not quite sure, but the money has been re-voted.  It has not been spent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to congratulate the Minister on the increased expenditure that has taken place in connection with Child Welfare and Schools for Mothers.  The amount expended last year was greatly in excess of the Estimate, and I am glad to see that the Ministry is estimating for a larger expenditure now.  I do not think money could be better spent than in this direction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister give us a little enlightenment on this? I, too, am full of faith that this is an improvement, and that the Estimate of £3,500 over and above that of last year indicates an extension of the work, but I think it would be well to have from the Minister some information respecting this work and where the increase arises.  What extensions have there been, either in the number of places where the work is carried on, or increased activities in the places where it has been carried on hitherto?  I think that the Minister would be well advised to give us some enlightenment on this matter and to justify the increase. I am quite sure that he can do so, and I think it would do something to rehabilitate him in the good graces of some of the Deputies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of fact the Estimate for last year was £7,000 and the amount spent was £12,879, so that the expenditure had run up at a tremendous rate during the year, and the Estimate now is for <Col N="1963" /> something in the neighbourhood of £800 more than the actual expenditure that took place during last year.  It is quite evident that the Minister has no idea that there will be the same extension of this work during the coming year as took place during last year, when the expenditure was £5,870 more than the Estimate.  If the expansion were to take place on the same scale as last year we should require an Estimate of something like £18,000.  I shall be very glad, with Deputy Johnson, to hear in what direction this expansion has taken place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>At present this whole question of medical treatment of school children and child welfare schemes is more or less limping with a halt, as somebody referred to local government in Ireland some days ago, and until the Local Government Bill goes through I am afraid we will not be able to do anything very comprehensive in the way of giving the necessary support to this very desirable object which, I am glad to say, all Deputies are in sympathy with.</P>
      <P>In its broader aspect the Maternity and Child Welfare grant may be vindicated by a recent pronouncement of an eminent authority:&mdash;&ldquo;The health of mothers and children is quite fundamental. It lies at the basis of all public health and of all true national wellbeing.&rdquo; In its local application the grant provides for a helpless section of the community, affording trained nursing services for attendance and for instruction, medical advice and hospital treatment, nourishing food for the necessitous and institutional or other maintenance for those deprived of parental care.  The interval of seven years since the grant was introduced has witnessed a marked and well sustained reduction in infant mortality, most notably affecting those stages of infancy which are susceptible to the effects of an improved knowledge and practice of mothercraft.  The infant mortality rate in 1922 was the lowest on record. Furthermore the grant has indirectly served the purpose of maintaining a number of district nursing societies, which would otherwise have succumbed owing to shortage of funds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1964" /> The Vote of £10,000 for the present year is not a true measure of current or future requirements, seeing that it represented an arbitrary curtailment of the figure £13,000 recommended twelve months ago.  The actual outlay for 1922-23 was just short of that figure, but should be supplemented by an amount of somewhat more than £300, which for accidental causes fell to be paid in the current financial year. In addition, there is &ldquo;normal growth,&rdquo; due to such causes as increased remuneration of officers for meritorious service, as well as the revival or reappearance of schemes which did not come under review for recoupment during the troubled period.  I have recently expressed the view that the liabilities for the current year may be reckoned at a minimum of £13,000.  As a means of retrenchment it has been decided to exclude, temporarily, capital outlay from recoupment&mdash;this would be likely to affect one scheme, with a possible saving of £500&mdash;and to re-transfer to local authorities the primary liability for food schemes of voluntary agencies, undertaken by the grant under Treasury authority as an emergency measure in 1921&mdash;contemplated net saving: £500 in a full year.  It is not, however, expected that an immediate reduction of grant expenditure would follow, firstly, because we should have to finance the voluntary food schemes up to 31st March, and secondly, because the instalment principle, for which approval has been obtained, will be applied to local authorities in the next financial year.  The expenditure to 31st December, 1923, was £4,906 18s. 9d.  The greater bulk of the expenditure will arise during March quarter, when the claims of the voluntary agencies for the year 1923 fall to be met.  On the whole it is considered essential that a sum of £13,500 should be provided.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister indicate to us to what extent those schemes, such as Child Welfare Schemes, are operating in the various parts of the Saorstát?  Are they confined to the cities, or are they in existence in the rural areas?  The whole sum is not very great, spread over the Twenty-six Counties.  It would be interesting <Col N="1965" /> to know whether it is Dublin, Limerick and Cork which are getting the benefit of those schemes, or whether anything is being done in the country.  I admit the need of the cities is greater, but it would be interesting to have an idea as to the extent to which this very necessary and valuable work&mdash;I am not opposing the grant&mdash;is prevailing in the various parts of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that provision is made both in the rural and urban districts.  I have not got the list here at the present time, but I would be willing to furnish the Deputy with a list of the areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say whether the expenditure of £13,000 is mainly employed in the cities of Dublin, Cork, Limerick and Waterford? I think that the Dáil will be satisfied if we can have some general indication as to what the £13,500 is for and where it is to be expended.  We are not asking for details, but in general we think the Dáil is entitled to some information as to the scheme and the places where this work is being carried on. We want a little information as to why the Minister requires £13,500.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister say who is responsible for carrying out this scheme in the rural areas?  I understand where this scheme is carried out in an urban district the urban council is responsible, or a committee is set up by the urban council containing some outside people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>The Wexford Corporation have adopted that scheme.  They have appointed a committee to deal with it, but I think we only get £160 from the Ministry, and they are very hard-set to give us that at times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me to be obvious that under this important heading either the thing is not a very comprehensive operation or that the sum of £13,500 will certainly not cover it. After all, if there is general application in the Twenty-six Counties, both in the rural and urban districts and in the cities, £13,500 would not go a very long way.  I would like to know from the Minister if all those small services that we see here will, under the new Bill, come under a central authority, the <Col N="1966" /> Health Authority, or will they still be in those small detached amounts? Child welfare is very popular.  It appeals to people as being a very necessary thing to be carried out thoroughly.  If it comes under the Public Health official under the new regime I think it ought to be of a much more comprehensive nature than it is at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>In the rural areas this money is administered mostly by voluntary societies, but the great bulk of the fund, I should say, is administered in the cities.  There is a very comprehensive scheme in Limerick, Dublin, Cork and the larger cities.  Under our Bill it is intended, as far as possible, to centralise this expenditure under the County Medical Officers, and owing to the fact that it is carried out by different voluntary societies at present, it is very hard at a moment's notice to give detailed information about the scheme.  The great bulk of the money is expended in the larger cities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I must take exception to the Minister's remark that it is at a moment's notice.  These estimates have been on the paper for weeks, and it is the duty of a Minister, when he comes down to the Dáil to defend his estimate, to be furnished with facts necessary to support every subject.  It is quite unfair, in dealing with the Dáil, to say that this is only at a moment's notice.  These are the Minister's estimates, and it is our function to criticise them.  We are doing our duty, are putting questions, and we have a right to information.  We should not be told that the matter is being raised at short notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as the point is concerned of the Minister not giving information, I think I can give a little information as to what is done about this matter.  The proper way to find out what is actually expended is to multiply it by two.  At least £27,000 is expended for this particular function. It would be more than that.  That is approximately what would be spent. Under this scheme, local authorities are entitled to give free milk to necessitous children and expectant mothers.  There is a highly-trained nurse employed. She is called a Jubilee Nurse, I think, <Col N="1967" /> and the Department pays half her salary.  That is how the Department's money is spent&mdash;on provision of free milk and the payment of half the agreed expenses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputies wish to pass the item I will be able to deal with it more fully later on.  I think Deputy Cooper took me up wrongly in what I said.  I have no objection to criticism in this matter at all; I welcome it.  At the same time Deputy Cooper must realise that it is hard for me to anticipate what questions will arise on any particular item, and I would have to come down with a bundle of statistics &ldquo;that height&rdquo; to answer any possible questions of that kind in detail.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think what I have stated is correct.</P>
      <P>Sitting suspended from 6.30 p.m. till 7.15 p.m.</P>
      <P>Committee resumed at 7.15 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>On Vote 39, sub-head N&mdash;Grants under the Education (Provision of Meals) (Ireland) Act&mdash; I note an increase of £500 over the Estimate of last year.  It is a very small increase, but it would be well that we should know how it is accounted for, and whether it indicates pressure on the part of the Ministry upon local authorities to apply this Act and enforce it in their own areas, and what response has there been applied. that pressure, if it has been applied. I would like if the Minister would oblige us by indicating the terms of the circular which he may have sent to the local authorities on this matter.  He will agree about the desirability of enforcing this Act and putting it into operation in the larger towns and cities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think we should be told what has been the action of the Minister in the direction of bringing the powers they have under the Act to their notice, and what kind of pressure he has laid upon them to enforce it.  If the response has only been an increase of £500, it has not been very satisfactory to the local authorities, and if he will show me that he has brought the requisite pressure to bear on the authorities, and that they have refused to respond, <Col N="1968" /> I think then we can direct our criticism to the local authorities.  In the meantime I would like to have some indication of the Minister's policy in this matter, and to what extent he has brought his persuasiveness to bear upon the local authorities in regard to the Act.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>In this matter, I would like to know from the Minister if it is the policy of his department to object to pupils in the Christian Brothers' Schools taking advantage of this provision of meals for school children.  I know that some of his auditors have drawn the attention of some councils in the Saorstát to matters that were considered illegal.  The idea was that the poor children in the Christian Brothers' Schools should be prevented from having meals under this Act.  I think we have arrived at that stage now that such disabilities should be removed.  I would like to hear from the Minister that, in future, there will be no objection to pupils in Christian Brothers' Schools being treated the same as pupils in National Schools.  Christian Brothers have done a good deal in this country.  There are poor children endeavouring to take advantage of the education afforded them by the Christian Brothers, and the Minister ought not to stand in their way in the matter of having meals provided for them.</P>
      <P>Recently the Minister sent out a circular objecting to the procedure of some local authorities in the allocation of this grant.  I think most urban areas are limited to striking a rate of 2d. in the £.  In Wexford that rate realises £160 and we get £160 from the Minister.  The School Attendance Committee there meets monthly, and at a certain period in the year they ask the different schools for a list of the poor children attending.  The Wexford School Attendance Committee adopted the procedure of spreading the money over five or six schools in the year, <i>pro rata.</i>  The Ministry object to that procedure, and they insist that the School Attendance Committee should administer the money in detail.  That is an impossible task.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>By itself the School Attendance Committee, with the amount of money <Col N="1969" /> provided, would not be able to cope successfully with the number of poor children attending the various schools. All the schools have a certain amount of their own money, and with this they augment the amount obtained from the School Attendance Committee.  It would be a most injudicious thing for the Minister to insist on the regulations that he sent out to the local authorities. I would ask the Minister to agree to the arrangements that existed up to the present.  The School Attendance Committee get the money, and they superintend the serving of meals periodically, and are satisfied that the thing is done properly.  Considering the small amount spent in urban areas, I do not think that the Minister should insist on any rigid regulations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestHAlton" hpid="Mr. ALTON Mr. ALTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ALTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know whether Deputy Johnson asked for a categorical answer to his question of how much was actually expended last year by the Government in this way. We have not got the appropriation allowances for this year, and the grants, of course, gives us no idea of how much was actually spent.  Perhaps the Minister, if he has not given the information already, will give it now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Practically the whole Estimate has been spent.  Deputies Johnson and Corish have asked for rather comprehensive information under this sub-head.  With regard to the position of Christian Brothers' Schools, I have no objection to allowing them to come under those provisions, but I have no legal power at present to allow the granting of meals to their pupils.  I would have no objection to any amendment to that effect that would be introduced in the Local Government Bill.  The urban councils are empowered to make arrangements for the provision of meals for children attending the National Schools if there are any children who, by reason of lack of food, fail to take full advantage of the education provided for them, and when there are no other funds available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In those circumstances, the council may be authorised to expend from the rates such sum as would meet the cost of such food, the amount not exceeding an expenditure equivalent to the <Col N="1970" /> produce of a rate of ½d. in the £ on the district.  The amending Act of 1916 doubled this amount, and the limitation was entirely removed by the 1917 Act, which also contained provision for the recoupment to the Council of any sums they expended in providing meals for school children, subject to certain regulations.  It will be noted that the limit of expenditure on successive occasions pointed to a rapid increase in the outlay.  This upward tendency in the cost appears to have continued.  The most expensive scheme is in the Dublin Co. Borough, and the highest point was reached in 1919-20, when £14,560 11s. 10d. was spent. Owing to lack of funds the scheme was curtailed the following year, and only £1,926 19s. 7d. was earned from the grant.  The recoupment in 1922-23 rose to £4,461 4s. 6d., and the total expenditure of the latter year was £12,166 10s. 10d.  According to the return received in the 33 schools in the Dublin scheme, 6,143 children were authorised to receive meals, at an average daily number of 5,640.  In Cork Co. Borough the recoupment rose from £375 to £1,123 for the last financial year.</P>
    <P>It will thus be seen that this grant, if it is not rigidly controlled, is likely to reach an excessive amount, and, for that reason, our Department has to be very careful as to the amount of money expended under it.  I am not aware that any circular issued from our Department has resulted in hardship in this particular line.  If Deputy Corish has any recommendations to make on the head of that circular, I would be willing to give them every consideration.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The information that the Minister has given with regard to the history of this Act and the experience of past years is very valuable and useful in many ways.  But we are dealing with the Estimate for this current year, and I was anxious to know what was the policy of the Ministry in regard to the utilisation of this Act by the local authorities.  In the last phrase or two the Minister suggests that it is necessary for the Department to be somewhat rigid in its sanction or in its approval of schemes. Does that mean that the Department is <Col N="1971" /> not to encourage the local authorities to put this Act into operation, or does it mean that it is to discourage the local authority from putting this Act into operation?  The amounts mentioned undoubtedly are very small, and it is perhaps true to say that the local authorities, or some of them, would be quite willing to vote sums of money for the purpose of feeding school children. But others of them would probably require some prompting and would require some advice as to the necessitous.</P>
      <P>We have had information of circulars having been issued from the Department regarding the rates of pay that should be fixed by local authorities, all in the direction of cutting down the rates of pay.  In a general way, that implies a lowering of standards, and, incidentally, has the effect, as I would argue on a fitting occasion, of extending the area of unemployment. But the Minister realises himself, as he has expressed several times, that there is a great amount of distress.  There is a great amount of poverty, and here in this country, and in this city, as in every other place where poverty is general, the children suffer, very often unknown to themselves.  Weakness develops, and they do not realise it. There is no apparent suffering, but there is actual deterioration of physical stamina.  Under this Act local authorities have power to levy rates and make provision by the collection of funds from private sources.  I should take it that the Minister will have no alternative but to provide for the half expenditure on sanctioned schemes.  What I desire to know is: What has been the policy of the Ministry in regard to this Act?  Have they, in fact, encouraged the local authorities to meet the needs of the children by providing school meals?  Inasmuch as only £5,500 has been budgeted for, this year, can he say where the fault lies?  How many of the local authorities have been recalcitrant in this respect?  How many of them have refused to follow his advice or can he say how many local authorities have taken advantage of the Act, and made provision for the feeding of school children?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I believe, of course, that this whole scheme should be developed to a very <Col N="1972" /> great extent and that it should not be confined to the provision of a very meagre or plain meal, bread and cocoa, bread and jam and cocoa or bread and jam and milk, as it too often is.  I would like to see this whole scheme developed so as to be part of the educational system, where children in the National Schools would be dealt with in regard to their dinner or their meal just as they would be in a boarding school and learn to delight in the common meal. But I suppose we are a little bit distant from that, and we have to be satisfied with what is available at the moment. But are we making the best use of the powers that exist?  Is the Ministry doing its best to encourage local authorities to make provision for children attending school so that they shall not be a burden upon their teachers for one thing, and that they will be able to take advantage of the education that is provided for them, and that the education vote, that we will be dealing with at a later stage, will be more economically spent because the children will be in a better position to take advantage of the lessons that are put before them?  This is not a simple matter, not a matter that should be passed over carelessly or with a few words explaining what was intended.  It is a matter going to the roots of the policy of the Ministry and quite apart from and different from other measures which are compulsory and which we will deal with later.  Here we have a voluntary Act, that is to say, an Act under which the local authorities have the option of putting the scheme into force, but when they do so, then the Central Authority, the State, comes to the financial assistance of these local authorities.</P>
    <P>I want to know whether the Ministry have, for this positive, constructive work of upbuilding the children and keeping them in physical fitness, adopted a policy of suggestion and urging in these cases as they have done in other Departments of their responsible work, or are we to blame the local authorities wholly?  Have the Ministry, as a matter of fact, brought the suggestions to the local authorities with regard to the utilisation of their powers under this Act?  Will the Minister produce for us or tell us what has <Col N="1973" /> been the line of his advice?  Will he give us the terms of his Circular Letters? I have not had supplied to me, and I have made some inquiry, but those from whom I have inquired are not able to say whether any urgings of this kind have come from the Ministry. It seems to me that if the Ministry have not taken positive steps to bring before the local authorities the desirability of using their powers in this matter, then the Ministry has failed in its duty.  I would like the Minister to tell us fully what his Department has done in this matter, and I would like further, if he would tell us what local authorities have made use of their powers under this Act in the last year, and does he propose to bring to their notice early the necessity for making provision and making preparation for a fuller expenditure under the Act in the coming winter months?  Because, unfortunately, it is in the winter months that the greater need is for the provision of meals for school-children.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>I said a few days ago that Ireland had been cursed with permissive Acts of Parliament. This is one of them.  We want to get public opinion with us in this matter, and it will take some time to bring it up to the point Deputy Johnson has in mind.  I have been advocating for a considerable time the necessity for some food to be given to children in the National Schools.  As Deputy Johnson has pointed out, the children cannot take the value out of the educational facilities afforded them if they are hungry or under-fed.  In particular, I pity the children in the rural schools&mdash;children who get probably a breakfast at seven or eight o'clock in the morning.  They get a little to take with them, but sometimes this is eaten before they get to school, and these children are kept in school for six hours, after which they have to walk two or three miles home again.  In the case of the rural schools there should be some provision made.  I would not care whether it was done by voluntary association or otherwise.  I would rather see it done by the local sanitary authority which, if the Bill now before the Dáil passes, will be the Board of Health.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1974" /> At all events, as I say, we must get the public educated up to the point to say that the children must be fed in the middle of the day.  In the schools of the city there are two classes attending. They are children who could go home and get something to eat, and children who could go home and get nothing. But you cannot differentiate between these two, and in my opinion there must be a simple meal provided.  I do not care about cocoa; I would prefer that the children get a half-pint of milk with a slice of bread and butter.  That may be resented, by some of the teachers. Some of the teachers do not want the bother of getting the meal for the children.  But we should endeavour to teach the teachers that that would necessarily be part of their duty, and I do not think that in the long run it would be very expensive, number 1, or very difficult to carry out, number 2, if even this simple meal I suggest were given to them.  But I do say that this is a great necessity, and I repeat that as far as Deputy Johnson and his followers are concerned, I think they should, on all occasions when they speak in public, refer to this as a necessary matter. One can see from the amount that is spent here, how few of the District Councils have taken advantage of the adoption of this scheme that, I have no doubt, was put up to them by the Government. I may say in passing that the discussion this afternoon has shown that we are sadly wanting in not having a Minister of Health, or as I suggested on the Estimates before, at least a Parliamentary Secretary, because it is absolutely impossible for the Minister for Local Government, who has no knowledge of these matters, and who only quite recently has come to his present position, to give the information at a moment's notice.  It would be impossible for any Minister for Local Government to carry all this information and to give it to us at once when requested.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to know, before the Minister replies, what proportion of the local authorities has taken advantage of this Act and is there, a tendency in the urban areas towards an increase or decrease, as here set out in this item of expenditure?  So <Col N="1975" /> far, I entirely agree with what Deputy Sir James Craig has said.  The question of cocoa and bread certainly means nothing.  I can speak for Wexford, where we insist that the children should be provided with soup and milk on different occasions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the policy of my Department to give every encouragement to this scheme, and the Department has circularised the local authorities to this effect, and sent out our inspectors with instructions to give the local authorities very full information as to how this scheme should be carried out.  We are in the fullest sympathy with the idea of extending and developing this scheme.  Deputy Sir James Craig has referred to the fact that it is a permissive Act.  In some respects, probably that is a good thing, but until we have the whole local government administration properly centralised in an Act, when I believe this would come in under the control of the County Medical Officer, we have very little facilities for having our views on matters of this kind put into operation. I have no reason to wish to interfere unduly with the undoubted discretion of the local authorities in such matters. As I say, we have done everything to explain the benefits which will be conferred upon the growing population, and it is a necessity in very many cases to the local authority, and we can do very little more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Different councils provide different meals.  In some cases, as Deputy Corish has mentioned, soups and stews which are a very substantial kind of food, are provided.  In other cases bread and butter, or bread and jam and milk and cocoa, are provided.  Deputy Sir J. Craig has referred to the rural districts.  I do not think that the necessity is by any means as great in rural districts as in towns for provision of this kind.  As a general rule country children are very much better provided with healthy food, and in my own experience, I saw very few children going to school in the country districts who did not carry their lunch under their arms.  With regard to the local authorities who have taken up this scheme, I think they only number <Col N="1976" /> 24; they are:&mdash;Athlone U.D.C., Athy, Bray, Carlow and Cavan&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister give the figures of the amount they expend or of the amounts to which they are entitled?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I have these details by me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Because some of these local authorities applied the Act years ago, but have not continued to carry it through, and I would like to know whether these 24 authorities include those who may have dropped it since.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>The authorities I am giving are those actually operating, but I could not give the figures at the moment:&mdash;Cork County Borough, Dublin County Borough, Dungarvan U.D.C., Enniscorthy U.D.C., Fermoy U.D.C., Kells U.D.C., Kilkenny U.D.C., Killarney U.D.C., Dun Laoghaire U.D.C., Listowel U.D.C., Navan U.D.C., New Ross U.D.C., Templemore U.D.C., Tullamore U.D.C., Waterford County Borough, Waterford City, Wexford Youghal, Mallow and Sligo U.D.C's.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>We now come to sub-head (O), and there we have a very different classification from that with which we have been dealing. There we come to something that is mandatory upon the county councils. I would find it very hard here to reserve any nice things to say of the Government if matters had not been so difficult for them.  Until a county medical officer of health is appointed who would be able to take charge of this and look after it properly, I kept very quite.  At the same time, I think that the Government should have made an effort, as far as possible, to get this scheme, which they drafted, and which I presume they sent round to the county councils, adopted.  At the same time I say their difficulty was that there might have been an officer appointed who would have been placed in a position that he might not have been able to retain when the Local Government Bill which has been introduced came into force.  For that reason, I am very easy upon them.  But <Col N="1977" /> we want to make quite sure that there will be no mistake about the inclusion of this provision in the scheme adopted in connection with the new Bill.  As was pointed out by Deputy O'Connell and myself, when there was no reference whatever in the Local Government Bill in regard to this matter, the Act at present in force is mandatory, and the county councils must adopt it if the Government insisted upon it.  But, as I say, we are not going to criticise too severely, because we want to see the county medical officer of health appointed.  He will be, as it were, the head of all these services.  All these services will be co-ordinated under the county medical officer of health.  The small sum of money put down here for inspection of schools and treatment of school children is simply absurd, and there is very little use asking the Minister what county councils adopted it when the whole sum only amounts to £1,660.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, want to draw attention to the fact that this is not a voluntary optional scheme.  It is one which is mandatory, and imposes upon County Borough Councils the duty of providing medical treatment for school children.  The Act further provides that if local authorities fail in their duty, then it is for the Minister to enforce the Act by appointing persons to do the work and to pay them.  The duty is then upon the Minister to see that the Act is enforced.  If it is not enforced by the county authority, he is obliged to do it.  I would like to know in how many cases that has been done. I would like to know from the Minister in how many towns or counties, or county boroughs, the Act has been enforced. On the last Vote the Minister pleaded the necessity for centralisation and for a compulsory law in the matter of the provision of meals.  Here we have a compulsory Act providing for the medical treatment and inspection of children, and what, I ask, has he done in connection with that?  What is the policy of the Ministry in respect to this Act?  Has he enforced the law? Let me say that it is not enough to point to the defects of the county <Col N="1978" /> councils if there have been defects. Here we have, as I say, a mandatory Act.  Will the Minister tell us what the Commissioner, who has been responsible for the administration in Kerry, has done?  Has he provided for the medical inspection of school children?  Is the law carried out in Kerry in respect to this?  Is the Commissioner, who is administering the affairs in Leitrim County at present, carrying out the law in respect to this? If not, what has the Minister done to bring his duty to his notice?  There are £1,600 paid for this work.  I ask, will the Minister bring immediately to the notice of the Commissioners for the County Borough of Dublin that they must provide medical inspection and treatment of school children, that it is the law?  The provision of £1,600, as Deputy Sir James Craig has mentioned, rather suggests that not a great deal has been done.  The Act was passed in 1919, and one can explain quite easily why it was not given effect to during the two or three years following its passing.  But the year 1923 was one in which the Act could have been enforced, and this is a year in which the Act could be enforced.  Will the Minister tell us what is his policy in regard to this Act?  Has he insisted upon any of the county councils, or to bring the matter close home to him, upon any of the Commissioners that have been appointed by him to do the work of the county councils&mdash;has he insisted upon these persons fulfilling the law in respect of the medical treatment and inspection of school children?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>There was an English Act, and I assume it was drafted more with reference to the conditions in England than the conditions over here.  A county in England is a much more important unit than a county in Ireland.  The appointment of a medical inspector of schools would, I imagine, be an economic proposition for a big populous area like an English county, but it might be altogether uneconomic for an area of the size of the average Irish county.  In addition to that, at the present time we have no machinery for putting this Act into operation.  It is true, of course, that the Act is mandatory, but, even though <Col N="1979" /> it is mandatory, you would want to have some machinery for giving it effect.  I am in full agreement with the idea of putting this measure into operation.  It is intended under the new Bill to put it in force.  At the present time we are encouraging the idea in county boroughs where we have a medical superintendent officer of health to have it enforced.  If we were to enforce it in the various counties at the present time it would mean duplicating the work, and it would mean having to pension these officers when the county medical officer was appointed.  When the county medical officer is appointed in the various counties he will be able to perform several of these services, including the medical inspection of school children, tuberculosis officer, and other services, or, at least, he will be able to control those who are administering them.</P>
      <P>For these reasons I have not attempted to enforce the Act at the present time, not even in counties where Commissioners have been appointed, such as in Kerry and Leitrim.  I may say that I have issued instructions to the Commissioners of the Dublin Corporation to put the Act in force forthwith. Dublin is a place where we have the machinery for enforcing it.  Deputy Johnson cannot have it both ways.  He cannot hold up the Local Government Bill, which would give me the machinery to enforce this measure, and at the same time condemn me for not putting the Act in force.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>I just wish to correct one statement made by the Minister.  The Act dealing with the medical inspection and treatment of school children, although passed in the British Parliament, was an Act referring to Ireland.  The Act is entitled &ldquo;An Act to make provision for the Medical Inspection of Children attending Elementary Schools in Ireland, etc.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not true that the Irish Act was based on the English Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>The English Act was of old standing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has not told us whether the £1,600 was expended. <Col N="1980" /> Perhaps he will do that, because it will help us to understand the position better.  I may tell the Minister at once that if he will bring in the Local Government Bill to-morrow, shorn of its evils, and making provision for public health services, I will give him every support.  But, I am not going to be enticed to take poison under the cover of jam.  I am not quite able to understand the attitude of the Minister on this matter.  It is well that the Minister for Justice is not present.  The Minister here says that until a new law is passed that we are not going to enforce the old one; that until something is enacted which may be enacted or may be refused, we are going to let the present law lie in abeyance.  That is a rather strange doctrine to come from the Ministerial benches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that the question of medical treatment, or more particularly medical inspection, of school children is probably more important than, certainly of equal importance to, the feeding of school children, with which we have just dealt.  This sum of £1,600 refers, I presume, to two or three districts&mdash;I do not know how many.  We have no information as to whether the Act is in force.  Possibly, it is partially in force here and there, but if the Ministry is going to rely on the future enforcement of this Act, or any such Act, upon the activities of the medical officer, of the county officer of health, who is to be appointed, and if he is the person who inspects the children in the schools, as well as doing the other work, then it is going to be an enormous task.  It is quite impossible, and the work will not be done.  There is no need to wait, and I submit that it would not be a difficult task to consult with Deputy Sir James Craig and find out how the Act could be brought into operation next week.  I do not know what the Minister is boggling at when he speaks about the necessity for machinery.  Surely, there is not a great deal of machinery required to enforce an Act of this kind, and if we want to curtail the charges on the State, and upon the local authorities, in the matter of sickness, disease, and death in future years, we are going to <Col N="1981" /> expend the money in the most economical way possible, by spending it in the inspection of school children.  You would save very many thousands and hundreds of thousands of pounds, in ten, fifteen or twenty years' time, by spending a few hundreds of pounds in the care of children, in advising them when they need treatment.  I would like the Minister to take this matter up very seriously, and not to wait until a new Act comes into operation before he endeavours to put into force the law that at present exists, and should be operative.  I would like him to tell us before we pass from this where, as a matter of fact, this £1,600 is likely to be spent, and in what districts, or parts of the country the Act is in operation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson has informed us that if I brought in my Bill shorn of its evils, he would be quite willing to support it.  I am afraid if I bring in a Bill shorn of all the evils from the point of view of all the Deputies, there would be very little indeed of a Bill to bring in, because every Deputy would see the evils from a different point of view.  At present we are only attempting to apply the Act to the county boroughs, and the county of Cork is the first place where that scheme has been accepted.  We also, as I say, intend to put it into force in Dublin.  As well as that, there are various other voluntary agencies at work in different parts of the Saorstát, whose labours we are supplementing at the present time.  The present position with regard to the Estimate is of a highly speculative character, owing to the different contingencies&mdash;I mean when we were making this Estimate we did not know but our Bill would be through, and it was very hard to fix any specific sum.  Assuming that the two last-mentioned projects, that is the Dublin and the Cork schemes, should mature, a grant contribution of, say, £2,000 may be reckoned on.  In the case of one definite scheme, Cork, the initial expenditure may be taken at £80 a month, but after the preliminary surveying covering six months, the expenditure will approximate to the full estimated figure of £3,000 per annum. <Col N="1982" /> A grant requirement of £835 seems possible for 1924-25.  Another small scheme is under consideration, but the charge on the grant would be only about £50.  In considering the case of the small voluntary schemes which have been assisted from the grant pending the introduction of the Bill and arrangements we shall make under it, particulars of twelve such schemes are on record, but it would seem that only eight are still operative within the local limits in which they work, and these seem to be performing a useful service in attending to the dental defects of school children.  The cost of such might be put at £125 a year.  To meet all purposes an estimate of £2,000 is recommended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask if a scheme is actually in force in Cork?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>The scheme at the moment is not actually in force.  There is a difficulty between my Department and the county borough over the appointment of an officer who is not qualified according to our rules, and the local body was very stubborn about agreeing to the appointment of an officer who had all the qualifications we required for this purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to call the attention of the Minister on this sub-head (P) to the welfare of the blind. I want to recall to him the pledge that was given by the Minister for Finance when we were discussing the Old Age Pensions Bill.  I think several Deputies felt great reluctance about reducing the pensions for the blind&mdash;far more reluctance in that matter than in dealing with the pensions for the aged for old age is a calamity that comes to all except the more fortunate; but the blind are stricken by the hand of God.  We were able to persuade the Minister for Finance to give us an undertaking that if a suitable scheme were put up to him by the responsible Minister he would devote the savings he made on the pensions of the blind to the welfare of the blind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now, that was, I think, almost a remarkable occurrence.  The Minister for Finance usually says, like Richard III. in Shakespeare's play: &ldquo;I am not <Col N="1983" /> in a giving mood to-day.&rdquo;  But, for once in a way, the Minister for Finance was found in a giving mood.  But the Minister for Local Government has not taken advantage of that giving mood; and so far from presenting us with an increased Estimate for the welfare of the blind on a scheme to which these savings that are made in the pensions of the blind could be applied, the Minister is presenting us with a reduced Estimate, an Estimate reduced by only £60 short of £1,000.  Now, I humbly suggest that there is no justification for that action.  Once the Minister for Finance had given that undertaking, it was the duty of the Minister for Local Government, as the responsible guardian of the blind, to take advantage of that undertaking and to put to the Minister for Finance and to the Dáil a scheme for using those savings to benefit those unfortunate persons who have lost their sight. I am not suggesting that he should enlarge the bounds to include people who are merely short-sighted, who merely have a defect in seeing.  I am speaking solely of those people who are so blind that they cannot provide for themselves or look out for themselves. And I say with regret that, as their trustee, the Minister has failed in his duty.  I know he has.  I hope he will not think that I am criticising him too harshly.  He has an immense and a complicated Department, and I hope my criticism previously was not unduly severe.  He has got an enormous Department with very many details to look after, and in his zeal to eliminate the unfit, in the shape of local governing bodies, he has possibly not been able to go into all these details with sufficiently meticulous care, and to put them before the Dáil. I would suggest that in another year he would give us a White Paper, before the Estimates are discussed, giving us the details of where schemes have been put in force and the amount of money spent.  That would help the Dáil.  He is not an Executive Minister; he is responsible only to the Dáil; and this is the one opportunity that the Dáil has of canvassing his doings.  If we let this thing pass, if we wait for him <Col N="1984" /> to give us the information that he has to give, and that I know he will give us, the time will have gone by and we will have to wait until next year; and by that time the matter will be out of date.  Nobody liked to vote for the Old Age Pensions Bill, but the thing I disliked, above all other matters in it, was the cut in the pensions of the blind, and I reconciled myself to it solely and entirely because of the pledge given by the Minister for Finance.  Now, I find that the Minister for Local Government and Public Health has not availed himself of that pledge; he has neglected to put forward any scheme involving increased expenditure on behalf of the blind; he actually proposes to reduce expenditure on the blind; and I have only one course to follow, and that is, as a protest, to move the reduction of this Vote by £1 in order that we should have a division on this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I must come to the aid of the Minister, and I notice that he sits down when that happens.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Something gone wrong in the works.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>It is my sense of justice. Realising how accurate and true my position has been up to now, I feel that my position must continue to be accurate and true.  In respect of this matter, I suggest to the Deputy that the Minister had prepared this Estimate before the promise of the Minister for Finance had been made.  And we have a right to assume&mdash;I am quite sure of it&mdash;that the Minister will be coming along in a little while and saying that he has persuaded the Minister for Finance to keep his promise, and that there will be a Supplementary Estimate adding the sum that is to be purloined from the blind pensioners, and that the Minister will urge that it should be used for some other purpose under the Blind Persons Act.  And I suggest to the Deputy who wants to move the reduction that he had better wait and allow the Minister an opportunity of bringing in this Supplementary Estimate, because it is quite apparent that the promise made followed the preparation of the Estimate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>But then, again, I want to know why <Col N="1985" /> the Ministry has not carried out the law, why the Ministry has not urged upon the local authorities, who are bound by the Blind Persons Act, to put the law into operation.  There is a reduction&mdash;as the Deputy has pointed out&mdash;in this Estimate of £940, as compared with the Estimate of a year ago. It is mandatory upon the local authorities to make provision for the welfare of the blind in their districts, and to provide opportunities for employment suitable for blind persons.  That has been done to a very little extent indeed. As a matter of fact, so far as one can learn, most of this money that is to be voted will be transferred from the local authorities to certain institutions where, no doubt, good work is done, but not the work that was called for under the Blind Persons Act.  Now, if the Minister can show us that he has brought the requisite pressure to bear on the local authorities to fulfil their duties in this respect, as he has done in respect of other matters, I will acquite him of the amount of negligence that I now fear he is guilty of.  I think that it is his duty to prove to us that he has told the local authorities that they are bound to do these things, and to put into operation this Blind Persons Act.  It is his duty to prove to us that he has taken steps to find out whether the local authorities have failed to do this, and to find out what preparations they are making to put the Act into operation.  Quite apart from the promise of the Minister for Finance, how does the Minister for Local Government justify a reduction in this Vote by £940?  Is it that the local authorities are not doing as well this year as they did last year?  Is it that his instructions regarding the fulfilment of the law have been disobeyed? Then, will he tell us which of them has disobeyed in this matter, and what is he going to do?  The instructions that have been given regarding these people seem to imply that when we are dealing with matters affecting the diseased, and the sick, and the young, the Ministry is not insisting that the provisions which the law required shall be made operative, and that it is only when we come to questions of rates of <Col N="1986" /> pay, what is called economy, that the Ministry is rigid and insistent.  Now, as I said on the last Vote, there is greater economy in enforcing these Acts than in saving a few pounds, or a few thousands of pounds, or a few tens of thousands of pounds on reductions in rates of wages.  You are investing money with the certainty of a very big return in a very few years; and it is a pity to see a reduction in the Vote under this welfare of the blind scheme, such as is now presented to us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I find myself in an awkward position with Deputy Johnson coming to my rescue in such a gallant way.  I am afraid that in coming so far to my point of view he has gone a little outside his own orbit, because I find him advocating bureaucracy in this matter of asking me to interfere with local authorities in administering this fund.  All the arguments the Deputies are addressing here are arguments in favour of my Bill that has been laid on the shelf. Deputy Cooper has complained of the fact that I am not sufficiently in touch with all those activities of my Department. But in its present chaotic condition it is absolutely impossible to get in touch with every detail of administration. We have got none of these health services centralised.  They are all divided up between local authorities and voluntary societies and agencies. It is really a very difficult task to keep in touch with them all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Johnson is quite correct in saying that this estimate was made before the Minister for Finance gave his undertaking.  The Estimate was made in December.  I am quite willing to put up a scheme as promised by the Minister for Finance, and I am certainly desirous of doing what I can to help or improve the position of these unfortunate blind people.  As in so many other cases, the provision of relief in this case rests with the local authority.  The scheme which county and county borough councils are required by Section 2 of the Blind Persons Act of 1920 to formulate with a view to promoting the welfare of the blind in their areas, has not yet been adopted in any district, although a <Col N="1987" /> circular letter urging the desirability of taking action under that section, was sent to all such Councils on the 22nd March, 1922, and our inspectors have brought this matter under the attention of those Councils on several occasions.  Our grant in this particular case is based on the estimates of local authorities, and our recoupment, according to their estimate, falls short by £940, compared with the estimate for last year.  That is the explanation of the reduction of the estimate.  It is really a matter over which I have no control, except in so far as I can persuade or use persuasive powers with the local authority.  I do not believe that Deputy Johnson would suggest that I should put in Commissioners because they have refused to accede to my entreaties in this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest to the Minister that if he is going to let the law lie aside in a case of this kind, under the cover that to enforce it would be bureaucracy, he had better let it lie aside in other matters under the same cover.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I have always been brought up to believe that the most wonderful sight in the world was Satan rebuking sin.  We now have his parallel, Deputy Johnson, defending the Minister for Local Government and Public Health.  I cannot remain unmoved by such a sublime spectacle and, therefore, having regard to the undertaking given by the Minister, that he is preparing a scheme for the welfare of the blind and is going to force it home on the Minister for Finance, I will withdraw my amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>As to sub-head Q, I have really no experience of the tuberculosis schemes throughout the country, but I am told by those who do know, that these schemes have been practically failures.  Therefore, I am not encouraged to support the increase from £35,000 to £38,000 in this Estimate. I am told by those who know that these schemes are comparative failures because of want of knowledge, lack of experience, and want of enthusiasm in administering the schemes. <Col N="1988" /> No one will be better pleased than I shall be if this is denied.  It has been impressed upon me by very many people, but if the Deputies here, who have knowledge of them, state that these schemes are really producing good effects, no one will be better pleased to hear it than I shall.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I would think that an opportunity is not likely to recur, and that the Minister should take this opportunity of making a very full statement as to exactly what these schemes are, and how the administration of them stands.  No one will know better than you, sir, exactly what a scourge this matter is in certain parts of the country, especially in the extreme West.  I have had some knowledge of it myself.  In the West tuberculosis is such a scourge largely owing to mal-nutrition, and the fact that houses, infected for generations with this disease, go on being inhabited.  I know houses in Achill with which I am acquainted and with the people of which I am acquainted, where it is an ordinary thing to see young girls and boys being taken out of these houses regularly with tuberculosis, and when they are once infected with the disease, it is only a matter of weeks or months with them.  Then, if there be anybody in the locality interested to try and help these particular cases, it is the greatest difficulty in the world to try and get in touch with some part of some definite scheme that can come to the assistance of such persons as these.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I speak from long experience of lads and girls whom one has met here and there in Achill.  In the last resort one has had to apply to Dublin to friends of one's own for private charity to meet cases of this kind.  There are schemes, but nobody knows what these schemes are and exactly how the machinery may be set in motion.  Unless there be somebody on the spot who can busy himself or herself in the interests of those poor people, what generally happens is that robust men become affected and in less than twelve months are taken off to the graveyard.  The people there have not actual knowledge of the scourge, and, even when they see the thing happen <Col N="1989" /> they do not know what the scheme is, what the machinery is, and how assistance can be brought to them.  Even where people interest themselves in cases of the kind, it is difficult to find out how these schemes can be worked round to the benefit of the people affected.</P>
    <P>I think it will be admitted that, particularly in the West&mdash;I have no experience elsewhere in this matter&mdash; there ought to be a campaign of education. It should be, not merely a scheme, as I believe most of these schemes are, to help persons once they are affected by tuberculosis, but a general campaign, so that people might know exactly what a scourge it is and take preventative measures, especially as regards children being brought up in houses saturated with this infection. I urge the Minister to take this opportunity of making a statement to the Dáil, very clearly and very fully, with regard to a disease which is laying waste so much of our national life. Beginning with such a statement, the Minister should undertake a campaign throughout the country where his statistics inform him the disease is a graver evil than in other parts.  Having done that, he should bring to the knowledge of the people what exactly is meant by this scourge, and how best it can be prevented.  Where infection has occurred, the public should be told exactly how they may bring the available machinery to the benefit of those who are infected.  I can say that that knowledge is not now present to the people.  They do not realise what the scourge is, nor do they realise what infection means.  When persons are affected they do not know exactly how to get such help as might in the early stages effect a cure.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to support Deputy Figgis in what he has said regarding tuberculosis.  I would also like to hear from the Minister a statement as to the measures that are being taken in the country to call special attention to it.  I agree with Deputy Figgis that it is by means of propaganda more than anything else the disease will be conquered.  I understand tuberculosis is largely a disease arising from mal-nutrition and poverty. <Col N="1990" /> It can be prevented very largely by the use of proper food and by fresh air. Medical science, I believe, has made wonderful strides in the treatment of this disease, and it is generally recognised that if children can be kept healthy, they are pretty safe from the danger of contracting the disease after they reach a mature age.  That, I think, is not generally known.  I trust I am not trespassing in medical matters in dealing with this disease, but I happen to know something about it.  Before we can have people healthy, the first consideration, I believe, is the need for proper housing.  If people have to live in miserable homes and dirty slums, we will have tuberculosis.  The Minister cannot change that state of affairs at a moment's notice, but, he can, certainly, help by propaganda, and by getting people to recognise that almost the very poorest can take measures that will have an effect in preventing the spread of the disease.  I am afraid a great deal of misconception exists with regard to tuberculosis throughout the country, and that people are afraid of those who have the reputation of having it.  As a result, the disease is largely concealed.  I understand there is comparatively little danger of infection, except in youth, and that with fresh air, and good food, the disease can be largely prevented.  I might say that the school houses, in my opinion, are very largely to blame in the country districts. They are very often insanitary, small, and badly ventilated.  The children are crowded into these schools, and the heating is very often inadequate, the result being that such buildings are potent factors in spreading the disease.  I do not know a great deal about the county schemes, but, I think, they are not as effective as they might be.  Probably that is due to lack of finances.  The Minister may think it strange that I should urge him to spend money, but no matter how keen we may be on economy, this is a matter of urgent national importance, in which we should forget, for once, the possibility of economising.  I believe there are very elaborate schemes in England where they have tuberculosis hospitals and special medical men who <Col N="1991" /> attend and supply the patients with medicines for use in combating this disease.  The finances of this country would hardly stand that expense, but I think a good deal of tightening up might be done, and that the new county medical officers of health who are to be appointed, might be made responsible for seeing that these schemes were more effective.  Some special attempt should be made to have this disease, which has been so fatal to our race, and to which we are supposed to be particularly liable, stamped out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBRIDE Mr. MacBRIDE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBRIDE</NameTxt>
      <P>I fear that Deputy Figgis is rather prone to exaggeration in this as in other matters.  I think I ought to know the West and Achill. There are fine, intelligent, strong boys and girls in Achill, and their fathers are strong and intelligent.  As far as I know, tuberculosis is not very prevalent on the island.  If there are cases of tuberculosis there, the people know very well that they can be treated in the infirmary.  Not very long ago a very distinguished lady travelled through this country and tried to demonstrate to the world that Ireland was reeking with tuberculosis.  It is rather belated now for any Deputy to come along and tell us that one particular place in the country, that I and other Deputies have the honour to represent, is reeking with tuberculosis. It is not.  Furthermore, through the agency of the late Congested Districts Board, nearly all the houses on the island have been or are being rebuilt, and as for the lack of fresh air which Deputy Figgis regrets is not to be found as cheaply and as freely as he would wish, I can promise him that if he will come to Achill he will get plenty of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN (Clare) Mr. HOGAN (Clare)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN (Clare)</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want it to be taken for granted, because I rise to speak on the tuberculosis question, that Clare is reeking with consumption. It is not, but I think there is sufficient tuberculosis in the whole country for every Deputy to give his help in endeavouring to stem the tide of what is to some extent eating into the vitals of the nation.  I do not want to travel the ground that has already <Col N="1992" /> been travelled, and very ably travelled, by the different Deputies who have spoken, but it is quite true and, I think, obvious that this matter is important. It is more or less a problem of housing, the feeding of necessitous school-children, the medical examination of school-children, and the thousand and one other things that do not seem to have any direct touch with it when you examine it purely as a problem of disease.  It is quite true also that there should be an educative campaign, a campaign which will teach the people what exactly they should do to avoid more than to cure the disease, because I think that is what we should aim at.</P>
      <P>When it gets its grip it does not seem to be curable; at least, as far as we laymen know, it has very rarely been cured, and what we should aim at is to prevent it.  There is one point that has not been touched on so far, and that is the new scheme by which the National Health Insurance and the benefits that it will give will come under the control of the Minister for Local Government.  I should like to know if he has any scheme in his mind by which there could be co-ordination &mdash;that is to say, that there could be a supplementary scheme under his Department, together with the benefits supplied by the National Health Insurance and the other schemes that are connected with it.  It is a matter that we have to consider, and also it is worth considering whether there should not be an enforcement of notification of the disease, so that it would not spread so rapidly as it seems to do.  I would suggest very sincerely the consideration of a scheme which would provide for those people who are suffering from tuberculosis and who are drawing benefit under the National Health Insurance&mdash;that there should be some special benefit and some means by which they would get special treatment, and I would submit that for the consideration of the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would not be at all fair if any reflections were cast upon the committees who have been working the Acts in connection with the prevention of tuberculosis. From my knowledge I can state that <Col N="1993" /> some of the committees with which I am acquainted have met regularly and have considered the reports from the medical officers appointed to deal with cases of tuberculosis, and have afforded domiciliary treatment and nourishment where requisite.  They have also sent affected cases for treatment to sanatoriums.  I think these committees have done their duty in that way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDaly" hpid="Mr. DALY Mr. DALY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DALY</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been associated with two societies in the great county of Cork, the largest county in Ireland, and the best.  These societies have for their object the treatment and the management, one of them of the insured persons and the other of the sanatorium at Heatherside.  After the great war, nearly every soldier who came home was affected with consumption, from colds contracted at the front, and from other causes.  They got domiciliary and other treatment between the British Government and the County Insurance Committee, and they were sent to different sanatoria and have had treatment at home.  We were the first in Ireland to build a sanatorium, before any other county.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A DEPUTY A DEPUTY">
      <NameTxt>A DEPUTY</NameTxt>
      <P>Did you want it more?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDaly" hpid="Mr. DALY Mr. DALY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DALY</NameTxt>
      <P>We might have wanted it more.  I think the time is now opportune for me to make a retrospective claim on the Local Government Department, as £13,500 is still due on that sanatorium.  When it was built it was a national sanatorium; it provided relief for every county in Ireland; we refused nobody.  I think some of the officials of the Local Government Department will be able to testify as to that. We were promised, I think a year ago, if we made a scheme for the public notification of disease, that this £13,500 would be recouped to us, and I will ask the Minister for Local Government in good faith to try to give us back that £13,500, and we will make the scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A DEPUTY A DEPUTY">
      <NameTxt>A DEPUTY</NameTxt>
      <P>Another sanatorium.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDaly" hpid="Mr. DALY Mr. DALY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DALY</NameTxt>
      <P>Not a sanatorium.  The sanatorium that I would like to see is the sanatorium that Deputy Hogan has pointed out, that is to prevent the disease by building plenty of labourers' cottages, and if you had enough of them in time, you would not want any <Col N="1994" /> sanatoria, with all their expenses.  I think I would not be doing my duty to that big county of Cork if I did not ask the Minister for Local Government now, as the Estimates are before us, to remember that he owes us £13,500, and that if he wants absolution from that great county he had better pay up. The bargain is that we make a scheme. If we get the £13,500 we will make the scheme.</P>
      <P>There is another matter that I would like to bring under the notice of the Minister.  Throughout the country there are a number of old schoolhouses, obsolete old buildings, and into these cold structures will march tender little children of seven, eight, ten or twelve years, perhaps two or three miles in the morning.  They may be wet, and they have to stand all day looking at one another, shivering in the cold, or shivering before the schoolmaster.  I think that if there was anything to give them consumption these old schools would, more quickly than the trenches gave it to the soldiers.  I am really in earnest when I ask the Minister for Local Government to institute an inquiry and send Health Inspectors around.  That was one of the reasons that I supported the proposal to appoint Health Inspectors.  The sooner you appoint them the better, even better than the abolition of the rural district councils, which you will never abolish.  You cannot go against the will of the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Can they not?  Do not make a mistake about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDaly" hpid="Mr. DALY Mr. DALY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DALY</NameTxt>
      <P>I bet they will not.  At any rate my experience of the Minister for Local Government and his staff is that they are good fellows.  That will tell you that the tax is not on soft soap yet. I would ask him in all sincerity to look after these old schoolhouses.  I believe they are the primary causes of disease. As I pointed out a moment ago, a little boy or a little girl will go two or three miles to these schools and will be, perhaps, without a drink of water all day, without any comforts that a child would have at home, and he cannot go to the schoolmaster as he would to his mother at home.  All these little incidents <Col N="1995" /> pile up, and the unfortunate lungs are affected.  The old schoolhouse was next door to me, and I never caught a cold there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite agree with the Deputies who said that a great deal more could be done by way of lecturing and that kind of thing with a view to preventing the spread of tuberculosis, but there is one thing I think sufficient attention is not being paid to, and that is the question of proper sanitation. The sanitary laws as they apply in urban areas are not sufficiently rigid, and do not give sufficient power to local authorities to remove nuisances which are a distinct menace to public health.  I do hope that if that Commission of Inquiry is set up to go into this whole question of Local Government, due attention will be paid to the lack of proper sanitary laws.  As I pointed out last week, the machinery is too cumbersome.  For instance, in some towns what is a very bad menace to public health cannot be abated for weeks because of the fact that local authorities have not the power to deal with them.  Under a certain Public Health Act, if a sewer is stopped in a person's yard, or if there is a lack of proper sanitary conveniences after an order is served, if the nuisance is not abated, the only power the local authority has is to come in, and do that work itself.  It has to apply to a court in order to recover what it costs to do it.  That requires in most cases a couple of months.  Very serious injury may have been done, and the particular nuisance may have been a very serious menace to the public health, not alone of the inhabitants of that particular house, but of the whole area. I think this whole matter ought to be gone into carefully in all its details, and should occupy the attention of the Commission that is about to be set up to consider this Local Government Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Before I finish, because it is the last item so far as I can see that deals with public health matters&mdash;I do not see anything about infectious or contagious diseases, and tuberculosis is an infectious disease&mdash;I would like to <Col N="1996" /> know if the Minister and his Department have taken any action in connection with the matter of the present disease of sleeping sickness.  This is becoming very prevalent in Ireland. In view of the seriousness of it, and the number of deaths that have taken place in Belfast&mdash;a few in the Saorstát&mdash;and the numerous deaths in England, I would like to know if the Minister and his Public Health Department are taking any steps with a view to drawing the attention of the different local boards to the necessity of counteracting the disease, and if any instructions have been issued.  I would like to know if his medical advisers are doing anything to counteract this disease. It does seem to be a serious matter, and I think the Minister and his Department ought to take it in hands.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I have recognised how foolhardy a thing I was doing in crossing a matter touching the constituency of Deputy MacBride. I did not say what he attributed to me, that the place was infected with tuberculosis, nor did I choose it because it was in any way singular.  I chose it because it was a place I knew, and there were families I knew in it. While making this explanation I want to say that the biggest single evil of such parts of the country is tuberculosis. I want to add, however, this much, that from my personal observations I know that nearly always the scourge can be traced to a house.  I have a case in mind, one of five or six which I can give and one which Deputy MacBride can go and test, where within two years four out of a family of five, one after the other, were stricken, simply because the house was infected, and the fifth fled the island although infected before he fled the island.  The last I heard of him when he returned to Achill was that he was entirely cured.  Had he not gone, he would be where the remainder of his family are.  I only say that now. I repeat what I said a few moments ago, that the greatest benefit that can be given is the benefit of education.  Deputy MacBride says those persons when they are infected <Col N="1997" /> can be treated in the infirmary. I know they can be treated in the infirmary, but I am inclined to think, from having seen some of them going to the infirmary, that they would have been even better to remain in their own homes.  They are being sent to sanatoria like Newcastle, and other places.  What happens when they do go there?  After a few weeks the bed is required for some other case.  There are too many demanding admittance, and so the patient has to be returned home.  I have handled 20 or 30 cases like that within two years, and they have to go back again into the infected houses.  If the matter is to be handled, medical treatment will be required. Many forms of treatment will be required.  Proper schoolhouses and proper nutrition will be required, but I do say that the most important matter of all is not any of those, but propaganda and proper education.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There was one point mooted by my namesake and fellow-Deputy from Clare.  It has reference to making tuberculosis a notifiable disease.  I am afraid at the present time that it would be premature, for I am aware that, in the few areas where the local councils have made it a notifiable disease, the results have been far from satisfactory, and have been disappointing. When the disease is notified after any case is detected, or when the disease is notified to the Public Health Authority, it unfortunately becomes common knowledge, and it very often happens that the family of which the affected person is a member becomes somewhat ostracised.  So there is a natural tendency to conceal the existence of the disease.  I rather think that when the Local Government Bill becomes law, as we are all agreed on the necessity for the existence of a county medical officer of health, he would be the proper authority and the proper person to receive notification of the existence of the disease, and treat it as confidential as coming from a patient to a physician. At the present time, having regard to the fact that it is broadcasted within a very short time, if any person has the disease he and his family become shunned by the neighbours, and it is <Col N="1998" /> not wise, it is not fair, and it is prejudicial to public health to have it a notifiable disease.  I do not agree that we can regard consumption as really due to malnutrition.  As a matter of fact many persons have been stricken with the disease who were in comfortable circumstances of life, and it would be invidious to draw such conclusion. Then again, I look more to education and to dissemination of proper information to detect the disease in the incipient stages and diagnose it, and to have early treatment.  I believe, as well, that we must, to a very large extent, go on preventive rather than curative hygiene, coupled with curative pathology, ere we can eradicate the trouble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBRIDE Mr. MacBRIDE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBRIDE</NameTxt>
      <P>I fear that Deputy Figgis has lost his vocation in this matter as well as in other matters.  He should be the new Minister for Public Health, just as he might have been the Minister for Finance or the Minister for Reconstruction.  Now, in Achill there is a very clever medical practitioner, and he ought to know the number of people who are suffering from tuberculosis in this island of Achill that Deputy Figgis tells us is reeking with tuberculosis.  In addition to that medical officer there are in the island several clergymen, who I am to assume, from their position, ought to be at least educated in this as well as in other matters, and it would be part of their duty to see that these people were properly taken care of.  Then there is a county tuberculosis officer whose duty it is to see about these matters.  I object to the people of Achill or any other part of Mayo being slandered in this way. It is not the Duchess of this or that or the other who is now parading the land.  It is a member of this Dáil and it is quite uncalled for in any Deputy to stand up and traduce not only the people of Mayo but the medical officer and the people in charge of the Achill district, and the medical officer in charge of the county.  We have in this Dáil Deputy Nally, who is practically chairman of the Mayo County Council and has a knowledge of the tuberculosis cases that come out of Achill.  I do not suppose that any of them are sent to England, or that any of them are sent <Col N="1999" /> forward depending on the charity of friends of the Deputies here in this House or in any other House.  I am sure if the Island of Achill, or any other part of Mayo, is reeking with tuberculosis the chairman of the county ought to know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinMNally" hpid="Mr. NALLY Mr. NALLY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NALLY</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputies present hardly realise the fact that nearly all of the 26 counties have got a tuberculosis medical officer, who is a whole-time officer.  All these officers hold dispensaries in the various towns, and any of the patients who come before them are sent to a sanatorium. The patients from Mayo are sent to the sanatorium at Peamount, and I understand that Peamount has not been overcrowded at any time for the past five years.  My experience is that the Local Government Department have been doing all they can to stamp out tuberculosis at its source.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say one word as to my remarks in relation to this matter for fear they might be taken as a reflection on the local tuberculosis officers or nurses.  I would say that the work done by these people in my county, and I am sure in the other counties, has been excellent.  The suggestion that I want to make is that schemes have not been as elaborate as they might be and probably not so well financed by the Ministry of Local Government or given the attention which the importance of the matter deserves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say I was very pleased to listen to the very interesting and informative debate on this question. The only thing I regret was that it did not occur during the Second Reading of my Local Government Bill, where it would have fitted in admirably, because the arguments addressed to this subject here are arguments specially in favour of that Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>And the abolition of rural councils?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with most of the Deputies who have spoken that the chief cause for the high percentage of consumption relatively in this country is the absence of any real understanding of the preventive side of public <Col N="2000" /> health, and also it is due to the fact that the disease is not compulsorily notifiable.  It would be impossible to organise a proper propaganda system in this country until we have Local Government established on a county basis and have an officer in charge of the medical service in each county.  I am surprised that Deputy Hogan did not notice that under that Bill tuberculosis is to be made compulsorily notifiable. In regard to the other matter raised by Deputy Hogan, the re-organisation of National Health Insurance and the co-ordination of it with other medical services are being referred to a committee which is being formed by the Minister for Finance.  That disposes of his other difficulty.  Deputy Corish referred to the outbreak of sleeping sickness.  Every outbreak is being investigated by the medical inspectors and inquiries in the other cases that arise are being made.  The Local Government authorities in some cases have made the disease notifiable. It has been made notifiable in the case of Rathmines and Dublin.  With regard to the general position of tuberculosis, the disease is decreasing.  Of course, it is a very tedious disease and it is a very difficult thing to give exactly the reasons why it is decreasing. I believe it is owing to the curative and preventive system introduced here in 1912 and 1914, but it may to some extent be due to the standard of living.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course that is very important.  The mortality from tuberculosis is decreasing.  The death-rate from the disease in Ireland per thousand of the population varied from 2.9 in 1904 to 2.7 in 1914.  During the great war, from 1915 to 1919, the figure rose to 2.2 and in 1919 it dropped to 1.94. The reduction continued through 1920, when it was at 1.7, and in 1921 it was 1.5.  The figure for the Free State for 1922 was 1.4.  We have not got the returns for last year.  Approved tuberculosis schemes are being administered by councils in twenty counties and two county boroughs, while partial schemes dealing only with insured persons and their dependents are being carried out by Insurance Committees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2001" /> In Mayo and Leitrim the approved schemes have fallen into abeyance. Tuberculosis schemes have not been adopted in Cork, Longford and Roscommon, and in Cork and Limerick County Boroughs.  On the whole, we have reason to be satisfied with the decrease in the disease, but until the disease is made compulsorily notifiable, and until we are in a position to start a proper information bureau on the subject, which can only be done when we have set up our county medical service, we cannot expect to make any more rapid advance than we are making, and that is rather slow.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the attitude of the Ministry of Local Government in connection with the question of the provision of houses for agricultural labourers?  A great deal of confusion prevails in different rural areas in view of the fact that there were many schemes approved immediately prior to or about the time of the European war, and rural district councils had embarked on certain schemes which had entailed a certain amount of expenditure. They had acquired sites, and had gone through the initial stages of the schemes, and spent an amount of money.  I would like to know if any of the money that was alleged to have been earmarked for the different rural areas at that period is available now.</P>
      <P>What is the attitude of the Ministry generally in connection with the provision of houses for rural labourers? I do not suppose it will be suggested by the Minister or anybody here that an agricultural labourer could take advantage of the recent Housing Bill, because even the minimum rent for a three-roomed house would be out of all proportion to what an agricultural labourer could be expected to pay. The Minister ought to give some indication of his attitude on this matter. By no stretch of the imagination could anybody conceive that the Government's latest housing effort could cater for the rural labourer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not quite sure if Deputy Corish is correct in his last statement, because I know the recent Housing Bill is being availed of much <Col N="2002" /> more eagerly in rural districts than in urban areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation, I have no doubt the Bill will be availed of so far as rural areas are concerned. I think, however, that the Minister will find on examination that it is not the rural labourer who is going to build houses.  The Bill is not limited to workers, and he will find that the builders will be small or large farmers who are people better able to afford the money than the labourers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not in a position to go into detail as to the type of person who is building those houses in all parts of the country.  All I know is that we are getting far more demands from the rural districts than from the urban areas.  With regard to the general question of labourers' cottages, we have built 41,000 of these cottages already, and I do not think any other country in Europe has made such provision for rural labourers.  Under the Labourers Acts of 1906, loans were advanced to rural district councils on what are known as land purchase terms, repayable by an annuity covering principal and interest, of £3 5s. for every £100, for a period of 68½ years. The Act of 1906 provided that only 64 per cent. of the interest charges would have to be met out of the local rates, the remainder being met by the Government out of the Labourers Cottage Funds, which, in addition to interest accruing on capital investments of the fund, receive the amount voted under sub-heads (i) and (j).</P>
      <P>The general financial position at present does not permit of the immediate provision of State assistance for rural houses.  The terms on which advances were heretofore made have, in the course of time, become unduly onerous on the State as a result of the depreciation of the land stock by which the necessary monies were raised.  We are not in the position to go ahead with any more of these labourers cottage schemes.  In proportion to other sections of the community, those for whom labourers' cottages were provided have fared very well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The only question that arises here is the 1919 Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2003" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I had not noticed that until now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I had noticed it all the time, but I would like to give Deputies a certain amount of latitude.  The Minister has made a statement on sub-heads (i) and (j).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I debarred from speaking on this matter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid so, unless the Deputy knows more about the 1919 Act than I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I was anxious to express my appreciation of the Minister's tribute to the district councils.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>On this sub-head S, &ldquo;Grant to Municipal Authorities under Government Housing Scheme,&rdquo; I would like to know what particular scheme is referred to.  I understood that the local authorities had nothing to do with the last housing scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the unexpended balance of the President's housing scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing available for the local authorities as that is all earmarked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>The next item, sub-head T, is concerned with the housing scheme we have been dealing with and I would ask, can the Minister give us any information, other than what he has given, as to the extent to which this scheme is being availed of.  He said that much more had been done in the rural areas than in the urban areas.  I think that is a misfortune becauses houses are much more needed in the urban areas. If my information is correct a lot of these housing schemes in the rural areas are undertaken by individuals on the strength of the £60 Government grant, and in the hope that when they have spent the £60, the Government will again come to their rescue and enable them to finish the house.  In one part of the country I have heard that that has happened.  Deputy Corish said it was being done by the small farmers.  My information is that it is done more by small tradesmen, tailors and men of that kind.  They start to build a house on the assumption that the £60 is a first instalment, and they hope that the <Col N="2004" /> next will follow in good time.  If the Minister could give any light on this matter I think it would be helpful and it might disabuse false impressions that have arisen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that those enthusiastic builders will meet with an unpleasant surprise when they come to the Treasury, after they have expended the £60, to look for further recoupment. By the way, they do not get £60 as a full quota at first.  They only get that in full when the building is complete.  They get 50 per cent. when the building is roofed, and the remainder when it is completed.  I receive about 600 or 700 letters per day inquiring about these houses.  A great many of these letters say that the parties writing them intend to start construction work immediately and, from all the indications we have had so far, we believe that the grant will be expended this year or fully availed of this year. At this stage it is impossible to say exactly how many have started building. I would not be in a position to give such definite information till probably a month or so later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Minister is it possible for his department to make any money available for local bodies who wish to acquire land in order to be able to present sites to people who wished to build houses under the new Act?  I know a case where there is military land available. The local authorities are willing to acquire it, and the people are willing to build upon it if the local authority can be financed in the acquisition of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>According to the Bill the local authorities have power to borrow up to twice the amount of the grant supplied by the Government, and the money borrowed in that particular case will not be taken into consideration when the statutory borrowing limit of the local authority is being calculated, so I think that completely covers the case Deputy Heffernan has put forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>Now about this £6,000?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2005" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Which £6,000.  Is it the £6,000 that is not being expended?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Pensions and gratuities awarded.&rdquo;  What I want to know is what it was actually expended upon last year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That question should have been asked last year, I am afraid.</P>
      <P>Question:&mdash;&ldquo;That a sum, not exceeding £628,365, be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1925, to defray the salaries and expenses of the Ministry of Local Government, including grants and other expenses in connection with housing, grants to local authorities, and sundry grants in aid, and the expenses of the office of the inspector of lunatic asylums&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE" RHead="41&mdash;HOSPITALS AND CHARITIES">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - VOTE 41&mdash;HOSPITALS AND CHARITIES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;&ldquo;That a sum not exceeding £4,738 be granted to complete the sum necessary to complete the charge which will come in the course of payment during the year ending on the 31st March, 1925, to pay the charges connected with hospitals and infirmaries and certain miscellaneous, charitable, and other allowances, including sundry grants-in-aid.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to bear some tribute to the good work done by the hospitals receiving this State grant.  I do, however, intend to suggest to the Minister that one of these hospitals might be abolished, that is, the Lock Hospital, which is receiving £2,600 and which is working undoubtedly entirely upon this grant.  I think I could give good and sufficient reasons to show that it might very advantageously be abolished, as its work could be done in one of the other institutions at least in the city where we have 100 beds available.  Not more than 20 or 25 beds are occupied for the treatment of this particular disease, as practically it is out-patient treatment that is required in most cases and only about 5 per cent. perhaps require intern treatment. This institution has a matron and <Col N="2006" /> a secretary and all the paraphernalia of an hospital, whereas the out-patient work could be done equally as well at a general hospital as it is undoubtedly being done well in the Lock Hospital. The only argument I have been able to find against the abolition of this hospital is that if a certain class of patients treated there were to be treated in a general hospital in this particular department it might prevent married women and others who are there for that class of treatment from coming to the hospital, and I would like to suggest to the Minister that it might be worth his while to ask the superintendents of the Dublin hospitals to give him a report on this matter and see if it would not be possible to abolish it. So far as I know, no such institution exists in either Belfast or Cork, and I do not know that such an institution is a credit to the city of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to go further than Deputy Sir J. Craig and to consider this whole question on a general and broader basis.  I do not think anybody will quarrel with the principle of State aid to hospitals, but I do think that the manner in which the State aid is applied is open to reconsideration and possibly, to revision. We are told that these grants which we are now voting were recommended by a committee of the House of Commons in 1854, and by a commission in 1855.  That is a very considerable time ago.  The Ministers were not alive then.  I was not alive and even my father was not alive when these grants were voted.  During that time circumstances have altered, just as Deputy Sir James Craig says the circumstances of one particular hospital have altered. I think that the circumstances of other Dublin hospitals, which do not receive these grants, have also altered.  I am the Governor of an hospital which has an endowment which, probably, in 1854 and in 1855, at the prices then prevailing, was a sufficient and adequate endowment, but which is now struggling with considerable difficulties.  I would suggest that the time is ripe for the appointment of another commission, and that instead of Deputy Sir James Craig bringing his evidence before the Minister that <Col N="2007" /> a small Commission might well be appointed to consider all the circumstances of the hospitals in Dublin.  I say hospitals in Dublin and not Dublin hospitals, because they serve practically the whole of the State&mdash;all the provincial counties&mdash;I do not know what Cork does or Limerick, but the patients in Dublin hospitals do not come from Dublin alone.  They come from practically every county in the Saorstát, and in the case of one hospital they certainly come from the Six Counties as well.  That being so, I think that, without alarming the Minister for Finance in suggesting that this grant of £15,850 should be increased, we might reasonably argue that the distribution might be reviewed and reconsidered, and that a small Commission composed of people versed in the matter might go into the whole case for the Dublin hospitals. Dublin is full of comparatively small hospitals which are worked on the whole uneconomically.  A common purchasing Board for the Dublin hospitals would probably be very advantageous. There is a prestige and pride in one's own hospital that one would not wish to destroy.  I think the hospitals should preserve their separate existence.  Some system of grouping and specialising, so that certain hospitals could be used for certain diseases, might be devised, but the buying of the common necessities, food, stores and so on, that are needed for them might be done more economically if it were done on a large scale. All these points are points that we could not well consider here just as we cannot consider here the merits of one hospital as compared with another, but I think that some consideration by a Commission, or if necessary by a Departmental Committee&mdash;not a very large body&mdash;that would work quickly and report quickly, would be to the advantage not only of the State but of the hospitals themselves and of the sick to whom they minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is rather difficult to understand on what lines these particular grants have been allocated. I agree with Deputy Cooper when he says that it would seem as if re-consideration of the whole of this <Col N="2008" /> grant was a bit overdue.  On the question of the hospitals in Dublin the man in the street thinks that there are too many hospitals for the size of the place. No doubt, there are arguments against that, but on this Vote I think the matter is worthy of consideration.  Deputy Sir James Craig has raised a question about the necessity of maintaining a very small hospital in Townsend Street, Dublin, which is entirely supported by the Government grant.  It does not seem to be run very economically or to be very necessary for the type of work it carries out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>There is just one question I would like to raise in reference to the hospitals.  It is pretty well known that the hospitals are one of the chief means of educating doctors and perhaps this may not be an inopportune moment to be informed in some official way of the position regarding medical practitioners in view of the statements made by the President of the medical council.  Perhaps it may not be out of order to ask that some indication might be made as to the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>What position?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The position of doctors or those trained in these hospitals and going in for examinations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>No, that question cannot be raised now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir JAMES CRAIG Sir JAMES CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir JAMES CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>On the last occasion on which this Vote was before the Dáil I suggested what Deputy Cooper suggested this evening, that the time had come when the matter should be enquired into by a Commission.  I pointed out that there were 28 or 29 hospitals in Dublin, not counting the mental hospitals, the convalescent hospitals and other classes of hospitals, as well as the hospitals in Blackrock or Monkstown.  These would have to come into a scheme, if there was to be a reconsideration of the amount to be distributed. I could not speak very strongly upon the matter because the hospital I am attached to receives no grant from the State, and therefore it might be felt that I was fighting the matter and was jealous of the other hospitals that get the grant.  I do not take up that attitude <Col N="2009" /> at all.  There is another point that I urge very strongly upon the Ministry and it is that the Government should get some control over the establishment of new hospitals.  I pointed out what was a very true fact, that anyone who was dissatisfied with an hospital which refused to appoint him could start an hospital of his own.  He gets a small committee gathered around him and after a time he can appeal, not only for public funds to support this hospital, but for other funds from the State.  There is no controlling influence whatsoever over those hospitals except what is known as the Hospital Sunday Fund Committee.  This Hospital Sunday Fund Committee, of which I am a member, discovered in looking through the figures that one hospital was putting down £180 as the cost per bed, and that a similar hospital situated on exactly similar lines was cosing only £60 per bed.</P>
      <P>Some excuse or reason had to be given for this great discrepancy, but no real reason was ever given.  These two hospitals were each relying on the public for funds to support them, and they were each receiving a Corporation grant.  As I say, I would be very pleased indeed if the Government were able to institute some sort of control. I remember mentioning, when I spoke about the institution of a new system of public health, that the Minister for Health should take under his control the Dublin hospitals, and exercise some sort of supervision over them, but if the Minister appoints a Commission to inquire into this matter and hear the evidence from 25 or 30 hospitals that would want to be brought into the scheme it would be a good thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>This question of the grants is a rather peculiar one.  Some of these grants go beyond the Act of Union, and they have been granted in the most arbitrary and most irregular way.  I am quite willing at the earliest opportunity to go into the question of all these grants, and see that they are put on a sounder and more equitable footing.  These grants have only recently come under our Department. They were formerly under the Chief Secretary, and not under the Local Government Board.  I agree, as a layman, with Deputy Sir James Craig's <Col N="2010" /> point of view, and with Deputy Cooper, but I consider that this matter will have to be considered by a Committee. It is very technical and only a body of medical men, and people with training in hospital work, would be competent to express an opinion on this matter.  It is really an ideal case to be left to that Consultative Council which is to be established under our Bill.  I hope the Deputies will take this as an additional argument in favour of hurrying through with the Bill as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister cannot advocate legislation at this Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>No matter what you say now you are told about the Bill.</P>
      <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE." RHead="- AONACH TAILTEANN">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - AONACH TAILTEANN.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That a sum not exceeding £7,500 be granted to defray the charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1925, to provide for an advance to the Tailteann Council in respect of Aonach Tailteann.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. CAHILL Mr. CAHILL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CAHILL</NameTxt>
      <P>Before this Vote is passed I wish to draw the attention of the responsible parties and the Deputies to the manner in which this handbook has been compiled.  The chief reason, I understand, in publishing this book is to supply information concerning the Games to the many thousand visitors who are expected to visit this country during the month of August.  The compilers have taken on themselves the burden of supplying historical information. Such information is inadequate, inaccurate, and not in harmony with the national sentiments of our people.  We are assured, in a note inserted after the publication of this book, that &ldquo;the General Council of Aonach Tailteann take no responsibility for anything in this handbook except the information directly relating to the competitions.&rdquo; That announcement may satisfy the General Council, but I hold it should not satisfy us.  I will crave your indulgencé whilst I briefly go through portion of this handbook, and I promise <Col N="2011" /> not to read the advertisements if you allow me to proceed uninterrupted. On page 135 we find a list of committees. Many of the names are familiar, and I have not much to say about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy distribute copies of the book?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. CAHILL Mr. CAHILL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CAHILL</NameTxt>
      <P>Every Deputy, I presume, has received a copy.  It came through the post to me.  Turning to page 163, we find under &ldquo;General Information&rdquo; a list of the principal churches.  The first page is devoted to the Episcopalian Church.  Now the vast majority of the people of this country are Catholics, and yet we find the list of Catholic churches relegated to a secondary position, and dismissed with a total of seven.  What impression will this create in the mind of visitors to the Aonach?  Turning to page 167, we find under the heading &ldquo;The Castle of Dublin&rdquo;: &ldquo;The south side of the Upper Court Yard contains the State apartments of the Lord Lieutenant.&rdquo; It contains no such thing.  Very interesting reading!  On page 171 there is this reference to the City Hall: &ldquo;Occupied by the Dublin Corporation for their meetings.&rdquo;  When was it occupied by the Corporation?  I need not ask when it will be occupied by the Corporation. Only the Minister for Local Government can answer that question.  O'Connell Street is dismissed with these words: &ldquo;It was here that some of the fiercest fighting took place.&rdquo;  Not one word about the signatories to the Proclamation of Easter Week, 1916.  The National Gallery of Ireland is thus referred to: &ldquo;One of the best collections in the kingdom.&rdquo;  What kingdom? On page 177 we find the Royal Hospital of Kilmainham referred to as &ldquo;The Chelsea of Ireland.&rdquo;  It is regrettable that we cannot get rid of the slavish habit of naming our health resorts and places of interest after similiar places across the Channel.  I can understand titles appearing in Deputy Hewat's railway, posters, such as &ldquo;Bray, the Brighton of Ireland,&rdquo; and &ldquo;Kilmainham, the Chelsea of Ireland,&rdquo; but one never expected to see them in a handbook on the Tailteann Games.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On page 181, &ldquo;Phoenix Park,&rdquo; the principal places and objects of interest are:&mdash;&ldquo;Viceregal Lodge, the Wellington <Col N="2012" /> Testimonial, the Civic Guard Barracks, Ordnance Survey Works, cricket and polo grounds.&rdquo;  I am certain that the Postmaster-General, who is a patron of the G.A.A., will be surprised to hear that our only national games are cricket and polo.  Of course it leaves the Magazine Fort out of it altogether.  Bad memories are associated with a place of that kind.  In the article on Howth no reference was made to the Abbey of Howth, which the late Dr. Joyce, in his book, &ldquo;The Neighbourhood of Dublin,&rdquo; describes as the most interesting object in the town from an antiquarian point of view.  It is not mentioned that there is a record of King Criffan's return from an expedition abroad, and of his death at his Fort at Dun Criffan, Ben Edar, in the year 9 A.D., and there is no reference to the origin of the name, Ben Edar, and no reference to Aideen's Grave, but we are informed that George IV. landed here on August 4th, 1821.  On page 195 we find: &ldquo;Kingstown&mdash;originally called Dunleary; named Kingstown in 1831 in honour of the visit of George IV., who made this his point of embarkation for England, a small obelisk marking the spot.&rdquo;  So it is still &ldquo;Kingstown.&rdquo;  Now I wonder what authorities were consulted by the Committee responsible for supplying this information to the public?  Did they ever hear of the late Dr. Joyce's work concerning Dublin and its vicinity, or that excellent little handbook of the Rev. Dillon Cosgrave, entitled, &ldquo;The History of North County Dublin,&rdquo; published by the Catholic Truth Society at 1s. 6d. or 2s. per copy?  In conclusion.  I hope the Committee will withdraw this book from circulation.  It is un-Irish, and will cersolutely Seoinin product, and will certainly create false impressions in the minds of many visitors to our country. Finally, I would like to assure the Committee that the Irish people have got beyond the stage when they were content to allow their country to be described as &ldquo;a breakwater of England.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to add my quota to Deputy Cahill's complaint.  I am not sure that the work he has been quoting from has been tabled, but <Col N="2013" /> owing to the kindness of the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs, I have become the possessor of a copy without paying for it.  I looked at the section dealing with sports.  I happen to be, not by merit, the vice-president of a golf club.  I think they wanted a vice-president and trustee whom they could identify and who could not run away very easily.  That golf club four years ago changed its name to the Dun Laoghaire Club.  Looking at the orange-covered pamphlet from which Deputy Cahill has been reading to us, and examining the golf section, I thought at first that my club had been omitted altogether, but presently I found it there camouflaged as &ldquo;Kingstown.&rdquo; I really do not know whether we are invited to vote for the circulation of this misleading and erroneous pamphlet, but if we are I should be very strongly inclined to oppose the vote. I take it that the funds we are asked to vote are funds for the getting up of the Games themselves and not for subsidiary&mdash;I shall not call them attractions, but activities.  We are not giving the money.  We are loaning the money.  I want to ask the Minister for Finance have we a first charge on the gate receipts?  Is the Minister for Finance going to send down Inland Revenue Inspectors to keep an eye on the receipts to see that we get our share? Because there was recently a libel action which suggested that there are very various differences of opinion as to the number of people who go into Croke Park.  Also, has the Minister, as a condition of this advance, made a stipulation that the Entertainments Tax should be paid on the various entertainments? I think before we vote this money we are entitled to answers of these questions.  I ask them in the most friendly spirit, but I think we have the right to know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. BAXTER Mr. BAXTER">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAXTER</NameTxt>
      <P>I happen to be fortunate enough to have a copy of this very interesting booklet that Deputy Cahill has read so many interesting extracts from this evening.  I must say that my knowledge of Dublin and the surroundings is not so well up-to-date as Deputy Cahill's and I, perhaps, was not as critical of what is contained in the booklet.  I do feel that Deputy Cahill is justified in bringing those points to <Col N="2014" /> the notice of those who are responsible for the issuing of the booklet.</P>
      <P>Now, as regards the question of this advance in respect of the Tailteann Games, I must say that I look on the revival of these games as an event in our national life.  They will be to the nation a part of its life in the future. And while some may question the advisability of even granting a loan to assist in the revival of these games, I would be inclined to think that it is a national duty that these games should be assisted and that the committee should be aided in bringing about their revival.  And when we consider that what is being lent is £7,500, anyone who is in any way optimistic as to what the outcome of the games ought to be will agree that they will be worth much more to the nation in very many ways than £7,500; and even if the £7,500 were spent as an investment and not a loan at all it seems to me that it would be £7,500 very well spent.  I do not know, if it were even a question of investing the money and if no return were to be claimed, that it would not be a very good investment.  But no such claim is being made by the Tailteann Council.  The revival of these games was decided on some years ago when the conditions were happier in this country.  I hope the same conditions will prevail when the games are brought off. If this loan would be in any way of assistance to the committee in their efforts for the revival of the games, and would lead to the bringing of a better spirit to the country than has been exhibited for the past eighteen months or two years, this House will agree that even if this money were given as an investment it would be well spent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN (Clare) Mr. HOGAN (Clare)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN (Clare)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid to pronounce the name of the games, it is pronounced in so many different ways. Some people call them the Dailthín Games.  Whether that is because of the patronage of the Postmaster-General I do not know.  There is one thing I do not find in the handbook that is so profuse in many other things.  There is no stipulation as to a knowledge of Irish by people before they are allowed to compete in any of the Games.  I think that if the spirit that animated those who took part in these games long ago is to be preserved, if we are <Col N="2015" /> to perpetuate that spirit, we should insist on a knowledge of Irish from everybody who takes part in the games.  A knowledge of Irish should be insisted upon before they are allowed to enter or take part in the games.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>It would appear to me that any persons who would take the trouble to look over this booklet would have, first of all, discovered that there were so many advertisements in it that they would not be disposed to read the subject-matter referred to by Deputy Cahill.  I do think that if the advertisements are to be paid for on the ordinary scale we shall not have any reason to grumble about the cost of the booklet having to be met out of any advance from the loan given by the Dáil.  In other words, I should imagine that the booklet would have more than paid for itself by the amount of money received for advertising purposes.  I do think that the manner in which the Tailteann Games have been organised is bound to do some good to the country.  It is the first attempt, at any rate, by any committee of any kind to induce visitors to come to this country for the past five or six years.  We must recognise&mdash;and I think everybody will recognise&mdash;that the huge number of tourists who are likely to patronise the games, even though they may come from America, are bound to spend a considerable sum of money and that that money will find its way back to the farmers and to every section of the community that provides food for these visitors while they remain here.  In that way I think the people responsible for the organisation of these games have rendered a service for which they are entitled to some gratitude from the people as a whole. I remember that in the Third Dáil, I think it was, £10,000 was given for the same purpose.  I am informed&mdash;I am subject to correction in this&mdash;that the amount of money granted or advanced by way of loan amounts to, in or about, £20,000.  I should like to know from the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs in what way this money has been expended. Has it been spent upon stands in Croke Park, or the improvement of the grounds?  Has it been spent in the payment of organisers' expenses?  Or has it been spent, for instance, in payment <Col N="2016" /> for the booklet which Deputy Cahill has so ably criticised?</P>
      <P>I, at any rate, expect that the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs will disclaim, as far as he is personally concerned, all responsibility for the subject-matter of this particular booklet. I would like to know how the money already advanced has been spent, whether it has been all spent for organising purposes, and whether all the money already advanced by way of loan, or given as a grant, has been used up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="MINISTER FOR POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS (Mr. Walsh) MINISTER FOR POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS (Mr. Walsh)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER FOR POSTS AND TELEGRAPHS (Mr. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>The total amount of money voted to the Tailteann Games, contrary to the many figures given in the Press and elsewhere, from the first Dáil to the present time, amounts to £6,500.  The present sum of £7,500 is a loan which is a first charge on the takings of the games, and is re-payable, in addition, with five per cent. interest, which I think is the customary percentage for banks to charge.  The General Council had the alternatives of securing this money from one of the banks or getting it in this way.  I may say that there was a strong minority-feeling in favour of the former course.  I myself favoured the latter course and I think that is the reason that this Dáil is discussing the loan of £7,500 to-night. represent every department of sport, that the Council of the Games, which represent every department of sport, music and literature in the country, do not feel themselves under any extraordinary compliment in getting this loan.  I want to emphasise that.  I must further say that I am rather inclined to think that they will very strongly resent some of the remarks made by Deputy Cooper here to-night. The people who constitute the various Councils of the Tailteann Games, not only here, but in many foreign countries, run into close on 2,000, all of them volunteer workers&mdash;men and women who devoted not only their time but their money to resurrecting this historic festival.  I cannot let the occasion pass without expressing the belief that a great many of these will feel very resentful at the imputation contained in one of the remarks of Deputy <Col N="2017" /> Cooper to the effect that the gates will need special watching.  That is the implication one might reasonably take from his remark.  I think the Minister for Finance can feel assured that this loan will be quite secure in the hands of the General Council of the Games.</P>
      <P>It is regrettable that a syllabus containing incorrect information should have been issued.  In our desire to economise we offered the production of this little volume, which is concerned solely with the imparting of information to competitors, to public tender. A firm of repute here paid us what we consider a reasonable sum for the right of producing.  It cost the Tailteann Council nothing; they made a profit on it.  We made it clear to this company that we took responsibility only for that part of the material properly called a syllabus, dealing with the Games themselves, and anything else included in the book was on the responsibility of the producer.  This fact is clearly stated in the fly-leaf attached to the cover, which every Deputy should have seen.  If the outlook of a Catholic firm in Dublin&mdash;I use the word Catholic because it has been used in the introductory remarks of Deputy Cahill&mdash;should be so distorted as to give rise to comment on the part of another particular body, the Council of the Games refuse to take any responsibility. We refused to take responsibility for anything whatever contained in this book, except that part of the book relating to the syllabus.  Let that be clear.  This is not the official guide to the Tailteann Games.  The official guide which is being produced will be carefully scrutinised by the body responsible for its production, and we hope that no material for offence will be included therein.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Apart from the historic side, I think, as Deputy Davin has said, the men and women who are working for the revival of these Games deserve some measure of gratitude from the people.  The total cost to the nation so far, as I have said, has reached £6,500, and, as a matter of fact, it would have cost the nation nothing had not the civil strife of 1922 intervened to cause a postponement of the Games.  Let us see what <Col N="2018" /> we have got for the expenditure.  I would remind the Dáil of the fact that while there has been an agitation for a good part of a generation to bring about more general shipping contact between America and Cobh, we have not observed any particular success until this year.  During the last four or five months the following steamship companies have made arrangements to open up connection between America and the Southern port:&mdash;The Hamburg-American line, beginning operations in July; the Canadian-Pacific, which is beginning directly; the Cunard line, operating from Halifax; the United States line from New York.  Then, of course, there will also be extra-ships of the White Star and Cunard Companies from New York.  Deputies will remember the long-sustained agitation for the calling of American liners at Cobh, but we never saw any results from that agitation.  When we find these different companies operating between America and Cobh we can attribute it to one fact, that we have supplied justification for the calling of these particular lines.  We have provided the passengers. Prior to the opening of the games something like 25,000 people from the United States and Canada will take direct shipment to this country. That is why these lines are calling and are going to call in future.  If we did nothing else but that, apart altogether from the considerable sum of money which foreigners must spend in the country, we have more than justified any expenditure incurred so far. It is of some importance to have foreigners coming here and spending money.  We do not want to turn this country into a Switzerland.  At the same time we feel we are justified because there are many Irish-Americans who, having made money, desire to return to the old land, settle down here, buy property, and help this country. That is actually what is occuring. Irish-Americans have come back to this country and are buying property. Apart altogether from the money spent by the usual excursionists, that is a very desirable development.  I do not suppose anyone wishes to do anything to discourage that.</P>
    <P>There is another feature in the games.  It is no harm.  I think, that <Col N="2019" /> some such organisation as the Tailteann Games should exist in all those countries where the Irish people are pretty numerous, if only for the purpose of giving them some neutral ground on which they can co-operate for the general upliftment of their race.  The games provide neutral ground and an arena outside the contentious scope of politics.  Through that channel we are hoping that our race will be more effective for the general good.  In other words, it will bring harmony amongst the Irish race.  We have not been unsuccessful in that respect.  I would like to remind the Dáil that we have not been unsuccessful in our endeavours to bring about a more brotherly feeling amongst the Irish people, regardless of political or religious differences.  Before the Games materialise we are hopeful that we may be even more successful. That, I think, is a development worthy of commendation.  There are too many forces in this country moving in an opposite direction; too many forces out to cultivate the spirit of hatred and distrust.  It is well, at any rate, that some big force should be brought to play which will work in the other direction.</P>
    <P>I can again assure the Minister for Finance if it is necessary, that this loan will be repaid.  We anticipate that the takings of the games will be pretty considerable so that we do not doubt our ability to justify our promise that this money will be repaid.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BryanRiccoCooper" hpid="Major COOPER Major COOPER">
      <NameTxt>Major COOPER</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of personal explanation, I had no intention of offending the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs.  I did not wish to make any imputation at all.  If I wished to be offensive I could express my thoughts very much more fully.  The only point I wish to make was that, while dealing with voluntary funds you might place the utmost confidence in voluntary workers.  I would not ask the voluntary workers who are to decorate the streets of the city for the Tailteann Games to produce vouchers in return for my subscription.  But when you are dealing with public funds you must adopt a more rigid standard and you must realize that your stewards are the public as a whole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I wished <Col N="2020" /> to have cleared up is this question of the total amount voted for the Tailteann Games.  It is quite clear the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs is under a misapprehension.  In 1922-23, £10,000 was voted as a grant-in-aid, in respect of the improvement of Croke Park in connection with the Tailteann Games.  There was voted as a grant-in-aid from Dáil Eireann funds in 1922 a sum of £6,500, which the Minister has referred to.  There was also a loan made to the Gaelic Athletic Association, which sum is repayable and forms part of the assets vested in the Minister for Finance.  Whatever we may say about the last loan of £7,700 voted from Dáil Eireann in 1922, presumably that will be in the same position as this £7,500 will be.  The vote of £10,000 was distinctly for the purpose of the Tailteann Games.  It may be that the Minister has in mind a different association, or that a new association is running the Tailteann Games project now.  I do not know.  The Dáil did vote £10,000 for the improvement of Croke Park in connection with the Tailteann Games, and we should not be under a wrong impression as to the actual sums voted out of the public funds for this purpose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>The £10,000 was voted for the purpose of making Croke Park fit for the Tailteann Games and was paid direct to the owners of Croke Park, the G.A.A.  The Tailteann Council had no control over that.  The £7,700 given to the Gaelic Athletic Association is secured by a deed of mortgage of some sort on Croke Park.  This £7,500 will not, of course, be secured in that legal way.  We have to depend upon the honour of the very respectable committee that have control of the Tailteann Games.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="Mr. WALSH Mr. WALSH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WALSH</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say, in connection with Deputy Cooper's remarks, that our accounts have been duly audited by the Comptroller and Auditor-General.  That point should be understood.</P>
      <P>Question put, and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Progress ordered to be reported.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE." RHead="- DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>Progress reported.  Committee to sit again on Wednesday.</P>
    <P>Dáil adjourned at 10.30 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>