<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="7" Month="Mar" Year="1924" Vol="6" No="24" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 7 Márta 1924" DateEnglish="Friday, 7 March 1924" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1807">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1807" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar a 12 a clog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - KINSALE PUBLIC BODIES DEBT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - KINSALE PUBLIC BODIES DEBT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEÁN PRIOMHDHAIL SEÁN PRIOMHDHAIL">
      <NameTxt>SEÁN PRIOMHDHAIL</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether he has had an application from the Kinsale Harbour Commissioners and Urban Council for a remission of the debt of £1,176 10s. 5d., the balance due on loan for the construction of Kinsale Pier, on the ground that the cost of construction exceeded by several thousand pounds the original amount estimated by the Board of Works, due chiefly to releasing the original contractor and his sureties from the obligations under their joint bond; and whether he is aware that the town ratepayers are called upon to pay an annual rate of one shilling and twopence in the pound in liquidation of the debt on this pier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. E. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. E. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>The application referred to has been received, but I see no sufficient reason why the outstanding balance of the loan to the Kinsale Harbour Commissioners should be remitted. I am aware, however, that the financial position of the Harbour Commissioners makes it difficult for them to fulfil their obligations at present, and in order to afford some relief in respect of the loan I am prepared to accept payment by half-yearly instalments of, say, £75.  This would reduce the instalments by more than one half, and would extend the period of repayment by approximately nine years.  I am aware that the instalments for the past few years have been paid by the Urban Council, owing to the inability of the Harbour Commissioners to meet them, but my suggestion <Col N="1808" /> above will afford a considerable measure of relief.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnPrior" hpid="Mr. PRIOR Mr. PRIOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. PRIOR</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that this is due to the fact that the old Local Government Board released the contractor from his bond and increased the estimate by £4,000?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that the facts are as stated, but it seems that a number of circumstances contributed to increasing the cost of the original estimate.  I will look into the matter further.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- TRADESMEN'S UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - TRADESMEN'S UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. JOHN GOOD Mr. JOHN GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHN GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state the number of bricklayers, plasterers, and carpenters (giving separate figures for each trade) who are in receipt of unemployment benefit in (a) the City and County of Dublin, (b) in the Free State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Industry and Commerce) Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Industry and Commerce)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Industry and Commerce)</NameTxt>
      <P>The number of carpenters, bricklayers and plasterers who had claims to unemployed benefit current on the 25th of last month, the latest date on which figures are immediately available, in</P>
      <P>(a)  The City and County of Dublin.</P>
      <P>(b)  An Saorstát,</P>
      <P>are:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="20*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="4" colnum="4" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Carpenters</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bricklayers</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Plasterers</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>An Saorstát</entry>
            <entry>659</entry>
            <entry>210</entry>
            <entry>78</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>City of Dublin</entry>
            <entry>244</entry>
            <entry>142</entry>
            <entry>35</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>County of Dublin</entry>
            <entry>8</entry>
            <entry>16</entry>
            <entry>2</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS. -" RHead="UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT: CO. TIPPERARY CASES">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT: CO. TIPPERARY CASES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA">
      <NameTxt>DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state why unemployment benefit has not been paid to the following:&mdash;James Toohey, Connolly Street, Nenagh; Michael Bourke, William Street, Nenagh; Thomas Reddin, William Street, Nenagh; Laurence Whelan, Abbey Street, Nenagh; Edward Hickey, Burke Street, Fethard; and William Dwyer, Carney, Borrisokane, Co. Tipperary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1809" />
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Industry and Commerce) Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Industry and Commerce)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Industry and Commerce)</NameTxt>
      <P>The claim of James Toohey, Connolly Street, Nenagh, made on the 15th December last, was disallowed because the workman had no contributions to his credit in the Unemployment Fund.  The workman was notified of the disallowance in due course.</P>
      <P>The claim of Michael Burke, William Street, Nenagh, made on the 5th January, 1924, was disallowed because no contribution was paid for him in the 1922-23 Insurance Year, and he was, therefore, disqualified for benefit under Sub-section 4 of Section 8 of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920.  The applicant was duly notified of the disallowance.</P>
      <P>In the case of Thomas Reddin, William Street, Nenagh, the applicant was not entitled to benefit on the contributions to his credit, and at the time he made his claim he had not made application for contributions in respect of his Army service.  Delay necessarily occurred in the action which had to be taken to bring the Army contributions to his credit, and his claim was authorised for payment on the 28th February.</P>
      <P>Laurence Whelan, of Abbey Street, Nenagh, is disqualified for the receipt of benefit by Sub-section 4 of Section 8 of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920.  He is not entitled to the contributions payable under Section 7 of the Act of 1923 in respect of his military service, because less than 10 contributions had been paid for him prior to the date of his enlistment.  The applicant was duly informed of the decision on his claim.</P>
      <P>Edward Hickey, of Burke Street, Fothard, was disqualified for the recept of Unemployment Insurance Benefit under Sub-section 4 of Section 8 of the Unemployment Insurance Act, 1920.  It subsequently transpired that he was entlitled to contributions under Section 7 of the Act of 1923, in respect of his military service, and action was accordingly taken to bring such contributions to his credit.  His claim was authorised on the 18th February, and forwarded to the local office of the Ministry at Clonmel, for payment of benefit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>William Dwyer, of Carney, Borrisokane, <Col N="1810" /> was paid benefit for 45 days in the first Benefit Year, which ended on the 17th October last.  On the further claim which he lodged in the Second Benefit Year on the 18th October, he has been paid benefit for seven days, and has thus exhausted all the contributions to his credit in the Unemployment Fund.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- CO. CLARE OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - CO. CLARE OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he will state why payment of the old age pension has ceased in the case of Mr. Lynch, Querrin, Lisdeen, Co. Clare, having regard to the fact that he has received it since 1909 at full rate, and that the cash value of the perquisites received from his son is low.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Local Government) Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Local Government)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Local Government)</NameTxt>
      <P>Payment of pension ceased in this case, as it was estimated that the value of the claimant's maintenance on his son's farm exceeded £49 17s. 6d. per year, which debars him from the receipt of a pension. The claimant is maintained on the farm assigned by him to his son at marriage in 1909.</P>
      <P>The holding is 42 acres in extent, and the land is described as of good quality&mdash;valuation, £16 13s.; rent or annuity, £12 Os. 6d.  It has seven milch cows, seven calves, a horse and a jennet, whilst 3¾ acres are under tillage. There is also free turbary, and the usual pigs and fowl are kept.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- RECONSTRUCTION WORK IN CO. CORK">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - RECONSTRUCTION WORK IN CO. CORK.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="TADHG O MURCHADHA TADHG O MURCHADHA">
      <NameTxt>TADHG O MURCHADHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether he has received a resolution from the Cork County Council appealing for a grant for reconstruction work in Castletown Bere and Allihies districts, Co. Cork, and whether he is aware that the roads from Allihies Mines and Castletown Bere are in a very bad and dangerous condition and interfere seriously with the development and output of the mines, and whether, in view of the fact that the Castletown Bere portion of the Dáil distress grant was not <Col N="1811" /> spent and reverted to the Ministry of Finance, he will consider the case of Castletown Bere and Allihies for a special grant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Local Government) Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Local Government)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE (replying for Minister for Local Government)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received representations and have had this matter under consideration.  The resolution referred to does not appear to have been brought to my notice, and the Cork County Council are being addressed concerning it.  On learning the proposals of the Council the representations of the Deputy will receive further attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS. - TELEPHONE" RHead="SERVICE: MILLSTREET (CO. CORK) APPLICATIONS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - TELEPHONE SERVICE: MILLSTREET (CO. CORK) APPLICATIONS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="TOMAS DE NOGLA TOMAS DE NOGLA">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS DE NOGLA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Postmaster-General if he has considered the application of residents of the town and district of Millstreet, Co. Cork, for telephone installations, and if he intends to meet the wishes of these people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="POSTMASTER-GENERAL (Mr. J.J. Walsh) POSTMASTER-GENERAL (Mr. J.J. Walsh)">
      <NameTxt>POSTMASTER-GENERAL (Mr. J.J. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>In response to an application for a telephone service from a resident of the town of Millstreet a canvass for telephone subscribers was recently undertaken, but the amount of support forthcoming was so small as not to warrant the heavy expense which would be incurred in extending the system to Millstreet and opening an Exchange at that place.</P>
      <P>I hope, however, that the modified charges which have now been authorised by the Ministry of Finance may be instrumental in securing the necessary support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="Mr. NAGLE Mr. NAGLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NAGLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Postmaster-General inform me how many subscribers would be needed to warrant the installation of the telephones?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="Mr. WALSH Mr. WALSH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WALSH</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the new arrangement I should say the number for Millstreet would be about twenty.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS." RHead="- OWNERS' APPLICATIONS FOR RETURN OF GUNS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - OWNERS' APPLICATIONS FOR RETURN OF GUNS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA">
      <NameTxt>DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he will state whether he proposes to return shot guns taken up by members <Col N="1812" /> of the Royal Irish Constabulary, and similar guns commandeered by the I.R.A. prior to the truce, on application from the owners who furnish him with copies of receipts for guns so taken, and, if so, whether he will state the reason why such guns have not been returned to the following owners, who applied to the Quartermaster-General or Chief Ordnance Officer, giving necessary vouchers as to such guns having been collected, viz., James Maher, Monsea, Nenagh, date taken by R.I.C., as shown by receipt, 31st August, 1920; Vincent Power, Summerhill, Nenagh, 1 gun taken by I.R.A., 14th August, 1920, 1 gun taken by R.I.C., 2nd September, 1920; Thomas Mackey, Dublin Road, Nenagh, 2 guns surrendered by him to I.R.A. on 14th August, 1920; John Delaney, Ballylisheen, Killeen, Nenagh, 1 gun surrendered to R.I.C., 9th September, 1920; Philip Gleeson, Clonolea, Toomevara, Nenagh, 1 gun taken up by R.I.C., Toomevara.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>Guns taken up by the late R.I.C., and those commandeered by the I.R.A., so far as they can be traced, are being returned to owners licensed to hold them.  In the cases of the persons mentioned, efforts have been made to find their guns, but up to the present without success.  These efforts are, however, being continued, and the results will be communicated as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. MORRISSEY Mr. MORRISSEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MORRISSEY</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say if it is the intention of the Government to compensate people from whom guns were taken, and which cannot now be traced or found?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like the Deputy to put down a question with regard to that because there are different classes of &ldquo;takings.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say that in any cases where it can be proved that the guns were taken by officers or members of the Republican Army on the authority of that body, there will be compensation in such cases where guns cannot now be found and returned to the owners?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the question Deputy Morrissey will put down will cover that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL ANSWERS. - PURCHASE" RHead="OF MILITARY STORES FROM BRITISH AUTHORITIES">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - PURCHASE OF MILITARY STORES FROM BRITISH AUTHORITIES.</Title>
    <Col N="1813" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that previous to the evacuation of the British Army from Portlaoighise Barracks, Leix, Messrs. Gaze and Jessop, auctioneers, purchased a considerable quantity of stores and other property, for which they paid the British Army authorities; whether it is correct to state that all such property was taken over by officers of the National Army on condition that Messrs.  Gaze and Jessop would be fully compensated for same; whether he has received repeated claims for £1,045 3s. Od. covering the value of such commandeered property, and if he can now state definitely when he will be in a position to pay the amount due in this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Messrs.  Gaze and Jessop purchased a quantity of stores from the British Authorities for a total sum of £600.  It appears that only a small portion of these stores were taken over by the Army.  The amount of the claim made by the firm has, however, far in excess of the sum paid for the whole of the stores.  Moreover, the firm cannot produce a receipt for the articles alleged to have been handed over to the Army.  Correspondence is in progress with the firm in the matter, and it is hoped to settle the case at an early date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it correct to state that an agreement has been arrived at on behalf of the Army Authorities and Messrs. Gaze and Jessop for compensation to be paid on a basis of £776 7s. Od.; and, if so, will he see, if such agreement has been arrived at, that such amount should be paid at an early date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that such agreement has been made, but I will have inquiries made.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - MOTOR COLLISION IN LEIX">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - MOTOR COLLISION IN LEIX.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="IIAM O DAIMHIN IIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>IIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received a report from the Military Authorities, Templemore, in connection with a collision which took place at Cappalinnan, Rathdowney, <Col N="1814" /> Leix, between a military lorry and an armoured car proceeding from Templemore to Rathdowney, on January 11th, 1923, and two cars belonging to Mrs. Bridget Ringwood and Mr. Robert Barton, in which the cars owned by the latter were damaged beyond repair, and a horse seriously injured (since died); whether the military lorry and armoured car were travelling at a speed of 20 miles per hour without lights, and whether he has received several applications for compensation from Mrs. Ringwood for £15, and from Mr. Barton for £17, and if he can now state the decision of the Ministry in connection with this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received a report in which it is stated that the persons mentioned were driving in one car, and leading the horse attached to the second car, which at the time of the accident, was on the centre of the road, both cars being without lights. The armoured car, in trying to pass the second car, struck it with its mudguard. The horse became frightened, jumped into a ditch, and as a result both cars were somewhat damaged.  In all the circumstances, I am not prepared to approve of any payment being made by way of compensation.  In any case no legal liability lies against the military authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that an affidavit has been made by the parties to whom this damage has been done, which disputes the statement made by him in answer to the question, and would he cause another Inquiry to be made in view of the charges made in this case?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of the facts stated by the Deputy, but I will take note of them and have the matter gone into.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - CO. CORK PRISONERS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - CO. CORK PRISONERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="TADHG O MURCHADHA TADHG O MURCHADHA">
      <NameTxt>TADHG O MURCHADHA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is in a position to order the release of William O'Brien, Derrigna, Ballineen, Co. Cork, interned in Harepark Camp; Joseph Turner, Chapel Hill, Macroom, who is presently confined to hospital, and Seán Driscoll, of Ballydehob, Co. Cork, also <Col N="1815" /> interned in Harepark Camp, and, further, whether he will order the release of John Doyle, Kilnore, Bandon, Co. Cork.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to continue the detention of William O'Brien and John Doyle.  The case of Joseph Turner is under consideration. Seán O'Driscoll has been sentenced by a Military Tribunal to three years' penal servitude.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="ORAL ANSWERS. - A SPORTING GUN">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - A SPORTING GUN.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. A. BYRNE (for Major Bryan Cooper) Mr. A. BYRNE (for Major Bryan Cooper)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. BYRNE (for Major Bryan Cooper)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether several requests have been received from Captain E. G. Woods, of Milverton Hall, Skerries, for the return of a sporting gun deposited with the British Military Authorities at Island Bridge Barracks; whether there is any difficulty in identifying the gun, and whether Captain Woods will be allowed to inspect the guns at Island Bridge to assist in identification.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Captain Woods has requested the return of a gun made by Holland and Holland.  It has not yet been possible to trace such a gun having been registered in Captain Woods name.  However, further inquiries are being made, and an early communication will be made in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS. - DUNDALK SHOOTING">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   ORAL ANSWERS. - DUNDALK SHOOTING.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is prepared to grant compensation or ex gratia payment of any kind to Mr. Neil J. Treanor, who was shot and permanently injured on September 22nd, 1922, in Dundalk, by Thomas Carroll, an Intelligence Officer in the National Army; if he will say what the finding of the Military Inquiry into the incident, which was held on the 3rd January, 1923; or if he can in any way assist Mr. Treanor to recover the damages of £1,500 awarded against Carroll by a Dublin Sheriff's Jury on September 4th, 1923.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The question of compensating Mr. Treanor has been sympathetically considered, but I regret <Col N="1816" /> that it is not practicable to make any payment to him out of public funds.</P>
      <P>The Court of Inquiry held to investigate the incident, found that the bullet which struck Mr. Treanor was accidentally discharged by Lieutenant Carroll, and that Lieutenant Carroll was guilty of gross negligence in carrying his revolver cocked in his pocket.</P>
      <P>Lieutenant Carroll's military service was terminated on the 15th October last.  In the circumstances, it is not feasible to assist Mr. Treanor to recover damages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of that answer, I would like to ask the Minister if he has seen the report of the trial and the findings by a Dublin Jury, and if so, are they not in contradiction to the statements he has now made to the effect that the bullet was accidentally discharged?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I have seen the findings of the Dublin Jury and the report of the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it to be taken that an officer going into a public house is by that fact deemed to be not on duty?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Not necessarily by that fact.  He was not on duty at the time he went into the public house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that Carroll was an Intelligence Officer, and by reason of that fact can be on duty anywhere?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it a fact that he is not on duty when acting illegally, and that he is on duty when acting legally?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Not necessarily.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="QUESTION ON THE" RHead="ADJOURNMENT">
    <Title>QUESTION ON THE ADJOURNMENT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to give notice that, on the motion for the adjournment, I will raise the question of the deprivation of Mr. Lynch, Querrin, Lisdeen; Co. Clare, of the old age pension, after fifteen years' enjoyment of it, as raised in question 4 put to the Minister for Local Government to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="HOUSING (BUILDING FACILITIES)" RHead="BILL, 1924&mdash;RECOMMITTED">
    <Title>HOUSING (BUILDING FACILITIES) BILL, 1924&mdash;RECOMMITTED.</Title>
    <Col N="1823" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>New amendments are tabled in connection with this Bill, and it seems that it will be necessary to recommit the Bill for the consideration of these amendments.</P>
      <P>Ordered that the amendments be considered in Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In Section 8 (1), page 5, line 17, to add at the end of the sub-section the following words&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;and may at any time and from time to time by order continue, vary or revoke all or any prices or amounts prescribed by him or on appeal from him under this Section.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The effect of the amendment is that if an enquiry has been held and the price of material has been fixed by the Minister or by the Appeal Tribunal, on appeal from him, the Minister can, at any time, increase or diminish the price so fixed as circumstances of the trade require. An order of the Minister altering the price under the amendment can be appealed against under sub-Section (2) of the Section, so that if the Minister is given power to vary the price fixed by the Appeal Tribunal there is still an appeal from his decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid this proposal is but a further example of what several people have objected to recently under the heading of &ldquo;hasty legislation.&rdquo; It would appear now from this proposal that this Bill has not had the consideration that its importance deserved, and it has been shown that this particular clause to which considerable exception was taken in Committee was of a much more far-reaching character than the farmers of the Bill had anticipated. I think one of the lessons to be learned from the time that has been spent on this Bill is that before these Bills come before the Dáil they ought to receive more consideration than certainly this Bill, and some other Bills that we have had before us, received. Deputy Cooper complained very justly a little while ago that the Bill then under consideration was the worst, from the point of view of draftsmanship that he, in his somewhat lengthy <Col N="1824" /> experience of Parliamentary work, had come in contact with.  My experience of Parliamentary work is exceedingly brief, but I am quite satisfied that this Bill is one of the worst examples of draftsmanship that certainly has come before this House.  I think the amendment that is now put forward makes that point particularly clear.  As an old writer puts it, &ldquo;He goes furthest who knows not whither he goest.&rdquo;  This proposal, I am afraid, will not add very much to making this Bill of the workable character that some of us would desire.</P>
      <P>If I were to attempt to put forward the proposition that a Circuit Judge could review, alter, or revoke a decision that had been made by the Court of Appeal, I am quite sure that the Attorney-General and those associated with him would rise in righteous anger and would tell me that that was rank heresy, that the principle I attempted to set aside thereby was an old and recognised principle in law, possibly established as far back as Magna Charta, and that it would be exceedingly unfair and unwise to attempt to alter that well-known principle and the practice that had been established by it.  Yet that, in substance, is exactly what this amendment proposes.  May I point out exactly the position as we find it under this Bill, so that the members of the House may clearly understand this amendment and its effect.  Under Clause 8 the Minister takes power to fix the prices of building materials.  If the aggrieved party finds fault with that decision of the Minister he has the right under Clause 10 to have his case considered by a Court of Appeal Clause 10 reads as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(1)  Whenever a right of appeal from an order of the Minister is given by this Act, the appeal shall, subject to prescribed rules of procedure, be made to a standing tribunal of appeal consisting of three persons to be appointed by the President of the Executive Council, and such tribunal shall have power to confirm or to annul the order appealed against, or to make such other order in the matter as the Minister could have made under this Act, and the decision of the tribunal of appeal in the <Col N="1825" /> matter shall be final and not subject to appeal or to review by any court.</P>
    <P>(2)  Where any appeal to which this section applies is not finally determined within fourteen days after the date on which notice of appeal was given, the operation of the order appealed against shall be suspended as from the expiration of the said fourteen days until the appeal has been finally determined.</P>
    <P>It was pointed out that that clause was absolutely unworkable.  As every member in this House knows, building commodities, like many other commodities, are subject to fluctuation in price from time to time.  As conditions alter the prices vary.  It was pointed out that under this decision of this Court of Appeal there was no power to alter the price of a commodity once that price had been fixed by that Court of Appeal, so that if the price of that commodity happened to fall that particular person or merchant was precluded from altering his price.  His price was fixed by the Court of Appeal. There was no power to alter it; if the price happened to rise he had no power to alter it.  So that really what this proposal meant in substance was that it put that particular firm or that particular individual out of business, because it precluded them from dealing in that commodity.  When that was pointed out, the President undertook to consider the matter, and the result of the consideration is this proposal. Now, what is the proposal?</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That the Minister may at any time and from time to time by Order continue, vary, or revoke all or any prices or amounts prescribed by him or on appeal from him under this Section.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In other words, notwithstanding the fact that the Court of Appeal has power to fix, power to reconsider, and, after reconsidering, to alter, the Minister's proposal and to fix a certain rate, the Minister can, if this clause is passed, on the following day revoke the decision of the Court of Appeal and reinstate his own decision. Now, gentlemen, I ask you what is he use of such a clause as that? You fix under the Bill a Court of Appeal <Col N="1826" /> from the decision of the Minister. The following day the Minister can revoke the decision of the Court of Appeal, and has power under this proposal to reinstate his own decision. Gentlemen, such a proposal is childish, absolutely childish.  What is the use of putting in a clause establishing a Court of Appeal, and then putting in a sub-clause doing away with the effect of the Court of Appeal.  Would not it be better to do away with the Court of Appeal altogether and leave the matter in the Minister's hands, as this proposal now leaves it?  So I say again, gentlemen, as I said before, legislation of this kind is exceedingly unwise, and whoever framed this Bill originally ought to be put in a glass case and kept there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>In answer to Deputy Good, I have got to say that the parallel between this Court of Appeal from a decision of the Minister and the Minister's subsequent reviewing of the decision of the Court of Appeal, with a matter which comes before a Court and is decided by a Court, is not a fair parallel.  It was never intended to be on parallel lines.  In order to explain the matter, let us take any item pleasing to Deputies.  Let us take, for example, bricks.  Suppose bricks cost £1 to-day and the Minister says the price should be 19s. 6d.  That case comes before this Appeal Board and the Appeal Board, having heard the arguments, decides that the price should be restored to £1.  In a week's time a huge quantity of bricks comes on to the market and the persons engaged in that particular trade, being satisfied that £1 is too dear, it is open to the Minister, in the special circumstances of the case, to review the decision, having regard to the altered conditions.  The altered circumstances might be many.  They might be a reduction in wages, they might be a reduction in transit, they might be a reduction in the cost of materials necessary in the manufacture of bricks; a different set of circumstances would therefore exist a week, a fortnight, three weeks or a month after the decision of the Court of Appeal.  It is under these conditions that the Minister would so review and so alter the price that had been fixed by the Court of Appeal.  Even then, if the <Col N="1827" /> brick manufacturers or others thought the Minister had not fixed a fair price, they could again come before the Court of Appeal and have the case reviewed, and if the Minister's decision was not correct another price could be fixed.</P>
      <P>I do not think there is a likelihood of continual change of prices made by the Minister, but this particular amendment is proposed in order to meet an infirmity in the Bill which Deputy Good had discovered.  The real objection of Deputy Good is not to this amendment, but to the principle that is involved, and which is met and covered by this amendment.  On more than one occasion I have stated that we are not concerned with the particular vested interests of any persons in this industry &mdash;neither with labour as such, nor with the employing builders as such, nor with the persons who sell building materials.  We are concerned with seeing one thing which is fairly obvious to everybody&mdash;that between those three parties there is a very considerable blister put on the backs of the people who are supporting this State, and whose money is necessary in order to keep each one of those in their present vested position.  We are not concerned with dealing with&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Prima facie</i> evidence is three instead of with one?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as that is concerned, we are taking this opportunity of dealing with one, and if Deputy Good will take the opportunity of advising us as to how we should deal with the other two, we are open to receive his suggestions.  The Bill has been before us a long time, and, from the angle of Deputy Good, nothing has come but the criticism that this is an attack on one section.  It is not.  I have appealed to the other two sections.  I have implored them to see this matter from the point of view of the citizen, and not of the person involved in any of the three services connected with the question of housing.  It may be possible&mdash;I think it is possible&mdash;that the employers in certain cases will make an effort to make this appeal a success.  I believe and hope that the same consideration will be given by employees.  But is it <Col N="1828" /> the case that Deputy Good wishes that I should say to the employers: &ldquo;Unless you take only 4 per cent. profit on your particular line&rdquo; and say to Labour, &ldquo;Unless you will agree either to reduce your wages or increase your output&rdquo;&mdash;we are not going to allow any building whatever to go on in the country.  I have explained, more than once, that it is not by finding fault or criticising whatever proposals are put up, but by putting up better proposals, that the question will be advanced.  Is it the case that persons engaged in the sale of building materials have not made very considerable profits out of such sales?  If it be denied, those people will not be hampered and their business will not be interfered with by this proposal.  It is in cases where there is or where there are&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Prima facie evidence is not necessary under this Bill.  If it were, it would put a different complexion upon it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Supposing it be not necessary, any particular limitation that is put on profits in this Bill is a necessary limitation in the circumstances. If the case can be put that the present profits are such that no limitation of them should be imposed by either the Minister or an Appeal Board, I am satisfied that no such limitation will be imposed.  We are endeavouring to deal with profiteering here in one particular service, and only one.  I have made some inquiries recently about the labour end of housing.  Those inquiries have not disclosed the fact that there is such a shortage of output as I had been led to believe.  I do not mean to say that in every case where building has gone on there has been a generous output.  There has not.  There have been individual cases in which the output has not, by any means, been a credit to Labout, as such.  I do not believe that the Deputies opposite would subscribe to any such limitations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>You are going very far away from this amendment now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not go so far only that Deputy Good interjected&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1829" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>You are doing splendidly, Mr. President.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Good thinks that when we are only dealing with one of the three parties to this measure it is unfair.  I would say it is unfair to the draftsman to blame him for the method in which he gave expression to my interpretation of what was required.  I certainly gave him a very difficult task to interpret.  He has interpreted it to my satisfaction.  The language may, perhaps, lack some of the elegancies that a Bill might have, but if it achieves its purpose I am satisfied with it.  I will put up with any infirmities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the objection is that this amendment does not achieve Deputy Good's purpose and is unnecessary.  I would suggest that Deputy Duggan would not press this amendment.  Nobody wants it.  It is unnecessary, and may cause confusion. I do think Deputy Good has made a hit&mdash;a very palpable hit.  The Section would read: &ldquo;The Minister may at any time, if he thinks fit, order a local inquiry into the cost of building materials.  The Minister may, by Order, prescribe the maximum amount of the wholesale or retail price which may be charged for such materials.&rdquo;  Then the amendment reads: &ldquo;And may at any time, and from time to time, by Order, continue, vary, or revoke all or any prices or amounts prescribed by him or on appeal from him under this Section.&rdquo; The game of shuttlecock and battledore Deputy Good visages should not be possible.  But it is possible, and it will be possible, if this amendment is carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister already has power to make a variation of the cost, and may prescribe the maximum amount at any time before he makes the first order under the inquiry, or after he makes the first order.  He may at any time prescribe the maximum amount to be charged once the inquiry may be held. And that order may be appealed against.  But under the amendment, as Deputy Good rightly points out, after having had the appeal decided against him, he may, under the powers proposed to be given. vary the order of <Col N="1830" /> the Appeal Court and make a new maximum, irrespective of what the Appeal Court declared should be the maximum.  That is bad, I think, and it is unnecessary.  And Deputy Good, who asked for an amendment of this kind, is not satisfied with the amendment. It does not achieve his purpose. Nobody else wants it.  It is not necessary for the Minister's purpose.  I suggest that Deputy Duggan should withdraw the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not satisfied that the see-saw methods which appear to be prevalent in this amendment will serve the ultimate object that the Minister has in view.  I do not think that anybody will deny that there is a ring in existence.  Deputy Hewat stated on the Second Reading of the Bill that there was no evidence of any ring amongst the providers of building materials, and that there was no reason for control of prices.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I said there was a very definite ring amongst labour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>The unfortunate thing at the moment is that there is control of prices.  The ring has control of prices in their own particular interests, and again I congratulate the Government upon bringing in this clause in their Bill, even though they did it from within the precincts of a glass house. As I said, it is rather unfortunate that this amendment appears at this stage, because I think the amendment that Deputy Good would like would be something that the Government would bring forward stultifying the whole clause.  I appeal to the Government to stand by that clause, because it has a wholesome controlling influence on people who have formed a ring for the control of prices in their own interests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>During the time this Bill has been under consideration, it has been stated again and again from the Labour Benches that there was profiteering in building material.  I can only say now, as I said before, that I have no knowledge of this profiteering. I challenged those who make those statements&mdash;and they have had many opportunities right through the period this Bill has been under consideration&mdash;to <Col N="1831" /> put forward evidence of profiteering.  We have arrived at a state when no such evidence has been produced.  In that case I think it is unfair, at this stage, in view of that challenge, to adhere to the statement without bringing forward any proof.</P>
      <P>The President has pointed out, and pointed out very properly, that there are three different parties concerned in this matter of the cost of building materials.  He has only dealt in this Bill with one of them.  I hold it is unfair to deal with that one, particularly where there is no evidence of any kind, not a scintilla of evidence, that there has been any profiteering.  I think it is unfair to segregate that particular section for legislation, when there is no proof of profiteering, and to leave the other sections alone.  If the Dáil wants to deal fairly let it set up an inquiry. If, as a result of that inquiry, profiteering is found to exist in building materials, as far as I am concerned, I will withdraw any opposition to a proposal of this kind, but that Commission must&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I allowed the Deputy to make an allusion to this question of profiteering because it was raised by Deputy Corish.  But he is really speaking now on the section rather than on the Amendment.  We have passed the Section which sets up the control.  The Amendment is with regard to the variation by the Minister of orders made by him or on appeal from him.  It is rather narrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>But might I point out that certain statements were allowed to be made in the course of the debate, and surely the other side ought to be allowed to refer to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I am doing.  I allowed the Deputy to go as far as saying that he did not agree with the other statement, and I allowed the President to go a certain distance.  Then I told him he was going too far.  We cannot go into a discussion on whether or not we were right in passing Section 8 unless we had a motion to delete it on Report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>The country wants houses, and I think the people are entitled <Col N="1832" /> to know why they cannot get them.  As far as I am concerned, I am prepared to give them every assistance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no objection to all this information being disseminated in the best possible manner, but it is my business to see that that is done at a particular time, and that the right thing shall now be discussed.  What we are now discussing is a particular amendment, and not the general question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. A. BYRNE Mr. A. BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know whether I would be allowed just one half a minute to give a short statement in regard to what has already taken place?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you now speaking on the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="Mr. A. BYRNE Mr. A. BYRNE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. BYRNE</NameTxt>
      <P>When you hear my statement, I think you will agree it could be taken in connection with the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we not discuss this matter again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>This is simply an amendment to a section. Later on there will be a motion to the effect that the Bill be received for final consideration.  When that motion is made the whole Bill will be before us, and anything that concerns it will be in order.  It is only a difference of, perhaps, half an hour, or at most, two or three days.  There will be no injustice done to anybody, and Deputies will be allowed to give full vent to their opinions when that motion is made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think you have been long suffering over the matter of this amendment.  I do not propose to trespass much further by getting out of order, but the amendment, I suggest to my colleague, Deputy Good, that was put down by Deputy Duggan on behalf of the Government, is an amendment which has a bearing on the Section.  In so far as it has a bearing on the Section, it improves the Section.  But that is only damning it with faint praise, because the Section itself is so rotten it would take more than the whole force of the Executive to put it in anything like a decent shape.  It is the blot on <Col N="1833" /> the whole Bill.  If I test the Section, no doubt I will be called to order, so I must really confine myself to the amendment.  It is a harmless effort in a good cause; that is what I say of it.  I would be rather inclined to pat Deputy Duggan on the back for his efforts in the direction of improving the unimprovable. The only way to improve the Section is to delete it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am supporting this amendment because I have been informed that once this Appeal Court fixes a price, that price cannot be revoked or altered.  In other words, there would be no appeal from that appeal. If the Appeal Court were to fix a price for three or six months, and circumstances were to alter in the meantime, it is for that purpose this amendment is put in, so that the Minister himself may alter, revoke and so on.  It has been put to us there has been no profiteering. There is one class of person we wish to attract in the operation of this Bill, and that person has been almost put out of business.  I refer to the small builder.  I am informed on very reliable authority that the small builder suffers a disadvantage in the matter of prices as compared with the larger builder. If that be so, and if the Minister holds an inquiry, to which I now understand Deputy Good has no objection, and if the small builder makes a case for the same price for this particular housing scheme in which we are all interested, I think there is some justification, in the event of some innocent brother in the confraternity not hearing of the inquiry, for some effort on his part to endeavour to persuade the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>The President is touching dangerous ground again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>If the provision remained in the Bill as it stands without this amendment, notwithstanding the legal advice the Minister has received that there would be no power to alter the decision, there would, at least, be power to order a new local inquiry which might take a quarter of an hour&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1834" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>And which might take three months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is simply a case of an extraordinary rise or fall in the price of bricks&mdash;and that is the kind of new fact which the Minister has in mind&mdash;the evidence is palpable, and does not require a great deal of inquiry, and that new inquiry would warrant a new order.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 5, line 33, to add to Section 8 a new sub-section as follows&mdash;(5) Neither this section nor any order made thereunder shall continue in operation after the expiration of eighteen months from the passing of this Act.</P>
      <P>When the Bill was previously in Committee, there was some question raised as to the limit of time there was upon its operation.  It is desirable to have it made clear that it will not operate after eighteen months from the passing of the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>This is but another evidence of the many ambiguities in this Bill.  When this Bill was introduced it was clearly understood that this clause only applied to the material in the houses embraced within the Bill. Then we were told at a later stage by the President that it includes all houses and that its operation was limited to the period of the Bill.  Some of us doubted the accuracy of it.  While the idea was all right, we doubted whether the Bill meant that or something else. An opinion was obtained, and it was shown this particular clause operated until it was repealed by a further Bill. In view of that decision, the President said he would reconsider the matter, and this is the result of that reconsideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I note the Deputy supports this amendment with a certain amount of pleasure.  I oppose it with equal pleasure, and probably with less anticipation of satisfaction.  The intention appears to be something like this: &ldquo;We cannot trust (that is to say, the Government cannot trust) the building material providers to provide materials <Col N="1835" /> at the price for houses to be built during the period with which this Act deals.  Houses which are to be assisted in their building by Government grants will be made more difficult to build, or may be made more difficult to build, by virtue of the fact that building material providers may conceivably rush up the price.  We must put the barrier against that possibility.  After the Bill ceases to operate, then the building material providers are free to do what they like to the public, rob them ad lib. and be not subject to any check.  The check may be provided during the period of 18 months, but after that you can go your own way and we, as a legislature, will have nothing to say to you.&rdquo;  That is the proposal in the amendment.  I wonder is it the intention of the Ministry to tell the building trades that they only ask them to hold their hands for 18 months, to soothe the savage beast, so to speak, and generally to go easy for a little time.  After that they can make any profit they like and charge any prices they like.  Certainly that is the message contained in this amendment, and I think the House should not accept it.  Why do you want to limit the operations of this Section for 18 months?  Is not the object of the Bill that a check should be placed upon profiteering in building materials?  Presumably, the Ministry have some definition of the term &ldquo;profiteering&rdquo; in their minds.  I am waiting anxiously to know what that definition is, and by the way, perhaps it will come, in the course of a week or two, but there is the definition here that excessive prices may possibly be charged for building materials.  Now, if it is undesirable to allow excessive prices to be charged for building materials under this Bill, surely it is equally desirable to prevent excessive prices being charged for building materials at any time.  Why then do you want to limit the period of check to 18 months? In doing so by a specific clause or section of this kind, you are telling the building providers that you are only asking them to hold their hand for a little while.  You are inviting them to save up for the rainy day, to be a little patient, and then after 18 months they <Col N="1836" /> can just run riot in regard to prices.</P>
      <P>Now, if one could imagine that the number of houses comprised within the ambit of this Bill was going to remedy the evils of housing, or to satisfy the demand for houses, one could understand the Ministry saying, &ldquo;Well, we are against Government control; we are against checking private enterprise; we trust the innate good nature of the building trade; and we only want to give the public a certain amount of confidence that their money, which is being spent in grants under this Bill, will not be unduly and disproportionately taken by the providers of building material.&rdquo; I can understand that.  But surely it is a bad thing to allow these excessive prices to be charged for any houses that are required for the next 10 or 15 years if, as has been said authoritatively, there are 60,000 houses required in the Saorstát to meet the present shortage. You want some check against profiteering, at least, until these 60,000 houses are provided; but by the adoption of this amendment you are telling the trade that after 18 months they may charge as they like.  You are hinting to them that the check upon their rapacity will not extend beyond the period of 18 months.  Consequently, I think this amendment should not be accepted.  You say it may happen that within 18 months a new Bill may be required; that there will be a new Dáil, and that Deputy Good's party, associated with Deputy Gorey's party, may be in a majority, and then they will not be willing to insert a section such as Section 8.  I suggest, therefore, to the Ministry that they should not accept this amendment of Deputy Duggan, and that they should, at least, lay the foundation for putting a permanent check upon profiteering.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Whether by labour or by anybody else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, whether by labour or by anybody else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good; I am with you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>And when Deputy Good has defined profiteering and leaves a reasonable payment for labour we shall have something more to say to <Col N="1837" /> him.  If the Ministry wants to tell the country that they only desire to check profiteering while they are in office, let them do so in so many words.  If they do not want to do that, let them stick to the Section of the Bill as originally introduced, or, at least, as it has come to us in this stage and not accept the amendment of Deputy Duggan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise to support the amendment.  The amendment is another instance of where the Government are trying to improve a bad proposition. So far as Government money is concerned in the building of these houses, they have a case that may appeal to the gallery, but I do not think it will appeal to anybody else.  But Deputy Johnson wants to make this the foundation of future legislation that is going to govern prices.  I do not think any Deputy in this House knows better than Deputy Johnson that he is trying to do the impossible, that is, to lay the foundations for an impossible building that would come smashing down about his head before he knew where he was.  It would not be the master builders who would build on that foundation, but rather, I think, irresponsible politicians. When I was a little bit younger in the ways of this House than I am to-day, I saw that a very interesting Bill was brought in by Deputy Johnson. It dealt with the nationalisation of the railways, and I respectfully suggest to Deputy Johnson, who has at his command and control an army of draughtsmen and an army that is very well drilled and can supply him with a great deal of information from various sources, even as to what politician is going to come up for election in the County Dublin, that his energies might be thrown into an effort which, as far as I am concerned, I will welcome gladly, to produce a private Bill in the House, under the auspices of the Labour Party, which will deal with the whole subject, in the 18 months that will elapse after this Bill comes into operation and its termination.  I think it would be a very good work if Deputy Johnson and the Party to which he belongs would formulate another Bill on the lines of the Bill for the nationalisation of railways, nationalising all profits, and that it would probably help <Col N="1838" /> him in his march toward Treasury Bench.  He outlined the time that Deputy Good and myself would be more prominent in this House than we are to-day.  I would like to contemplate the time when our friends on the Labour Benches would occupy the enviable position of the Labour Party on the other side of the water with the aid of Deputy Good and myself, and if we were not enough we could import some noble lords into our Labour administration, as they have done in Great Britain. At all events, in supporting this amendment, I would like to suggest, as Deputy Johnson and his Party feel so keenly on this question of profiteering, that responsibility rests with them to give the Government all the assistance they can in every case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am supporting this amendment because I do not think it would be good business to insert in a Bill which is to have a life only of 18 months, a provision that is to last for all time.  I said on more than one occasion that this Bill was not entirely a philanthropic measure on the part of the Government; that we had our minds centred upon two or three things.  First on compensation, second on the provision of these houses, and thirdly on a general reduction in the cost of building, which would be beneficial to the State.  Consequently, it is not in respect of this Bill alone that we want accommodation from the three persons or bodies concerned with this particular industry, which I need not mention again.  Now, it is more than likely that another Bill will be introduced within twelve months, and another Bill within the succeeding twelve months.  The Government's intention at the moment is to deal with this housing matter by a Bill each year. I do not think this particular Section that we introduced into this Bill will be a success in the sense that it is experimental, as all legislation dealing with profiteering or excessive prices or costs must necessarily be.  If it be a success and achieves its purpose, if we consider it is necessary in the next Bill, we will introduce it into that or amend it, so as to suit the altered circumstances of the times, but on the other hand, if it is no longer necessary&mdash;and I do look forward <Col N="1839" /> to a time when such corrective of ordinary prices should not be necessary, I look forward with great hope to see that time come&mdash;and if it should not be necessary then, naturally, it would not be introduced in next year's Bill. I think a measure such as this, with a <Col N="1840" /> life only of 18 months, ought not to have an ordinance in it which would run for any longer period than the period for which the Bill would normally run.  I do not think there is anything more to say.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 46; Níl, 13.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Pádraig F Baxter.<br />Earnán de Blaghd.<br />Seoirse de Bhulbh.<br />Próinsias Bulfin.<br />Séamus de Burca.<br />John Conlan.<br />Máighréad Ní Choileáin Uí Dhrisceoil.<br />Patrick J. Egan.<br />Darrell Figgis.<br />Henry J. Finlay.<br />Desmond Fitzgerald.<br />John Good.<br />John Hennigan.<br />Connor Hogan.<br />Tomás Mac Artúir.<br />Peadar Mac a' Bháird.<br />Alasdair Mac Cába.<br />Domhnall Mac Cárthaigh.<br />Liam T. Mac Cosgair.<br />Séamus Mac Cosgair.<br />Pádraig Mac Fadáin.<br />Pádraig Mac Giollagáin.<br />Seán Mac Giolla 'n Ríogh.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Seoirse Mac Niocaill.<br />Liam Mac Sioghaird.<br />Liam Mag Aonghusa.<br />Pádraig Mag Ualghairg.<br />Patrick McKenna.<br />Peadar O hAodha.<br />Mícheál O hAonghusa.<br />Criostóir O Broin.<br />Seán O Bruadair.<br />Aodh Ua Cinnéidigh.<br />Séamus N. O Dóláin.<br />Peadar S. O Dubhghaill.<br />Eamon S. O Dúgáin.<br />Seán O Duinnín.<br />Mícheál R. O hIfearnáin.<br />Seán O Laidhin.<br />Aindriú O Láimhín.<br />Séamus O Leadáin.<br />Fionán O Loingsigh.<br />Pádraic O Máille.<br />Seán M. O Súilleabháin.<br />Caoimhghín O hUigín.<br />Seán Priomhdhaii.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl.</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Seán Buitleír.<br />John Daly.<br />Séamus Eabhróid.<br />David Hall.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Risteárd Mac Fheorais.<br />Tomás de Nógla.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Tomás O Conaill.<br />Aodh O Cúlacháin.<br />Liam O Daimhín.<br />Domhnall O Muirgheasa.<br />Tadhg O Murchadha.<br />Pádraig O hOgáin (An Clár).<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Amendment declared carried.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL" RHead="RESUMES">
    <Title>DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>Bill reported with further amendments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is: &ldquo;That the Bill, as amended, be received for final consideration.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood that the President was to look into the Schedule. Am I in order in raising the point this time?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, the whole Bill is before the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>When we had the footnote attached to the Schedule under consideration there was an amendment to alter 5 to 6, and when we were considering that, certain matters arose which the President undertook to look into.  You remember the connection where the price was to be reduced by 50 per cent. when the local authority gives an equivalent grant to that of the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I have not been able to get any further on that point.  The point, I took it, that Deputy Good was making was that he was in some doubt as to whether if the local authority gave that it would reduce the price of the house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>Reduce the selling price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The benefit in that case was divided equally between <Col N="1841" /> the builder and the person purchasing. I have not been able to find a better method of dealing with it than that.  I think on the last day Deputy Good misinterpreted the reading of the note, and that the advantage, although actually of the value of £100, is open to some discount, discount to this extent, that taking the virgin soil site the development of that would necessarily be more expensive than if a person had a frontage on which the development would be nil.  We considered that the easiest way of meeting the whole case was estimating the value at a certain figure, and then allowing only 50 per cent. of that to the two persons concerned, the builder in the one case and the purchaser in the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>What it practically amounts to is this: From the builder's point of view, this clause takes away from him a moiety of the Government grant, because whether you take it away by reason of a reduction in the selling price, or whether you take it away in only giving him half of the Government grant, it amounts to the same thing in the end.  The builder only gets the equivalent of a moiety of the Government grant.  That, as I pointed out to the President, takes away from the attractiveness of this measure, because it is quite obvious, as has been pointed out several times during the discussion on this Bill, that the local authority, in view of what it has to do, will find some difficulty in carrying out that work at a sum equivalent to the Government grant.  Take the case of the three-roomed house.  The Government grant is a grant of £60.  It is quite obvious from the figures where the local authority has purchased the ground and laid out the site that it would find itself in some considerable difficulty to carry that out and keep within this particular clause of the Bill.  We may take it for granted that practically in every case the local authority will have to spend a sum equivalent to the Government grant, and that that being so, the Government grant will practically be reduced by a moiety.  That is the effect of this, because it reduces the selling price, and if it reduces the selling price it is exactly the same thing as taking <Col N="1842" /> half off the Government grant.  That will affect the three-roomed house very seriously, much more so than the five-roomed house, because the price allowed for a five-roomed house is really larger. As the grant is on a room basis, as you reduce the number of rooms the expense increases.  This grant may possibly cover the cost of carrying out the work for a five-roomed house, but it is fairly obvious that the three-roomed house will be handicapped under this proposal.  The effect of that will be that we will encourage five-roomed houses, and that we will prevent three-roomed houses from being built.  As far as I have been able to judge the mind of the President, it is exactly the opposite he has in mind.  We are anxious that we should get the largest number of houses, and if we are anxious that we should get the largest number of houses, surely there ought to be an incentive to building the smaller houses rather than the big houses.  The effect of this proposal, I am satisfied, will be to make three-roomed houses practically an impossibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Before you put the question, A Chinn Comhairle, I would like to ask the President could he possibly insert in the Bill some reduction in the rents charged in Part 1 of the Schedule.  It is beyond the power of the ordinary people to pay the rents set out there.  If the President cannot see his way to reduce the maximum rent, perhaps he would state the minimum, so that people will know exactly what they will be required to pay. Twelve and threepence halfpenny for a five-room house in the country is more than the people are able to pay.  If the minimum were set out at 6s. it might be possible to find means to prevent landlords charging more than the minimum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I misinterpreted what Deputy Good said.  I take it now that what he means is, that taking a five-room house which is scheduled at £450, for sale, after getting the £100, the price that house ought to sell at would be £450, no matter what the local authority would grant.  In other words, if the local <Col N="1843" /> authority gives £100 worth of value&mdash; either by way of site or money&mdash;as permitted by the Minister, I take it that Deputy Good's point is that with that and with the £100 we give, this house should be sold at £450.  I see the point now; I did not see it before.  My opinion is that it will be possible to get builders to construct a particular house which, taking into consideration the concession that will be given by the local authority, can be sold, with profit to the builder, at £400.  The point in dispute between us, so far as I can see, is the saleable, commercial value of this particular property.  On that, I am informed that it is a business proposition.</P>
      <P>With regard to what Deputy Seán Lyons said, he might as well ask me could we, by Act of Parliament, reduce the interest on money.  In other words, having got £10,000,000 by way of loan from the people, can we say, by Act of Parliament, that we will reduce the interest on that money from 5 per cent. to 3 per cent.?  We cannot do it.  It would be immoral.  You entered into a contract with a man three or four months ago, and arranged a certain price, and you cannot reduce it.  We would have to go further and pass an Act compelling builders to put up houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Why not do it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid, whatever power there is in the State, that is a little beyond its power&mdash;even with the assistance of the National Army, the Civic Guard and the Deputy himself.</P>
      <P>Question: &ldquo;That the Bill, as amended, be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and declared carried.</P>
      <P Just="Center">FIFTH STAGE.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is no objection, I would ask to have the final stage taken now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We passed a new Standing Order on this question yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry I was not present.  If there is no objection, I <Col N="1844" /> move the suspension of the Standing Orders to take the final stage of this Bill.</P>
      <P>Standing Orders suspended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill do now pass.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not expect that we would have this stage of the Bill today, but I am not raising any objection. The Bill has been brought forward, on the responsibility of the Ministry, as their contribution to the solution of the housing problem.  It has not been opposed from this side, and its failure, which I predict cannot be charged against any action on the part of the Dáil.  I hope I shall be proved wrong in my prediction.  But I have no expectation that the Bill will result in the building of the number of houses prescribed.</P>
      <P>I want to raise the question of the housing of the common, working-class people now, and to ask the Ministry when they intend to bring in a measure having reference to the housing of the working classes?  The Bill does not pretend to meet the case of the average wage-earner in the country who is short of a house.  It proposes to assist in the building of houses, which in the towns may be let at: 8/3 for a three-room house, 11/1 for a four-room house, and 13/10 for a five-room house.  In the country, where sewers and water mains are not available, the charges are to be: 7/4½ for a three-room house, 9/10 for a four-room house, and 12/3½ for a five-room house.  The country worker, on a wage of from 28/- to 35/- per week, is being asked to provide for his family, and, if he has a three-room house, to pay 7/4½ for it; that out of a wage of 28/-!  One-third of his income is to go in rent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That obviously is not a proposition that is intended for the rehousing of the workers.  If he has a larger family and requires a little more comfort and is in receipt of a little higher wage, and requires a five-roomed house in the country, he will be obliged to pay 12/3½ per week as rent.  A 36/- or a 37/- a week wage-earner will again be required to pay 33 1-3 per cent. income of his wage as rent.  That, again, <Col N="1845" /> is evidence that this Bill is not calculated to assist in the rehousing of the working classes or to provide houses for the workers in any way unless the few specially fortunate.  For a town house of four and five rooms he has to pay a rent of 11/1 and 13/10 a week.  Well, undoubtedly many people will be very glad to get such a house even at that charge.  But it is not going very far towards satisfying the present demand for houses at the rate of wages that are ruling.</P>
    <P>If this is the proposition that is to be put before the wage-earner as all he can expect, under the Government scheme, then it will follow that not reductions, but advances in wages will be demanded, and ought to be paid.  So that in view of that evidence, I take it that this scheme is not intended to facilitate the housing of the wage-earner except indirectly.  And it is because of this exception that I have acquiesced in the passing of this Bill, the exception being that for every new house that is built there is a little easing of the pressure, a little lessening of the demand.  To that extent some good is obtained, but it is going to be so slow and so gentle an easement of the pressure, that nobody will feel it, and in practice, as far as the wage-earners are concerned, it may be said to be hardly worth while.  Now, I would like to hear what the Minister's proposals are towards the solution of the housing problem.  The housing problem is, in the main, the problem of the housing of the wage-earners.  It is the problem which affects the city and the town and country.  I said in an earlier discussion that we have had it on authority that 60,000 houses were required to supply the present demand, and to make up the present deficiency of decent housing accommodation that exists. Now to tackle that problem with anything like vigour and earnestness requires not to deal with it piecemeal, as this Bill proposes to do, but to look ahead for at least a period of ten years, and promote a scheme with a ten years' programme in view.</P>
    <P>It would be necessary to have a real national outlook and a purpose to utilise all the resources of the country, material and human, that may be required to supply this demand for <Col N="1846" /> houses.  I believe that if there were some imagination brought to bear and a resolute purpose to make an attempt to deal with this problem on a big scale, with a view to remedying the evil, within ten years, if possible, I think it might be possible to double the supply of houses that we have contemplated in the Bill.  If it were taken up on a national scale then you could prepare accordingly a supply of materials, you could prepare accordingly schemes in advance, and you could organise your labour supply for the very definite purpose of building houses.  I believe that if these schemes were tackled you could enlist the support of all those for whom Deputy Good speaks as organisers of this industry, and we could enlist the support of all the operatives engaged in the industry for the purpose of building houses.</P>
    <P>I maintain that it is quite wrong to proceed on the assumption that you can trust to the enterprise and activities of a thousand separate employers, and thousands of separate groups of workmen, each acting independently of the other and unrelated, without any general scheme of co-ordination or common supply.  Unless you organise the whole scheme with a view to the utmost output for a long period you are not going to get the work done in as advantageous a manner or as speedily as you otherwise would.  I think the plan of putting the whole undertaking of re-housing the people under a special housing authority, having power to utilise all these resources of labour and material, and make contracts ahead, to import what may be necessary on the very biggest scale that may be necessary; to prepare supplies ahead and to tackle the whole problem as one great national scheme, is the only way in which this problem can be dealt with, with any expectation of solving the problems within a reasonable time.</P>
    <P>The plan proposed now in the Bill is, as I said before, peddling with the problem, and is very unlikely, in my opinion, to result in the benefit of the houses being built to the extent even calculated for in the Bill.  I know the trouble is finance.  I have a belief that if this scheme were tackled in a national way that you would find the <Col N="1847" /> means of raising the money to finance it outside the ordinary courses and at probably a considerably cheaper interest than the market rate.</P>
    <P>You would probably have to look for the assistance of people who would be quite prepared to assist in the building of houses and supply money for the purpose without the expectation of getting the market rate of interest. People have been known to do things for a purpose of that kind on a big scale, and I can imagine that millions could be obtained, at least for a few years, at a very low rate of interest if there is any faith that the country will be secure and prosperous, and I believe there is that faith.  I believe those people would assist in providing the monies necessary for a re-housing of the people at a rate which would allow very much cheaper houses.  I believe an organised attempt could be made to meet the problem on the biggest and widest scale.  Unless and until this problem is tackled with that idea, you are not going to make any big impression on the evil, and every year that passes in which so many thousands of people are born and bred and live under the conditions in which they now live, would be adding to the future problems of the country.  There is economic loss as well as moral loss in these housing defects, and it is worth the country's while to run great risks for the purpose of getting as large a number of people as possible re-housed under decent conditions, so that the economic, material and moral losses which we might look for in the absence of that re-housing in ten, fifteen or thirty years' time, may be avoided.  I am disappointed that this Bill, which some had hoped for and looked for with generous anticipation, is of so meagre a character and is so unhopeful in its provisions.</P>
    <P>If the houses are built and some of the pressure is relieved, then I shall be very glad, but I hope the Ministry will set themselves to work so that the Bill that the Minister has promised for a year hence will be on a very much bigger scale and with a very much bigger prospect of doing something to <Col N="1848" /> solve this problem of housing in Ireland.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Private business should be taken at 2 o'clock&mdash; that is to say, the resumed debate on Deputy Corish's motion.  Is it intended to make some other proposal in view of this debate?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps we could go on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall be quite prepared to acquiesce in any suggestion for continuing this discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite agreeable to this discussion being continued.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Then we may take it that this debate continues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>I was sorry to hear from Deputy Johnson that he is afraid that this Bill will be a failure and will not achieve any very useful object.  When this measure was introduced the President pointed out that he was satisfied this great difficulty of providing houses could only be achieved by the co-operation of all parties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>took the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>After all the discussions that we have heard during the time this Bill has been under consideration, I am satisfied that that original idea is the real and the correct one.  Except all parties are prepared to co-operate with the real desire of providing houses for those who need them, I am afraid, with Deputy Johnson, that we shall not have the houses.  I think Deputy Johnson&mdash;I am speaking now from memory&mdash;was of that view when we started the consideration of the Bill.  He was of the view that it should have the co-operation of all parties.  If that is so, might I ask Deputy Johnson what has been the co-operation shown by him, and those associated with him, as representing those people who will benefit almost entirely by the housing measure?  What has been that co-operation and what part has he taken?  It is all very well to protest, criticise, and say so-and-so, but except we are prepared to do something practical in this matter, it is quite obvious we shall not get the houses.  What has Deputy Johnson and <Col N="1849" /> those associated with him done towards helping a solution of this matter?  Building to-day in Ireland is not in the condition in which we would like to see it, and the reason for that is that it is not an economic proposition.  Why does building, particularly the building of houses, seem to be a more difficult problem in Dublin and in Southern Ireland&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Where?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;Than what it appears to be in other countries?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy tell us what he means by the words &ldquo;Southern Ireland&rdquo;?  I am not trying to pick the Deputy up unfairly, but I think it is undesirable that in the Dáil at any rate, whatever may be done elsewhere, that we should adopt that phraseology of referring to the Saorstát as &ldquo;Southern Ireland.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. GOOD Mr. GOOD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOOD</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no objection if it will satisfy Deputy Johnson, to substitute the &ldquo;Free State&rdquo; for &ldquo;Southern Ireland.&rdquo;  Why, I ask, has this difficulty that I have been referring to, arisen? We have been discussing it here as regards the city of Dublin, and why, I ask, is the difficulty so much greater in getting houses in the city of Dublin than appears to be the case in adjoining counties?  The answer to the question is a simple one.  The wages paid to tradesmen in the building industry in the city of Dublin to-day are the highest wages paid in Europe.  We are a poor country, and can we afford to pay for house-building the highest rate of wages paid in Europe to-day?  I do not want to magnify this, because we will never get over our difficulties by magnifying them.  I want, on the other hand, to co-operate with those whom Deputy Johnson represents, and get them to see what are the real difficulties underlying this problem, and having pointed out what these difficulties are to them, to try and find out what way they can be solved.  I am satisfied that that is the only way this difficulty can be met.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As soon as we make up our mind to co-operate and meet it in that way, the sooner we shall make some advance in dealing with this difficult problem.  I <Col N="1850" /> agree with Deputy Johnson that these rents are too high.  How are we going to get down the cost of living while the rent, which is a very essential and considerable part of the cost of living, stands at a high figure?  This is one of the difficulties that seems to rise up against us everywhere, this difficulty of housing, and until, as I have said, we can meet together and consider the problem in all its aspects, and try and put forward some practical proposals for dealing with that difficulty, I am satisfied that until that time arrives we will have this difficulty with us.  As I said, I do not want to magnify the difficulty.</P>
    <P>Let me explain to Deputy Johnson that even when you get into the arena of building material you are up against this same question of bricks.  The Deputy has quoted several times the question of bricks.  Let me tell him, as one who has some knowledge of that particular subject, that labour costs over 40 per cent. in the manufacture of bricks. Consequently, if you have to pay labour a high rate of wages, it means that the cost of that commodity is increased, and also the cost of the particular object to which that commodity is to be applied.  So that the ramifications of this question are exceedingly wide.</P>
    <P>The President said there were three parties concerned in the erection of houses, but he has only taken one of these parties into consideration under the Bill.  That, I have protested all through, is exceedingly unfair.  If the three parties had been taken in and dealt with under the Bill, as far as I am concerned, I would have had no objection to that.  But I have a decided and a strong objection to taking in one section, when there has been no proof whatever of any excess charges in the case of that section, and to include that section and leave out the others is unfair.  That, to my mind, is not the form that legislation should take.  Legislation should not be of a party or partisan character.  If it is of that character we will object to it, but if it is of a broad and fair character, as far as I am concerned.  I will not object to it.  But when it takes this individual character, as it does here, I certainly will object to it as strongly as I possibly can.  What would have <Col N="1851" /> been a fair and a right course to adopt in connection with this matter was this: to have had an inquiry into the high cost of building, when you could have had all the different aspects of the question examined.  If as a result of that inquiry it was found that legislation was necessary, even legislation of what I might call an individual character, even then I would not object to it; but to take up and single out one individual interest and trade for special treatment, in the absence of any such evidence, is to my mind casting a slur upon that particular industry which is not justified.</P>
    <P>Deputy Johnson has pointed out that this question should be dealt with on a much larger basis than the Government has proposed.  I am quite satisfied that that is impossible at the moment.  If a commodity is uneconomic, and the State has to subsidise it to a large extent, I think it is exceedingly unwise to suggest that the State should subsidise that particular commodity at a time when that commodity is at an exceedingly high figure.  That is the position at the moment.  One of the reasons why so much building is kept back at the moment is that everybody expects that, in the natural course of events, building must get cheaper than it is to-day.  It is quite obvious that it must get cheaper by and by, and to urge that the nation should embark on a huge expenditure and to maintain these conditions for a period of ten years, is not a practical proposition. And at the end of ten years the State will have parted with a very large sum of money, and I do not think the problem will be very much improved. The experience of those who have dealt with housing on the other side on these particular lines has been anything at all but a satisfactory one. They have come to the conclusion that there is only one way in which this housing difficulty can be solved, and that is by private enterprise.  That is the line they are taking now on the other side, and it is the line that the President here has decided on in view of his experiences in this country.</P>
    <P>Those who have studied the subject are quite satisfied that that is the only <Col N="1852" /> line that we can look to as being likely to produce the houses.  If that is so, it is quite obvious, as I have said, that we must try and make building an economic proposition.  That is the first task to be undertaken, and I think it is to that task that possibly more attention might have been devoted than has been devoted to it, because, as I said at the start, it is only by the co-operation of all parties connected with the industry that we can achieve anything.  It is only right to say here, in connection with the high cost of wages in Dublin, that an effort has been made recently to get these wages reduced.  The reply received was that in view of the volume of work that is to be carried out, they could not see&mdash;this is the reply from Labour&mdash;any necessity for reducing wages.  I do not want to say anything now that would aggravate the situation. The line I have taken is rather the opposite one, but is it reasonable, in view of the fact that we here require houses, for those who produce the houses to sit down and say that &ldquo;in view of the volume of work that is before us, we do not see that the occasion calls for a reduction in wages.&rdquo;  That means, in substance, taking advantage of a situation in order to maintain a high wage. That, I think, is particularly unfortunate at the present time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>We, on the Farmers' benches, have paid very little attention to this Bill, because we regard it as a Bill intended almost exclusively for the advantage of urban dwellers. On the Second Reading I said I did not believe that this Bill would be of any great use to those who are in most urgent need of houses, and I agree with Deputy Johnson in his remarks in that regard.  I believe that the economic rents which must be charged for these houses will make it an impossible proposition as far as the ordinary worker is concerned.  Of course, I also see the point of view of the Government in introducing the Bill, and of their intention to relieve one class of the people. They believe that by doing so they will eventually make a certain amount of room for the poorer class of people, to get the houses vacated by the first class. I believe there was no intention whatever when this Bill was drafted, or <Col N="1853" /> when it was introduced, to make it apply to those who dwell in the rural districts, and I believe it will not be availed of even to the smallest extent, by those dwelling in such districts.  I was very sorry that the President did not see his way on the Committee Stage to accept my amendment, which dealt with the reconstruction of houses, and with the making of grants for the purpose of having the reconstruction of houses carried out.  The President allowed Sub-section (2) of Section 3 to stand in the Bill, and under this Sub-section dwellers in rural districts are not entitled to get any grant for the reconstruction of a house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Since that discussion took place I met one of my constituents, a small farmer, a progressive farmer, who came to me and asked if it were possible for him to get any grant for the purpose of reconstructing his house.  He was in a situation that would have fitted exactly into this Bill, if the Section I referred to had not been included.  I had to tell him that he could not gain any advantage under the Bill, as the Section I am speaking of provided that the grant would not apply to a rural dweller.  I was sorry to have to tell him so, because if that Section had not been introduced into the Bill, the Section dealing with the reconstruction of houses would have been of use to the class of persons of which this man was a representative, living in the rural districts of the country. Seeing that the Bill, as it stands, is of no use to the farmers or to rural dwellers, I would ask the President to give serious consideration to the introduction of a Bill at a future date which will deal with the housing problem as it applies to rural districts, because there is a definite housing problem to be solved in rural Ireland, and the problem is getting more acute day by day.  I have listened to Deputy Good and to Deputy Johnson discussing the devilments and other things connected with this problem as it affects urban areas.  The builders appear to be placing the blame on the workers, and the workers place the blame on the builders. As far as we in the rural districts are concerned, we are caught between the upper and the neither millstone, between the profiteering merchant <Col N="1854" /> and the builders' providers on the one hand and between the profiteering artisan on the other.  As between the two I leave it to the House to decide which is the more to blame, or if the two are not equally to blame.  But between the two the position is becoming financially impossible for us, and it is quite impossible for any house to be built in the country as things stand at present.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson has stated that it is essential to have a big, bold effort to deal with the housing problem, and I must say that in a sense I partly agree with him, but we have not got big, bold material upon which to operate in order to do anything on a big, bold basis.  Two years ago the Provisional Government set apart a million pounds to deal with the housing problem.  Now, after two years, something like 2,000 houses have been constructed, or in the course of construction, under that Bill.  That was a Bill which was operated by the local authorities, and the Government contribution in the case of it was £2 for every £1 put up by the local authority.  I am not prepared, in the case of any service of that sort, to make any proposal of the same kind to Parliament again.  It is too much, and it cannot be afforded, and even if it could be afforded it is not a good headline to adopt in which you have got to give £2 for every £1 put up by another person.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>No response whatever was received from twenty out of ninety local authorities in connection with the working of that Act.  In other words, they wanted more.  It is more than possible that they would even want us to go down and build the houses for them, and then that we should graciously ask them to dispose of them.  I submit that the experience during that time was not a very happy experience, and certainly was not one which sounded like any reasonable attempt at co-operation by anybody concerned, and did not mark any advance on solving the housing problem.  In two years, as I say, 2,000 houses have not been put up.  Now, we are coming forward with a measure which certainly is not so extravagant and which calls for greater co-operation <Col N="1855" /> still than the other measure, and the assumption is that its operation will have the effect of putting up something like 3,000 houses in one year.  That is an optimistic prognostication, as Deputy Seán Lyons would say.</P>
    <P>At any rate, there is room for plenty of work.  The proposal, examined minutely by its most advanced critic, discloses this fact, that in the case of a five-roomed house where the maximum advantage is to be put up by the local authority, in other words, the equivalent to the Government grant, namely £100, a man who builds a house gets for £400, six hundred pounds' worth of property, with a considerable reduction in the amount of rates that he would have to pay, extending over a period of twenty years.  We are giving him even more than one-third of the price of the house that he is going to occupy.  That is, what this miserable unnamed child of a Bill is going to give a man, and everybody on looking on it and speaking of it says it is miserable, and unworthy of baptism, and that they do not think it will live. As Deputy Good said on one occasion, it is dead already.</P>
    <P>What are we asked to do?  Are we to give more than one-third of the price of the house?  Are we to make the house to be free of rates for ever, or what is the proposition?  A big, bold effort!  It is a big, bold effort; it is a brave effort.  If I know anything, it suffers from one infirmity, and that is it is too generous.  If it was less generous people would appreciate it more. Whatever is cheap they say, is not of much use.  It must be expensive in order to be attractive.  Unless housing be made a commercial proposition, it does not appear to me to be at all likely that we will make any real effort towards solving the problem.</P>
    <P>Coming to the point raised by the Deputy who spoke last from the Farmers' benches, £250,000 out of £300,000 is to be made available for the farmers as well as for any other section of the community. £50,000 only is being reserved for urban districts.  Why?  The people whom that £50,000 is intended to benefit in cities and towns are not persons who have a business to maintain <Col N="1856" /> them, as a rule.  They are the working classes, the majority of whom have not got more than a week, in a great many cases a fortnight, in a lesser number of cases three weeks, in a still lesser number a month, and in some case two or three months, lease of a particular occupation.  Whatever may be said about the disadvantages of agriculture, and I am sure they are many, it has had its cycle of prosperous years. It can scarcely be said for the working classes, for whom this particular measure was introduced, that they have had the same cycle of prosperous years, the same continuity of employment, or that if employment were bad that they had any reserves other than the thrift that might have been exercised during the more favourable years.  The conditions under which those people live are deplorable.  The £50,000 that we intended to use to make habitable certain houses, that some years ago would probably be condemned, is certainly a reserved service for towns and urban districts.  It is not that we operated against the farming class, as such.  If you analyse the position of persons for whom the Bill was intended, I think you will find that the smallest farmer who hoped to have some benefit out of that £50,000, would have an estate ten times the value of any person we intended to benefit by this particular Section. It is not a question of excluding them.  It is a question of seeking to drag back from the abyss houses that were falling into it, at a time when congestion is, perhaps, more intense than ever it was in the experience of anybody who knows the City of Dublin, the City of Cork, the City of Waterford, and the City of Limerick, or any of those other places.  It is an attempt to relieve that congestion by saving those houses from toppling over, or adapting other houses which would become tenement habitations to accommodate families in better conditions.  We had not in mind the farmers when we introduced this Bill.  We had in mind the class for whom a case has been made for years.  No real attempt has been made to deal with the housing problem.</P>
    <P>When it is put to us that there is just as much need for houses in rural districts as in the urban districts, we <Col N="1857" /> examine the records and we find that in 1913 the case that was put up by the rural districts for housing was that they had exactly the same number of persons living in insanitary conditions in insanitary dwellings, as the number who were living in single-roomed dwellings in the City of Dublin, according to the Census of the year 1911.  The case that was made for £1,000,000 grant from the British Government by the rural districts disclose the fact that the numbers were 78,000 persons housed under insanitary conditions in the rural areas.  The Census returns for the year 1911 disclose the fact that something like the same number of persons were living under practically insanitary conditions in Dublin, leaving out Cork, Limerick, Waterford, or any of the other towns or urban districts throughout the entire country.</P>
    <P>Further, we find that over a period of something like 20 or 30 years, 50,000 cottages were constructed in the rural districts.  Examining the case for towns we find that in something like 60 years only 10,000 houses were put up by local authorities in urban districts.  Our proposal two years ago was to put up 2,000 houses in a year.  We did not succeed.  As a matter of fact, we have not 2,000 constructed after 2 years, but before the whole of the million pounds is exhausted I anticipate that there will be 2,000 houses.  That is one-fifth of what was done in 50 or 60 years.</P>
    <P>The proposals under this particular Bill are that 3,000 houses will be erected in one year.  I admit, as Deputy Johnson has stated, that it is not a contribution towards a solution of the housing problem, as such, but I submit at the same time, that if people are waiting and expecting that the housing problem will be solved under the conditions we have at present, and at the present prices, there is no likelihood whatever of those hopes being realised.  I suppose it is better for us to be honest about a statement of that sort.  I do not admit that if any other order in the community occupied the positions that we occupy here, there could be a Royal, a Republican, or a Democratic solution better than the one we have put up. They may get better results in a short period, but the ultimate result will be <Col N="1858" /> still the same.  It might be that with a huge amount of capital good results would be obtained for a year or two years, but I do say, taking the problem over a number of years, say 5 or 10, the result would not be more satisfactory than from this scheme.</P>
    <P>I do certainly subscribe to what Deputy Johnson states; that is that we ought to try and get a big push from all sections to deal with this problem. I would be prepared to guarantee, as far as the life of this Government goes, if it has any lease of life at all, that we would undertake each year to make the same sort of proposal we have here, so that the people for whom he speaks would be guaranteed employment and so that insecurity of tenure of occupation would not be a continual bar to efficiency and output.  I do say that as the problen becomes less expensive on the State and on the local authority the likelihood is that there would be more employment.  I would like to see, and I am sure the Deputy would agree with me, this £300,000 producing twice the number of houses.  We would be both equally satisfied with the result and I am sure Deputy Good would join with us in singing a thanksgiving hymn.  That is all I have got to say. We could not continue the two-thirds cost which we put up last year and the year before.  This year, by spreading the burden and getting in the local authority, we are giving more than one-third, and I could not, if I had any regard for a reputation as an honest man, ask the Dáil to give a bigger contribution than that towards the solution of even such an important problem as this.</P>
    <P>Question:&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>A Message will be sent to the Seanad accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="POLICY OF MINISTER" RHead="FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT">
    <Title>POLICY OF MINISTER FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT.</Title>
    <P>Motion by Deputy Risteárd Mac Fheorais (resumed).</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That the Dáil disapproves of the policy of the Minister for Local Government, so far as it has been made known through the general activities of his Ministry&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="1859" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephMcGoldr" hpid="Mr. McGOLDRICK Mr. McGOLDRICK">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGOLDRICK</NameTxt>
      <P>I have only a few words to say in addition to what I stated on the last occasion this Motion was before the Dáil.  I think we cannot join in any general condemnation of the Ministry of Local Government. They have been dealing with a situation which was not normal.  They are acting under conditions which are extremely difficult and I am sure they are doing the best they possibly can. The amalgamation scheme was a hurried one.  It requires a lot of revision and it will require a great deal of consideration before it is capable of being applied to the conditions of the country, and so that it may best serve the interests which it is supposed to serve. Still I think it is a step in the right direction.  I am not very much in favour of centralisation but I think it is necessary to centralise in this case. Otherwise, it would be impossible for the ratepayer to meet the demands upon him, the expenses are becoming so extravagant that if continued on the same lines, I do not know exactly what the end would be&mdash;probably bankruptcy for the ratepayers.</P>
      <P>Officialism is taking charge of things to such an extent that it would be impossible to deal with the matter other than by centralisation and bringing it into some sort of reasonable relationship with the ability of the ratepaying community to pay, while at the same time trying to give commensurate advantages to the poor.  The poor people, it is true, are brought to a central home, which may be a long distance&mdash; and sometimes is a very considerable distance&mdash;from where they live.  But the conditions that prevail in those homes are, I think, vastly superior to the conditions in the isolated institutions where the poor were accommodated heretofore.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The question of hospital amalgamation is a different one.  I expect the hospital amalgamation system is only a tentative one, and that the Local Government Department will see that the road is kept clear for the establishment of what ultimately must be brought about&mdash;Cottage Hospitals in dispensary districts for the poor.  I think that must be the ultimate object in dealing with the hospital question. <Col N="1860" /> The Local Government Department, I should say, would aim at having a Central Home for the aged and destitute poor, with a Cottage Hospital in each dispensary district, and a surgical hospital and an infectious disease hospital to meet the requirements under these heads.  If that were done, and these institutions linked up, I think it would solve the problem very well.  That would be my idea, in any case, and I know that those in touch with the administration of local government are very much in sympathy with that particular method of meeting the requirements.</P>
    <P>The question of surveyors has been mentioned.  I think if there is to be any devolution of powers from the County Councils&mdash;I think the County Councils are overloaded as they are and they will be considerably more overloaded if further duties are added&mdash;the administrative authority from the County Councils should deal mainly with the road question in the various districts to which the devolutionary powers would extend.  District supervision, district control, district co-operation and district guidance should, I think, centralise itself in some sort of authority or road board, and confine itself largely to that particular work.  The surveyors should be made responsible to that authority, and they should be made do their duty, because we have no control over surveyors in the County Councils.  The surveyors are supposed to be their own controllers.  They ordain and execute and report.  They can make an elaborately-worded report, but they have nothing to show that anything has been done.  When we do go to examine the roads, or when we have experience of them, we know that nothing has been done.  That is the position with regard to surveyors. Something must be done by which these officials will be made directly responsible for the districts they are in charge of, and that they will see that some value is given for the money expended on roads.  There is an immense grant being expended on trunk roads in the different counties, and the question was raised here that the State should not have prescribed any particular wage in any particular district in respect of this work.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1861" /> I would like to see wage-earners getting as good wage as is reasonably fair in the circumstances, but I am very much afraid, as I said before, that if it were left to the Co. Councils to fix a wage, it would be worse for the wage-earners&mdash;and worse to a very great degree. I think it was a mistake to advocate that the Local Government Department should not have insisted on fixing the wages.  I do not know how far the amount fixed has been consistent with what is fair or equitable. I am not prepared to go into that, but I think it would be better that the fixing of these wages in respect of work under the grant should be in the hands of some central authority, rather than in the hands of the local bodies.  If it were left to the local authorities it would, I think, result in general chaos, and I do not think any arrangements could be made at all to secure the expenditure of this grant in the circumstances, knowing, as I do, the view of these authorities as regards these questions. Economy is all very well. Economy has been the watchword of the Local Government Department here, and I think they have insisted upon economy with a fair amount of firmness.  That was absolutely necessary. If it had not been done it would have been very serious for the country in every respect.  I think a great many of the complaints which are made against the Local Government Ministry are in the nature of propaganda.  Any man can make out a case for anything at the present time.  The conditions which prevail in the country we know are not normal.  As long as they are not normal, you cannot prescribe any fixed system by which any particular interest can be guided, governed, or managed properly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Is living on 29/- a week propaganda?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephMcGoldr" hpid="Mr. McGOLDRICK Mr. McGOLDRICK">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGOLDRICK</NameTxt>
      <P>It is only possible to arrange a system on some tentative basis.  I am not going into the question of the respective rates between respective individuals or respective items; I am dealing with the general policy that must guide those in charge of the affairs of the country.  They must be guided by a policy that will <Col N="1862" /> take a broad, comprehensive view. While it may be tentative, it must be one that will bring them into a safe position, and that will enable them to ordain or sanction legislation that will be just to all interests, and to the advantage and benefit of all agencies. Meantime, I think they are doing the best they can in the circumstances, and if they continue to do as they are doing until we get on to that firm basis in which we can enact solid legislation to meet the needs of the country and deal with the matter in a proper way, I think they will be doing a good thing for the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>My purpose in intervening in this debate is to direct attention to some grievances which exist in the county of which I am one of the representatives, and which we contend is due to hasty or unwise schemes which have been brought forward in the way of amalgamation of Unions.  These schemes have resulted in the closing of two hospitals which served for the relief and treatment of the sick poor.  One of those was the hospital at Athy.  The town of Athy is a populous one, containing some 4,000 inhabitants, and it is the centre of a large tillage district, the population of which, compared with others in the country, is a rather dense one.  Under these circumstances it will be allowed that a large percentage of the population is composed of people whose means will not allow them to have private treatment, but who, in the time of sickness or accident, must have recourse to hospitals.  Well, Athy hospital was closed some two years ago, and one general hospital was established in the County of Kildare.  That means that poor people and sick people, many of them perhaps <i>in extremis,</i> have to be conveyed by road in some cases a distance of 30 miles to the hospital at Naas.  Athy Hospital was well equipped.  There was a medical officer attached to it second to none in his profession, as far as the provinces are concerned. The nursing staff was efficient, and there was proper equipment in every respect.  I was on a deputation some time ago, which waited on the Minister.  The object was that he would at least make this concession, that he would consent to the establishment of <Col N="1863" /> 20 beds in Athy Hospital which would meet the cases of an urgent nature. Well, we have not heard since that that concession had been granted.  Again, the closing of another hospital outside the borders of Kildare has entailed great hardship in the northern parts of the county.  I allude to the Edenderry Hospital.  Before the scheme of amalgamation that hospital served a large district in the northern parts of Kildare. Since the people from the northern districts had to be brought to Naas.  I attended a meeting in Edenderry on Tuesday last, at which a strongly-worded resolution was passed protesting against the closing of that Hospital.  That meeting was composed exclusively of farmers, so it cannot be insinuated, as was insinuated here in the course of this debate, that anyone there had a money interest in keeping that hospital open.  It may be urged perhaps that economy would be effected by its closing.  That is very doubtful Even if that were so, the people present at that meeting, most of them large ratepayers, were not prepared to support a paltry economy at the expense of the poor or sick people.</P>
      <P>Farmers are credited with being rather severe economists or as our Yankee friends would style them, &ldquo;tight wads.&rdquo;  But they are not going that far.  They are not going to save money at the expense of the poor. I think that is a matter that the Minister should look into, and try to meet the popular demand in that respect.  I would ask him not to look at this question through official eyes, or through the glasses of permanent officials, but that he should look into this case himself, and take into account the feelings and views of the people in the localities affected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another question that has cropped up is the question of the abolition of District Councils.  Well District Councils, as we all know, were established in 1898 under the Local Government Act passed by the British Parliament.  It was looked upon as a great measure as it gave the people control of their local affairs which they had not up to that time.  I have been a member of a District Council a great number of <Col N="1864" /> years and have taken a fairly active part in the carrying out of its duties. I think I can honestly say that I have never seen the corruption or jobbery that has been alleged against these bodies.  The constitution of District Councils is not so much at fault.  What is really at fault is that at the recent elections not so much attention was paid to the administrative capacities of the men who were elected as to their political opinions, and that has resulted in the Councils being made up of men who do not pay so much attention to the details of administration as the members who composed those bodies formerly did.  They have not the same regard for the needs of the taxpayers, or the same regard to the ability of the taxpayer to pay the rates struck.  I think that if you abolish the District Councils you will place an intolerable burden on the County Council.  The County Councils have a large amount of work to do at present, and if you ask them to look after the ratepayers and if you ask them to look after the repairing of every cross-road pump in the country and after every pane of glass broken in a labourer's cottage you will be putting them in a position of staying there constantly, not for days, but for weeks, to get through their work.  It may be that a change is necessary in the relations between the County Councils and District Councils.  A suggestion has been made to me by a gentleman who is known to a great many Deputies&mdash;Mr. Patrick Phelan&mdash;a Kildare man himself, and a member of the Kildare County Council and a most constant attendant. In fact he told me that during the last 12 months he has attended 70 meetings of the County Council and the Committee of Health.  His suggestion is that you should give the County Councils the power of revising or vetoing the estimates sent forward by the District Councils.  At present they have no such power.  They have to accept the estimates sent in by the District Council. I think that, perhaps, that would meet the case.  Then, as to roads, the cost of maintaining the roads entails a very large burden on the ratepayers at present.  The abolition of the contract system in the repair of the roads brought an increase in the rates in the <Col N="1865" /> County Kildare of no less a sum than £10,000.  Well, we all know that the contract system was abandoned in the interest of particular people by the pressure which I will hardly call gentle.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot go into that question of the contract system.  It was brought about by local bodies and not by the direction of the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConlan" hpid="Mr. CONLAN Mr. CONLAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONLAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry.  I will conclude by urging the Minister to take these matters into consideration and not to adopt any hard and fast rule with regard to the hospital, but to look at the conditions obtaining in the different districts, and if he does that, I think he will find that the people in these localities are not putting forward impossible proposals, but ones which are really needed for the proper administration of all the poor laws, and also for the provisions connected with the Local Government Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Corish, in his motion censuring the Local Government Minister, covered a great deal of ground.  I do not propose to travel over the whole of it.  I rather prefer to confine myself to the attack he made on him for making certain conditions in connection with the million-and-a-quarter grant which is being provided for the remedying of unemployment, and which is to be spent on the roads.  One of the conditions, I understand, is that some of this money is to be spent on employing ex-members of the National Army, and it is characteristic of the Labour Deputies that on very many occasions here in my presence they have expressed very keen sympathy with demobilised men; but whenever it is proposed to give any definite expression to the wishes of the Government to compensate these men or to pay these men who have saved the country for us, there is an immediate squeal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="Mr. T. MURPHY Mr. T. MURPHY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. MURPHY</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not want them to starve on 29s. a week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>To my mind a great deal of these protestations of sympathy from the Labour Deputies are mere lip service.  I have often wondered why they should be opposed to the members <Col N="1866" /> of the National Army getting any share of the grants that are going.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation, I think I made it perfectly clear, in speaking to my motion, that we had no objection to members of the National Army.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>We never have had.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>The only objection we had was on the ground that they were being utilised as a lever to bring down wages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>And being made tools and slaves of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJMurphy" hpid="Mr. T. MURPHY Mr. T. MURPHY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. MURPHY</NameTxt>
      <P>That was made very clear all along.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to have that assurance, but I am afraid I am not convinced.  However, I will let that pass.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps, the Deputy will give us some evidence on the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>If you will be good enough to give me a little time, perhaps I will.  Quite recently there was a sum of £10,000 proposed to be given to the Dublin Corporation, and I understand that in connection with that grant, wages were set out at 50/- a week.  I am aware, from personal knowledge, that there is a great deal of distress in Dublin.  A friend of mine happened to be visiting a Convent only two days ago, and he met there a large number of people who were applying for relief. He questioned some of them, and they described to him their very pitiable condition. They said they were quite willing to work for this 50/- a week, but they were not allowed to work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now, if it is the considered policy of either the Labour leaders inside the Dáil, or responsible leaders outside to prevent men who are starving from accepting a wage of 50/- a week for work which is going to relieve unemployment, I say it is a very cruel policy, and it is a policy which, to my mind, is not in the best interests of Labour itself.  I would like to ask Deputy Corish does he seriously consider that the Minister for Local Government ought to put up one and a quarter millions of public money <Col N="1867" /> and make no condition.  Does he say that the Minister should hand the money out <i>carte blanche</i> to local bodies throughout the country to spend at their own sweet will?  If that is his contention, I must say that I, for one, am in complete and honest disagreement with him.  I think if the Local Government Minister did anything of the sort there would, undoubtedly, be an epidemic of extravagance, and there are not lacking reasons to support that contention.</P>
    <P>The Deputy has accused the Minister of conspiring to reduce wages.  I think he would be putting his grievance in a little truer form if he said that he was really disappointed the Minister did not give this money to local bodies in order that wherever they had a majority they could use it for the purpose of increasing wages.  That, at any rate, is my humble interpretation of what was at the back of the Deputy's mind.  A good deal has been said from time to time about the question of a living wage. There is a great difference of opinion, not only amongst members of the Labour Party in the Dáil, but responsible Labour leaders outside, as to what is a living wage.  Sometime ago, Deputy Morrissey, in referring to road wages, mentioned scales which were obtaining in different parts of the country. He told us wages ran in various districts from 28/- to 40/-.  I forget whether he went any further than that. I can give him an instance where there is a wage of 50/- being paid to people in an agricultural district for working on the roads.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it too much?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>If Deputy Johnson will define for me what is a living wage&mdash;if it is within the bounds of his capacity to do that&mdash;I might express an opinion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy quotes it.  Does he quote it as being too much?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I quote it as being too much in certain districts.  I do not say it is too much everywhere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>For my own information, I would like the Deputy to give me the name of the agricultural district where that wage is being paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1868" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is Tullamore&mdash;my own town.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not an agricultural district.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a town in the middle of an agricultural district, and that is as near as I can go to a definition of what is an agricultural district.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand the wages paid there are 45/-a week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Deputy say why is a wage of 36/- paid in other districts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not a walking encyclopedia, Deputy Lyons.  I am quite willing to discuss this matter on the merits on some other occasion.</P>
      <P>As I interpret the directions given by the Minister for the expenditure of this Grant, I think I am correct in stating that he has laid it down that the rate of wages shall be the rate of the agricultural wages in the district where the money is being spent.  I put it, in all fairness, to Deputies on the other side&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. EVERETT Mr. EVERETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EVERETT</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, that is not correct.  No such order has been issued to public boards, that the agricultural rate must be paid on the roads.  It is a lesser rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I withdraw the word &ldquo;must,&rdquo; if I said it, but in any case my interpretation of the instructions given by the Minister for Local Government in the circular is that the wages should not exceed the rate of agricultural wages in the district.  I do not want to exaggerate the matter at all.  In view of the fact that a great number of agricultural labourers are working for a definite wage for definite productive work, is it a very extraordinary thing for the Minister to suggest that in the case of a huge sum of money which he is producing out of the pockets of the people to relieve distress and unemployment, that the same rate should be paid?  I submit that his position is perfectly fair, perfectly just, and perfectly honest.  I do not think that anyone can have a legitimate grievance when a large sum of public money is being produced to relieve distress, and <Col N="1869" /> the condition made is that the rate of wages should not exceed the rate of agricultural wages ruling in the district. Deputy Corish would appear to have a very strong confidence in the powers of local bodies to administer these grants in justice to the ratepayers. I am sorry that my experience does not bring that conviction to my mind.  In the town of Tullamore, which I come from, and which is a fairly important industrial district&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought it was an agricultural district a few moments ago?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I am discussing a different matter now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be better if Deputies would refrain from interrupting Deputy Egan, because an ample opportunity will be given to reply to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is quite evident that I am beginning to search their economic conscience.  In the town of Tullamore, which, as I have said, is a fairly important industrial district, as Deputy Davin knows, we have a highly organised branch of a workers' body known as the Irish Transport and General Workers' Union, with which I am very familiar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a very familiar name.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very familiar to me, I can assure you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>You are not a member?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Some time ago we had a little difference of opinion as to the correct wages that ought to be paid in the district, and as a result of very many interviews, and a good deal of pain and grief and so forth, we finally succeeded in getting a rate of wages fixed for the whole district, and an agreement signed, sealed and delivered, by the employers and by the responsible leaders of the Transport Union, backed up, as well, by representatives from headquarters in Dublin, and the rate of wages for unskilled labourers was fixed at 44s. a week.  As I have said, labour is highly organised in Tullamore.  I happen to be Chairman of the Urban <Col N="1870" /> Council, and the labourers at the moment, and for some time past, have had a majority on their Council.  The rate of wages in Tullamore was 50s. a week at the peak, and the Urban Council insisted on preserving that 50s. rate, notwithstanding that their own Union had signed, sealed and delivered an agreement that 44s. was a fair rate and that they agreed to it.  That is the sort of evidence which certainly does not carry any conviction to my mind that these grants for the relief of unemployment would be administered to the best advantage if they were given over to these bodies.</P>
      <P>Deputy Colohan referred to surveyors. I agree with the Deputy in almost everything he said on that particular topic.  I think undoubtedly some of these surveyors at times do take up a very high-handed and autocratic attitude. I was up against that position myself on one occasion as chairman of the urban council.  It was a case where the whole council, including myself, were unanimous in trying to get rid of a certain official, and it took us about two years to do it.  I am quite in agreement with Deputy Colohan when he says that the surveyors want gingering up.  I believe possibly we all want gingering up at times, but at the same time I would like to put in a good word for the unfortunate surveyor.  In the Offaly County Council some time ago a surveyor, in the legitimate exercise of his discretion, dismissed a man who was supposed to be at work, whose name had been returned as being at work, and whom he found in a house some miles distant from his work.  I cannot say how long this had been going on, but the surveyor having dismissed him, an immediate meeting of the council was called by the people interested in labour, and the surveyor was told that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Deputy is travelling outside the terms of the Motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I was doing my humble best to defend the Minister for Local Government.  However, in deference to you I will try to keep as much to the point as possible.  The Minister has other difficulties.  Not only are <Col N="1871" /> there difficulties inside the councils, but sometimes a considerable amount of pressure is brought to bear from outside the councils to direct their actions. I see our genial friend and Deputy, Deputy Lyons here, fresh from his experience in the Westmeath County Council&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation I will tell you something about that later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Lyons a short time ago, in order to give more vigorous expression to his convictions, entered the Westmeath County Council, divested himself of some of his raiment, and proceeded to bring physical arguments to bear on the council's deliberations&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is the Deputy aware that I am a member of the Westmeath County Council?  I did not enter it.  I am entitled to be there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>If you did not enter it, I do not know how you got there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not enter it as a member of a deputation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidHall" hpid="Mr. HALL Mr. HALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HALL</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is Deputy Egan in order in discussing the action of Deputy Lyons at a particular county council?  I thought we were discussing the functions of the Minister for Local Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It has a bearing on the wages rates suggested by the Ministry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to know, without pretending in the least to defend Deputy Lyons, who, I am sure, is pretty well able to defend himself, if we are dealing with facts or Press reports?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>If Deputy Davin wants to know the source of my information, it is what Deputy Lyons told me himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWalterShaw" hpid="Mr. SHAW Mr. SHAW">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SHAW</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation, if any evidence is required I can give evidence, because I was present at the meeting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1872" />
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be better to allow Deputy Egan to proceed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I congratulate Deputy Shaw on having recovered from the effects of that meeting.  I do not want to delay the Dáil in mentioning this little incident, engineered by our genial friend Deputy Lyons, but I want to point out some of the difficulties that the Minister for Local Government has to contend with in securing that this grant, or any similar grant which he gives, will be properly administered. I would like to say a few words on the general economic situation.  As far as I can make out and understand the policy of the Labour Party, it appears to be one of high wages at all costs.  I will not put it any stronger than that&mdash; high wages, and let the consequences be consigned to all manner of warm regions.  I submit that that appears to be a policy of high wages for the few, and a big unemployed list.  I can assure Deputy Corish and others&mdash;and I am making this statement with every sense of responsibility and in all honesty, that the present economic situation of the country is really very serious.  Enterprise is being absolutely choked off.  I, as a business man, and I venture to say that I will be supported by numerous other business men, know for an undoubted fact that capital is becoming very shy.  Capital is afraid to invest itself, and I honestly believe that if there is not a little more resiliency on the part of Deputy Johnson and his supporters, the ultimate economic consequences will be very serious.  Capital is leaving the country. We have gone through a very severe crisis.  We cannot afford the luxuries which a rich country like England can afford.  Deputies have only got to refer to this much-maligned Fiscal Report to find a comparison of the wages in Ireland and those paid in England in similar trades, and they will find that in a great many cases Ireland, a poverty-stricken country is paying an infinitely higher rate of wages than wealthy England.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I submit, in all fairness, reason, and logic, that is a position that cannot be maintained if our whole economic structure is not to be shattered.  Take <Col N="1873" /> the case of Cork.  I do not suppose that my information, speaking at the moment, is absolutely stop-press, but you had an extraordinary state of affairs in Cork some time ago.  An employer in Cork could get a skilled mechanic over from England and pay him 56/- per week, plus his travelling expenses, and the gentleman who stood at the bottom of the ladder, passed him up his blow-lamp or his screw-wrench, or held nails for him, received more.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, are we discussing the general economic situation, or the supposed functions of the Local Government Department?  I think this particular thing prejudices the minds of Deputies against my motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should confine himself to the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely there is no other way of justifying economy by my Department than by taking into consideration the general economic conditions, and if we cannot do that it will be impossible for me to defend my position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>If we can be guaranteed the right to discuss the economic situation at all stages of the debate I would be satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot go into all these matters under the motion before us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit it is an entirely different thing to discuss the general economic situation from discussing the economic situation as seen from the angle of the employers, and that is what we are listening to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. EGAN Mr. EGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, I bow to your ruling.  I assure Deputy Corish and every Deputy on the Labour Benches that anything I have said is said not from the employers' point of view, but because it is my honest and sincere conviction. Seeing that I have been choked off so frequently, I am afraid that the general trend of my thoughts has been somewhat disarranged, but I submit, with great respect to Deputy Corish and the other Deputies who support him in attacking the Ministry, that not <Col N="1874" /> only is the Minister amply and fully justified in the arrangements he has made in expending this enormous sum of money, but further that he would be false to his trust as the custodian of the interests of the people if he did anything else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree with the terms of this motion.  To my mind, it is a vote of censure upon a Minister who is not really responsible for the action causing the grievances against which this motion is brought forward as a protest.  Take, for example, the grievance of the amalgamation of Unions which was started in 1920.  The President of the Local Government Department then was not the present Minister at all, and I do not see how he can be held responsible for any want of facilities felt by the people owing to amalgamation.  There are lots of actions on the part of the Local Government Department that the present Minister has had nothing to do with at all.  Now, for the moment, let me dwell upon the amalgamation of Unions, started in 1920.  At that time the President of the Executive Council was President of the Local Government Department, and not the present Minister. It must be remembered that at this period it was very hard to get a quorum of the public boards to come together. For the purpose of appointing members to the County Homes, people were met on the street and asked to act as members of the County Home Committees. These people have acted ever since, and this whole grievance can only be remedied by holding elections for those bodies, so that the people selected to represent the local bodies on the County Home Committees will not be people who were simply selected in the street.  I cannot see how the present Minister for Local Government can be held responsible for this particular item of amalgamation.  I have been told that amalgamation is a huge saving to the Saorstát.  Amalgamation, to my mind, has not alone penalised the old and infirm, but it has closed down several district hospitals, with the result that the patients have to be taken now from 20 to 30 miles, and in some cases patients have died upon the journey. The town of Athlone has a district <Col N="1875" /> hospital, but if a person who cannot afford to pay gets sick, that person has to be moved to Mullingar, a distance of 30 statute miles, or if the person lives on the far side of Athlone, he has to be removed to Roscommon.  We were told that we had last year a saving of £9,000 in the local administration of that Committee, and we were told early this year that there is a saving of £8,000; that is, a saving in the two years of £17,000.  I find from the estimates that the Poor Law charges in 1921 amounted to £34,000.  That includes all the Poor Law charges of the county, but I find that the Poor Law charge for the present year, 1924, is £34,300.  Superannuation in 1921 in the Westmeath Co. Council was £27, but the superannuation to be paid now will be £2,700.  That is an increase of £2,900, in place of a decrease of £17,000 as we were told.</P>
      <P>I would welcome a motion condemning the amalgamation system, but I will not vote in favour of a motion condemning the child for the sins of the father.  That is exactly what is done by this motion&mdash;it condemns the present Minister for Local Government for the action of the previous Minister.  Deputy McGoldrick mentioned that it would not be right to give the County Councils the opportunity of fixing the rate of wages to be paid out of the Government grant.  I wonder did Deputy McGoldrick know exactly the position of some of those County Councils who waited for years until they found a victim in the present Minister. They come in now under the cloak of anxiety for a certain level of economy when they had not the courage to come forward themselves and introduce this motion.  They go for the Minister of Local Government and they flock in to try to get another occasional kick at him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestHAlton" hpid="Mr. ALTON Mr. ALTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ALTON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy explain this mysterious action?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>The meaning of the mystery is this: these Councils which would not or did not recognise this Government acting through this Dáil waited until the Government sent out a letter of economy and they flock in, <Col N="1876" /> welded together, both Free State and Republicans, to fight for a reduction of wages.  Some of the Deputies on the Labour Benches may not agree that it is necessary for every unemployed man in the Saorstát to find employment. The mover of this motion has already explained that he is quite satisfied that every demobilised man from the National army should find employment at a living wage; we have been asked on several occasions what is a living wage.  As I am not acting officially with the Labour Party, I will leave to some official Labour Party man to answer that question.  Is the Minister for Local Government responsible for the reduction of wages that has taken place at the present time?  Now, under the grant the wage laid down would not be sufficient to keep two people, let alone a family.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Anybody who reads the history of his own country will find that after the famine people had to work for 4d. a day.  That was what they got to go out and work and earn a living.  I presume that you would get as much for fourpence at that time as you would for the four-and-sixpence which is being given now.  I hold that we should look to the men who have been in regular employment, and I am of opinion that the circular letter sent out by the Minister for Local Government did not compel any county council to reduce the wages of the permanent or regular workers by 13s. a week.  The circular stated that 30s. a week was to be paid under the grant, but the members took advantage of that circular and they reduced the workers' wages by 13s. a week.  The idea was that for the people who were employed, as well as for the unemployed, there should be a flat rate of 32s. a week.  That is why the scene occurred at the Westmeath County Council meeting.  I was not present in the Dáil yesterday, but reading the newspaper reports this morning I saw that the Acting Ceann Comhairle called Deputy McKenna to order for referring to the scene at the Westmeath County Council meeting and told him that the Minister was not responsible for that scene.  I would like to say that, in my opinion, the Minister was primarily responsible owing to the letter that had been circulated <Col N="1877" /> from his Department and sent to the different Councils, and especially to the Westmeath County Council.  The circular was sent by the Minister for Local Government, or perhaps it would be more correct to say by his staff.  The old staff is there still, and I think the Minister ought to get them weeded out. As I say, the old staff is there still, and until the Minister succeeds in getting shut of these old aristocrats, these fellows who, I believe, have been there for twenty or thirty years and who were there during the hard times, he will have to put up with a lot of the abuse he is getting.  It was through that letter from the Minister for Local Government that this scene occurred at the Westmeath County Council, and it was owing to that letter that I took off my coat without offering any challenge or offence to anyone.  I am quite prepared&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. EVERETT Mr. EVERETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EVERETT</NameTxt>
      <P>To do the same thing again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, in a good cause, but not in support of this motion.  The Minister for Local Government, since he came into office has, in my opinion, done more good by one little turn than all the actions put together of the previous Ministers, and that little turn was the letter he sent down to the different county health and home committees, asking them to appoint inspectors. There are two inspectors appointed at £250 a year in Westmeath.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Prior to amalgamation we had nine relieving officers, as they were called then.  Now we call them inspectors of home health.  These nine officers were, of course, dismissed.  They were in receipt of about £60 a year for acting and working, and at present they are in receipt of about £62 a year superannuation. With the additional officers appointed for the purpose of distributing home health these positions involve a sum of about £500, and now we must appoint another superintendent to watch these two inspectors.  I can assure the Dáil that they want watching. Their duties are not carried out, and that is why I say that it was one of the best actions that had been authorised by the Minister when he appointed that inspector.  I would ask the <Col N="1878" /> Minister as soon as possible to try and have an election of public bodies&mdash; county councils, district councils and urban councils.  I do not believe that the district councils are going to be abolished.  I do not mind what any Minister says.  The voice of the people will prevail, and surely the people will not cry in the wilderness.  They want these councils to remain, and I presume that they shall remain.  I think that the proposal to abolish district councils was like that to abolish the workhouses, and was mainly for the purpose of creating jobs.  Deputy Egan gave us a very illuminating address concerning capital, and said that it was too shy.  In Westmeath and Longford capital is shy at the modesty of the workers.  These poor workers are so patient and kindhearted that they will not even dare to look at capital straight in the face.  It is just like the case, a long time ago, when eggs were at 5s. a dozen, no one dared look at a hen straight in the face. It is the same with us, and that is why capital is shy, but if capital lost some of its shyness, and put its pride under its feet, and released money for the purpose of industry and employment, it would suit it better.  I think it was Deputy McKenna who dwelt yesterday upon the scene in Westmeath County Council, and he asked whether it was fair or constitutional that a body of men should attack a public body, assembled to carry out its duties.  I would like to ask the Minister for Local Government whether that public body should attack the workers by trying to reduce their wages by 13s. a week.  If the workers have a right to live in the country they surely have a right to adopt the best means in their power to get a decent wage.  There was no red flag used at the council meeting.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A LABOUR DEPUTY A LABOUR DEPUTY">
      <NameTxt>A LABOUR DEPUTY</NameTxt>
      <P>Shame!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcKenna" hpid="Mr. McKENNA Mr. McKENNA">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McKENNA</NameTxt>
      <P>Labour snatched it from your hands at the last election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but I think I snatched it back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot go further into the matter of the scene at the County Council meeting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1879" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going further into it because every time I think of it it reminds me of the old cock-fighting days in Tipperary.  I want to put a few suggestions to the Minister for Local Government concerning the old and infirm who are in receipt of home help. At first, home help was sent out once a fortnight, but now it is sent by post once a month.  Those poor people should have a few shillings given them at least once a week.  It has been proved in Westmeath that the administration of home help is very inefficient, and costs in stationery alone about £500 a year.  If that is so it would be much better for the Minister for Local Government to make those inspectors distribute the home help themselves. They are being paid for it.  It is a terrible thing to see poor people waiting and not being paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWalterShaw" hpid="Mr. SHAW Mr. SHAW">
      <NameTxt>Mr. SHAW</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the statement of Deputy Lyons is not correct.  They are paid every fortnight.  There was a slight delay&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy cannot make a speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>The order of the Committee is that the home help should be sent out once a fortnight to towns and once a month to country districts. Deputy Egan mentioned that 50s. a week would be the rate.  It may be the rate for the town of Tullamore, as it was for Athlone, but it was not the rate paid by the County Council of Offaly to the workers on the roads.  In the County Council the highest rate paid is 36s.  In Westmeath the rate is 45s. But 45s. meant 22s. 6d. and 36s. meant less in Offaly because those men never got constant employment.  The members of the Council were so generous to their workers and they tried to assist them so much that they reduced their wage by 13s., telling them that they would get full time.  Strange to say, since wages have been reduced they are working not at 22s. 6d., but at 16s. They are still on part time in Westmeath. They are on strike at present. I hope the Minister for Local Government will take into account the administration of this home help to the old people.  I do not hold the Minister responsible.  He is not very long in office and he has done, not indeed wonders, <Col N="1880" /> but at least something that he can look back on and say that there is some of his work there at least.  Are we quite sure that the Minister thought the plan of 28s. a week out of his own head?  It may be possible that his colleagues on the Government Benches are associated in the suggestion.  One sure fact is that, no matter who invented the idea of this reduction of wages, the present Minister for Local Government, no matter who dances, will have to pay for the tune.  If this motion goes to a division I shall vote against it.  A motion put forward condemning the action of the Government would be a vote of censure on the Government.  As a whole I would not vote for such a motion, because I am of the opinion, and Deputies on the Labour Benches know, that the Government have carried on in the hardest of times.  Some of the members on the Labour Benches have delivered speeches here doing credit to the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing the Government. We are only discussing the Minister for Local Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>For that purpose I do not see why we should alter our opinion now, and if the Minister for Local Government had the courage to accept that office in the hardest of times I think it is our duty as a whole to support him in any honest methods he brings forward.  I do not agree, however, with the circular he sent round, and if this motion was for the purpose of voting against the party instrumental in having that circular sent out I would vote for it.  As the motion is against the Minister for Local Government personally, I will vote against it if it goes to a division.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that I cannot undertake to entertain the Dáil in the admirable manner in which it has been entertained by the last Deputy.  Deputies who have been speaking are in most cases Deputies who have had long experience of local administration.  On that account perhaps my point of view may be interesting, because it is the point of view of an individual who never sat upon a <Col N="1881" /> local Board, and perhaps never will sit upon a local Board, and who can therefore, give an outside point of view.  I think it takes a certain amount of moral courage to get up and speak on this matter; because I have noticed in the past that as soon as any Deputy got up and cast the slightest aspersion upon local administration, there were certain Deputies who regarded it almost as a matter of personal honour, immediately to get up to support the rights and dignities of the local boards.  There is one important matter to which I would like to call the attention the Minister for Local Government, and that is that the present Councils have long outstayed their welcome.  Their period of power expired in June last year, and they have been kept on since by Statute. There is a feeling in the country that these Councils, elected in a time of stress, and elected almost altogether on a political basis, do not represent the people at present and should not be allowed to control local government, expend money, and make permanent appointments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>resumed the Chair at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the principal objection to the administration of local boards is the reckless extravagance that has been going on.  That extravagance applies not alone to the question of workers' wages, but to salaries and general expenditure all round.  There was a return made to the Dáil a short time ago showing the salaries of Secretaries of Co. Councils. One of the highest in that return was a salary of £1,700 for a Secretary of a County Council in one of the poorest counties in Ireland.  It is only right and fair that if by means of this Circular Letter, which we have heard so much about, the wages of the road workers are to be reduced, at the same time steps should be taken whereby the salaries of officials would be reduced. What is sauce for the goose is sauce for the gander.  It is only right, if the wages of workers must be reduced, owing to the exigencies of the times, that the salaries of officials should also be reduced.  There is another matter which we in the Farmers' Party feel <Col N="1882" /> a certain amount of grievance in regard to, and that is the incidence of rates. We are called upon to pay rates which we believe are altogether in excess of the requirements of the situation, and beyond our ability to pay.  We are obliged at present to pay for the upkeep of main and trunk roads which are mainly used by the traders in the towns for the purpose of conveying goods by means of heavy wagons which cut the roads to pieces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister for Local Government responsible?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think his administration should be able to rectify it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid we cannot go into a discussion of local administration.  We are discussing the policy of the Minister, or we ought to be discussing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Does not the policy of the Minister affect local administration?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy wants to argue that he can go into every question of local administration, he certainly cannot.  Would it not require a Statute to make this change?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry the Ceann Comhairle was not here a while ago, because we went into the most extraordinary questions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not responsible for that.  We will have either to approve or disapprove of what the Minister is doing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I disapprove. I would like to refer to the matter of amalgamation.  I regard this matter as being to a large extent in an experimental stage at present.  I think it is very doubtful if it is going to work out as an economy.  One of the unfortunate features of it is the number of officials superannuated and the number of officials appointed to hold new positions. That means that we are now building up a large superannuation fund and at the same time paying fresh officials.  I think it would be only right when these schemes were brought in <Col N="1883" /> that a definite arrangement should have been made whereby the former officials should have been appointed to the new positions, and not have Boards of Health issuing advertisements for new officials at somewhat extravagant salaries, while the former officials, who are comparatively young men, are drawing high superannuation.  What I would like to express to the Minister is that the farming community, which is mainly responsible for the financing of local government administration, is now in dire stress, and that the local boards will very soon find that they will not be able to collect the rates which they are levying.</P>
      <P>I would like to remind the Dáil that it is not only the rich farmers who have to pay those rates, but also the very smallest farmers, and at the present time they find these rates an intolerable burden.  There are cases in some counties where farmers with a valuation of £20 have to pay as much as £15 in rates, in the third of extremely bad years from the agricultural point of view.  I would be inclined to forecast that the boards at present in existence have not got the confidence of the people.  If they strike rates this year that are beyond the capacity of the people to pay, they will find that they will not be able to collect them.  No Bills or special Statutes introduced here would have the effect of forcing farmers to pay rates that are beyond their resources.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>More red flag work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the debate until Wednesday.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ADJOURNMENT. - CO. CLARE" RHead="OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM">
    <Title>ADJOURNMENT. - CO. CLARE OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the Dáil until Tuesday at 3 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. CONNOR HOGAN Mr. CONNOR HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CONNOR HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I gave notice that I would raise on the adjournment <Col N="1884" /> a question about the refusal of the Ministry of Local Government to continue the payment of an old age pension to Mr. Lynch, of Querrin, Lisdeen, Co. Clare, who has already enjoyed it for 15 years.  I do so, not alone to draw particular attention to this individual case, but to get an expression of opinion from the responsible Ministers as to their policy with regard to kindred cases and its application to farmers similarly situated to this man.  It appears that he has been in receipt of the pension for something like 15 years.  He assigned his land, to come within the terms of the Act.  I do not want to say much on the morality of the thing, but in any case it has been legalised, and his position is quite clear up to the present. On the strength of that presumably he was allowed certain freedom.  I am informed the freedom he was allowed was a room in the house, sufficient turf for a fire, milk, £5 a year, and the use of a jennet.  In a reply by the Minister for Finance on behalf of the Minister for Local Government, I was told that in this case he had estimated the value of the claimant's maintenance on the son's farm exceeded £49 17s. 6d. yearly, and that it debarred him from the receipt of the pension; that the extent of the holding is 42 acres, the valuation is £16 13s., and the rent or annuity £12.  From my knowledge of farming, when I see a holding of 42 acres, the valuation of which is only £16.  I am forced to the conclusion that it is necessarily bad land and very difficult to make a living on.  I am forced to the conclusion that £2 a week is the greatest productive capacity of that farm, even if the produce is sold under the most favourable circumstances. On that the family of the present owner, consisting, I understand, of 10 or 12 persons, have to be maintained. We certainly sympathise with the Ministry in endeavouring to bring down expenses, and to rigidly apply the Old Age Pensions Act, but in this case, where the claimant received 5/- originally, and later 10/-, I do not see why, at this stage he should be deprived altogether of the pension.  By all means reduce it proportionately.  Even in the hey-day of war prices the man evidently got the full pension.  I feel that <Col N="1885" /> it is necessary the Minister should state his attitude towards farmers who assigned their land on the strength of the Old Age Pensions Act to their sons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. Burke) MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. Burke)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not quite clear as to what Deputy Connor Hogan is driving at.  If this farm was assigned <Col N="1886" /> on the strength of getting the old age pension, the man would not be entitled to anything.  It does not make any difference at all, so long as the farm is in the family, whether it belongs to the old man or to any member of his family.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 4.4 p.m. until Tuesday, the 11th March.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT CLAIM">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT CLAIM.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnButler" hpid="SEAN BUITLEIR SEAN BUITLEIR">
      <NameTxt>SEAN BUITLEIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state what are the reasons for disallowing Unemployment Benefit to Michael Goulding, No. 19 New Lane, Waterford, and, further, whether he will reconsider his decision in this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1817" />
    <Speaker pid="JosephMcGrath" hpid="MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. J. McGrath) Joseph McGrath">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for INDUSTRY and COMMERCE (Mr. J. McGrath)</NameTxt>
      <P>Michael Goulding claimed Unemployment Benefit at the Waterford Employment Exchange on the 21st January last.  Reference to his account with the Unemployment Fund showed that the only contributions paid for him were as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>3 in the 1920-21 Insurance Year.</P>
      <P>4 in the 1921-22 Insurance Year.</P>
      <P>None in the 1922-23 Insurance Year.</P>
      <P>9 in the 1923-24 Insurance Year.</P>
      <P>As, therefore, no contributions had been paid for him in the 1922-23 Insurance Year, he was disqualified for the receipt of Unemployment Benefit by sub-section 4 of Section 8 of the Act of 1920.  He is not entitled to the contributions payable under Section 7 of the Act of 1923 for men who have served in the Army, because less than 10 contributions had been paid for him prior to the date of his enlistment in the National Army.  It is regretted, therefore, that his claim could not be allowed.  The disqualification lasts until 12 contributions have been paid for him, exclusive of those paid up to the end of the 1921-22 Insurance Year.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - INCOME" RHead="AND CORPORATION PROFITS TAX">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - INCOME AND CORPORATION PROFITS TAX.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredORahilly" hpid="AILFRID O RATHAILE AILFRID O RATHAILE">
      <NameTxt>AILFRID O RATHAILE</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he is aware (1) that distraints are being widely enforced for the non-payment of arrears of Income Tax, Corporation Profits Tax, and Excess Profits Duty, such arrars relating ten years prior to the financial year 1922/'23; (2) that first and additional assessments are now being made in respect of Income Tax and Corporation Profits Tax for years prior to 1922/'23, and for Excess Profits Duty for years prior to 1920; and that Inspectors of Taxes and the various Collectors are not alone pressing for the payment of these arrears so assessed, but are also asking for the infliction of penalties by the Appeal Commissioners by reason of the taxpayers' delay in disclosing sources of income to the British Government during the years to which these now made first and additional assessments apply; <Col N="1818" /> if he will state under what legal authority arrears are collectable; if these arrears are to be accounted for or paid over to England when collected or otherwise; if these arrears when collected are to become the absolute property of the Free State Exchequer without set-off, accounting or payment of their amount, either now or at any future time to England under the Treaty Article 74, or otherwise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. E. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. E. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>srd</P>
      <P>(1)  I am aware that distraints for arrears of Income Tax are being widely enforced.  While no cases involving Corporation Profits Tax, Excess Profits Duty or Income Tax covering so great a period as ten years prior to the financial year 1922-23 have come to my notice, the powers of recovery must be used without regard to the period covered by the arrears.</P>
      <P>(2)  Regarding the assessments referred to in the question, these will continue to be made where the circumstances require and permit of such assessments being legally made.  On the question of penalties, the attitude of the Revenue Commissioners has been fully set out in the notices which appeared in Irish newspapers on the 2nd August, 1923, and towards the end of October, 1923.  Where taxpayers have assisted the Revenue Commissioners by voluntary disclosure, within a reasonable time, of sources of income previously undisclosed, the Commissioners are prepared to waive the penalties. Where disclosure is not voluntary the Commissioners cannot grant the same consideration as in the case of a voluntary disclosure.</P>
      <P>(3)  The legal authority for collecting arrears is contained in Section 1, sub-sections (1) and (2) of the Irish Free State Agreement Act, 1922, paragraph 2 (ii) of the Order in Council, dated 1st April, 1922, and the Irish Free State Constitution Act, 1922 (Clause 80 of the Constitution).</P>
      <P>(4)  The answer to this is in the negative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(5)  The arrears become the absolute property of the Saorstát Exchequer. The reference to Article 74 of the Treaty is not understood, but the question <Col N="1819" /> of a set-off of the arrears does not arise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - ARMS SEIZED" RHead="(QUESTION OF COMPENSATION)">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - ARMS SEIZED (QUESTION OF COMPENSATION).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received an application from Edward Davin, Clonmeen, Errill, Ballybrophy, Leix, for return or compensation for loss of a gun (value £15), taken from him by members of the Irish Republican Army in February, 1920; if he is in a position to trace it, and if he will return it or compensate the owner for loss of same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mr. Davin's application has been received.  It has not yet been possible to trace his gun, but further efforts to find it are being made. The general question as to a claim of the kind for compensation has yet to get consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS." RHead="- BICYCLE SEIZED">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - BICYCLE SEIZED.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that a Raleigh bicycle (value £12 10s.) was taken from Joseph Kelly, Ballinakill, Leix, by members of the National Army stationed at Abbeyleix, on July 6th, 1922; whether he has received repeated applications from the owner for the return of the machine, or compensation for loss of same, and if he can now state the decision of the Ministry in connection with this claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Applications have been received from Mr. Kelly. The matter is now under local investigation, and an early decision will be given.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - CLAIM FOR PLUMBING" RHead="AND GASFITTING (PORTLAOIGHISE.)">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - CLAIM FOR PLUMBING AND GASFITTING (PORTLAOIGHISE.)</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received several applications from Patrick Cavanagh, Borris Road, Portlaoighise, Leix, for payment of an amount of £43 4s., representing charges for plumbing and gasfitting work done at Military Barracks between February 1st, 1923, and June 2nd, 1923, and if he can state when he will be in a position to pay this amount, which is so long overdue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1820" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>A claim for £43 6s. was recently received at Headquarters. Mr. Cavanagh has been requested to furnish certain details.  On their receipt the claim will be settled as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS." RHead="- LEIX ACCOUNTS">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - LEIX ACCOUNTS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received repeated applications from Patrick Gorman, bootmaker, Chapel Street, Rathdowney, Leix, for payment of an account of £2 10s. 6d., representing charges for work done for members of the National Army stationed at the Bank, Rathdowney, in June, 1922, and if he will expedite payment of the amount due.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>No claim has been received at Headquarters from Mr. Gorman.  Enquiries are now, however, being made with a view to early settlement of any outstanding account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received several applications from James Ryan, The Square, Rathdowney, Leix, for payment of an amount of £21 5s. 10d., representing charges for goods supplied to the local garrison of the National Army over twelve months ago, and if he can now state when he will be in a position to pay the amount due.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Of the amount of £21 5s. 10d referred to, a cheque for £1 11s. 6d. was issued on the 18th October last, but on inquiry it is found that the cheque was not presented to the Bank.  This cheque is being cancelled, and, pending investigation, a cheque for the balance of the account was issued yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="DEPENDENTS' ALLOWANCES">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DEPENDENTS' ALLOWANCES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received an application for dependents' allowance on behalf of Volunteer A. Holohan, Stradbally, Leix, who attested 20th April, 1922, and if he can now state when it is proposed to give a decision in his case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>An application <Col N="1821" /> for dependents' allowance in respect of Private Holohan has been received. Mrs. Holohan was notified on 15th November, 1922, that her claim had been disallowed.  It was rejected on the ground that the amount normally contributed by her son to his home over and above the cost of his own maintenance therein for a reasonable period prior to enlistment was less than the minimum required by the regulations, 12s. per week, before an allowance might be issued.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnButler" hpid="SEAN BUITLEIR SEAN BUITLEIR">
      <NameTxt>SEAN BUITLEIR</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that two weeks' dependents' allowance, amounting to £5 12s., due to Margaret Hennessey, 25 Smith's Lane, Waterford, on November 24th, 1923, is not yet paid, and whether instructions will be given to expedite payment of this amount.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>A cheque for the amount was sent to Mrs. Hennessy on the 1st instant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA">
      <NameTxt>DOMHNALL O MUIRGHEASA</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he is aware that a sum of three pounds, balance of dependents' allowance, is due to Mrs. Mary O'Brien, Claim No. 3226.  Grace's Street, Nenagh, and if he will arrange to have this amount paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that any money is due to Mrs. O'Brien in respect of dependents' allowance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received several applications for dependents' allowance on behalf of Edward Flanagan (4698), Raheen, Clara, Offaly, who joined the National Army in April, 1923, and is now serving at the Curragh, and if he can state when a decision will be given in this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>An application was received from Mrs. Flanagan on the 17th December, 1923.  She was informed on the 15th February, 1924, that the claim had been disallowed.  It was rejected after due investigation on the ground that the amount normally <Col N="1822" /> contributed by her son to his home over and above the cost of his own maintenance therein for a reasonable period prior to enlistment, was less than the minimum required by the regulations, 12s. per week, before an allowance might be issued.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS." RHead="- GUN TAKEN">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - GUN TAKEN.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence if he has received repeated applications from J. Colgan, Stradbally, Leix, for return of a gun (value £25) taken from him by members of the Irish Republican Army at Stradbally, on December 26th, 1921, and if he is now in a position to trace and return the gun to its owner, or compensate him for loss of same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mr. Colgan's applications have been received.  It has not yet been possible to trace his gun, but further efforts to find it are being made.  The general question as to whether a claim of this kind for compensation has yet to get consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="AN OFFALY ARREST">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - AN OFFALY ARREST.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that William Pigott, 11 Davitt Street, Tullamore, Offaly, was arrested in August, 1922, and is still detained at Hut No. 1, Camp No. 2, Tintown, and if he is prepared to order the release of this prisoner, or state the reasons why he is being detained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>It is intended at present to continue the detention of Mr. Pigott for considerations of public safety.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>