<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="14" Month="Dec" Year="1967" Vol="64" No="7" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 14 Nollaig 1967" DateEnglish="Thursday, 14 December 1967" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="499">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="499" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take No. 1 on the Order Paper and, with the approval of the House, it is hoped that the Minister might get in to reply not later than 4 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald to speak at 3 o'clock?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>0</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The House would want to get agreement.  The agreement is that Senator FitzGerald will get an opportunity to speak at 3 p.m., the Minister to conclude at 4 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Greek Government Crisis:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Greek Government Crisis: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like with your permission to say that in view of the regrettable rejection by the Greek Government of the constitutional authority of the King and what appears to be the temporary failure of the attempt to restore some form of democratic government in Greece, the sponsors of the motion on Greece are with regret withdrawing it from the Order Paper.</P>
      <P>We are, nevertheless, glad that an opportunity occurs to express the concern of Members of this House, which we believe is shared by all sides of the House, for the democratic forces in Greece suppressed by the present regime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad that Senator FitzGerald had the sense to withdraw that motion because it was obvious from the start that it was a foolish motion, since we had very little information of what was happening in Greece and we could not afford the time to debate it here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I still give <Col N="500" /> credit to people on all sides of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order. Should we not begin by defending democratic practice here?  Surely all this is out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion is withdrawn from the Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appropriation Bill, 1967 (Certified Money Bill):" RHead="Second Stage (Resumed) and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Appropriation Bill, 1967    (Certified Money Bill):    Second Stage (Resumed) and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>When we adjourned last night I was pointing out that the estimated rise this year in national income has been more than double the estimated average for the OECD countries in Europe this year.  I was pointing out also the extraordinarily large increase in the last 12 months for which we have figures (up to July last), an increase of some 20 per cent over the previous period, which compares more than favourably with an estimated increase of some 8 per cent for the countries of the OECD in Europe.  We have, in fact, been increasing our national income and our exports at a very much more rapid rate than Europe as a whole.  The most startling increase that has taken place in the past year or so is in exports of industrial goods which are up by almost one-third &mdash;a very big increase, coming in a single year.</P>
      <P>As a result of these increased exports, output in industry has increased so far this year according to the figures available to us.  In the 12 months ended July, 1967, which is the most recent 12 months for which figures seem to be available, the increase in the output of Irish industry is 14.9 per cent.  This is in startling contrast to the output of other countries in Europe.  In OECD Europe, that is, all the countries of Western Europe, the position in regard to their industry in the same 12-month period shows an overall decline of 0.2 per cent in industrial production: in EEC countries, also, there was a decline of .4 per cent. Britain has a somewhat larger decline of 1.5 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are, in fact, increasing our industrial production at a time when Europe <Col N="501" /> and the world at large are going through a period when the output of industry is tending to decline or, at least, to remain static.  If we examine the output of most European countries in the 12 months ended July, 1967, we shall see that the figure for Ireland is more than twice as high as that of any other country except Italy which shows an increase of eight per cent.  The Irish figure was higher than that of any country in Europe.  The average for Europe as a whole shows a decline. Last year, which was not a good year for Ireland, we had a certain slowing-down in the growth of the economy but, even last year, our increase in industrial output was slightly more than the European average.  This year, with our recovery, we are outstripping the rest of Europe in this respect.  In the 12 months ended July, 1967, an extra 3,000 workers were employed in Irish industry.  There has been a tendency on the part of Fine Gael Senators, and Deputies also, to suggest that this very rapid improvement in the past 12 months or so had really nothing to do with the Government, that it was some sort of spontaneous combustion that occurred without any help from the Government.  That is trying to have it both ways.  When anything goes wrong, it is the fault of the Government but when anything goes right it is spontaneous and has nothing to do with the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>It cuts both ways as far as the Government are concerned, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think you can have it both ways.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>You do not want it both ways itself?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me explain.  First, it is obvious that at least a considerable part of the difficulties we had in recent years arose from external factors. The Central Bank, for example, in its 1967 report, states, on page 17: &ldquo;It must be recognised that the difficulties of recent years were, to a considerable extent, due to external the numbers employed in agriculture, <Col N="502" /> causes.&rdquo;  I mentioned some of these causes yesterday&mdash;the continued and long-standing depression of our main market in Britain; the very serious position raised by the import surcharge; the difficulties with cattle prices due mainly to the EEC ban on meat imports; restrictions imposed by other countries such as the United States on the export of capital.  Then we even had matters of some limited and unexpected extent such as the very prolonged shipping strike which undoubtedly did us considerable harm while it lasted, and our agricultural industry was damaged between November, 1965, and April, 1966, by what was uniformly recognised as the worst weather that has ever been recorded. These factors obviously affected our economy and must be taken into account in estimating the causes of our recent recession.</P>
      <P>The Irish economy is now going ahead.  Our exports, in particular, are booming and not because of external causes but in spite of them.  So far as external causes are concerned, in particular so far as the position of our main markets is concerned, one would expect that our exports would be falling, not rising.  Every conceivable factor that one would expect to reflect on us is adverse in the external market, yet we have had this very considerable increase.  Obviously, the Free Trade Area Agreement made with Britain last year is one cause of our exports going so well this year both for agricultural produce and industrial products.  It is fair to suggest, also, without trying to have it both ways, that the very considerable work done of modernising and rationalising Irish industry, with considerable help from the Government by way of loans and grants, has at least something to do with the increase this year in our industrial exports.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Rooney was very worried about employment.  If he reads my speech, which perhaps is improbable, he may be edified to know that in the five-years 1961 to 1966 there was a rise of almost 60,000 persons in employment outside agriculture.  Even allowing for the fall from year to year in <Col N="503" /> the numbers employed in agriculture, there was in that period an overall rise of some 14,000 in the number of people at work which represented a very radical change from the experience of the previous 20 or 30 years.</P>
    <P>We are now at last entering into a period when the overall number at work is rising.  Along with that, of course, there has come a very considerable fall in emigration and a rise in population.  The 1966 census showed a rise of some 63,000 in the total population in the country and there has been a further rise since then.</P>
    <P>One of the severest tests, I suppose, that any Government can face is a period of economic strain such as we have just gone through in the past two years or so.  Action must be taken at the right time&mdash;taken not too late or, for that matter, not too early.  The steps taken must be geared so that the difficulties will be overcome as rapidly as possible but without doing any permanent harm to the economy.  In all these conditions, the present Fianna Fáil Government have succeeded remarkably in overcoming recent difficulties without any serious or permanent harm to the economy.  Inside two years we have got back to the same rate of expansion planned in the Second Programme.  During this period, the actual rate of growth declined but, in fact, it never stopped.</P>
    <P>The first sector in any economy to suffer in a credit squeeze is housing and we have in this respect the appalling example of the 1956-57 collapse of the housing programme under the last Coalition Government.  It is worthwhile reminding ourselves of what happened at that time, not simply for the sake of casting aspersions at the Opposition benches but as an example of what can happen in a situation of this kind when the Government first of all waited too long before taking action and, as a result, had to take action so drastic that it harmed the economy considerably, particularly the housing industry.</P>
    <P>We had the situation when, in twelve months, between April, 1956 and April, 1957, the number of workers on local <Col N="504" /> authority housing declined from 6,300 to 3,900, by more than a third.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Between when and when?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>Between April, 1956 and April, 1957.  In Dublin city, taking the period from 1954 to 1st August, 1957, the number of workers in housing under Dublin Corporation fell from 2,738 to 925.  In other words, at the end of the Coalition Government's period of office there was one-third the number of workers engaged in local authority housing in Dublin.  That was a catastrophic situation and I mention it to show what can happen when deflation has to be carried out in the drastic way it was found necessary to do it at that time.</P>
      <P>In the recent instance of economic difficulty, nothing like that happened to the housing campaign.  There has been in recent years a very substantial increase in the number of houses built under the present Government.  It has, in fact, almost doubled since 1961. The figure reached the very high total of 11,255 dwellings completed in the 1965-66 financial year.  In the following financial year, when we were more or less in the middle of our recent economic difficulties, the figure fell by only a fraction, from 11,255 to 10,984, a very small decrease in the severe credit difficulties we had.  It shows the manner in which the Government were able to keep on, even at a difficult period, the supply of capital for the housing campaign.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Of course, since then there has been an improvement and in the twelve months to 30th September last the number of houses rose to 11,301.  In the six months ending on 30th September last, the number of local authority houses begun or authorised rose to 2,475 from 1,087 in the same six months of the preceding year, well more than double.  When we come to private housing, there has been an increase of a thousand in the number of grants allocated.  In the recent difficult period, therefore, there was a slight, only a slight, fall in housing output which has now been more than made up&mdash;a very different situation from <Col N="505" /> that which arose in previous years under the previous Government.</P>
    <P>Senators have spoken, and no doubt will again, about what they described as the collapse of the Second Programme. It is worth while looking at the facts with regard to it.  The rate of growth aimed at for the period was 4.3 per cent.  In the first year of the Programme, 1964, the rise in national income was around 5 per cent.  Then we started the period of difficulty and in 1965 this fell to 2½ per cent and last year to one per cent.  This year we expect it to be back again to 4 per cent or a little more.  From now on, appearances are that the growth in the next couple of years will be back to the figure aimed at, or perhaps higher.</P>
    <P>I think Senator FitzGerald will agree with that estimate of the present situation. All the signs are that there will be a period of quite rapid growth in the next couple of years.  We have, therefore, the position that the Second Programme growth targets will be reached or perhaps passed in five of the seven years.  Some targets, though by no means all, will not be reached but it is already quite clear that the period of the Second Programme will be one of quite unprecedented progress in the history of this country.  It is quite clear already that during this period we shall move ahead in almost all aspects of the national economic life at a faster rate than ever previously.</P>
    <P>If that is collapse, then all I can say is that my definition of the word is not quite that of the Opposition Senators. The last two years have finally shown the soundness, not the unsoundness, of the whole expansion programme.  We had a £42 million deficit in our balance of payments two years ago.  Last year, we reduced that to £16 million and this year all the appearances are that we shall have a surplus of £10 million or so&mdash;not that I am suggesting that a surplus in our balance of payments is something to aim at, though Senator FitzGerald seemingly thinks a surplus is a bad thing in itself.  I would not aim at one though I do not agree with Senator FitzGerald's seeming proposition that a balance of payments deficit <Col N="506" /> has some mystic symbolism that we should all aim at.</P>
    <P>If we can achieve a satisfactory growth without having a large balance of payments deficit, I think we should aim at it.  At any rate, we have overcome the problem raised by the deficit of £42 million in a very short time and within two years we have got back to the target rate of growth.  Any programme can go ahead so long as there are no difficulties and no external problems.  It is when problems arise that the degree of soundness of the programme is shown.</P>
    <P>We now know that the expansion programme which was begun around 1959 by the Fianna Fáil Government is now so soundly based that even when difficulties arise they do not prevent the programme from going ahead. At no time was growth stopped.  It was only slowed down, as happened all over Europe, but to a greater extent than here.  We are now back on the target set in 1959.  If that is the collapse of the programme which Senator O'Quigley, Senator Rooney and other spoke about I hope collapses of this type will continue for a long time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to comment, first of all, on the serious position that has arisen in England and, by virtue of the fact that it has arisen there, will affect us here, namely, the foot and mouth disease.  I approve completely of the measures taken by the Government to prevent this dreadful plague from reaching the shores of Ireland but I think at the same time what has happened in recent months in England should give food for thought here not alone to the Government but to the people of this country as a whole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The illusion that was foisted on the people that this was a highly developed country and one that had long since moved out of the primary production stage in agriculture has been shown up for what it is.  The people begin to realise now that it is a matter of regret that the bullock is still the prime source of sustenance for the majority <Col N="507" /> of the people.  It is not my intention to criticise the cattle trade as such but I want to bring home the almost pathetic dependence which the nation has on the bullock in 1967.</P>
    <P>Back at the time of the Land League the slogan was: &ldquo;The land for the people and the bullock for the road.&rdquo; Our Irish Governments seemed to take the view that the most important thing in this country was the people and that we blamed alien Governments for the fact that landlords were allowed to evict Irish tenants and replace them by bullocks.  The simple fact of the matter is that after 40 years of native Government the bullock has succeeded in ousting the people far more under this native Government period than ever before.  I think no economic expert would challenge my contention that for the small farmer the production of store cattle is something of economic suicide, yet the small farmer of this country has been encouraged, directly or indirectly, down the years to pursue a line of husbandry in agriculture that has left him almost totally dependent on the production of store cattle for his livelihood.  The results are there today.  I can do no better than quote the position in one county in the West of Ireland&mdash;County Roscommon.</P>
    <P>In County Roscommon 20 years ago there were 24,000 holdings of land described as agricultural holdings. That figure has fallen by 6,000 holdings in that period of 20 years.  The type of holdings are 30 per cent below 15 acres, 25 per cent between 15 acres and 30 acres and 40 per cent between 30 acres and 50 acres.  The important thing to remember with the small holdings is that 95 per cent of the land of that county is under grass. The return per acre for land which is devoted to the production of store cattle is the lowest of any form of husbandry in agriculture that is known today, yet that has been encouraged down through the years.</P>
    <P>The results are there in County Roscommon and what has happened there is typical of all the West.  The process of heavy and excessive rural depopulation <Col N="508" /> is being encouraged by the type of husbandry that obtains there.  The very fact that this dreadful disease has occurred off our shores should give us food for thought that not enough attention is being given to the necessity for diversifying our agricultural products.</P>
    <P>I know attempts were made in very recent years by the Sugar Company, and by other companies, to interest the small farmer particularly in the growing of fruit and vegetables but in my view the importance of this has never hit the small farmer.  This is something which the Government should examine in greater detail.  I know it may be said by members of the Government that attempts are also being made to bring in milk production in a big way now in some of the western areas.  I admit it is a help to get a pay packet going in every week but I still think there must be a further move away on the small-holdings from this particular line of production because the small farmer has been in chains to the rancher in the midlands and the large farmer.  He has been bound and as the producer he supplies the large farmer with an easy form of income at a later stage. When I say I approve of the measures being taken to prevent the occurrence of this foot and mouth disease.  I think it should also be borne in mind that the Government have a responsibility to see that the goodwill of our emigrants is kept.</P>
    <P>There is a well-known belief in forestry circles that if you insist on bringing forestry operations into an area where there is a strong feeling that the particular land in question should be utilised by the local farmers the forestry people are very wary of carrying out their activities where local control is not available to them.  That is the reason, in a matter of this nature, we should be blunt and frank about it.  The small farmers I mentioned here, they and their families have been driven out for the last 40 to 50 years to the tune of three-quarters of a million.  When many of them wish to come home for Christmas they do so to meet their relations and to enjoy the Irish get-together at the Christmas period.  I feel it should be very diplomatically handled.  As far <Col N="509" /> as they are concerned to a great extent they have little for which to thank this country.  The majority of them have been driven out of the country with nothing higher than a national school education which has been defective in many regards.  To a great extent, when they went to England particularly, they have been hewers of wood and drawers of water.  They got the rough end of the stick and there is unquestionably a feeling of bitterness among many of them at the lack of appreciation of them by Irish Governments and that goes for all Governments.  Therefore, when we appeal to them not to come home we should be very careful to have it explained fully to them that even though they may feel rather bitter against the Irish Government over this failure to provide them with a means of livelihood in the country, at the same time their own relations would be the sufferers here.</P>
    <P>An interesting point has arisen as a result of this plague in Britain.  It is the fact that the Irish people who come home here at Christmas are described as tourists by Bord Fáilte when their statistics come out in April and May. I gather that approximately 80,000 Irish people come here from England for Christmas.  We have a false figure here as far as tourism is concerned. Let nobody for a moment believe that it is the advertisements of Bord Fáilte or the activities of Bord Fáilte in any shape or form that bring those 80,000 people here to Ireland, and yet in the hard statistics that are produced annually Bord Fáilte have the brass neck to suggest that these people are tourists and that Bord Fáilte in some magical way has been responsible for their homecoming.  I feel there should be a complete overhaul or a fresh analysis of tourist figures as far as Bord Fáilte is concerned.  Let us eliminate from tourism the question of Irish people returning here on holidays either in summer or winter so that a truer picture of the activities of Bord Fáilte may then be obtained by examining the number of non-nationals who come here.  Even as it is, I think we will find that some of the best people for persuading English people to come here are their Irish neighbours who have <Col N="510" /> been driven out of this country.  It is through their contacts with Irish people in England that many English tourists come over here and not through the activities of a State body like Bord Fáilte at all.  At any rate, I want to make it clear that I feel that the Government should now examine the position very carefully.</P>
    <P>As far as the small farm is concerned we have been shown to be at the mercy of the bullock economy over the years and that if by some terrible mischance this disease got a foothold here this country would be up the Swanee.  It is perhaps a warning in time to move to other lines.  There is no question about it, the markets are there and have been proved to be there in other fields of agricultural production if there is enough drive and an interest taken by the Government through the various agencies under their control.</P>
    <P>Some of the other points I want to mention may not sound of great importance to the House.  I feel that in the long run very few people outside the House take us as seriously as we do ourselves, but when we talk about amenities that are being destroyed I feel we have a duty here to put our views on record at any rate with regard to this planning that came into operation in recent years.  When I refer to planning I refer to the central planning that takes place in the Department of Local Government and the local authority planning.  Both are dovetailed, or supposed to be.</P>
    <P>We have at present the very important and attractive amenity which belongs to the Irish people, the canal, which is the subject of so much discussion here in Dublin and throughout the country at the moment.  It would appear from the controversy which is taking place that it is not clearly understood that this is a national concern in which the people of the country have a right to have their say; that it is not a question of Dublin at all taking a decision one way or the other in the survival of this canal.  I do not want to go back to the time when it was constructed any more than going back to the time when the railways were first constructed, but when you consider the <Col N="511" /> mentality of people here in Ireland today who hasten to destroy what are very valuable amenities in one regard and necessities in another, it is quite clear that these same people would be the last to initiate something new. They are destroyers, they are barbarians rather than builders.</P>
    <P>I was on a deputation six or seven years ago to the Minister, Deputy Childers.  I am damned if I can recollect what he was Minister for, but he had something to do with the Grand Canal at any rate.  A number of Deputies and others from outside attended on the Minister to discuss the threat of closing the Grand Canal.  I put the point to the Minister that people who made their mark in history were remembered either through statues or plaques put up to them so that people could always look at the statue or plaque and say: &ldquo;That man was responsible for improving such and such a facet of our life.&rdquo;  I suggested to him that whoever was responsible for taking a decision to close this canal should also be remembered by a plaque or statue so that in a hundred years time when people saw it they would say: &ldquo;That is the man who took the decision to close the Grand Canal.&rdquo;  The Minister was horrified at this suggestion.  The reason I made it, and I repeat it now, is that it might halt some of these people in their tracks if we could take them out from behind this air of anonymity and let them be shown publicly as the people who are making those decisions.</P>
    <P>I have referred to the canal and I shall tie it in with another matter which has shown the terrible shortsightedness of technical people and those who make decisions as a result of technical advice.  I am referring now to the closing of Harcourt Street Station.  That decision was taken by experts.  If they were honest today and confessed their feeling they would say it was a major mistake at a time when this city is choked with traffic and when other cities all over the world are making arrangements to utilise railways more and more and, indeed, are engaged in building railways for a <Col N="512" /> commuter service in the cities.  Can we have anything but a feeling of uneasiness that these experts are not quite what they are put up to be?  If they were wrong in a decision of that nature taken so few years ago, is it not quite possible and more than likely that they are wrong to make a decision, or to be allowed to make a decision, to close this wonderful potential amenity, the canal?</P>
    <P>Any confidence I would have in their ability is shattered by decisions such as that to close Harcourt Street. I dislike the mentality behind it and the haste with which these things are done.  Once a decision is taken how ruthlessly it is pursued in spite of public refusal.  Here we have had strong public indignation and it has been brushed aside as if the people responsible for planning the protest did not matter.  We may not agree with their views in many ways.  Very often people can antagonise others in the way they go about trying to achieve something, but this is no reason why we should accept the proposition to close the canal.</P>
    <P>I understand that Dublin Corporation have plans to get rid of what I can describe as a jungle.  There is an area adjoining the canal banks which is a kind of slum area where people who fail to pay their rents, and do not come up to requirements as far as the corporation are concerned, are given substandard houses.  I refer to Keogh Square.  I understand there are plans for the demolition of Keogh Square.  I believe that area should be razed to the ground; that it should be made a first-class amenity, landscaped down to the canal, making it a place where there will be open space where children can be reared in a better environment.</P>
    <P>The argument put forward for housing is not a fair argument to use against the canal.  We all accept that housing is a priority need but I believe that the housing needs can be met in other ways.  I know, and I am sure that many Members of this House know, that the big trouble with housing is that speculators and developers are allowed a free hand to buy property or, better still, to take an option on <Col N="513" /> land in any area that they believe would prove suitable for the building of houses at some stage.</P>
    <P>To me there are two things which are vital to man.  One is food and the other is shelter.  In this country food and shelter are two of the most exploited things I know of.  There should be a stamp of maliciousness on those who seek to exploit food and shelter, and when I refer to shelter I mean housing.  Shelter is being exploited by so-called developers and speculators.  When people talk about how wrong it is to close this canal we are hit immediately with this cry&mdash;it is necessary for houses.  We have babble from Dublin Corporation and from those representatives who generally do not think beyond their noses, who cannot see but that this canal bed can be used only for sewerage purposes.  How is it that in many other places and in England they can solve their sewerage problems without the course of action proposed by Dublin Corporation? They have as big a problem and they are still able to apply proper processing arrangements for sewerage, but it would appear that no other solution is available to the technical experts in Dublin except laying the pipes for sewerage under this canal.</P>
    <P>I am not a technical expert but I would put the point to Senators that the level of the canal depends on tht lock system which is the most important aspect of the canal, set up as it is. The height of the canal varies from lock to lock.  I cannot understand how sewerage pipes can be laid with a proper gradient which will not interfere with the lock system if we are to accept the point of view put forward, that the closing will only be temporary.  I do not believe it is a practical proposition to have these pipes laid and afterwards restore the canal.  I do not think it is technically feasible.</P>
    <P>I believe the idea is to lay the pipes and build a road over it and to hell with the objectors.  People say this is only a temporary closing.  We know from questions asked in the Dáil this week that the laying of a road over the sewerage piping is being discussed.  I think that would be a dreadful step to <Col N="514" /> take.  This canal and its banks provide a beautiful green strip right through the heart of the city and to replace that with a concrete road would be a backward step.  It would be advisable to send our technical people to some comparable cities in Britain to examine the position in those cities.  That would be a much more desirable way of dealing with it than calling some so-called expert from Europe and when he comes in whisper in his ear and, if you like, nose him into a certain line of approach.  We had this before when the problems connected with drainage were so great and it was decided to bring over a man from America to deal with the Shannon.  I refer to Mr. Rydell. He was to do a tour of the Shannon accompanied by Board of Works engineers and it was an extraordinary thing that Mr. Rydell's opinions coincided with those of the people who brainwashed him on his tour of the Shannon.</P>
    <P>What I think must be done is to send our engineers to examine works carried out by Mr. Rydell in America and apply them in our own country; in other words, examine schemes elsewhere rather than bring over an expert here to a country with which he has nothing in common.  On this question of the sewerage problem which is a major one, we should send our experts to other cities and examine what has been done there before we allow these philistines to close the canal.  Once it is closed that is the end of it.</P>
    <P>I talked of the mentality of those planners which can be seen in the wholesale destruction in rural areas of beautiful trees where road-widening plans have taken place.</P>
    <P>When engineers come out of the university, as far as I am concerned they are technically competent men but I do not think they can be credited with having any great regard for landscaping or for the improvement of the countryside. It would appear, at any rate, that their main objective is to lay down a strip of road between here and Cork, here and Galway or here and Belfast and anything in the line of beautiful countryside, trees, and so on, must be sacrificed to so-called &ldquo;development&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>We have areas all over the country <Col N="515" /> where very beautiful trees have been removed and very tasteless wiring has been erected instead, mile after mile of wiring with dreary concrete posts, as the result of the planning we have had in the Department of Local Government. I believe that people who think on those lines and who produce this monotonous picture in rural areas have no compunction about doing away with amenities here in the city so that it is a matter in which we should all take an interest.  I feel that public opinion must be sufficiently aroused to bring about a change of mind in this field.</P>
    <P>While on the subject of roads, I want to mention that I believe it is time the Government intervened in a big way with regard to the usage of heavy vehicles on the roads system.  Today, we have these huge monsters, huge trucks with trailers, moving all over the countryside on main and arterial roads and on the network of country roads.  I am satisfied that the majority of these trucks carry goods which could easily be transported by rail.  It may not be a very diplomatic thing to say but I am convinced that, instead of banning these trucks off the road directly, which would appear to be undemocratic in that sense, there is another way to deal with them and that is to make them pay for the damage they do, to make them pay heavily through taxation.  If you make them pay sufficiently through taxation, I think you will force them to put their goods back on the rail.  That, in my opinion, would be one of the ways in which the roads could be made much safer than they are today.</P>
    <P>The feeling of irritation that is built up on the roads by a procession of these lorries day and night causes accidents.  I do not think it is an economic proposition for the country to be paying huge sums for oil, petrol, tyres and so on, from abroad, thus upsetting our balance of payments, when the greater percentage of the goods carried by these trucks and trailers could and should be carried by our national rail.  Although the people to whom I refer are a fairly influential lobby&mdash;they may subscribe heavily to dinners, and so on&mdash;I think that factor should be ignored and that the welfare <Col N="516" /> of the greatest number of our people should be taken into consideration.</P>
    <P>I think the railways should be utilised properly.  I know there has been a mentality to get rid of the railway by degrees and to substitute the usage of the road.  I think that is beginning to change again, not because of commonsense on the part of those on our railway, but because they see in other countries that a change is taking place, too, and that the railway is coming back of its own.</P>
    <P>I referred earlier to housing.  I should now like to say that the Government should give some more consideration to a change in the system of the transfer of houses and lands to expedite and ease the position with regard to the purchase and sale of property and land.  The system which operates here today is based on that which operated in feudal times when a house and land were very valuable and when the solicitors built up a very intricate type of transfer system that certainly helped them financially, too.  That system of transfer is archaic at the present time. It is an anomaly that a painting worth £1 million can be transferred by a simple process from one owner to another.  Similarly, a very valuable piece of jewellery can be transferred. Why a house cannot be transferred on the same lines is a mystery to me unless it is that a vested interest has been built up in our system which, I am afraid, is the case&mdash;for instance, the legal profession and the estate agents, the auctioneers.  Between the two of them, they are a brake on progress as far as housing is concerned.</P>
    <P>As Senators know, the present system of the transfer of property dates back to the first keeping of documents dealing with the piece of land on which the house will be built. That is pursued right up to the sale of the house and that search takes place when each sale takes place.  We know that a defect in title or an error in deeds can hold up the sale of a property for ages.  Here in Ireland, the ordinary man in the street is very worried about the whole idea of buying or selling a house.  If that is the position, it is a brake on progress.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="517" /> If we look at this city alone, we see we have people living on the north side who work on the south side, and <i>vice versa.</i> I am quite satisfied that many of those people, were it not for the present archaic system of transfer of property, would be very pleased to live in the vicinity of the area where they work.  I am quite satisfied they would prefer to change house from the north side to the south side and <i>vice versa</i>, but the cost and the worries involved are too much.  These people contribute to traffic jams during peak hours and this is a factor that should be considered.</P>
    <P>The same type of restraint is exercised where small business premises are concerned.  The man may have premises which are too small for his business, but at the same time he is cowed from leaving the locality to buy new premises because of the costs involved, the matter of title and all the expenses attached to it.</P>
    <P>I am informed that a great improvement in this field has taken place in many European countries and if this country is contemplating entry to the new Europe, as I am led to believe by all the hubbub, it behoves us to improve our position in the matter of transfer of property.  In Europe a man can transfer his property by a simple entry in a register kept by local authorities or by the central authority so that the bother and fuss and expense that are involved here are eliminated.  Senators will know that the cost is appalling as far as housing is concerned.  The minimum charge in legal fees, auctioneer's fees and stamp duty on a £5,000 house is £500.  That figure is added to the cost of the house.  It should be at least halved and it would still leave sufficient remuneration for all those involved in the transfer.  The costs here are fantastic in this respect.  I know the Minister for Justice has been taking an interest in it and I hope some effective measures will be taken in the immediate future.</P>
    <P>On the general picture as far as the country is concerned, I do not propose to comment in any detail because other speakers of the Labour Party will deal with it.  We can judge only in our own <Col N="518" /> areas what the impact of Government policy has been and I wish to make it quite clear that though the Government have had a free run without a break since 1957&mdash;they cannot argue that any other group have been responsible&mdash;the position has worsened with regard to the numbers employed and also the number of people retained on the land.</P>
    <P>As far as the West is concerned, the measures taken by the Government have been ineffective in stemming the rush from the land.  I am not suggesting there is an easy solution to the problem but I am satisfied the Government should now take in all the threads of the various agencies at work and combine them in one.  We must have a special western development authority so that one Minister will be given the responsibility to co-ordinate the efforts of the various groups, whether they are voluntary or State, who are only nibbling at the problem now.  They are ineffective, and through their ineffectiveness they are bringing about further cynicism.  There is sufficient talent from which to draw one man to whom to give responsibility to go ahead and set up this authority.  If that is not done I cannot see any hope whatever of holding the population in the West.  I believe it will become a kind of a home for tourists in the summer and fishermen in the winter.  That would be a tragedy.  A tremendous amount of organising can be done to prevent it happening.  Even at this late stage such an authority would give hope where now there is none.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>A good deal has been said by various Senators, by Senator O'Quigley first of all and lastly by Senator McQuillan, about agriculture and the policy of the Government towards agriculture.  I suppose a Dubliner, a city dweller like myself, should hesitate to make any major pronouncements on agriculture, though it is true, of course, that the dwellers in cities are the major consuming public supplied by the farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I agree with the criticisms expressed by Senator McQuillan and also by Senator O'Quigley in relation to the Government's methods of dealing with <Col N="519" /> the farming community.  No matter what the rights or the wrongs of the disputes between the Government and some, at least, of the farmers, the Government at any rate should always be ready to discuss them.  I do not think the Government can be expected to allow any group in the country to dictate Government policy, but it is extremely distressing to the whole country to see the reluctance on the part of successive Ministers for Agriculture to listen to the case of those who are most vocally critical of Government policy.  Perhaps the crux of the matter may be the failure both on the part of the farmers and of the Government to face the facts about the small farm.</P>
    <P>The small shop, it is generally realised, is doomed, and is being displaced by the bigger concern, simply because it has become more and more an uneconomic method of distributing consumer goods.  I think it not impossible that the small farm, similarly, in relation to agricultural produce, is becoming less and less economic and I think the Government in their policy must face the possibility that from the point of view of the community it is not economic further to subsidise small farms beyond a certain limit, because the cost of production in these uneconomic units may be more than the community can afford.</P>
    <P>If the Government take this point of view and face the facts, a lot of the public would agree with them, but I feel the Government are trying, on the one hand, to placate the small farmers because the small farmer has one vote as well as the big farmer, and, on the other hand, having made the pretence of helping the small farmers, in practice they are behaving as if they were convinced that the small farmers were doomed to disappear.</P>
    <P>Senator McQuillan gave some figures about the reduction in the number of holdings in one county, Roscommon, and this certainly is the pattern in most of the country.  If the Government are really serious in desiring that their policy on agriculture should have, as one of its fruits, the encouragement <Col N="520" /> of small farmers, I suggest that their general policy in this respect should be based mainly on the effective promotion of co-operative farming.</P>
    <P>It would appear that the time is getting near when the small farmer will be able to survive only if he is in active participating co-operation with farmers similarly placed.  It is quite obvious, of course, that the farmers of Ireland are under-capitalised.  Almost all of them are under-capitalised and they have very little access to technical means.  I would question whether enough is being done by the money voted to the Department of Agriculture for the purpose of giving to the less well-off farmers access to the greatly improved technical means of running a farm, whether it be in relation to harvesting, or ploughing, and so on.  It is sometimes said that more money is made out of farming in Ireland by the local garage man who owns the combine-harvester and lets it out on hire or the tractor owners or the contractors who contract to plough the land, than is made by the farmer who owns the land.</P>
    <P>I should like to feel that access to improved techniques in farming would be rendered easier by Government tractor stations, combine-harvester stations at suitable points in the country, so that farmers could have recourse to them in order to gain more benefit from technical progress than has been made possible to date owing to the lack of farming capital.</P>
    <P>I remember, I suppose it is 25 years ago, that Dr. Beddy read a paper to the Statistical Society of Ireland.  This paper was divided into two parts.  It was a statistical review of the situation in Ireland and in Denmark.  The first part of this paper was a review of the natural advantages of both countries, Ireland and Denmark.  On the question of natural advantages Ireland was ahead of Denmark in every way, the richness of the soil, the even distribution of rainfall, the capacity to grow a variety of crops, the relatively mild winter conditions, the fact that summer drought conditions were rare in this country.  For every natural resource Ireland was ahead.</P>
    <P>The second part of the paper dealt <Col N="521" /> with what gain each had got out of the natural advantages, first in Ireland and then in Denmark.  Here they were statistically set out in regard to the production per acre, the production per farm labourer, the amount to which each acre was capitalised, the capital investment in the farm, the access to machinery, the percentage use of machinery and the percentage of money lent to the farmers by their own co-operative banks.  In every single one of those items Denmark was way ahead of Ireland.  The picture there is that we have immense natural advantages which we lamentably fail to use.  I would lay the blame there at the feet of successive Ministers for Agriculture who have failed to take a lesson from another small country which has succeeded in making from less good natural resources far better use than we have so far made from our far greater agricultural resources.</P>
    <P>Senator McQuillan referred to the Land League and some of the slogans of the Land League.  I have here a book, which I intend, with the permission of the Librarian, to give to the Library of the Oireachtas.  It is a book written by my own father as far back as 1907 and now reprinted.  It is a biography of Michael Davitt.  He refers in a good deal of detail to the land policy which was advocated some 90 years ago in this country, in the days when it was thought if only you could get rid of the British landlord everything would be all right in Ireland.  It is very striking to see that Davitt, both in Ireland and in England, where he lectured and taught a lot, and indeed in America, was preaching agricultural doctrine which today would be regarded as wildly radical by our Irish Government in power.  For instance, in December, 1878, nearly 90 years ago, having toured America, Davitt succeeded in getting passed unanimously a resolution in Boston which included, and I quote:</P>
    <P>A demand for the immediate improvement of the Irish land system by such a thorough change as would prevent the peasantry from being further victimised by landlordism. . . . This change to lead up to a system of small proprietorship similar <Col N="522" /> to what at present obtains in France, Belgium, and Prussia.  Such land to be purchased or held directly from the State.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Held directly from the State.&rdquo;  It becomes apparent in other passages also, from which I intend to quote, that what Davitt was preaching was the nationalisation of the land whereby each Irish farmer would hold his land in trust from the community.  This, which it was regarded as legal to preach in the Ireland of the 1880s, would now, I suppose, be regarded as a form of communism or of Bolshevism. Yet in 1879, and I quote from page 81 of the book, reference is made to the famous Irishtown meeting:</P>
    <P>Attended by fully seven thousand men, with a large &ldquo;cavalry&rdquo; contingent, it was an extraordinary testimony to the keenness of insight which had led Davitt to the conclusion that the land question was the true key of the Irish situation.  The speakers, invited by Davitt, were Messrs.  Brennan, O'Connor Power, John Ferguson, Louden, and Daly. Davitt himself was not present; but he sent the resolutions, which at once struck the keynote of the whole subsequent campaign.  They passed far beyond the moderate land reform programme with which Butt (and Parnell too) had till that time been satisfied, and declared uncompromisingly for the complete abolition of the landlord system.  The speakers differed in their proposals&mdash;or suggestions, rather&mdash;for the replacement of the doomed system: Brennan, always the nearest of the Land Leaguers to Davitt's position, adumbrated land nationalisation; Ferguson, dealing with the problem from the too often overlooked standpoint of the town dweller, dealt with the taxation of land values; while O'Connor Power, more moderate than the others, even though he went beyond his parliamentary colleagues (he was then member for Mayo), advocated peasant proprietorship.</P>
    <P>The point I should like to make is that I would like to see Fianna Fáil bringing themselves sufficiently up to date <Col N="523" /> in order to reach roughly the 1890s.  I hope this is not asking too much.  They might hover for a bit in the 1880s if they were afraid of coming too far forward in a rush but there is no question, in all seriousness, but that if we had employed this method of land nationalisation when we first got our political independence in this country, none of the problems in relation to land speculation would have arisen.  I would like to see in this Appropriation Bill some indication that the Government are aware of the problem, and are concerned to tackle at last this question of land speculation.</P>
    <P>I would like to quote our Constitution if I may.  Article 43 says in its first clause:</P>
    <P>1.  The State acknowledges that man, in virtue of his rational being, has the natural right antecedent to positive law, to the private ownership of external goods.</P>
    <P>2.  The State accordingly guarantees to pass no law attempting to abolish the right of private ownership or the general right to transfer, bequeath, and inherit property.</P>
    <P>The second subsection says:</P>
    <P>The State recognises, however, that the exercise of the rights mentioned in the foregoing provisions of this Article ought, in civil society, to be regulated by the principles of social justice.</P>
    <P>In other words, as they make clear in the second paragraph of this second subsection,</P>
    <P>The State, accordingly, may as occasion requires delimit by law the exercise of the said rights with a view to reconciling their exercise with the exigencies of the common good.</P>
    <P>I should like to see more evidence in the Appropriations as they come before us of concern with the common good and less concern with the private profit motive.  I remember being shocked many years ago when I heard Jim Larkin, Senior, saying that for land that used to cost less than £100 an acre out Kimmage and Crumlin way, when they were building there, in <Col N="524" /> some cases Dublin Corporation had to pay as much as £1,000 or even £1,200 an acre.  Larkin rightly made the point that the tenants, and indeed the city, were being held to ransom by speculators who had moved in and bought this land realising that its value would be increased by community effort and had taken a high and quick profit from it, this profit being paid, ultimately, by the future tenants of Corporation housing in Kimmage, Crumlin and so on.  It seemed horrifying to me then that land should be selling at such a high price, but I read a report the other day that land up near Glenasmole on the banks of the Dodder has been selling for something like £7,000 an acre.  This site of course will be developed by sewage and so on, and eventually the people in the houses will pay in their rents for this quite unwarranted increment in so-called &ldquo;land value&rdquo;.  Again as Senator McQuillan and Senator O'Quigley have said, the Government would appear to be less than actively concerned about this racket of land speculation, people deriving an enormous private profit from guessing correctly that the community will soon improve the value of a piece of land by supplying services, roads, sewage and so on.</P>
    <P>It was recognised by Davitt, as I have suggested before, that not only in Ireland but in England itself the best method of dealing with this would be for the community itself, the State, to own the land.  I shall quote from page 109.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is a little concerned that the Senator should base his whole speech or a great part of it on something which would involve considerable legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, the Chair of course has no evidence that what I have said so far constitutes a great portion of my speech! That might prove to be optimistic but I hope the Chair is right.  I shall pass away from this fairly rapidly but I would just like to quote this which seems to be relevant to the situation:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>For this Davitt was largely responsible; he was one of those whose persuasions had had most weight in <Col N="525" /> inducing Henry George to come to Europe and to bring out an English edition of <i>Progress and Poverty.</i> It was one of his cherished aims to convert the English democracy to land nationalisation, which he rightly declared was of paramount importance for them also.</P>
    <P>I would suggest that the motive force to which the Government refer in their decision as to how they spend the money, our money, is to a major extent not community interest but private profit; this form of mammon worship is to be deplored, and I would like to see some change in future Appropriation Bills that they are not simply making it easy for people to derive big private profits from the system.  I shall make one last quotation from this book.  It is page 121:</P>
    <P>At one of the first of these meetings, held in St. James's Hall, London, under the auspices of the Land Reform Union, with the Rev. Stewart Headlam in the chair, Davitt gave utterance to an indictment of the individualist system which travels beyond the scope of the land question and is perhaps the nearest approach to a definitely socialist pronouncement to be found in his speeches.</P>
    <P>Then there is this quotation from Davitt:</P>
    <P>The individualistic civilisation of the present system denies to the million the possibility of giving play to what is good in human nature, by putting its passions and selfishness into deadly activity in a cut-throat competition for wealth.</P>
    <P>This is a description of our present system of production, of ownership, of speculation, of stock exchange gambling and of distribution through greed.  I feel that it is part of the Government's function, by its various measures and by its general policy, to try at least to modify this system, ultimately to change it so that community interests will be the prime concern and not private greed.</P>
    <P>I should like to speak now about <Col N="526" /> something that has been mentioned before, and that is the moving of Departments to different centres outside Dublin.  I cannot help remembering that when a Bill was introduced in this Seanad for the founding of a new Department, the Department of the Gaeltacht, I proposed an amendment to the effect that the new Department should be situated in Galway. I got no support at all, but the following week a deputation composed of a number of Senators and TDs from the West travelled up to Dublin.  It included some Senators who had voted against my amendment.  They waited on the Minister in a deputation to plead with him to start the new Ministry in Galway and the Government turned it down.  They would have nothing to do with it.  Whatever case you can make for or against moving ministries now, certainly a very big case could have been made in the case of a new ministry and particular a Ministry of the Gaeltacht to put it in the Gaeltacht itself or in the city of Galway.  The Government then felt that this was not worthwhile and they set it up here in Dublin.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>Was it this Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, it was this Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>No it was not this Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, it might just have well been, I find it very hard to distinguish between them, I was just thinking when listening to Senator O'Quigley that I hope he will be as good if and when his Party gets into power as he is in the Opposition. I apologise for my error there but the members of both Parties voted against my amendment and members of both Parties came up to wait on the Minister, which seemed to me to be an example of not very coherent thinking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Early repentance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Early repentance, yes.  One of the Ministries which is not being moved is the <Col N="527" /> Ministry of the Gaeltacht.  That is to remain in Dublin.  I wonder why that is.  I wonder would the Government policy on that be capable of logical explanation?  I am not convinced, I may say, that any of the other Ministries will function better from some part of the West.  It is, of course, nice to think of jobs and consumers' demands being shifted down to the West.  From the point of view of the West it may be a good thing.  Is it a good thing from the point of view of running a business, the business of Government?  I do not think it is.  I think this notion of shifting the Department of Education to Athlone derives from the false notion that the function of the Government arises from &ldquo;providing jobs&rdquo; rather than with a preoccupation with tackling the jobs that require doing.</P>
      <P>The Government seems to regard the giving out of jobs as being a prime function instead of the discovery of the great number of things that require doing and the tackling of them, whether they be in the West&mdash;and many things require doing in the West &mdash;or in the East.</P>
      <P>This brings me to the question of community interests in such things as the closing of the Grand Canal, which has been mentioned by other Senators also.  It seems to me criminal folly, not merely to say that we will close this canal, perhaps permanently or perhaps temporarily, but criminal folly also to have failed down the years to make the maximum use of the amenities of such a waterway.  We have criminally neglected this.  Indeed, we have neglected a lot of our rivers too.  Anybody who looks at the upper reaches of the Liffey and some of the upper banks sees that they are rendered squalid by commercial undertakings right down to the water edge.  If this were in any Continental city, say in Vienna, one would find that it would be used for public parks, complete with restaurants and boating facilities, and not left at the disposal of one or two private owners, but at the disposal of the people of the city.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Why have we not done that in the last 50 years?  Why did we allow the <Col N="528" /> banks of the canal and the Liffey to be turned over to commercial undertakings which might far better be situated in place of derelict sites in the City of Dublin.  I should like to make a plea not only to preserve the canal but to develop it into parks which would have facilities for the public enjoyment of this waterway.  Senator McQuillan is right to stress that the Grand Canal is a national asset, but let us not lose sight of the fact that it can also be a major asset for the people of Dublin.  Stupid arguments can be put forward by such people as that children get drowned in the canals.  This is a shameful argument. The reason they get drowned thus is that we, as a city, have long failed to provide swimming baths in anything like the quantity or quality that would be required in any civilised city of our size.  To say children get drowned in the canal indicates that our public policy condemns a number of children who have no other facilities than the canal in its present state.  The canal, properly used and its potential realised and developed, would be a great asset to this city and to the country and to think of its not merely being closed down and being used as a sewer which may not even be technically possible, but to think of it being covered by a thickly laid concrete highway is to show how far we have struck in our failure to realise the potentialities of the beauties and amenities now still within our reach.</P>
    <P>We are not in fact a community interested, as is implied in the minds of those who are governing the country, in encouraging such so-called &ldquo;planning&rdquo;, which clearly is not for the benefit of the community.  I should like to put this question which is one related to the general policy of the Government, a simple question which ought to be answered.  For whose benefit is this Republic of ours being run?  Is it for the benefit of the politicians, for the benefit of the friends of the politicians, or is it for the benefit of the ordinary citizens of this Republic, including the children who are &ldquo;cherished equally&rdquo;, in capital letters, at every Ard-Fheis until the Ard-Fheis is over.  I would say as I look about me that, <Col N="529" /> engendered and fostered by Government policy, is exemplified in the type of expenditure and the type of planning which the Government has so far done, is, I suggest, that of the enthusiastic Mammon-worshipper and the well-heeled Yahoo, because the lack of appreciation of what can and should be preserved in the way of amenity and beauty is overlooked, and this failure in appreciation means that many people in positions of power, not just in the Government but in our municipal and local authorities, merit the name of Yahoo, coined in this city of ours by a great Dubliner some 250 years ago.</P>
    <P>I should like to see the Government placing people first, and not being actively concerned first with so-called &ldquo;economic propositions&rdquo; based on the private motive.  I should like to insert at this point the hope, which I have expressed before, that the Government will soon have a comprehensive widows' pension scheme for State servants. I know the Minister for Finance has introduced legislation for widows' pensions for members of the Oireachtas. Would it not be more decent if he were first to introduce a scheme for widows' pensions for State servants?  It is something with which the Minister for Finance is concerned, I know, and I would express the hope that we may see some result of this soon.</P>
    <P>The last point I want to make is in relation to External Affairs.  I have great admiration for our Minister for External Affairs and in relation to the Vote for his Department I should like to say that he has shown himself down the years in the United Nations and in the Council of Europe to be a man of initiative and a man of courage; and the Government policy on many occasions has given all of us legitimate reasons for pride.  I am sorry, therefore, to notice that Ireland has not been as vocal as it could and should be in support of the Secretary-General of the United Nations, U Thant, on his proposals for the solution of the Vietnam War.</P>
    <P>I should like to hear from the Government an expression, and see some evidence from it, of their desire to back U Thant there, and to throw <Col N="530" /> whatever weight we have as a nation in on the side of the Secretary-General for the early cessation of hostilities in that little country.  I remember that Japan of course occupied Vietnam&mdash;it used to be called French Indo-China &mdash;having thrown out the French in the early 40s.  I remember years ago reading a significant article in the American Weekly <i>The Nation</i> which mentioned the meeting of the executive committee of the Indo-Chinese Communist Party; an illegal organisation then, they met in Saigon in the early 40s before Japan had been defeated</P>
    <P>The discussion at this meeting of 20 executive members of the Communist Party of Indo-China was on the question as to whether they ought to content themselves with trying to throw out the Japanese and set up a Nationalist State or whether they should help the Allies to get back into Indo-China&mdash;the French and the British.  The question was asked: &ldquo;What does Stalin say? What is the directive from Moscow?&rdquo; It was: &ldquo;Help the Allies in.&rdquo;  A vote was taken.  By 19 votes to 1, this Communist executive decided to help the Allies back in&mdash;the people referred to subsequently as the &ldquo;Imperialists&rdquo;. The one vote was that of Ho Chi Min. He was in favour of a National Free Indo-China without the Japanese but without the French or British either.</P>
    <P>The British were the first into Indo-China after the war.  They helped the French back with the help of the Foreign Legion, which was recruited to a considerable extent from the defeated Germans.  So you had Nazi soldiers, fresh from fighting in Europe, being brought in by France, into what is now called Vietnam and the French trying to do a deal with Bao Dai, the Emperor at that time.</P>
    <P>I mention all these factors because of the divided responsibility for the present situation.  It would be quite wrong for us to lay the blame&mdash;the nation and the Minister for External Affairs in the exercise of his duty&mdash;on any one nation intervening there at the present time.  I think one final point that is often forgotten is that for the first ten months of the French war against the Indo-Chinese, after the European war was over, not only were there Socialists and Communists in the <Col N="531" /> French Government but, the French Minister for Munitions was a Communist at this time when the French were battering the Indo-Chinese, for the first ten months of the &ldquo;imperialist war&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Having said all that, and having recognised that it is not only the United States that has been battering away at this unfortunate country, we see that now the major battering is being done by the United States, brought in at the behest of France many years ago. U Thant deserves the support of our Minister for External Affairs and of those in Ireland who value the whole concept of peace and also of the right of small nations to decide their own destinies.  U Thant is eager that the Geneva Agreement of 1954 should be honoured.  He asks particularly for three things.  I should like to see Ireland's Minister for External Affairs supporting him in this.</P>
    <P>The first thing he asks for is the stopping of bombing.  One recalls, of course, the bombing of Addis Ababa in the mid-1930s when Mussolini was invading Abysinnia.  Horror was expressed then that Mussolini was using mustard gas upon the Abysinnians. To many in Europe, this seemed to brand Mussolini as a barbarian, as a totally insensitive person, as, in fact, a person who should be regarded as a war criminal.  Consequently, when we see the Americans now bombing the Vietnamese with napalm bombs, and see the results in photographs, and when we get testimony to that effect from people such as Salisbury, one of the editors of the <i>New York Times</i>, then I feel we have a right to ask if war crimes are not now being committed by the United States against the people of Vietnam.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Senator seen pictures of what Ho Chi Minh's boys have done against American pilots?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I have seen pictures.  I am not in a position to deny or confirm them.  Those that are true&mdash;and a great number are true, unfortunately&mdash;are equally to be deplored. <Col N="532" /> I detest the point of view implied by Senator Ó Maoláin that if the other side engage in filthy atrocity then it is perfectly all right for the civilised United States to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>That was not the point.  The whole blame was being put on the United States, according to the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington was only recording what U Thant said and asked to be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>He failed to record that the United States did stop the bombing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>The record will show that I have been very far from placing the blame on one side only.  Take those who say: &ldquo;Atrocities are being committed by the other side, so let us keep our mouths shut when the United States, our friends, our allies, the people with whom we have intimate links of race commit them.&rdquo; When people such as Senator Ó Maoláin suggest that people should say nothing because Ho Chi Minh's troops also committed atrocities, then I accuse him of cowardice and poltroonery in the face of a situation which demands he should have the guts to speak out against atrocities on both sides.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not cowardly or lacking in guts.  Come back to Ho Chi Minh now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is more interested in coming back to the debate on the Appropriation Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ó Maoláin has a fund of adjectives which he can produce in praise of his own courage.  I should prefer to see an example.  He has not yet spoken.  He can get up and condemn atrocities on both sides and, if he does not do it, I hereby accuse him of poltroonery.  I was speaking of U Thant and of his appeal that the bombing be stopped.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Senator hear that the Americans did stop the bombing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="533" />
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Chair for protection from Senator Ó Maoláin who is afraid to make a speech on his own and refer to these things, but who would like to prevent me from appealing for support for the three points that U Thant makes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be better if Senator Ó Maoláin refrained from interruption and if Senator Sheehy Skeffington refrained from making charges against Senator Ó Maoláin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>My purpose in making these charges is not necessarily to suggest that they are true but to stimulate Senator Ó Maoláin into active participation in the debate not merely by means of interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall send my seconds to wait on the Senator afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I know that Senator Ó Maoláin is no coward.  I believe his courage is such that he will even get up and condemn atrocities on the American side as well as on Ho Chi Minh's side.</P>
      <P>The three points U Thant is asking for are &mdash; (1) to stop the bombing; (2) a phased withdrawal of all foreign troops from both North and South and (3) internationally supervised elections in both North and South which were, in fact, agreed at the 1954 Convention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Personally, I believe and I think it should be said that Ho Chi Minh ought to be prepared to negotiate now even if the bombing does not stop.  I believe that during the three weeks or so when the Americans did halt the bombing, Ho Chi Minh should have negotiated, I can see reasons for his hesitation, but I think we should say here that negotiation is always better than a continuance of war.  I want to leave this point now, but to stress finally that I believe that in external affairs, Ireland's voice should be raised in support of the Secretary-General of the United Nations, in order that this horrible war may be brought to a speedy conclusion. We are not lacking in courage as a rule.  I heard, just the other night, at a meeting in Dublin, Father Michael <Col N="534" /> O'Neill speak on this whole Vietnam question.  He spoke out very strongly in favour precisely of this, of Ireland's &mdash;and he knows a great deal about China and the Far East&mdash;being in favour of U Thant's proposal.</P>
    <P>When the Minister for External Affairs showed courage some years ago by asking for the question of the admission of China to be put on the agenda of the United Nations, he was very stupidly attacked in this country by Fine Gael, who suggested he was playing the Communist game.  I hope Fine Gael have sufficiently changed since then not to make this kind of stupid attack.  It did not harm the Minister, but it did a great deal of harm to the image of Fine Gael and to Ireland that there still could be people who would try to smear our Minister for External Affairs as a Communist, a stupid kind of smear, simply because he had asked that the question of the admission of China be put on the agenda.</P>
    <P>I have said practically all I wanted to say.  In conclusion I should like to add something about general Government policy.  In a recent debate, I referred to the fact that I remembered when Fianna Fáil were a republican Party.  Rather unwisely, the Minister for Finance interjected that I must have a very long memory.  I am afraid he was right, in a way he did not entirely intend.  I can remember quite well Fianna Fáil out of office, Fianna Fáil pre-1927 and Fianna Fáil after the oath in 1927 and up to 1932.  They were republican, they were near-socialist, they were libertarians, strongly liberal and even radical.</P>
    <P>I remember reading in <i>The Bell</i> an article about the foundation of the <i>Irish Press</i> by Dr. Vivien Mercier.  He said that the <i>Irish Press</i> had started with high ideals and a big overdraft, and that the two had diminished down the years side by side, and that now they have no overdraft.  Fianna Fáil have no overdraft now, but I hope their high ideals are not quite dead&mdash;that some, at least, remain of the days when they were a progressive, radical, near-socialist, liberal and republican Party. I should like very much to see signs of this in their policy, not for the purpose <Col N="535" /> of &ldquo;providing jobs&rdquo; but with a view to tackling the things in this country which need tackling for the good of the people.</P>
    <P>I should like to see their policy put the good of the community before private greed, not being so concerned with what Davitt called the &ldquo;cut-throat competition for wealth&rdquo;.  I should like to see in that policy the assessment of our material wealth and our skills of hand and brain; the assessment of our major human needs. I should like their policy harness our skill of brain and hand to our material wealth for the satisfaction of human needs, not just of private greed.</P>
    <P>We have a very beautiful country, with a sensitive, intelligent population of whom some 20,000 or 30,000 every year are driven out of the country by economic policy.  I should like Government policy to aim above all at preserving the beauty of that country, and at enabling our people to stay here in Ireland and place their skills and hearts and minds at the service not of the backroom boys, the slick political operators, but of the country as a whole, their fellow Irish men and women.  A really good policy would consist of the implementation of such aims and I look forward on a future occasion to seeing some evidence of such a radical change of Government policy in a future Appropriation Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been represented to me that there are several Senators who, under the arrangement made this morning, may not get in to speak if we have a luncheon break.  It has been suggested, therefore, that we do not rise for lunch to accommodate such Senators.  I am in the hands of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a matter for the House to decide.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to speak.  I support the suggestion that we do not rise for lunch.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall support it by speaking through the interval.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="536" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The suggestion is reasonable and we ought to accede to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is agreed, then, that there will be no luncheon interval.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The debate on the Appropriation Bill in the shadow of Christmas makes the debate seem rather unreal or badly placed.  This is the second year when this has happened rather than having the debate in July when the Budget provisions are still fresh in the minds of Senators.  It was then more timely.  Senators had an opportunity of discussing the Budget. Now, however, the Budget is gone and forgotten and we may feel perhaps that by commenting on appropriations we might in some way influence the appropriations in the coming 12 months.</P>
      <P>I am afraid we are too late for that, that all major decisions have already practically been made in the Departments I therefore suggest to the Government that the present experiment, as far as the Seanad is concerned, has not been successful.  I suggest that we should try to move the debate back about two months, to the beginning of the new session when we would have an opportunity of debating details of appropriations, of criticising and suggesting reapportionment which might have a considerable influence on the Government's Budget arrangement in the following year.  The most we can hope to do at this time is to put some points down on the record.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I hope to keep to two sectors, and I shall open with education.  I realise that there is a motion dealing with university education before the House on the Order Paper and I will naturally refrain from referring to any matter that would be more appropriate on that motion.  It has been heartening in one sense to us in the university to see that at last the present appropriation shows that the capital programme is getting under way for university buildings and that in point of fact building has now reached a fairly satisfactory advanced state in our new science building in <Col N="537" /> UCC.  I am also glad to see the recent announcement in connection with UCG that they have a first instalment of their needs.  We hope that those will be followed up and that there will be an effort made to ensure that all our educational facilities are brought into line with modern conditions and that the grave neglect of the past 30 years is repaired as speedily as possible.</P>
    <P>It has been heartening also to know that there is a public awakening to the necessity for education, the desirability of it, and even the economic advantage to the nation of a wide diffusion of education.  It is also heartening that there is at last a tardy recognition that education costs money.  I think we may hope in the years ahead that more of our gross national product will be devoted to education and that our facilities will be considerably improved.</P>
    <P>The Appropriation Bill before us shows the outstanding increase there is in post primary education.  We must welcome this.  It is good to see that the rather premature influence in the past few years of regarding primary education as the No. 1 priority has now been replaced by the realisation that post primary education is the No. 1 priority.  That is all to the good. We may quarrel, and, indeed, the Minister for Finance may have second thoughts on priorities, when it comes to paying the bill for the innovations during the past year, such as the school fees and so on.  While they are laudable and there is no objection to getting something for nothing&mdash;in other words, not having to pay school fees&mdash; still if three-quarters of those who have been relieved of paying school fees would be able and willing to pay those fees, and would probably feel better for having to make the added sacrifice to pay those fees, at least for many years in the future while other priorities are receiving scarcer funds, because education is receiving increased funds, they should pay them.</P>
    <P>I also consider that we are doing a good job in introducing the free transport. This is a very desirable amenity in a modern world.  Again, I hope that the funds for it are not being provided at the expense of other priorities.  The <Col N="538" /> main priority is that of the profession of teaching.  This is the main bottleneck in our whole system and also the size of the classes.  There are 50 or more students being taught by one teacher and this is something which is obviously wrong.  We are anxious to hear from the Government what plans they have for teachers.  You can put up buildings in one year or two years but the training of teachers is something which takes years.  They take at least four to five year courses.  We are not conscious at the present moment so far as the Government or any of the authorities are concerned of any increase in the enrolment of teacher classes or an increased diversification of prospective graduates into teaching.</P>
    <P>Indeed, the conditions in the teaching profession do not help to attract the required number into the profession. I feel in this regard&mdash;this is something I have stressed in this House on a few occasions&mdash;that we should seek to take on part-time teachers. Many people, especially married teachers.  Who have raised their families, should be got back as much as possible in a part-time capacity or even on a whole-time capacity and, while rearing their families, they may still be able to contribute a part-time service.</P>
    <P>The biggest bottleneck in teaching is in the teaching of science and mathematics.  The Government should recognise that the greatest numbers of our science and mathematics orientated graduates have gone into engineering and industrial fields.  I suggest that it might perhaps be possible to get those, as a work of national importance, to contribute a few hours per week to teaching those subjects in our schools throughout the country.  This would help to relieve the bottleneck which now exists in those subjects in many rural districts.</P>
    <P>I welcome the recognition by the Government of the necessity for a comprehensive district plan.  I think this is the proper development and one which was called for here at a time when the comprehensive schools were on the go.  What is needed is that each district should have as many facilisocialist <Col N="539" /> ties and as wide a spread of education as possible.  It seems that we are swinging from one extreme to the other and in our concern for post-primary education we hear a lot of educational nonsense about students having the right to proceed right up to Leaving Certificate without ever having passed an educational test on the way up.  That is wrong educationally and it is impossible financially.  It is detrimental to the students concerned because it is only by showing how they appreciate the facilities that are made available to them by the hours of study they put in and by their performance at examinations that the students can be judged and it can be ascertained how they are equipped to proceed to further education.  I suggest if the school-leaving age is raised to 16 years then of course all must attend up to 16 years, but beyond the age of the compulsory limit only those who show they are capable of benefiting from further education should be allowed to proceed full-time at the taxpayer's expense to that education. It is wrong, if they have not shown the capacity for it before 16, to allow them to be, in many cases, just idling away their time for a further two years before eventually having to get a job.  Many of those would be far better if they had to face the hard decision at the age of 16.  If they have not shown sufficient interest or aptitude for education to pass the necessary tests then it would be better for them to face the hard reality of going out and working with the equipment they have got at that time.  By all means provide night classes that would be available for some of those who later on may realise their folly and may then in their early adulthood want to get back.  Allow the way back, but please do not base our system on having a crowd of morons sitting in classes between the ages of 16 and 18 merely wasting space and time and distracting other serious students who are anxious to avail of the facilities provided.</P>
    <P>One note on education: while all are concerned that it should be as widespread as possible and that we <Col N="540" /> should have as much co-operation as possible, let us then have as much charity as possible.  Charity begins by a clear recognition of the unselfish and the devoted service that has been given to this country by our teachers in the past, and especially by the Christian Brothers who provided at a pittance, ever since they were founded, education for our post-primary pupils second to none.  I speak as a former pupil of the Christian Brothers and I have the greatest pleasure on every occasion in acknowledging publicly my great debt to them.  It infuriates me to see the modern reformers who so glibly criticise the shortcomings of the work done by our Christian Brothers and Sisters and our lay secondary teachers without at the same time realising that any shortcomings that have been in the system&mdash;and there are shortcomings in it&mdash;are due to inadequate resources being given to the system by the State itself.  With a gross expenditure of less than £40 per pupil in our secondary system we have the cheapest secondary education system that is available anywhere in the world.  Give that system and those who are in that system the resources and we as a nation can feel confident that they will make the maximum use of the resources.  Please then, in our approach to education let charity dominate all; a recognition of our debt to the past and a recognition of our debt to those wonderful Orders is the only solid foundation on which we can advance, now that we have reached an enlightened age where we are prepared to put more resources at the disposal of our teaching authorities.</P>
    <P>There is, of course, running all through the question of education here an uneasiness on the question of consultations. In fact, it is more than an uneasiness.  It is a feeling that decisions are made without adequate consultation with the teaching bodies involved. That is to be deplored at all times.  I hope that the civil servants who have been rightly criticised for their approach to consultation in the past will learn from the recent decision to decentralise some Departments.  These decisions of the Government have been rightly criticised by the Civil Service associations for the lack of consultation with <Col N="541" /> the civil servants involved, quite rightly so, but I want to point out that this is the same lack of consultation from which the vocational groups have been suffering right down the years.  Therefore, I suggest that we should get on and realise that we are all partners in these enterprises.  We are all concerned with the national welfare and anxious to contribute to it.  Therefore, let us have mature, responsible and democratic consultations on our problems and on developments, especially in education, in the years to come.</P>
    <P>I cannot pass from this without commenting on the decision to decentralise the Department of Education to Athlone.  In fact, I will go as far as saying it is about the craziest decision I ever heard made anywhere.  One would think from the statements that all that was necessary to settle down a Department of Education was that the golf course should be of an adequate standard, that the clubs in the town were adequate.  There was no thought and I have not seen any question raised about providing the intellectual climate that is necessary for the functioning and the development of all Departments but especially of the Department of Education.  In other words, it is crazy to put the Department of Education anywhere but in a university city.  Unless the Government have immediate plans for building a university in Athlone I cannot see anything being worse for the morale, for the intellectual development and the intellectual activity of the Department of Education than placing it in a non-university town.</P>
    <P>I will pass on because I know there are many other speakers anxious to get in but I want to touch on a few other topics.  I am glad to welcome to the debate the new shadow Minister for Agriculture.  I refer to my colleague Senator Sheehy Skeffington.  Indeed, I feel it is well that people in the city should sit up and look at the agricultural situation.  I am not saying I agree with his diagnosis or prescriptions but it is good to see him venturing into this difficult and tangled arena. Nothing but good can come from such involvement.  We are, of course, at the cross roads.  In fact, we are past the <Col N="542" /> cross roads because we have missed the cross roads to Europe, with the EEC negotiations generally recognised as being just a failure with the attitude as adopted by France at present.  Indeed, I think in many ways that may be all to the good of this country because I cannot see how our industries would have stood up to the type of competition to which they would have been subjected.  It means we have to go back and again evaluate.  What is given in the appropriation account is based on the assumption that we were going to be members of the EEC by 1970.  If that major premise has fallen or is abandoned, then it follows that there has to be very radical rethinking on Government policy as to how we are to survive as a nation.</P>
    <P>As shown here, I cannot see too much evidence of that rethinking in the sense of voting.  It should have been obvious a year ago that our prospects of getting in were very slight. Indeed, the Taoiseach's odds of 50:50 were over-optimistic but we have to get back now and realise that agriculture, on which we based our mainstay in getting into Europe, is even now more so the mainstay of our economy, and we have to face up to the task of developing and marketing our products.</P>
    <P>I was very interested in Senator Sheehy Skeffington's quotation and his advocacy of co-operative farming.  The Senator will recall that many times in recent years here I have called for development of agriculture through the co-operative movement.  It is somewhat different from co-operative farming but there are many features in common.  If the small farmer is to survive and if farming is the only way of life for keeping the worker on the land, the type of leisure that modern man needs can come through development of the co-operative movement.</P>
    <P>I spoke at great length on that on previous occasions but it does not yet seem to have made an impact.  Again, looking at the Estimate we find there is provision here in the grant for the IAOS of an additional £18,000 for reorganisation.  I do not know what is meant by that but I would like to see <Col N="543" /> more activity.  We have had in recent years some excellent reports calling for modernisation of the co-operative movement.  We had the NAC Report which is now gathering dust in our libraries.  We had the interdepartmental Report which was rather reactionary and somewhat anti-cooperative in tone but yet it represented a report for serious study in conjunction with the NAC Report.  Earlier we had the <i>Ibeck</i> Report on Agricultural Finance.</P>
    <P>I should like to ask whether it is contemplated to take any action on these reports or why did we pay the cost involved in producing them and getting these excellent consultants if there is no anxiety or desire to follow up this work.</P>
    <P>To the co-operative movement I would like to see attached a co-operative centre with a pool of skilled workers equipped with the necessary machinery which would be available for doing various tasks on the farms. The owners of these farms would be entitled to employment in these co-operative communities and perhaps the owner of a small farm might spend most of his time working for the co-operative movement.  He would have the advantage of working in a group with modern equipment and at the same time his own work at home would be done by a gang of which he himself was one.  At the end of the year the profit and losses would be added up. It could be reckoned how much would be paid for his labour with the co-op. gang and how much for his own labour and the necessary adjustments made. That would also ensure that if the owner of the farm fell ill and was unable to milk his cows he could call in the co-op. to do it.  If he wanted a week's holidays, which modern man is entitled to, he could make such arrangements.  If he was a farmer who was elderly and was unable to cope with the difficult task of dairying any longer he need not have to face the terrible choice he has to make today and get out and, to quote a Senator who spoke recently, be at the mercy of the bullock economy.  He need not do that.  The co-op. could do the milking for him.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="544" /> Senator Sheehy Skeffington will recognise that there are many features in co-operative management.  There are many features that could be blended with those of other countries.  I am not advocating that we should import any other system lock, stock and barrel but we should critically examine what other countries have to offer and fit it into our natural surroundings.  We can keep our small equipment viable and let the small farmer benefit and make decisions as to what is to be done on his own 20 acres and, at the same time, provide opportunities and an acceptable working pattern with adequate machinery for the small farmer, provided we develop the co-operative movement adequately.</P>
    <P>The failure of the past has been a failure due to the fatalistic approach, that we must take it that we will lend so much per year more to agriculture. That is national suicide.  It is genocide and despite any strides we make in industry we cannot provide for that loss.  The burden is too great, There is enough to be done in industry to provide the new jobs required for what we hope is a rising population rather than provide for the loss in agriculture.</P>
    <P>I do not want to repeat figures I have quoted before showing that we have far fewer workers per 1,000 acres in agriculture than are in a thousand acres anywhere else in Europe.  Consequently, work on the land is only at the price of diminution of production. We do not need figures.  We are all convinced of the tremendous potential there is for increased production in agriculture if only we get down to the job.  But this is conditioned, of course.</P>
    <P>We have the question of selling the produce.  We have been far too conservative in that.  We can look at what the Danes, the Dutch, the Belgians and the New Zealanders have done.  Ever since the last war, did they at any time curtail production in dairy products because they felt, and, indeed, knew, that market conditions were difficult? Certainly not.  They increased their production, knowing that conditions were difficult but that the world needed these products.  There was a starvation problem in the world.  This was the <Col N="545" /> answer to it.  They had confidence in their ability to produce and market in competition with all others.  I suggest that, this time, we should take that same courageous outlook and face up to marketing.  At the moment, we are contributing £300,000 a year to the World Food Programme.  Well, it is something but it is not nearly enough. This programme&mdash;on a world scale, of course&mdash;should be expanded as fast and as quickly as possible.  It is required on the highest humanitarian grounds.  It has been appealed for by Pope Paul, by U Thant and by many other great figures.</P>
    <P>The wealthy nations have been asked to place more of their wealth at the disposal of the World Food Programme. What they are producing and giving at present is just a pittance.  If only they could give even ten per cent of what they spend at present on national defence, what an impact it would make on this programme.  While we are all in favour of this programme &mdash;indeed I think all our citizens will be prepared to make sacrifices for the development of this programme&mdash;it also has a very distinct economic significance for us, obviously, because the main line of food that is required is the dairy products line.  It is now becoming much easier to store and to transport dairy products.  Therefore, we are coming, in the next decade, we hope, into the era when the call will be not &ldquo;Can we sell our dairy products?&rdquo; but &ldquo;How much can we produce so that we can make the maximum contribution to the alleviation of world hunger?&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I think the Department of External Affairs, both on the highest humanitarian grounds and on the grounds of national advantage, should take a leading and a far more active role than they have taken up to now in pushing this programme and in goading the wealthy nations of the world into putting much more of their wealth into this programme than they have done. When we speak of nations increasing their gross national product by four per cent per annum, why not suggest, when they are doing that, that they should give at least one per cent of <Col N="546" /> that four per cent&mdash;25 per cent of their increase&mdash;to this food bank?</P>
    <P>We, as a small nation, could and should play a very valuable rôle because, being a small power, and therefore with no political overtones or undertones in our work, we would obviously fit very well into such a scheme.  If this comes about, it would offer our economy a much bigger market and much greater opportunities than EEC would ever offer.  Therefore, I appeal to our Government to throw their full weight behind this as a major plank of policy.</P>
    <P>The other item here which I find much too small is the contribution to the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign&mdash;a sum of £24,000 is provided in the present Estimates.  We are moving into an era of freer trade.  Indeed, we have unfortunately been subjected to a great deal of take-over by chain stores.  Where, products from all places are being pushed on our consuming public and are being advertised in the newspapers, on television, and so on, it is all the more urgent that we should try to bring home to our people, while there is still some time, the necessity to buy Irish.</P>
    <P>If we could only get our people to associate buying the Irish product with employing their own children at home &mdash;because that is what it means&mdash; if the era of free trade comes and if our people grasp sufficiently the significance of buying Irish&mdash;that it is the means of providing jobs for their own children at home&mdash;then they will buy Irish despite the sales pressures and even, perhaps, price inducements for imported articles.  I think the trade unions should play a much greater rôle in trying to get across the significance of this to their members, to make them feel that, behind that trademark which says &ldquo;Made in Ireland&rdquo; is the guarantee of their children's future at home.  No regulations of free trade can take the market away from a nation that is nationally conscious of the necessity to support it own industries.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Government, as a No. 2 plank&mdash;after the first plank of supporting the World Food Programme&mdash;to <Col N="547" /> foster a really dynamic approach to the &ldquo;Buy Irish&rdquo; campaign. Let us reach groups that have not been touched before and try to get the message across.  Rather let us ask them, in relation to the purchase of the foreign products: &ldquo;Do you want your children to have to emigrate?&rdquo;</P>
    <P>On the agricultural front, we cannot but deplore the continued disputes between the Minister and NFA.  The onus to end that dispute rests on the Government.  The Government should have read about the action of the French farmers which, indeed, went far beyond any action taken by our farmers.  In France, barricades were erected on roads: it went extremely far.</P>
    <P>Did that cause the Minister for Agriculture in France to sulk in his corner, to say he would not deal with that group, that they were trying to usurp Government authority?  Certainly not.  He had sufficient confidence in the standing of the French Government and the recognition by the French people that such an idea or a group usurping power was nonsense, that the work of Government is to go and meet people with grievances, see what the grievances are about.  The function of a Minister in any Department is, by and large, to be a leader of that group and to spur them on to great national effort.</P>
    <P>Otherwise, a Minister is a failure.  I am sorry that after twelve months in office we have come to realise that the present Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries, whatever his talents in other areas may be, has failed in that primary respect&mdash;the responsibility to lead his particular vocational group. Therefore, I call from the Seanad for his removal from that office.  I am not suggesting he be shifted from the Cabinet but I am suggesting there should be a reshuffle of Ministers and that the present Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries be put into a Department more suited to his talents. He, or any other Minister who over a prolonged period fails to live in harmony with the vocational group of which he is supposed to be the leader, should be removed.  That is what is <Col N="548" /> done in any country that appreciates the role of a Minister in democratic government.</P>
    <P>We cannot but deplore, in this or any other review, the action which removed certain members from public boards, through which the President of the IAOS was removed from the Agricultural Credit Corporation, a body in which obviously a person of his standing and, indeed, of his ability would be an asset, a body of which he should be an <i>ex officio</i> member.</P>
    <P>We had the removal also of Mr. Litten from the Chairmanship of the Agricultural Institute.  When the history of Irish agriculture comes to be written the name of John Litten will stand out in letters of gold with that of Steve Cullinane, the founder of Macra na Feirme and of the men who really got our agricultural community education conscious and got agriculture moving. I add to them that brilliant Father Collins who in Warrenstown has contributed so much.  I have never been so saddened by public action as I have been by those actions and I should not like to let this opportunity pass, in the dying days of 1967, to attest to the most disgraceful performance in the past year or in the past 60 years.</P>
    <P>Looking through the Book of Estimates one cannot but be struck by the Ministerial salaries, by the ridiculous situation that prevails, and continues to prevail, by which a Minister is paid little more than half what is paid to the Secretary of his Department.  We call for immediate action to remedy that situation.  Surely it is making a mockery&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Ministerial salaries are matters for legislation and legislation may not be advocated on this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that, but in passing I suggest that in the Estimates these figures are much too low.  In dealing with administration, far too much Ministerial time is taken up with public meetings and political affairs.  I should like to feel that once Ministers are appointed they have a 40-hour week and that they have not got time for all this travelling to meetings up and down the country, <Col N="549" /> as reported in the newspapers.  It is not fair to the Ministers and it is not fair to the country that we should have, in effect, part-time Ministers.</P>
      <P>I shall conclude by joining with previous speakers in protesting against the type of barbaric age that seems to be taking hold of the country.  I refer to the question of the Grand Canal, our national monuments and our Georgian buildings.  Anyone travelling abroad, in America, in England or in any of the small European countries, is struck by the great respect in which their symbols and monuments of the past are held.  We seem to be absolute philistines in that respect.  The canal here could be like the canals in Holland and be a source of pleasure to our people.  A type of national park could be provided along its banks throughout the city.  It is correct to say that the proposed closure will be the end of the canal and I have great pleasure in lending my support to those who have spoken against it.  I should also like to add my voice on behalf of those who protest against the fantastic idea of shifting national monuments.  It is unbelievable that it should have been contemplated and frightening to think it was carried out at Government expense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Gibbons) James Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Gibbons)</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not carried out at Government expense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Have we got the Parliamentary Secretary's assurance of that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>What the hell else is he doing?  Such a stupid question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Nothing so crazy has ever been attempted abroad.  It removes from those districts the uniqueness they have got&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>They are all going back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Once the pattern is established in this jet age it will not be possible any longer for people in <Col N="550" /> the capital city to go to the country to see these monuments in their natural habitat.  This will not just happen once. It is a pattern and we should fight against it and decry it.  I have been thrilled at the wonderful work done by archaeologists in this matter and particularly by my colleague in Cork, Professor Michael O'Kelly&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I was wondering when the Senator would come to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;one of the most eminent archaeologists in the country, who has lectured in Europe and elsewhere as a special guest of leading archaeological societies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Senator see the exhibitions in the museum?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>That type of misinterpretation of the work of Professor O'Kelly just displays ignorance of what the profession of archaeology is and the central contribution they can make to our community and to maintaining our friends.  This is one certain argument for autonomy in the university when you have people like Professor O'Kelly who are not afraid to come out and give leadership when leadership is needed, such as the movement of our national monuments.  I appeal to the Parliamentary Secretary for whom I have a very high regard, to see that this does not recur and to try to get back those national monuments and to realise that not by bread alone does man live and neither by humans alone does a nation live.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>Obviously the Senator has not seen the monuments on display at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>1967 has been one of the blackest, most depressing and worrying years which the Irish farmers have had to endure in a long time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a very good year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about the worry with which farmers are faced at the present time and with which they were faced in the early part of this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="551" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a very good year.  There was a very good harvest and cattle prices were good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Farmers at present in every part of the country do not know the moment when they will be sealed off if the scourge of the foot and mouth disease should raise its head in our country.  Therefore, it is true that they have worries at present.  It is at least gratifying to know that all sections of the community are foursquare behind the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries in regard to every effort and every regulation he plans and every precaution he takes against the spread of foot and mouth disease. The Minister has everybody's full support in everything he does about this because we all realise the tremendous catastrophy this would be for this country.</P>
      <P>Nevertheless, there has been failure by the present Government to formulate long-term plans for agriculture.  It has been more so in regard to agriculture than in regard to any other single sector.  The responsibility for our failure to deal adequately with the nation's chronic and social problems and, in particular, to deal with the economic disintegration of large areas of the country rests with the Government. Until recently Irish agricultural products were our greatest exportable commodities.  Our land and climate were our principal natural resources. In recent years the development of industries capable of being exported has made our national dependence on agriculture less absolute.  Despite this, and even assuming the national rate for the industrial development which could reasonably be expected in satisfactory national development cannot be achieved without a comprehensive and long-term dynamic programme for agricultural development, neither could any programme of industrialisation solve the very serious social and cultural problems which are the result of our not having had such a programme in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Over the years very large sums of money have been spent by the Government in an effort to improve farmers' incomes or at least prevent them from deteriorating too much in relation to <Col N="552" /> those of other sectors of the community. This subsidy to agriculture over the years has been as an essentially short-term kind in the form of subsidies of various sorts designed to deal with past social demands rather than forming part of any long-term plan to improve the competitiveness or the productive capacity of our Irish farmers. There is at present an enormous gulf between the State agencies seeking to help agriculture and the individual farmers on whom the success of any scheme must ultimately depend.</P>
    <P>There is a tendency for officials and policy-makers in Dublin to cut themselves off from the actual problems of the farmers.  They become involved in administration and tend to lose touch with realities.  An example of this has been the failure to involve farmers sufficiently in policy-making.  The agricultural advisory service attempts to bridge this gap by giving farmers proper help to improve their operation. At the present time far too much of the time of advisory officers is spent in finding <i>ad hoc</i> solutions to day-to-day problems and far too less time is spent on long-term and comprehensive planning.  Any national programme for research in agriculture on a scale which we generally recognise to be necessary must begin with a sound scheme of organisation to ensure that the investment is effective.  No such scheme can hope to succeed which is not based on the confidence of the individual farmers themselves.</P>
    <P>Local enthusiasm and initiative are essential for any successful programme in agricultural investment.  Such initiative and enthusiasm can only be stimulated by delegating responsibility to local level, delegating to the farmers and their advisory authorities the taking of decisions about the development of their farms.  In the past, decisions about such matters have had the effect of stifling local initiative in many fields apart from agriculture.</P>
    <P>Over the past few weeks we have read and heard much about the decentralisation of some Departments, the physical movements of Departments westwards.  However, in Fine Gael we prefer to advocate the decentralisation of the functions of those Departments, <Col N="553" /> especially in regard to agriculture. After the next general election we in Fine Gael propose to set up a rural development authority to implement such a programme.  This authority will be financed with long-term capital to be provided by the Exchequer.  We believe if we tackle our agricultural problems along those lines substantial additional capital will be available from the World Bank, for example, and will ease the strain on our own national resources.  The rural development authority which we envisage would take over the operating functions of the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries Advisory Service, the Agricultural Credit Corporation, the Department of Lands, the Administration of the Land Reclamation Scheme and other activities in the rural development field&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Those are all matters for legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am dealing with decentralisation and we advocate, rather than the actual physical movement of Departments, to decentralise the functions and, therefore, cut out a lot of the unnecessary red tape in getting these functions moving smoothly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is widespread recognition of the vast amount of research which needs to be done in numerous aspects of Irish agriculture.  It is essential that this research be effectively coordinated to avoid duplication and to ensure that the resources devoted to it contribute fully to achieving the long-term agricultural development plans.  The national agricultural research programme should be geared to meet the needs of the rural development authority and I feel that as far as agricultural research has gone in this country a tribute should be paid to the work of An Foras Talúntais. Under its excellent board the institute has achieved much and made great strides and why the Minister should have changed the board that achieved so much in quite a short space of time is a matter of amazement to me.  Dr. Walsh, the Director, and his colleagues at the institute deserve the country's best thanks and admiration for the hard work they have done and their <Col N="554" /> dedicated service to Irish agriculture. If I single out the institute's farms at Oak Park, Grange and Gowla it is because I have had the experience of visiting these places and of benefiting from their work and their experiments. I feel that the real value of the work of the institute is borne out by the many thousands of farmers who annually avail of the opportunity to visit these farms on the open days that are held during the summer months.</P>
    <P>I feel that the Department of Agriculture have ceased to give a lead to the farmers of this country.  It is regrettable that at present they are lagging behind the rest.  I feel the Minister should endeavour to rectify the situation.  I read that Mr. John Bland has said, and I support his view, that the contract rearing of dairy herd replacements and the organised marketing of beef calves from dairy herds should be established and organised in this country.  This is something that is quite widespread in Britain and other countries and yet no effort was made to introduce it here although it obviously has many advantages. For instance, dairy farmers of limited acreage are being constantly advised to specialise in milk production as a means of increasing the family farm income.  This advice entails the sale of both beef calves and dairy heifer calves at birth and the purchase of dairy replacements at the point of calving thus realising the additional acreage for the production of more milk.  Such sound advice is often difficult to follow because of the practical difficulty of being able to afford to purchase suitable cows at the right time.  I feel that the Department could very well give a lead and encourage this type of husbandry.  It could certainly fall in with the co-operation that Senator Quinlan dealt with at length some time ago.  The Department of Agriculture should and must give a lead in matters of his kind and be ever vigilant and ready to encourage new techniques and methods.</P>
    <P>In this regard I feel that the scale of agricultural grants is in need of reform.  I strongly urge the Minister to introduce immediately grants for unroofed silos or silo bases in an effort to <Col N="555" /> encourage the wider use of grass sileage in this country.  In the Northern European countries the use of unroofed silos and flat bases is very widespread and proving both profitable and easy to manage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>There are grants already for concrete paths.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but they are only at the rate of 2/6 per square yard and this, as the Parliamentary Secretary will agree, is not very encouraging.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMGibbons" hpid="Mr. Gibbons Mr. Gibbons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gibbons</NameTxt>
      <P>We would like them to be bigger but they are there though. There are grants for sileage paths.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>They are completely out of date and they do not induce or help the poor farmer to erect these things.  It is all right for the wealthier men who can afford to build whatever they like; they do not need the aid of grants but for the small men who would possibly benefit from new techniques I am afraid sileage is still a long way out of reach.  For that reason I would ask the Minister if the Department believes in a superior quality of sileage, that he should increase the grants especially for unroofed silos.</P>
      <P>As far as Local Government is concerned there are one or two small points I would like to mention.  The first one concerns people who are taking a driving test in order to qualify for a driving licence, people who might own a car with automatic transmission. They are forced to hire and take lessons on cars with manual gear changes.  I feel that is very unfair.  I understand that in Britain if a person owns a car with automatic controls he can use it for the test, but for some reason one cannot do that here.  This is unfair for a minority of people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I also feel the time has come when the Government might consider allowing some expenses to chairmen of county councils.  This is a voluntary post, but at the same time Lord Mayors get expenses and I feel that chairmen of county councils would be entitled to at least £200 to compensate <Col N="556" /> them in some way for the many hours each week they must spend in council offices signing the hordes of documents it is their job to do.</P>
    <P>I should like to appeal to the Government and to the Department of Local Government as a matter of urgency to bring the grants for group water supply schemes up to date.  I should like to remind the House that grants for these group water supply schemes are now over eight years old. Over the past few months we have witnessed a drastic, and in many instances expensive, change in the water supply schemes under the Department of Local Government.  The Minister decided that regional water supply schemes were to go by the board despite the fact that many communities had plans for regional water supply schemes, plans which cost many thousands of pounds.  In my county, I think, we have spent up to £26,000 on plans alone.  There are some schemes where it is found that now that the work has been completed the people concerned are unable to meet their liabilities or debts and the main reason is that grants have not kept pace with rising costs.</P>
    <P>I should like to see the £60 grant per house increased to at least £80, and the Minister paying three-quarters of the cost of the work, compared with the present two-thirds and £60.  Perhaps to most people this would not seem large.  To an old age pensioner living in a little cottage on a small pension the extra £5 means a lot.  If the Department are sincere in wishing to extend this excellent service to rural Ireland this should be a matter of urgency&mdash;the increase of the grant to three-quarters and at least £80 per house.</P>
    <P>I should like to refer to the plight of the thousands of road hauliers in this country.  Under recent legislation in the North of Ireland the Ulster Transport Authority was abolished and the Six County authorities proposed to grant freight operators licences on demand to anyone in the Six Counties. Licences would only be granted, however, to persons outside the State by arrangements with the Governments of <Col N="557" /> the Republic and Great Britain. Licensed hauliers in the Republic who have been carrying on cross-Border traffic for many years were told by the Department of Transport and Power that they were not eligible for the Northern licences.  The Department's attitude was that only the licences of those who had reciprocal arrangements with the former Ulster Transport Authority would be replaced.  This left only CIE and Donegal Railways and, I think, the Greenore Ferry Service.</P>
    <P>When the Licensed Road Transport Association took over this matter their prior concern was to preserve the <i>status quo</i> for the licensed hauliers in the Republic who had been operating for many years across the Border. They succeeded in getting hauliers whose Twenty-Six County licences covered them through the Border under this cross-Border arrangement. Experience has shown that the present cross-Border arrangement is weighed too heavily in favour of the Six County carrier.  The reciprocal arrangement is on a licence for licence basis but there is no restriction on the number of vehicles the Northern Ireland operator can use under a Six County tax.  In fact, I understand that there are 200 vehicles being operated by one specific merchandise licence granted by Deputy Childers to these Northern Ireland carriers.  This places our carriers in the Republic in an unfair position.  In addition, only the holders of merchandise licences in the Republic covered under the Border arrangements are covered for Six County licences.  Yet, all Six County licences get a Republic licence and can pick up or set down anywhere in the Republic.  I also understand that the Six County operator can only pick up a load in the Republic provided he brought a load down here.  That is not so.  Six County hauliers are coming down empty for traffic and taking it back up.</P>
    <P>This is unfair competition because, after all, the tax in the North is cheaper, the lorries are cheaper, fuel is cheaper, tyres are cheaper and we have hauliers in this country and each and every one of them are hardworking men who work long hours in a <Col N="558" /> dangerous and risky job.  The tax alone on their lorries is over £140 or £150 a year.  They are good importers and certainly they are not getting a fair crack of the whip.</P>
    <P>The Licensed Road Transport Association have asked for corridor facilities to be granted so that all licensed hauliers can pick up goods from the Six Counties and deliver goods there from any district to the Six Counties even though their merchandise licences did not reach the Border.</P>
    <P>I understand this particular arrangement has been in operation for some months or almost a year and that it will soon be reviewed.  I would appeal to the Government to give this heavily taxed small section of our community at least parity with the people in the North and ensure that licences should be given out on a vehicle basis rather than on the licence for licence basis. On 30th November last the Department of Transport and Power issued 87 merchandise licences to Six-County freight operators which allowed them to use 487 vehicles into the Six Counties while only 162 of the Republic lorries were allowed into the North. Surely there is a great case of injustice here and I would appeal to the Government and to the Minister for Transport and Power to rectify this situation.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I should like to pay a tribute to CIE who, in my experience in my own county, have been most accommodating and very agreeable and flexible in the organisation of the school bus services.  This was something new and it got away without a loss of time, work or organising and I feel we should pay small tribute where tribute is due to the excellent work of the CIE people and the way they were ready to help and meet every possible child.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>This Appropriation Bill gives to the Seanad the only opportunity it has to deal with all the facets of Government policy, opportunities which are available to Deputies in the Dáil on the various Estimates for the various Departments. We had an arrangement up to a few years ago that the Appropriation Bill came to this House at the end of July <Col N="559" /> or early in August.  That was unsatisfactory. We were always caught under the pressure of Ministers being tired, wanting to get away on holidays, of staff wanting to get away and of Senators themselves wanting to get their own holidays.  This experiment of taking the Appropriation Bill at this time of the year is, I think, an improvement over the previous arrangement but it is still not quite satisfactory.</P>
      <P>We have the situation here that we are trying to finish up this debate by this afternoon.  Arrangements have been made accordingly.  There are still some Senators offering to speak.  I do not want to delay the House unduly and therefore I shall bring down the number of points I wanted to make in this debate to about five or six and make them as briefly as I can.</P>
      <P>The first matter I want to deal with is the question of wages and salaries in relation to the economic situation. We have been told by the Minister for Finance, particularly, that the economy is in a very healthy state.  I think he was rightly making the point in the Dáil recently that the economic difficulties which brought about devaluation in Great Britain did not necessarily apply in this economy and that the reason for our devaluation was therefore different.  As reported at column 1302 of the Official Report of Dáil Éireann, volume 231, No. 9, the Minister, speaking in the Dáil last week, said:</P>
      <P>Any objective examination of the statistics shows this clearly, shows that far from our economy stagnating it is, in fact, moving forward at a satisfactory rate&mdash;four per cent this year&mdash;and I cannot see anything to indicate that we cannot keep up to that growth rate.</P>
      <P>In the Labour Party, particularly, we have been critical of the lack of growth in this economy.  Therefore, I want first of all to acknowledge that, this year, there has been that growth rate which is relatively good.  However, I want to take this a step further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are told that the economy is doing well.  The difficulties that <Col N="560" /> brought about devaluation in Britain, the attempts to halt wage increases in Britain, do not necessarily apply in this economy where the economic situation is different.  This economy is growing.  However, many of the people in this economy see no evidence of the health of or of the growth in the economy.  I refer particularly to wage and salary earners.</P>
    <P>In that same speech, and reported in the same column, the Minister said the real incomes of workers in industry rose by 6 per cent in the first half of 1967.  Again, this might have misled us or might give us to suppose that workers are better off.  I have not seen these figures but I should imagine that the explanation for this six per cent is, in fact, the overtime being worked in many industries, particularly in building and construction.</P>
    <P>The unfortunate situation is that, for many workers, their real standard of living has continued to decline in 1967. The tenth round of wage increases, the £1 per week, was advocated by ICTU and accepted by the unions as an interim increase in the particular difficulties which faced the economy in that year&mdash;1966.  It did not, at that time, compensate for the change in the value of money since the ninth round.</P>
    <P>Congress, as the Minister will know, has been insistent that the trade unions face their obligation and indeed their right to recover the standard of living which workers lost after the ninth round and which has been reduced considerably by the change in the value of money since then and in relation to which workers voluntarily held their hand in the circumstances facing the economy in 1966.  The Minister will also know that Congress has laid down a policy for its affiliated unions, which, amongst other things, calls for the restoration of the real wages and salaries lost by price increases since 1964, the protection of workers' real wages and salaries against price increases and the sharing by all workers of increases in productivity, including the increase in productivity since 1964.</P>
    <P>This is the policy of Congress which unions will be attempting to apply in <Col N="561" /> the year to come.  I want to draw the particular attention of the Minister for Finance to the situation we are facing. The cost of living index which in 1964 stood at 165 had gone up to 193 by November, 1967&mdash;a phenomenal increase in a period like this or, to express it differently, a 17 per cent increase in the cost of living since the ninth round was secured for workers. Those workers who have got the £1 per week, the tenth round, have got only partial compensation for the change in the cost of living.  There is still a gap there in that respect, an ever-widening gap.</P>
    <P>In this debate I want to direct the particular attention of the Minister to the plight of workers affected by the policy statement issued by the Government in relation to the economic difficulties which faced us at the time of the tenth round&mdash;and that was in the Spring of 1966.  It might be no harm, very briefly, to fill in the background of this.  I think the House will recall the long negotiations which took place between the employers and the trade unions, which ended in failure.  Congress took the initiative in saying that the trade unions should voluntarily restrain themselves to claims of £1 per week increase, in the circumstances then obtaining.  The Government, in March, 1966, following that declaration of policy by Congress, issued a statement calling attention to the difficult economic circumstances of the country. They referred to it as &ldquo;this critical year&rdquo; and went on to say, in a statement issued by the Government Information Bureau in March, 1966:</P>
    <P>It may be assumed that in the public sector, and this is recommended for the private sector, the Government do not contemplate this year any increase for persons earning more than £1,200 per annum.</P>
    <P>This policy has been held by the Government since in respect of all their servants and it has had effects in some other employments.  In a number of employments in the public sector and in private industry the ceiling of £1,200 was not applied&mdash;it was broken through&mdash;but in Government employment and in some other employments <Col N="562" /> in the public sector the ceiling still obtains.</P>
    <P>We have a situation that the change in the cost of living has seriously taken from the value of wages and salaries which obtained arising out of the ninth round.  Some workers have got some compensation for the change in the meantime&mdash;more needs to be done&mdash; but those affected by the ceiling declared by the Government in the critical year of 1966, have got no compensation whatever and I am suggesting that the Minister might take another look at the situation.  I refer him back to the statement made at the time, the fact that the emphasis was on a critical year; and when reading the statement I underlined &ldquo;this year&rdquo;.  The statement said:</P>
    <P>This year the Government do not contemplate any general increase for persons earning more than £1,200 per annum.</P>
    <P>That was in March, 1966.  We are now at the end of 1967 and the Government are telling us the economy is in a very healthy state.  Surely it is rank injustice, therefore, that the Government should continue a policy which they said was necessary in the critical year of 1966&mdash;which they said would apply for that year&mdash;that they should continue that policy up to the end of 1967.</P>
    <P>An injustice is being done to these people but there is another aspect of it which I should like the Minister to consider.  It is the prudence of continuing this situation.  It is very easy to let it drift but sooner or later the position will arise when recompense will have to be made for the change in the value of money. We remember the difficulties that were created in all quarters some years ago when civil servants got status increases, increases which were the subject of negotiation for years.  They were long delayed and eventually the Government had to face up to the situation that large increases had to be paid in order to rectify the position of most of their employees.</P>
    <P>That created difficulties for the Government.  It created difficulties for the trade union movement and it gave <Col N="563" /> rise to much unfair and unreasonable criticism at that time.</P>
    <P>I am suggesting to the Government it would be prudent to avoid that situation developing in the future.  As I have said, the change in the cost of living has been substantial and the reasons for the blanket ceiling in 1966 cannot any longer be said to apply. Therefore, it would be prudent for the Minister to look quietly at the position again.  It can be let drift and I suppose there is a temptation in all quarters to say: &ldquo;Leave this alone.  It will be taken up and rectified when further reviews of salaries and wages take place.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This is precisely what I am afraid about because you are then trying to close a wider gap and thereby leading to expectations in other quarters in which the interim increase of £1 a week has been operating.  The Government, therefore, may be creating difficulties for themselves and for other people if this position is allowed to drift much longer.</P>
    <P>I am speaking from memory, but I think I am right when I say that there is a view put forward by the NIEC&mdash; I underline the fact that I am speaking from memory&mdash;that adjustments in wages and salaries should be at shorter intervals, the implication being, I suppose, that they will therefore be of smaller amounts which would not be so difficult for the economy to absorb.  Here we have a situation for many Government employees, for many employees in the rest of the public sector where employers have adopted the Government's policy of applying a ceiling, in which it is nearly four years since there has been an adjustment in salary levels.  There may have been&mdash;I did not agree at the time&mdash;some merit in the attitude of the Government in March, 1966.  There is certainly no merit in persisting in this situation at the end of 1967.</P>
    <P>It is ridiculous to have a gap of nearly four years between adjustments in the incomes of these people.  It will lead to difficulties for everybody if it is not tackled soon by the Government: and I should like the Parliamentary <Col N="564" /> Secretary to direct the Minister's attention to this, to appeal to him in justice and prudence to look immediately at this question of the ceiling adopted and advised by the Government in March, 1966.</P>
    <P>The Congress policy in regard to wages and salaries makes particular reference to lower paid workers.  The people to whom I have just been referring are regarded by many people as being better paid workers, but the problem of the lower paid workers is, in my personal opinion, a very difficult one for the trade union movement and I do not think it can be solved by the trade union movement alone because you will find that most lower paid workers&mdash;there are many also in Government and local authority employments&mdash;are in marginal occupations.</P>
    <P>We had the situation recently in the bacon curing industry of a strike taking place.  I think the real difficulty, looking at it in retrospect, was the inability of the industry itself to recognise a situation where wages were unduly low.  The same applies in local authority employment where there are so many workers on less than £10 per week and where, if the trade union movement can put enough strength into it, the danger is that if you succeed in raising the level of the lower paid workers you are running the great risk of putting them out of employment.</P>
    <P>That is why I say I do not think this is a problem which can be solved solely by the trade union movement. I think the Government have a responsibility because the figures published recently show that the level of children's allowances paid here work out at less than one-fourth the average level of those obtaining in EEC countries and in the United Kingdom. I made a calculation at the time and I think that is what it worked out at. I think that this is a field where the Government have a responsibility to help the lower paid by a very substantial improvement in the level of family allowances.  Yesterday for a moment we drifted into the question of taxation and I might be allowed to say in passing that we strongly contend <Col N="565" /> in the Labour Party that the taxation necessary to bring a substantial improvement in the level of family allowances should be raised by way of direct taxation and not by indirect taxation.  Of course, when we accept this we accept that the workers we have been talking about earlier, the sector of people over £1,200, will have to bear a substantial share of this.  We accept that.  It will have to, by way of direct taxation, in order to help the lower paid workers.</P>
    <P>I cannot see in my experience that any holding back of money to better paid workers, any restraint by them in limiting any increases they can negotiate, helps in any way the lower paid workers.  I have never seen that if you agree to take a lower increase for a particular group for whom you are negotiating that that will help the lower paid workers in the same employment or any other employment.  The facts of life are such that that does not happen.  It is no solution to the problem of lower paid workers to depress the standard of living of the better paid workers.  That is what has been happening by reason of the Government's policy of maintaining a ceiling on those above £1,200.</P>
    <P>The second matter I want to deal with is in regard to decentralisation. Here again let me acknowledge that we in the Labour Party&mdash;I think we moved the motion on that very subject quite a number of years ago so it can be acknowledged and accepted right away&mdash;favour a policy of decentralisation. We advocated to the Government, the Fianna Fáil Government at that time, to adopt a policy of decentralisation, but I know in fact that since then two Government Departments have been set up and they have been set up in Dublin.  It seems to me to be appropriate that where you are, in fact, establishing a new Department, and you are moving people, they will voluntarily apply for promotion into any new Department.  When you are setting up a new Department that is the time to take steps in regard to decentralisation.</P>
    <P>We are in favour of decentralisation but I criticise the way it was handled by the Government, in regard to their <Col N="566" /> recent announcement and I criticise the reasons for it.  First of all, in regard to the way it was handled, there was a blatant lack of real consultation. We all agree that this is one of our real problems and is something which should be approached patriotically and that it should improve the level of employer-employee relations in this country.  When you have a Government acting in this way it is very bad example for private employers.</P>
    <P>Now, the Government have some example from which to draw.  The decentralisation policy is being pursued by the Government in Britain for some years and the Government here know how the problem there is handled.  They know that before any firm decision is taken as to a Department going to any particular city, it is a matter for quite a lot of discussion and consideration by the staff of that Department before arrangements are made for representatives of the staff to visit alternative cities.  It gives some choice to the staff concerned as to where they are going.  Maybe some people might say it is a choice of how you are going to be executed.  I may be too cynical but there is this meeting of the sections concerned instead of facing them with an announcement made by the Minister for Lands, which is read by the civil servants in the paper the following morning: &ldquo;You are going to Castlebar.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That brings me to the second criticism I want to make.  I believe this was a Party political decision.  It was made for Party political purposes and not for any other purpose.  You could not imagine the Government here giving any choice to Department of Lands civil servants asking if they would like to go to A, B, C or D.  That would not suit the Fianna Fáil Ministers.  That would not suit the Minister for Lands who wanted his political pride.  He wanted his Department in Castlebar.  I believe that is the reason for the way this decision was taken.</P>
    <P>Much has been said about the hardships that will be involved for the people concerned.  There are very real hardships involved.  It is all right to say that the Minister or the Government <Col N="567" /> will give the option to people to volunteer to go to Castlebar or Athlone, but I think we all know from the information we have to hand that, in fact, the staffing cannot be dealt with by way of volunteers.  There will not be sufficient of them.  I would be very happy if the Minister or the Parliamentary Secretary could contradict me and say: &ldquo;Yes, in fact, it would be possible to solve this problem by way of volunteers.  People will be willing to transfer to those new places.&rdquo;  Another criticism I want to make about this is the choice of the town.  Again, I am speaking from memory, but surely the NIEC were advocating some time ago that we should concentrate on growth centres, that this general idea of hoping to set up industries in every little village and town around the country was simply not feasible no matter how desirable it would be and that if we wanted to make progress we would have to pick a number of places.</P>
    <P>Galway was mentioned, Waterford was mentioned, Limerick was mentioned and Cork, of course, last but most important.  Progress has been made in this direction.  An industrial site is in process of being established and has been built in Waterford.  I think progress has been made in Galway, I am not clear as to how far, but surely places like that which we have consciously picked as growth centres would be appropriate places to send Departments in the process of decentralisation, where civil servants could be absorbed in the local community and where they would not exist in a ghetto.  For example, in Galway there is the university available.  In Waterford we hope to eventually have a college of technology, another good place where the movement of a Department would not create as much hardship for the people concerned.  They would be in a larger centre and it would help in the growth of these centres which we have already consciously decided should be regarded as growth centres.  Instead there was a Party political decision made.  It suited the Minister for Lands to get his Department to Castlebar and that was the end of it.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="568" /> Senator O'Quigley yesterday criticised the Minister for Labour for his attack on the general president of the Irish Transport and General Workers Union.  Let me say at the start that we in the Labour Party are not a bit afraid of attacks and criticism.  In fact, we love it because it is an acknowledgment by this Government that the Labour Party is the Party to fear; that the Labour Party is the Party that will take power from them eventually.  We welcome this sort of criticism.  We had it in Cork and the Cork electorate in the by-election gave a suitable answer.  However, this was something more than a political Party criticism and this is where we take issue with the Minister and the Government.  It was a personal abuse of the general president of the largest union in this country.  It was not simply a disagreement on policy.  I read it and I regard it as a personal attack of a very low order.  I resent it on that account.  It was deplorable coming from the Minister for Labour who is charged with the responsibility of trying to improve employer-worker relations.  What was most nasty about it was the implication that because this official did not agree politically with this Government, did not agree with Fianna Fáil, he was, therefore, unfit to hold an office in Bord Fáilte, to be a member of the board of Bord Fáilte.  That was what was read and understood by the people in the newspapers.  Maybe the trade union movement are being told that to secure positions, to be nominated to the boards of semi-State organisations in the future, one will have to be something more than a trade union official, one will have to be a member of Fianna Fáil.  I hope we will be able to stand up to that.  I think we have more guts than to be kicked around in that way.  This is a man who is the principal officer of the largest union in this country.  All of us who know him, whether we agreed with his viewpoint at various times or not, accept that he is a most sincere individual, hard-working and self-sacrificing, sacrificing himself for his members and the ideals in which he believes.  We resent bitterly the sort of personal abuse that was heaped on that <Col N="569" /> man.  We do not mind political arguments. We love them, in fact, but this sort of attack by a Minister for Labour and his reference to the fact that this man was a member of the board of Bord Fáilte was deplorable.</P>
    <P>The next item I would like to deal with is the NAC.  Maybe the climate is changing.  We have had assurances from all sides of the House that all parties, the NFA included, support the Minister for Agriculture in any steps he may think necessary to protect the country from the ravages of foot and mouth.  I hope in this changing climate there might be a bit of back tracking. We in the trade union movement have always advocated that agriculture should be represented on a national economic committee.  It should simply not be a national industrial committee, it should be a national agricultural committee.  It is no solution to simply take people from the NAC appointed by the Minister and of whom the Minister is chairman and place them on top of the NIEC.  That is out as far as I can see.  It is no solution but maybe in the changing climate an opportunity might arise, without scoring any political points, for the Minister concerned to quietly wind up the NAC but, at the same time, come to some agreement or arrangement to have agriculture represented on a national economic committee.  I shall leave that subject.  It is not a subject on which any of us wants to score political points.  We regret the situation which has developed in agriculture over recent years.  I feel we are all sufficiently patriotic to hope that these will be overcome and I do not want to create any difficulties at all.</P>
    <P>The next point I want to mention briefly is the Vietnam issue from which I think we are running away.  I thoroughly agree with Senator Sheehy Skeffington that our Minister for External Affairs should come out openly and support the proposals of U Thant for peace in Vietnam or for some improvement in the situation there.  Of course, we have more&mdash;and this is something that we as a Catholic country are conscious of&mdash;than the proposals of U Thant.  We have the <Col N="570" /> appeals of the Pope for peace in Vietnam repeated again and again and again.  We seem to be silent on this issue.  There is some fear that we might hurt the feelings of the US.  I must confess that I have every sympathy for the US because I think they were put in a bad position by France in regard to Indo-China&mdash;Vietnam&mdash;but they have compounded the position ever since and they seem to be making the position worse week after week.  I think what they are doing is probably destroying the whole moral fibre of the nation in the situation in which they find themselves.  I certainly do not want to avail of this opportunity to make any attack an the US.  I have the utmost sympathy for the position in which they have found themselves and their apparent inability to extract themselves from the deplorable situation in which they find themselves in Vietnam. Here we have the proposals of the Secretary-General of the United Nations and I do not think it is taking from the dignity of even the United States that they should accept and go along with the proposals of U Thant.  Whatever about hurting the feelings of our United States friends, our Minister on behalf of this country should be prepared to get up in the United Nations and support U Thant's proposals.</P>
    <P>I do not want to dwell on the subject.  Other people want to speak, but may I briefly go back on one point, and perhaps other people will support me, if there is time?  It relates to the injustice and to the imprudence which exists in regard to continued statements which might have been necessary in the circumstances of the 1966 wage and salary increases.  This was a statement made by the Government in what I call this critical year.  In this year, that is in 1966, no increase was contemplated for persons earning more than £1,200 per annum, That policy was recommended for this year, that is 1966.  It is now the end of 1967.  We are told the economy is sound and completely different from the economy in Britain, and I am suggesting that it would be prudent and that it is time for the Government to look vitally at the problem of this issue and quietly withdraw the ceiling.  Otherwise, they <Col N="571" /> would only create for themselves large and difficult problems for the future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Our Minister for External Affairs at the United Nations is not, I am sure, awaiting the advice of Senator Sheehy Skeffington or Senator Murphy as to what he should do to assist in bringing to an end the unfortunate situation in Vietnam.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>He would not despise that advice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We are incensed in this country by a lot of strange people, and I am afraid I will have to include Senator Sheehy Skeffington and Senator Murphy in this unpopular front, in regard to this matter.  Many people who know very little about what happens abroad and who are prone to serious misdirection, are always appearing on the publicity bandwagon whenever there is anything of a critical nature at issue from Greece and Vietnam and a lot of noise is being made in many quarters. This morning we were witness to a Senator, who had jumped on the bandwagon with regard to the situation in Greece, telling us that we should declare in favour of setting up a democratic Government in Greece led by the King.  Fortunately, the mover of the silly resolution withdrew it when he found the King was gone, but it is typical of the way people jump on the bandwagon so as to get publicity.  We have in this town groups of people sending around circulars and making telephone calls about Vietnam bombing. This inspires Senator Sheehy Skeffington to speak in the Seanad as I take it he is the spokesman of this group on any and every issue which can be used for certain sinister purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Vietnam is one of them and it is sickening to listen to Senator Sheehy Skeffington and Senator Murphy on this question.  The position in Vietnam, as Senators should know, is quite simple.  There can be peace negotiations at any time, tomorrow morning, provided that Ho Chi Minh and others agree to negotiation.  President Johnson <Col N="572" /> says he will meet them anywhere on land, on sea or in the air.  The United States stopped the bombing in the hope that something would happen and the only thing that happened was the infiltration of 25,000 regular troops of the Ho Chi Minh army into the Mekong Delta in South Vietnam and the fact that the bombing had stopped had no effect whatever.  Every effort was made on the western side to get these people to the conference table but without success.</P>
    <P>Another thing that seems to have missed Senator Sheehy Skeffington is that this is not a unique capitalistic imperialistic operation.  This is an operation in which there are the armed forces of Australia, New Zealand, North Korea, the Philippines and Thailand along with forces from the United States.  When I get circulars from people in Dublin asking me to attend a protest meeting or put my name to a document which contains a lot of other signatures of very worthwhile people, misled, no doubt, I say to myself that surely a sensible person like Senator Sheehy Skeffington should stop trying to use Seanad Éireann for getting publicity for crackpot groups like those people about whom I am speaking.</P>
    <P>Vietnam is not as easily solved as the Senator thinks and even U Thant, unremitting in his efforts to get peace not only in Vietnam, but in Cyprus, and in other parts, can get little effective support.  Our Minister for External Affairs, and Senator Sheehy Skeffington was obliged to pay tribute to him at the start of his remarks, has since 1957 been in the forefront in the United Nations of every effort that was made by the small nations to bring influence to bear on the great powers in regard to the maintenance of peace and prosperity among the nations.  The Senator will see how difficult it is to get anything done by them by the withdrawal of our proposal for the financing of a peace-keeping force in the United Nations last week.</P>
    <P>It is all right about signatures and support for the United Nations but I recommend to the Senator to take time off at midnight, if he is not too immersed in the story of Greece, to <Col N="573" /> listen to the United Nations Radio and he will hear some interesting things about people at the United Nations and about the efforts being made by many small nations to bring the big powers to a sense of reality.  That is all I want to say about Vietnam.</P>
    <P>With regard to other points made by Senator Sheehy Skeffington in which he condemns Fine Gael for their attack on Mr. Aiken some years ago when he attempted to have the problem of China placed on the agenda of the United Nations for consideration, I am afraid he omitted to mention that along with Fine Gael&mdash;of course he has the Fine Gael mentality&mdash;the most active and vociferous critic of the proposal was Professor Quinlan who today inspired us again with his great knowledge of the cure-alls for the various ills from which we are supposed to suffer.  One of the cures suggested was the immediate removal of the Minister for Agriculture.  One would think that the Minister for Agriculture had done nothing, that he was a complete failure, whereas there can be no doubt whatsoever that his handling of the present emergency created by the foot and mouth disease in Great Britain has won the admiration of people of all classes of political opinion here and in Great Britain.  He has proved himself one of the most capable Ministers ever to be in charge of that Department.  If Senator Quinlan has the belief that he has fallen down in consultation with the farming community I would remind him that the much-derided NAC, which is operating despite NFA boycott, can be availed of to hear the views of farming people on the agricultural policy that should be pursued for the good of this country.  If Senator Quinlan wants to make any constructive effort to bring that about, he should use his influence with the leaders of NFA to get them to have sense, to realise that the door is wide open at any time they wish to talk turkey and that there will be a welcome for them in doing so.  The Minister has said that on many an occasion.  There is no reason in the world why they should have any grievance in that regard.</P>
    <P>One thing that strikes me about Senator Murphy's speech relates to this <Col N="574" /> question of TUC having obligations to restore the standard of living of its members.  I was glad he made reference to the lower-paid workers.  At a Trade Union Congress, I think in Cork, a couple of years ago, of which Senator Murphy was then President of the Congress, there was some discussion on the difficulty of ensuring proper wages and salaries for lower-paid workers as that was taken by the higher-paid people as an incentive to go looking for their share of the spoils also.  That is the difficulty.  Congress have obligations to ensure not alone a decent standard of living for all their workers but also that there is employment available and not wreck the employment which is available.  Congress have obligations to ensure that, in the conditions facing the world today, they play their full part.  In that regard &ldquo;their full part&rdquo; includes the sale and contribution of Irish-manufactured goods.</P>
    <P>Irish-manufactured goods give work to thousands of Irish workers who are members of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions.  If the factories making these goods shut down it will be very hard to find alternative employment.  I made an appeal in this House a few years ago to the leaders of TUC to do something about what I regard in my experience &mdash; and I have consulted many others&mdash;as the failure of workers in the distributive trade to push the sale of Irish-manufactured goods.  That was a few years ago.  I am now repeating that appeal.</P>
    <P>I had an experience in this regard in the past couple of months.  It reminded me of a serious situation which existed here many years ago. Deputy Colley, the Minister for Industry and Commerce, referred to this in a recent speech when he spoke about the danger of the mail order business when full free trade conditions obtain in this country.  Many years ago, before we had tariff barriers and boundaries against the importation of foreign goods, a vast mail order business was done in this country, particularly by British firms.  I remember that, week after week, catalogues were sent by cycle companies, pram companies, gramophone companies and all types and varieties of clothing companies <Col N="575" /> throughout Great Britain addressed to dentists, artists, engineers, professional men: every teacher got one of those catalogues week after week.</P>
    <P>A vast supply of goods was involved. An easy payments system was made available to anybody who signed the coupon and sent it off.  Already, with the prospects of complete free trade, many British firms are again beginning this catalogue distribution to Irish homes.  If TUC does not face its obligations to educate and inform the workers on the dangers which that mail order business will present, and also on the dangers now presented by the failure of many shop assistants to do their bit in regard to the selling of Irish goods, they are bringing down on themselves the chaotic conditions which inevitably will exist when Irish factories producing these goods must go out of production.</P>
    <P>It is all right to say that they are doing their best and that the employers are guilty.  I have been in stores in this city in the past few weeks.  I have seen a vast array of foreign goods on the shelves and on hooks.  For instance, I asked for socks.  The assistant behind the counter was as Irish as anybody else.  That assistant showed me three different boxes of socks, not a single one of which was made in Ireland. The socks in each box were foreign-made.  I had to ask if they had not any Irish-made socks.  Yes they had.  He presented them.  Why he did that, I do not know, but it is typical.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Why did the Senator not walk out of the shop?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>My wife had the same experience in regard to coats in the same shop.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Why did she not walk out of the shop?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a big line of coats, all foreign models.  She asked if no Irish coats were available and was told &ldquo;Yes&rdquo;, that they were up at another corner of the shop&mdash;beautiful tweed coats.  There was no indication from the assistant that the Irish coats were better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="576" />
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Senator would allow me to interrupt?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Murphy does not like to take the medicine, I cannot help him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ó Maoláin never interrupts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington appealed for the protection of the Chair earlier today when unruly elements were interrupting him.</P>
      <P>I hope Senator Murphy will take those remarks in the spirit in which they are made.  Some effort should be made by TUC to drive home to the workers that, on every occasion they are in a position to influence the sale of a product, they should push the Irish product because, by so doing, they are safeguarding their own employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's criticisms are destructive.  He will not acknowledge the constructive efforts made by Congress.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be well if Senators would cease interrupting because so little time is left in the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I acknowledge any constructive efforts made by Congress.  I hope that in the efforts to secure the further wages of which Senator Murphy speaks, Congress will have regard to the development of the unfortunate situation in Britain where, under a Labour Government, so undisciplined did the trade unions become that they practically wrecked any chance the Labour Prime Minister had of pulling his country out of the &ldquo;red&rdquo; this year.  If the Irish Congress of Trade Unions take suitable action to ensure discipline amongst their members I shall certainly acknowledge with gratitude that they are playing a noble part in helping this country to survive&mdash;rather than the cut-throat action the trade unions have perpetrated on Harold Wilson in Britain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator O'Quigley gave us two hours of a banshee wail followed by Senator McDonald with the allegation that the farmers had a bad year, followed by <Col N="577" /> Senator Sheehy Skeffington on the amenities and beauty of the canal. Having heard these intellectuals whinging about the closure of the Grand Canal and, at the same time, moaning about the failure of the Government or of somebody else to provide decent housing, sewerage facilities and the rest of it, I ask myself if they have gone crackers altogether or if they can get away with that kind of bluff forever.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Tell us about the shortfall in new jobs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>For two hours and 20 minutes, I listened to Senator O'Quigley yesterday.  I said nothing, though I was sorely tempted to do so. I must say that Senator O'Quigley, with his loneseome story of the many miles which Ministers travelled and of the 70,000 miles which each car does&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;almost depressed me, but not quite.  Senator O'Quigley attempted to indicate that Ministers were never in their offices, that they were always eating dinners or attending meetings and could not be expected to administer the affairs of the Departments to which they are designated.  Is that not typical of the poison pen scribe employed on the Fine Gael Sunday newspaper in Dublin?  I wonder if Senator O'Quigley happens to have gone asleep with a copy of that newspaper, because only recently the same type of muck-raking appeared in it.  I expected better from the Senator and I hope the next contribution he makes will be much more sensible and much shorter.  It was really too long.  Senator Quinlan referred to the need for a dynamic approach.  That is a great phrase of all the pseudointellectuals. What sort of approach is it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>It means to get cracking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator goes outside I will come in person instead of sending my seconds.  I have <Col N="578" /> undertaken to allow Senator FitzGerald in by 3 p.m. so I give him the floor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know if I shall raise the tone or lower the temperature&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>You will not be interrupted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the House had better let me get going. Among the statements made in reference to our economic situation we have those by Government Ministers who have said that our present economic difficulties are due to circumstances outside our control, to external events, to economic conditions elsewhere, and that what has been happening here has been a sort of sympathy movement with economic events outside, in other countries.  This is not altogether true.  What is true is that in a certain difficult situation created by our own mismanagement of our own affairs, some external difficulties, not of great importance to us, aggravated our situation and made things more difficult for us; but our difficulties go beyond the temporary and not very extreme economic situation with which Europe has been faced.</P>
      <P>In 1964, when there was economic growth in small countries in Europe at a fairly rapid rate, in this country the economy was expanding at the cost of massive inflation.  We had a 12 per cent wage and salary increase which itself might have been accepted if it had not been aggravated by other conditions. At the same time, we had an increase in Government expenditure, an increase in taxation, of one-third in a period of two years, and an increase in capital expenditure of 50 per cent.  In 1964 there was an increase of 23 per cent and in the same year credit was allowed to be increased by 14 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The cumulative effect of all these things, some of which were not within the competence of the Government to control but some of which could have been controlled, were felt.  Unfortunately, at the same time, some external events transpired which aggravated the difficulties.  The British import surcharge has been mentioned by the Government.  The Government are <Col N="579" /> too modest; they do not take credit for the fact that their policy provided for marketing grants and for ensuring that the payment of those marketing grants would not be held against us in other markets.  That action by the Government then, for which I have already paid them tribute, saved industry in this country because we did not feel the full impact of the surcharge. However, one cannot recognise simultaneously that they did the right thing then so that the effect of the surcharge was not only minimised but practically eliminated, and give the import surcharge as an excuse for the adverse situation of the economy in 1965.  The effects of the surcharge were largely mitigated by the Government steps. Therefore it was not a major development in our economy in that year.</P>
    <P>It has been pointed out that there was a slowing down in the British economy.  This is true, but if you examine it in detail you will find the volume in Britain continued to rise quarter by quarter at an annual rate of from 2½ per cent to 3 per cent.  The fact that it did continue to increase has gone against Britain since then because the economy was overstrained by the excessive expansion in that period.  The fact is that the economy continued to expand right up to the end of last year, and while there was some slow down in 1965 and while British imports did not increase as much, this was not a major but an aggravating factor in the difficulties we created for ourselves.</P>
    <P>There was a fall in the net capital inflow which lasted only for a few months and which any well-run economy could have taken in its stride. Since then, it has increased to new and unexplained heights.  To attribute our difficulties in the last two years to these external causes could not therefore be justified.  They helped to some degree to aggravate our difficulties.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>The Central Bank attributed them to those causes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It did not.  It mentioned external causes as being relevant aggravating factors.  The report of the NIEC pinpointed the three <Col N="580" /> causes I have mentioned as being the main causes of our difficulties, which were due in part, but only in part, to outside events.  If we had not been in a prior inflationary situation we would not have faced the difficulties we did face.  The Economic and Social Research Institute has given a diagnosis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> Which do you accept&mdash; that or the Central Bank?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the report of the Economic and Social Research slightly more readily than the Central Bank.  The Central Bank had a bias towards conservatism.  I shall quote from the report of the Economic and Social Research Institute:</P>
      <P>An unstable boom was allowed to develop in the early part of 1964 and to continue until the middle of 1965.  The unprecedented size of the ninth wage round was a major factor in causing this boom but cannot be regarded as the sole cause of the boom . . . .  The very rapid rise in the Retail Sales Index in 1964 took place because consumer credit was allowed to rise <i>pari passu</i> with industrial earnings.  Had hire purchase controls been tightened and the growth of personal and professional allowances been checked early in 1964, the rise in personal consumption would have been much more modest.  Similarly, the jump in Exchequer expenditure in 1964 cannot be attributed solely to the increase in wages and salaries.</P>
      <P>Not only did wages and salaries go up but the Government should have moderated the growth.  The report continues:</P>
      <P>Had action been taken to offset this increase in wages by some curtailment in the volume of Government consumption rather than to augment it by an explosion, the pressure of Government spending on Final Demand could have been less sudden and less severe.</P>
      <P>The report goes on to say:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The authorities were mistaken in early 1964 in failing to counteract by appropriate policies with regard to the volume of public expenditure and <Col N="581" /> the availability and attractiveness of consumer credit, the abnormally long rise in wage and salary rates which had been permitted to take place at the beginning of that year.</P>
    <P>Then it goes on to say:</P>
    <P>The action which should have been taken in 1964 was finally forced on the authorities in the middle of 1965.  By this time there was little upward pressure on demand from rising wages, so that the effect of the measures, instead of moderating the rate of growth, as they could have done in 1964, was to cause an actual downturn in economic activities.</P>
    <P>Having described those economic restrictions as appearing &ldquo;rather too vigorous&rdquo; the Economic Research Institute goes on to say that:</P>
    <P>the restrictions introduced in 1965 were maintained for far too long in 1966.  In the first half of 1966 the balance of payments had already recovered.</P>
    <P>It then refers to:</P>
    <P>the extent to which the economy had been over-deflated in the earlier part of the year.  The timing of short-term economic policy measures since 1964 has been far from ideal.  Decisions have been delayed so long that they have had destabilising effect rather than the stabilising effect which surely should be aimed for.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> So you believe in modern inflation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe in inflating the economy in a timely manner and also in slowing it down when it is necessary.  It has been borne out that the Government should have adopted this policy.  I am suggesting that we must learn from the mistakes of recent years, and I am quoting from the Economic Research Institute which goes on to say:</P>
      <P>Deliberate fiscal action in budgeting for a deficit or surplus in particular years seems to be out of favour as a policy tool.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This has never come into favour.  It goes on to advocate policies involving <Col N="582" /> changes in the volume of public expenditure.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Finance has claimed that the Government did deflate the economy in 1964 and 1965 and he has given reasons for this.  First of all, he said that the Government had spent rather more than they should, but he could not remember whether it was £1 million or £1½ million, on housing and sanitary services.  I can give the Minister full credit for it being £1½ million.  He also said that the building industry had a lot to do with it too but it did not prevent them cutting down on housing in 1964.  He also referred to the removal of hire purchase restrictions in the late summer of 1966.  Those restrictions, when they were removed, I remember some time afterwards that somebody drew my attention to a fact which I missed at the time.  I made inquiries to know what those were removed on.  I was concerned that I had missed it.  When I inquired in the appropriate sources I found that that was in fact purely a technical measure to help a particular difficulty which had arisen in one particular industry.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> What were the sources?  You should quote them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I got my information from official sources.  I wanted to find out what had happened. The information I got was that it just related to a particular area and a particular industry and was not, in fact, a general inflationary move, which is what the Minister for Finance is attempting to claim it was.  He also mentioned the extra credit provided by the Central Bank and the extra spending in the Budget although it was set out to be a balanced Budget.  There was no attempt to inflate in the last Budget.  It was rigidly balanced.  Finally, he mentioned the increase in the public capital programme. The fact is that many of those measures have been utilised to the full. Senator Yeats was critical about our external reserves.  He spoke about a surplus.  A surplus means that we are living at a much lower level of capital <Col N="583" /> investment and living standards than we can afford at a point in time, at a time when we have had a steady inflow of £40 million to £50 million and we come out with a deficit of £20 million.  We have instead a surplus of £10 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> You believe in inflation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator stop interrupting?  Senator FitzGerald has only one hour in which to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not talking about inflation.  I am talking about keeping the economy moving ahead.  I do not suggest that we should inflate to anything like we did in 1964. I am suggesting that we can live within our means.  The reason we have not is because the Government set out to have an external surplus.  It is because they have misjudged the situation and have failed to inflate the economy sufficiently. The Minister has claimed that this year we will see a four per cent growth rate and that this is the kind of growth rate which the people in Europe like to see.  That is not a sufficient answer.</P>
      <P>This country has come through a period in which for two years our growth has been severely restricted.  We have not succeeded in achieving the growth rate which was fixed for one year of the programme.  The Minister has given on one occasion a figure of 2.5 per cent in 1965 and a figure of .75 per cent in 1966.  He gave those figures in a television discussion in which I also took part a couple of weeks ago.  In the Dáil he has given a figure of 2.3 per cent in 1965 and a figure of 1.6 per cent in 1966.  However, we are now at last moving again into a period of growth but we could have expanded much more rapidly this year. We could have caught up on some of the growth losses but we did not because the Government are so slow to act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Government have travelled through the past 18 months without taking action to get the economy moving again.  Again, I am quoting <Col N="584" /> from the Economic and Social Research Institute which said:</P>
    <P>The balance of payments situation would appear to permit a higher rate of growth in 1967 than appears likely to be achieved on the basis of present policies.</P>
    <P>The institute goes on to stress the need for:</P>
    <P>much more continuous watch on the performance of the economy and a willingness to take decisions more frequently</P>
    <P>and not waiting for 18 months.  The institute also says:</P>
    <P>It also involves willingness to take action on incomplete evidence.  If decisions are delayed until all the relevant statistics are available, often many months after the events they describe, it is a near certainty that official weight will be applied to the wrong end of the economic seesaw.</P>
    <P>This is what has been happening in this country during the last three years. That has a more long-term importance. I will refer to it later on in reviewing the Second Programme. Were they waiting until they could get the actual statistics?  If they wait for the full statistics in industrial action for 1966 it will be then 1969 or 1970, and there is not much point in leaving the progress until then.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Finance in the Dáil referring to the proposals of the Fine Gael Party for a more flexible economic policy was very critical of the Fine Gael proposals.  He wanted to know what real benefit there could be from reducing duties for a few months and then putting them back on again in order to make good the revenue lost and he said that it was quite a nonsensical proposal.  This shows several misconceptions simultaneously.  First of all, there was no suggestion by Fine Gael that taxation should be cut and restored again shortly in order to get the money back.  The point that was made was that we needed to reflate the economy now, should have done so before, and should be getting it moving rapidly again but should be prepared, if and when there is a significant wage round, to take steps to control the growth of the economy again at that <Col N="585" /> point.  It is to keep it moving evenly despite the disappointing fact of two yearly wage rounds that we recommended reflation of the economy now by reductions in taxes or increases in Government taxation should be then checked again by a re-appraisal of that taxation policy in line with the policy advocated by the Economic and Social Research Institute.  That is what we proposed and there is nothing in any Fine Gael speech that would give the Minister grounds for saying that we advocated getting money back by re-imposing taxation.  For him to say that this is a nonsensical proposal is a remarkable statement by a Minister for Finance 35 years after Lord Keynes first put forward his ideas on economic management.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are all Keynesians now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Everybody except Deputy Haughey apparently. He regarded it as quite a nonsensical proposal.  The truth is that our annual budget system is not appropriate for the management of a modern economy for the purpose of capital programmes. We must have four- and five-year programmes such as we had in relation to the Second Programme for Economic Expansion.  Every year the capital programme has to be separately approved by the Government and all activity is held up until it is approved. There is no system by which local authorities can get ahead with their spending plans a year ahead without waiting for months during which Ministers fight over the amount to be allocated for each purpose.  This should not happen.  A much greater part of the capital programme could be allocated for four or five years in advance leaving a small part over for regulating the economy and for the circumstances in which it is necessary to cut back spending.  At the moment nothing can be done until it has been approved by the Government and nobody can take action to get ahead with their plans for investment until such time as this approval has been given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the building industry this means that contracts have to be given each <Col N="586" /> year.  Efficiency is reduced when a man who could get a contract over a number of years and get more efficiency in that way cannot do so.  There have been exceptions such as the Ballymun scheme but the normal run is for one year.  It is an unfair system.  While the annual budget involves too short a period of capital spending it involves much too long a period for the regulation of the economy, a situation under which, if the Government finds that it has in April of any given year misjudged the economic situation and that it needs to review this, it has to wait for a whole year and that is quite unsatisfactory.  This, in fact, does not happen on one side of the ledger.  If the Government, as they did in 1965, allow excessive inflation they have then to pull back and a second budget of a deflationary character is brought in to regulate the economy by cutting back growth.  This is done by interim budgets.  It has been done on several occasions.  There is an inflexibility here in our system which needs to be changed.  It can be argued that I am giving, in the short time available to me, an over-simplified account of the problem.  It is over-simplified and in some elements over-emphasised but that is necessary in order to highlight that there is a problem here.</P>
    <P>The final comment I want to make from the institute is the ultimate condemnation of Government policy:</P>
    <P>Official mistiming has aggravated if not indeed caused the economic difficulties of Ireland since 1964.</P>
    <P>Those are harsh words.  They may even, in fact, though I say it from these benches, be a little over-harsh in suggesting that official mistiming has possibly caused these difficulties.  It seems to me that official mismanagement aggravated them rather than caused them but these are the comments of the Social Research Institute. I emphasised these points and, indeed, they are in some respects the points I emphasised last year, because it is so important that we should learn from our mistakes.  One of the unfortunate facets of democracy is the defensiveness it engenders on both sides, but particularly the Government.  We have at the moment a very defensive <Col N="587" /> Government.  Any criticism is swept under the carpet.  This is unfortunate because the purpose of public debate is the processing of Government policy. If criticisms are to be rejected this process is not working properly.  In retrospect the Government can say: &ldquo;We had a difficult situation, but we see where we went wrong and we are taking steps to see that it will not happen again&rdquo;.  If that was the reaction we could look back on the difficulties of the last few years and almost feel that they were worthwhile.  But the stonewalling attitude of the Government and the constant insistence that there had been no difficulty are not encouraging.</P>
    <P>Senator Yeats had something to say about economic growth statistics.  I find if difficult to reconcile the picture that he was giving of what was happening in Europe and in Ireland with the picture as recorded in any statistical publications I can find.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a romantic conception of the statistics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I have tried to see just what is the position.  I do not want to be unfair or selective in my choice of dates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Lies, damn lies and what not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Yeats introduced the statistics for the period from 1964 to 1967.  Up to 1964 the economy was growing satisfactorily. Our difficulty has been that there has been disagreement about what happened here since 1964.  What happened here between 1964 and 1967?  Taking the most up-to-date estimates of economic growth for 1967 and the ones I am using are, in respect of most countries, the estimates in the Institute for Economic and Social Research Review published by the Institute for Economic and Social Research in London, brought up to date with a publication by the EEC which I received yesterday, which gives figures for Belgium and Holland.  Those are my authorities for the figures of growth of the economy of these countries <Col N="588" /> between 1964 and 1967&mdash;Canada 16.5; Italy 15.0; United States 14.4; France 13.8; Netherlands 12.7; Belgium 9 to 9½; Ireland 7.4, the latest of the latest figures of the Minister for Finance; Western Germany 6.2; United Kingdom 4.9.  That is the average for the industrial countries and this is the comparison Senator Yeats was making.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it is not; I did not make any comparisons back to 1964 with European countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The comparison you made was for the OECD countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>It was for the 12 months to July last for those countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>There are no figures for national output for 12 months to July last for these countries. There are only four countries in the world that publish figures for national output for short periods.  The Senator is confusing industrial output with national output.  I am talking about national output, which is the overall criterion of the performance of an economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not go back to 1964.  You say my figures are wrong and I did not even quote figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The figure you quoted was OECD 2 per cent increase in national output.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>For the 1967 estimate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes; I am quoting national output figures, not making a confused comparison with national industrial output figures in the industrial countries which approximate to OECD countries' growth for the three years averaging 13.35 per cent. Let us be clear on this.  The growth of these countries is 80 per cent greater for these years than growth in the Irish economy because 13.5 is 80 per cent more than 7.4; I am open to correction on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>What countries?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The industrial countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="589" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Mention them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>They are not listed.  They are the countries I have mentioned plus some of the smaller industrial countries, particularly Sweden, Denmark, Switzerland&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Japan is included; what are the wage rates in Japan?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>They approximate ours now according to the general European information, but there was 80 per cent national growth in the past three years in these countries more than in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you want Japanese conditions in Ireland and in Irish factories?  Is that Fine Gael policy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Not at all.  Do not be daft.  That is the usual Fianna Fáil misinterpretation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not saying that one can accept that in any given period this country can necessarily be performing up to the average of all the other countries.  Of course, every country has its phases when things go wrong.  You could take the case of Germany which is going through difficulties at the moment.  A few years ago it was France and a couple of years before that it was Italy. Each of these countries experienced cycles of difficulty caused by inflationary difficulties, and sometimes of their own creation as in our case.  Our experience is not unique, nor is it anything we have to get into a terrible panic over.  But if we fail to recognise the fact that we did get into difficulties through our own fault we will fail to avoid them in the future.  There are a few other points I should like to make.  Senator Yeats commented on the remarkable export performance this year in the face of a deteriorating position in Britain.  In fact, the British situation from an importing point of view has not deteriorated to that extent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>The public have not as much money with which to buy, there <Col N="590" /> is a credit squeeze; I take it the Senator admits that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a credit squeeze last year when British imports were up six and a half per cent. I do not want to stress this point excessively because I should like to emphasise that our export performance this year is remarkable.  It is remarkable in relation to the situation in Britain which is not as bad as Senator Yeats painted it.  Nevertheless, from the point of view of imports, it is particularly encouraging for us.</P>
      <P>I should like to come to the question of exports.  The Taoiseach has on several occasions said that the increase in industrial exports this year is due to the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement. I am concerned that he should commit himself to a statement which is at best misleading if not at worst untruthful.  The fact is that the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement has had very little impact on our industrial exports which constitute the greater part of increases in exports in the current year.  I have examined these export figures, I have gone through them to extract every item in the industrial export field in respect of which there could be an influence from the Free Trade Area Agreement.  You will recall that industrial goods contain synthetic fibres, motor car components and other goods like tea and coffee which we do not make either.  The only significant benefit we receive is in respect of synthetic fibres.  If we put all the items together which constitute synthetic fibres, or which could contain synthetic fibres, although most goods do not contain synthetic fibres, and put the whole lot together, every conceivable item that you can trace in these figures, the increase is 1.4 million in exports in the first eight months of this year.  The total industrial exports is 1.8 million increase.  Of the industrial exports increase this year only 12 per cent is attributable to the increase in goods which contain or might contain synthetic fibre.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There may be some minor concessions in the Agreement.  There were a few minor products but none of the items which have increased this year <Col N="591" /> falls within these categories.  It is quite untrue, therefore, to attribute the industrial increase this year to the Free Trade Area Agreement.  With regard to the increase in agricultural exports some of the value of this increase owes something to this Agreement, not in any way in so far as the volume of meat and cattle are concerned, because of the fact that cattle output could not yet have been affected by the Agreement. Certainly the cattle could not have been brought to maturity because the Agreement was only signed two years ago.</P>
    <P>In the case of butter exports the Agreement led to an increase.  There was 1.1 million increase in butter exports for which the Agreement can get credit.  Also the price secured in relation to beef and cattle must have been affected to some degree.  Put the whole lot together and you will get only a fraction of the increase in export secured this year, credit for which goes to the much greater export orientation of the Irish economy and the adaptation measures taken by Irish industry assisted by Government grants which has resulted in an export potential which has now been realised. There was a great increase in exports in the current year.  It has very little to do with the Free Trade Area Agreement, and I deplore the fact that the Taoiseach should seek to justify that Agreement, which has proved so far disappointing to us, by a statement which I must say I regard at best as misleading.</P>
    <P>I want to come to another matter that is dear to my heart and that is the question of economic planning in this country.  I shall deal with it with the brevity which time, unfortunately, requires.  Senator Yeats, I think, accused Fine Gael of talking of the collapse of the Second Programme. The word which I have used in this context was certainly not &ldquo;collapsed&rdquo;. What has happened is that the principles of planning and the practice of planning have been abandoned by the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator had been here he would have heard it used <Col N="592" /> several times by Senators from the front bench.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The case I make is that I think the Programme has been abandoned.  The only area in which planning has been effected so far, in which there have been targets set and progress reviewed in that sector of the economy is industry, areas for which the NIEC is responsible for reviewing the economy and establishing such a review.  This year there has been a full and thorough review showing what progress has been made and the difficulties that have arisen and suggesting what policies need to be changed and where necessary to provide targets.  Outside of that area under the control of the NIEC there has been almost total silence on the targets, on what is happening to them and what implications there are for policies and results being achieved to date.  There is no reference to progress in other areas.  In the Department of Finance review of the economy which comes out each year there is scarcely a single reference to any target for public expenditure and public revenue set in the Second Programme, things which have never been heard of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What has the Department of Agriculture to say about the target?  There is not one single reference to one target casually referred to in the document handed out with the Estimate this year, the cattle target being the only one which has, in fact, been retained.  There is no other reference anywhere to any other target of the Programme.  The mid-term review of the Programme has been repeatedly postponed.  There are two excuses given.  The first is that we had to wait for the actual figures.  This, of course, is nonsense.  This was thought out a year after the review was originally promised.  Indeed, if there were any truth in it it would be a reason for not having the review until a certain date, not a reason for postponing it several times and then postponing it further.  The other explanation given by the Taoiseach was even more spurious. He told us there was abundant information on the progress of the economy but, while it is certainly true there is abundant information on the progress <Col N="593" /> of the economy, we have no information whatever as to how this compares with the progress implicit in the Second Programme which set out targets for 1970 but did not clearly indicate what the targets were for the intervening years, or what the implied targets were for the intervening period, which in any event is expressed in terms of 1960 money values.</P>
    <P>We have abundant information on the progress of the economy but nobody, other than somebody engaged in economic research, can discover how that compares with the targets which had been set.  The Taoiseach, in suggesting that that was the reason for not having the review, was evading the whole issue.  He went on to say that the more substantive part of such a review&mdash;lessons of experience&mdash;makes clear and confirms once more the general validity of conditions of economic progress stressed in the <i>Second Programme for Economic Expansion.</i> Fine words, but they do not help us at all.  We do not want to know about the &ldquo;general validity of conditions of economic progress stressed in the Second Programme.&rdquo;  But what lessons can we learn in regard to progress, economic and agricultural?  What can be said about agricultural policy? What can be said about economic policy?  In respect of these, we have no comment from the Government.</P>
    <P>The Minister stressed the defects of making an assessment of future prospects and the formation of appropriate policies in view of uncertainty about EEC membership.  There was the attitude that, in view of doubts about EEC membership, discussion about it could be dangerous.  This is utter nonsense. The basic assumption of the original Programme was membership of EEC.  To turn around, half way through, when at last we know a bit more than we knew four years ago, is certainly unhelpful.  We are no worse off now than we were in 1963.  We are talking about targets up to 1970. Nobody has explained how discussion of membership of EEC, which cannot be attained before 1970, can be assumed to be dangerous in the light of the fact that prospects are at least as clear now as they were in 1963-64 <Col N="594" /> after the veto&mdash;that is, unless the Taoiseach wishes to imply that EEC assumption in 1964 was dangerous.</P>
    <P>The question of whether we join EEC in 1970 is crucial.  It has nothing whatever to do with the performance and targets mentioned in the Second Programme for Economic Expansion. As it is certain that we shall not attain membership of that Community before 1970, how, then, can it be suggested that, by discussion of membership, we are prejudicing our prospects of attaining that membership?  Such suggestions are utter nonsense.  In any event, as regards conditions of membership, the Taoiseach made a speech pointing out that there is very little room for manoeuvring and that there is not really much about which we have to negotiate.  Therefore, the question of conditions can clearly be kept open up to 1970.  The position in relation to the transition period is clear.</P>
    <P>A &ldquo;shortage of expertise&rdquo; has suddenly been discovered.  That is just nonsense.  If it were true that we had not the expertise to find out what had gone wrong, the Government could have got an economist to inquire into the matter and he could do all the necessary work in a few days.  That statement about shortage of expertise is as dishonest as the other statements. The work of reviewing the Programme is carried on in a different area from the area dealing with EEC.  No great strain would be placed on the resources of the Government to discover how we stand <i>vis-à-vis</i> these targets today.  The work could easily be done if the Government wanted it to be done, but all the Government do is make these excuses for not doing it.  The plethora of excuses by the Government as to why the review has not been carried out indicates that the Government are postponing such a review for as long as possible.  There are plenty of economists available if they are required.</P>
    <P>What is disturbing is not the temporary postponement of the review because, in any event, that will come next year, but that the Government and the Minister for Finance, in particular, are so anxious to insist that the Third Programme will not have any significant number of quantified targets.  I am <Col N="595" /> thinking in terms of steady sustainable growth based on a realistic view of what can be achieved.  The Minister mentioned targets, national accounts, expenditure, and so on.  Reading the list which he gave, it is obvious that the Minister clearly intended to exclude certain crucial and important targets. All of the targets contained in the Second Programme have been dropped: clearly, these are to be excluded from the Third Programme lest they should not be attained, which would be a severe embarrassment to them if a Fianna Fáil Government were in office at the time.  This is a matter of serious concern.  It is not simply a political point.</P>
    <P>The whole concept of economic planning is to impose some kind of discipline on the process of the formulation of public policy.  To drop it merely because it is politically awkward to do so at a particular moment is not something a Government have a right to do. The announcement of the postponement of the review and the position in relation to the targets for 1970 is a disastrous decision and indicates that the Third Programme will have much less quantification.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We have suffered in this country not just in the past ten years but for the past 50 years from Governments announcing changes in policy, from a lack of the discipline which is an essential feature of planning. We are back to the old business of policy without qualified targets which results in no check on attainments. We have never been subject to the necessary disciplines here.  We have had literally hundreds of different policies on agriculture and we have had scores of different schemes.  We have had endless schemes operating but we have not had anybody to examine what happened.  There is no discipline by which to measure performance and, as a result, we are subject to every demagogic pressure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are certainly subject to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="596" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Economic planning was designed to change the situation and to create one in which the Government would be subjected to these disciplines.  That the Government have rejected it at this stage is seriously damaging to the national interest.  I challenge the Minister to find any economist in Ireland who has been concerned in any way with economic planning who is not, at this stage, deeply disturbed by Government policy and who does not feel that the Government are in process of abandoning economic planning.</P>
      <P>Had there been more time, I should have liked to analyse the deviations that occurred in targets.  However, there are a number of other things about which I wish to speak.  One is to distinguish whether the targets themselves were originally defective, such as the under-estimation of investment requirements and the over-estimation of agricultural expansion potential.  I am thinking of cases where there were unforeseen deviations, such as the status increases in the civil service and the slowing-down in the growth of the economy in the past couple of years. There are, also, cases consequential on all of these, as a result either of an original defect or through some deviation.</P>
      <P>The burden of taxation is now eight per cent higher than was planned in the <i>Second Programme for Economic Expansion</i> at this point.  It is due not to some direct error in itself but to the combined effect of output being lower than was planned, because of failure of Government policy, and status increases in the civil service.  Similarly, with regard to national output.  A larger amount of money was required to do the same amount of work.  The result was that tax went up by eight per cent.  That is a consequential effect. There are cases where failure to achieve targets is due to external causes&mdash;outside or inside our control: causes not foreseen&mdash;and such failure is not consequential.  It would give a basis for considering more seriously the Third Programme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I was surprised that the Minister for Finance should make this mistake.  He <Col N="597" /> referred to the increases in the marriage and birth rates as indicating how healthy our population situation is.  The birth rate has been going down quite significantly in the past few years despite the increase in the marriage rate.  The Minister ought to be aware of that fact.</P>
    <P>There are a number of other points to which I wish to refer but, in view of the shortage of time, I shall have to be brief.  The first is in relation to education.  I am concerned at the failure to staff the Educational Development Unit in the Department of Education in accordance with the proposals in the <i>Investment in Education</i> report.  The professional staff required there have not been appointed as proposed in that report.  Has there been negligence in not seeking them?  There are lots of economists around the place, I can assure the Minister.  Can it be that the feeling was that they were not needed?  In that case, the Minister can scarcely have understood the <i>Investment in Education</i> report.  Nor is that unit apparently doing the kind of work proposed in that report.  Nor is it working as an independent professional unit such as the Statistics Office.  Much of it certainly is relevant to what is in Fine Gael's education policy, with which the Minister is no doubt familiar.  I am glad the Department have begun to provide funds recently for educational research.  I trust that more sums will be provided.  Quite small sums could achieve enormous advances in this area.</P>
    <P>I want to correct something I said on another day at another debate on this point.  It was misreported in the newspapers at the time but the form in which I said it was perhaps misleading. I referred to educational research in Saint Patrick's Training College, to its great value and to the fact that it is the only place where serious educational research is carried out.  I was referring to academic departments of education. I was well aware of educational research being carried out in the fields of psychology and sociology.  I was looking narrowly at the field of education itself at the time.  I was not denigrating or ignoring or unaware of <Col N="598" /> the work in other fields and financed by the Department of Education.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator corrected all that in the three daily newspapers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am correcting my correction at the moment. I want to reinforce what other speakers have said.  This business of housing and the canal is a disgraceful distortion. The proposal to run the sewage down the canal is said to hold up housing.  If the sewage were disposed of as it is disposed of in all the inland cities of Europe&mdash;quite healthily, apparently&mdash;then the project could be carried out much more quickly.  It is antiquated to suggest that the sewage must be run out into the sea through a long pipe, in all its pristine form&mdash; if that expression can be used in relation to it.  If that is decided upon, the whole project will be held up for many years.  If a more modern approach were adopted, and the old restrictive views that led to this proposal were done away with, we could have our housing more quickly.</P>
      <P>Far from the Grand Canal being crucial, it is a red herring.  What appals me is the dishonesty, the pretence that nobody knows that this road is proposed, that the intention behind the closing of the Grand Canal is to build this road.  The pretence is that they are taking it up and putting it back when they have no such intention.  The contempt shown by some public administrators, not necessarily those in central Government, for the public whom they are supposed to serve is disgraceful and I am concerned at the ineffectiveness with which we in Dáil and Seanad seem to deal with these situations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The second point I wish to express agreement on is the matter of agriculture and the Minister for Agriculture. I want to emphasise that this situation cannot be allowed to continue.  It is totally unsatisfactory that a Minister should take up the attitude the Minister for Agriculture has taken up.  I am not closely allied to the National Farmers' Association nor have I any connection with them, but I realise that <Col N="599" /> they are the only seriously representative farming organisation, adequately staffed, with experts, economists and others, to represent the farming community; and to exclude them&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody is excluding them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;is intolerable. Worst of all is that the Minister should abuse his power to control the public purse by refusing to issue advertisements to a certain newspaper while every other newspaper in the country carry them.  Even in this situation of the foot and mouth epidemic, the <i>Farmers' Journal</i> has been cut off.  To use his power to do that is an abuse of public authority on the part of the Minister for Agriculture, which in any country with any sense of democracy would result in his being out of power long ago.</P>
      <P>Finally, I wish to say I agree&mdash;and in this matter I speak in a personal, not a representative capacity &mdash;with what other speakers have said on Vietnam.  We have a duty to concern ourselves with this matter because of the fact that our relationship with the United States is one that ensures that our views will be taken more seriously than our 2.8 million population merits. We have contributed greatly to the United States, not only in business but in politics as well, as we all know. Therefore, it cannot be said that our views would irritate, though initially they might, because no country likes to be criticised by another.  However, in the long term, our views would be regarded as helpful and useful.  Our views would have much more effect than those of other countries which have far less close links&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Why not call on Ho Chi Minh?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe we should take some action.  As the Senator knows, the number of our emigrants in North Vietnam is very small.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The groups you are associated with have great power.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Other <Col N="600" /> Senators have implied as much by association and if the Senator wishes to do so he is welcome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has forgotten the history of Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact is, this a serious matter.  Other European countries, fellow members of NATO with the US, have taken a stand.  I speak personally when I say we should make our voices heard, as the Pope has done, as other countries have done. Why we cannot express accord with the views of the Pope I cannot understand. I appeal to all Parties to take some action&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>What action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not suggest we should get involved in the merits of the fighting in Vietnam.  The pros and cons are difficult to weigh up, but the Secretary General of the United Nations has asked the UN to take action and I think we have a duty to support that appeal and the appeal of the Pope to bring an effective end to the fighting there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. B. Lenihan) Brian (Snr.) Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. B. Lenihan)</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had a very helpful debate on the Bill which is always the occasion of a total review of the nation's activities in every sense, covering every Department. We have just had Senator Garret FitzGerald on External Affairs and I do not intend to go into that avenue at all.  Basically, what I think we are concerned with here is the question of economic expansion in Ireland, raising the number of people at work, cutting down on emigration figures and improving our economic figures.  I feel those are the real meat of the annual Appropriations Bill here.  On that criterion I think the recent census returns show that we are making progress in that, for the first time since the famine, our population is rising.  The exact figures show that in 1961-1966 the increase is 59,000 in the non-agricultural sector. The increase in the population at work is 59,000.  Taking out the inevitable decrease in agricultural employment the net increase in 1961-1966 is 14,000.  For the first time since the <Col N="601" /> famine we have an increase in the total employment in 1961-1966.  That increase is coupled with an increase in the total population as well.</P>
      <P>I regard this as a basic criterion by which to assess Government policy. I think every effort, both at Government level and every other level, must be geared towards providing more work for people within the community. This is the basic standard with which to assess any Government.  The previous Taoiseach said this on several occasions and I think on this very basic criterion the present Government, with a rising graph of people in employment and a rising population graph, are entitled to say that progress has been achieved on that particular point.</P>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald is concerned about the whole question of economic planning and programming.  I will not go into an analysis of this but I will say that what we have done here since 1957-1958 is that we have established certain target ranges for social expenditure, economic development potentials. The targets in the First Programme were exceeded.  In regard to the Second Programme we got into difficulties last year.  I am saying quite bluntly that we did.  This year we have got out of the trough again and we now have a national income rise in the nature of 4 per cent in the current year.  So we are out of the trough we got into last year, something which could not have been targeted for.  The result is that by 1970 we hope to come close to the targets set in the Second Programme for Economic Expansion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Indeed, the review which is being prepared in the Department of Finance, and which will be announced by the Minister for Finance in the New Year, will bear out what I am saying here roughly.  We have made certain adjustments. In the first year everything went according to the programme.  We had a bad year in 1966.  We are coming out of the trough in the current year and next year things will go reasonably well.  We preserve at the present time, with devaluation and the problems associated with the British economy, a national attitude of mind in this country This involves an appeal to <Col N="602" /> patriotism and the national instinct to make sure that there are no sectors which push too far ahead.  Last year we had certain pressures from the farming front.  We got over that.  This year, if there are any sectional pressures they must be exerted in a rational way.  Every section is entitled to make its claim but it is very important that it is the national approach which should be adopted at the present time.</P>
    <P>I do not have to emphasise here in the Seanad the importance of maintaining our competitiveness.  This applies to all levels.  I am not talking just about the worker level.  There is the management level and the employer level.  It is most important to make sure there is a competitive attitude adopted and provided that attitude is adopted, we will make from the national point of view what use we can make out of devaluation.  It is up to everybody in every walk of life to make sure that the message gets through and that it comes in that way. Unless this attitude is communicated to every section of our society, unless we make the effort which is needed as a nation, we will not get out of devaluation the advantages which we should and we will not get the advantages which we should out of the present situation generally in Britain and throughout the world.</P>
    <P>On the question of programming, generally, as I said, there will be the review of the Second Programme early in the new year.  I have tremendous belief, apart from the Government's policies, in programming or planning of some sort, even if the aims are not always achieved.  At least targets should be set and the people should be geared to future achievements. It is important in every sector that the sights should be set and people should move towards some targets or feel they are going towards such targets.</P>
    <P>This is the great benefit to be achieved from programming.  Inevitably, in our economy, with private enterprise and State activity, all one can do is to programme make forecasts and try to gear the people to forecasts. <Col N="603" /> We cannot compel the people to do this.  If some of those figures are not achieved in any particular year that is part of the democratic system and part of the price we have to pay.  This is the reality of the matter and we cannot get away from it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the public sector?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the public sector Senator FitzGerald is well aware that factual and other matters arise in this respect and it is very hard to define precisely where you want to go.  In our sort of society, the sort of society where you have a mixed economy with public and private sectors, you can only assess as far as you go.  Sometimes the assessments go wrong but we should have programming and targets placed.  Inevitably, in our sort of democratic society, if those targets are not achieved, that is part of the price we have to pay for having a democracy.  We must live with that. The basic point which I think was ignored by Senator FitzGerald to a very large extent, in that it really involves the great imponderance of Irish policies and European policies, is the question of the EEC.  This, undoubtedly, is a factor in regard to planning and programming.  We set certain targets for 1970 based on the supposition that we would be within the EEC in 1970.  This is a factor which I do not need to say here in the Seanad is, to put it mildly, nebulous.  It is a factor that we would wish to see achieved but at the moment we just do not know how it is going to be.  This is not just our quandary, it is Britain's quandary as well.  It is one of the realities of present-day European and world politics.  Again our mixed economy and our situation with Britain and Europe makes programming slightly more nebulous than we would desire.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Not up to 1970.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Those are the facts of life.  There is one particular point I would like to refute.  That is Senator Garret FitzGerald's point in regard to the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement. <Col N="604" /> There is no question about it, were it not for the Free Trade Agreement this economy would be in a very much worse state than it is, thanks to the recovery in our cattle trade, which has taken place from midsummer and right through autumn of this year was entirely due to the existence of the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement where we had our entry in regard to the store cattle and we had our guarantees in regard to carcase meat; so much so that the British Government came in for very severe criticism from the British National Farmers' Union on this aspect.  There is no question about it, were it not for the existence of this Agreement, the cattle trade which moved into difficult times about 12 months ago, would have gone into a far more difficult situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>What clauses in the Agreement is the Minister talking about?  The store cattle trade was not changed by the Agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>It was changed by the Agreement and in particular we got guarantees in regard to carcase meat, of which Senator Garret FitzGerald is very well aware.  There is no need to say any more on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The exports would have been there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not in regard to the carcase meat trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, we got a subsidy but the trade would have been there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps Senator FitzGerald should reread his article in the <i>Financial Times.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no question that the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement in the context of our involvement in Europe which we are still negotiating was a large step in that direction and should be viewed in that context.  Senator Garret FitzGerald is well aware that if we are to survive we must be an exporting country to a great extent.  These are basic economic facts.  In that situation we must continue to explore and <Col N="605" /> negotiate for our country markets of a guaranteeable character in regard to industrial and agricultural exports. This is common sense.  This is the whole reason we negotiated the Anglo-Irish Free Trade Agreement. This is the whole reason behind our negotiations in regard to entry into the EEC.  In that context we must export and trade more, agriculturally and industrially, if we are to survive and improve our standard of living.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One important point which I think it is necessary to emphasise again is the fact that we have in the past 24 months gone into a difficult period and pulled out of it.  Questions may be asked by the community on how this was done.  I feel the basic reason is a political reason in that you have had a Government which has had the resolution to take decisions and you have had a situation where the Government of the day has had the confidence of the financial and industrial community. This indeed is very apparent when one looks at the situation which obtains in Britain at the present time.  We have pulled out of our balance of payments difficulties.  I do not need to elaborate here on the situation that arose in 1965 when we had a deficit of £41.8 million. Last year it was £16.1 million.  This year the figure will probably be a plus figure, we do not know yet.  It is surely a graph that we should be very happy about, not complacent, but happy in the sense that we have a Government that has taken decisions, difficult decisions, taken them in a positive way and incurred unpopularity for a period in order to do that.  We have got out of that trough again like the difficulties in regard to the Second Programme.  It is important that this sort of thing should happen in an administration because otherwise there would be a complete recession of confidence.  One does not mind a recession in the sense of temporary difficulties but if there is a recession of confidence it is fatal in so far as any economy is concerned or any government or any country.  We have not had last year or this year a recession in confidence compared to the recession in confidence which we had in 1956 and 1957.  It cannot be denied that we have got out of similar type <Col N="606" /> of difficulties without that recession in confidence, and I think it is a legitimate point to make that the present Government have pulled out of a difficult period in 1966 and we are moving into 1967 was a rising graph balance of payments-wise, employment-wise, population-wise, national income-wise. We have pulled through a difficult situation and this situation is a very definite improvement on what happened when another Government was faced with a similar type of situation in 1956-57 but did not have the necessary competence, unity and discipline to deal with it.  I feel this is a fair and valid point to make and history, I think, will write it in precisely that way.</P>
    <P>Other points made during the debate concern the farming problem and the agricultural problem generally.  I think it was Senator McDonald who spoke on this basis.  Again on that plane we have surmounted difficulties, difficulties which I feel should never have arisen. Fundamentally it was a situation where the Government had to act in a positive way in regard to particular farming problems.  I want to say again precisely and spell it out that as far as the NFA are concerned, as a farming organisation they have their seats on the National Agricultural Council. They are there for them to take any time they wish.  There is no question of the NFA or any other farming organisation being excluded by the Government, or by the Minister for Agriculture, from their proper place in giving advice on farming matters to the Minister for Agriculture.  I want to reiterate that in case there is any misunderstanding arising from some remarks made by Senator Garret FitzGerald.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It depends what you consider their proper place. Two members out of 14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>The NFA along with every other organisation are welcomed by the Minister to take their proper place on the NAC under Lieutenant-General Costello as Vice-Chairman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="607" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>And the Minister as Chairman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, they are very welcome there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Two seats out of 14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the National Agricultural Council more positive work has come from that body than has come from many other farming organisations over a long number of years, in that there have been a number of very positive recommendations made and the new small farm incentive scheme whereby a small farmer up to a certain acreage will participate in a scheme to achieve certain targets of production and on that basis will be allowed £60 a year. This is a positive scheme and is one of the best things that has come out of Irish farming for a long time.  It has come from a body composed of a number of positive farming organisations and I would only wish that the NFA would also come in on that and show positive thinking in that respect.</P>
      <P>I do not think there is anything more that I should say beyond emphasising again the fact that it is important in any Government thinking or any parliamentary thinking on where we were going in the future, to emphasise the social aspect of Government policy. All economic progress and achievement should be geared to certain social achievements and social objectives.  On that account I might say that we have proved in the past 12 months that we are a Party with a reasonably good social conscience.  Without doubt, the most important social development in recent years has come about since September this year when we set out to initiate the free post-primary education system.  Other people talk about a just society but there was not much talk about education in the documents produced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister keeps repeating that; it is not true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Labour Party had their Convention recently and there was not much talk about education at <Col N="608" /> that Convention.  We believe this particular scheme for free post-primary education, to give every boy and girl the same chance to make the most of his or her talents, is the greatest progress of any government since the formation of the State which under our Constitution says that we should cherish all the children of the nation.</P>
      <P>As a Party we are happy to be a social Party with a conscience and a social Party of action.  I do not believe in talk and debate about this matter. I believe in doing something about it. As far as social development is concerned we are up to date, as we were in the 30s, 40s and 50s.  We have consistently been the workers' Party and are proving ourselves to be so again in 1967 in regard to our new educational policy.  This very fact proves that, along with being a Party concerned with making economic progress, we are also concerned with social progress and as long as I am a member of this Government this will be our attitude.  Along with economic expansion I also think in a very positive way of the social progress and social improvements which can be made.  That should be the attitude generally and most members will agree with that.</P>
      <P>All I would say in conclusion is that we have proved ourselves largely to be a stage ahead of the other political Parties in this particular aspect which is essentially a matter for the people to decide.  The people have decided so far in a certain direction and they will continue to decide in that way.</P>
      <P>I should like to mention that the Minister for Finance has a heavy flu and that that is why I am here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We understand that; we wish him well.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="609" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Sul a gcuirim an Seanad ar ath-ló ba mhaith liom beannachtaí na Nollag agus na h-aithbhliana a ghuí do gach Seanadóir, don Chléireach agus don Leas-Chléireach. <Col N="610" /> Gach beannacht agus rath go raibh oraibh go léir.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 4.30 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>