<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="15" Month="Mar" Year="1967" Vol="62" No="16" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 15 Márta 1967" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 15 March 1967" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1437">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1437" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business, as on the Order Paper, from No. 1 to No. 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Diplomatic Relations and Immunities Bill," RHead="1967: Recommittal, Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Diplomatic Relations and Immunities Bill, 1967: Recommittal, Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair suggests that amendments Nos. 1, 2, 3, 7 and 8 be taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the complexity of the situation created by all these amendments and the discussion the last day, I would suggest we recommit these particular amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a matter for the House; in so far as these amendments are concerned, the matter is recommitted; is that understood?  I want the House to be clear with regard to the procedure.  The Chair is proposing that amendments Nos. 1, 2, 3, 7 and 8 be taken together.  The suggestion is that amendments Nos. 1 and 2 be recommitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose that all the amendments to the Bill be recommitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>All the amendments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That was my intention, if it is acceptable; I am sorry if I did not make that clear. I do not quite see how we could discuss five amendments together if only two of them are recommitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Aiken) Frank Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Aiken)</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that perhaps the Seanad might recommit all the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1438" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, that is the intention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Nevertheless, amendments Nos. 1, 2, 3, 7 and 8 are being discussed together.</P>
      <P>Bill considered on Recommittal.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>1.  In page 9, to delete lines 19 to 32 and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Experts (other than officials or servants of the Organisation) performing missions for the Organisation shall have and enjoy such privileges, immunities and facilities as are necessary for the independent exercise of their functions during the period of their missions, including the time spent on journeys in connection with their missions. In particular, they shall have and enjoy&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  immunity from arrest or detention and from seizure of baggage;</P>
      <P>(b)  immunity from legal process in respect of acts done by them in the course of the performance of their missions aforesaid;</P>
      <P>(c)  inviolability in respect of papers and documents.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 1 is brought forward in an endeavour to meet the uneasiness which Senator FitzGerald expressed at such great length the other day.  I could not persuade him that the parliamentary draftsman's language in the section to which this refers&mdash;section 28&mdash; meant what was said in the protocol to the OECD Convention, which gave certain immunities to experts appointed by the Secretary General of the OECD to work here.  In order that we might not be having a dispute as to what this protocol meant, I asked the parliamentary draftsman to redraft this section using, as far as he could, the language in the protocol to the Convention.  This has been done. Therefore, nobody can dispute, I think, that this amendment covers exactly the same subject and gives the same immunities as we have agreed to give under the Convention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1439" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We are in a number of difficulties in this matter. First of all, the Minister has just referred to some Convention.  I am not clear to what Convention he is referring. I wonder if perhaps I could ask him to clarify that point before I proceed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The Convention of the OECD.  The protocol which was added to that Convention covered the immunities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the OECD Convention of the 14th December, 1960?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Senator is probably aware, when the Organisation for European Co-operation changed its name, it also changed its charter to a certain extent.  It then added a supplementary protocol to the Convention which set out the immunities that were to be granted to experts other than officials.  I shall read out Article 18 of the protocol and I suggest that the Senator might at the same time read the wording of amendment No 1.  The article states:</P>
      <P>Experts (other than officials coming within the scope of Part V) performing missions for the organisations shall be accorded such privileges, immunities and facilities as are necessary for the independent exercise of their functions during the period of their missions, during the times spent in journeys in connection with their missions.</P>
      <P>In particular they shall be accorded (a) immunity from personal arrest and detention and seizure of their baggage; (b) in respect of the things done in the course of performance of their missions, immunity from legal process of every kind; (c) inviolability of all papers and documents.</P>
      <P>Perhaps I should also read out the following article which I think Senator Sheldon had in mind when putting down his amendment.  Article 19 reads:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Privileges, immunities and facilities are granted to experts in the interests of the organisation and not <Col N="1440" /> for the personal benefit of the individuals concerned.  The Secretary General shall have the right and the duty to waive the immunity of any expert in any case where in his opinion the immunity would impede the course of justice and it can be waived without prejudice to the interests of the organisation.</P>
    <P>What I am attempting in the amendment I have put on the Order Paper is to meet certain of the criticisms voiced here on the last occasion.  Firstly, it was suggested we were giving an inordinate immunity to an Irishman who might be appointed by the Secretary General of OECD to some job here&mdash; that during his appointment he could rob and murder all over the place and nobody could do anything about it. Secondly, we were concerned to take care of the anxiety that might have been aroused by Senator FitzGerald. If he does not accept the amendment, I am prepared to criticise the amendment put forward by him as an alternative.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister would postpone that until he sees my reaction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall see how we get on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad I provoked the Minister by question, to develop his original statement because what he has just said has been very helpful to us to understand the reason for his amendment.  It seems appropriate that the form of this exemption should be as set out in the Convention and one is puzzled as to why this was not done originally.  Secondly, because of the change in the wording the draftsman has effected between the Convention and what we have here, we are puzzled.  I notice that the Minister has included servants in his amendment. They are not included in the Convention. Also, the Convention states &ldquo;they shall be accorded&rdquo; whereas the Minister says &ldquo;they shall have and enjoy&rdquo;. It may be because this is internal legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>May I deal with that now?  It is a complicated subject and <Col N="1441" /> I think we should deal with it, bits at a time.  The reason that the original section 28 in the Bill was different in wording from the Article in the protocol was that the parliamentary draftsman wished to bring the language in this section as closely as possible to the general run of the language in which Irish Bills are couched, that is when he does not quote verbatim the various international Conventions.  That is the only reason.  I suggested to the draftsman following the discussion here the other day that he should do one of two things.  The first was that he should take the whole Convention and schedule it here in the Bill.  That would entail a great deal of work and he decided he would instead accept our second suggestion to substitute for section 28 wording which came as closely as possible to Article 18.</P>
      <P>In the amendment we say &ldquo;experts other than officials or servants of the organisation&rdquo; simply because it is more in keeping with the language of some of the other protocols and Conventions than the statement in Article 18 of the OECD protocol which stated &ldquo;experts other than officials coming within the scope of Part V&rdquo;.  If we were to take that wording we would have to quote Part V.  Officials referred to in some of these Conventions are meant to be people in high offices.  It is for that reason the parliamentary draftsman in this new amendment decided to use the words &ldquo;experts other than officials or servants of the organisation&rdquo; in the opening lines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say on that particular point that I have examined all the Conventions, including the different organisations of the United Nations.  Perhaps I am in error regarding this but I have not come across anything in relation to servants.  It does not come from the United Nations Convention, the ILO Convention, the FAO Convention, the IKAO Convention, or UNESCO nor does it come from the World Health Organisation or the Inter-Governmental Maritime Organisation. I am not objecting to this but <Col N="1442" /> the Minister's explanation does not quite hold water.  There must be some particular reason for using the word &ldquo;servants&rdquo; here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the reason.  It is quite difficult to go through all those Conventions to get at it but that is the reason.  In this amendment we say &ldquo;experts other than officials or servants&rdquo;. As a matter of fact, the word &ldquo;experts&rdquo; is not used in the normal way here.  The wording we use is as close as possible to the language of Article 18 of the protocol.  We decided to put in the word &ldquo;experts&rdquo;.  &ldquo;Experts&rdquo; means whatever it means.  We all know generally what it means.  We put in &ldquo;experts other than officials or servants of the Organisation&rdquo; instead of saying &ldquo;other than officials coming within the scope of Part 5 of the OECD Protocol&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to be a point of importance and I will not pursue it further.  What I am actually trying to say is that the word &ldquo;expert&rdquo; is used in all the Conventions. The introduction of the word &ldquo;servants&rdquo; has no precedent attached to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not accept that.  It is there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I have listed all the Conventions and I do not think the word &ldquo;servants&rdquo; occurs anywhere. It it does, I should be grateful to be advised where it occurs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>If I may intervene in this private war, I should like to say that it may be due to the fact that servants are specifically provided for in the first two Conventions, the diplomatic and consular Conventions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>These are diplomatic immunities.  None of the conventions which we have attached to the Bill makes any reference to the word &ldquo;servants&rdquo;.  Why should we use it in regard to the OECD?  I should like to know where there is any reference to this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The parliamentary draftsman assures me that it is in <Col N="1443" /> keeping with the ordinary language used here and it will be understood.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the parliamentary draftsman has looked at the diplomatic Conventions and has slipped up here.  A parliamentary draftsman will not usually admit to slipping up on a point.  The next point is the use of &ldquo;shall have and enjoy such privileges, immunities and facilities&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;shall be accorded such privileges, immunities and facilities&rdquo;. This is a change of wording.  As this is domestic legislation, I should like the Minister's assurance on this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the ordinary language that would be used here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I notice then instead of &ldquo;immunity from legal process of every kind&rdquo; it is &ldquo;immunity from legal process in respect of acts done in the course of the performance of their missions&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>That is to bring it a little bit nearer to our normal wording.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to &ldquo;inviolability of all papers and documents&rdquo; there is no significant difference intended there?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>In my amendment I have used a different interpretation from that of the Minister. I am not against the Minister's amendment. I should merely like to explain the reason for my amendment.  The form I have used in my amendment is the one which applies to FAO, WHO and UNESCO.  I should like to say, at this stage, that acceptance of the Minister's amendment is entirely without prejudice to our position in respect of amendment No. 11.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope to bring the Senator around to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a difficulty in relation to amendment No. 3, which, technically, of course, must be discussed with amendments Nos. 1 and 2 <Col N="1444" /> because it seeks to alter the wording of the existing section.  If the Minister's amendment is accepted, the existing section disappears and so does my amendment.  In fact, amendment No. 3 is related more to amendments Nos. 11 and 12.  It seeks to do in a different way what they seek to do.  I think, technically speaking, if I were to pursue that point now it would be out of context in relation to the present debate.  On the question of amendments Nos. 1 and 2, I think a great deal of the confusion that has arisen could be avoided if we had heard at an earlier stage that this would relate to the wording of the Conventions that were not in the Schedules to the Bill.  I am afraid that I understood that everything in relation to the Bill was in the Schedules.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to have had that but the draftsman said that it would make the Bill even worse than it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>Doubtless that is the position, but it would have made things a lot clearer if we had no references here to those other Conventions.  This clears my mind in regard to this.  I was already inclined to agree to the Minister's amendment rather than to that of Senator FitzGerald because the Senator's amendment appears to me to be related more to the United Nations than to anything else.  If the Senator is going to shake his head, I shall quote from page 59.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not saying that it is not related to the United Nations.  It also applies to three of the United Nations' special agencies from which I took it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say so.  It is still the United Nations.  I still consider that is a very different type of organisation from the OECD.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It refers to the organisations relating to the United Nations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>I consider the wording of the Minister's amendment is preferable, even from that point of view.  Now that we know it is related <Col N="1445" /> almost exactly to the Convention with which Part VI deals, I would be quite satisfied with the Minister's wording, subject to what I want to say on amendment No. 3 at a later stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister and his draftsmen are to be congratulated on this amendment.  I think this has been very carefully and usefully done because the original clause remained vague and referred to persons performing assigned duties and so on, whereas the present form says that they should &ldquo;have and enjoy certain privileges, immunities and facilities as are necessary for the independent exercise of their functions&rdquo; and so on.  This seems to me to be much more specific.  The fact that the Minister has shown us that it accords very closely with the wording of protocol strengthens the case he made.  I feel that this is a good deal better than the original wording and better also than Senator FitzGerald's rather longer amendment.  Therefore, I think the Minister is to be congratulated both on his willingness to think this over and to amend it is a point which demonstrates (a) the value of a week's reflection and (b) the value of the Seanad as an amending body.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 2 and 3 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not clear about this.  Is amendment No. 3 not being moved or is it being postponed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>Technically, I understand it cannot be moved because if I had entered it as an amendment to amendment No. 1, it might now be valid to move it but as it is moved to a section which has now, by will of the Seanad, disappeared from the Bill, I do not see how it can be moved. I would suggest that the spirit of it be discussed in relation to the two later amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is suggested that amendments Nos. 4, 5 and 6 be taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1446" /> In page 9, between lines 32 and 33 to insert the following:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The inviolability and the privileges, exemptions and immunities conferred by section 28 of this Act are accorded not for the personal benefit of the individuals concerned but in order to safeguard the independent exercise of their functions in regard to the Organisation and may be waived by the Organisation.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This amendment was entered in complete ignorance of the fact that Part 6 was related to a Convention that was not before me.  I am not terribly sure whether or not it is necessary. In section 29 of the Bill there is a reference, funnily enough, not to the Convention to which the Minister has directed our attention but to the fifth Schedule of the Bill and in it in every instance, in regard to Ministers, in regard to members of the Consultative Assembly and in regard to officials, something similar to the wording of amendment No. 4 is inserted. There is no general provision put in in regard to the Convention.  It is put in in each individual case and as the Bill stood drafted the persons referred to by section 28 did not appear to me to fall into any of the categories in the fifth Schedule.  Therefore, this advice on the subject of the nature of the immunities granted to them was missing so I thought it should go in in order that the same type of inclusion in regard to immunities should appear in relation to the people mentioned in section 28 as appear in relation to all these other people in various parts of the fifth Schedule.  The Minister has drawn our attention to the fact that in the Convention dealing with OECD there is precisely a similar provision.  I think he said Article 19?</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, Article 19.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>All I want to suggest now is that the Minister might perhaps have a look at it to make sure that Part VI of the Bill, as it stands, is sufficiently worded to give a reference to Article 19 of the Convention.  This is not something which, I quite agree, can <Col N="1447" /> now be done, but, fortunately, in this case the Bill has been introduced in the Seanad and has to go to another House which will provide the Minister with another opportunity to make further amendments.  I should like him to keep that point in mind and to make sure that his experts will have their attention drawn to the limitation of immunities mentioned in Article 19 of the Convention on OECD.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator will give way I shall deal with that point.  The fact is that as we are giving the force of law to the whole Convention here we also give the force of law to Article 19 which is pretty well the same as in the Senator's amendment.  It is almost the same wording.  Therefore, it is not necessary nor would it be very appropriate for us to repeat it in the Bill. It is all right for the organisation to tell the Secretary General that he shall have the right and the duty to waive the immunity of any expert if in his opinion the immunity would impede the course of justice and it can be waived without prejudice to the interests of the organisation.  It is there and it remains there as an instruction to the Secretary General from OECD that he is to waive and that it is his duty to waive an immunity if it would impede the course of justice and if it can be waived without prejudice to the interests of the organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator Sheehy Skeffington would say I admit the Minister has a <i>prima facie</i> case, and so long as he is sure I am content.  I do not see anything in Part VI which, in fact, enacts, as he says, the Convention in the same way as these other Conventions referred to in the various schedules because anything that is in the schedules is enacted quite definitely by the Bill but I do not see anything in Part VI which enacts that Convention. I hope the Minister will make sure of this point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>All these amendments are so interrelated that it would be difficult to disentangle any particular point but in <Col N="1448" /> sections 23, 24 and 25 of the Bill where there is a reference to immunities, it is always put in brackets: &ldquo;including the waiver thereof&rdquo;.  I hold that it might be no harm if in this reference in section 29 to various parts of the fifth Schedule which grants immunities it was made clear that it includes the waiver of the immunities and privileges.  Everything else is stated: inviolability and exemptions, immunities, facilities <i>et cetera</i> and the very fact that no reference is made after all this precision to waiver might possibly be held to mean that waiver was not included.  It is not a terribly material point but it does not tie up with some other suggestions in relation to other amendments so it is difficult to relate it precisely to this point.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>May I interrupt the Senator?  He wants to put these words into section 29 in order to make certain that the waiver is there but if he reads on he will see that section 30 says:</P>
      <P>(1)  The inviolability and the exemptions, facilities, immunities, privileges and rights conferred by this Act on an official of the Organisation or a person referred to in section 28 of this Act may be waived by the Organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the Minister, but my next amendment proposes to delete that section.  Amendments Nos. 4, 5 and 6 taken together deal with waivers in a different way from the Bill.  They make it clearer.  The waiver in regard to the persons in section 28 and the waivers mentioned in relation to other people would all have been brought together under my amendments Nos. 4 and 5 and, therefore, the section would not have been needed.  I agree it is only a different way of doing the same thing.  What happened was that we drafted these amendments not first having seen the Minister's amendments.  They might have been drafted in a different way or left out altogether.  As everybody will remember, we appeared this day week in an effort to embark on all these and there was not much chance to amend one's hand.  Probably the <Col N="1449" /> points are met by the Minister's amendments.  They might be met in a neater way following my ideas.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 5 and 6 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 7 and 8 have already been discussed.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 7:</P>
      <P>In page 10, to delete lines 30 to 43 and substitute the following:</P>
      <P>Experts (other than officials or servants of the Council) performing missions for the Council shall have and enjoy such privileges, immunities and facilities as are necessary for the independent exercise of their functions during the period of their missions, including the time spent on journeys in connection with their missions.  In particular, they shall have and enjoy&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  immunity from arrest or detention and from seizure of baggage:</P>
      <P>(b)  immunity from legal process in respect of words spoken or written or acts done by them in the performance of their missions aforesaid and within the limits of their authority;</P>
      <P>(c)  inviolability in respect of papers and documents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>This follows directly from what went before.  I withdraw my amendment and accept the Minister's amendment No. 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I might say that while we welcome very much the greatly improved version by the Minister and his draftsman, we should also recognise the fact that it is the persistence of Senator FitzGerald that has made this possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>We might have a word on that in another section.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 8 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 9 and 10 may be taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1450" />
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 9:</P>
      <P>In page 13, line 5, to delete &ldquo;conclusive&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;prima facie&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Section 47 which I am trying to amend by this amendment reads as follows:</P>
      <P>In proceedings in any court a certificate purporting to be under the seal of the Minister, and stating any fact relevant to determine whether a judicial or semi-judicial body, an arbitration or conciliation board, an organisation, community, body, diplomatic mission, consular post or person is entitled to inviolability or to an exemption, facility, immunity, privilege or right under a provision of this Act or of an order made under this Act shall be conclusive evidence of the fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It seems to me possible to deal with this in one of two ways that have occurred to me.  First of all, it would have been possible to say &ldquo;In proceedings in any court a certificate under the seal of the Minister and purporting to state any fact relevant ...shall be conclusive evidence of the fact&rdquo;; or else to say &ldquo;In proceedings in any court purporting to be under the seal of the Minister and stating any fact... shall be <i>prima facie</i> evidence of the fact.&rdquo;  The tenor of my amendment is to replace the word &ldquo;conclusive&rdquo; by &ldquo;<i>prima facie</i>&rdquo;.  The result of this would be that such a certificate would be taken as evidence unless it were shown to be otherwise.  I quite understand the necessity to shield the Minister, or his representatives, from having to appear to verify or certify every certificate but it seems to me to say that a certificate purporting to be under the seal of the Minister shall be conclusive evidence is going too far.  I could imagine a representative of the NFA, for instance, with the co-operation of the creamery workers, getting a milk bottle top and bringing in a certificate showing that their representative was a representative of the International FAO and saying that this milk bottle top was the Minister's seal, and this would be a certificate purporting to <Col N="1451" /> be under the seal of the Minister.  It would not have to be under the seal of the Minister but would have to purport to be under the seal of the Minister and this would be conclusive evidence that this representative of the NFA was entitled to all the diplomatic immunities, freedom from arrest and exemption from all kinds of things. It seems to me that the placing of the word &ldquo;purporting&rdquo; is faulty, or else the word &ldquo;conclusive&rdquo; is faulty. I would say that it would be legitimate to have the words &ldquo;under the seal of the Minister&rdquo; and &ldquo;purporting to give evidence of the fact&rdquo;.  But, &ldquo;a certificate purporting to be under the seal of the Minister&rdquo; merely means that anyone who wishes can claim that it is under the Minister's seal.  It would not matter whether it was a milk bottle top, a half-crown or a bit of sealing wax.  I decided in proposing this amendment to say instead of &ldquo;conclusive&rdquo;&ldquo;<i>prima facie</i>&rdquo;, which would mean that 99 times out of 100 the Ministerial statement would be accepted and would have to be accepted unless it were shown not to be what it claimed to be.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington's suggestion is an improvement on the section as it stands.  I would be prepared to accept it only for the fact that, as the parliamentary draftsman has pointed out, in sections of this kind in various other Bills&mdash;and there are a great number of them&mdash;the wording is &ldquo;it shall be accepted as conclusive evidence of the fact unless the contrary is shown&rdquo;; practically the same purpose would be served by inserting &ldquo;<i>prima facie</i>&rdquo; or &ldquo;unless the contrary is shown&rdquo;.  These are the words in sections of this kind in other legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>As I understand the position in law, you have two kinds of situation.  One is where you produce rebuttable facts, rebuttable proposals, and the other is where you produce irrebuttable facts and irrebuttable proposals. The rebuttable facts are <i>prima facie</i> evidence of the things which they state but the antithesis of <i>prima facie</i> is what is conclusive.  It seems to me <Col N="1452" /> that what the parliamentary draftsman suggests is contained in other details along the lines that a certain thing shall be proved by that fact unless the contrary is shown.  I do not think the Minister will be able to produce any precedent for such bad legislation or bad draftsmanship as &ldquo;shall be conclusive evidence until the contrary is shown.&rdquo; That does not make sense.  I am aware of quite a number of cases where it is &ldquo;shall be evidence of these facts&rdquo; or &ldquo;proof of certain facts until the contrary is shown&rdquo;.  I think that Senator Sheehy Skeffington has, for a non-lawyer, done very well in the amendment he has suggested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I would accept Senator Sheehy Skeffington's amendment for peace sake if the Senator would agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's stature is rising all the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to thank the Minister.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 10 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that amendments Nos. 11 and 12 be taken together.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 11:</P>
      <P>In page 13, between lines 22 and 23, to insert the following:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Officials of an international organisation, community or body referred to in this Act or an organisation to which this Part applies serving in the State or persons performing duties in the State assigned to them by any such organisation, community or body shall not be appointed from among persons who are Irish citizens except with the consent of the Government, and the consent may be withdrawn at any time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald on the last occasion dwelt at great length, and repeated himself several times, on the difficulty we might find ourselves in if an expert appointed on a temporary mission of the Secretary General of the OECD went on the rampage and we could not arrest him, detain him or <Col N="1453" /> bring him before the courts.  He stressed the fact that he was not even nominated to the Government, or the Government were not even going to be informed that there was such a gentleman on the loose in Ireland with these privileges and immunities.  I do not want people to be scared into believing that the Secretary General of the OECD would send somebody here or appoint anybody who could not be trusted to behave himself whilst he was performing the functions of the Secretary General.  Senator Sheldon's, amendment was right on this point. He wanted to stress that the Secretary General was under an obligation by the Charter of the organisation to waive the immunities of an official if in his judgment not to waive them would be unjust, and that the waiving of them would not conflict with the best interests of the organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This section as we have it drafted conforms to the general spirit and trend of all these international conventions dealing with immunities and privileges of diplomatic and consular officers, of members of various international bodies like the Council of Europe, the OECD, the FAO, the United Nations and so on and so forth.  Our job here in dealing with this matter would have been very much facilitated if a number of these Conventions had been drafted by these organisations after the Vienna Diplomatic Convention.  The Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations could be regarded as simply a drawing together, and putting in the one piece of paper, the practices that had grown up over the years in relation to the treatment of diplomatic representatives. If that Vienna Convention had been implemented before the OECD or before the United Nations was organised, or any of these other bodies, I have no doubt that the draftsman of the immunities to be granted to members of the organisation and to officials of these various organisations would have taken the Vienna Convention as a headline and simply written into a very short protocol or Convention &ldquo;Number 1, 2 or 3 section shall apply to members representing governments or parliaments on these organisations, and <Col N="1454" /> X, Y or Z shall be applied to officials of various sorts.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I have no doubt that we could leave this situation as it is without inserting this section, and leave it to the good sense of anybody who would be appointed as Secretary General of the OECD to inform the Government here that he proposed to appoint or have appointed somebody to do some work for him here in Ireland.  But to keep this Convention, or our own law, pretty well in line with the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations we have to keep in mind that there is a very clear article in the Vienna Convention setting out how diplomats are to be appointed and the notification that is to be given to the receiving State. Article 8, section 1 says &ldquo;Members of the diplomatic staff of the mission should in principle be of the nationality of the sending State&rdquo;.  That is if a French diplomat is being sent here he should be a Frenchman, or if it is an American, he should be an American, and so on.  Section 2 of that Article says: &ldquo;Members of the diplomatic staff of the mission may not be appointed from among persons having the nationality of the receiving State, except with the consent of that State which may be withdrawn at any time.&rdquo;  It is, therefore, clearly in order that the relations should work smoothly that it is laid down here as a headline that in the usual way a diplomat coming to Ireland should be of the nationality of whatever country sends him here, and that no Irish citizen is to be appointed as an official of a foreign diplomatic post here unless with the consent of the Irish State.</P>
    <P>I think, seeing that this Vienna Convention was drafted by men who were the heads of their various protocol divisions, political divisions, and of the governments that combined to draft it, it is something that should be treated with respect and we should not go against it, unless we are clear in our minds we are doing something contrary to what those gentlemen, who drafted the Vienna Convention, thought was the right thing to do.  It is for that reason we suggest the Seanad should adopt amendment No. 11 which simply says <Col N="1455" /> that the officials of an international organisation, whether it is the OECD, the United Nations, or FAO, serving in the State, or persons performing duties in the State assigned to them by those organisations, shall not be appointed from among persons who are Irish citizens, except with the consent of the Government, and the consent may be withdrawn at any time.</P>
    <P>I want to make it quite clear this does not set out to control Irish men or women who want to take a post in the OECD, the United Nations, or FAO in another country.  But if an Irishman is offered a post here by an international organisation, we think it wise that the Secretary General of that organisation should clear the appointment with the Government of the Irish State.  I would think it would be very unusual for the Secretary General of any of those organisations to make an appointment without alerting the Government here to the fact that he was doing so.  But I do want to meet the criticism of Senator FitzGerald that there is the danger that in giving immunities to a person appointed by the Secretary General of an international organisation it does give them certain immunities while they are carrying out their duties.  I do not think the courts should be in any doubt if such a person ever happened to be taken up on some charge; there should be no doubt as to whether or not that person is entitled to immunities and some papers should pass between the Secretary General and the Government here.  The paper we suggest by this amendment is the same as would pass when a diplomatic person is being appointed here; that is, that the State sending him, the organisation sending him, should ask the Irish Government for their agreement and it should also be quite clear&mdash;as in the case of a diplomat&mdash;that the Irish Government can say at some stage they are not prepared to grant those immunities any longer and that the person concerned is <i>persona non grata</i>, that is, he is not acceptable to the Irish State in the position to which he was appointed.  I think it is good both for the international organisations <Col N="1456" /> concerned and for the State here that this procedure should be followed. We are not taking any control in relation to what an Irishman with the United Nations may be appointed to do in some other country at the ends of the earth; it is only when they are coming here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>In this section, the Minister clearly is trying to meet the point I raised the last day.  I suppose I should be grateful to him but I am afraid I shall display some slight ingratitude in the matter.  First of all, what I tried to establish the last day was whether it was the Minister's intention to do what the Bill purported to do in the way it was drafted; that is, to give complete immunity to people who would not even have to be named by the international organisation.  I was not objecting to that procedure but I wanted to know did the Minister intend to do this.  Unfortunately, we got bogged down because, first of all, the Minister said it was not complete immunity and, secondly, that the Secretary General of an international organisation would have to submit a list of people he wanted to do work here for the organisation.  In fact, neither of those statements was correct and I was concerned to try to convince the Minister what the Bill, as drafted, did and to ask him to accept my interpretation of what the Bill did: further to say whether he really wanted to do that or not and, if he wanted to do it, what were his reasons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been established today that the point made by me as to what the Bill purported to do was correct and the Minister has made certain adjustments because, apparently, he does not want to do that.  But the difficulty we are in now in is that the course of action he is proposing is objectionable on several grounds.  I see the Minister's difficulty because the Conventions dealing with international organisations are all drafted peculiarly in this respect &mdash;that where an official is to be sent to a country concerned, there is, in fact, a provision with regard to notification of his name in advance and so on but no such provision exists anywhere as regards <Col N="1457" /> experts.  This is regrettable; perhaps it is an oversight; perhaps it was intended.  I think it is regrettable but that is the form those Conventions take.  We have signed those Conventions, accepting that such experts could be sent here without any limitation on our part or any right of objection on our part.  Perhaps we should not have signed them but that is what has happened. I do not see it is in our power, at this stage&mdash;having signed those Conventions&mdash;to abrogate them in the way the Minister proposes.</P>
    <P>I am in doubt, indeed, about whether or not my own amendment would be contrary to those Conventions and I would be open to guidance by the Minister on that point.  But the Minister's amendment is drafted in such a way as to tell the international organisations what they shall do.  This is something this House has no power to do because this would not only impose limitations on rights we have given in those Conventions but we would also propose to tell the organisation what it shall or shall not do in the carrying on of its own functions. This we have no power to do.  We might have power to tell Irish citizens not to accept appointments just as we have power to tell them not to accept honours from foreign governments.  I am in doubt about whether they might not accept employment of a certain kind without the permission of the Government.  That is another point. It may not be constitutional but, if it were constitutional, it would be legally within our competence to say what jobs Irish citizens should take and lay down the law for them.</P>
    <P>If the amendment took the form of saying Irish citizens shall not accept appointments as officials, or persons performing duties in the State, this might conceivably be legal, subject to its constitutionality.  But, what we have no power whatever to do is to tell the organisation who they shall appoint.  This, in fact, is null and void as a provision in this Bill and could have no effect whatever because we have no power to control those bodies in the appointments they make. Secondly, quite apart from the fact <Col N="1458" /> that the amendment, as drafted, is meaningless&mdash;in that it purports to control something not within our power to control&mdash;I would object very strongly to any attitude of the Government here to control such appointments by any method simply in order to get over a difficulty about diplomatic immunity.</P>
    <P>This Government have signed a series of Conventions which give diplomatic immunity to experts, whether they are Irish citizens or not, it is quite clear.  I am not attempting to blame the Government for signing them.  They all take this form and we are only one country among perhaps 110 who have ratified such Conventions. Having done that, I do not think we can abrogate the Conventions in the manner set out in the section nor should we try to get out of the problem of giving diplomatic immunity to people in Ireland by saying that these people should not accept appointments.</P>
    <P>The intention of the section is quite contrary to our practice in this country, quite contrary to what is acceptable in the country.  We are a country in which the right of people to take any employment they like is not interfered with even when it involves the taking up of jobs in the defence forces of other countries.  That is the practice in Ireland, though in other countries very stringent regulations govern it.  For us, therefore, suddenly at this stage to lay down that if an Irish citizen gets an appointment as, say, a consultant with an international organisation he cannot undertake that appointment without the permission of the Government is to go far beyond what should be attempted by any government in order to get over a technical difficulty about diplomatic immunity.  It is to go far beyond what this House ought to do.</P>
    <P>However I sympathise with the intention behind the Minister's amendment. He felt I had raised a valid point at an earlier stage.  In fact, I am not convinced that my own amendment gets over the difficulty.  I say &ldquo;shall not apply unless the organisation has applied to the Government&rdquo;.  That in <Col N="1459" /> itself may be an abrogation of the Convention because it purports to take back an immunity which is given unconditionally by the Convention we have signed.  Since I have that doubt about my own amendment, I am prepared to withdraw it if the Minister decides to share my point of view on this matter.  At least my amendment has the virtue of doing no more than what we set out to do&mdash;to seek to limit diplomatic immunities&mdash;but it does not act to interfere with the right to employment in this country.  The Minister's amendment does.</P>
    <P>I gave the Minister an example during the previous Stage of a case that can arise.  I instanced my own case when I was asked by the United Nations to prepare part of the agenda for the World Tourism Conference in Rome.  Part of that I did in Dublin and under this provision I could not have been appointed in the ordinary course unless the Irish Government had agreed.  I would personally resent interference of that kind.  Our whole tradition and practice in this country are that people are entirely free in the matter of employment, not requiring the permission of the Government. There are continental countries where there are rigid controls in these matters but this amendment represents a wrong-headed departure from our tradition&mdash;wrong-headed because it interferes with the rights of employment of Irish people far beyond the need to achieve what the Minister has set out to achieve.</P>
    <P>For those reasons I am plainly opposed to the Minister's amendment in its present form.  I ask him to withdraw it, realising that in seeking to introduce it he was meeting a point made by me on the previous Stage.  If he intended to give immunity to the people the amendment was supposed to be designed to cover, why did he want to do so?  Was it because he had no alternative?  Was it because he was bound in some way internationally? I had to establish these facts before expressing a view on whether we should give this immunity or refuse it. Having established the facts by careful <Col N="1460" /> reading of the legislation and by listening to the Minister today, it is clear to me now that we probably have not got the power to limit diplomatic immunity to experts because it is not covered in the Conventions we have signed.  If the Minister feels we could do so, if he feels I am wrong in my interpretation of the effect of these Conventions, then I ask him to accept my amendment at all costs, or some version of it if he finds difficulty with it in its present form, but not to press his amendment which goes too far and which, in any event, has been drafted the wrong way round.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>At the moment I feel myself battered into the ground. Senator FitzGerald raised so many points that I have now completely lost track.  In relation to both amendments I wish to suggest that a very proper approach could have been attempted if the drafting I suggested earlier had been acceptable to the Minister&mdash;in section 28 that notification should be given to the Minister of any of these appointments.  That would have been in accordance with diplomatic usage as given in Article 10 of the Diplomatic Convention which states that the receiving State shall be notified of the various appointments.  I can see Senator FitzGerald's point in regard to a perfectly innocent Irish citizen, offered an appointment and now apparently subject to the ukase of the Government, but the Senator should realise there could be other cases.  Supposing the expert was a retired civil servant from an important Department of State here who had had access to important papers.  In such a case it would be very proper that the Government should have the right to veto that man's right to send information of any sort to any organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator FitzGerald has read this in one way and I am not sure he has read it correctly.  I take it that &ldquo;appointment&rdquo; in the Minister's amendment means appointment of a person under sections 28 or 35&mdash;the new ones&mdash;that is, a person with certain immunities attached to the appointment.  I do not know whether I am right or wrong.  It would help the <Col N="1461" /> Minister's case if I am right.  Supposing OECD were foolish enough to imagine that I was an expert in some cultural matter and wrote to me telling me they would be glad of my observations in my own country on such a cultural matter.  There was no question of appointing me as an expert.  They just wanted to know what I thought.  They were not appointing me as an expert. I hope I am not misjudging Senator FitzGerald, but I would take it that this is very like the type of thing he was asked to do in relation to tourism. While he was considered, very properly I am sure, an expert by that organisation, there was no question of granting him any immunities.</P>
    <P>I suggest, even with the Minister's amendment if any of those organisations want to appoint an Irish person to produce something for them as long as there is no question of their putting that person above the law, as it applies to his fellow citizens, then the Government do not come into it.  I should imagine that it is only where one of those organisations wishes this Irish citizen, in relation to his work, to do something that would put him above the Irish law, in the way it applies to his fellow citizens, that the consent of the Government would be involved.</P>
    <P>This is very proper.  It is all right for a Frenchman coming here, in relation to a diplomatic post, to get certain immunities but it is not quite the same thing when an Irishman is to get certain immunities and be put above the law as it applies to his fellow citizens.  I would suggest that in relation to the Minister's amendment we are not using quite as large a stick as in Senator FitzGerald's amendment.  Once the Minister is given any notification of appointment in regard to some foreigner or Irish citizen he is in the position to write back to the organisation and say: &ldquo;I note this proposed appointment but we are not willing to grant immunities.  We are quite happy if he comes here and does his work provided he does not seek those immunities&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>This would create the right atmosphere in regard to this matter.  There is <Col N="1462" /> always notification in regard to the international organisation.  In my view there is notification to the Government of the receiving State&mdash;if it is not written in it is implied&mdash;and they are always in a position to say <i>non grata</i> in this case and that such immunities should not apply to an Irish citizen. There is only one doubt in regard to an Irish citizen and that is whether it is making it possible that other nationals, such as a Japanese or a Peruvian can come here and snap their fingers at the Government and claim immunities. That would be very improper.  I think the Minister's amendment is simpler than Senator FitzGerald's.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>There are a couple of points I should like to deal with here. Some of them are rather intricate. Senator Sheldon has put his finger on one point.  If a person is here legally in possession of diplomatic immunities there is nothing the Irish Government can do in the way of legal proceedings in our courts to make him amenable for infringement of the law.  Therefore, it is important that there should be the right sort of procedure for the appointment of such persons.  It is very important, particularly, that where an Irish citizen in Ireland is being put above his fellows and is entitled to all those diplomatic immunities and privileges that they should be set out and there should be a reasonable way of having such a person nominated to the Government and being accepted.</P>
      <P>It is also important for our courts if some appointee of one of those international organisations here committed an offence and if he is an Irish person, that he should be amenable to the Irish law within the terms of this section.  If there is some breach connected with his service to the international organisation it is important that there should be some concrete evidence that can be presented to the court indicating that he had or had not certain immunities or that he had immunities with limitations and stated exactly where he stood <i>vis-à-vis</i> the Irish law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would say to Senator FitzGerald that it was not for nothing that the people in Vienna who examined the <Col N="1463" /> matter and who put down on paper all the immunities and privileges which had evolved and been accepted over the years should put in Article 8 that members of a diplomatic staff and persons who had diplomatic immunities, ought, in principle, be of the nationality of the sending State.  In the case of an international organisation no person has the nationality of that sending body but at least it should be normal practice for an international organisation if they want to send somebody to a member country, that the person appointed should not be of the nationality of the receiving State, unless for very good reasons.</P>
    <P>We all know that diplomatic immunities are subject to criticism in practically every country in the world. People who have studied the matter know that if we are to have international relations at diplomatic level we have to give immunities.  We have to safeguard the people who have been sent by other countries.  We had a very good example in recent months of the importance of diplomatic privileges and immunities.  If recognition of these rights and privileges was not so strongly embedded in the international conscience we might easily have had real trouble when certain diplomats were under attack.  It is important that if a person is coming here or is an Irish citizen living here and gets an appointment either from a foreign government by being taken into the diplomatic service in its mission here or in the service of an international organisation the Government should be made aware of the fact and should have expressed their agreement.  I feel it will help towards keeping good relations between the people here and the organisation which has sent an official.</P>
    <P>Subsection (2) of Article 8 of the Vienna Convention says:</P>
    <P>Members of the diplomatic staff of the mission may not be appointed from persons having the nationality of the receiving State except with the consent of that State which may be withdrawn at any time.</P>
    <P>I was inclined to disagree with Senator FitzGerald's fears but I can see that <Col N="1464" /> the fact that they have been expressed will stir people up to have a very close look at the appointments that may be made in this State by some of those international organisations.  From the point of view of the person involved and of the organisation involved and for good relations all around, I think what we have suggested in amendment No. 11 is advisable, and that it is appropriate.  In the ordinary course of events there could not be any objection by the Government here to an expert being appointed by an outside body to do some work and it is only in a case where an organisation is about to appoint somebody who might not keep within the law that any government could have an objection.</P>
    <P>This suggested amendment is in line with many of the articles in the various Conventions.  If one takes the Council of Europe there is an obligation on the Secretary General there to supply the names of officials appointed to the governments of the member States.  Article 17 of the Convention schedule affecting the Council of Europe says:</P>
    <P>The Secretary General will specify the categories of officials to which the provisions of Article 18 (below) shall apply.</P>
    <P>That is the immunities.</P>
    <P>He shall communicate them to the governments of all members. The names of the officials included in these categories shall from time to time be made known to the above-mentioned governments.</P>
    <P>With regard to the United Nations the General Convention on the Privileges and Immunities of the United Nations, section 17 says:</P>
    <P>The Secretary General will specify the categories of officials to which the privileges of this Article and Article 7 shall apply.  He shall submit these categories to the General Assembly.  Thereafter, these categories shall be communicated to the governments of all members.  The names of the officials included in these categories shall, from time to time, be made known to the governments of members.</P>
    <P>The same thing applies in regard to <Col N="1465" /> the Convention on the Privileges and Immunities of the specialised agencies of the United Nations.  The wording is on a par with Article 17 in regard to the United Nations Convention.  We have all these pointers then to the desirability of the person in control or acting on behalf of an organisation or government wishing to send an official or a representative to a certain State that they should take steps to notify the receiving State of their intention to send a named person and to ask the government of the receiving State to grant him certain well-defined immunities and privileges.  It is desirable that the receiving State, having for the purposes of international relations, been compelled by the general practice and now by the Vienna Convention to grant these privileges and immunities to the representative of an outside organisation or foreign government should have, at the same time, the power to withdraw them by saying, as can be said in the case of a regular diplomat, &ldquo;He is <i>persona non grata.</i>&rdquo; He is no longer acceptable to the government of the receiving State and they are not prepared to continue to grant him these privileges and immunities.</P>
    <P>It is an even stronger case where a foreign government or an international organisation appoints someone, either resident in Ireland or an Irish citizen living abroad to come to Ireland, that the consent of the Government should be obtained ahead of time and that they should agree that he is a fit and proper person to be in receipt of these immunities and privileges.  After all, it is the Irish Government who are responsible for the welfare of the people.</P>
    <P>We have to recognise that the immunities which are granted are immunities from arrest and from trial and punishment for certain acts for which the ordinary citizen could be put to prison, if nothing more.  Therefore, in these cases as well as in the case of diplomats coming from abroad, the Government should have the right to say: &ldquo;No, we are not prepared to grant these rights and privileges.&rdquo; I do not fear that any <Col N="1466" /> Government here could refuse to grant immunities and privileges to a person appointed by an international organisation, if, in fact, he is known to be a fit and proper person to be in receipt of such privileges and it were recognised that he is not a person likely to abuse them and take advantage of his fellow citizens by doing something against them or committing an offence which is against the law or against the rights and interests of a fellow citizen.</P>
    <P>As long as the Government can be assured that he is not likely to commit an offence against his fellow citizens they should and would, I am certain, agree to receive him as a representative of the international organisation concerned and give him the privileges and immunities to which he is entitled as a representative.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>As between these two amendments one by the Minister and one by Senator G. FitzGerald, at first sight the Minister's amendment seems more attractive to me because it is briefer and less cumbersome and I think amendment No. 12 by Senator G. FitzGerald contains unnecessary detail. The wording of the first portion of the Government amendment is neater and covers everything that needs to be said. I do not think it is necessary to refer to all the articles, annexes, and so on. There is, however, an important point of difference.  That is, the Government are asking in their amendment that nobody, not even an Irish citizen, shall be appointed to do a job of work for an international organisation as an expert here except with the consent of the Government, whereas Senator G. FitzGerald's amendment asks simply that the immunities shall not apply to an Irish citizen performing a mission unless the organisation has applied to the Government to have such privileges and immunities extended to such experts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is an important difference in principle here.  The Government asks for the right to say that a particular Irish citizen shall not even be appointed to the task, whereas Senator FitzGerald's amendment merely asks that the Government shall have the right to refuse to allow diplomatic immunity <Col N="1467" /> to an Irish citizen if they think fit.  I feel the Minister is in his expressed concern more in agreement with the second amendment than with his own. He states, for instance, that an Irish citizen should be&mdash;and this is his phrase&mdash;&ldquo;amenable to Irish law.&rdquo;  He also states: &ldquo;We ought to have the right to say: no, we are not prepared to grant these rights and privileges&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>I would agree with him&mdash;and I think Senator FitzGerald would also agree&mdash; that the Irish Government must have the right to say: &ldquo;No, we are not prepared to grant diplomatic immunity to a particular Irish citizen.&rdquo;  What the Minister's amendment is asking for is the right to say that a particular Irish citizen shall not be appointed.  That is asking far more.  It is open to two objections, as I see it.  If, before an Irish citizen is asked as an expert to do a particular task for an international body here in Ireland, the consent of the Irish Government has to be obtained, it is possible that there may be delay.  I am not suggesting that the Irish Government are slower than other bodies but Government Departments are not noted for speed.  They may be noted for flexibility and good humour but speed is not one of the qualities in which they excel and, therefore, there might be what can be an annoying and very inconvenient delay.</P>
    <P>Secondly, I think the Government amendment asks for too much power to say &ldquo;No.&rdquo;  It is possible, after all, that party political prejudice might enter into such a position.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>If other things were not equal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>It is unlikely that political prejudice would enter into it but it is conceivable that a Government or a Minister might say that citizen A is <i>persona non grata,</i> and can have the right to say so on appeal from the international body for one or other expert.  In other words, I think too much power can be given to the Government under amendment No. 11, which would enable them to say that particular people who are Irish citizens <Col N="1468" /> should not be appointed, to have a complete veto on their appointment, whereas amendment No. 12 merely asks that the Irish Government shall have the right to refuse the granting of diplomatic immunity to Irish citizens if they are appointed.</P>
      <P>There is also, if I might mention it in parenthesis, the question as to whether we have a legal definition for &ldquo;Irish citizen&rdquo;.  What is an Irish citizen? Is a man living in Newry with an Irish passport an Irish citizen?  Is a man living in Newry with a British passport an Irish citizen?  Is a man having an Irish passport and a British passport living in Belfast an Irish citizen?  I am not sure that the phrase &ldquo;Irish citizen&rdquo; has a connotation that would be agreed on by all lawyers.  I say this in parenthesis.  While the words are not clearly defined we all know what they mean&mdash;a citizen of the Irish republic.  But there is a concept which refers to the whole of this island as being Irish.  This concept is shared by the Minister and the Government and, therefore, an Irish citizen might be a citizen who is Irish although regarding himself as a citizen of the United Kingdom.  I am not sure that the words &ldquo;Irish citizen&rdquo; in either amendment is clear.</P>
      <P>I feel that in amendment No. 12 there might usefully be added some words at the end.  The operative words are: &ldquo;The privileges and immunities ...shall not apply to an Irish citizen performing a mission for one of these organisations in Ireland unless the organisation has applied to the Government...&rdquo; I would add the words &ldquo;and obtains its agreement to have such privileges and immunities extended to such experts&rdquo;.  I do not think it is enough to say that an organisation has applied for agreement.  I feel the addition of these four words &ldquo;and obtains its agreement&rdquo; between the words &ldquo;Government&rdquo; and &ldquo;to have&rdquo; make this twelfth amendment readily acceptable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To sum up, as between the two amendments I would prefer Senator FitzGerald's amendment, which grants the Government the right, which I think it should have, to refuse immunities <Col N="1469" /> to certain Irish citizens employed by international organisations in Ireland but which would not give the right to the Government to refuse any citizen's right to be employed on such tasks in Ireland by an international organisation.  That is the distinction I see.  I think that the Government should have a right to say that a particular Irish citizen shall not enjoy these immunities, but it should not have the right to say that a particular Irish citizen shall not be appointed. That is the crucial difference between the two amendments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington has said that a great deal of the burden of the Minister's contribution to the discussion on these amendments has rather been arguments in favour of amendment No. 12 rather than amendment No. 11.  There are at least three categories of people concerned here.  Firstly, in this Bill there are diplomats who receive full diplomatic immunity.  Next there are officials of international organisations, and thirdly there are experts appointed by international organisations.  The point raised on the Committee Stage by Senator FitzGerald related to the position of experts appointed by international organisations, and he raised the point of whether these people might be receiving a greater measure of immunity than was appropriate, and whether the matter might not be looked into.  The Minister in introducing amendment No. 11 has looked into the matter a bit too far. In his opening statement on amendment No. 11 he repeatedly referred to the Vienna Convention, and again in his second intervention in the debate he referred to the Vienna Convention. He quoted this Convention in support of the words used in amendment No. 11 concerning appointments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To my mind the Vienna Convention, which relates to diplomatic representatives, which was signed in late spring, has very little to do with the case.  The position is that we are concerned in this discussion not about the position of diplomats who are afforded full immunity, who are sent from one country to another in order to act <Col N="1470" /><i>vis-à-vis</i> the Government of that country.  We are concerned rather with officials who are sent to do limited things, or with experts who could be asked to do one of two things.  An expert who is appointed by one of the international organisations to do something in Ireland might be doing one of two different types of things.  He might be doing public work in Ireland or he might be doing private work in Ireland.  A person could be appointed as a consultant by an international organisation, and he could do a great deal of the work of that consultancy in his own house without ever going outside the door.  Senator FitzGerald has mentioned that he was in this position.  I have been in this position myself with regard to the OECD doing consultancy work, a great deal of which was done at home before an eventual meeting in Paris. We are concerned about the position of such people.</P>
    <P>The point is that we are not concerned that these people should have immunity.  The cardinal point of this argument is not whether they should have immunity or what type they should have.  The cardinal objection to amendment No. 11, and the desire to put forward amendment No. 12 in preference, is due to the fact that Irish citizens should not be prohibited from accepting such positions if offered.  It seems to me that it is an undue interference with people who are being asked to do work in an expert capacity to provide that because they are Irish citizens and are doing part of this work in Ireland, though it does not impinge on the Government or on public affairs in any way, it is necessary to go through the full diplomatic procedure, seeking first whether the Irish Government approve of their being appointed to do this particular job.  It is for the Minister, for the Government and for the Houses of the Oireachtas to decide that in all the circumstances these people should have diplomatic immunity, but I do not think we should allow ourselves to become tangled up in Conventions to the extent that the only way out is to say that no person residing in Ireland can accept appointment to do any type <Col N="1471" /> of work as an expert for an international organisation without the consent of the Government of Ireland.  I do not think that there would be any difficulty with regard to this.</P>
    <P>Senator Sheldon said that it is very desirable that this consent should be needed because we might have the case of an ex-civil servant whom the Government might not wish to become a consultant in this particular matter.  I do not think that this is really a valid objection.  I do not think that difficulties would arise in this regard.  I know that the Minister has in the past favoured very much the participation of Irish people in the international agencies, and I know that it is not his general attitude to such matters that Irish citizens should be hampered in any way.  If we were to insist on the procedure which is in amendment No. 11 we might well get ourselves into the position that the only result of the whole thing would be that Irish citizens would not be asked to act as experts, that where the OECD or some other organisation are looking around for somebody to do a particular job if they find that in the case of Irish citizens it is necessary to go through this whole diplomatic procedure they would be inclined to take the easy way out and say: &ldquo;There is somebody in Sweden who could do almost as good a job, we will get him and not have all this trouble.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In trying to meet the case made the last day the Minister has gone too far. He has treated the appointment of such experts as if they were full diplomatic appointments.  There may be a case for treating officials in such a way. Amendment No. 11 which starts off talking about officials of international organisations, but goes on to refer to &ldquo;or persons&rdquo;, which I take it means to include experts.  We are applying the full stringency of diplomatic appointment and diplomatic acceptance, which I think is going too far.  To accept what is in Senator G. FitzGerald's amendment or what is in Senator Sheldon's amendment would be quite appropriate to the case.  There is no doubt that we agree with the Minister that it is undesirable <Col N="1472" /> that a large amount of diplomatic immunity should be given to any person whom the Government do not think it would be proper that it should be given to, but we feel that this question of whether immunity is given to the person is a separate question from the question whether or not an Irish citizen should in the future have to get the consent of the Government here to carry out even the most short term work for any international organisation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say that in the early stages of this debate I listened with a very open mind.  Like Senator Sheehy Skeffington, I was more attracted to the Minister's amendment because of its apparent simplicity and its direct approach to the solution of this problem.  I also formed a feeling of a certain amount of sympathy with the Minister, who has told us that he approached this matter with good intentions, as he described them, of endeavouring to go as far as he could to meet the arguments and objections posed for him by Senator G. FitzGerald.</P>
      <P>This debate has been of tremendous value and use to the House because we can all see what is really wrong in this particular amendment on the part of the Government; we can read into it, I think, very clearly now a very serious and far-reaching implication, one certainly I do not think anybody in his sane senses could possibly support.  I am one of those Members of the House who believe firmly that the Government should and must have the right at any time either to withhold or withdraw any immunities extended by way of privilege to persons in this category. Clearly, they cannot withdraw or withhold those immunities from people outside their jurisdiction.  Consequently, that right can only be applied, in effect, to Irish citizens.  I certainly find myself in complete agreement on that point but there I must pause.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would be entirely wrong for this House to give its consent to a proposal which would enable any government&mdash; I am not alluding to this Government any more than any other which may <Col N="1473" /> follow&mdash;to say that Irish citizens should be denied employment.  There, I think, is the crunch of this whole argument.  I think&mdash;whether knowingly or unknowingly&mdash;the Government have made a mistake in writing in that particular proposal into this amendment. Therefore, I would appeal to the Minister, even at this stage, to realise that in his efforts to do some good here, to meet certain objections of Members of this House; to meet their ideas and intentions, he has gone just a step too far.  I would urge upon him that this amendment be taken back and looked at again.  I would oppose it vigorously if it is intended to railroad it through the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say I despair&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister would give way to Senator O'Quigley?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I observed a note of despair about the Minister. I never despair of converting people like the Minister who have an open mind on problems of this kind.  In this particular set of amendments we are obviously all trying to achieve what is best in the interests of the country and not to extend unduly the diplomatic immunities and privileges with which the Bill deals.  One of the things we should recognise is we ought do nothing to prevent Irish citizens from being appointed as often and as numerously as possible to international organisations.  I think Irish influence in those organisations is likely to be beneficial.  Therefore, we should not do anything in this legislation, or in any other legislation, which would hamper or restrict the appointment of Irish citizens to international organisations. It seems to me, straight away, this amendment would do this when it says, in effect, to international organisations: &ldquo;You shall not appoint the persons you want.&rdquo; That is what it sets out to say: &ldquo;Unless you have the consent of the Irish Government.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what it says; that is not what it purports to say; &ldquo;that they shall not appoint a person living in Ireland to a job in Ireland.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1474" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am speaking within the context of this amendment, where we are saying to an international organisation: &ldquo;You shall not appoint an Irish citizen to a job&rdquo; and, to meet the Minister's point, I shall go on to say&mdash;&ldquo;to a job in this country, on your behalf, unless you have the consent of the Irish Government.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>That is different from what the Senator said first.  What the Senator said was that we were trying to prevent an international organisation from appointing Irish citizens to a job in the organisation, without the consent of the Irish Government.  That is not what the section says, as the Senator has since admitted, but we will hear that allegation from him again, I am sure, when he is in some other place where he cannot be contradicted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I may not have been as legalistic as I should have been but I do not always like to be legal and surround myself with parentheses.  I am talking within the context of this amendment and I am saying that what this amendment does is to say to organisations: &ldquo;No, you shall not appoint Irish citizens as officials of your organisation.&rdquo; Now, to please the Minister, I shall say: &ldquo;To act on your behalf in this country.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister need not thank me for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I like to be courteous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is always courteous, but he should not get cross with me.  I am trying to be helpful, as indeed I hope I always am; we ought to try to permeate as many international organisations as we can with Irish influence.  That should be our objective, not unduly, but we certainly ought not to do anything which would restrict any international organisation, or hamper it in any way, from employing Irish citizens on their behalf, abroad, or in this country.  We may be restricting them from appointing people, on their behalf, in this <Col N="1475" /> country if the Minister's amendment is accepted, and I do not think that would be a good thing.</P>
      <P>Equally, I quite agree with the Minister and, indeed, as the Minister spoke in favour of his amendment my admiration for him blossomed, but the blooms wilted when Senator FitzGerald pointed out the error contained in the Minister's amendment. What we are all agreed upon&mdash;and I entirely support the Minister on this&mdash; is that we ought not to allow persons to be appointed in favour of the appointers of international organisations in this country who are Irish citizens and who can get all the diplomatic immunities and privileges as if they were foreign diplomats acceptable to the Irish Government, because I can envisage a situation in which such a person&mdash;who might be responsible but whose character might not be well known to the international organisation&mdash;would knock down somebody, say, the breadwinner of a family, and there would be no action at law to recover damages against that person because he was covered by diplomatic immunity.</P>
      <P>I am all with the Minister that we ought not extend the area of diplomatic privileges too freely.  But what we are doing in this particular amendment is creating an obstacle to international organisations appointing Irish citizens to do jobs of work on their behalf in this country.  I think what Senator FitzGerald seeks in his amendment and what Senator Sheldon was seeking to do in the amendment he could not move was correct.  The Minister might very well reconsider the position to ensure that officials shall not have the immunities and privileges unless their appointment is made with the consent of the Government&mdash;that is, an Irish citizen.  The Government will then have the right of refusal; the international organisation is not hampered in its choice; it can choose who it wants but, if it wants a particular person and the Irish Government says &ldquo;We are not going to grant him diplomatic immunities&rdquo;, then that is the affair of the international organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1476" /> If it wants a particular person to do a particular job, then it can have that particular person but that person would not have any of the diplomatic immunities and privileges.  That is the way we ought to do it.  In practice, the international organisation would not appoint a person the Government did not approve of but what we are doing in the amendment&mdash;it is a question of emphasis and I would ask the Minister to look at it again&mdash;is that we are making a barrier and laying down a rule of law to be observed by an international organisation in relation to the appointment of an Irish citizen, to act on behalf of the organisation, within the jurisdiction of this State.</P>
    <P>What Senator FitzGerald is saying and what I should like to say is: &ldquo;Very well, you can appoint whoever you want but if you want the diplomatic immunities and privileges accorded to that person, then you must get the consent of the Irish Government to that person's appointment&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>The Minister's amendment does not seem to me to be right for yet another reason.  I do not say this in any kind of carpingly critical way.  If we wish to talk about officials and appointments and exclude the <i>ad hoc</i> appointment in a consultative capacity where immunities would not arise, we ought to specify that and to enlarge on it in the amendment.  I do not know of any interpretation section which defines officials.  A person might be appointed <i>ad hoc</i> to do one mission and it would seem to be the organisation who would have to apply to the Government to make an appointment of an <i>ad hoc</i> nature.  If the appointment is of a temporary character, of short duration, that should not be necessary.  If that is what we mean we ought to say so. If it is officials with an appointment of fairly long duration in the country, say of six or nine months, or if it applied to an appointment of an Irish person for six or nine months or a year and it might be desirable that these people should be extended immunity, then we ought to distinguish between the <i>ad hoc</i> mission and the appointment, even though temporary, of a more permanent character.  The Minister's <Col N="1477" /> amendment does not meet the wishes of his side or of this side.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Mr. Garret FitzGerald rose.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I was about to call on the Minister to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I was about to clarify the issue and make a proposal which might solve the problem and shorten the debate.  The problem we are facing is that we want to control the immunities of experts which we feel should not be extended to Irish citizens in this country.  I was disappointed the Minister did not advert to our difficulty, which is that we have bound ourselves by a variety of Conventions to grant such immunities unconditionally, without any condition as to the character of citizenship or otherwise. This may have been a mistake, an oversight, or it may have been forced on us by events.</P>
      <P>I should like the Minister, in replying, to tell me, first of all, whether he has been advised that we are empowered, without breach of these Conventions, to limit that right.  The OECD Convention itself makes no qualification in the matter of these rights for experts but it provides a means of dealing with the situation if we are dissatisfied with the nature of the immunity. It is under Part VII, Article 20, and it sets out that the organisation concerned may conclude with any member or any members supplementary agreements adjusting immunities. Here there is a provision to vary the immunities.  The UN Specialised Agencies Convention attached to the Bill lays down provisions in relation to the abuse of privilege and the Minister might feel that the granting of such privilege to an Irish person in Ireland might be an abuse in itself.  In such cases there is provision referring the matter to the International Court of Justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is an international undertaking on our part to apply these immunities and the Minister's amendment, and perhaps mine but not so flagrantly, would be in breach of Convention.  I should like the Minister to say if he has been advised whether our amendments, <Col N="1478" /> his and mine, similar amendments purporting to limit that right of Irish citizens, are in accordance with these Conventions.  I feel both amendments might be in breach, mine being a minor breach, his being <i>ultra vires.</i></P>
    <P>My second problem is under what authority he purports to limit the rights of these organisations to make appointments. He is not proposing to limit the rights of Irish people to accept these appointments.  That, if constitutional, might be legally possible and when I first saw his amendment and read it hastily I thought the reason he had adopted this procedure was because, recognising the danger of being in breach of these agreements, he thought he had found a way around this by limiting instead the right of Irish citizens to accept appointments.  Even this he has not, in fact, done because, instead of directly attacking the right of Irish citizens to take up employment, he purports to limit the right of the organisations to make appointments. Not only would this be in breach of the Conventions but it is, in effect, an attempt to legislate for these organisations, which no Irish Parliament has the right to do.  We could conclude agreements with these organisations to act or not to act but we have no power to legislate as to how they should act.</P>
    <P>Thirdly, we are in evident breach of the Conventions by seeking to limit the application of these immunities. The Minister's amendment has at any rate been carelessly drafted because in the first place it does not accord with the Minister's amendments Nos. 1 and 7.  The wording in regard to &ldquo;persons performing duties&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;experts performing missions&rdquo; is out of line with the rest of the Bill. Moreover, the phrase &ldquo;experts performing missions&rdquo; is mentioned in all these Conventions and this has weakened the force of an argument which either Senator Sheldon or Senator Sheehy Skeffington made.  I forget the exact phraseology but it was suggested that perhaps what was meant here were persons performing duties, and this is too broad to fall within the point which I think Senator Sheehy Skeffington was trying to make in that respect.</P>
    <P>I should like the Minister, in his <Col N="1479" /> reply, to state if he is clear these amendments are not in breach of the Conventions and also how he proposes to control by legislation the action of international organisations to make appointments here.  I think those points should be dealt with.  He has not, in his reply, adverted to them.  Senator Sheehy Skeffington suggested that if the words &ldquo;and obtain its agreement&rdquo; were added to my amendment this would deal with this problem intelligently and would avoid a flagrant breach of those Conventions.  Both of us were trying to see that those rights shall not be given unless they were asked for by such people, and if they were asked for the Government could say that such persons should not be appointed with such diplomatic immunity. Both of us were aiming at the same thing.  We recognise that we would not bind those organisations completely and complicate matters.</P>
    <P>I think Senator Sheldon's amendment is the best one.  I was not too happy with it at first, but now I think it deals with this thing as neatly as possible.  Because there is so much doubt in regard to this matter, and because the Minister's amendment is defective in not taking into account his earlier amendment, because it goes too far in interfering with the right of employment and because perhaps my amendment and Senator Sheldon's amendment would themselves be a breach of the Conventions and could involve us having to go to the International Court of Justice, for all those reasons, and in order to give the Minister and his advisers time for reflection on how to tackle this problem, I would be prepared to withdraw my amendment if the Minister would also withdraw his.</P>
    <P>I think Senator Sheldon's amendment has technically been withdrawn because his amendment was taken with earlier amendments.  I would certainly be quite prepared to withdraw my amendment if the Minister would withdraw his and consider what is the best course that should be adopted.  I think the position has got so complicated that I almost regret having raised this point at all.  I raised it by way of a <Col N="1480" /> query as to whether the Minister did not intend to do it.  It appears he does not intend to do it.  Our international obligations may make it difficult to get out of this commitment at this stage.  I think all the reasons I have mentioned are cogent and if the Minister between now and consideration by the Dáil were to consider this matter further and bring in some amendment in the Dáil to cover this matter, I should be perfectly satisfied to withdraw my amendment. I am not fully satisfied that this is not a breach of any international convention and that it does not go further than is necessary to achieve the object which we all wish to achieve. I, therefore, suggest to the Minister that both amendments be withdrawn and that the matter be given further consideration.  This might be the best answer to the matter at this stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I think anybody listening to Senator FitzGerald and not knowing what was really involved in this would agree with him that the matter has become complicated.  I do not know any problem that would be so simple that could not be complicated by Senator FitzGerald if he once got loose on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure that is intended as a compliment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator FitzGerald, first of all, spent a long time here in the Seanad the last day complaining that the Bill, as it stood, would give the Secretary General of one of those international organisations the power to appoint some Irish citizen living in Ireland and that that would give that person immunity from arrest and detention, that he could not be taken before a court and that this was very unfair to the law-abiding citizens of the country who might be aggressed against this mythical official of an international organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If Senator FitzGerald had not raised the matter at all things would have been reasonably simple because I do not believe that the Secretary General of any of those organisations would appoint an Irish citizen living here to be an official of the organisation <Col N="1481" /> without consultation with the Government.  Indeed, he is under obligation to keep governments informed and also to see that anyone who is given an appointment which carries with it immunities, keeps within the law and does not get himself into a position that the Secretary General, in order to protect the interests of the organisation, has to claim immunities.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing experts rather than officials.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Experts and officials. This is one of the difficulties of the Bill.  We are dealing in certain parts of it with the sort of language that is used by a number of international organisations and in other cases the words are those of the parliamentary draftsman and they are in keeping with the general wording of our laws.  I want to say this.  I do not think that anybody objects to conforming to the diplomatic immunities, the Convention of which was drafted in Vienna.  That Convention, in Article 8, gives the right to the receiving State to refuse to accept an official.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>A diplomat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>An official appointed by a diplomat who has already been recognised.  We can refuse to accept the diplomat.  When he comes here we can also refuse the officials.  We can hold out against the employment by the diplomat of an Irish official who does not get the consent of the Government. That is recognised to be a sensible way to establish international relations. After all, why are they coming here? They are coming here because they want to keep the relations between the two countries, the sender and the receiver, on an even keel.  Why should a Secretary General of an organisation send an official here or employ an official here if there was any danger that the employment of that official or the sending of that official here would lead to bad relations between international organisations and the State here?  There is, I believe, a good reason to think that if this Vienna Convention had been agreed on before <Col N="1482" /> those other Conventions were negotiated the Vienna Convention would have been taken as the basis of those other Conventions and they would have included in these various Conventions a clause similar to this one where a Secretary General of one of these organisations appoints an official or expert.  In many of these Conventions &ldquo;expert&rdquo; simply means an official who is overseas for a few days.  If the Vienna Convention had been in being at the time they would have incorporated a clause similar to this one and there could be no argument about it.</P>
      <P>The words in amendment No. 11 &ldquo;shall not be appointed&rdquo; are in keeping with the words of Article 8 of the Vienna Convention which says in subsection 2: &ldquo;Members of the diplomatic staff of the mission may not be appointed from persons having the nationality of the receiving State except with the consent of that State which may be withdrawn at any time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an international Convention under which States agree what they shall not do. We are now enacting an Act of the Oireachtas purporting to bind an international organisation.  The two are quite different.  The Minister has, quite properly, changed the wording of the international Conventions to incorporate it into our domestic legislation. These changes were necessary, but in this case he has failed to do so and the amendment, as drafted, purports to control international legislation which we could do as one of a number of states signing a Convention but not as an Act of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should realise that what we are doing in this is preventing some person here in Ireland, an Irish citizen, claiming that he is a representative of an international organisation and claiming immunity when he is called up before the court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot prevent him being appointed.  We can prevent him from accepting appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot prevent an <Col N="1483" /> international organisation giving him a piece of paper saying they hereby appoint him, but we can get our courts to accept that the Oireachtas here has a right to say whether that person has any right to claim the immunity, to say that he shall not be tried for robbery or whatever it is because he is an official of an international organisation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what my amendment says.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is exactly what Senator FitzGerald's amendment says.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is saying we have no right to say he shall not be appointed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that.  I said that we had no right to say that the organisation shall not appoint him which is a totally different thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is true, equally have we not the right to say, as the Senator is saying in his amendment, that the immunities shall not apply to an Irish citizen unless the Irish Government approve?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We have. My amendment might be in breach of the Convention but the Minister's amendment is <i>ultra vires</i> because it purports to bind an organisation outside this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a change of the Irish law within Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>But the Irish law within Ireland cannot bind an action of an international organisation. It cannot bind a citizen not to accept an appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>It can prevent the citizen claiming international immunity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what it purports to do.  It does not say anything about that.  It says that the official &ldquo;shall not be appointed&rdquo; which purports to bind the organisation concerned with the appointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1484" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The only thing it can bind is the Irish courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case the amendment is pointless and ineffective.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall see.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Minister whether he has been advised that these amendments purporting to limit these powers are in abrogation of the Conventions?  I suggest to him that the best solution now would be for the various amendments to be withdrawn to give him time for reconsideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>After hearing this discussion, I am even more satisfied than before that amendment No. 11 is the right one to go through with.  There have been all sorts of allegations made here that it is anti-Constitutional and that it is <i>ultra vires</i> the international Conventions but I think that any sensible person looking at this and seeing the problem will agree that this is not so.  Before giving an Irishman living here privileges and immunities very much greater or altogether different from the privileges that an ordinary Irish citizen has there should be grave necessity.  This amendment will throw the onus on the Government to give ordinary Irish citizens an assurance that no person is misusing his appointment to do acts in breach of the Irish law.  I do not think it is going to happen.  I do not think these immunities are necessary for the ordinary correspondence type of work that a number of people are asked to engage in by the secretaries of these international organisations.  I believe that amendment No. 11 will give the assurance that these international organisations cannot give immunities and privileges to our citizens here beyond what the ordinary citizen has without the consent of the Irish Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel that Senator FitzGerald has made an unusual suggestion in that he has suggested that both these amendments should be dropped leaving the Minister open to carry forward the Bill unamended <Col N="1485" /> in this respect to the Dáil. If between now and the Dáil he feels that on the whole amendment No. 11 is worthy of putting forward, he can put it forward and get it passed by the Dáil.  If, on the other hand, he feels, on reflection, that it is not the thing to do he can leave it as we are prepared to leave it.  I would be inclined to urge him to respect Senator FitzGerald's suggestion because I think it is probably the best solution for the reasons, the rather complicated reasons, but I think sound ones, put forward by him.  I draw attention to the fact that the Government amendment asks that the person &ldquo;shall not be appointed from among persons who are Irish citizens&rdquo; whereas Senator FitzGerald's amendment asks that the immunities &ldquo;shall not apply to an Irish citizen&rdquo;<i>et cetera</i>.  I feel, personally, that if I am forced as between these two I must vote for Senator FitzGerald's amendment. I should feel happier if the Minister would say: &ldquo;All right, for the moment we are dropping this&rdquo;.  He may feel that he will be bound to introduce an amendment similar to amendment No. 11 in the Dáil in which case good luck to him.  I think if it is opposed now many of us would feel that we would have to vote for amendment No. 12 and not for amendment No. 11.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we should pass amendment No. 11.  Let me say that at least I have a precedent for incorporating the words &ldquo;shall not be appointed&rdquo;.  I have referred to that which is the basic Convention on immunities and privileges&mdash;the Vienna <Col N="1486" /> Convention&mdash;and so we are using these words &ldquo;shall not be appointed&rdquo;.  There is no precedent that I know of for the suggestion made by Senator FitzGerald, that the privilege shall not be granted except the Government agree.  I think the amendment I suggest is clear, shorter and is more in line with the general Convention.  However, we will, of course, have to examine this again, even though our amendment goes through, to see if there is some way in which it can be improved.  I am perfectly satisfied with it as it stands. However, we will have a look at it.</P>
      <P>There is one objection to taking both out.  It would mean inevitably that if there was a section put into the Bill in the Dáil it would have to come back to the Seanad and this would drag out the procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>A fate the Minister wishes to avoid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It will have to come back to the Seanad in any event.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senators wish to put down a resolution, I shall be delighted to come back and I might have a few words to say to Senator G. FitzGerald if he puts down a resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister is in error.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I recommend that we pass this now and I need not assure the Seanad that if between now and the passage of the Bill through the Dáil I see that this section can be amended or improved in some respect, of course, I will do that.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 29; Níl, 14.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Ahern, Liam.<br />Boland, Gerald.<br />Brennan, John J.<br />Browne, Seán.<br />Cole, John C.<br />Connolly O'Brien, Nora.<br />Dolan, Séamus.<br />Eachthéirn, Cáit Uí.<br />Egan, Kieran P.<br />Farrell, Joseph.<br />Fitzsimons, Patrick.<br />Flanagan. Thomas P.<br />Honan, Dermot P.<br />Killilea, Mark.<br />McGlinchey, Bernard.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Martin, James J.<br />Nash, John Joseph.<br />Ó Donnabháin, Seán.<br />O'Kennedy, Michael.<br />Ó Maoláin, Tomás.<br />O'Reilly, Patrick. (Longford).<br />Ormonde, John.<br />O'Sullivan, Ted.<br />Ryan, Eoin.<br />Ryan, James.<br />Ryan, Patrick W.<br />Ryan, William.<br />Sheldon, William A.W.<br />Teehan, Patrick J.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1487" />
      <Col N="1488" /> Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Carton, Victor.<br />Conlon, John F.<br />Crowley, Patrick.<br />FitzGerald, Garret M.D.<br />McAuliffe, Timothy.<br />McDonald, Charles.<br />McHugh, Vincent.<br />Malone, Patrick.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Mannion, John.<br />O'Quigley, John B.<br />O'Reilly, Patrick. (Cavan).<br />O'Sullivan, Denis J.<br />Rooney, Éamon.<br />Sheehy Skeffington, Owen L.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá, Senators Browne and Farrell; Níl, Senators McDonald and Rooney.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 12 falls in consequence of that decision.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 12 not moved.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 13:</P>
      <P>In page 16, line 6, to delete &ldquo;aceptable&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;acceptable&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>This is just a drafting mistake.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 14:</P>
      <P>In page 87, to delete the Sixth Schedule and substitute the following:</P>
      <P Just="Center">SIXTH SCHEDULE</P>
      <P Just="Center">ENACTMENTS REPEALED</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="30*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="35*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="35*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Number and Year</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Short Title</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Extent of Repeal</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>(1)</entry>
            <entry>(2)</entry>
            <entry>(3)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 6 of 1967</entry>
            <entry>Income Tax Act, 1967.</entry>
            <entry>Subsection (3) of section 49 and sections 341 and 342.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 18 of 1957</entry>
            <entry>Bretton Woods Agreements Act, 1957.</entry>
            <entry>Paragraphs (a) and (b) of subsection (8) of section 3.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 22 of 1958</entry>
            <entry>International Finance Corporation Act, 1958.</entry>
            <entry>Subsection (7) of section 3.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>No. 35 of 1960</entry>
            <entry>International Development Association Act, 1960.</entry>
            <entry>Subsection (8) of section 3.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one minor point, and this in relation to the first enactment, that is a subsection of the Income Tax Acts 1967.  This Bill relates to diplomats, so it is fair enough from the point of view of such a Bill, but it strikes me that we have just consolidated the income tax law even though it seemed to cause some constitutional difficulty, and now we are amending the Consolidating, Act again.  The reason that I raise this is that anyone in the future who wishes to know what the income tax law is and is presented with the Consolidation Act will have to look as well at the Diplomatic Immunities Act for amendment to the Income Tax Act.  It strikes me that this is the sort of thing that leads to confusion&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>And to the need for lawyers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Mr. Sheldon Mr. Sheldon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sheldon</NameTxt>
      <P>Something should be done about this sort of thing.  There should be some cross reference somewhere, because people looking at the Income Tax Consolidation Act would not realise that within a couple of weeks in a Diplomatic Immunities Bill part of this Consolidated Act had disappeared.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that any diplomat coming here will, among the first things he does, look into how his <Col N="1489" /> income tax is going to be charged, and I am sure that the Consolidated Income Tax Act will be amended many times before the year is over, during the next few years at any rate. When we drafted this Bill and put it before the Seanad the Consolidated Income Tax Act had not been passed into law, and that is the reason why we have to amend this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is, of course, acceptable, but I should like to make one point in relation to the Income Tax Act which we discussed in this House last week. In the course of the discussion it emerged clearly, and the Minister for Finance made it perfectly clear and indeed emphasised the point, that the Procedure for the signature of the Acts would be that the amending Act which we were passing would be signed first and the principal Act afterwards.  It is disconcerting to discover that this statement was not only incorrect as regards what was going to happen but, in fact, was contrary to the statement which the President had made to the Council of State prior to that, and that we were misinformed.  This is of some importance because, if he had known of the stated intention of the President, the whole form of the Bill would have needed to be changed.  I take the occasion of this coming up here again to protest against the misleading information of the Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>What we are concerned with here is the Income Tax Act, 1967, that it is now proposed to amend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the form of signature that concerns me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This hardly arises.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendments and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I note that the Minister did not exclude the possibility <Col N="1490" /> of amending the amendment that he was pushing through and I hope that the point made will receive careful consideration and that some further amendment may be made in the Dáil.  I should like to thank the Minister for his courtesy in a prolonged debate on a technical point where he could understandably have been irritated by the length of time involved. I thank him also for the courtesy with which he dealt with the points.  It is always a pleasure to have him in the House and I have enjoyed the debate but I do hope the Bill will be further amended in the sense we have suggested when it goes to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnRooney" hpid="Mr. Rooney Mr. Rooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rooney</NameTxt>
      <P>On a matter of procedure, if we agree &ldquo;that the Bill do now pass&rdquo; does that mean the Minister would have no further obligation even if he had no intention of amending or that the opportunity would not be left to him?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo; this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>There is another House.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at 6 o'clock and resumed at 7.15 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Rent Restrictions (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1966: Second Stage">
    <Title>Rent Restrictions (Amendment) Bill, 1966: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. B. Lenihan) Brian (Snr.) Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. B. Lenihan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The main object of this Bill is, as the explanatory memorandum states, to encourage the maintenance in proper repair of the present stock of controlled houses and to do this without causing any hardship to existing tenants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is extremely important that we preserve as long as possible what stocks of housing we already have, and that we use resources on repair and reconstruction rather than on replacement of such stocks by new buildings.  This is true of all houses but it applies particularly <Col N="1491" /> to those covered by the Bill, most of which were built before 1919. It is particularly relevant when the demand for new housing continues to exist at such a high level.  It is noteworthy that the percentage of our housing stock which was built before 1919 is, at 58 per cent, one of the highest in Western Europe.  Only France, which has 62 per cent, exceeds it.</P>
    <P>We, therefore, particularly need to provide every encouragement possible to keep our old houses in good repair. The provision of repair and reconstruction grants on a considerable scale has done much in this direction. Over 150,000 houses have been repaired or reconstructed since 1948. These grants are for repairs of a more or less capital nature and not for ordinary running repairs.  It is only commonsense to advocate a &ldquo;stitch in time&rdquo; policy in the matter of housing maintenance to be followed by all owners of old houses, whether they be owner-occupiers, local authorities or private landlords.</P>
    <P>We are concerned in this Bill only with premises owned by private landlords which remain under the control of the Rent Restrictions Act, 1960.  A considerable number of rented dwellings are still controlled, though the proportion of controlled to uncontrolled dwellings is continuously declining. This is primarily due to obsolescence of existing dwellings and the construction of new, and, therefore, uncontrolled, dwellings.  Figures relating to the subject are hard to come by but in 1961 the percentage of controlled dwellings was approximately 14 per cent.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt that controlled rents are far below present open market levels, even when full allowance is made for the fact that many of the dwellings involved lack amenities which are now provided as a matter of course in new houses.  And I think there will be no disputing the proposition that, having regard to the increase in the cost of repairs since 1960, when landlords who were liable for repairs were given their last increase of 12½ <Col N="1492" /> per cent, landlords who have to carry out such repairs can do so only at a considerable reduction in their net income.  This, of course, has led to a disinclination to have the premises properly maintained.</P>
    <P>Since 1960 the cost of repairs to house property has increased substantially as a result of increases in building wages and the cost of materials.  The increase in building costs is estimated officially at 29 per cent from 1960 to June, 1966, but as the proportion of labour to materials in house repairs is higher than in building operations, the figure for the increase in repair costs would be substantially higher than this.  Moreover, the increased incidence of income tax since 1963 on the income from unfurnished lettings has further reduced the net income from controlled property.</P>
    <P>It is against this background that I am proposing in this Bill certain measures to encourage the maintenance of controlled property in proper repair and, not only this, but to strengthen the remedies of the tenant against the landlord who fails in his obligation in the matter of repair.</P>
    <P>First of all, the Bill proposes to allow an increase of 15 per cent in present net rents, subject to a minimum of 2/6 weekly.  This increase is no more than the maintenance of the <i>status quo</i> as in 1960, and it is subject to the important limitation that not only must the landlord be liable for repairs but he must have spent certain specified sums on the repairs in the six years before the 8th June, 1966, when the Bill was introduced. The form of notice of intention to increase the rent, which every landlord must serve to avail himself of this increase, will require particulars of this expenditure to be specified.  In other words, only landlords who have actually been carrying out repairs are going to get the increase.  Except in the case of landlords with more than 300 houses, this expenditure must be related to each individual dwelling.  In the case of these big estates, of which there are very few, the expenditure may be averaged.  I think the proposed increase is reasonable, and that tenants <Col N="1493" /> generally, who are equally as interested as the landlord in the proper maintenance of their dwelling accommodation, will regard it as such.</P>
    <P>The second provision relating to the maintenance of controlled houses is that which proposes to allow a lawful addition to landlords who have to spend more than one-fifth of the current rent in any year on any kind of maintenance.  The addition is to be 10 per cent on the excess expenditure. This addition will replace the existing provision allowing the landlord a graduated percentage of his outlay on what might be called &ldquo;once-and-for-all&rdquo; expenditure on major repair and reconstruction work.  It is at present 15 per cent on the first £100 of the excess expenditure over two-thirds of the basic rent, 8 per cent on the second £100 of the excess and 6 per cent on the remainder.  As the law stands, there is no provision for the recoupment to the landlord of what might be heavy expenditure on other repairs, for instance, on the replacement of the water pipes leading from the mains. He has no incentive whatever to incur expenditure on regular outside painting, which is necessary to preserve the fabric of the building itself quite apart from any considerations of decorative effect.  The Bill will ensure that, where landlords comply with their obligations to keep the premises in repair, they can no longer say that they will not receive a reasonable return on the expenditure.</P>
    <P>As a corollary, the Bill proposes, in section 11, to remove a great deal of the present uncertainties as to the incidence of liability for repairs in weekly or monthly lettings.  The tenants of many of these lettings have no written agreements and there is very often a great deal of difficulty experienced in determining who is liable for particular repairs.  From now on tenants will be able to pinpoint liability in this respect.  The section implies a convenant in such lettings that the landlord will be liable for keeping in repair the structure, including floors, the exterior, including painting, facilities for water, gas, sanitation, etc., and, in the case of flats, <Col N="1494" /> the ceilings.  This provision, together with the increased powers which section 8 gives to the court to reduce the rent in cases where landlords neglect their repairing responsibilities as well as the increased powers in this regard conferred on tenants by the recent Housing Act, will ensure that tenants can insist on their dwellings being kept in good repair at all times. Tenants have, of course, a number of other remedies against a landlord who fails in his obligation to keep property in repair and the removal of uncertainties about liability to repair will give these remedies fresh significance.</P>
    <P>I should like to draw special attention also to the provision in section 7 which enables a tenant to disallow a lawful addition obtained by the landlord for expenditure on maintenance if he satisfies the court that the expenditure was rendered necessary by breach of an obligation imposed on the landlord by contract or statute and that the landlord has not, during the three years immediately preceding the expenditure, spent a reasonable sum on the maintenance of the dwelling. However, in order that landlords may have an opportunity to put controlled property in good repair, it is proposed that this provision will not apply except to expenditure incurred on repairs done in 1970 or subsequently.</P>
    <P>What I have said so far deals with the primary purpose of the Bill, that is the conservation of existing controlled property, but the provisions in section 2 for the decontrol of certain houses will also indirectly serve to further that purpose.  The proposed decontrol will take place in three ways, in every case with full protection for the interests of existing tenants.  First of all, there will be an extension of decontrol on the landlord getting vacant possession.  At present there is decontrol on getting vacant possession only in respect of houses exceeding £30 valuation, in Dublin, and £25 elsewhere.  Under the Bill this will apply to all houses and also to self-contained flats.  This provision, naturally, does not affect sitting tenants at all.</P>
    <P>The other decontrol provisions in section 2 relate to very highly valued <Col N="1495" /> houses and self-contained flats and also to houses and self-contained flats which become occupited in future by unmarried persons between 21 and 65 years of age.  The tenants who may be decontrolled under these provisions are being given by section 13 automatic rights to a twenty-one year lease under Part III of the Landlord and Tenant Act, 1931.  I should not imagine that there are many of these houses or flats which would be occupied by persons who could not reasonably be asked to pay an economic rent for them but, in case there are, I have made special provision to ensure that no such tenant can be required to pay a rent under the new lease which would cause him or her hardship.</P>
    <P>The decontrol will not apply to existing lettings of rooms or non-self-contained flats in houses which are over the valuation limits.  Moreover, future lettings of such rooms and flats in houses decontrolled under either of these provisions will still be subject to control, though section 5 of the Bill provides that the controlled rent will be determined on a basis which will not be quite so restrictive as at present. The court, in determining such a rent, will have regard to the rents of other dwellings, not exclusively controlled dwellings.</P>
    <P>The final provision to which I should like to draw attention is that which will enable what I might call the &ldquo;small&rdquo; landlord to have a fair rent fixed by the District Court, a rent which will be reasonable and which will take into account all the circumstances of the case but, in the words of the Bill, in particular the necessity of avoiding financial hardship to the tenant and the landlord.  I am satisfied that this is a fair and just provision to insert in the Bill and that it will help to remove certain cases of hardship under the present code.  I have had several instances brought to my notice&mdash;and I am sure every Senator will know of similar cases&mdash;where the landlord has only one house or a few houses and is in relatively bad circumstances whereas the tenant is very comfortably off <Col N="1496" /> indeed.  Where this is the case I see no reason why the tenant should not be asked to pay a fair rent for the house, a rent he can afford.  It will be observed that this provision applies only to the review of the rents of controlled houses and self-contained flats.  It does not apply to any lettings of rooms.  These will continue to have the full protection of the Act.</P>
    <P>This Bill has been available now for some months and has been the subject of some very useful discussions in the Dáil.  I think I am correct in saying that the reaction to it has been such as to give me reason to believe that the Bill will be regarded generally, as I hoped it would, as a reasonable attempt to deal constructively with a matter of vital importance to tenants as well as landlords.  From the landlords' point of view, it will make it possible for them to recoup the costs of necessary repairs.  From the tenants' point of view it should help to ensure, so far as the law can do it, that they will have properly maintained houses to live in for as long as proper maintenance can keep the houses in existence. I hope that Senators will also see it as being a fair and reasonable approach to the problem.</P>
    <P>The Bill itself is, in form, somewhat complex, and necessarily so, because it is mainly concerned with amendments of the provisions of the 1960 Act.  For this reason I have had included in the explanatory memorandum, circulated with the Bill, as amended in Dáil Éireann, an Appendix which shows the effect of these amendments on the 1960 Act and I hope that this will be of assistance to Senators.  When the Bill becomes law arrangements will be made to have the sections as amended printed in such a way that they can be incorporated in existing copies of the 1960 Act.</P>
    <P>Finally, if there are any provisions on which Senators may require information I shall endeavour to deal with them now, and later in greater detail on the Committee Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very difficult to come to grips with this Bill because it deals with a very intractable problem <Col N="1497" /> and it is another effort within a period of six years to do justice as between the landlord and tenant and to try, at the same time, in the national interest to conserve and perhaps to increase our existing stock of houses.  I do not know and I suppose the Minister will not say to what extent that object will be achieved by the Bill.  I suppose it is a hope that the Minister has and one which we all share but I do not think it can be anything more than a hope.</P>
      <P>It seems to me extremely strange that a Bill of this kind should be introduced by the Minister for Justice.  I am always happy to see the Minister for Justice in this House introducing a Bill but it is strange that a Bill which deals with houses, housing, the repair of houses and the rent of houses is one that is introduced by the Minister for Justice whose chief preoccupation is certainly not the building of houses.  Why, in this day and generation, we cannot transfer this particular aspect of the Minister's functions to the Minister for Local Government I do not know.  Of course, it could be a precedent that in 1923 or 1924 when the first Rent Restrictions Act was introduced it was introduced by the Minister's predecessor in title. It is of interest to note that that particular Minister was the Minister for Home Affairs.  At least he had some connection in name if not, in fact, with rent restrictions and the application of rents to homes.  We have the crazy situation now where we have the Minister for Justice introducing this particular Bill and presently we shall have a Bill with which the Minister for Justice is intimately concerned being introduced by the Minister for Local Government, that is the Road Traffic Bill.  I suggest that these functions should be swapped by the Minister for Justice and the Minister for Local Government after consultation with the Taoiseach to make it regular and that the Minister for Justice should not be put in the position of having to acquire all this knowledge and information and that his Department, theoretically at least, should not have to be keeping all the statistics up to date when it is the proper concern of the Department of Local Government and its Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Perhaps that is the reason why there <Col N="1498" /> is such a refreshing air of frankness about the Minister's statement.  He has no delusions whatever as to the gap between housing requirements and the supply of houses in this country, nor has he any delusions as to the manner in which we have failed to keep pace with current and future needs.  He has been very frank on that.  It was necessary for him to be as frank as he was for the purpose of justifying this Bill and sketching in the background.</P>
    <P>Another general comment that occurs to me about the Bill is the criticism that the Minister has already anticipated.  I am sure the Minister was keenly aware of the fact that this is most undesirable type of legislation or very badly drafted type of legislation. We have the Rent Restrictions Act, 1960, and the main part of this Bill is concerned with sections 2 to 10 and with amending existing provisions in the Act.  May I say that some of the earlier provisions, particularly section 8, of the existing Rent Restrictions Act, are by no means simple and there is no lawyer who can say with certainty what they mean?  When to this we add the amendments provided by this Bill, it will not make the position clearer.</P>
    <P>This is something that should be borne in mind by the Minister in dealing with legislation of this kind.  We are dealing with people who have no incomes, who should be in a position to take up an Act of Parliament relating to their legal position and to read it with some hope of understanding it.  The Rent Restrictions Act, 1960, as passed, and as now to be amended, is a hopeless legal mess in so far as its interpretation by the ordinary citizen is concerned.</P>
    <P>I should like to say a word of gratitude to the Minister for the efforts which he has belatedly made in, I am sure, realising the situation and in incorporating the amendments in the existing sections of the Bill.  I am much obliged and I am sure the legal profession and the public will be greatly facilitated when the Bill is passed.</P>
    <P>I must confess that I do not like rent restriction, for the simple reason one can see many cases where it causes <Col N="1499" /> injustices to a person whose only source of income may be the dwelling which was left to him by a deceased spouse and which is let out in flats. Some people found themselves actually stuck by having these premises controlled, and being unable after a particular date in 1941 to increase the rents. These are diminishing in number but the problem may be very great for these people.</P>
    <P>At the same time, the supply of houses is hopelessly inadequate to meet the present needs.  This is borne out in the Housing Progress and Prospects White Paper laid by the Minister for Local Government before the House in November, 1964.  If my recollection is correct, the Minister indicated on the final reading of the Housing Bill in this year that although a substantial number of dwellings were built in the past 30 to 40 years, they did not keep pace with the deterioration and the obsolescence of premises, and that a very substantial number were required to be built each year in order to close the gap.  I understand that something of the order of 14,000 to 15,000 houses are required every year to meet the needs of the community.</P>
    <P>It is against that background we find that housing accommodation is an item in short supply and whenever you have an item in short supply, free market forces, as Senator Garret FitzGerald and others would say, begin to operate.  Rents will rocket as high as some of the skyscrapers which are being built as offices around Dublin at the present time.  Therefore, it is desirable to exercise control over rents and to provide that the shortage of this particularly necessary commodity will not be exploited, as happened in relation to other commodities in this country in time of war and no less in times of peace.  There is an acute shortage of houses.  We know what happened in Britain, which has come to be known as Rachmanism there.</P>
    <P>It is with mixed feelings that we look at this Bill.  There is a case for increasing rents.  Some of them are hopelessly low and are a tremendous bargain for the tenants; but there is also a case for <Col N="1500" /> ensuring that the rents of properties do not become oppressively high.  I am greatly concerned with the fact that as houses become decontrolled, the rents on these premises will become inordinately high and the owners of these properties will be able to exploit the current housing shortage.  That is a shortage which will persist for many years to come.  If there is a prospect of an increase in the immediate five or six years ahead in the stock of houses available in the country, and particularly in the cities, one would not feel too concerned by the prospect of decontrol. My fears at the present time are that the decontrolled houses will lead to a very definite upward increase in rents, in many cases beyond the point justified by the accommodation offered.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether the Minister, or the Government, contemplates at some later stage, or in some other measure, doing anything about the exploitation that will undoubtedly take place if this situation develops.  It may be that if the situation gets out of hand, and there may be some difficulty in getting statistics to show what the position is, the Government will have to act at some future time.  I should like to know the Minister's, and the Government's, view in relation to that problem if it should arise in the immediate future.</P>
    <P>I remember when the Rent Restrictions Bill, 1960, was brought before this House, many of us had mixed feelings about the increase of 12½ per cent given to landlords on the pretext that it was given because they were liable for repairs.  As I understand the Bill at the present time, and the Minister,s statement, I think the provision for an increase of 15 per cent will only lead to permissible open proof by the landlord that he has expended money on the repair of premises to justify his getting this increase.</P>
    <P>I felt at the time the 12½ per cent was being allowed that it should only be allowed where, in fact, the repairs had been carried out and were continued to be carried out by the landlord. The Minister might consider <Col N="1501" /> between now and Committee Stage, before this Bill passes the House, whether we ought to incorporate in the footnotes to the regulations prescribed under the Rent Restrictions Bill, and I presume to be prescribed under this Bill, some reference to the fact that a tenant is entitled to see that these repairs have been carried out, to see the basis on which he is being charged and, furthermore, is entitled to be informed by his landlord of his right to compel the landlord under the provisions of the Rent Restrictions Bill, to carry out certain necessary repairs. There are, unfortunately, far too many people in ignorance of their right to secure repairs on the part of the landlord under the Rent Restrictions Bill, and as a result of propaganda here in this House from time to time, unfortunately, and in many other places, and the general view of the public about lawyers, people are reluctant to go to lawyers to inquire what their rights are.  There are many persons who are in rent-controlled dwellings&mdash; in fact, I met one such recently&mdash;who would not go to any lawyer to find out what their rights are, though many of them would benefit substantially in their dwellings and their way of life, which would be more commodious and agreeable, if they knew that by service of a particular notice on the landlord, with a right afterwards to go into court, they could require him to put the premises in order or to provide the money.  They would very quickly avail themselves of it, but they do not know about it.  The Minister might consider, and I suppose the House when amending this Bill, making provision that this right to enforce repairs should be brought to the notice of the tenant.</P>
    <P>I am a bit disappointed that in a Bill like this that obviously has raked over every section of the Act there is not some clarification of what is the law in the present Act in relation to furnished lettings.  If certain lettings are furnished they may be controlled if the amount of the rent attributable to the furniture is equal to or less than one fourth of the rent.  The Minister, I am sure, is aware of this, that nobody knows how you are to assess <Col N="1502" /> what the portion of the rent is attributable to the furniture which is let. There are two different decisions by the Circuit Court in this country, and neither is entirely satisfactory.  If it is possible within the rules of the standing orders of the House to amend subsection 2 of section 3 paragraph D we ought to give some rule of thumb which would enable the amount of the rent attributable to furniture in a furnished letting to be calculated quite readily.</P>
    <P>Experienced auctioneers and valuers in my experience, have great difficulty in making up their minds what the position is, and nobody is certain about it.  Equally so before the Rent Restrictions Act nobody was certain what was meant by &ldquo;a member of deceased tenant's family&rdquo;.  Happily in the enactment of that Bill we got down to defining what the deceased tenant's family was.  A great deal of time was wasted in determining whether a son-in-law who was living in the house was a member of the deceased tenant's family, or if his sister, after he died, was a member of the deceased tenant's family.  All that kind of worthless litigation has been avoided by defining what the Legislature thinks ought to be the position. I can see different ways of defining this particular value to be attributed to furniture let in a so-called furnished letting.  There are particular ways of doing that.  If it is at all possible it should be done.</P>
    <P>There is a section in the Bill and I must confess that it fills me with apprehension and alarm.  Most civil servants will have heard of the notorious Finance Circular 44 of 1924.  This subsection 4 of section 2 is an echo of that.  We are now introducing a new principle into rent restrictions.  We are introducing what is called in the Civil Service marriage differentiaton, and we are going to provide that a bachelor or a spinster between the ages of 21 and 65 years of age are to be less favourably treated than a well-to-do married man who has a wife and no children or a married widower with no children or a widow with no children.  The introduction of that kind of distinction between citizens on the <Col N="1503" /> basis of their status whether married or single is a quite hopeless one and on principle I would object to it most strenuously.</P>
    <P>Many people in flats have grown from what one would call lovely young girls into their thirties and forties, and they have done that because they have stayed at home to look after an ailing father and mother or to support a widowed mother, and they may be one of the spinsters between the ages of 21 and 65 whom we are going to single out for unfavourable treatment.  We ought to observe the constitutional provision that all citizens shall as human persons be equal before the law in the matter of rent restriction equally as in other matters.  I do not know of any defence that can be offered for discriminating against people who are bachelors or spinsters, some by choice which they are entitled to exercise, and some by necessity, through social necessity or for family reasons.  I should like to hear the Minister's justification of that.  I do not know how anybody can justify subsection (4) of section 2, and, mark you, this is going to apply only to those persons who become tenants after this Bill is passed.  I am not concerned with that.  I am concerned with the principle that we ought not to discriminate against people who are very worthy and admirable members of society and who have remained or been obliged to remain bachelors or spinsters, some through misfortune and some through motives of family benevolence.</P>
    <P>The Minister has very rightly referred to the age and to the shortage of houses in his speech on the Second Stage here in the House.  This is the kind of thing that puzzles me.  While we are concerned about the shortage of houses and trying, in fact, to make available a greater flow of dwellings for the community, we are proposing to loosen restrictions and free from control a number of houses that are at present controlled, but at the same time the Minister's colleague who should be dealing with this Bill, in my view, the Minister for Local Government, is making an order under the Local <Col N="1504" /> Government (Planning and Development) Act that permits persons to knock down perfectly good houses, perfectly fit for use as dwellings, without even seeking planning permission or permission from anybody else.</P>
    <P>It seems to be quite absurd to say that on one hand we recognise that there is a housing shortage and that we are proposing to permit landlords to increase rents because there is a housing shortage, and at the same time to permit perfectly good dwelling houses to be demolished without reference to anybody.  To my mind there is something that has a ring of Marie Antoinette here&mdash;&ldquo;if they cannot get bread let them eat cake&rdquo;&mdash; about the permission that is given by the Planning and Development Act to people to demolish houses while there is such an acute shortage&mdash;a shortage so acute that the Government are prepared to ask this House by legislation to increase the cost of housing to the citizens by permitting certain increases in rent.  I think that the Minister for Justice, who has no responsibility for the stock of houses in this country, and no responsibility for the administration of the Local Government (Planning and Development) Act, should in the exercise of his collective responsibility within the Government get in touch with the Minister for Local Government and say that on the one hand it is crazy to say that there are not enough houses and on the other that we are permitting speculative builders who are coming in from England to demolish houses which are perfectly good and could well be used for the purpose of housing people who are badly housed.  There is no escape from the obligation on the Government to prevent this unbridled licence to demolish, incorporated in the planning regulations and, at the same time, saying we must increase rents in accordance with the increasing stock of houses.  As the Minister has indicated, this Bill is largely a Committee measure.</P>
    <P>Before I conclude, I should like to ask the Minister if he would have a look as subsection (3) of section 10. I should like to know if we are not, <Col N="1505" /> in that particular subsection, resurrecting the ghost of sections 10 and 18 of Deasy's Act which I thought we had laid peacefully to rest in the Grounds Rents Bill recently?  I have not gone into it very deeply but perhaps the Minister would deal with that in his reply.  In addition, perhaps he might clarify another matter for the benefit of existing tenants: what is the present liability, under section 39 of the Rent Restrictions Act of 1960, of the landlord for repairs?  Section 39 of that Act provides:</P>
    <P>For the purposes of paragraph (b) of subsection (2) of section 10 and sections 14, 15 and 40 of this Act, the landlord shall be deemed to be responsible for any repairs for which the tenant is not under any liability, whether expressed in the contract or implied under section 42 of the Landlord and Tenant Law (Amendment) (Ireland) Act, 1860.</P>
    <P>That, to my mind, is the kind of legislation which is most unhelpful to people who want to ascertain their rights and liabilities and, in the context of increasing rents, where the landlord is to be entitled to an increase because he carries out repairs, I should like the Minister to indicate&mdash;perhaps this is a question on which he should have more notice and if he does not do so now, perhaps he could at a later stage&mdash;what is the liability of tenants, having regard to the provisions of section 39 of the Rent Restrictions Act of 1960.  It is extremely difficult to ascertain as the whole of the law is not to be found in section 42 of the Landlord and Tenant Law (Amendment) (Ireland) Act, 1860, because there are some decided cases which deal with the position at common law and the whole thing is extremely vague.  In a Bill of this kind, where we are dealing with people of modest incomes, we ought to try to set out clearly&mdash;if it can be done within the Standing Orders of the House&mdash;what is the liability so that anybody can know and we will not have to have test cases to ascertain the position.</P>
    <P>Having said so much, I do not intend to offer any welcome to the Bill, because I view it with misgivings; I <Col N="1506" /> have mixed feelings about it and much depends on the examination we shall make of it on Committee Stage as to whether&mdash;at the end of the day&mdash;we shall say we have done a good job for housing, for landlords and tenants in passing the Rent Restrictions Bill of 1966.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make up for the fact that Senator O'Quigley is not prepared to welcome the Bill: I am prepared to do so.  I think this is a very necessary Bill which deals with the problem set out for us by the Minister in a very resonable way.  The figure given of the number of houses in the country built before 1919&mdash;I think it was 58 per cent&mdash;certainly illustrates the fact that we have a very large number of houses which must be in constant need of repair and which will become quite useless in a relatively short time, unless they are maintained very diligently and repaired, when necessary.  It proves the necessity for giving landlords some financial incentive to carry out the repairs which are necessary.</P>
      <P>I do not think anybody in the House would wish unnecessarily to remove or to decrease the amount of protection given to tenants but, in the circumstances outlined to us by the Minister, it is quite clear there must be some decrease in the amount of protection given, in order that these repairs should be carried out.  The very high rise in the cost of building&mdash;mentioned at 29 per cent&mdash;and the even higher cost of carrying out repairs certainly make it quite clear that considerable financial incentives will have to be given to landlords if they are to be encouraged to carry out these repairs.</P>
      <P>Most of the Bill is, of course, more a matter for Committee Stage than for this Stage and I do not propose to go into any of the sections in detail but I should like to comment on what the Minister said in regard to the fact that when the Bill had been passed, he hoped to make arrangements to have the sections printed in such a way that they could be incorporated in the 1960 Act.  This is a very useful suggestion and an arrangement which I hope the Minister will carry out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1507" /> I had a discussion recently with one of the German diplomats accredited to this country and he discussed with me the Income Tax Consolidation Bill which was in the news at that time. He was particularly interested in this question of consolidation because, he said, that as far as Germany was concerned, consolidation legislation was something they did not have.  He said the reason for this was that as each Act was passed in Germany&mdash;which amended a previous Act&mdash;the previous Act was immediately printed again, incorporating the amendments which had been made.  Consequently, there was no necessity for going back through various Acts to see how they were affected and amended by the latest Act.  As each Act was passed, it was incorporated into the old Act and one could, at any time, know all the law on a particular subject by looking at the up-to-date edition of the Act dealing with the particular subject in question.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Justice has been introducing quite a lot of legislation in recent years, and will probably continue to do so.  I would suggest to him that he might look into the question of introducing a system, something on the German lines, for Acts in this country. It is something which would certainly be of great benefit to practitioners and to the public generally if the law were brought up to date regularly as each new Act was passed.</P>
    <P>In the meantime, as this seems to be a rather ambitious change in the practice in this country and something which it might not be possible to introduce immediately, I would ask him that when amendments are made in Acts, instead of passing amendments which merely say that a section shall be amended or altered in the following way, the amendment be made by way of deleting the section in the previous Act and substituting a completely new section, so that at least it would not be necessary to carve up the whole section, put in new words or take out other words, as the case might be.  It certainly would be a step in the direction I have suggested: it would be a <Col N="1508" /> great help if amendments were made in that way&mdash;that sections would be entirely deleted by amendment and a new section incorporated and the change required put in its place.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Giving it a rebore, like reboring a car.  I suggest to the Minister that he might even do it in this Bill because it is already available in the Appendix.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That really is all I have to say on the Bill at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have just a few brief observations to make, additions to what my colleagues, Senators O'Quigley and E. Ryan, have said. We can appreciate the Minister's difficulty and anxiety in introducing this legislation.  His anxiety is shared by many who are concerned about the maintenance and the state of repair of our houses and about doing justice as between landlord and tenant.  The Minister referred to the fact that a substantial proportion of our houses are controlled by comparison with those of other countries, with the possible exception of France.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the interests of the appearance of our buildings, this Bill should certainly be welcome because it offers to landlords an incentive which had not been previously available to them&mdash; compensation for external repairs. All of us concerned with the general appearance of country towns in particular and the tenement areas in our cities must welcome an attempt to deal with that problem, Senator O'Quigley rightly pointed out that the Bill would be very acceptable, were we guaranteed or assured there would be an adequate number of houses available.  This is something on which we cannot be helped by present experience.  We all appreciate the need for providing an adequate number of houses at reasonable rents and prices for those who are not able to make provision for themselves.  In putting these tenements, as one could call them, on the open market and allowing the rents to be determined by the market demand, the Minister is taking a <Col N="1509" /> calculated risk.  It is certainly one that is warranted in the situation.  If it appears that market rents are inflated and are more than those in need of such accommodation can afford, it is quite open to the Minister to come back and review this legislation.</P>
    <P>This is not by any means comprehensive legislation.  It decontrols a substantial number of types of controlled property but it does not close the door to the introduction of amendments to the amendments introduced in this Bill.  This has been the tradition in rent restriction legislation and even though it may make the legislation more sloppy, more difficult for lawyers to understand, at the same time this is hardly the first consideration.  If further amendments appear necessary in the light of experience, I feel sure the Minister will feel obliged to introduce them.</P>
    <P>I share Senator O'Quigley's inhibition in relation to the fact that apparently bachelors and spinsters will be treated differently from other members of the community.  Senator O'Quigley has indeed made a fair case for what is a very exceptional problem, that of a spinster in the city of Dublin or elsewhere&mdash;there are many such&mdash;who finds herself in difficulties &mdash;&ldquo;difficulties&rdquo; is a reasonable word in the circumstances&mdash;for voluntary reasons and sometimes for involuntary reasons&mdash;I suspect more often for involuntary reasons.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>And therefore deserving of our pity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>In so far as the Legislature should be concerned with pity, I cannot see why we are making provisions for our bachelors and spinsters.  It may be intended to ensure that those people who have not dependants, in the same way as married men and women, by virtue of their status will be asked to pay somewhat more.  That may be the general thinking behind it but I foresee experience may prove that the purpose, while apparently being justified, may not justify the result because this could amount to a restraint on marriage.  If <Col N="1510" /> we are to see &ldquo;No married couples&rdquo; notices going up all round because landlords feel they will be in a more advantageous position with bachelors and spinsters, we shall find ourselves coming back quite quickly because married couples will find it more difficult to be accommodated.</P>
      <P>There is only one other doubt I have and I think it is one the Minister may be able to clear up.  Under section 13&mdash;the one which gives the right, where a tenancy has become uncontrolled, to obtain a new 20-year lease&mdash; the right appears to attach not to the tenant but to the premises, and it appears to me&mdash;I may be wrong&mdash; that a tenant could go into a premises which had become decontrolled, a new tenant who never was a controlled tenant, and could rely on the right to a new tenancy under this section.  I may be taking a very drastic view of this but I am not satisfied as I read it that the right does not attach to the premises rather than the tenant.  If this were so, it would be a very unfair restriction on landlords and would confer an unfair right on tenants, who could come from as far afield as America, Africa or some other continent&mdash;students or otherwise&mdash;and find themselves in the position of uncontrolled tenants.  That can hardly be what the section was intended to mean but it is open to that interpretation as it stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>Unlike other Senators who have spoken, I am not at all too sure I can extend a warm welcome to the Bill.  Certainly any welcome we could extend to it would be qualified. The Minister admits that the measure is very complex.  It is obviously the type of Bill which you would want to have a very close look at before you could say that you approve of all its provisions.  From the examination I gave to the Bill so far I am left with the impression that there are certain aspects of it which are quite discriminating. This is something which my colleagues and I want to have a look at.  We may have something more to say about that on Committee Stage and we may have some amendments to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1511" /> The other aspect of the Bill on which I should like to comment at this stage is that the Bill provides better housing for certain people.  You talk about incentives here but we should keep our feet on the ground in this regard and bear in mind that any incentives in this Bill will be provided at the expense of a lot of people who in many instances are the very people who will be subjected to increased rents.  The Minister and the Government are taking a grave risk at the moment in assuming that any section of people to whom this class of housing would be a direct concern, are in a position, under present circumstances, to pay anything in the line of increased rents.</P>
    <P>That is a feature of the Bill which requires very serious study by every Member of this House.  I suggest that if there is any calculated risk involved here of a further fairly substantial contribution towards another upward jump in the cost of living for a lot of people this is something which we should look into very carefully.  The next impression I am left with, on my reading of the explanatory memorandum, is that the Bill appears to be nibbling at the whole complex problem of housing in this country.  I am not at all satisfied that this is the type of legislation we should be dealing with when, in fact, we are making any approach to this problem.</P>
    <P>I should like to say at this point, on my own behalf and on behalf of my colleagues, that the responsibility for a dynamic housing policy rests fairly and squarely on the Government.  I do not think that the problem of housing will be solved by measures of this kind.  Because of the complex nature of the Bill the Labour Party propose at this stage to study the measure.  On Committee Stage we may have a lot more to say about it and we may, indeed, have some amendments to propose.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMolone" hpid="Mr. Malone Mr. Malone">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Malone</NameTxt>
      <P>I was rather relieved to hear Senator O'Quigley and Senator O'Kennedy coming to the rescue of the bachelors and the spinsters.  It is outrageous in this day and age that we <Col N="1512" /> are going to differentiate between those sections when it comes to housing.  Very often spinsters and bachelors have had to retire from business or from their profession due to illness or other causes.  The circumstances may not be equal in any way to the commitments which they may have to meet in their rents.  I hope that by the time we come to Committee Stage the Minister will have made provision to delete that section from the Bill.</P>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill, as the Minister pointed out, is to help to conserve our stock of houses.  He states it would be better to preserve it by building new houses.  Most of those houses he states were built before 1919.  The lack of housing at the present time is causing people to pay rents far in excess of what they can afford.  It is a question of getting a roof over your head and waiting until such time as you may get a site to build a house of your own.  Unfortunately, there are landlords whose consciences are a bit elastic and who are prepared to charge rents in excess of what they should.  I think the cost of repair and reconstruction of some of the houses people are living in at present, especially in the cities, would almost equal what they cost to build originally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another problem in this regard and that is town planning. Many of those houses are being allowed to fall into disrepair because it was suggested at some stage or other that they would be demolished for street-widening or something else.  We had an example in Dublin out in Ballsbridge where big old houses were reconstructed and huge sums of money spent on them.  They were made into luxury flats and people are living in them quite happily.  Now hanging over their heads is the threat that those houses will be demolished to make room for the Kennedy Memorial Hall. There is a terrible lack of liaison between the various Departments in this regard.  Money is being spent where demolition will take place and money is not being spent in case demolition will take place.  That problem is being aggravated rather than <Col N="1513" /> relieved.  As some of the other speakers said we can deal with this better on Committee Stage but it will take a lot of cleaning up to make me welcome this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> There is one aspect of this matter which should be referred to, that is the basic reason for the introduction of this Bill.  Now, it appears that nobody is over-happy about it.  The Minister did not seem over-happy but he made it apparent to the Houses that it was necessary to have a wider freedom in regard to the control of houses in order to ensure that houses would be kept up to a higher standard in view of the housing shortage.</P>
      <P>That tempts me to raise a question in the hope that I may get an answer. Perhaps it may not be the correct answer or I may not get any answer. I should like to inquire if we have any notion at all as to the length of the useful life of our housing estates throughout the country, having regard to the capital investment in housing estates.  I should like to inquire if we have comparative figures in relation to any other country.  I raise these matters because it occurs to me that, as a people, we would need to pull up our socks in regard to the question of maintenance and repair.  I suggest that in regard to motor cars and machinery of all kinds our capital investment is substantial.  I also suggest that because we are not machine-minded or perhaps because of our lack of care we obsolete our capital investment in motor cars more rapidly than other countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To what event does that apply to our housing?  It appears to me that it is the basic reason for the Minister having to introduce the Bill.  Speaking of machinery, this applies very much to farm machinery.  I believe our national loss from failure to maintain properly our farm machinery is very great and that there is a large area of national wastage in that regard.  Perhaps that also applies to our houses. The Minister is introducing this measure in the hope of enticing people to do more maintenance and more repair.  &ldquo;Repair&rdquo; is the word, maintenance is carried out daily, weekly <Col N="1514" /> and yearly.  Repair is a different thing. Our failure to maintain and repair creates a major problem in regard to reconstruction of houses.</P>
    <P>I shall not enter into a discussion upon the different things that have been referred to by other Members, Senator E. Ryan, Senator O'Kennedy and Senator O'Quigley, in regard to the question of differentiation.  This measure was passed by the Dáil. Without going into the merits of it, I would find it hard to accept that if it is anti-social no member of Dáil Éireann saw fit to raise it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is why we are here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> I have not a firm view on that.  Just as we obsolete our national capital too quickly on motor cars so we are inclined to do the same in regard to housing and it is regrettable that the Minister has to bring in this measure because it contains certain risks.  There is always the risk that some people might suffer severe hardship or exploitation as a result of decontrol in certain circumstances.  I am afraid, however, we must face up to the fact that it is necessary with a view to maintaining our national estate in housing.  It would be far better if we adopted a better attitude to maintenance so that the money we invest in housing would last longer and houses would have a longer useful life and not in a very short time become drab, unkempt establishments.  Many of our housing estates in the private and in the local authority sectors leave room for improvement along that line and it is only if we keep an eye on that that there will be hope for improvement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>The discussion in the Seanad has been a constructive one.  The Bill, as is obvious, is largely a Committee Stage Bill.  There are two main principles in the Bill which are the main subject of Second Stage debate.  They are (a) the greater degree of decontrol which is introduced and (b) the increased rent which we are now permitting the landlord to get having regard to repairs carried out by him since 1960.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1515" /> The main purpose of these two aspects is to ensure that the stock of houses which we have by way of controlled premises do not go into disrepair and so cause not alone loss to landlord and hardship to tenant but greater loss to the country as a whole by reducing the available stock of houses and so compelling the community to invest at far greater expense in new houses.  It is necessary to ensure that we preserve our existing stock of houses.  A measure of this kind does it by providing a greater degree of decontrol where that does not cause hardship and also by providing for increased rents in order to ensure the proper maintenance and repair of houses by landlords.</P>
    <P>Of course, in any measure of this kind one must preserve a balance between the interests of the community, the interests of the landlord and the interests of the tenant.  This marks a step away from control which was introduced originally as an emergency measure in the first world war, and extended in the second world war.  The policy now is to move away from that degree of control which was initiated during two emergency periods.</P>
    <P>The 1960 Act marked a substantial step away from control and this amendment of the 1960 Act marks yet another step away from the rigid control which was involved in the original emergency legislation.  At the same time, we are ensuring that we step away from control in such a way that justice is done to tenants and no hardship caused to people in the process.  I see this as a continuing process and indeed this was set out in the Second Programme for Economic Expansion as being a desirable development because there is no point in having a substantial corps of houses subject to control which will go into disrepair due to inadequate rents or over-rigid control. One must maintain a balance to ensure that one goes away from the principle of control gradually while, at the same time, not causing hardship to tenants in the process.</P>
    <P>This is the thinking behind the Bill in general principle.  In detail, of course, there is much to be discussed <Col N="1516" /> on Committee Stage as, indeed, there was discussed on Committee Stage in the Dáil so as to ensure that this Bill, when grafted on to the 1960 Act, will work as we intend it to.  The whole field of rent restriction legislation is, to put it mildly, a very complicated one.</P>
    <P>As I mentioned in my Second Reading speech, one idea which we are bringing in here for the first time in this Bill is to set out in the Appendix to the Memorandum the sections in the 1960 Act which are being amended. This is for the convenience of the general public and practitioners.  I should mention that when this is in final form for publication I propose to have each of these pages of the Appendix bare on one side.  At the moment they are written on two sides but I propose to have them bare on one side so that a complete section can be seen.  For instance, if one looks at page 9 of the Appendix one has there a major part of section 3.  I would like to see that with nothing on the back so that it can be grafted straight away on to the original 1960 Act.  This will mean that the pages on one side can be lifted from the Appendix and pasted on to the 1960 Act.  Then one has the amended 1960 Act in one complete document.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister take the bold step of doing what Senator Ryan suggested?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am coming to that.  This is a matter which I am having considered at the moment.  The reason why I took the immediate practical step of doing what I have just described is that there are certain complications in regard to parliamentary procedure in going any further. But I am having these complications examined with a view to having as a permanent feature the system which exists in Germany of grafting on in printed form amending enactments to existing measures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have in recent years embarked on a fair amount of consolidation measures in this country.  This is an appropriate time to consider how we can organise the publication of a printed edition incorporating both the <Col N="1517" /> amendment and the original provision. I understand there are a number of difficulties in regard to this but I shall not go into them at the moment.  I thought the practical measure of the Appendix would suit and when this explanatory memorandum will be in final form it will enable the practitioner and members of the public to paste it on to the original statute and thus give the full picture.</P>
    <P>In regard to a number of matters which were raised by Senators and which I think are largely of a Committee stage nature, I will have them examined between now and Committee Stage.  I might reply in general terms now to them.</P>
    <P>Senators O'Quigley, O'Kennedy and Malone mentioned a point which probably caused the greatest discussion here and, mind you, which escaped comment in the Dáil.  From the comments made by the Senators concerned I can see some validity in what they say. What we are proposing to do in section 2 in regard to unmarried parties between the ages of 21-65 is that we are taking them out of the controlled category and giving them the protection of the Landlord and Tenant Act. The thinking behind that is that you have, again in accordance with the general thinking behind the Bill, many cases of under-occupied houses throughout the country, where you have a spinster or a bachelor living in a house which can be occupied by a large family.  While they remain in occupation because of the operation of rent control it does appear an under-utilisation of the house or houses concerned. This was the thinking behind the section.  However, it could operate as a hardship in the case of a small house.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly in the case of a flat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Or in the case of a self-contained flat.  It occurs to me in regard to what has been said that we might consider between now and Committee Stage restricting this provision to houses and excluding self-contained flats and excluding houses under a certain valuation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1518" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford) Mr. P. O'Reilly (Longford)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Longford):</i> Valuations vary from place to place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us not get too technical.  Justice might be done by the general principle which I have in mind.  We might ensure the greatest utilisation possible of our stock of houses and also avoid hardship towards people in the category mentioned. A balance might be achieved by excluding self-contained flats and by limiting the provision to houses over a certain valuation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister consider in making the best possible use of houses, going the distance of persuading his colleague the Minister for Local Government to prevent the automatic demolition of houses that is permitted&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is another day's work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us ride one hobby horse at a time; that has nothing to do with the matter under discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister to conclude on Second Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Quigley mentioned another technical point concerning a definition of &ldquo;furnished letting&rdquo;.  That has been a vexed question for a long time, not alone because of this Bill but because of the 1960 Act and preceding Acts as well and this is a matter to which I have already directed the attention of my advisers. There are court decisions in regard to the definition of furnished lettings. The difficulty is that any change you might make in regard to a definition could adversely affect existing tenants who have benefited by reason of these decisions.  You might bring in a definition which might decontrol them where they have up to now got away with it under the court decisions.  Still, it is not satisfactory and it is a matter we are looking into with a view to seeking a more precise form of definition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The whole question of over-definition under the Rent Restriction code is an awkward one.  For instance, Deputy Dillon in the Dáil thought we should <Col N="1519" /> have a more precise definition of &ldquo;self-contained flat&rdquo;.  This has been a subject of discussion over the years and it is probably better, having regard to the very nature of furnishings, the very nature of flats, whether they are self-contained, or not self-contained not to have precise definitions.  It is often undesirable to over-define matters of this kind because of their very nature and may be better, on balance, to leave it to the courts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not mind leaving it to the courts to determine whether a flat is furnished or unfurnished or self-contained.  The real difficulty is in trying to calculate the amount of rent that is attributable to the letting value of the furniture.  What figure do you take?  This is the difficulty the courts have and there are two different decisions by the Circuit Court and these have never gone to the High Court.  There is nothing in the Bill to say how you calculate the proportion of the rent that is attributable to the letting value of the furniture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Again I understand that valuers at the moment have a formula which works pretty well in the courts.  It is a formula without a statutory basis but, in practice, it works out all right.  It is certainly important that we should look into this because I would prefer, as Senator O'Quigley prefers, a more precise form of definition, but it is not an easy matter.  It is one which we will examine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards section 10 (3) I do not think Senator O'Quigley need have any worry about our bringing back the provisions of Deasy's Act which we repealed under the Ground Rents Act. The subsection only relates to restrictions on assignments outside the tenant's family.  This is desirable having regard to the new principle in the Bill which prohibits assignment of controlled premises to any person outside the family.  It is only fair to landlords. A number of cases have come to my notice where tenants have made a substantial sum of money by assigning <Col N="1520" /> their controlled interest to a person outside their family, to the detriment and prejudice of landlords existing on very small rents.  If there is any merit in such controlled tenancy passing on, such merits would only lie in the case of a transfer or assignment to a member of the tenant's own family.  What has come to my notice in meeting various people concerned with this Bill, and indeed with the Grounds Rent Bill, is that, contrary to popular mythology, there are a number of poor landlords &mdash;very poor and small landlords, and a number of landlords with one, two, three and four houses deriving their income from controlled rents while the tenants living in their controlled houses are far better off, far wealthier and in receipt of far higher incomes than the landlords concerned.</P>
    <P>What struck me very forcibly both in connection with representations on this Bill and on the previous Bill, now an Act, was the quite large number of such people who exist.  These are unorganised people; they do not form any pressure group.  They are quite ordinary people, and every person has a right to write into the Minister for Justice or to make representations.  I might say that a substantially large number of representations to me, both by letter and personally, showed the greatest hardship to landlords.  Since this Bill was published some months ago, I had no representations or complaints from any tenants in regard to increasing the rent.  I had, naturally, representations from big landlords. One would expect this, as they are organised.  But the representations that struck me most personally and on a humanitarian basis have come from quite small landlords&mdash;elderly people, widows or widowers or people in that category, who are in receipt of quite meagre incomes out of quite a small number of houses which are controlled. That is why we are bringing in here a novel provision, which has not received much comment here in the House, whereby small landlords are now to be permitted to apply to the court to have a fair rent fixed.  This is only right and proper, because it has always been the concern of the House when passing legislation to ensure that justice is <Col N="1521" /> done to all citizens.  We are providing that landlords with six houses or less of a valuation not exceeding a total of £60, will be able to apply to the court to have a fair rent fixed, just as at present the tenant may apply.</P>
    <P>I do not think that there is anything more that I should speak about. We have had much constructive discussion on the principles of the Bill.  I take it that that constructive discussion and our thoughts on the matter between now and Committee Stage will lead to the framing of amendments by myself and by Senators on which we can again have a useful discussion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>As has become customary with the Minister.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 5th April.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Criminal Procedure Bill, 1965:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Criminal Procedure Bill, 1965: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. B. Lenihan) Brian (Snr.) Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. B. Lenihan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The main object of this Bill is to abolish the present procedure for the preliminary examination of indictable offences and to substitute for it a procedure which will, I expect, result in the virtual abolition of the taking of depositions.  There are other provisions in the Bill, such as those dealing with remand in Part III and the miscellaneous amendments in Part IV, but they are subordinate to this main object.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under our system of criminal procedure, and that of most other countries, there is provision for a preliminary investigation by a judicial officer of the case against a person accused of a serious crime.  That officer has power to decide whether or not the case disclosed by the prosecutor is sufficient to justify putting the accused person on trial.  For a very long time now our procedure has been that this investigation is carried out before a district justice and all the evidence has to be written out by the district court <Col N="1522" /> clerk in longhand.  The written deposition is read over to each witness after his evidence has been taken and, finally, all the depositions are read over to the accused at the conclusion of the evidence for the prosecution. The district justice then considers any statement the accused himself may make on being cautioned, and finally decides whether or not the prosecution has established a sufficient case to justify putting the accused on trial.</P>
    <P>It is hardly necessary to say that this can be a most tedious and expensive procedure.  It takes up to some 600 days a year of the time of district justices, not to speak of the time, expense and inconvenience of the other persons concerned in the proceedings. Although it has the advantage from the accused's point of view that the depositions provide an indication of the prosecution case which the present system does not otherwise give him, he has to undergo a distressing period in court even when, in fact, there is no doubt that the evidence against him is more than adequate to justify his being sent forward for trial.</P>
    <P>Experience shows that very few accused persons disclose their defence at this stage or bring forward any witnesses on their behalf.  Only about one per cent of persons arrested or summoned for indictable offences are discharged at this point of the proceedings.</P>
    <P>To obviate what everybody agrees is an undesirable situation I am proposing in this Bill that, whenever an accused person is brought before the District Court charged with an indictable offence, he is to be supplied with a complete statement of the prosecution case before the commencement of the preliminary examination.  The accused is also being entitled to waive the preliminary examination.  He may still consent, as he can under the present law, to be tried summarily by the district justice in certain circumstances; or he may plead guilty and be sentenced there and then by the District Court or be sent forward for sentence by the Circuit Criminal Court.  In deference to views expressed during the passage of the Bill through the Dáil, I have preserved the absolute right of <Col N="1523" /> the prosecutor or the accused to require evidence to be given on sworn deposition.</P>
    <P>Previous experience suggests that the deposition procedure will in future be availed of very sparingly, so that the proposed new procedure should be of considerable benefit to all concerned. From the point of view of the State, although local State Solicitors will have the task of preparing statements of the evidence to be given at the trial on the basis of the statements made to the garda, there will be a substantial saving in the time spent in the District Court on the preliminary investigation. This saving of time and expence applies to everybody concerned in the proceedings, including witnesses.  From the point of view of the accused, he not only retains his present right to have evidence taken on deposition but he will know, in advance of the preliminary examination, what exactly the prosecution evidence will amount to.  He is also saved the distress involved in prolonged attendances for taking unnecessary depositions. He has these advantages in addition to those inherent in the present procedure, that is, he may require the evidence that is to be given against him to be given on oath and he may test it in cross-examination and possibly succeed in satisfying the district justice that no <i>prima facie</i> case has been made out against him.  He has also the further advantage, to which I will refer again in a moment, that the case against him at this preliminary stage may not be published unless he himself desires it and, even then, the district justice has discretion to refuse his application for publication.</P>
    <P>On the whole, therefore, I think I can fairly claim that the Bill represents a reasonable balance between the necessity for modernising the present procedure and ensuring at the same time that the rights of accused persons are fully preserved.</P>
    <P>On the question of publication of the proceedings at the preliminary examination, the Bill provides that, unless the accused person requires publication, no one may publish any <Col N="1524" /> information about the proceedings other than a statement of the fact that they have been held in relation to a named person on a specified charge and also, of course, a statement of the decision of the district justice at the conclusion of the examination.  Provision is made in subsection (3) of section 17 that this prohibition will not apply to the publication of such information as the justice permits to be published at the request of the accused.  Side by side with this prohibition on publication, which goes further than the existing restrictions on publication contained in the Criminal Justice Act, 1951, there is a re-affirmation, in section 16, of the provision that a preliminary examination must be in open court.  There will still be cases, however, where the court will have power to exclude the public where this is desirable in the interests of justice or required by any enactment.  Apart from cases, such as incest cases which must be held <i>in camera</i> this power of the District Court to exclude persons from the court room will not apply to press representatives or to certain other persons such as parents or friends or an accused person who, under the present law, have a right to be present.</P>
    <P>Here again, I think the provisions of the Bill are such as will command a good deal of general support.  As I mentioned in the Dáil, I am gratified to learn that our journalists individually, and the Press as a whole, were overwhelmingly in favour of non-publication of the preliminary proceedings for the reason that publication might be prejudicial to the fair trial of the accused.  This was also the unanimous view of the Committee on Court Practice and Procedure, under the chairmanship of Mr. Justice Brian Walsh, on whose First Interim Report Part II of this Bill has largely been based.  I should like to pay tribute here to the work of this Committee, not only as represented by that particular Report, but also by the various other reports which have been received from them on other aspects of court practice and procedure and which are now under examination.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1525" /> The opportunity presented by the promotion of this Bill has been availed of to make a number of other amendments in criminal law and procedure. For example, section 19 amends the list of indictable offences which may be tried summarily by removing the monetary value of stolen property which may be dealt with summarily and adding a number of other indictable offences to the list of those which may be dealt with in this way.  The consent of the Attorney General will be required in larceny cases where the value of the property exceeds £200.</P>
    <P>In Part III of the Bill, which contains a number of provisions dealing with the remand of accused persons, provision is made to allow the District Court, if the accused and the prosecutor consent, to remand an accused person in custody for a period of more than eight days but not exceeding thirty days.  Eight days is the present maximum limit.  The object is to avoid the necessity for having to bring the accused before the court at frequent intervals when there is no prospect of the prosecution being able to proceed with the preliminary examination.  The present limit will continue to apply when the accused is first remanded, because it is reasonable to assume that the accused may not at that stage fully appreciate what is in his own best interests.</P>
    <P>Also in Part III, there is a provision &mdash;in section 28&mdash;allowing information to be given regarding the fact that a person is already on bail in connection with another offence or regarding previous convictions for offences committed while on bail, subject to certain safeguards.  Part IV was added to the Bill in the course of its passage through the Dáil and contains mainly amendments of the Extradition Act, 1965, which are designed to remove some minor difficulties of a technical nature which have arisen in its operation. There is also in that Part section 34, which enables the Attorney General to get a final determination from the Supreme Court of what the law is in a case where a trial judge has directed the jury to return a verdict in favour of the accused person on a question of <Col N="1526" /> law.  The decision of the Supreme Court will be without prejudice to the verdict in favour of the accused person.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I should like to thank the various people, and there are many of them, who have communicated views and suggestions for the improvement of the Bill since it was first published. In such a radical reform of existing procedures as this Bill contemplates, it is only reasonable that there should be concern to see that the new procedure will be as good as we can possibly make it.  One of the problems in a Bill of this kind is to try to decide what should be left to be regulated by the Act and what to be settled by rules of court.  Ideally, the Act should concern itself only with a bare statement of the fundamental principles involved and the rules with detailed implementation of these principles.</P>
    <P>The District Court Rules Committee have been working on rules to take account of the new procedure contemplated by this Bill and they expect to submit a draft of the revised rules to me shortly.  In this way, I hope that the new procedure for preliminary examination will come into operation very soon after the enactment of the Bill.  There is no need to hold up the commencement of the provisions of Part IV which, as I have said, deal mainly with amendments of the Extradition Act, 1965, and these will come into operation immediately the Bill becomes law.</P>
    <P>Although the Bill has been amended and improved during its passage through the Dáil, I have little doubt, from my previous experience in the Seanad with Bills of this nature, that it will get a very careful examination here also and that constructive proposals for its further improvement will be forthcoming.  May I say in advance that I shall welcome them very much and give them sympathetic consideration?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Bill I have no difficulty and no hesitation in welcoming, unlike its predecessor here this evening.  The Minister is quite right when he says the Bill will get a careful examination and I hope he is also <Col N="1527" /> right in saying our proposals to amend it will be constructive.  I am quite certain we can rely on sympathetic consideration of such proposals as we shall make.</P>
      <P>The Bill is a fine example of the result of harmonious co-operation between a Minister of State, different strata of a particular profession and other members of the public.  Indeed, I join with him in the appreciation he has expressed of the Committee on Court Practice and Procedure for the number of very valuable reports they have produced.  This particular Committee may well be setting an example of the kind of way in which problems of great complexity and magnitude should be tackled by issuing&mdash;on limited aspects of the particular problem&mdash;interim reports which are quite compact and can be given effect to legislatively, if such a course is thought desirable.  All the reports to date have been very clear, simple, with a minimum of detail and yet sufficient statistics to enable&mdash;where this is required &mdash;a judgment to be formed on the matter by interested members of the public.  It is interesting to know that this Committee, in one of its reports&mdash; I think it is that in relation to the jurisdiction of the District Court and the Circuit Court&mdash;have been totally divided as to what the restriction should be in different branches of law, injuries, contract, and so on.  But the whole work of the Committee is altogether admirable and it is not so long a time between the publication of the 1963 Report and the issue of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think it is quite correct to say the legal profession in general will welcome very much the provisions of this Bill because, for many years, many legal practitioners&mdash;and I am quite sure members of the public who read the newspapers&mdash;must have thought it extremely unfair to an accused person to have depositions taken in public, published in advance, read by men who would be jurors, and then have the somewhat farcical situation of a judge saying to sworn jurors: &ldquo;Now put out of your mind everything you have heard about this case <Col N="1528" /> and decide this on the evidence&rdquo;.  Of course, jurors do put out of their minds as well as they can what they may have heard but they may well be influenced by discussions in the local golf club, around the table at a social gathering, or elsewhere.  For that reason, it has always seemed to many of us to be unfair&mdash;having regard to our code of fair play to persons who are accused&mdash;to have depositions published.</P>
    <P>I am very pleased to hear the Minister say that the Press&mdash;who are, to some extent, robbed of the copy of depositions provided, as there is always interest in a crime&mdash;have agreed on the restrictions imposed by the Bill, and have co-operated in the restrictions being imposed as to non-publication of certain parts of the preliminary hearings. Of course, in modern times&mdash;and I am glad the Minister has taken his courage firmly in his hands&mdash;it is quite absurd to be using pen and paper: indeed they were bad pens supplied by the Stationery Office, in many cases, for the taking down in longhand of depositions.  It is quite absurd, in modern times, that this should be the procedure.  The new method seems to me to incorporate everything that has been beneficial in the old system and to give every opportunity to the accused person to defend himself&mdash;to test all or any witness he wants to challenge before making an application to the justice to refuse informations.</P>
    <P>I think the Bill as passed by the Dáil has retained all that was good in the old system and incorporated everything that can be of advantage to the prisoner and to those endeavouring to defend him.  It will save a great deal of public time, not that I think a saving of public time is of importance as far as civil liberty is concerned.  I should like to say in passing that this Bill will throw a great deal of increased work of a very important character on State Solicitors and possibly on the superintendents in charge of different stations.</P>
    <P>Already, State Solicitors, from what I know of their work and I know something of it, are not an over-remunerated <Col N="1529" /> section of the public service. They get a single salary which is supposed to cover travelling expenses, maintenance and so on.  They do not have nearly as good conditions as other public servants.  The more diligent a State Solicitor is, the more conscientious he is in the fulfilment of his duties, the less profitable his remuneration becomes.  He has to travel around large counties like Cork, Galway, Tipperary or Mayo.  I do not know why the salaries of State Solicitors are so low.  Unlike county registrars, who have looked for something and will be no doubt looking for increases, State Solicitors have not got the right to arbitration and will certainly be entitled to something extra in the way of relief for the additional work that will be put on them.</P>
    <P>This system we are introducing of serving copies of evidence on the accused does not differ from what happens at the present time.  If an accused person pleads guilty he is sent forward for trial to the Circuit Court or the Central Criminal Court and is always entitled to change his plea and gets a copy of all the evidence the Attorney General will present to the court against him.  The new system will not differ greatly from the present system which has not been found in my experience to work any hardship or injustice.</P>
    <P>However, we are in the Bill providing the additional safeguard of supplying the sworn evidence.  There is one matter of detail on which I should like to hear the Minister when he is replying.  An accused is always entitled to be supplied with a copy of the charges and of the statements of evidence and so on and he is to be entitled to see the exhibits.  Where the exhibits are written documents I wonder is there any objection to giving the accused copies.  Should we not write into section 6, where we provide that he is entitled to see copies of the relevant exhibits, the documents of which he is entitled to copies?  The section sets out merely a list of exhibits.  It might be a charge of forgery of a cheque, it might be in regard to a statement of accounts he <Col N="1530" /> was alleged to be concerned with falsifying, or things of that kind that in modern times can be readily photo-statted. As far as possible these should be supplied to the prisoner.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>There would be difficulties with a big mass of documents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>Sometimes that might be so but the legal adviser, in order to make any shape of things or to understand what the case was about, should get copies of the documents. We could write in &ldquo;as far as possible&rdquo; or &ldquo;as far as practicable&rdquo;.  In a simple case of a forged document or of a falsified account, where it is practicable to do so in the opinion of the justice, we should make this right available to the accused.  There is the question of the accused's right to inspect exhibits. It will be difficult for a person behind bars in Mountjoy to inspect all exhibits. I take it he will be entitled to do so through the person defending him. The Minister might clarify what the situation will be.</P>
      <P>There may be a case where it might be necessary to have a technical person have a look at the exhibits.  I do not wish to push the Minister too far in this matter because I realise the spirit behind the Bill is to be as fair as possible.  However, I should like some clarification of the situation to be created by section 6 (3).  We could apply it to solicitor or counsel if it be necessary.  There is no use applying it to an accused person who might be behind bars.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have heard discussion among my colleagues in the Dáil about the provision in the Bill to imprison&mdash;that is what it amounts to&mdash;witnesses who are about to abscond, whether they be witnesses who appear on behalf of the Attorney General or the accused person. I may inform the Minister in advance that there is a degree of unrest among my colleagues in the legal profession at this power.  On the other hand, one can see the argument that the administration of justice should not be thwarted or defeated by a witness absconding.  As far as I can see, there is not any power under any <Col N="1531" /> extradition agreement to extradite a person if he goes and, as a result, a person who should or would be found guilty may have a <i>nolle prosequi</i> entered and would get off scot free. That is undesirable from the point of view of the protection of society.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, if a person who found himself in an embarrassing situation in respect of an accused person says: &ldquo;I will not be there; I will take the boat to Timbucktu&rdquo;, it might be said it would not be fair to imprison him.  It is difficult to know what to do about the situation.  It occurs to me that no provision seems to be made as to what is to happen to the family of such a person.  If a man who should have been at home with his wife on a particular night was in a place he did not like his wife to know and he decides he will go to England until the trial is over, it might not be in the interests of justice from the point of view of the public or of the accused.  That man can then be taken and put into jail because the district justice is satisfied he is likely to abscond.  What is to happen to that person's family in the meantime?  What is to be their means of sustenance or livelihood?  We all know that those kind of things happen.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether we should not, in the interests of justice to the dependants of the person who is about to abscond, make some provision in this Bill for them.  Perhaps the Minister may be able to point to some legislation which will afford the necessary maintenance.  That is a matter which has to be considered.  I want to tell the Minister and the House that it is a matter which has been the cause of some anxiety among my colleagues. In fact it was my colleagues who drew my attention to this in the Bill and expressed alarm and apprehension with regard to it.  I do not always raise the hares.</P>
    <P>Finally, while on this Bill, I regret that the Minister, in dealing with the Succession Bill, did not excise from the existing code of law such time-honoured and well-known phrases as <i>executor de son tort</i> and &ldquo;estreating recognisances.&rdquo;  Do we all know what <Col N="1532" /><i>executor de son tort</i> was?  We all know what is meant when you refer to a person entering into recognisances but I do not know what all those things mean.  I know the effect of them but they are not in keeping with modern forms of expression.  I do not know why we cannot get some more up-to-date medium.  I wonder whether the Minister and his advisers cannot think up some more modern way of getting the same meaning in regard to those different phrases.  We know what is meant when you say that a person went bail or that somebody has forfeited his bail.  Subject to that, I wish to give unqualified welcome to the Bill.  As I indicated at the beginning, it is a very fine effort on the part of the Minister to moderate and reform the law.  I hope that while the present Minister is Minister for Justice we shall have many more of this type of Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should also like to welcome this Bill.  It is such a good thing in its present form that I doubt if even the Seanad will be able to improve on it.  However, we will probably succeed in doing so.  This is, as Senator O'Quigley says, an attempt to simplify procedure which was really quite intolerable.  It is indeed surprising that the present system has lasted until now.  While saying that, I do not want to detract in any way from any credit due to the Minister for doing something which was very necessary. It lasted a long time and it was time to improve it.</P>
      <P>This Bill is very successful in providing us with the best of both worlds. We have, on the one hand, an expeditious way of dealing with the preliminary investigation and on the other, the right of the accused to rely on the old system.  Consequently, there can be no suggestion that the citizen who is in peril will have his basic rights in any way interfered with.  I believe very few accused people will avail of the old way of having the preliminary investigation conducted, but if they want to have it done that way, they may do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill is a very good one in many ways.  One reason for that is that it arises from the recommendations of a <Col N="1533" /> Committee.  This Committee put forward some excellent suggestions and recommendations which were sound law but were also sound commonsense. Recognising the fact that the Bill is to a great extent the result of the recommendations of a Committee, we can contrast it very favourably with a number of other legal Bills, which were produced in recent years, which were not the result of recommendations by a Committee and which I think suffered very considerably as a result.  I do not propose to name any Bills in particular.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>It sticks out like a sore thumb.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There were two which did not have the benefits of a Committee and which very definitely suffered as a result.  I just want to mention a few points which will arise and can be dealt with at greater length on Committee Stage.  I should like to mention them now and perhaps the Minister can deal with the points which arise and eliminate the necessity for going into them at greater length later on.</P>
      <P>Section 6 deals with the documents which must be served on the accused but it does not say when those documents must be served on him.  It would be possible to comply with the Bill when it becomes an Act by serving them on him a half hour before the preliminary investigation.  The Committee recommended that those documents should be served on the accused not less than 14 days before the preliminary investigation.  It appears to me&mdash;perhaps I missed it in the Bill &mdash;that there is no time limit in this connection.  It would, therefore, be open to abuse and, if possible, some time limit should be introduced into the Bill as to the minimum time before a preliminary investigation within which those documents should be served.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In connection with the time and the circumstances in which the accused may waive the preliminary investigation, it is not quite clear from the Bill at what stage he should do this.  There is furthermore the danger that an <Col N="1534" /> accused person, who is not professionally represented, and does not fully understand this procedure, may be encouraged to waive the preliminary investigations without fully realising his rights.  There is no doubt whatever that everybody concerned in such a case, the court itself, the people conducting the prosecution and all the apparatus of the court will be hoping that the preliminary investigation will be waived.  There will be a temptation not to make the accused fully aware of his rights, and that being present I think it would be helpful and desirable that the Bill should contain some proviso that the district justice should be obliged, possibly in the course of section 7, to explain the procedure to the accused and ensure that he is fully aware of his rights before he makes the decision to waive preliminary investigation.</P>
    <P>As regards section 17 I welcome the decision to prohibit the publication of the details of the preliminary investigation. I have no doubt at all that in the past publication of this must have prejudiced and biased jurys when the case came up for hearing subsequently. I feel this is a very proper section to include in the Bill.  I have some doubt about whether it will be possible to operate subsection (3) of this section successfully because it appears that the district justice may allow publication of certain information if requested by the accused but if the accused, for instance, calls some witnesses and requests that all the evidence favourable to him be published and nothing else this would be an impracticable request and one which may place the district justice in a very difficult position in deciding whether or not to accede to a request of this kind.</P>
    <P>Finally, I want to again deal with a question which I have referred to in the past and that is in regard to the way in which amendments are dealt with in the Bill.  Until such time as amendments can be dealt with in the way which I suggested on the previous Bill, I think it is desirable that not only repeals but amendments should be included in a schedule at the end of the Bill.  Certainly, when one goes <Col N="1535" /> to an Act to see whether it has affected previous Acts it is extremely useful to be able to look at the back of the Act and find the previous Acts which have been affected by this Act.  If one has to go through the full Act to find out what previous Acts have been affected it takes very much more time, and, as far as the effect on previous legislation is concerned, the difference between a repeal and an amendment is, for practical purposes, no difference at all.  It is a distinction without a difference. Consequently, I think the Minister should consider having two schedules at the end of a Bill such as this, one dealing with repeals and the other with amendments referring to the Acts and the sections in Acts which are the subject of amendment by the Bill in question.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOKennedy" hpid="Mr. O'Kennedy Mr. O'Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>In common with the speakers who have already contributed, I should certainly like to welcome this Bill in that it deals with two important aspects of the taking of depositions and that the remedies it proposes are effective and acceptable to all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>First of all, if we just consider the machinery under which these depositions were taken we realise, as Senator O'Quigley has said, that it was certainly an antiquated system and one which tended to bog down the work of the court, and certainly did not in any way contribute any material factor to the essential elements of justice which had to be considered on behalf of the accused.  The amazing thing is, at the same time, that this system of note taking by shorthand or by longhand which we are now abolishing, in fact, exists in one form or another either by longhand or shorthand in court procedure in every instance.  Indeed, it exists in this very House, and I have often had the utmost sympathy for the notetakers in this House when people like myself, who might not be as considerate as they should be, ramble off on our usual hobbyhorse. It certainly does not expedite the business of the courts that notes have to be taken of the cross exchange on evidence, of the remarks and comments <Col N="1536" /> which may be made by a witness.  I do not think that even the most effective notetaker can possibly give any idea of the nature of the cross-examination or the manner in which questions were answered or anything of that sort.  In this House the difficulty is not so great because the notetaker is only concerned with a particular delivery.  For that reason I would suggest to the Minister that he might have a look at all aspects of court procedure.  Whether it is necessary to have a notetaker for the purposes of criminal procedure or for workmen's compensation on matters of that sort I doubt and, indeed, it has been my experience on reading over these notes that they have not been as accurate in the small details as one would expect them to be.</P>
    <P>Secondly, one welcomes this Bill in that it intends to prohibit publication of the evidence by the district justice. Of course, the main factor in this is that publication of evidence at deposition stage certainly can, and I am sure often has prejudiced the interests of the accused.  This is particularly so because I am afraid our newspapers, particularly our evening newspapers, appear to thrive on this type of publicity. I was, I must say, pleased to hear the Minister say that the journalists individually&mdash;and I certainly have the highest respect for the journalists individually&mdash;and the newspapers in general welcomed this prohibition.  One could never guess from the manner in which they gave prominence and publicity to some of the more notorious murder trials at deposition stage in recent times that they would welcome anything of the sort.  Possibly in this their actions were being determined by the fact that they are commercial interests as well as vehicles of public opinion.  I certainly think and I point a finger quite directly at the evening papers in this country that they have not contributed too much up to this time in doing justice to the accused in their reports on depositions.  While on that point I might say that most of our newspapers throughout the country could probably do their readers a lot more service by neglecting the prurient details that sometimes arise in court cases and by paying a little more attention <Col N="1537" /> to matters of positive social benefit and positive intellectual interest.  One sympathises with local newspapers but I cannot see that performances of lawyers or the unfortunate circumstances of litigants should be matters which are widely publicised in newspapers. I welcome this as being a first step in the right direction and I am glad to hear that even at this late stage the newspapers are in favour of this restriction of their hitherto unrestricted right.</P>
    <P>The only other matter which occurs to me at this stage is a matter of general detail.  One is not too clear, as Senator E. Ryan has suggested, as to how or when these statements are to be given to the accused person.  It is very obvious from reading this Bill that every effort is being made to safeguard the right of the accused person but what is not so obvious is the machinery of procedure under which these rights are being safeguarded.  The Minister probably has in many ways answered this objection before it was made in that he said that this may well be a matter for the Rules Committee rather than for legislation.  One would be particularly anxious that the statements of the evidence to be given by the witnesses, which I presume would be taken, after caution, would be taken in the strictest possible fashion and generally, as is the custom with the Gardaí, according to the rules of evidence.</P>
    <P>One hears quite a lot in court from time to time about statements being admissible or inadmissible.  This appears to be something of an extension, in that the statements rather than the depositions will now be the first launching ground of a trial, and one would be happy if the Garda authorities were made aware of this and exerciesd even more diligence, or the utmost degree of diligence, in taking these statements, now that the responsibility is being given to them.</P>
    <P>Finally in conjunction with Senator O'Quigley and my colleagues who were alarmed&mdash;the same colleagues probably conveyed their views to me&mdash;I feel there are some grounds for concern at the power which is given to the <Col N="1538" /> district justice to make the witness order, as it is called in section 7, the order of the reluctant or unavailable witness.  Very important principles arise here and there is a balance of consideration on both sides.  This is a matter which would be considered appropriate for discussion on Committee Stage.  I welcome this Bill in its intention and indeed in the sections by which it implements that intention.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLenihan" hpid="Mr. B. Lenihan Mr. B. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill has been generally welcomed in the Dáil and Seanad and by members of the public and legal practitioners.  It represents a radical change in that we have operated the present system of taking depositions for over 100 years.  The important thing was to ensure that there would be no diminution of the accused person's rights.  While it was necessary to modernise the law in this respect to make it more expeditious and efficient, to eliminate the obviously time-wasting procedure of taking evidence in longhand, which evidence had to be repeated again at the actual trial proper, it was more important, and I felt it my main duty in promoting the Bill, to ensure that there would be no diminution in the rights of the accused person. We have managed to guarantee the accused person, if he or she wishes, the right to have any State witness give his evidence in court at the preliminary hearing and subject himself to cross-examination by the accused or his representative.</P>
      <P>I do not think that that right will be used to any great extent but there are cases where the accused person may wish actually to fight the case all-out at the preliminary hearing stage.  There are certain cases, admittedly a small minority&mdash;about five per cent&mdash;in which the accused person may wish to refute, challenge and defeat the State case at the preliminary examination stage.  It would be wrong to deny the accused person that right if he or she wishes to avail of it.  That is why the right to challenge witnesses and the right to cross-examine witnesses on the part of the accused is retained in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would say that in 95 per cent of <Col N="1539" /> cases the position up to now has been that the preliminary examination was a matter of routine, where there was no real questioning by the accused person or his legal representative of the merits of the case.  That position will in all probability be reflected in the operation of the Bill when it becomes law by the accused person waiving the preliminary examination in most cases. That would be the likely practical outcome of the Bill and would mean a substantial saving in time and energy on the part of court gardaí, members of the public, witnesses and accused persons, whose rights again are fully protected by the provisions that the documents relative to the case against him by the State must be served on him.  In relation to that, a point has been made in the House that we have not specified a time within which prior to the actual hearing the documents must be served.  This time factor will be a matter of rule and will be contained in the District Court Rules when they are furnished to me.</P>
    <P>It is often a matter of debate on a measure of this kind whether to have a particular aspect incorporated in rules or embodied in the statute.  In a measure of this kind it has been the practice to have matters like this, where a period of days or hours has been given in regard to court procedure, met by rule rather than in the statute itself. I would admit that in any case where the accused would make the case that he was prejudiced by reason of not receiving particulars of the case against him in time, he would automatically get an adjournment from the District Court.  This is a matter which I will look into between now and Committee Stage.  My preference at the moment is that it should be made a matter of rule rather than statute.</P>
    <P>A point was made about section 9 (3) by Senator O'Quigley that this was a new provision.  It is not.  It is merely a redraft without any change of section 13 (6) of the Petty Sessions (Ireland) Act, 1851, under which the present procedure was established.  The person not complying with the witness order under section 9 of this Bill is in a no <Col N="1540" /> worse or better position than he or she would have been under the relevant provision of the 1851 Act.  There is nothing new, therefore, in that particular provision.</P>
    <P>A point was made by Senator E. Ryan with which I am in considerable agreement.  It is a matter I propose to look into.  It refers to having a Schedule to measures of this kind listing the enactments being awarded.  It would be a good idea, I think, and I understand it is the practice in some other countries.  While the main purpose of the Bill is to abolish the devious procedure as we knew it heretofore and substitute this new procedure of preliminary examination, there are also amendments of both the Criminal Justice Act, 1951, and the Extradition Act, 1965, to mention only two things. It is a good idea, I feel, that such amendments should be brought to the notice of both practitioners and citizens in the form of a Schedule which can be easily referred to.  This is a matter which I will look into.  It may not be possible to deal with it in this Bill, but I will consult the parliamentary draftsman as to the possibility of doing it in future legislation.</P>
    <P>On a measure of this kind, the Committee Stage will be the important Stage to ensure that we copper-fasten the Bill thoroughly.  We have taken very considerable care with it, because I am very conscious of the fact that it is a substantial departure in criminal procedure and probably the most important amendment of criminal procedure that has taken place for many years.  Having regard to that, it is important that when changing to a completely new system, we should make sure that the system works.  There is very little justification in adopting new procedures if the target cannot be attained.  Certainly I would not like a situation where the new Bill, however desirable theoretically, might not in fact work practically.  That is why I see the importance of the Committee Stage discussion here in the Seanad, that we can iron out any problems which might frustrate the efficient working of the Bill and at the same time in the course of the detailed discussion at that Stage, ensure that individual <Col N="1541" /> rights protected under the present system, however cumbersome it may be, will continue to be protected. Indeed, I would say again that, subject to the practicality of its operation, individual rights are probably protected by section 6 to an even greater degree than heretofore, because the person knows in detail the case which is being made against him and has due notice of it.</P>
    <P>One last matter: I would like to thank particularly the National Union of Journalists who passed a resolution supporting the proposal to prohibit publication of details of the evidence given on the preliminary examination. I regard this as a very courageous and honourable stand by the National Union of Journalists in Ireland, because the fact is that certain tentative proposals of this kind prohibiting publication of evidence on preliminary examination have been made in Britain in the past few years and have been rejected fairly outspokenly by both the newspaper proprietors and practitioners of the Press.  Here in Ireland when this proposition was mooted, although at first sight it would appear to be, as it were, an intrusion into the field of the rights of the Press, there was a welcome from the newspaper proprietors and a very substantial welcome from the National Union of Journalists members. This shows a mature approach. The essential justice of the matter was recognised, that there would be obvious prejudice to the accused person in the publication of the details of the preliminary hearing.  This would be bound to prejudice the mind of jurors at the subsequent trial, who are enjoined by the judge to look at the matter on the merits of the evidence presented before them; in fact the jurors' minds could not but be influenced to some degree in one way or another by reason of their knowledge of reports of the case at the earlier stage.</P>
    <P>I think we have in this Bill gone ahead of reforms proposed in Britain, although I know that the British <Col N="1542" /> Government is considering this particular type of reform.</P>
    <P>I would also like to mention one other aspect which was referred to earlier, namely the question of outmoded verbiage in regard to criminal law and, indeed, to all the law which we have inherited from earlier times. In the Succession Act, we cleared away a lot of this lumber in the form of ancient legal verbiage, and, I think, rightly so.  In the criminal law it is a more difficult matter, in that it is desirable that definitions be more precise in criminal law.  When a certain terminology has secured a definite precise meaning, it is not often easy to get a terminology to replace it.  Entering into recognisances, estreating a bond, and phrases of that kind have very precise meanings as far as lawyers are concerned, and while at this stage the idea of getting rid of such phrases is attractive, when one seeks to get an alternative, it is not at all easy.  However, I am looking into it.</P>
    <P>In that context I can say that we hope to have a Criminal Justice Bill published inside the next two months. It is at an advanced stage of drafting, and in it a number of these old phrases are being repealed, such as felony, misdemeanour, penal servitude, and so on, which now have no practical meaning but which are in the criminal law.  They are being repealed, along with a number of other matters.  I would envisage that the Criminal Justice Bill will, with this Bill, mean that the criminal code will be very substantially modernised.</P>
    <P>There is nothing more to add except to commend the Bill to the Seanad and to hope for a constructive debate on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 5th April.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 5th April, 1967.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>