<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="20" Month="Jul" Year="1960" Vol="52" No="20" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 20 Iúil 1960" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 20 July 1960" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="2075">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2075" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take items Nos. 1 to 8, inclusive, and, if the House agrees, item No. 9. An urgent Bill&mdash;the Defence (Amendment) Bill, 1960&mdash;authorising the dispatch of forces to the Congo is under consideration in the Dáil this afternoon and if it passes all Stages, it is proposed, if the House agrees, to take it as item No. 1 on tomorrow's Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Notice of Vacancies in" RHead="Seanad Membership: Motions">
    <Title>Notice of Vacancies in Seanad Membership: Motions.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Clerk of Seanad Éireann do send to the Minister for Local Government notice of a vacancy in the membership of Seanad Éireann occasioned by the death of Senator Frank Purcell, a member elected from the Nominating Bodies Sub-Panel of the Labour Panel at the General Election for Seanad Éireann, May, 1957.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Clerk of Seanad Éireann do send to the Minister for Local Government notice of a vacancy in Seanad Éireann occasioned by the election to Dáil Éireann of Senator Patrick Teehan, a member elected from the Nominating Bodies Sub-Panel of the Administrative Panel at the General Election for Seanad Éireann, May, 1957.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Criminal Justice Bill," RHead="1960&mdash;Message from Dáil">
    <Title>Criminal Justice Bill, 1960&mdash;Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá Dáil Éireann <Col N="2076" /> tar éis aontú le leasú 1 a rinne Seanad Éireann ar an mBille um Dhlínse Choiriúil, 1960, leis an mbreisiú seo a leanas:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;In section 9, lines 35 and 36, &lsquo;, provided the person consents,&rsquo; deleted.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>leanar mian aontú Sheanad Éireann a fháil; tá sí tar éis aontú le leasú 2.</P>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has agreed to amendment 1 made by Seanad Éireann to the Criminal Justice Bill, 1960, with the following addition:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;In section 9, lines 35 and 36, &lsquo;, provided the person consents,&rsquo; deleted.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>to which the agreement of Seanad Éireann is desired; it has agreed to amendment 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That Seanad Éireann do agree to the addition made by Dáil Éireann to Amendment 1 made by Seanad Éireann to the Criminal Justice Bill, 1960.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OscarTraynor" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor) Oscar Traynor">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Traynor)</NameTxt>
      <P>When this section was remitted by the Seanad back to the Dáil in its amended form, Deputy Dillon suggested that it would be an improvement if the words &ldquo;provided the person consents&rdquo; were deleted.  He suggested that it should not be left to persons of 16 to 21 years, particularly youths, to decide for themselves that they would go to prison in preference to going to an institution. He suggested that the decision in such matters should be left to the discretion of the court.  There was a fair amount of substance in that point.  On the other hand, what I had in mind, in having these words in the section in the first instance, was that the courts would have a discretion in sending girls to a convent&mdash;which would be an institution approved by the Minister for Justice&mdash;provided that the girl's consent was forthcoming.</P>
      <P>On balance, I feel that the words can be deleted.  I am satisfied that the courts will act reasonably and in the young person's interest in all cases.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2077" /> Ordered: That the Dáil be notified accordingly.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Social Welfare (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1960&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Social Welfare (Amendment) Bill, 1960&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. MacEntee) Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. MacEntee)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is to give effect to the extensions and improvements of our existing Social Insurance Scheme as forecast by the Taoiseach in statements on 4th July, 1959, and 11th December of last year. The Bill provides for the expansion of the scheme (i) to include old age (contributory) pensions as a further benefit, (ii) to continue to widows over age 70, whose deceased husbands had been contributors under the, widows and orphans insurance scheme, widows (contributory) pensions in lieu of the non-contributory old age pensions free of means test, and (iii) to pay to recipients of disability benefit, unemployment benefit or widows (contributory) pension who have more than two qualified children, an allowance in respect of each child in excess of that number, instead of limiting the payment to the first and second, as at present.  In addition to these new features, the Bill also proposes to improve the scheme by providing for substantial increases in the basic rates of disability benefit, unemployment benefit, maternity allowance, widows (contributory) pensions and orphans (contributory) allowance and in the rates of the allowances for adult dependants and the first two qualified children.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill has been framed in accordance with the general principles enunciated by the Taoiseach that the foundations of a sound scheme should now be laid and then built upon as conditions permitted and that it should confer upon all former insured persons who are now beyond their labours a substantial improvement in their existing conditions.  The old age (contributory) pension proposals have been based on existing services in order to simplify administration and keep administrative costs as low as possible. Therefore, the classes to he covered by <Col N="2078" /> the new pension scheme will be those who are insured for the main benefits under the Social Welfare Acts.  As they are outside the ambit of the existing social insurance scheme, selfemployed persons will not be brought within the scope of the pension scheme. Similarly, persons who are at present compulsorily insurable only for the purposes of widows and orphans (contributory) pensions, for instance, permanent and pensionable civil servants, officers of local authorities, etc. will not be insurable for the new pension.  The provision in the present scheme whereby persons under age 70 ceasing to be compulsorily insured, may, under certain conditions, preserve their insurance for widows and orphans (contributory) pensions by becoming voluntary contributors will be extended so that insurance for the new pensions may also be preserved.  It is important, however, to note that the right to become a voluntary contributor for old age (contributory) pensions in addition to widows and orphans (contributory) pensions will be limited to persons whose compulsory insurance covered other benefits in addition to widows and orphans (contributory) pension.</P>
    <P>The qualifying age for old age (contributory) pension will be 70 years for both men and women.  A lower qualifying age would, apart from the question of the extra cost involved, virtually necessitate the imposition of a retirement condition, with a concomitant earnings rule, at least up to age 70.  This would, in effect, be tantamount to the application of a means test, and would add considerably to the administrative complexity of the scheme.  In all the circumstances it is considered that the provisions in the Bill represent the best approach to the problem.</P>
    <P>The contribution conditions for old age (contributory) pensions as set out in Section 16 of the Bill are briefly&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  that the claimant has entered insurance before attaining the age of 60,</P>
    <P>(b)  that not less than 156 employment contributions have been paid since his entry into insurance, and</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2079" /> (c)  that he has an average of 48 contributions paid or credited in each contribution year since his entry into insurance.</P>
    <P>There is of course nothing extraordinary or unprecedented about these conditions.  They follow logically from the underlying requirement that to be entitled to a long term benefit a person should have a reasonably long insurance life and a reasonable record of genuine insurable employment.  Under the present social insurance scheme introduced in the 1952 Social Welfare Act, the conditions imposed for title to widows (contributory) pensions, marriage benefit and disability benefits of indefinite duration specifically require for the fundamental condition that the insured person shall have paid not less than 156 contributions in all.  It is convenient I think to refer to this condition as the &ldquo;156 contributions paid&rdquo; test.  For entitlement to disability benefit and unemployment benefit, the insured person must be in a position to show that not less than 48 contributions were either paid by him or credited to him in the governing contribution year.</P>
    <P>The first stipulation that a person must have entered into insurance before attaining the age of 60 years will apply to all insured persons seeking the new pension.  Persons who attain the age of 70 before 5th January, 1963, could not of course have entered into insurance under the Social Welfare Acts prior to the attainment of the age of 60 years as those Acts only commenced on 5th January, 1953.  To meet this it is proposed in regulations to be made under Section 13 of the Bill, to which I will refer later, to treat entry into insurance under the former National Health Insurance Acts prior to the attainment of age 60 as effective for the purposes of the new pension and those regulations will also provide for the counting, where necessary, of contributions paid or credited under the National Health Insurance Acts towards satisfying the remaining two conditions for the new pension.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2080" /> The first of these two conditions is that to qualify for an old age (contributory) pension the person concerned must have been an insured person and in that capacity must have paid not less than 156 employment contributions since his entry into insurance.  The number of contributions thus required is the equivalent of three full years of insurable employment.  These contributions &mdash;perhaps it may be necessary to emphasise this&mdash;must have been paid and only contributions which have been paid will be taken into account towards satisfying the condition.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, in formulating the terms of the remaining condition which must be fulfilled in order to obtain a contributory pension, provision has been made to meet the case of an insured person who, because he is either ill or unemployed, is presumed not to be in a position to have contributions as an employed person paid in respect of him.  This case which could otherwise involve hardship, is met, under Section 16 of the Bill.  This section will enable the average of 48 contributions per contribution year to be calculated on the basis, not merely of the contributions actually paid, but on those paid contributions plus the notional contributions with which the insured person has been credited.  The average will be calculated on the total of the paid contributions and the credited contributions, and an insured person who is either too ill to work and notifies the Department, or unemployed and signs the Unemployed Register is at present and will continue to be credited with a contribution for each week of such duly notified illness or proved unemployment.</P>
    <P>Until the new rates of contribution proposed in the Bill have become payable, nobody will have paid any contribution containing an element in respect of the new pension.  If title to pension were to be established only by the new contributions it would be some years before any pension would become payable and insured persons within a few years of the pensionable age and those now over that age, would never be able to qualify.  It could of course be argued <Col N="2081" /> that those now over age 70 should not get any concessions for the reason that they have passed out of insurance, having derived therefrom in the course of their insurance life such insurance cover and benefits as they were entitled to on the basis of the contributions they had paid.</P>
    <P>I hope the Seanad will agree with me that such persons should be given the opportunity of qualifying for the pension and, accordingly provision is being made in Section 13 of the Bill to enable contributions already paid under the Social Welfare code to be taken into account.  The manner in which this will be done will be set out in detail in regulations to be made under the section.</P>
    <P>As I have already mentioned earlier in relation to the conditions for the new pension, Section 13 also provides that the regulations made thereunder may modify the contribution conditions in the case of persons who entered insurance prior to 5th January, 1953, the date on which the co-ordinated social insurance scheme under the Social Welfare Act, 1952, came into operation.  Comprehensive insurance records are available, however, only as from that date, and it is intended that the regulations will ensure that apparent shortages of contributions which are due to the absence of comprehensive records will not penalise a claimant for old age (contributory) pension.</P>
    <P>As a result of this section, it is estimated that 23,000 persons who are now in receipt of non-contributory old age pensions, together with 7,000 adult persons who are dependent upon them, will qualify, respectively, for old age (contributory) pensions and the associated allowance in respect of dependent adults.  A further 13,000 persons aged 70 or over in respect of whom the modified conditions to be prescribed under Section 13 have been fulfilled will become entitled to the old age (contributory) pension, notwithstanding the fact that hitherto they have been disqualified from getting any old age pension at all.  In addition, about 6,000 allowances will become payable in respect of adult dependants.  Thus when the old age (contributory) pensions become payable <Col N="2082" /> about 50,000 persons will obtain at once the substantial benefit of the new pension.</P>
    <P>The rate of the new pension will be 40/- per week, and a supplement at the rate of 28/6d.  per week will be payable where the pensioner has an adult dependant.  A male old age (contributory) pensioner who is married, may receive the increase in respect of an adult dependant for his wife, if she is living with or being maintained by him.  A female married old age (contributory) pensioner, however, will receive such an allowance for her husband only if she is maintaining him and he is incapable of self-support by reason of some physical or mental infirmity.  If the pensioner dies, the amount of the increases in respect of adult dependency will continue to be payable to the survivor, unless he or she qualifies for a more favourable payment by way of benefit or assistance.  If a husband and wife both qualify for the pension neither will be entitled to the increase in respect of a dependent spouse.</P>
    <P>Under Section 10 of the Bill, regulations will be made providing for payment of the old age (contributory) pension at reduced rates where the average number of contributions paid or credited per contribution year is below 48.  The reduction in the rate of pension, however, will not operate to reduce the allowance in respect of the adult dependant, that is to say, the adult dependant allowance will remain at 28/6d. per week.  This is in line with existing procedure in relation to disability and unemployment benefit.  A person receiving the new pension and his or her adult dependant, if any, will be debarred from the non-contributory old age pension scheme.</P>
    <P>I come now to the extension of widows (contributory) pension.  Under existing legislation a widow's (contributory) pension terminates when the widow reaches the age of 70, and she then becomes entitled to the ordinary old age pension, but&mdash;and this, of course, is very important&mdash;without the means or residence test.  However, it is irrational to assume that the moment a widow passes her seventieth year that she will require something less <Col N="2083" /> for maintenance than when she was aged only 69 years and 364 days. Indeed, the contrary is the more general case.  Accordingly it is proposed not to terminate the widow's (contributory) pension when she reaches the age of 70, but to provide that the widow's (contributory) pension will be payable in future without reference to age.</P>
    <P>Widows' (contributory) pensions will, therefore, be paid to approximately 8,000 widows who are now over 70 and who were in receipt of such pensions prior to reaching that age or would have been if they had been widowed before attaining that age.  A widow over 70 receiving such a pension will be debarred, of course, from receiving non-contributory old age pension and, if she is entitled to both old age (contributory) pension and widows' (contribtuory) pension she will, by regulations, be permitted to draw only one of these pensions.</P>
    <P>The final quite new feature in the Bill relates to the dependent children of recipients of disability benefit, unemployment benefit or widows' (contributory) pension.  As the law stands an allowance at the rate of 8/- per week is payable in respect of each of the first two such children; nothing, however, is given in respect of any greater number of child dependants. Under the Bill, not only will the amount payable in respect of the first two children be increased by 25 per cent., that is, from 8/- to 10/-, but an allowance at the rate of 5/- per week will be paid in respect of each qualified child in excess of two.  By reason of these increased payments, the lot of about 73,500 children and their parents should become somewhat easier when the Bill is brought into operation.</P>
    <P>In addition to the new features I have outlined, the Bill also provides for increases in existing rates of benefit. The basic rates of disability benefit and unemployment benefit are being increased by 2/6 per week from 30/- to 32/6d. per week; the allowance for an adult dependant by 5/- per week from 15/- to 20/- per week and, as I have already indicated, the allowance for each of the first and second qualified <Col N="2084" /> children by 2/- per week to 10/- per week each.  The rate of maternity allowance is being increased from 30/- to 35/- per week, that is by 5/- per week; the rate of widows' (contributory) pension also from 30/- by 5/- per week to 35/- per week, where, the widow has a qualified child, and by 2/6d. per week to 32/6d. where she has no qualified child.  The rate of orphans (contributory) allowance will go up by 100 per cent., that is from 10/- per week to 20/- per week. Approximately 120,000 adults and 400 orphans will benefit by these increases.</P>
    <P>The overall effect of the foregoing increases can best be illustrated by some examples.  An insured man with a wife and five dependent children will receive 87/6d. per week when ill or unemployed as compared with 61/- at present.  Similarly a widow in receipt of widow's (contributory) pension who has five dependent children will receive 70/- per week as compared with 46/- per week at present. A widow over 70 to whom a widows' (contributory) pension will be paid under the provisions of the Bill will receive an increase of income of 4/- per week, i.e., from 28/6d. to 32/6d., assuming that she has no qualified child.  A guardian looking after a family of three orphans will receive an increase of 30/- per week to £3 per week.  These increases are quite substantial and should appreciably improve the position of social welfare beneficiaries.</P>
    <P>We have now to consider the all-important question of the cost of the extensions and improvements proposed in this Bill which will involve a considerable increase in expenditure from the Social Insurance Fund.  It is impossible to forecast with any precision what the increase is likely to be because the cost of the new old age (contributory) pension cannot be estimated with any degree of firmness. There are no statistics to show how many persons now over the age of 70 were formerly insured and how many of these insured persons are now receiving the non-contributory old age pension.  On the basis of broad estimation, it is reckoned that the yearly gross cost of the old age (contributory) pension scheme will be roughly <Col N="2085" /> £4,660,000.  The yearly cost of the other extensions and improvements is estimated at approximately £2,300,000. The yearly cost of the provisions in the Bill will, therefore, amount to £6,960,000&mdash;let us say in the roundest of figures £7 million.  Towards meeting this liability the increases in the rates of contributions are expected to yield £4,075,000 per annum.  Thus the deficiency in contribution income which must be covered by the Exchequer is no less than £2,885,000.</P>
    <P>It is estimated that savings to the extent of £2,550,000 will accrue on the Social Assistance Vote by the reduction in expenditure of non-contributory old age pensions.  This reduction will be due to persons in receipt of non-contributory pension qualifying for the higher contributory pension or widows over age 70 qualifying for the higher widows' (contributory) pension.  These savings will not be made at the expense of persons who continue to receive non-contributory pensions, none of whom will lose.  The savings are, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, being diverted to help finance the expansion of the Social Insurance Scheme.  Otherwise, it would not have been possible so to expand the scheme without an exorbitant increase in contributions.</P>
    <P>This diversion of savings is logical as the persons who will receive contributory pensions in the first few years of the expanded scheme will in fact have contributed little or nothing towards the cost of those pensions and, in the majority of cases, would, but for the expansion of the scheme, have been receiving non-contributory pensions. In addition to the devoting of savings on non-contributory old age pensions towards meeting the deficiency in the income of the Social Insurance Fund referred to earlier, the Exchequer will have to meet the balance of that deficiency, £335,000 as well.</P>
    <P>The present and the proposed rates of contribution for the different categories of insured workers are set out in the explanatory memorandum circulated with the Bill, from which it will be seen that an increase of 3/6d. per week in joint contributions is the most <Col N="2086" /> that is required of employers and workers.  In general, it may be said that the principle followed in deciding on the increases in each rate was that the rate should bear its due share of the cost of the increases in benefits to which it gives title.  Thus the ordinary rate of contribution, which gives title to all benefits, must bear its proportion of the increased cost of all benefits, whereas the contribution in respect of civil servants, teachers, and others, which gives title only to widows and orphans (contributory) pensions will have to bear only that proportion of the overall increase of 3/6d. attributable to the increased cost of those pensions.  In the case of agricultural workers and share-fishermen, and others coming within that category, the increases proposed are, however, much less than would be warranted by the strict application of the principle to which I have just referred.</P>
    <P>In relation to the form of the Bill, which has been drafted largely by way of amendment of the Social Welfare Act, 1952, I should explain that while this procedure does make the Bill somewhat difficult to examine in that it has to be read by reference to the earlier Act, it has the overriding merit that it will enable the new benefits to be operated within the existing administrative machinery.  This will obviate duplication of the statutory provisions required to deal with, for example, decisions on claims, appeals, payment of pensions, and so on, and simplify administration.  Moreover when the time comes to codify and consolidate the whole Social Welfare and Social Assistance Schemes that operation will be facilitated by the form in which this Bill has been drafted.  For the rest, I trust that the explanatory memorandum and the information I have now given will enable Senators to form a clear picture of the new scheme of old age (contributory) pensions and of the improvements to be made in the existing schemes.</P>
    <P>Under the Bill as it stands, the new or extended social insurance benefits will improve the lot of more than 200,000 of our aged population and our less fortunate men, women and <Col N="2087" /> children to the extent of close on £7 million a year.  Of that sum, over £4 million in round figures will be met by employers and their employees, but the balance of close on £3 million must be provided, through taxation, by the community at large.</P>
    <P>The proposals in this Bill are intended to be a further step in the development of our social insurance code.  These proposals are the best that can be made in existing circumstances but there is no reason why, if our economic progress continues, a more comprehensive and liberal scheme should not be devised.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Did I understand the Minister correctly to state that there would be an increased cost to the State of £3,000,000?  Is that increased cost to be linked with £2½ million of savings, and does the net increase mean the difference between the two?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  I said that, in addition, the State would have to cover the deficiency to the extent of £335,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I heard all that. Could I repeat my question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not usual to cross-examine a Minister in the course of a debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is just a single question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator propose to speak?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but before I speak, I want to get what the Minister said clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the point might be raised in the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a common thing in either House to ask a single question.  The Minister did not answer my question.  He introduced another thing altogether.  Might I ask him now if I understand correctly that the State will put up an additional sum of £3,000,000, or whether savings will be credited against that £3 million so <Col N="2088" /> that the net sum which will be put up by the State is £500,000?  That is a simple question, but the Minister does not want to answer it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not said so. I am quite willing to give the Senator all the information he requires, but I was at some pains to emphasise that it would not be possible to submit this scheme to the Oireachtas if the Minister for Finance had not agreed to forgo savings to the extent of £2½ million arising on the Social Assistance Vote, but that in addition to the diversion of this sum of £2,500,000 to the Social Insurance fund the Exchequer was also coming in to the extent of a further £335,000.  I said that, and the Senator could have heard me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has now made it clear that the State is coming in only to the tune of £335,000. Technically, it seems to me that the Bill is quite all right.  It is a bit involved, and for myself, I object strongly to this kind of constructive legislation.  It would be quite as easy to produce an original Bill setting out the new situation&mdash;just as easy as all these constructive efforts, reading paragraphs and phrases into other legislation; but the lawyers like it this way and I suspect the managers also like it very much this way, because they can always put somebody on the wrong foot by saying: &ldquo;You misconstrued it&rdquo; or &ldquo;You did not give enough attention to it but we can give it all our attention&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>However, subject to that criticism as to the form of the Bill, it seems to me that it is all right technically. The Minister laid great emphasis on the increased benefits that will accrue from this Bill&mdash;it will improve the lot of 100,000 persons, and so on.  Could I say this about it&mdash;it has all the imprint of an old man's Bill, who does not have to look forward 25 or 30 years to the time when people will be paying for these increased benefits, that he need look out only for whatever period of a few years ahead he desires to look?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister talked about improvements in old age contributory pensions, <Col N="2089" /> and substantial increases to other persons, and said that certain people will be entitled to futher long term benefits. So keen is the Minister to bring this into operation immediately that he gets himself into technical difficulties about the fact that this Bill amends an Act which came into operation only seven years ago, and he wishes people to pay ten years' contributions before they will be entitled to benefit.  The Minister gets over that in Section 13.</P>
    <P>The Minister tells us that so many people will benefit immediately&mdash; 23,000 old age pensioners, 7,000 dependants, so many widows and orphans and so on.  The question one asks immediately if one sees an expenditure of £7,000,000 towards which increased contributions are £4,000,000 and a transfer of £2,500,000 from the State is: how is this brought about? Of course it is brought about by making the future pay for the present.  It is, shall I use the word, tempting, to talk about leaving debts behind one, and I take it that it is &ldquo;commitments&rdquo;, that more moderate word, that was subsequently used&mdash;a commitment to posterity, unless posterity, which I take it they will not be willing to do, should agree to eliminate the system.</P>
    <P>The Minister says that it is impossible to forecast how many old age pensioners will qualify under the terms of the Bill.  I appreciate why that is so, but I think that is an accounting and statistical answer, because any person who did some sociological study of the matter could come to quite an accurate answer, if he wished.  For example, figures were published some years ago showing that the great bulk of the old age pensioners were living in the counties of Kerry and Mayo, and therefore along the west coast.  Probably if you drew a line from Derry to Bandon straight down you would get the great bulk of them west of that line.</P>
    <P>We all know that not one person in fifty west of that line has been paying insurance contributions: therefore they would not come into the picture at all.  We also know that the great bulk of the contributors are in the industrial towns and cities, and <Col N="2090" /> that they do not tend in big numbers to live to the age of 70 or very much beyond it.  We cannot get away from the fact that when the Minister has finished his litany of benefits, he had to come back to the reality of this scheme.  He glossed over the extra amounts that will have to be paid. It will be 3/6 a week by employer and employee, that is, 1/9 for the employee.</P>
    <P>I take it that the employer and businesses in general will within the whole system have to adjust themselves to the changed position, but unless the employee is to ask for a further increase in wages, he will have to put up 1/9 per week.  That, of course, again to employ a phrase used by the Minister on a number of occasions this afternoon, is tantamount to an increase in the cost of living.  There is no question about it.  The Minister is an expert on increasing the cost of living.  He is probably the most expert person in this whole country on the question of increasing the cost of living, and so he is at it again.  He has increased the cost of living.  In other words, for one person who benefits there are to be eight for whom the cost of living is increased, for whom the Minister is going to increase the cost of living by 1/9 per week.</P>
    <P>Strictly speaking, if the State wants to institute a scheme of this sort and if the Minister were really social welfare minded, he would charge it up to the State.  He has not charged it up to the State, but to the contributors. He is charging it up to the employers and employees.  In other words, instead of the fund increasing to meet greater commitments in future, the fund is to be depleted.  It will never increase. Looking at it from a reasonably long term point of view, even four or five years, the only part of the community the Minister will benefit is the Government.</P>
    <P>They are accepting a liability in theory but they are shifting off an equivalent liability.  It is roughly an equivalent liability.  There is no question about that.  The total cost of this scheme will be £7 million a year.  It will come, as to £4 million, from the employers and from the employees.  It <Col N="2091" /> will come, as to £2½ million, from saving on existing non-contributory schemes and it will come as to well under £1 million, at any rate, from the Exchequer.</P>
    <P>Let me say this about it: at least it has one merit.  The Minister is now economically-minded&mdash;much more effectively economically-minded on this Bill&mdash;than he was some years ago or his colleagues are today.  This Bill is not going to throw nearly so heavy a burden on the Exchequer, if any, by comparison with the burdens put on the Exchequer in recent years by his colleague, the Minister for Finance. The Minister says that the savings are not at the expense of those receiving non-contributory pensions.  Of course, they are not, but they are at the expense of the community as a whole and they are at the expense of the people who will be working for 20 or 30 years to come.</P>
    <P>It reminds me of the very first social welfare system in the world in modern times&mdash;the system originated by Prince Bismarck, whose reputation in this country is different from his real reputation which is in fact, built much more on his social activities and organisational activities in his own country.  The system of social insurance that he established in Germany nearly 100 years ago has been commented on as &ldquo;a system of making the poor pay for the poor&rdquo;.  There certainly is a great deal of that in this Bill&mdash;a great deal of the system of making the poor pay for the poor, a system which ends up by making the rich richer and the poor poorer.  The working class poor will pay for the poor who cannot work.</P>
    <P>The workers among the poorer sections of the community and, indeed, other people also, but in particular the workers, will pay on the double.  The worker who makes his contribution will pay an increased contribution of 1/9d. and will also pay whatever amount comes upon the cost of living otherwise in relation to the manner in which the employers must recoup themselves for their end of the outgoings. Therefore, the person who works, who actually contributes with <Col N="2092" /> his labour to the community and who is among the social insurance classes, that is to say, the person with an income of under £800 a year, as I think it is to-day, will pay on the double. Other people may pay once and a small part of the population will benefit, indeed, and benefit in the early years (which I take to be the Minister's political purpose in this Bill) to a much greater extent than is warranted by the position.</P>
    <P>It is all very fine for the Minister to come in with a great flourish about the Bill.  When one analyses it, one sees that the essence of the Bill is in Section 14.  That is the section which deals with the increased contributions. They are to be very much greater. These contributions are much greater on the existing workers, younger people, than they should be.  But the benefits are too great for the Fund to be built up as it should be.  If the Fund is to be solvent through time, then some day somebody may have to take other measures to make it solvent.</P>
    <P>The Minister wins on both feet.  He kicks a goal with the left foot and the right foot.  So far as giving the old age pensioners an increase, is concerned, it is a matter that will be justified having regard to the fact that although the general standard of living of this community is supposed to have gone up by 30 per cent. since before the war, the real value of the old age pension at present is hardly equal to what it was pre-war.  Even when the famous 1/- was taken off the old age pension making it 9/-, I would be prepared to say that 9/- was worth more then the present old age pension.</P>
    <P>Therefore, the underlying idea of increasing the old age pension to 40/- for a certain number of old age pensioners is to be commended.  There is no question about that.  Everybody will feel that it really gives the older people, who have made their contribution to our community, their share of the improved position in which the community finds itself after a lapse of 20 years.  That is one aspect.</P>
    <P>I do not see why our community as a whole should not be able to pay for <Col N="2093" /> it, were it not for the extravagant increase in expenditure brought about under the aegis of the Minister for Health, when he was Minister for Finance and when expenditure, the ordinary Estimates, went up by £40 million in three and a half years, and under the aegis of his successor when the expenditure has gone up by £20 million in a similar period.</P>
    <P>That, of course, means that the State is now tight for money to meet current expenditure and it cannot give to the old age pensioners, on account of increases in expenditure which are unjustified by the national income, what everybody would like to see them getting, that is, their part of the total increase in the national wealth.  In fact, the Minister has adopted this method of giving some of them that increase by making, as I say, the poor pay for the poor, that is, he is imposing a burden on the existing workers in their youth and middle years, who in the main will not benefit by the scheme for a long time to come.  I take it that he is assuming the maximum of credit to himself for having given something to the old age pensioners.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Fáiltím-se Ó chroí roimh an mBille seo mar 'sé mo thuairim gur Bille tairbheach é do na h-aicmí atá luaite ann.  Sean-daoine go mbeidh 70 bliain bainte amach acu agus a bhí fé árachas le linn dóibh bheith ag obair, baintreacha go raibh a bhfir chéile fé árachas, daoine a bheidh ar ceal oibre agus daoine ná fuil ar a gcumas obair a dhéanamh de dheasca tinnis nó easláinte, cuirfidh an Bille Sóisialach so feabhas mór ar a mbeatha san.  Beidh níos mó cabhrach le fáil acu ón Stáit in am an ghátair.</P>
      <P>Anois do'n chéad uair beidh dhá phúnt sa tseachtain le fáil ag an lucht sean-aoise go mbeidh 70 bliain sroiste acu iad san atá nó a bheidh páirteach san scéim árachais agus ní h-amháin san ach go mbeidh 28/6d. sa tseachtain le fáil chó-maith ag éinne a bheidh ag brath ar na sean-daoine sin le h-aghaidh cothuíochta.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Go deimhin is mór an chéim ar aghaidh é sin agus 'sé mo thuairim go <Col N="2094" /> mbeidh a lán sean-daoine agus daoine nach iad buíoch den Aire mar gheall ar an mBille seo&mdash;baintreacha, dílleachtaithe agus daoine atá nó a bheidh ar ceal oibre agus na daoine nach féidir leo obair a dhéanamh mar gheall ar easláinte.  Dár ndó, ní beag a mbeidh á chaitheamh againn ar na seirbhísí sóisialacha anois breis is 27 milliún púnt.  Nuair a bheidh an Bille seo rite beidh isteach is amach le 7 milliún púnt sa bhreis.  Is cruthanas é sin ná fuil faillighe a dhéanamh ag an Rialtas ins na h-aicmí daoine seo nach acmhainn dóibh seasamh ar a gcosa féin.</P>
    <P>Mar a dúirt cheana cuirim fáilte is fiche roimh an mBille seo agus traosluím leis an Aire i dtaobh an bheartais atá curtha roimis aige sa Bhille seo.</P>
    <P>I followed the remarks of the previous speaker.  Senator O'Donovan, and while he went to great pains to detract from the merits of the Bill, I think it is true to say that he made a very poor case against it.  First of all, he seemed to fall into the error into which certain speakers in the Dáil fell when they tried to persuade themselves and others that the State was making a very meagre contribution towards the scheme.  However, as the Minister pointed out, out of the £7 million, roughly, which the scheme is calculated to cost, the taxpayers will be asked to bear no less an amount than roughly £3 million.  Whatever argument the Senator or anybody else may endeavour to put forward to deny that fact, the figure is there, the calculation is there and there is no going beyond that.</P>
    <P>In my opinion, this is one of the most important measures of its kind to be introduced in the Oireachtas for a number of years.  I would say that it is going to be a very beneficial measure for the classes of people covered by it and to whom the provisions will apply.  It is of course based on the concept of social insurance and that is as it should be.  That should be the guiding principle for measures of this kind in the future.  This is an amending Bill and it is purely an administrative Bill and what is of most concern to the classes of people to be catered for is how much they will get <Col N="2095" /> from it.  There is no doubt about that. There are many classes who will benefit from it.  This Bill is another important step on the part of the Minister and the Government in coming to the assistance of the most needy sections of our community.  It is just another proof, if proof were needed, of the Government's concern for the needy sections of the community.</P>
    <P>Before I proceed to deal with the Bill generally I should like to refer to some other remarks made by Senator O'Donovan on the Bill.  He said that the people in the west of Ireland would not benefit from its provisions.  I wonder does he believe that or does he know&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I said that very few of the old age pensioners in the west of Ireland would benefit from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;or does he know anything at all about the conditions existing in the west and southwest of Ireland?  Of course there are many people in the west and southwest who will benefit from the provisions of this Bill&mdash;agricultural workers, shop assistants, road workers and so on.  All these will come within the ambit of this scheme and benefit from it as the occasion arises.  It is wrong therefore to say that it will be of no benefit to the people living in the western and south-western parts of the country.  He also said that this Bill was designed to make the poor pay for the poor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to point out to the Senator that people earning from £12 to £20 a week will benefit under this Bill, and they cannot be described as poor people.  There is no agricultural worker in the country today earning less than £5 per week, so to say that this is a Bill which will compel the poor to pay for the poor is quite wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have no poor people then in the country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>We have not. The people of this country are very <Col N="2096" /> well catered for at the present time under our social welfare code, and when this Bill is enacted, they will be much better catered for and will get further and better benefits from our social welfare code.  There is no doubt that, as the Minister pointed out, some 200,000 people will benefit under this Bill.  Old age pensioners, their dependants, widows and orphans, unemployed persons, sick persons. people in receipt of maternity benefits, and so on, will all benefit under this measure, and I think Senator O'Donovan will have to admit that.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Donovan also referred to an increase in expenditure.  There has been no great increase in expenditure since this Government took office, and if the previous Government balanced their Budget and made provision for all their commitments, there would be very little difference between the sum they would have presented to the Irish people and the sum presented by the Minister for Finance this year.</P>
      <P>As I have said, many classes of the community will benefit under this important measure.  This is the first time that old age pensioners and people who have been in insurable employment in their working careers on reaching the age of 70 will have been brought into this contributory scheme of social insurance.  They will now be in receipt of £2 a week, which is a very substantial increase over what an old age pensioner gets at the present time.  There is a good difference between 28/6d. a week and 40/- a week. As well as the old age pensioner getting £2 a week, if he has an adult dependant, that adult dependant will get 28/6d. a week.</P>
      <P>That is a very important provision, and a very important benefit for both the old age pensioner and the adult dependant, and I think the Minister is to be complimented on having introduced a provision in this Bill whereby old age pensioners who have been, who are, and who will be, in insurable employment during their working careers will get £2 a week, and 28/6d. a week for an adult dependant.  That is a provision which is not to be sneered at.  It is a good provision and a generous one, I must say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2097" /> The second class of persons to which I wish to refer are widows in receipt of contributory pensions.  Their pensions are to be increased substantially, and as well as that, when they reach the age of 70 years, they can retain their widows' contributory pension and they will not, as has been the case, be compelled to abandon that contributory pension and accept an old age pension at a lesser rate.  I must say I always thought it was quite wrong, in principle, to compel a widow whose husband was in insurable employment and made the necessary contributions towards the national social insurance fund, to abandon her widow's contributory pension and accept a lesser pension when she reached old age pension age.  If the Bill contained no other provision than that, it would still have to be commended.</P>
    <P>As well as all that, people in receipt of unemployment benefit or disability benefit will get a very substantial increase in their basic allowance, and as the Minister pointed out, for the first time the third and subsequent children will be brought within, the scope of the social insurance code. They will be eligible for the allowance. The allowance for the first and second child, as the Minister pointed out, will be increased by 25 per cent. from 8/- to 10/-, and each child after the second will qualify for an allowance of 5/- a week.  I submit that again is a very generous provision on which the Minister is to be complimented.</P>
    <P>There are other classes, of course, who will benefit under this Bill. Orphans and persons in receipt of maternity benefits will derive much advantage from this measure when it becomes law.  I am sure the people of the country generally, even those who will not directly benefit themselves, will acclaim this measure as being one of the best, if not the best, social measure that ever came before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  I am glad to be able to compliment the Minister on introducing it here today.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Donovan also complained about the increase in the contribution rates, but I do not think there is any cause for complaint there.  After all, the increase is not very much.  An increase <Col N="2098" /> of 1/9d. on a working man is not very great.  It is the price of a small packet of cigarettes and a box of matches.  That is the increase per week that the insured worker is called upon to pay, and when one considers the many benefits that such a person stands to get from the Bill, I think no one will cavil at that very small increase.  Of course, there is also an increase in the contribution, the employer has to pay, but no one seems to lay any emphasis on that, and I shall not deal with it It is not a very great increase either, considering the merits of the Bill and its many generous provisions. I am sure it will be welcomed by the people as a whole as well as by the beneficaries.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister on the introduction of this measure.  It is progressive and well thought out.  It is equitable in the distribution of benefits, in the amounts contributors will have to pay and as it affects all classes of the community.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a rather complicated Bill.  We are indebted to the Minister and his Department for the explanatory memorandum which makes it a little more intelligible.  On behalf of the Labour group, I would give a general welcome to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the increased benefits for insured workers and the old age contributory pension.  We should not exaggerate the old age contributory benefit.  We will change from the inadequate old age pension, subject to a means test, to a less inadequate pension without a means test for which a contribution has to be paid.  That will apply to only a limited proportion of the population.  It will apply to a limited proportion of people who attain 70 years of age.  It will apply only to those who have been in insurable employment and who have complied with the regulations in regard to maintaining their benefit.  It will not apply to that other section of the community who attain 70 years of age, that is, those who have not been in insurable employment.  I have no idea as to the proportion.  I suppose one would be expected to regard the people in insurable employment as a substantial and <Col N="2099" /> an important section of the community but we have no information to show the proportion of people attaining 70 years of age who will be entitled to the contributory old age pension and the proportion for whom this Bill provides no benefit whatever.</P>
    <P>Senator Ó Ciosáin was very enthusiastic about this Bill.  Towards the conclusion of his speech, he said the new rates of contribution are equitable. If he were paying into an insurance fund and his rates of contribution were increased by 63 per cent. and his benefits were increased from about 8? per cent. to about 33? per cent., would Senator Ó Ciosáin regard that as equitable?</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make a comparison between the increase in contributions being provided for and the increase in benefits.  These new contributions will carry a benefit which was not previously provided to the extent that we now have the old age contributory pension.  It should be borne in mind that this old age contributory pension will increasingly replace, at least for insured workers, the existing pension which is subject to a means test.</P>
      <P>In looking at this question of pension, we should bear in mind also that only a fraction of the workers who throughout their working life will be required to pay for the benefit will reach the age at which it will be paid. I was interested to see in Table 15 of the <i>Statistical Abstract</i> the expectation of life.  In the urban areas, the expectation of life for a man joining insurance at 21 years of age is a little over 46 years.  According to the Tables, he has not an expectation of life sufficiently long to draw the benefit at 70 years of age.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I accept that these increased rates of contribution carry a benefit which was not previously provided for.  I hope I am putting it into proper focus in relation to the new benefit.  According to the same Table a man would <Col N="2100" /> have to survive, paying insurance in the meantime, to 47 years of age before he would have a life expectation to bring him up to 70 years.  At 47, according to the Tables, he would have a life expectation of 23.04 years.  In other words, he will expect to live .04 of a year past 70 years of age.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the date of the Table?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The 1959 <i>Statistical Abstract.</i>  It is as up-to-date as I could get it.  In spite of the improvements the Minister has made in his capacity of Minister for Health unfortunately these are the facts of life which affect all of us.  I do not know what .04 of a year represents.  I do not imagine it would be very expensive in regard to the old age pension provided for under this Bill.</P>
      <P>However, and here I shall give the Minister a point, a female at that stage, at 47 years of age, has a much longer expectation of life; and indeed at 21, a female has an expectation of nearly 50 years, so that a female would have an expectation of living to draw the old age pension.  Females may sometimes complain that they have not equal rights, but at least statistically they seem to have greater expectations.</P>
      <P>I should not be regarded as objecting to this new provision, but I am trying to put it into proper focus and to show the real value of this benefit which has been provided and for which the insured worker will have to pay.  From what I have said I am entitled to suggest to the Minister that at the earliest opportunity consideration should be given to the qualifying age, that 70 years of age is too late, and that even if people do survive into their sixties, they are not, especially when they are engaged in manual labour, in a position to work for very much longer until they could qualify for this old age benefit.</P>
      <P>I am therefore urging on the Minister&mdash;and I hope his experience will enable him to do so&mdash;to reduce the qualifying age from 70, and if he cannot make it 65, which is generally regarded as the retirement age, that he should make it somewhere about 67.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2101" /> I referred to the rates of contribution, and I should like to make some comparison, though, again, it cannot be very exact because these new rates of contribution are providing for a benefit which was not previously provided in this form.  The rates of contribution for the ordinary worker are being increased by two-thirds.  It is all right for Senator Ó Ciosáin to say that they are being increased by only 1/9 per week, but in a matter like this, we must have regard to proportions, and the exact increase is 63 per cent., which is nearly two-thirds.</P>
    <P>Then when we come to look at the increased benefits being provided, we find the first benefit being increased according to my calculation by 8.3 per cent., the second and third the same.  The provision for adult dependants is to go up from 15/- to 20/-, and this is a bit better, being an increase of 33? per cent.; but, again, it is only half the increase in respect of contributions.  The increase in a case of a qualified child or each of two qualified children is 25 per cent., and there are other increases.  The biggest increase, which I welcome, is the increase for an orphan's contributory allowance, which is from 10/- to 20/-, an increase of 100 per cent.  All in all, it is not possible to be exact, but I am entitled to draw the conclusion and to draw the attention of the Seanad to the fact that the increased rates of contribution are much higher than the corresponding increase in benefits being provided under this Bill.</P>
    <P>In this respect, I would like the Minister to consider the position of young workers, the people starting in employment, serving their apprenticeship. I suggest that to a young worker in receipt of a £1, 30/-, £2 or £3 a week, the sum of 4/6 a week is in the nature of a poll tax.  It is too heavy at that rate of pay.  Even though this point was put to the Minister in the Dáil and he would not accept it, I would again urge that he look at that problem and consider whether it would not be possible to provide for some smaller rate of contribution from an insured worker at that stage, when he is young and in receipt of very little wages.  Remember that at that stage <Col N="2102" /> there is no great point in trying to tell a worker that in paying this contribution, he is also providing for an old age pension at 70, because statistically at 21, he has a life expectation of 46 years which of course will not bring him to 70 years of age; and that sort of argument, statistically or in any other way, will not carry much weight with a young person.  I therefore urge on the Minister that he should, if at all possible, make provision for a smaller rate of contribution from that type of worker.</P>
    <P>We are being told that in the new rates of contribution, we are providing for the old age pension at 70 which will not be subject to the objectionable means test, but it is the experience of trade unionists that good employers&mdash; and I am glad to say there are many good employers in this State&mdash;already provide retirement benefits for their workers, and in many cases they require only a nominal rate of contribution from the workers.  They do not regard as sacrosanct the principle which the Minister and the Government generally regard as sacrosanct now, that in the social benefits there should be the same rate of contribution from the worker as from the employer.  If good employers can do this, if they see to it that they pay far more than 50 per cent. towards retirement pensions at 65, why should the State in this measure provide that the employers who are not already providing pensions should pay only the same rate of contribution as the workers?</P>
    <P>Again, having regard to the fact that the rate we are requiring the worker to pay is being increased in a far greater proportion than the benefits, particularly to the younger and lower paid people, it will be a very heavy burden.</P>
    <P>The Minister may argue that the costs of social services are very heavy, but according to calculations I have seen, they generally run at about £26,000,000 per annum.  That seems a very big sum, but on the other hand, it only equals the tax collected on tobacco.  In other words, the cigarette and tobacco smokers contribute in taxes roughly the same amount as the State has to meet for the various social benefits.  Allowing for the increased <Col N="2103" /> expenditure on social welfare in the current year, the bill will be only 28 per cent. of the total Government expenditure. Again, that seems a big proportion, but if you look back over the expenditure of previous years, you will see that it has virtually remained unchanged for the past four years. There is no great change in the proportion of Government expenditure allocated to social welfare generally.</P>
    <P>I should like at this stage to ask the Minister to look at a particular group&mdash;it is a small group&mdash;involved in this Bill.  I refer to the people who contribute only in respect of widows' and orphans' benefit.  I wonder would it be possible, would it be desirable or practicable to allow such people, if they so wish, to contribute for the old age contributory pension?  I make that suggestion because it is my experience that even though such people have superannuation provided for them at retirement at 65 years of age, owing to the change in the value of money, if they live, as some of them do, to 70 years of age, they get poorer and poorer.  The value of the superannuation for which they have contributed throughout their working life, unfortunately, tends to decrease.  We find that such people become inevitably poorer and less well able to provide for themselves.</P>
    <P>If that is not possible, I would ask the Minister, again in relation to that section of the workers, to look at their position in respect of widows' and orphans' benefit.  As I understand the position, their cards are stamped or they stamp them themselves while they are working but when they come to retire at 65 years of age, they must then, in order to retain their entitlement to this benefit, purchase stamps themselves.  In other words, they have to purchase stamps at the rate of 2/- per week or, under this Bill, at the rate of 2/6d. per week at a time when they are out on pension and when obviously they can ill-afford to have to pay out for these weekly stamps.</P>
    <P>If they do not do that, they lose their entitlement, their cover for widows' and orphans' benefit.  Where that applies, I always advise these people it is prudent that they should <Col N="2104" /> maintain the insurance but at that stage some of them, after leaving employment, find it hard to understand these things.  They have no experience of stamping cards or maintaining insurance. Too often, I think they drop out of insurance.  The Minister may say they can, as an alternative, save the 2/- per week or attend at the local employment exchange and have their cards stamped or have credits allowed instead of purchasing the 2/- or the 2/6 stamp.  Again, I think they can have credit given them by sending in a medical certificate that they are unfit for work.</P>
    <P>I think the Minister will see my point in this.  These sort of people are reluctant to make these purchases. Instead of going along to an employment exchange, instead of sending in medical certificates that they are unfit for work, they prefer, if they do maintain their insurance, to stamp their own cards.  These people were stamping the cards while they were in employment.  I would urge the Minister sympathetically to consider their position, having regard to the fact that they are not working because they have reached the retirement age.  They have been retired because it is a normal feature of their employment to retire them at 65.  They have to go and because of that, I would suggest that the Minister should allow their retirement to stand without having to purchase stamps or, on the other hand, without having to go along to an employment exchange and register there and have their cards stamped there.  They have retired on pension and I think the Minister in those circumstances could allow their entitlement to continue and not drop because they have not continued stamping cards.</P>
    <P>There is another point again in relation to this limited section of workers.  I should like to hear from the Minister if anything could be done about a certain group who should be voluntary contributors for widows' and orphans' benefits.  The position there is that, when they go over the limit of £800 per year, they have then to contribute the cost of the stamp themselves in order to maintain <Col N="2105" /> benefit.  I am not objecting to the fact that they would have to meet the 2/6 themselves.  What I am concerned about is the time limit they are given in order to continue on as voluntary contributors.  As I understand the position, when they reach £800, they are no longer compulsorily insured for widows' and orphans' benefit.  They are then given some time in which they can opt to become voluntary contributors.  If they do not do so within that time, they cannot change their minds.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>They are given 12 months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  Some of these people go out of insurance because they may change their employment. They may get a new job carrying a salary of over £800 per annum.  I cannot imagine that the Exchequer would be at any loss if those people were allowed to come back into voluntary insurance, to provide cover for their widows and orphans.  I am not advocating, nor would I attempt to advocate, that they should be in any better position than the people who have exercised the option within the 12 months and stamped their cards.</P>
      <P>I do not know whether many people are involved or would want to do so. I think, if they want to, they should be allowed to come back into insurance by purchasing stamps for all the time they were out, with the permission of the Department.  They could come back into insurance that way.</P>
      <P>I do not think there would be any cost to the Exchequer in providing that sort of cover for them.  It would be a voluntary effort and I think the Minister would be with me in this, that where people want to provide this insurance on a voluntary basis, they should be encouraged to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I mentioned earlier the new cost of the stamp contributions.  As I am on the question of widows and orphans and the people who are insured only for that purpose, I think I could pertinently remark that the increased contribution amounts to an increase of 25 per cent.  They are not by reason of this increased contribution providing <Col N="2106" /> for an old age pension at 70 years of age.  That is not part of their stamp at all.  So we cannot say that this new rate is providing for a new benefit. In fact, it is not in that respect.</P>
    <P>There is an increase of 25 per cent. in the benefits which are being provided; an increase for a widow of 16? per cent. and where a widow is not so qualified, an increase of 8? per cent. But again, as I said earlier, there is an increase of 100 per cent for orphan's contributory allowance.  I cannot imagine that there is very much in that in the sense that there would not be many involved.  It seems to me that the increased rate of contribution is out of line with the new benefits which are being provided or rather, I would say it the other way, that the new rates of benefit are not up to the level of the increase being provided in the rates of contribution.  I hope, however, that the Minister will be back to us next year providing for increased pensions for all these types of workers. Might I end on the note on which I started and say that the Bill is a step in the right direction?  I may feel that it does not go far enough in the right direction, but I welcome it and I hope the Minister will be back again soon to make improvements, both in regard to pensions and also in regard to reducing the qualifying age for the new old age pension.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryDavidson" hpid="Miss Davidson Miss Davidson">
      <NameTxt>Miss Davidson</NameTxt>
      <P>Any measure which seeks to improve the existing social welfare schemes must receive our approval and therefore I also welcome the introduction of this measure which will undoubtedly improve certain social welfare benefits.  The new and perhaps the most important thing which the Bill will do is to provide contributory old age pensions, which is a most desirable provision long overdue.  No person could quarrel with giving our aged people a statutory right to receive a pension but I think it comes too late in the lives of the recipients to give them a reward towards the end of their days or to provide a feeling of warm security.  At 70 years of age, as we have already been told, the road of life is very short.  In most progressive countries, retirement pensions have <Col N="2107" /> become a commonplace and generally speaking, the pension comes much earlier than is proposed in this Bill. It comes around the 65 mark.  I think the Minister might have aimed at giving ageing workers a better deal by giving them their pensions at 65 for men and perhaps 60 for women.</P>
      <P>I would hesitate to say that women work twice as hard as men but I think most will agree that they work twice as much as their menfolk.  Very often a woman's work differs very little from that of her male colleague, although it is very rarely she receives as high a wage as he does; but while the man's work, in the general run of things, ends when he leaves his place of employment, the woman continues to work as she generally has to cope with at least some portion of the domestic work in the home.  Therefore I think that the few years earlier payment that I claim on behalf of women is easily justified.</P>
      <P>Another aspect of the situation which I should like the Minister to consider is the availability of work to men and women beyond the age of 60 and 65.  A man of 65 who has paid insurance for the greater part of his working life might lose his job around the 65 mark and would in today's circumstances find it exceedingly difficult to obtain employment and would not have the means to become a voluntary contributor.  Industry today is highly mechanised and is becoming more so. In elderly persons, eyesight is impaired, reactions are slower and such persons are more accident prone. Employers therefore seek young, active employees who are quick and easy to train.  They consider elderly employees a bad investment from a production point of view and a bad risk from the accident point of view.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These arguments apply both to men and women.  There is a big population of women workers who operate power machines and many who are employed in light engineering occupations, all of which require good eyesight, nimble fingers and quick reactions. I cannot see an employer welcoming a woman between 65 and 70 <Col N="2108" /> years of age for such occupations-Other employments which absorb very large numbers of women workers are the hotel and catering industry and shop work.  It is a fact that ageing waitresses and women shop assistants will just not be employed.  How is it intended that these people will fill the gap of five or ten years between 60 or 65 and 70 in order to receive the full 40/- old age pension for which many of them will have subscribed in some measure through their insurance contributions?</P>
    <P>These people are not ill and, therefore, they cannot draw sickness benefits and thus obtain credits.  They have become unemployed mainly because their faculties are impaired. Surely we cannot condemn these aged people to trudge around the employment exchanges after they have exhausted their benefits, so as to claim credits by registering for jobs which they know are not there.  That surely is false pretences and we should not place our industrious aged workers in such a position.  I know of course that if these old people cannot fulfil the conditions for obtaining the new benefit and are able to exist until they are 70, they may qualify for a pension at a lower rate, or for the lower existing non-contributory old age pension with its means test and other distasteful conditions, but that is not a fair way, to my mind, to treat these people.</P>
    <P>Surely, having gone so far in this scheme, the Minister will stretch his generosity a bit more to preserve the dignity of our ageing citizens.  I know that under the Bill it is not necessary to retire to qualify for the new pension but does the Minister really think there will be so many to whom the Act will apply who will be able to remain in employment after reaching the age of 70?  Even if he does think they will, would it not be a better bargain for this country, with its deep pool of unemployment, to make the pension a little higher with the qualification of retirement and the qualifying age a little lower so as to make employment openings available to younger people and keep them off the emigrant ship?</P>
    <P>The fact that the self-employed man is outside the scheme is a shortcoming. <Col N="2109" /> Many a skilled worker with contributions to his credit in the insurance fund, finding himself without a job and with a young family, has feared the consequences to them if he emigrated.  By sacrifice and hard work, he has built up a business for himself at home.  It should not be outside the ability of the Department of Social Welfare to devise a scheme to extend the contributory old age pension scheme to such a person who, having kept his skill and his family in the country, is entitled to a reward for doing so.</P>
    <P>I turn now to the conditions for the old age pensions which the Bill says are:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  that the claimant has entered insurance before attaining the age of sixty,</P>
    <P>(b)  that not less than one hundred and fifty-six employment contributions have been paid in respect of the claimant since his entry into insurance, and</P>
    <P>(c)  that the average per contribution year of the contributions paid in respect of or credited to the claimant in respect of the period beginning at the beginning of the contribution year in which the claimant's entry into insurance occurred and ending at the end of the last complete contribution year before the date of his attaining pensionable age is not less than forty-eight.</P>
    <P>Conditions (a) and (b) seem to be quite reasonable but (c) appears to be capable of disqualifying a large number of workers from any hope of receiving the contributory pension of £2 per week.</P>
    <P>I am aware that, in explaining the conditions of receipt, the Minister stated at column 1183, volume 182, No. 9, of the Dáil Debates:</P>
    <P>It is proposed, however, in regulations to be made under Section 13 of the Bill ... to treat an entry into insurance under the former National Health Insurance Acts prior to the attainment of age 60 as effective for the purposes of the new pension and those regulations will also provide <Col N="2110" /> for the counting, where necessary, of contributions paid or credited under the National Health Insurance Acts towards satisfying the remaining two conditions for the new pension.</P>
    <P>These regulations, when they are made available to us, may allay our fears, but as the Bill stands, I have a feeling of great anxiety that very many persons who entered insurance some 30 or 40 years ago may find themselves&mdash;due to long periods of unemployment during which they have wandered far and wide in search of work, and during which they could not &ldquo;sign on&rdquo; and so obtain credits&mdash;without the contributions or the credits to fulfil the stipulations at paragraph (c): that they have an average of 48 contributions paid or credited in each contribution year since their entry into insurance.</P>
    <P>The same thing applies to a person who, when young, first entered insurance in a temporary job and then decided that such a job held no prospects, gave it up, studied for something better, got odd spells of temporary employment or perhaps emigrated for a period before finding permanent employment.  It seems possible that such a person, on reaching the age of 70, may find his contributions and credits leave him short of the necessary number to qualify with an average of 48 contributions in each contribution year since his entry into insurance.  As the value of credits is only now manifesting itself, I think the Minister should ease the qualification at paragraph (c) as many contributors seeking employment outside their home district did not register at the employment exchange, and so did not get credits.  I should like the Minister to consider the points I have raised and perhaps he could give me some more information on the application of paragraph (c) of the qualifications.</P>
    <P>In saying what I have said, I should not like it to be thought that I am attempting in any way to disparage the efforts of the Minister in what he is doing in this measure.  I appreciate that the proposed new old age pension of 40/-, with its allowances for dependants for those who can qualify, is a very great advance on the old noncontributory <Col N="2111" /> pension of 27/6d.  It means that a worker who is lucky can look forward to it, but I still think that the amount is rather on the low side measured against to-day's costs of living.  As I have already said, it comes too late to be of real benefit to the aged and, so far as I can see, the Bill will bring disappointment to a great many old people who thought they would be able to qualify for this new pension of £2 per week.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support the various pleas made by Senator Miss Davidson and Senator Murphy for an amendment&mdash;I shall not say a modification but rather an extension&mdash;of the provisions of this Bill, if not now, when presumably it is too late to have our recommendations accepted, at any rate early in the next session.</P>
      <P>I feel that the Minister is entitled to some praise for this Bill, and I think that Senator Ó Ciosáin, though perhaps he exaggerated in the terms he used, was justified in saying that this is a piece of legislation which takes quite an important place in the history of social welfare legislation in this country, principally by reason of this provision for a contributory old age pension without a means test.  That is a very pronounced forward step, and I think the Minister is entitled to take legitimate pride in introducing the Bill for that reason.</P>
      <P>I am rather tempted to think of the Minister here as having invited us, as it were, to come to see foundations which have been laid at his direction, and then asking us to admire the beautiful palace he has built when, in fact, what we are looking at are still merely the foundations.  I think many of us, and perhaps the Minister himself, will continue to look on this kind of Bill as merely laying the foundations. In a sense, the Minister made that point himself, in referring to the Taoiseach's aim in relation to social welfare, and suggesting that this is the structure or pattern within which fresh legislation can be evolved and in that spirit I welcome the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2112" /> I think the principle of the Bill in many of its provisions is good, but I would say that the practice is still very grudging.  I do not think the type of benefit that is mentioned can really be boasted about and I think many of the people who are excluded from its benefits for one reason or another will have to live in harsh conditions.  I feel that many of those who will benefit under this Bill will be deriving benefits not anything like the benefits to which they are entitled to lead an ordinary life.</P>
    <P>The Minister quoted a figure&mdash;I hope I have it right&mdash;that a widow with five dependent children&mdash;I think he selected his example fairly generously to himself as it were&mdash;instead of getting 61/- will get 70/-.  That is the kind of thing I have in mind when I say that I feel that this cannot be said to be generous. I accept the Minister's example that a widow with five dependent children will have to live&mdash;or is it suggested that there is something open to her&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>She does not have to live on the 70/-.  There is no means test.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no means test, and it is hoped that this will, in a sense, supplement what she has otherwise.  I feel that this type of pension is entirely inadequate and, in fact, I am strengthened in that view by the State's recognition of the fact that in order to compensate an institution for keeping a child, the State authorises a payment to that institution of 45/- a week, which, heaven knows, is not a large sum of money.  If an institution has to keep two children, they will be granted a weekly payment of 90/- for the two children, but the widow who has to struggle to keep five children will be given 70/-.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister may say: &ldquo;She can go out and work&rdquo;, and so on.  I am not satisfied that the State, as yet, is doing what the State could do.  The Minister will plead that we are a poor country, that our national income is low, and so on.  There are other levels on which comparisons of that kind are not usually made.  I have never heard people in this country say: &ldquo;I cannot buy such and such a make of <Col N="2113" /> expensive car simply on the grounds that our national income is low.  You can afford that in the neighbouring country but over here, we have to be content with the more modest car.&rdquo; I have never heard anybody in this country argue that he could not buy the big expensive car solely on the grounds that we must be content with a lower standard of living.</P>
    <P>I feel the argument there is not entirely genuine.  The principle of the Bill is good.  In particular, the principle of Section 21 is very good&mdash;the Minister rightly pointed to it with pride.  While the general structure, principle and foundations are good, we still have a long way to go before we can admire the building which we can look forward to seeing arise one day on such foundations, a building in which the people now drawing what I would call absolutely minimum benefits will get what they would be entitled to if they were to be considered worthy of a decent, ordinary, human standard of living all round and not just for a few.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>On the whole, the Bill and the Minister who introduced it have got a fair reception.  Every Senator will agree that the Bill is an advance in our social welfare system. Various arguments have been advanced in regard to the rate of contribution, and so on.  Certain Senators even went out of their way to deprecate the Bill.  Senator O'Donovan found a number of faults with it on the ground that it represents legislation such as the Iron Chancellor would have implemented.  The Iron Chancellor did not devote 26 per cent. of his revenue to social welfare.  In those days, Governments were not held to account for social welfare. Therefore, that comparison is worth about a fistful of sawdust.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Fault was also found with the Bill because the Minister did not shift the whole burden on to the taxpayers.  In the next breath, it was stated that the measure would result in a further increase in the cost of living.  Such arguments make for confusion and are no help in considering legislation of this character.  A contributory old <Col N="2114" /> age pension scheme is a considerable step forward even allowing for the fact that we are devoting £27,000,000 odd towards helping the poor and the distressed in our community.  All reasonably-minded people will agree that an insurance Bill such as this one affords relief to certain sections of the population.</P>
    <P>This Bill was mooted about the time of the Budget.  Last December, the Taoiseach said it was proposed to lay the foundations of a contributory old age pension scheme and to build on that scheme as circumstances permitted. It is a reasonable proposition. Having regard to the strength of the insurance fund at present, it is reasonable to proceed with a certain amount of caution.  We should all like a contributory old age pension scheme which would cover not merely people reaching 70 but people reaching 65 years of age.  We should all very much like to see people retire at 65.  Indeed, it would be necessary in our present circumstances.  However, we must ask ourselves if we can afford it.  If we proceeded in that manner, the Senators who found fault with the present measure would be very quick to find fault with the Government and the Minister for what they would call the savage taxation imposed on the community to meet the commitments.</P>
    <P>The underlying feature of the Bill is the contributory old age pension scheme which will be worked on the lines of the existing insurance scheme. I think that is wise.  The clauses are very much the same as the qualifying clauses for unemployment benefit and sickness benefit.  That also is a good thing.  It will make for simplified procedure and will keep costs low.</P>
    <P>Certain people will benefit considerably from the Bill.  Even though contributors will have to make an increased contribution, the stamp carries many compensations as well as the old age pension.</P>
    <P>We must also recognise that under the 1952 Social Welfare Act when the various benefits and contributions were consolidated, it carried the right to unemployment and sickness benefit as well.  Let us not lose sight of these <Col N="2115" /> facts when we come to consider legislation such as this.</P>
    <P>It was wise to keep within the existing framework, for the start at any rate.  It is understandable that self-employed persons could not readily be brought within the scope of the Bill, simply for the reason that they are not contributing anything towards it It is also quite understandable that we could not very well introduce a retirement clause in it, because should that be the case, then it would amount, as the Minister stated, to a means test and would be taking away from the benefits of the Bill as well as making for more complicated procedure.</P>
    <P>One of the most important sections of the Bill is Section 16, which states the qualifications.  It does not make any radical change in the existing arrangement and there is nothing very stiff about the conditions.  As a matter of fact, the proposals issued in the White Paper of 1949 visualised a retirement condition, and at that time, although it never saw the light of day in the sense that it did not become legislation, it visualised more or less a means test.  Attached to it, there is also a relaxing clause whereby persons who entered insurance prior to 5th January, 1953, will be allowed to share in the benefits of the scheme; and when we speak of contribution either by young or old, we must remember that this is going to extend certain benefits to those people.  Certainly they could not qualify on any other basis, and for that reason we could make the point that in that regard it is quite equitable.  It is likewise regarding shortages in records.  Assuming that a person cannot prove a record of stamps, then there is a relaxation in that respect.</P>
    <P>We have, as I say, a scheme designed to work, a scheme not purely based on means tests.  It is quite straight and clear, and every individual who stands to benefit under it will know what he or she is entitled to.</P>
    <P>Section 13 is of considerable importance. Roughly 23,000 persons, as the Minister stated, together with 7,000 adult dependants, will benefit.  That in <Col N="2116" /> itself is a considerable advance on the social insurance scheme of the past. Other modifications which can be brought about under Section 13 provide that roughly 13,000 people aged 70 will come within the terms to be prescribed under the section.  Assuming that they can prove title, they will also qualify for contributory pensions, plus a further category of dependants. This part of Section 13 also covers a completely new class of claimants who previously did not qualify for pensions at all.  Therefore, I take it that roughly 50,000 people will benefit under the section.  We know that the rate is £2, plus 27/6d.  for an adult dependant, and that as well as that, in the case of the death of a pensioner, the increase in respect of an adult dependant will be payable to the survivor, unless he or she qualifies for a higher award in some other way.</P>
    <P>Section 10 is also of importance in that it provides cover at reduced rates for those who have not an average number of contributions.  That is fair and equitable also.  The extension in favour of widows is to be welcomed. Hitherto it was a hardship on a widow that she had to forgo her pension when she came to 70 years of age and revert to the old age pension.  It is to be welcomed that now she can continue to draw the contributory pension.</P>
    <P>People who criticise a measure such as this oftentimes have no advertence to the facts.  It is all very well to advocate <i>ad lib</i> benefits for all, but it is a different thing when you come to provide the benefits and to levy taxes on the people who have to pay for them.  When the Government are under pressure to find money to grant reliefs to other sections of the community, then it is not so easy to indulge in a bout of indiscriminate taxation in order to extend social welfare benefits.</P>
    <P>As I said at the outset, it was wise procedure, to say the least of it, to proceed on the basis of the existing insurance scheme.  It will provide against the risk element at any rate, and I assume that the Minister, or whatever Minister is responsible for the Department of Social Welfare in the future, will gain experience from the basis now being laid in this Bill and <Col N="2117" /> that as time goes on, as was visualised, we shall be able to build better legislation on the basis of a Bill such as this.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. P. Crowley Mr. P. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>The general principle on which the Bill is based is welcomed, and rightly so, from both sides of the House.  As far as the trade unions are concerned, it must be said that, generally speaking, they look at this Bill with somewhat mixed feelings.  I am aware that some of them look at the Bill with a certain amount of misgiving. I do not have to point to the fact that the Bill imposes very substantial increases on the contributions payable both by the workers and their employers.  These increases represent quite a heavy additional charge on industry in general.  That additional charge could very well create other more serious problems for the working people generally.  We in the trade unions find that the working people generally are pressing the question in many cases as to whether, in fact, they are getting full value for these impositions.</P>
      <P>I think the scope of the Bill could and should be extended very much further in order to allow its benefits to be availed of by a much wider category of our people.  By bringing more people within the scope of the measure, the overall cost could be reduced very substantially.  I do not think there is any necessity to go into detail on these points because I think an excellent case was made both by Senator Murphy and Senator Miss Davidson to show that, in fact, the Bill has many defects as far as its application to workers generally is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, I want to repeat that the general criticism within the trade unions is that the Bill, in its scope and in the provision of the range of benefits, is far too restrictive.  It is not generous enough to attract any sort of widespread support or any great desire&mdash;and this is a most important point&mdash;on the part of any large body of people who are still kept outside the scope of the measure to participate in the benefits.  I want to support Senator Sheehy Skeffington in urging the Minister to address himself <Col N="2118" /> to these aspects of the Bill, if not in the present session, then at least in the next session.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill which will benefit the working classes. I am sure it will be very well received.  It will be of great benefit especially in the rural districts because a person receiving a contributory pension is allowed to work to supplement the pension by any means he likes.  It will be of great advantage in the country and to the economy in general.</P>
      <P>There is one class of pensioner to whom I should like to direct the Minister's attention.  I refer to people who have reached the age of 80 years.  I think some provision should be made in their favour.  There are many milestones between 70 years and 80 years. Those who have reached 80 years of age are very much in need and would probably require more for their upkeep and support than people of 70 years of age.</P>
      <P>I would suggest that the Minister might strike a special rate of pension for those who reach 80 years of age. The cost to the Exchequer would be very little.  We must remember that very few of those people would have the contributory pension because when they were 60 years of age, comparatively very few of them were insured. I think very few who reach 80 years of age would qualify for the contributory pension.</P>
      <P>The people to whom I refer will have worked harder in their time than the younger generation.  They worked in those days from morning until night and the work was very hard.  The rate of pay was very miserable, indeed. The fact that they survived all that hardship and reared their families is a tribute to them.  It would be a very gracious act if the leaders of our people today would remember those people and make the remaining few years of their lives somewhat happier by increasing the rate of pension.  I suggest that the Minister should consider giving a pension of £3 a week to those who reach 80 years of age.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill in some ways meets a want, particularly in the type <Col N="2119" /> of economy we have.  There are many persons working in small industries. These small industries find difficulty in providing some form of a pension for persons who, for one reason or another, have to retire from their employment. In many cases, these smaller industries such as creameries, which Senator O'Dwyer would represent, and many of the smaller type of industries we have in this rather small economy find that their employees, if they wish to retire at 70 years of age, will certainly get a better pension than would have been provided under the Old Age Pensions Acts.</P>
      <P>I am inclined to agree with many of the Labour speakers that if these suggestions had been issued in the form of a White Paper, we would have got a better Bill than by bringing in the provisions and being told to take them or leave them.  There is no doubt whatever that it will add another overhead and another deterrent to industry. Those of us who are engaged in industry find that every month the Government have passed another buck over to us.  We had P.A.Y.E. a couple of months ago.  The Minister for Finance got that and now the Minister for Social Welfare is going to ask industry to provide further moneys in order to help to form this insurance fund.</P>
      <P>It was suggested that this can be passed on to the public.  Anyone who suggests that any form of waste or overhead can be passed on to other than part of the public is very unaware of the situation.  Often in Dublin we hear people talking about trade not being good.  Often trade is not good because commodities are too dear.  All these little additions tend to make commodities too dear.  Anyone with any experience of industry or commerce knows that costs, overheads generally, have to be shared.  It has been well said years ago that prosperity is indivisible.  If you have a rich next-door neighbour, he is going to help you and it is equally true, I suppose, that if you have a poor nextdoor neighbour, that will be a disadvantage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>All these burdens are like sugarcoated <Col N="2120" /> pills.  You get them one at a time and you do not notice them but the effect, in the long run, must be that the exporting sections of our industry find themselves less competitive. The Minister for Finance comes in and requires industry to act as tax gatherers.  Now the Minister for Social Welfare asks industry to help him run what is akin to a superannuation scheme for insured workers, but I wonder do all these people who are putting these little burdens on us ever meet together to see what is the cumulative effect of all the things they are imposing on industry.  I do not want to widen this debate further than this point.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator is in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I may be in order if I do not develop it further.  It is like the grocer's bill.  It is not pounds that make the difficulty at all but the shillings and pence when all are totted up.  I suggest that representatives of all State Departments should meet and ask themselves whether the cumulative effect of all the shillings and pence they are asking the community to carry is not too much.  I believe that it just does not happen and that is why we find ourselves with this colossal bill of taxation, £150 million a year on three million people.  I hope that the Taoiseach will see his way to resist the various Ministers who are adding up these small amounts.</P>
      <P>I am very glad that Senator Crowley who can speak on behalf of some of the trade unions said they were perturbed about this position.  It is the Government responsible who should be perturbed in the first instance, but it is a desirable development that the trade unions, a group who influence public opinion in large measure, should be perturbed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These are all the objections I have to the Bill.  It can have advantages, but if we do get an improvement in social welfare conditions such as this Bill brings before us today, we must see that we do not interfere with or impede the people who, in the final analysis, are going to provide the money by <Col N="2121" /> their industry, work and labour.  I was glad to hear today a number of people entitled to speak for labour express much the same views on this as the employer.  If labour and employers can get the same view&mdash;it is like truth and truth is at the bottom of a well&mdash;we shall make progress in this country.  It should be easy with co-operation between employers and trade unions to get the Government to see common sense and ensure that the load is equal to the capacity of the people to carry it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. MacEntee) Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. MacEntee)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Opposition speaker who opened the debate&mdash;I do not know whether he was for or against the Bill&mdash;saw fit to describe it as &ldquo;an old man's Bill,&rdquo; but I do not know whether his jibe was directed against the old age pensioners who are to benefit so substantially under the Bill or against the somewhat elderly statesman who has been responsible for introducing it.  It is an old man's Bill in the sense I have pointed out: that a considerable number of elderly people who are past their years of useful work will, for the first time in this country, be able to retire, if they so please, with some provision for their old age which does not depend upon the fact that they are living just above subsistence level; that is to say, they will be able to enjoy this old age pension without having to satisfy any test in regard to means.</P>
      <P>I think it is a good thing that the younger generation in this country who have lived to enjoy what the older generation in large measure have won for them should be asked to meet certain obligations to their elders.  I am anxious to bring this Bill into operation. It is a measure which we in Fianna Fáil have long envisaged but unfortunately the economic conditions of the country were not such that it was practical to introduce a measure such as this until this last year and a half, until it seemed reasonably clear that we had created the conditions for an expanding economy in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been said that we are asking the future to pay for the present as far as the benefits are concerned which this Bill proposes to confer upon a very large number of our people, I think to <Col N="2122" /> the number of 200,000 at least.  That is not true.  We are merely asking the present to pay for the present.  The increase in the contributions now being asked will not meet the increased cost of the new extended and increased benefits.  In spite of the saving which can be made on the Social Assistance Vote, we shall nevertheless have to meet the cost by no less a sum than £335,000.</P>
    <P>It is true that as time goes on and the charge on the Social Assistance Vote tends to diminish, owing to the increased transfer of old age pensioners from the non-contributory to the contributory sector, it is very possible, bearing in mind that the contribution from the Exchequer will remain fixed, that there will be an increase in benefits. As the years go on, those who are coming into the insurance scheme now as young people will live to derive very substantial benefits from the contributions they are paying now.</P>
    <P>I could not quite appreciate the point made again by the opening speaker from the Opposition side of the House when he said we were laying certain burdens on those engaged in industry on both sides, whether employer or employee. What are we to deduce from that?  Is it that the Senator who made that point is opposed to any extension of social insurance in this country or that he wishes that the whole burden should be laid upon the taxpayer?</P>
    <P>The right way to proceed is by accepting that so far as it can be applied, the principle of insurance should govern and shape all schemes of social assistance and social welfare which this country may seek to organise and to maintain.  It is a fair principle that those who are to benefit specifically should contribute towards the benefits which in time they will enjoy.  On the contrary, I think that it is not a fair principle that the community on the whole should be taxed in order to provide benefits for certain specific classes, particularly for those classes which are not in such absolute need as to justify the extension to them of public charity.</P>
    <P>There is a degree of inconsistency running through this speech to which I am now referring because I understood <Col N="2123" /> that in relation to the very important question of the provision of medical attention for the members of the community, the Fine Gael Party had taken a firm stand upon the principle of insurance and that, in fact, their opposition to the Health Acts of 1947 and 1953 was based on the fact that powers were taken under those Acts to provide medical services for persons who could not pay for them and even for persons who, though they might have been able to pay for them to some degree, nevertheless were not being insured to cover themselves against the risk, or the contingency, that at one time or another they might have to avail of the health services.  I find that that insurance principle has been thrown over, perhaps temporarily, in order to find some ground for criticising this Bill.</P>
    <P>It was alleged also&mdash;and in this connection I could refer to the speeches made by Senator Crowley and Senator Burke&mdash;that this Bill was going to impose a heavy burden upon industry, a burden so heavy that, Senator Crowley suggested, ultimately it might involve an increase in unemployment in so far as workers might be put out of employment because the employers would not be able to pay the increase in the contribution and to maintain their industries in an efficient and competitive position.  I think that is an argument in respect of which we must ask ourselves the question which I asked in relation to the speech of Senator O'Donovan: what does that mean?  It either means that we cannot afford these social welfare schemes, these social insurance schemes, and therefore we should not have them, or else we should not accept the insurance principle at all.  I think that the most enlightened and realistic trade union opinion takes the view that it would prefer that the insurance principle would be given effect to.</P>
    <P>There is a good reason for that because after all if a person insures himself against a certain contingency and the contingency happens to materialise, whatever benefits he will enjoy he will enjoy as of right and not as a concession given by his fellows in the community. It is a very good thing to know <Col N="2124" /> that whatever benefits and whatever advantages you may enjoy in life are yours by right and not, as I say, by concession or by charity.  It seems to me that the argument which is based on the fact that there is going to be a charge on industry is an argument directed against the very existence, not to speak of the expansion of any system of social insurance, of any system of social assistance at all.  I do not think that that was in the mind of Senator Crowley and I do not believe either, to be quite candid, that it was in the mind of Senator O'Donovan.</P>
    <P>Let us see what is the imposition this Bill will make upon the average employer.  I think that it is a fair attribution of the cost of a product to say that in general, in any efficient industry, the labour cost will not exceed one-third of the total cost of the product. In fact we know in certain cases it is something below that.  The average earnings per worker&mdash;again I am taking a round figure, without having recourse to any statistical tables&mdash;it would not be unfair to say, taking workers by and large in any industry, are not less than £9 per week.  Some of them, as has been pointed out, earn a great deal more, but £9 is not an unfair figure to take.  The sum of 1/9d. in respect of a worker who costs him £9 represents one-third of the employer's labour costs so that we have the position that a worker who is earning 2,160 pence carries with him, or attaches to his employer, a liability of 21 pence. That is to say that represents 1 per cent. of the weekly wage earnings of that employee and the weekly earnings of that employee represent one-third the cost of the product.  Therefore, we are in this situation, that the total charge which this Bill would impose in general on industry or any particular part of industry would be about one-third of 1 per cent.</P>
    <P>In present circumstances, I do not think that is going to constitute any burden on any industry.  Therefore, there is no justification for the argument which is made here.  Of course, it is the sort of stock argument which is always trotted out by reactionaries whenever there is any proposal for the betterment of the workers.  But suppose we did not proceed on this basis and <Col N="2125" /> suppose we desired to make some sort of provision for our old people when they come to the age when they should retire, or at least be put in the position when they might retire, what are we to do?</P>
    <P>Are we to put the whole cost of the Bill directly on the taxpayers and indeed upon some of those people about whom Senator O'Donovan professed to be concerned?  Are we to bring in the west of Ireland where people do not see £9 a week coming into their homes and ask them to pay some part of these costs?  Mind you, they will pay under this Bill. Make no mistake about it, every person in the country will have to contribute. Almost 37 per cent. of the cost of this whole scheme will be paid, one way or the other, in taxation.  Are they to pay in addition to that 37 per cent., the other 63 per cent.?</P>
    <P>When we come down to the arguments and criticisms that have been used against this Bill that, in the first place, it imposes too heavy a charge on the employer and, secondly, that it imposes too heavy a charge on the employee, the only logical conclusion we can reach is that those who use that criticism desire that the whole cost should fall upon the community as a whole.  Of course if that happens, it will fall upon those who are less able to pay any additional charges.</P>
    <P>Senator Murphy had a number of things to say about the Bill in his very reasonable and informative speech. One of the points he argued just is not possible in present circumstances and it would not be possible to accept it because the principle involved is not a sound one.  He devoted quite an amount of his speech to the position of those who are insured only for the purpose of the widows' and orphans' pensions scheme.  In that regard, he made the point that those who had been insured for the purposes of that scheme, and for one reason or another went out of insurance, should be put in the favoured position that they could, at a certain period of their lives, elect to come in as voluntary contributors and, in that capacity, be entitled to pay in one lump sum, at one time, all the arrears of contributions which <Col N="2126" /> would have accrued over the years.</P>
    <P>That, of course, is not a sound principle of insurance.  The whole basis of insurance is that people carry risks. A person carries the risk of having to pay a premium for a longer period than he anticipated.  The insurer, on the other hand, takes the risk of the contingency against which the premium policy-holder is insured, maturing earlier than it normally would.  The whole idea is that the insurer, or the company carrying the policy, will have the use and benefit of the premiums which are paid in respect of any long term insurance proposition.</P>
    <P>It is the same with the widows' and orphans' pensions scheme.  That scheme was originally devised as an insurance scheme&mdash;perhaps the insurance basis is not as marked as it used to be, but the actuarial principle must be kept definitely in mind.  It is still the basis of the scheme, and the whole character of the scheme, that it is an insurance scheme based on insurance principles. Therefore, the State, which in this case carries the risk, should have the benefit and advantage of the insured person's money from the payments, from the beginning.</P>
    <P>It would not be of very much use or advantage to the voluntary contributor if at the time when he elected to join as a voluntary contributor, he had to pay not merely the total contributions but also all the accrued interest.  He would not be very much better off than he is at the present time.  I do not think there is any possibility of any Minister coming to the Oireachtas and suggesting that a person should be entitled to join this scheme as a voluntary contributor at whatever date he might elect to do so.</P>
    <P>I do not regard this point as of any great moment but I think it should be made clear.  Senator Murphy said a small percentage of the population attained the age of 70 years.  Estimates have been made with regard to this matter which show that between 4,000 and 5,000 insured persons attain the age of 70 years every year.  That is not a very small proportion of the number of people of 70 years and over in the country.</P>
    <P>Another point made by Senator Murphy was a comparison between the <Col N="2127" /> percentage increase in the rates of contribution and the rates of benefit.  Of the total cost of £6,960,000 under this Bill, a sum of £4,660,000 is for the new benefits&mdash;for old age pensions and the other increases in contributions in general&mdash;but the Senator ignores the extension of widows' and orphans' pensions after they reach the age of 70 years, and the new allowances and increases in respect of children, and in respect of children in excess of two. These all have to be paid for and they represent, in general, a further £2,300,000.</P>
    <P>Senator Miss Davidson referred to the third contribution condition.  Under Section 13 of the Bill, regulations will be made which will enable persons who do not find it possible to fulfil that condition to receive reduced benefits. Of course, there is a point at which their entitlement to reduced benefits ceases, but there will be provision by regulations made under this Bill which will allow reduced benefits to be paid to persons who have not succeeded in fulfilling the third condition. Again, self-employed persons, as such, are not excluded.  In the case which Senator Miss Davidson cited of the skilled worker becoming self-employed, he can become a voluntary contributor. Once he was in employment insurable for all purposes, he can become a voluntary contributor for the contributory old age pension.</P>
    <P>I do not think any other point arose in the course of the debate which calls for any further encroachment on, the time of the Seanad.  I want to say this is an experimental Bill.  As I said at the outset, I believe when starting a new enterprise that we should approach it with a certain degree of caution. My own estimate is reasonably conservative, but I do not think it is unduly pessimistic.  I think it will be found that the Bill will work out very much as we anticipate.  It is a beginning, and no doubt the matters which have been argued here today will arise for consideration at a later stage.  The main thing is to launch this scheme, to see how it works and, as time goes on, to see how much we shall be able to improve it, having regard to the economic circumstances of the time.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2128" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at</i> 6.10 <i>p.m. and resumed at</i> 7.30 <i>p.m.</i></P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Social Welfare (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1960&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Social Welfare (Amendment) Bill, 1960&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 12, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 13 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know if this is the section which deals with the qualification for people who were insured previously, who are now past 70 years of age and who may be in receipt of a non-contributory old age pension.  As I understand it, the Minister will make regulations specifying the qualifications necessary for this new pension.  I hope he will be as liberal as possible.  I am sure he appreciates that these people are past 70 and, because of their age, are not very well able to fight their corner or know their entitlement.  They would have been insured previously, maybe under the National Health scheme.  On behalf of the trade unions, I would ask the Minister to be as liberal as he can in order to allow as many people as possible to qualify for this new benefit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The regulations will be, in my view, liberal.  Whether they will be liberal in the opinion of everyone else is another matter.  The regulations will impose a very heavy charge on the Exchequer and will be subject to the sanction of the Minister for Finance.  I think I can assure the House that they could not be regarded as illiberal.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 14.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 14 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>No. (vi) refers to the amounts payable in respect of domestic servants.  In this country, in a great many cases, the wages are very small. The increase in contribution is very large.  Hitherto the employee's contribution <Col N="2129" /> was 11d.; it will now be 2/6d. The employer's contribution is being raised from 1/7d. to 3/3d.  That makes a total contribution of 5/9d.  Many young girls will probably not continue the insurance, being probably of marriageable age.  It is a big amount to take out of the wage.  The Minister might reduce that contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister told us today that the increase in the income arising out of the increase in contributions will be £4 million per annum.  I do not know where he got that figure.  I went to the trouble of looking up the income of the Social Insurance Fund.  In recent years, the income of the Social Insurance Fund has been around £6 million a year and is increasing.  When we look at these increased contributions, we find that many of them are fantastically high.  Whether it is that domestic servants are now regarded as a kind of super-luxury in this country, or whatever the reason, the increase there is fantastic.  It is about 250 per cent.</P>
      <P>My comments do not arise from that fantastic increase or the increase in respect of certain types of nurses, which also is about 250 per cent. Generally speaking, of the total number of people subject to social insurance, one-third are women and two-thirds are men.  If Senators look at the figures, they will see that, generally speaking, the increase for women in industrial employment is about 100 per cent. and the increase for men is the figure given by Senator Murphy, 63 per cent.</P>
      <P>The Minister tells us he will get £4 million a year out of this change. If, according to the figures, there are 650,000 persons&mdash;450,000 men and 200,000 women&mdash;and if the increase for women is generally well over 100 per cent. and the increase for male workers is 63 per cent., I do not understand where the Department or the Minister got the figure of £4 million.  I can well understand the motivating force which might suggest to them to say: &ldquo;We will take a conservative estimate.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Among his remarks the Minister said he had acted in a very conservative <Col N="2130" /> way and that this is the foundation of a new system.  Certain other foundations in this city have been laid for a long time.  I do not notice the Minister building on them, in another part of his responsibility.  In that respect, he shows no desire to spend money.  But, then, it is money in the control of the State; it is not money subscribed by contributors to a social insurance fund.  It is money in the Hospitals Trust Fund.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Hospitals Trust Fund does not arise on this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>A passing remark showing the difference in the Minister's approach is surely very much in order.</P>
      <P>In fact, it is very much in order to show that the Minister, having got the foundations of the hospital out at Nutley Lane six or eight feet above the ground four years ago, has left them there.  On this occasion, he is building on the most conservative foundations.  If he wants me to give him the reference, he will find it in the last Report of the Department of Social Welfare, 1957/58 on page 41, and the more significant figures on page 68, showing, as I say, an income of about £6 million a year.</P>
      <P>Arising out of these figures, I do not understand where the Minister gets his figures, whether things are &ldquo;trotted out by reactionaries&rdquo; or not.  I do not blame the Minister for that remark because I have said on occasions that the Minister was a right-wing Tory, and I do not mind repeating it now. He is not just a reactionary.  Every approach he makes to anything shows him to be a right-wing Tory.  I simply do not understand where the Minister gets the figure of £4 million, having regard to the fact that the increases in contributions range from 63% to 150%.  The average increase over the whole lot of them would be 100%. If there were a heavy weighting in favour of any one group, that is to say, if a big proportion, say 90%, had only an increase of 63% or 64%, I could understand the calculations, but there is no such weighting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2131" /> There are 200,000 women workers in the Social Insurance Scheme and the increase in contributions varies in the case of women from 100% to 250%.  My remark about an old man's Bill in one context has a certain weight attached to it.  There is a good deal more weight attached to it in this context.  It does not seem as if the Minister has had any undue regard for the interests of women in the way he has mulcted them in this Bill.  The contributions in respect of domestic servants and nurses would suggest that many people in this country think that domestic servants and certain classes of nurses are a super-luxury.  The remarks made this evening about wages of from £5 to £9 a week would give one the impression that a wage of that size was a significant wage today. Of course, it is not.</P>
    <P>There is no use in putting a tooth in it, in the western world of today, it is a miserable income.  The Minister tells us the increase in the contribution will bring in £4 million but in fact the figures I have given show it will bring him in a much greater sum.  That is one of the bases on which the scheme is to be financed. Otherwise, my original criticism stands, that the workers and those who will pay these contributions are paying for a benefit for which the Minister will get credit and he will leave the commitments to the people who succeed him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want again to draw attention to the contribution being paid by the person who is insured in respect of widows' and orphans' benefit only.  Unfortunately, I missed the Minister's reply.  I suppose my suggestion in this matter might be termed balderdash.  Nevertheless, I would ask the Minister if he could give any indication that he would sympathetically consider the position of people who retire on pension at 65 and who have to stamp their own cards to maintain cover for widows' and orphans' benefit. Could he regard those people as being unemployed and credit them accordingly, without the necessity of their having to go along to the employment <Col N="2132" /> exchange and register there? They are not disposed to do that, as can be understood.  They are not looking for employment, and they are not going along, as other people would be, to get unemployment benefit. I think the Minister might make provision for such people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The whole basis of this Bill is to continue people in insurance in respect of those benefits for which they have been insured during their working life, and, in the case of those who have been insured for national health purposes, to give them the right to a contributory old age pension. Those people have been paying considerably more than the others who have been insured only for widows' and orphans' pensions, and even in enlarging the benefits to be secured in the widows and orphans section of the Social Insurance Scheme, we have gone very far to benefit those people, particularly those to whom Senator Murphy has referred.  We are entitling their widows to a life pension at a minimum rate of 32/6 and in some cases considerably more.</P>
      <P>A particular difficulty is that this Bill must go through to-night in order that it may come into operation on 1st January, and the Dáil is going to adjourn.  Even if there were not that practical objection, there are many other practical objections to doing what Senator Murphy asks.  These people have no basis in respect of their former insurability for securing contributory old age pensions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr MacEntee Mr MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry if I misunderstood the Senator.  The other point is that people should be entitled to get this contributory old age pension without in fact continuing as voluntary contributors?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall sit down and let the Senator make the point again. We seem to be at cross-purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>These people have been insured for widows' and orphans' <Col N="2133" /> pensions until they retired on superannuation. If they do not then stamp their cards themselves, they lose the benefit of the widows' and orphans' cover and if they die, though they have been insured, if the card has not been stamped, there is no benefit.  That is what I am told.</P>
      <P>To maintain their cover, they have to stamp their own cards now at a rate of 2/6d.  They are out of employment; they are on pension.  The other people in that position who have been insured for all the benefits can go to the employment exchange and register because they get not alone credit but they also get the unemployment benefit. There is no purpose in these people going to the employment exchange. They are not looking for work as such. They are not getting benefit.  The only purpose would be to get credit instead of spending the 2/6d. on stamps.  I suggest that the Minister might, by regulations or such, provide that these people's entitlement would be kept alive without the necessity of themselves purchasing 2/6d. stamps and putting them on the cards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely that is going over far?  First of all, they are on superannuation.  They already have a pension.  The next thing is to secure an additional benefit, the benefit for which they were insured, the widows' and orphans' pension if they happen to predecease their wives, with allowances for their children, if they have qualified children.  They get all that for the sake of 2/6d.  That is all they are asked to do.  They may die within a very short period, one does not know. The Senator earlier cited statistics to show that their expectation of life was very dismal indeed.  It is not correct for the Senator to assume that very few people will qualify for old age contributory pension since we, know that at least 50,000 will&mdash;but I really do not think there is any merit in that contention.  If they pay 2/6d. until they reach 70 years of age or until they die as it would be in their case, they would be doing very well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator O'Donovan said he did not understand how this, that and the other was.  I am not going to accept the <Col N="2134" /> Almighty's responsibility for Senator O'Donovan's lack of understanding. The position is that the figures I gave are figures calculated by an actuary and the contribution income which is to be £4,075,000 is the calculation which he made.  I do not think that either Senator O'Donovan or I is qualified to challenge that.  I am not challenging it, whatever about Senator O'Donovan.  The Senator also suggested that the greatest proportion of the income was coming from women.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggested nothing of the sort.  Perhaps, the Minister will allow me to continue?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggested that the male contributors who were to suffer an increase of 63 per cent. were the great bulk statistically.  If they were 90 per cent. of the number, I could understand why the Minister's calculation of £4 million might be correct but, in fact, they are not.  There are 450,000 men and 200,000 women. There are many contributors who have to pay a 150 per cent. increase.  We have the changes here in paragraph 6 of Section 14.  You have 2/6d. and 3/3d., that is 5/9d., as against, I think, 1/7d.  That, by the law of Harry, is an increase of 200 per cent. or something of that order.  I said that the weighting was such that the Minister's figures could not be correct.  I did not suggest that the great bulk of the contributors were women or anything of the sort.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I see now, the Senator is suggesting that the estimates which have been furnished to me are incorrect.  As I say, we have a highly qualified actuary in the Department&mdash;one of the most brilliant, I think, in Great Britain or Ireland.  I am perfectly certain that his figures are correct and that the deductions which the Senator attempted to make on the basis of very flimsy statistics are not sound.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In any event, the general principle upon which the increased contributions have been determined is a simple one. I referred to it in my opening statement <Col N="2135" /> It is that the increases in the rates of contribution were fixed so that each rate should bear its due share of the cost of the increase in the benefits to which it gave title, that is to say, that every person will pay fairly for the increase which he is getting.  We cannot have it any other way.  If we are to reduce contributions in relation to one sector of the scheme, then we can do that only at the expense of the other contributors to the scheme or else, at the expense of the taxpayers&mdash;not of the State.</P>
    <P>Earlier the Senator was saying that the State should do this and that.  The State can do nothing.  All the State can do is to take that money out of the pockets of the taxpayer and use it for certain purposes, so that if the Senator wished to reduce any one of these rates of contribution, he could do it only at the expense of some other section of the contributors or at the expense of the general taxpayer.  No matter how I would propose to do it, the Senator would be bound to find fault and bound to criticise me because I did not do the other.  That is all I have to say in reply to the Senator's criticism.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that I shall have considerably more to say, for the reason that the Minister, having started off on actuarial grounds, ended up with the same line of argument as I adopted myself.  He said that Senator O'Donovan put forward the view that the State should pay more.  Senator O'Donovan put forward the view that if the State wishes to appear as a fairy godfather to the public in general and to a certain limited number of the public in particular, the State should be prepared to bear the burdens in the initial stages and should not shift the burden on to people who have no other option but to bear it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I stick to my point which is a matter of logic that if you have certain people contributing a certain rate and the minimum increase in contribution is 63 per cent. and the maximum increase in contribution is something like 250 per cent. to 300 per cent.&mdash;you still <Col N="2136" /> have a sizeable number of people, although apparently they are regarded as a luxury, domestic servants and certain kinds of nurses&mdash;I stick to my point that the Minister will receive a great deal more than £4 million a year. He is being conservative&mdash;&ldquo;a certain degree of caution&rdquo; is the phrase used by him.</P>
    <P>It is not true to say that we of the Fine Gael Party wish that this scheme should not be adopted at all.  The Minister in his statement this evening put together a certain amount of what looked like logic to him and said: &ldquo;You are faced with two options: we cannot afford them and therefore we cannot have them or we should accept the insurance principle.&rdquo;  Of course every right wing Tory from the year dot to this day, from the day that compulsory national education was introduced in these islands, always said: &ldquo;We cannot afford it; it will lead to immorality; it will create a disturbance in the community and everything else&rdquo;; every right wing Tory has put forward that point of view.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator tell us what is a right wing Tory?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The gentleman who stood with his back to the wall on Suez.  His name was Waterhouse, was it not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators might leave the right wing Tories alone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I should have thought that the right wing Tories worked the welfare state as well as their predecessors of 1945.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think they were right wing Tories at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing Section 14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has suggested that the question is whether it is fair that the community as a whole should be taxed to provide benefits for certain sections&mdash;not those who are in such need as to justify the burden. I argued in my Second Reading speech that the Minister, for political reasons, <Col N="2137" /> was giving out benefits now at the expense of workers who would have to bear the cost for many years to come; he was going to put the Social Insurance Fund in the red deliberately so that he might get a political benefit from it.  That is what I argued.  It had nothing to do with insurance.  The first time that insurance was introduced into any scheme in this country was by the Government with which I was associated, in the Health Insurance Bill.</P>
      <P>Let me say at least that when the Minister was answering my arguments, he did not twist them.  He put a slight veneer on them but he certainly did not twist them&mdash;I want to be fair to the Minister.  There is no use in the Minister suggesting for his own purposes that the social welfare provisions in this country are not part of a more comprehensive system and there is no use in suggesting that this is something original, something never thought of before.  The fact is that the Minister, for the next year or two, is going to give out, at the expense of all the workers in this community who are in the prime of life, benefits for which he as Minister is not prepared to take responsibility.  He is not prepared to place the burden where it should rest on his colleague, the Minister for Finance, rather than on the social welfare contributors, the people who do the work of the community and indeed on their employers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The result of all this will not be &ldquo;tantamount&rdquo; to an increase in the cost of living&mdash;though indeed I blandly suggested that on the Second Reading.  It will be an increase in the cost of living.  The only result of all this heaping up of burdens will be a further round of wage increases.  I was taxed on one occasion with saying that people should get an increase in wages when the cost of living goes up. I agree that they should regardless of whether there is an increase in productivity or not.  I do not mind declaring that as one of the ideas in which I believe.  In a modern community, there should be a sufficient increase in progress all the time as to enable that to happen, but whether there is an increase in productivity or not, it is <Col N="2138" /> certain that this section is going to put up the cost of living and the result of that will inevitably be a further round of wage increases.</P>
    <P>The Minister may think it a bright idea to adopt an extremely conservative line, a line of great caution&mdash;as I have seen indeed on many occasions&mdash;a caution which was not subsequently justified.  The Minister may say that, but at the same time he cannot say that he is laying the foundations of something, when he will not in other directions build on foundations already laid for him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to delay the Seanad but the arguments carried on between the Minister and Senator O'Donovan are so lofty that I am afraid I cannot get in my rather small point.  May I put it in a different way to the Minister?  People retiring at 65 have been either fully insured or insured to a limited extent, for widows' and orphans' benefit only.  If they were insured fully they register at the employment exchange because they draw benefit and under the Bill they will, if they are married, have a benefit of 52/6d. per week or get benefit by way of disability allowance.  They get the benefit and do not have to stamp cards to maintain the cover for widows and orphans in case they die.  But if they were insured only for widows' and orphans' benefit, they do not get benefits by going to the employment exchange.  I am not advocating that they should because they have not paid for them, but instead they have to stamp their cards and pay the sum of 2/6d. a week in order to maintain their cover.  All I would ask the Minister is that he should consider this matter in his Department and if he can, by regulations, ease the burden on these people who are out of benefit and for whom, whether we like it or not, it is an expense; 2/6d. is a sizeable sum to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid this has been disposed of on Section 13. We are now on Section 14.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to keep the Seanad.  I understand there <Col N="2139" /> is a very heavy agenda and I do not think Senator O'Donovan's remarks really require an answer.  After all, I did not lay any foundations on which I cannot build and continue to build. The foundations were provided by my predecessor and I am not going to be in the position he was in when he had to discontinue work which he had started.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 15 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 16.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 16 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>As a preliminary, I want to ask the Minister what the results of his cogitations were in accordance with his promise to Deputy J.A. Costello at Column 881 of the Dáil report for 5th July, 1960.  He promised he would see what he could do and bring in an amendment in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am writing to Deputy Costello on that matter to say I have not been able to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>One of the difficulties about Section 16 is that there are two subsections (c) in it.  I would refer to Section 16 (c), 6 (c).  It seems to me that this is extremely hard on the contributors.  They must pay 48 contributions minimum a year, I take it&mdash; this is my interpretation, subject to correction, for it is a complicated matter &mdash;over a period of ten years.  It seems to me that if a person were out of the system as Senator Miss Davidson mentioned or was unemployed for any period worth speaking about in the period of ten years, he would become ineligible under the scheme for the contributory pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to ask whether the Minister would not consider some more reasonable number of contributions over the period.  It is forty-eight. There is only a leeway of four per year over a period of ten years.  That seems to be a very small leeway which could quite easily be eaten up in a variety of ways.  I should like to <Col N="2140" /> know whether this subparagraph (6) (c) is not really too severe on the contributors who, having been in the system for ten years, qualify on that basis, but would have difficulty even if they had one period of unemployment, in meeting the requirements.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator does not grasp the significance of the words &ldquo;or credited to the claimant in respect of the period beginning ...&rdquo; and so on.  That means if a person draws unemployment benefit or disability benefit, he is credited for the period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 17 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 18 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have read the section carefully and I have read the Dáil debates on the section and I am still somewhat puzzled and uneasy as to what is intended.  I am particularly concerned with the question of redundancy.  In my trade union capacity, I have experience of the arrangements in operation in C.I.E. and I am particularly concerned to know that there is no intention in this section of making regulations which would have a retrospective effect.  The unions and the Board of C.I.E. in dealing with the problem have agreements relating to redundancy and people have gone out on compensation, as provided under the 1958 Transport Act, and they have gone out knowing what their entitlement is. It would be disastrous if there were any doubt or any question now that the Minister, or the Minister for Transport and Power, might, by regulations under this section, in effect diminish the entitlement under the 1958 Act or the expectation of the compensation on which they went out on redundancy.  That redundancy, of course, is reduced at a certain age, 65, but they have gone out knowing their entitlement and I should like to have an assurance from the Minister that there is no intention of making regulations <Col N="2141" /> which would diminish their expectation of what their compensation would be at 65 or indeed at 70.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not in a position to give any undertaking in respect of any other Minister whose responsibility may lie in respect of any scheme outside that which I shall be administering under the Bill.  The sole purpose of this section is to enable existing schemes to be fitted into this insurance scheme.  It may happen that in schemes which provide for redundancy, the people may wish, having regard to the fact that these schemes are on a contributory basis, to vary the redundancy conditions and at the same time, vary the contributions. Nothing will be done to affect the position of people already enjoying benefits under superannuation schemes.</P>
      <P>I think I can say for my colleagues, as I would say for myself, that in so far as there is any person who may be enjoying the benefits of any of the existing schemes, whether he is benefiting under redundancy conditions or not, his position will not be affected. It may happen however that in relation to schemes which provide for redundancy, where agreement has been substantially reached but is not unanimous, then, by regulation, the Minister may determine a certain issue in order that an <i>impasse</i> may be resolved, but it is not the intention, as I said already, and I wish to repeat it, to affect the position of any person already enjoying benefits under any of the superannuation schemes.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 19 to 21, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 22.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 22 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand from reading the Minister's statement in the Dáil on this section that there is a precedent for it.  He referred to a section in the Widows' and Orphans' Pensions Act, 1935.  I must say that this kind of section in legislation is <Col N="2142" /> obviously extremely objectionable.  The first part of the subsection reads:&mdash;</P>
      <P>If in any respect any difficulty arises in bringing into operation this Act or any amendment of the Acts or the Old Age Pensions Acts, 1908 to 1959, effected by this Act, the Minister may, subject to the sanction of the Minister for Finance, by order do anything which appears to be necessary or expedient for bringing this Act into operation, and any such order may modify the provisions of this Act so far as may appear necessary or expedient for carrying the order into effect.</P>
      <P>As we all know, there is in existence the Statutory Instruments Committee, which is a very excellent committee from the point of view of the Legislature, from the point of view of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  But this kind of blanket provision that the Minister may by Order modify the provisions of the Act seems to me to be extremely objectionable.  What it means is that we are handing over to the Executive part of the machinery of Government, powers which, strictly speaking, belong to the Legislature.  If any difficulty arises in bringing the Act into operation or in implementing the Act, the obvious thing would be to bring in an amending Act.  There is no great difficulty in bringing a short amending Act before both Houses and as far as effectiveness is concerned, it would be put through just as quickly as would an Order which has to go through the Statutory Instruments Committee and be tabled in both Houses.  This kind of provision makes the work of the Committee extremely difficult and I see no reason for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In reply to Deputy Corish in the Dáil, the Minister stated that there is no question of reducing any benefit.  I take it that perhaps Deputy Corish's question arose from the phrase &ldquo;subject to the sanction of the Minister for Finance&rdquo;.  The Minister for Finance might not be inclined to sanction anything which he might have to pay out of his own purse, but he might be inclined to sanction something which might have to be paid out of somebody else's purse.  I imagine, on the other hand, that the words &ldquo;subject <Col N="2143" /> to the sanction of the Minister for Finance&rdquo; would suggest an increase of some sort by association with that phrase in other Acts.  On the whole, this kind of section in legislation is objectionable and should not be resorted to by the members of the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Really Senator O'Donovan laid great stress upon the contents of the provisions of subsection (1) of the section but he glided very quickly over subsection (2) which leaves the final powers in this matter in the hands of either House of the Oireachtas&mdash;not both Houses, but either House.</P>
      <P>The Senator suggested that the laying of the Order before the House, and taking the steps necessary to secure its annulment, is a cumbrous procedure. He suggested that we should substitute for that the whole machinery whereby the law is fundamentally altered, that we should go through the solemn procedure of putting down a Bill for First Reading in either House, getting leave to have it printed, proceed to debate the principle of the Bill on Second Stage some days later perhaps, then go on to Committee Stage, Report Stage, and then to Fifth Stage, and when those five stages have been gone through in one House to proceed to go through four Stages in the other House.</P>
      <P>I think the procedure which is laid down here is simple.  It gives either House complete control over the actions of the Minister for Social Welfare, who himself, as Senator O'Donovan pointed out, is subject to a degree of control by his colleague, the Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>For the first time this evening the Minister sounded really happy on this Section.  He was able to detail the roundabout procedure that has to be implemented to pass a Bill through both Houses of the Oireachtas.  The Minister knows well that many Bills have been passed through both Houses of the Oireachtas in ten minutes.  It is not only with regard to this section, but in many aspects of our affairs, that this type of question arises.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2144" /> The Minister contented himself with saying that one procedure is easier than the other.  He even mentioned the printing of a Bill.  The fact is&mdash;if I may imitate the Minister for a moment in the same happy vein&mdash;that there is a great deal more printing in an Order than in an amending Bill because in an Order there are successions of &ldquo;whereas&rdquo; and so forth.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We could drop those, if it would please the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister could do that also, I suspect, without affecting it legally.  At any rate, that is the way it is done.  In fact, there is a great deal more printing in an Order than in an amending Bill.  There is no doubt that this kind of provision is objectionable.  There is no question about that.  It is eluding and sidetracking the Legislature.  We all know that an Order would be 21 days with both Houses, etc., but we also know that the number of occasions on which these Orders are queried is very few.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support very strongly the case made by Senator O'Donovan, because this is one other step towards government by Order which is lowering the status of both Houses.  We all know that a short amending Bill could be put through very rapidly and, in fact, we know to our cost also that in the discussion, on such a Bill, we are restricted very narrowly to what is contained in the amending Bill, and have not the power to refer to the Act which is being amended, or make suggestions for other amendments we might feel were necessary.  The Government know they can rely on a majority in both Houses and, therefore, they know that an Order cannot be rescinded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We all know that the Government could get an amending Bill through the House, if they wished.  On an amending Bill the Government have to explain precisely why the change is necessary, and in the ensuing debate, points may emerge which might even cause the Government to change their mind.  When an Order is laid on the Table, it is not queried usually because there is not a debate which might show the real purpose behind the Order, or raise unsuspected points about the <Col N="2145" /> Order that might not be apparent at first sight.</P>
    <P>I should like to protest against this inroad into the functions of the Legislature, and if this type of thing persists, we shall have no option but to challenge every Order laid before the House and in doing that, we shall fulfil our function as a legislative assembly and ensure that reasons will be given why Orders are necessary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>For the life of me, I cannot see any justification for the opposition levelled at these two subsections, especially subsection (2). In my opinion, it is usual in measures of this kind, where Orders have to be made, to have copies of those Orders laid on the Table of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  I think that should be acceptable to any reasonable person. We have also the Committee on Statutory Orders and Instruments functioning, and it is their duty&mdash;and they meet for that purpose&mdash;to examine all the Orders that are laid on the Table of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  I do not see what objection there can be to these subsections.</P>
      <P>Subsection 3 of the section provides:&mdash;</P>
      <P>No order may be made under this section after the expiration of one year after the commencement of this section.</P>
      <P>It would be a very unusual procedure to have an amending Bill dealing with Orders and, in my opinion, there would be no justification for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>The operative word in subsection (1) of Section 22 is &ldquo;modify&rdquo;.  If an Order made under this section is to modify the provisions of an Act of Parliament, if an ordinary Order made under a certain section modifies the provisions of an Act of these Houses, I think that if there were a provision that any such Order should be brought before the House within one year as an Act or some such provision, it would be all right, but it is wrong for us to pass legislation here allowing the Government or anyone else to modify the provisions of an Act of the Oireachtas.  Possibly there would <Col N="2146" /> be great difficulty in a measure such as this which is new legislation, but it is a principle we should not give away freely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the section has to be read as a whole.  If an Order has to be made, it will not be made for frivolous reasons.  It must be assumed that a Minister who makes an Order will act responsibly and in accordance with the terms of the section which gives him the power.</P>
      <P>This section starts with a proviso which governs it as a whole.  The proviso is: &ldquo;If in any respect any difficulty arises in bringing into operation this Act or any amendment of the Acts or the Old Age Pensions Acts, 1908 to 1959, effected by this Act,...&rdquo; If a difficulty arises in bringing into effect this Act, which the Oireachtas has already passed and, having passed, indicates it wishes it to be brought into effect, then the Minister is given temporary power&mdash; power for a period of one year&mdash;to make an Order, subject to a certain condition, namely, that either House of the Oireachtas has the power of veto upon any Order he may make.</P>
      <P>Having regard to the complex administrative difficulties, many of which cannot ordinarily be foreseen, in bringing a new Act containing novel provisions into effect, I feel that that is the least power that might be given to the Executive and that there is no encroachment whatsoever upon the legislative power of either House of the Oireachtas.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 23 and 24 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Provisions)" RHead="Bill, 1960&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1960&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="2147" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. MacEntee) Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. MacEntee)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators will have seen the explanatory memorandum which was circulated with this Bill and which sets out its provisions in some detail. I propose therefore to make no more than a brief reference to those provisions which need some additional explanation.</P>
      <P>In the first place, the Bill gives effect to the increases announced in the Budget. It provides for additional payments of 1/- per week in respect of all old age pensions and blind pensions. Rates of unemployment assistance are also being increased by 1/- a week for applicants themselves, 1/- a week for adult dependants and 1/- a week for each child dependant.  The extra shilling will be paid for every dependant child and not only for the first two qualified children to whom payments are confined at present.</P>
      <P>A man with a wife and two children will qualify for an increase of 4/- a week while a man with a wife and six children, who at present receives the same amount as a man with a wife and two children, will now qualify for an increase of 8/- a week.  For widows with non-contributory pensions the Bill grants an increase of 1/- a week for the widow herself, plus an increase of 1/- for the first and second qualified children.  Widows with three or more children will receive an additional 3/6d. for each child in excess of two. Thus a widow with four children will receive a weekly increase of 10/-. Orphans' non-contributory pensions are also being raised by approximately 50 per cent.  All the increases mentioned will come into effect on 1st August next.</P>
      <P>The Bill makes a number of other important changes in the law relating to old age pensions, widows' pensions and unemployment assistance.  One of these.  Section 6, affects old age pensioners who go to live in Northern Ireland.  At present payment of their old age pensions must be suspended when they cross the Border.  They cannot have their pensions restored unless they come back here and they cannot qualify for assistance under Northern Ireland legislation until they have lived there for at least five years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2148" /> This Bill will allow such people, provided, of course, they continue to satisfy the other conditions, to get their pensions in the North for five years, or until they are granted an old age pension or national assistance under Northern Ireland legislation. This pension would, of course, be paid directly to the pensioner, whether he is living in his own dwelling or in a home for the aged and infirm.  Pensioners who have already gone there and who have been less than five years in the North, will be able to have their pensions restored to them, if they have not already got a pension or assistance in the North.</P>
    <P>I am also repealing the provision in the Old Age Pensions Acts whereby a person who is detained in a Mental Hospital is debarred from receiving old age pension.  The effect of the repeal is that such persons will be no longer ineligible for old age pension, as they have been up to this. It is necessary to provide at the same time, however, for the appropriation of the pension, by the authority responsible for the maintenance of the pensioner in such cases, as a contribution towards his maintenance and upkeep. This, of course, will have an appreciable effect on the demands which the Mental Hospitals will make on the various health authorities.  Those who would be capable of deriving some benefit, however, will be able to obtain, at the discretion of the Resident Medical Superintendent, up to 10/- a week towards such things as extra comforts.</P>
    <P>The period within which payment of an old age pension may be obtained is being altered.  Under the law as it stands, pension orders which are not cashed within three months go out of date.  Many old people are unaware of this fact and sometimes fail to cash their orders before the three months have expired.  If payment has to be refused in this type of case it can often lead to definite hardship.  The Bill gives the Minister power, therefore, to extend the time within which payment on account of an old age pension may be made, up to six months, which is the period already in operation for widows' pensions and for children's allowances.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2149" /> Subsection (3) of Section 3 of the Old Age Pensions Act 1908 is being repealed.  This subsection, which does not seem ever to have operated, empowers a court to disqualify a convicted person over the age of 60 and liable to have a detention order made against him under the Inebriates Act, 1898, from receiving old age pension for a period of up to ten years.</P>
    <P>Section 13 of the Bill makes a change in favour of widowed working mothers, who are claiming or receiving non-contributory pensions.  Earnings of a widow from insurable or excepted employment under the First Schedule to the Social Welfare Act, 1952, up to a limit of £39 for each qualified child of the widow, may, when this provision becomes law, be disregarded when assessing her means.</P>
    <P>Some other concessions affecting the assessment of means concern those in receipt of allowances or pensions under the Army Pensions Acts and Military Service Pensions Acts.  These are dealt with in Section 10.  They also apply to those in receipt of Connaught Rangers' Pensions.  Under the Social Welfare Act, 1952, the first £80 of each of the first two types of pension which I have mentioned is already disregarded in calculating means for old age and widows' pension purposes.  The present Bill will extend this disregard to those claiming or receiving unemployment assistance, and, in addition, will apply the disregard of Connaught Rangers' pensions for all purposes.</P>
    <P>Section 13 also provides for the disregard of the maintenance allowances payable to disabled persons under Section 50 of the Health Act, 1953, and puts them on the same footing as the allowances of a somewhat similar nature payable under Section 44 of the Health Act, 1947.  This is being done by adding them to the relevant portion of the Seventh Schedule to the Social Welfare Act, 1952, and thus enabling them to be excluded from reckoning as means in old age and widows' pension cases.</P>
    <P>Old age pensioners who are also receiving a statutory pension from some other source will benefit from Section 9.  It sometimes happens under existing legislation that a small increase <Col N="2150" /> in another pension being received by an old age pensioner can cause a much greater decrease in the old age pension, the net result being that the pensioner's total income is actually reduced.  The necessary provision to avoid this is made in Section 9.</P>
    <P>Section 11 of the Bill is intended to benefit people who have endured a long spell of unemployment and relates to what is known as the three days waiting period which an unemployed person must serve before he can receive the benefit or assistance he is seeking.  During that period of three days he cannot receive either benefit or assistance.  If he remains unemployed long enough to exhaust his title to unemployment benefit and then looks for unemployment assistance he must, as the law stands, serve a further three waiting days, during which he can get neither benefit nor assistance.  This latter requirement is a definite hardship on people who have the misfortune to be unemployed for a long period and the section to which I have referred will abolish this waiting period.</P>
    <P>One of the contribution conditions for maternity allowances is that not less than 26 employment contributions have been paid before the relevant date&mdash;that is the date of commencement of the sixth week before the end of the expected week of confinement. If the contributions due in respect of insurable employment before that date have not been paid, the insured woman cannot receive any maternity allowance, even though the contributions may have been paid within a short time after the relevant time.  The amendment which is being made by Section 15 of this Bill will enable such allowances to be paid in future from the date on which the contributions are paid.</P>
    <P>The Bill contains some provisions designed to clarify the law on one or two points relating to the insurable classes, about which some doubts have arisen as a result of recent court decisions.  The amendments concern some classes of civil servants and student and trainee nurses and midwives. Civil Servants of the State, as, for instance, a solicitor employed <Col N="2151" /> in the State Solicitor's office, as distinct from Civil Servants of the Government, and certain student and trainee nurses and midwives are being added to the employments scheduled as insurable under the Social Welfare Acts.</P>
    <P>Every year large sums of money are lost to the State as a result of fraudulent claims to old age pensions and false statements regarding means. Accordingly, the Bill includes some provisions, Sections 16 to 22 inclusive, which aim to reduce, as much as possible, irregular payments of old age pensions.  The provisions in question are intended to deter people from making fraudulent claims, and giving false information, in order to get pensions to which they are not entitled.  Where people have succeeded in getting such pension money in these circumstances, the Bill will facilitate recovery of the money from them or from their personal representatives.  With a few exceptions the provisions and penalties are not new, but are to be found already in operation in relation to other social welfare services.  In some respects the old age pensions code differs from other social welfare services, and differs to the disadvantage of the State, that is, of the taxpayer, where proceedings for the recovery of money overpaid are concerned.  The amendments which this Bill proposes to the law will bring the old age pension code into line with the other services in that respect.  Among the new provisions is the requirement obliging the personal representative of a deceased pensioner, before distributing an estate, to give not less than three months' notice in writing of his intention to distribute the assets and making him financially liable if he fails to do so.  Another is the establishment of a legal presumption that once a pension is proved to have been awarded and payment made during any period, the pensioner shall be deemed, in the absence of any evidence to the contrary, to have received payment from the date of the award.  These provisions will be reinforced by Section 17 which authorises the suspension of pension where a pensioner refuses or fails to furnish information or produce <Col N="2152" /> books or documents, reasonably required to establish his continued entitlement to pension and by new provisions requiring the personal representative of a deceased pensioner, under penalty, to furnish similar information regarding the pensioner.</P>
    <P>The amendment being made by Section 12 of the Bill arises out of the need to adjust, on a legal basis, a claim in respect of overpayment by a local authority of its contribution towards the cost of unemployment assistance in its area under Section 26 of the Unemployment Assistance Act, 1933.  Under that Act local authorities in areas where the higher rates of unemployment assistance are payable are required to pay to the Minister in each financial year as a contribution to the cost of Unemployment Assistance certain sums levied on the rateable valuation of their areas.  For the purpose of determining the rateable valuations certificates are obtained annually from the Commissioner of Valuation.  Under the existing law the Commissioner has no power to amend any certificates furnished by him or to issue a revised certificate.  Previously, the Commissioner had included the valuation of certain small dwellings in the certificates furnished by him.  The local authorities concerned held that this was wrong and their view was upheld by legal opinion.</P>
    <P>Since legal opinion was obtained to the effect that the relevant legislation did not give the Commissioner power to amend his certificates the over-payments were adjusted by allowing the local authorities concerned credit in subsequent years in respect of the amounts over-contributed.  Both the Comptroller and Auditor-General and the Public Accounts Committee, however, considered this procedure and concluded that it was unsatisfactory and the Committee expressed the view that amending legislation should be introduced when the opportunity offered. It happens that further application for a refund of amounts erroneously contributed by a local authority in respect of the valuation of small dwellings was recently received, and the present amendment will enable the Commissioner <Col N="2153" /> of Valuation to issue a revised certificate as to rateable value where the facts so warrant and thus enable this and any other cases which may arise to be dealt with on a legal basis.</P>
    <P>Roughly a quarter of a million people including old and blind persons, widows and their dependent children, the unemployed and their dependants, stand to benefit by this Bill.  On the basis of present numbers, the cost in a full year of the increases announced in the Budget Statement and provided for in this Bill is estimated at approximately £657,000. Other increases and concessions will amount to £212,000 in a full year. The figures I have quoted add up to a yearly total, of £869,000 which of course is additional to the £21,354,000 originally framed as the Estimate for Social Assistance requirements for the current year.</P>
    <P>I should, perhaps, give a word or two of explanation in connection with the cost of the proposal regarding payment of old age pensions in respect of persons detained in mental hospitals. This will, it is estimated, add about £153,000 to the cost of old age pensions. The Exchequer provides 50 per cent. of the cost of mental hospital services and if the pension were being fully appropriated in all cases the net cost to the Exchequer of this repeal would consequently be only half the figure I gave, that is, £76,500.</P>
    <P>Since it is being provided that up to 10/- a week may be obtained by the patient, if he is fit to make use of it, the net cost to the Exchequer of repealing this particular disqualification will be substantially more than £76,500.  In fact, it may be over £100,000, depending on the extent, which there is no means of estimating, to which patients will he found able to avail themselves of the provision enabling them to get up to 10/- of the pension for their own use.  However, the repeal is a long overdue reform which I am happy to be able to provide for in this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not call this Bill anything but a miserable measure.  It is one of those pieces of legislation that has to be introduced as a result of the most unwise policy of the Government <Col N="2154" /> some years ago in removing the food subsidies which well nigh caused dislocation for several years in the economy. It was the principal factor in these rounds of wage increases that have taken place since the Government came into office.</P>
      <P>They have now decided, as a compensation to the weaker sections of the community, the old age pensioners and blind pensioners, to give them an increase of 1/- a week.  In fact, the little bit they have tried to do for that section of the community will be seen through, even by the blind.  It is a miserable effort.</P>
      <P>If there is any section of the community that deserves to have the cost of living kept down, it is old age pensioners and the blind pensioners.  In fact, anyone who is prepared to save for the future deserves consideration from the Government charged with the responsibility of carrying on the affairs of State.  I hope that even at this eleventh hour the Government will see the folly they engaged in a few years ago when they removed the £11 million subsidy and did not reduce taxation after wasting that £11 million.</P>
      <P>To-day they talk about a buoyant economy but the small farmers, the old age pensioners, the blind pensioners and all these sections of the community will not be a bit impressed by this talk of an increase in industrial exports when many of the small farmers who, when they get old, would be entitled to enjoy an old age pension, are just locking up the doors and leaving the west of Ireland.  That in large measure is caused by the inability of the Government to approach the cost of living in a realistic way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If there is anything worth while at all in the entire Bill, it is the suggestion to pay family allowances for all children rather than to pay them after the first two children.  I presume we have nothing else to do but to pass the Bill but I think it is desirable at least to put on the records of the House the fact that we disapprove of this type of parsimonious dealing with a subject of this nature&mdash;a sort of make-shift legislation caused by policies that were in their conception immature and <Col N="2155" /> which caused a great deal of damage to this economy.  If anything is necessary in Ireland more than in any other country, it is that it should be a cheap country to live in.</P>
    <P>The Government have done more to make this a dear country than any other Government we had in this country.  The 1/- increase for old age pensioners and blind pensioners is a sort of sop thrown out to those people for the depreciation in the value of the pension they had heretofore.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrady2" hpid="Mr. Brady Mr. Brady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
      <P>I am rather amused to hear Senator Burke describing this measure as a miserable contribution. Of course, that is nothing at all unusual coming from that side of the House. They will tell you at one time that taxation is going up, that the cost of living and everything else is going up. They will also tell you that the people are being reduced almost to a terrible plight to-day.</P>
      <P>I am probably the oldest administrator in the House.  Even if it were only for one section in the Bill I should rise to congratulate the Minister. I refer to the section concerning the mental hospitals.  I have been a member of the mental hospital committee in Ennis for 32 years now.  As a matter of fact, I think I made a suggestion on a few occasions in regard to the number of people in the hospital.  It is surprising the number of old people who are in the mental hospital, but the reason the number of people there is so high is that at the present time, with modern treatments, you have admissions and discharges, but on the other hand you have poor people who are there and who have to remain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There have been wonderful changes &mdash;I could almost call them revolutions &mdash;in mental treatment since I first became a member of a mental hospital board.  At that time it was regarded as a place of detention where people would scarcely go to see their relatives.  They would ignore them altogether. But at the present time the mental hospital is regarded as any other hospital and thanks be to God for <Col N="2156" /> that advance, in which medical science has played a big part.</P>
    <P>We have 700 patients in Ennis District Hospital and we have passed. resolutions on the question: why should they not get the old age pension? If there were nothing in the Bill to commend it but this section, I would feel bound in duty to stand up and offer congratulations to the Minister.  These people now are being very well looked after in mental hospitals. They have all sorts of amusements, recreations, occupational therapy and all the rest.  Next year will be a big year.  It will be the mental hospital jubilee year and we in Clare look forward to occupying a very high place.  We hope to get great credit for the strides we have made from people in high places.</P>
    <P>Ours is the first hospital in the State where certain drugs are being tried out.  If they live up to anything like the results they are supposed to give, it will mean a big revolution in mental treatment.  The patients have table tennis, tennis and football pitches, as compared with the conditions that obtained in those places 30 years ago when people were kept in Ennis County Home.  In consequence of the amalgamation and the great grants which came from the Sweep, there have been great changes.  We have an admission, unit which is in itself a hospital.  Patients are received there and segregated.  They do not mix with the other patients.  They get a reasonable chance of recovery before they mix with the others.</P>
    <P>I want to thank the Minister for this.  Although the patients have been well treated without any pension, the old age pension will give them great comforts like tobacco or cigarettes for male or female patients.  We have a very grave and serious duty to those people.  They are people who have been mentally afflicted by the Lord and are not able to look after themselves, and we have a duty to see that they get anything that will help them, mitigate their affliction, confer comforts on them or hasten the day of their recovery.  We should co-operate in every way to see that such plans are brought to fruition as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2157" /> I happen to know a lot about the other sections, too, in my various capacities.  Senator Burke sneers and jibes, of course, at this &ldquo;miserable pittance&rdquo;, but what did they give when they were in office?</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Value for money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrady2" hpid="Mr. Brady Mr. Brady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a very pertinent question.  When they wanted to get economies, the only person they could swoop on was the man with 10/- a week and he had to contribute 10 per cent. to ease the terrible economic pressure, but now they have the effrontery to get up and talk about &ldquo;a miserable pittance&rdquo;.  Anyone would imagine that they were great philanthropists when they were in office, that they were dishing out money for this, that and everything else, that this country was Utopia when they were in office, that they were increasing all sorts of benefits and at the same time, reducing taxation.  Such tripe!  In my experience, I never listened to such tripe because there is no logic of any kind there and it is very far removed from facts.  Facts are facts.  We in Fianna Fáil at any rate take pride in everything that has been done since Fianna Fáil became the Government.  The first consideration at all times was for the poor and I think the present Taoiseach will rank as one of the greatest social reformers ever in this country.</P>
      <P>The cheap jibes of Senator Burke are nothing unusual.  That is the introduction to nearly every opposition to a Bill presented in this House.  I want to thank the Minister for this further measure, which is designed to improve the lot of the poorer sections of the community.  I do not regard anything that runs to the sum of £860,000 as anything that warrants cheap jibes such as those made about this by the Opposition.  Again, I thank the Minister, and thank him very sincerely, for all the provisions in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill, as far as it goes.  It does clear up a very great number of small matters&mdash;at considerable expense.  There are small matters about which I am sure Senators and Deputies have had complaints. Some seem unfair treatment like <Col N="2158" /> certain means being taken into account which people felt should not have been taken into account.  Another matter, as Senator Brady says, is the 10/- for inmates of mental hospitals, if they are able to avail of it.  With modern ideas coming into force comparatively recently regarding the treatment and freedom of those patients, this is a very great step forward and I am sure that R.M.O.s in these hospitals who are interested in their patients&mdash; and I think all of them are&mdash;will at least appreciate that step.</P>
      <P>The Minister may not be able to do very much about this now but there is one trouble I have met with several times: when a widow or orphan gets a grant from a charitable society or an orphan society, I understand that is taken into account in assessing means, if it is a regular grant.  If that is so, and I think it is still, it is rather despicable that we should relieve the State of a certain amount of liability by reason of money collected or given by a charitable society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is one other point which I would ask the Minister to consider, if not now, then at some future date.  It is the case of the man in receipt of unemployment benefit who is offered a day's or two days' employment. The present position is that he cannot take that employment because if he does, he loses his week's money.  I wonder could some system be arranged whereby a man could accept one or two days' employment by notifying the exchange in the morning that he intended to do so and that thereby his money would be reduced by only a proportion and he would not lose the whole week's money?  Could the employment exchange not work out some system whereby if I were looking for extra men for harvesting or haymaking on fine days, I could go to a man and ask him to come to me for one or two days?  The present position of that man is that he will say: &ldquo;If I do, I will lose that week's money but if you can guarantee me the week, I might go.&rdquo; I cannot guarantee the weather and therefore I cannot guarantee him his week's pay.  In the country, we find that if a man takes a casual day's work, he does so illegally and he <Col N="2159" /> is working at the back of a ditch and hoping that the pensions officer will not appear at the other side because then he will lose his assistance and it might be some time before he can get it back again.</P>
    <P>I feel sorry for those men that they cannot earn a few more shillings and it would be a good thing if some regulation could be made whereby they could do casual work, provided they notified the employment exchange by telephone or by wire.  I welcome a great many of the provisions in the Bill, which I regard as a step in the right direction.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one section of the Bill which I should like especially to commend.  That is Section 6 which enables a person in receipt of a pension to retain that pension for five years after he or she crosses the Border to Northern Ireland. There have been cases of genuine hardship which this section will remove, and I congratulate the Minister on meeting this hardship in this way.  I should just like to ask&mdash;why five years?  Is it all we can afford, or is it that after five years that person may qualify for a pension in Northern Ireland?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>If the second alternative is the answer, then that is entirely satisfactory.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I have just a few words to say on this Bill and I must say that Senator Burke provoked me into making these few remarks. He described the Bill as a miserable one.  I do not think it deserves that description.  It is always right when dealing with measures of this sort to deal with them in perspective and we are entitled to examine the position as it has been since the present Minister for Social Welfare took over. Since he took charge of the Department of Social Welfare, this is the third increase which has been given to old age pensioners, amounting in all to 4/6d.  After all, an increase of 4/6d. in three years is not too bad and I venture to say that if old <Col N="2160" /> age pensioners received an increase of 4/6d. a week every three years, they would not be doing too badly.  It is more than they got during the previous three years when those who criticise the Bill and describe it as a miserable one had some authority to grant increases to these old age pensioners.</P>
      <P>There is more in the Bill than the granting of increases to old age pensioners. We also have the other categories, the recipients of unemployment assistance and the recipients of widows' non-contributory pensions, whose pensions are being increased as well. Added to that, additional allowances are being given in respect of the children of these people so that, in all, this Bill should not be regarded as an ungenerous one.  I am very glad the Minister has granted the same concession to recipients of unemployment assistance as that granted to old age pensioners <i>vis-a-vis</i> military service pensions and so on, and that the first £80 of a military service pension will be exempted from calculation for the purpose of unemployment assistance.</P>
      <P>I did not think that such matters as the cost of living and the abolition of the food subsidies would be introduced here in connection with this Bill.  I do not want to deal with them at this hour of the night&mdash;if I did I would have a lot to say indeed&mdash;but I am coming to the statement again that these are miserable provisions. The sum of £869,000 is no small amount and it is surprising to find Senator Burke advocating an increase when a colleague of his, in connection with another Bill which the House has passed, described a provision for other categories of these people as a brake on industry.  If we are to grant more to these people, will that be described as a burden on industry?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I was talking about the £11 millions which were wasted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister is doing fairly well in this Bill and if he continues to travel in the same direction as he is going and if an increase of 4/6d. a week is given to these people every three years, it will not be a bad thing at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2161" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr MacEntee Mr MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ó Ciosáin said something which I think it was necessary to say, that is, that the Fine Gael Party in the Seanad seem to be strangely at odds with themselves.  At one moment they are protesting that the cost is going to be a very heavy imposition on industry and then the next moment they are describing this Bill as a miserable one.  I am not going to go back over their sorry record in regard to social assistance and social insurance schemes, but I well remember the fate which befell the Social Welfare Bill of 1950 and the attitude which they then took up in regard to a proposal to increase old age pensions.</P>
      <P>The House will remember that the Social Welfare Bill, 1950, was brought in with a great flourish of trumpets. It was preceded by a White Paper and not only was it preceded by a White Paper but something which was unprecedented in the history of this State happened.  A number of civil servants were sent down to address political meetings throughout the country in order to proclaim to the people the benefits which the Bill would confer on them.  The Bill of course did not become law because the Coalition broke up.  The Coalition Government broke up for a number of reasons.  One of those reasons, I think, was that one element in the Coalition wished to give effect to the demands which had been made in the House by its own supporters that the old age pensions should be increased, and another element&mdash;represented in this House by Senator Burke and Senator O'Donovan &mdash;opposed that demand and the consequence was, as I have said, that the Coalition broke up.  We did not have a Social Welfare Bill of 1950, and it was left to the Fianna Fáil Government which succeeded them to pass the Social Welfare Bill of 1952, and to increase old age pensions in 1951 by 2/6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The next increase in old age pensions took place under the Fianna Fáil Government in 1952, when, following the increase of 2/6 which was given in 1951, the pensions were further increased to 21/6, and in July, 1955, an increase of 2/6 was given by the then Coalition Government.  Nothing further <Col N="2162" /> was done for the old age pensioners until the Fianna Fáil Government, in 1957, increased the pension by 1/-, and we increased it further last year by 2/6.  Now we are coming forward again with the proposals in this Bill to increase it by a further 1/- making, in three successive years, three increases, totalling 4/6.</P>
    <P>Having listened to Senator Burke in this House, contrast that with the record of those who are full of concern and solicitude for the plight of the old age pensioners.  Contrast it with the record of both Coalitions&mdash; the first Coalition and the second&mdash; and it will be found that our record compares very favourably indeed with theirs.</P>
    <P>There is no use in talking about this Bill in terms of contempt.  The two Bills which have been before the House this afternoon&mdash;the Bill relating to the social insurance side of the social welfare code, and this Bill which relates to the social assistance side of the same code&mdash;represent an increased expenditure of £1,200,000 upon social welfare schemes in a full year.  That is not an inconsiderable sum.  It certainly is not an inconsiderable sum to the Minister for Finance, who, as I have said speaking on the previous Bill, has to go to the taxpaying public and collect it from them.  Certainly having regard to our general resources, it is a very substantial and significant contribution to make to social welfare in a single year, apart from the increase which arises in the normal way upon the Social Welfare Estimates themselves as a consequence of the provisions of the 1952 Act and the other Acts passed subsequently.</P>
    <P>I was amused when I heard Senator Burke advocating the return of the food subsidies.  That would mean, of course, the imposition of a further £15,000,000&mdash;not less than £15,000,000 and probably nearly £20,000,000&mdash; having regard to today's prices, upon the taxpayer.  It would mean an increase of not less than 20 per cent., in round figures, on the existing tax rates, and 20 per cent., in round figures, on the amount of revenue which is extracted today by the Minister for Finance. That would appear to be the new Fine Gael programme so the taxpayers <Col N="2163" /> had better look out.  If they vote at the next general election for a Fine Gael Government, they will be voting to increase the load upon their backs by no less than 20 per cent.</P>
    <P>How would we raise £20,000,000? An increase of 5/- in the £1 on income tax might do it, provided we did not in that way strangle the goose that lays the golden eggs.  I do not know what it would mean to the price of the pint&mdash;and we remember how solicitous people were during the 1948 general election about the price of the pint&mdash;or what it would mean in terms of the price of petrol or of cigarettes.</P>
    <P>There is something else which I think is equally relevant to the speech Senator Burke made.  I remember in 1952 I was responsible, I may say, for taking steps towards the abolition of the food subsidies, a measure which was designed to put the remuneration of our working people on a realistic basis.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>And reduce taxation by £11,000,000&mdash;and it did not do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>It did not reduce taxation by £11,000,000.  On the contrary, in order to close the gap that had been left by my predecessor in the first Coalition Government, I had to increase taxation very substantially, even though I had, at the same time, to reduce the food subsidies by £9,000,000.  I remember in the debate on the 1952 Budget, Deputy Dr. Browne put a question to the leaders of the Fine Gael Party, then on the Front Bench, asking them, if they were returned to power, would they restore the food subsidies.  The answer which he got&mdash;I shall not say it was a blunt &ldquo;No&rdquo; because the Fine Gael people could not bring themselves to give a direct answer to any question &mdash;left no doubt in the minds of any person listening that one thing the Fine Gael people were determined not to do was to reintroduce that vicious system of food subsidies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder would the Minister restore the House to the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2164" />
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps we can hear the Minister to-morrow on the Appropriation Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>One criticism which Senator Burke directed against this Bill was that it would not be necessary to bring it in if we had not abolished the food subsidies.  I want to point out that, after all, it is quite inconsistent for the Senator here, where he has, in fact, very little financial responsibility, to suggest that if the Fine Gael Party got back into power, they would restore the food subsidies.  That question might be debated elsewhere on another occasion.</P>
      <P>Senator Cole asked one or two questions with which I might perhaps deal.  He asked whether, when a widow or orphan gets a grant from a charitable society, the amount of the grant is taken into account when assessing means for the purpose of the non-contributory widow's or orphan's pension.  The first £52 of any <i>ex gratia</i> payment is not taken into account, but if the amount exceeds £52, the excess is then taken into account.  That is the usual sort of provision in relation to all these social assistance schemes.  In relation to military service pensions.  Army pensions, and so on, the first £80 is not taken into account.  Where it is an <i>ex gratia</i> grant, the first £52 is not taken into account.</P>
      <P>There was a reference to a person casually employed for a day or two. It was asked whether, in all cases, such a person would lose his entitlement to benefit.  I should require more precise details about the position of the person concerned.  We have to start off with the condition that in respect of the first three days a person becomes unemployed, if he happens to be in the insurable category, he does not receive anything.  If he continues to be unemployed, then, provided he is not employed for more than three days in six, if they happen to be consecutive days, he does not lose his entitlement but he will not get benefit in respect of the three days he works.  I think that is the general position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If the Senator would be good enough to give me a more precise note of <Col N="2165" /> what he has in mind, I shall look into it and see if something can be done to deal with the case of a person who becomes casually employed for a day or two during a busy harvest period. However, if I were able to make any concessions of that sort, they would have to be very carefully safeguarded. It might suffice if the person gave notice to the exchange, or something like that, but I should not like to say so.  In the case of people remote from exchanges, they might have to go to the Garda barracks and so on.  I do not know what the position would be. If the Senator would let me have more precise particulars of the case he has in mind, I shall see what we can do in regard to it.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill considered in Committee.</P>
    <P>Sections 1 to 8, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 9 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>When I read the explanatory memorandum dealing with this section, it seemed to me to be very welcome.  The section itself does not seem to be as liberal as the memorandum rather indicated.  It says the provision is made to avoid a net loss in the income of an old age pensioner which might arise consequent on an increase in a pension from another source.  The Bill, however, seems to define the sources of those pensions which will not be taken into account as affecting means.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have had experience of representing people out on pension for a very long time, the value of whose pensions had depreciated, who sought some assistance from their old employing companies.  Both the companies and we ran into the difficulty that a supplementary pension, some extra assistance, did not leave the pensioner any better off because some State assistance he might have been receiving was reduced accordingly. I think £52 is not taken into account.  We have come up against the difficulty that where an employing <Col N="2166" /> company was willing, after maybe a little persuasion, to give extra assistance to a person a long time out on pension, they found there was no point in it because if they did so it meant that the money was taken off whatever pension the person was getting from the State.  That is undesirable</P>
    <P>This Bill does not seem to go as far as was indicated in the explanatory memorandum.  It seems to be confined to persons whose pensions are provided under statute.  The pensions I am talking about would not be provided under statute.  As far as I could ascertain, they would be paid by the old employing company.  It is unfortunate that where an old employer is willing to give some extra assistance, there is no point in doing so because of the consequential reduction in the pension the person is getting from the State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The section deals only with statutory pensions.  These are pensions which are awarded and which the person cannot reject or refuse.  It deals with that hardship.  I think it is clear from the section that provision is made to avoid a net loss in an old age pensioner's income which may arise consequent on an increase in a pension from another source.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not criticising that but I am expressing regret&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure that the existing law would operate as harshly as the Senator suggests.  The first £52 would be excluded.  That is not an inconsiderable amount.  The first £52 of any pension which he might secure from a non-statutory source would be excluded and he would still be entitled to the full non-contributory pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Fifty-two pounds is very little.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 10 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 11.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 11 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>In spite of the fact that I differ in politics from the Minister, <Col N="2167" /> I want to say that we welcome very much the withdrawal of the three-day waiting period.  I have heard the point criticised at so many trade union conferences that it is a relief to find that that grievance has been removed.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 12 and 13 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 14.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 14 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Does subparagraph (a) propose to set aside a decision of the Supreme Court that civil servants are not liable for insurance contributions? Is it not rather peculiar that we should use legislation for the purpose of setting aside a decision of that sort in the court?  I should like to hear the Minister on that point.  If we are using it for that purpose, I believe it is undesirable that we should do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is surely turning the question inside out.  After all, the Oireachtas makes the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>But the Supreme Court interprets the law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The laws we make are not like the laws of the Medes and the Persians.  We can alter them, if we like.  The necessity for this section arises from the very subtle distinction the Supreme Court made between those civil servants who are servants of the State and civil servants in the service of the Government.  The remuneration was all coming from the same source, but they are in fact attached to particular offices in the State like the State Solicitor's office. It was a person employed in the State Solicitor's office who was held not to be a civil servant in the service of the Government.  That necessitates this section, in order to make it quite clear&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>To make it uniform?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2168" /> Sections 14 to 18, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 19.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 19 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know if this is a new arrangement, but it seems extraordinary to provide that the poor old age pension recipient will not alone be chased after going into the grave but his personal representative will be liable for any few shillings he may have got out of the State.  I think this is quite unjustifiable.  The personal representative might not necessarily be aware that the person for whom he was acting was in fact in receipt of an old age pension, and even if he were, it seems that he cannot do anything about distributing what little estate there might be without giving notice to the Minister, and presumably would have to wait at least three months before he could touch anything, to give the Minister plenty of time to check over the records and find if by any chance this poor person who died got anything and whether it could justifiably be included in the assets.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am not attempting to condone the action of people who might get the old age pension by false pretences. They are more to be pitied than anything else, that at that stage of their lives they should be trying to hide away a few pounds they might have and dodge and scrape to get a few shillings from the State.  The Minister has got a bit too harsh in this respect recently, and really I do not see the need for this provision.  It is quite onerous and could put the personal representative in a very invidious position. He may not even know that the person for whom he is acting had an old age pension, and if he finds out that he had, he cannot do anything until he has notified the Minister and allowed three months to elapse so that the Minister can check back.  Then if by any chance he was not notified the Minister, because he did not know that it was necessary and if it is subsequently found that the Minister can claim anything against the estate, the personal representative is, by the last few words of this section, <Col N="2169" /> made personally liable to the Minister. That would make any of us think twice about acting as personal representative for anybody, if by a section stuck in a Bill like this, we can be personally liable for any few shillings a person may have got in error from the Minister by way of old age pension.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe this section is onerous, but I was rather interested that Senator Murphy raised it because he spoke very strongly in favour of the continuation of the most rigorous form of death duties last week, and this is really a poor man's death duties. I am not in favour of the poor man's death duties, but the Senator should be a little consistent with regard to these things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrady2" hpid="Mr. Brady Mr. Brady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to give the House one experience I had&mdash;the case of a woman who was in a labourer's cottage and who applied for an increase in the old age pension.  I am a member of an old age pension committee, and she made the case that she had nothing else to live on.  What happened?  That woman died and she had over £2,000 in Scarriff bank.  She had drawn about £366 unlawfully.  All that money was going back to the United States to some friend she had over there, so the local pensions officer stepped in and collected the £366 which was due to the State.  After the other things were paid, the balance went back to the United States.  I could give the name of the person.</P>
      <P>It is only when these things occur that you see how sometimes the State can be defrauded.  I am always in favour of giving the pension to a person who is needy and deserves it. Sometimes I have found it very hard to convince pensions officers of the need in some cases; yet other people whom I consider much better off find it much easier to get the pension.  I do not know why this is so.  Then when they die and do not have time to make a will, the whole cat is out of the bag and letters of administration have to be taken out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>In this question of concealment, one of the difficulties is that the people concerned are not <Col N="2170" /> educated in how to use the money. If you take £1,000 or £2,000, the only place such a person knew to invest it in was in the bank at one and a half per cent, which brings in £30 a year. He could not live on that, and the old age pension looks big compared with it.  Such a person would not dream of investing it in something that did not appear to be as secure as the bank&mdash;say, in a loan.  One suggestion I might make is that in some future improvement the Minister would make it possible for such people who are living in rather poorer circumstances, not spending very much, who have money hidden away in the bank, to buy an annuity from the Department of Social Welfare or some other agency that would for the payment of a sum give them what they really looked for&mdash;a State guarantee of a small amount each week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrady2" hpid="Mr. Brady Mr. Brady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course I am quite prepared to state that that was an isolated case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Brady has given us an instance which he says was an isolated case.  I might say that it is not as isolated as he thinks it is.  There are quite a considerable number of people who have falsely concealed their real means, and this section is aimed only against them and at those who would benefit by that concealment. Senator Brady referred to a case of a person who died leaving £2,000.  I have known of cases where £5,000 and £6,000 was involved.  I had a case before me the other day, which is as bad, of a person who left £800.  He had enjoyed the pension for quite a substantial period and had other sources of personal income.  When we tried to recover that, we found that his legal representative was a solicitor.  They are all shrewd enough to employ a solicitor to make their wills or their representatives, knowing very well they are comfortable people, are also shrewd enough, where they die intestate, to get a solicitor to take out grants of administration for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In all those cases, before the social welfare officer in the area can get evidence that, in fact, the deceased died leaving a substantial estate behind <Col N="2171" /> her, the assets are distributed.  The only way in which we can reduce the temptation to make false statements in regard to applicants' income is to make certain they will not benefit in the end by it.  That is the purpose of this.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the Minister.  It seems to be provided for in Section 18 where the personal representative must answer the questions and must disclose all information. You seem to be going further by providing in Section 18 that when he is approached, he must disclose all the information about the assets of the person who has died.  Then you provide in case we do not check up, if by any chance the personal representative distributes the assets before three months without notifying the Minister, that personal representative is personally liable.  That seems to me to be a bit onerous.  After all, the personal representative may not be a solicitor.  He may not know, in fact, that the person at some stage drew an old age pension. I think the Minister is adequately safeguarded in Section 18 as it stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. P. Crowley Mr. P. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>In support of Senator Murphy's point, it strikes me, listening to the debate, that Senator Brady's example proves Senator Murphy's point completely.  If it is possible for the State, under existing legislation, to recover moneys, surely it should be sufficient to protect the State without writing into the Bill a specific provision that the personal representative, regardless of who he may be, will be liable to the State for the refund of the amount in question. I submit that the case quoted by Senator Brady bears out Senator Murphy's point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Crowley would be very easily convinced.  I should love to appear before the Senator if I were endeavouring to defend myself in relation to an offence under this section.  I would scarcely have any hesitation in asking the Senator to be my judge.  What, in fact, does the section require a person, to do?  It requires the personal representative to give notice before he distributes the assets.  They are not so <Col N="2172" /> innocent around the country as people think.  Most people know who is drawing an old age pension in a country area and I suppose some people even in towns and cities know which of their neighbours are drawing the old age pension.  If a solicitor gets a substantial estate to administer and knows the circumstances in which a person has been living, as they all know in relation to their clients, then there is not any very great hardship imposed on him in requiring him to give three months' notice before he distributes the assets.  That is the position. If he does not give that notice, what are we to do except make him liable for his failure to comply with the law.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 20 to 26, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>May I suggest that we should, with the agreement of the House, continue to sit until we have disposed, if possible, of the remaining items on the agenda?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree, if the House will agree.  The remaining items may be very short.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed that we should meet at 10.30 a.m. to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Will we reach item No. 9 to-night?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Business has been ordered up to item No. 9.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Telephone Capital Bill, 1960 &mdash; (Certified" RHead="Money Bill) &mdash; Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Telephone Capital Bill, 1960 &mdash;  (Certified Money Bill) &mdash;  Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Hilliard) Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Hilliard)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Hilliard)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is to provide a further £10 million to be raised as required for telephone <Col N="2173" /> development over the next five years.</P>
      <P>The last Telephone Capital Act, that of 1956, was for £6 million.  At that time, the then Minister for Posts and Telegraphs explained that he would have asked for more but that acute shortage of capital had necessitated curtailment of capital expenditure on various State services and the telephone service would have to bear its share in the general pruning.  Over the past 4 years, therefore, our job has been to use limited capital moneys to the best advantage and I think it can be fairly claimed that we have done so.</P>
      <P>Since 1st January, 1956, over 47,700 exchange lines and some 60,000 telephone stations have been provided and the number of telephones is now over 150,000; 46 new automatic exchanges have been opened including those at Limerick, Galway, Sligo, Mullingar and Naas; 582 exchanges were extended; 261 telephone kiosks have been erected; and the trunk network has been increased by over 37,000 circuit miles.  The total number of telephone calls handled increased from 105.7 million in 1956 to 132 million last year. Continuous service has been introduced at 101 exchanges where service was formerly restricted and the hours of service at 151 other small exchanges have been extended.</P>
      <P>Improvements on the technical side have not been neglected in the general effort to meet day to day demands.  In addition to providing new automatic exchanges at various centres, a start has been made with the direct dialling of trunk calls by subscribers.  Formerly direct dialling was limited to local calls.  Dublin subscribers can now dial directly to all automatic exchanges within a radius of 20 miles and like facilities exist in the reverse direction. Subscribers at Cork and Athlone can dial directly to Dublin and other larger automatic exchanges.  Plans for the extension of this facility to other exchanges are well advanced.  Provision of trunk circuits by way of radio links is also being proceeded with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Last year a new system of charging for telephone calls was introduced. Broadly, it is based on the arrangement <Col N="2174" /> of exchanges in groups with a single group charging point for trunk calls and a local charge for all calls within the group.  At the same time reductions were made in certain rental charges.  These changes, which represent substantial concessions to subscribers, have resulted in a further increase in the demand for telephones. The number of applications received has been growing steadily in recent years but it has jumped significantly since these concessions were introduced. Outside Dublin it is particularly high; in the last 12 months it has exceeded the average for the previous three years by 83%.</P>
    <P>Although the rate of installation of telephones is now higher than ever there is still, because of mounting demand, a waiting list of about 4,570 applicants, but more than half of these are with the engineers for attention.</P>
    <P>The present Bill for £10 million is intended to provide for further development over the next five years approximately, but there are no specific conditions as to the period during which the money is to be raised or spent.  It is reckoned, however, that the average yearly expenditure will run to about £2 million.  The programme proposed provides for the installation of 65,000 additional subscribers' lines and 80,000 extra telephones and for considerable improvement in the trunk network both on the longer main routes and on shorter local routes.  It has been alleged that a call to New York may be obtained in some areas more quickly than one to a neighbouring parish.  That is no doubt an exaggeration but we do intend during the period ahead to give special attention to the shorter distance routes.  The programme also provides for the conversion of more exchanges to automatic working and for the extension of subscriber trunk dialling on a wide scale.  Contracts have already been placed to provide trunk dialling at Dublin and the principal provincial automatic exchanges and for the conversion of some 50 exchanges to automatic working.</P>
    <P>With more capital available, schemes which had to be deferred or curtailed can now be proceeded with. <Col N="2175" /> The estimated break up of the proposed expenditure is:&mdash;</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="30*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="20*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Subscribers' installations and local under- ground schemes</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">£ 6.42 million</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Exchanges &mdash; new and extended</entry>
            <entry>2.24 million</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Trunk and junction circuits</entry>
            <entry>2.13 million</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Buildings</entry>
            <entry>.53 million</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>making a total of £11.32 million. Allowing for a carry over of a balance of approximately £0.82 million on hand on 31st March last and for some possible over estimation the amount proposed to be raised has been rounded down to £10 million.</P>
    <P>In the post-war years we have seen many changes in the life of the country.  Old ways of working are being displaced by modern methods and up-to-date techniques.  Business is now more highly competitive and a speedy communication service is essential for efficient production and distribution.  The value of the telephone service for business, social and domestic purposes is reflected in the growing demand for telephones and in the rise in traffic.  We have not by any means reached the peak of development and in the coming years we must be ready to cater for greater expansion.  In this Bill we are asking the Oireachtas to provide the means to continue the work and I confidently recommend it to the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very impressive picture to put before the House at this late hour, both in respect of the amount of money to be spent and the improvements envisaged in the telephone service.  We all agree that this Bill is one we approve of because this expenditure is expenditure upon something which will improve the efficiency of the economy generally. Telephones nowadays are absolutely essential in business and even in one's private life so that at any level of the community or of the economy, telephones are something upon which money should be spent.  One reason why I myself approve of this expenditure is that it not only makes us more <Col N="2176" /> efficient in the whole country but it is something which will pay for itself. It will pay in many ways: to the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs in that he will be able to get a return on his money&mdash;and that is the kind of expenditure we all welcome&mdash;and in the unseen advantages in the improved efficiency produced in business generally.</P>
      <P>Another feature that is very welcome is that this money will be used not only to give increased communication all over the country but to give automatic communication.  The sooner we get away from the human element in telephones of all things, the better, because the more often we are forced to hear the human voice at the other end from the exchange, the slower will be the service compared with an automatic service.  That is not to criticise the personnel of the Post Office because I have always found them most efficient and courteous, but even with the most courteous and efficient staff, the telephone gives us some of the most exasperating and annoying moments of our lives when we have to deal with the human element. We are getting greater speed and efficiency with automatic telephones and that is one of the commendations I make on the Bill.  This is a subject on which we could all, I am sure, talk at great length.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>We are limited to three minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a good way to limit things at this hour of the night. On the question of the human element, one of the most exasperating things is that when one has to dial &ldquo;O&rdquo; it is very good at ordinary hours but from 6 p.m. to 9 a.m. there can be very long delays in getting any answer whatsoever. I have counted up to quite astronomical figures the number of buzzes before anybody has answered. Once or twice I have asked the man&mdash; it is usually a man at that hour&mdash;the reason for the delay and he says they are understaffed at that hour.  Anyway I take it that this amount of money which we are arranging to be spent on the telephones will eliminate the exasperations of dialling &ldquo;O&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2177" /> The only other point is the directory. This seems to be an insoluble problem, but there is no doubt that the print at the present time is too small.  We all know that the reason for the small print is the effort to force all the subscribers in the whole country into one volume.  It may be all right for people under 30 years of age whose eyesight is particularly good, but we find over 30 that we have to hold the book further and further away, if we are to read it without strong glasses and if the light is not good, it is practically impossible to read it at all, unless one has a magnifying glass.</P>
    <P>I feel it would be a better idea to go back to the system of two books, one for Dublin and the other for the provinces. I know that there is a lot to be said on both sides but much dissatisfaction has been caused by the small print in the present book and if some way could be found to get over the difficulty and to get a book which could be read in normal light with normal eyesight, it would be a great amenity.  I have much pleasure in supporting this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I also shall be very brief. I just want to congratulate the Minister and his Department on the telephone service. which I think is excellent. Any money they want to spend in extending and improving the service they should get.  I should like to ask the Minister if there is any possibility of having these telephone units assembled in this country?  Mr. C.O. Stanley operates in this country too and I see that he is trying to do this work for the British Government and I think the inquiry should be made. Finally, I have something more to say about the directory than Senator McGuire said.  If the Minister himself has to get needle and thread to get the directory out, will he do so?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise simply to support Senator McGuire's plea for a better directory.  It is quite true that both the print and the binding are entirely unsatisfactory.  I am sure we all hope that some part of the £10,000,000 will be devoted to producing a directory which will not <Col N="2178" /> exasperate the user every time he goes to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder would the Minister consider having some sort of cubicle erected for the public in rural parts where they are using telephones in sub-post offices.  Usually these telephones are hung or screwed on to the wall and whether the telephone call is to a hospital or to a mother-in-law, the people have to make the conversation in public, which is unsatisfactory. I think most people in rural Ireland would agree that what I am saying is true and that when a person comes into a sub-post office or a shop to make a phone call, he has to make it in public and that is not the most satisfactory way of doing business.  I should like the Minister to keep that in mind.  Some sort of cubicle from which the people can transact their business would be better than the present situation, so far as the public are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a rather peculiar observation to make.  In our area recently we have been experiencing great difficulty in communicating with the port of Waterford.  We have made official representations an behalf of the industries in our area.  Many of the leading industries are engaged in the food and drink businesses and it is essential that they should be able to communicate almost immediately with the port rather than to have a minimum delay of half an hour.  I am informed that the delay in summertime is due to the fact that the lines are very heavily engaged by the tourists, but the number of lines which the tourists can occupy would not be available except for the business people who use these lines for the rest of the year.  In fact if the business people were not paying for that system, the delay during the summertime would probably be two or three hours.  I think the regulations should be looked into with a view to allowing people who pay the commercial rental for telephones to get priority in such cases. There could be very serious repercussions on industry if the people who are handling perishable products find that they have not got effective communication with the port.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2179" /> For example, last week, in connection with the strike at Liverpool, I was telephoned two or three times a day as to the progress of that strike and whether or not shipments could be made.  One is placed in rather an appalling position if there is a minimum delay of half an hour on the phone services caused by the tourist industry.  There should be some way of getting over that difficulty and my suggestion is that people who pay the commercial rental should get priority over the people who do not.  I know that one answer which can be made to this problem is that you can get priority by paying double the rate but that is a penalty which one would have to pay.</P>
    <P>Finally I want to say that this Bill is a very realistic one.  It is an earnest that the Minister wants to give us a better and more up-to-date telephone service.  Great strides have been made and it must be a great source of gratification to all to see that the service is so well used and appreciated. While some areas like Cork and Athlone are able to dial trunk calls to Dublin other important centres are still on the old system and some effort should be made to bring the other centres on to the automatic system before one is able to dial New York direct from Athlone or Cork or Dublin.</P>
    <P>Another point which should be considered is that important centres should have direct trunk connections with Dublin and with their nearest port. They should not be put in the position that if there is a breakdown, they have to get into a queue and business, especially our export business, has to be neglected.  This is really an administrative detail but perhaps the Minister would give a direction that the industry of the country will not be impeded by the regulations as they stand at present.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I find myself in the position of being the only speaker so far who is trying to find fault with these proposals.  We are asked for £10,000,000 but we are given no estimate as to whether this service will pay for itself.  Will the services produce <Col N="2180" /> sufficient interest or can we look forward to their producing a surplus by which the amount will eventually be paid back?  In the United States of America and in other countries, the telephone services have to stand on their own feet and pay their way as other services have to do.  They have to provide their capital for expansion or make provision for repaying loans.  I fully appreciate the telephone service here and its difficulties but let us be realistic.  It should stand on its own feet and I should like to hear that this money is going to be paid back.</P>
      <P>We value this service but if we are looking for a better service, it is not asking too much to pay for that service. It will mean other demands on the country's capital and I do not think the telephone service should do that, unless it is we are merely investing the money and that it is to be paid back eventually.  The charge for a local call at present is threepence and I doubt if it was ever lower than twopence. It has not moved with the deflation of the £.  I feel that while we want the best and want everything to be automatic, we must reckon another indirect cost in this automation, that is, the displacement of many of those who are earning a modest living in the telephone services on this work.  We have got to reckon with that factor also.  I do appreciate that the telephone service is providing a valuable link with the country towns at the moment and a very valuable link between the members of the farming community.  That is good but I do not think any one of these sections can seriously expect to be provided for by the community as a whole when we sat here to-day and voted just 1/- to the old age pensioners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to give a welcome to this Bill, and particularly to the five year plan for the installation of new line phones trunk circuits, and automatic exchanges. I should like to emphasise&mdash; because apparently Senator Quinlan does not appreciate it any more than he appreciated a similar matter in connection with broadcasting and television development&mdash;that telephones are no longer a luxury.  Telephones <Col N="2181" /> are essential commercial and social amenities, and any step taken to provide an up-to-date service, or to extend or improve the existing service is certain of a welcome from the great majority of thinking people in the country.</P>
      <P>As the Minister has pointed out, great progress has been made in dealing with the ever-increasing demand for telephones.  Much remains to be done, but an energetic drive will, I am quite certain, be made by the Department of Posts and Telegraphs under this Bill, to ensure that we shall have, at the end of that period, the satisfactory services and net-work which are essential in a modern State.</P>
      <P>The fact that almost 5,000 applicants are now awaiting phones, as was pointed out by the Minister, is an indication of the popularity of the telephone service, and is also an indication of the job which faces the engineering section of the Department.  The Minister referred to the concessions which were made last year in regard to rentals and call charges.  I should like to commend him on that development and I hope he will explore every possibility of giving further concessions in that and other directions.</P>
      <P>The only real criticism that can be made of the telephone system and its administration&mdash;and it is a criticism which we all make&mdash;is a criticism of the telephone directory.  So far as I understand, it is intended to remedy the defects in the size of the type which was used in the current directory. There is no doubt whatever that for the majority of people, and particularly for those who have to use the public telephone kiosks under poor lighting conditions, it requires a miracle to find a name or a number in the directory as at present printed.  I am glad an improvement is anticipated in the next edition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to suggest in that connection that when this improvement is taking place, the irritating practice of using Gaelic and Roman type for Irish entries should be ended and that the directory should adopt the standard Roman type for Irish entries which is used by every other Department of State.  We should appreciate the fact that modern progress <Col N="2182" /> has resulted in the abandonment of the old script and we should see that our telephone directory is not, as it is in my view, blemished by the use of the double type system.</P>
    <P>The desirability of producing two directories, one for Dublin and its area, and one for the rest of Ireland, should be examined and a decision taken as soon as possible, because at the rate applications for telephones are received, and with the rapid development which is envisaged in this five year plan, it will be absolutely impossible to produce one book of a handy size that could be used in the post offices and in kiosks, apart altogether from private use.</P>
    <P>There is, of course, the difficulty of binding.  I understand it is not possible to get a better type of binding here or, in fact, if I am rightly informed, it is not possible to get the directory bound here under present conditions. I have often had the impression that with the tremendous amount of State printing &mdash; Government documents, publications and the like&mdash;the Government should give consideration to the establishment of a State printing and binding works which, in my opinion, in the long run, would result in great economy in expenditure under that head.</P>
    <P>Like every book of its type, the directory binding is not as durable as one would desire but, at the same time, I do not think it is quite as bad as some critics have alleged it is. Certainly for private telephone users, the binding is quite good, but where hundreds of people handle the book, turn the pages back and forth and roll them over, the binding is undoubtedly not strong enough to stand up to the strain.</P>
    <P>I have only one suggestion to make to the Minister in that connection, that is, that he should examine the feasibility of providing with each telephone directory, in the next issue, a binder or cover of soft cardboard. There are about 150,000 phones in use in the country at the moment, and I am satisfied that if even two-thirds of the telephone users were to pay 1/- or 1/6d. for a binder or cover, it would more than cover the cost of supplying them and keep those books in good <Col N="2183" /> condition and ensure that the binding would last in good condition.</P>
    <P>There is one other point which irritates me in relation to the present directory, that is, the omission of the circular hole on the top left hand corner which we had on previous directories, and which was very useful for handling the directory, and also for keeping the pages together, I hope when the next directory comes out, that matter will be attended to.</P>
    <P>I think there will be a general welcome for the Bill.  I should like to support the tribute paid by Senator McGuire to the courtesy and efficiency of the Post Office staff.  I, too, have done quite an amount of dialling &ldquo;O&rdquo; and, by and large, I think they are doing a good job.  Delays are quite understandable at certain times of the night but, on the whole, we have no great complaint to make on that score.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>The delay in answering on dialling of &ldquo;O&rdquo; was raised by Senator McGuire.  I should like to assure the House that the standard of answer from exchanges generally is good.  Tests are frequently made to ensure that a reasonable standard of answering is reached.  In Dublin, an average speed of answer of under ten seconds is aimed at, and is maintained for most of the day.  That does not mean that a delay of 20 or 30 seconds may not occasionally be experienced, but these delays are balanced up by calls being answered immediately or within a few seconds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>During the evening cheap rate period when there are frequently heavy rushes of traffic, occasional delays of longer duration may occur.  The exchange is staffed on a basis sufficient to handle the expected traffic and there is a margin for contingencies but the extent and incidence of abnormal rushes of traffic are not predictable.  It is more difficult to handle these rushes without delay in the evening because the total staff on duty is much smaller than during the day.  To be of much use to meet such sudden rushes, the staff must be available in the exchanges.  As Senators have stated, the staffs in the exchanges do everything they possibly <Col N="2184" /> can to meet the situation in which they find themselves during the rush periods.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke raised the question of facilitating as far as we possibly can the business community and the subscribers who pay at the business rate.  He pointed out that there was a difficulty in communicating with Waterford.  This is due to shortage of circuits between Clonmel and Waterford.  Arrangements will be made to provide additional circuits on this and other routes as soon as we possibly can.  At the moment, the Department and the Department's engineers are studying the situation. Along with the programme to go ahead with the work on the automatic exchanges, planned for the coming years, the Department's engineers have also in mind the other exchange areas that have to wait for development of the automatic system.  They will add extra circuits, on a planned basis, to meet the delays that we know exist in some of these exchange areas and to meet also the anticipated rise in telephone traffic.  The matter will take time.  We shall have to give priority to the exchange areas in which the greater delays occur&mdash;that is under-standable&mdash;and the areas in which the greater volume of our national business is situated, areas such as Waterford, Shannon Airport, and so on.</P>
    <P>The printing and binding of the telephone directory has been mentioned. That has caused a certain amount of criticism.  Prior to the decision to change the print of the directory, we received numerous complaints from subscribers all over the country regarding the previous directory.  They said the directory was getting too large, that it was falling asunder.  People even complained that the hole punched in the directory for hanging it up was causing it to fall asunder.  The decision had to be taken whether we should have two directories or a smaller directory which would be more manageable and which would be more likely to endure the full year of its life with the present binding.  A special kind of type was designed in America to keep directories within a manageable size. <Col N="2185" /> The decision was taken to avail of this type.  The same size of type was used in the British, Continental and American directories.  The view was taken that it would suit us to use that type, thus reducing the size of the directory, and that the binding was more or less likely to last with the smaller book.</P>
    <P>When the directory was printed with this new type, many complaints were made with regard to the size of the type.  I looked at it and thought it small.  I also thought the print in the directory here did not compare favourably with the print in the British or Continental directories.  I found there were technical difficulties involved and that the trade here in Ireland had to use equipment in printing and binding our directory which is also used for doing other work.  In Britain, the Post Office prints its own directory. The machine is not used for any other purpose.  I have made a decision in regard to the directory which is now about to be printed.  I found that the contract had been placed for five years. Therefore any decision now would have to be made with that fact in mind.</P>
    <P>One of the main reasons for the smaller print in the directory was to reduce its size so that it could continue to be bound in one volume without disintegrating within a short time under normal use.  It is true that larger volumes are bound here but in the case of the telephone directory, the problem is to bind a large number of volumes within a very short time.  There are machines for doing that work but the purchase of such a machine solely for the production of the telephone directory would not be warranted particularly as the size of the type used for the directory up to 1958 was perhaps the largest in Europe and the question of its reduction would have to be faced in any event at an early stage.</P>
    <P>I have tried to meet the criticism in regard to the size of the print in the telephone directory.  In future issues, the print will be heavier, the telephone numbers will be slightly larger and the exchange names will be in blacker print.  These improvements, which I think will meet all reasonable criticism, can be obtained only at the expense of <Col N="2186" /> some delay in the production of the directory this year.  I have seen specimen pages and I feel that the new directory will meet with general approval.</P>
    <P>I do not think the Department can do anything in this matter if we are to continue having the directory bound and printed in Ireland.  The policy is to maintain the directory in a single book as long as we possibly can. With the increased use of the telephone and the increased number of subscribers, a decision will have to be taken at some stage to have the directory in two books.  It will mean added cost to have to supply two books to each subscriber but that will have to be faced when the time comes.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan asked some questions in regard to the economic development of the telephone system.  He suggested that the House should be told whether the investment of this £10,000,000 would pay its way.  My answer is that financially the telephone service is in a healthy condition. The charges are reasonable by comparison with those of other services or on any other standard.  The service has been operated at a profit after providing for interest charges, depreciation and superannuation.  In 1958-59, the surplus was £413,000 and for 1959-60, it is expected to be of the order of £350,000.  I am confident that the telephone service will continue to pay its way in the future.</P>
    <P>I do not know if any other point was raised that calls for answer from me.  Listening to the debate, I think that Senators were satisfied with the development taking place in the telephone service generally.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Minister tried to get the phones made here?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>Some work of a limited kind on the manufacture of telephones has been done here, but there is no company at present manufacturing phones in Ireland.  As regards people in that business who may wish to establish an industry in Ireland for that purpose.  I am sure they will be facilitated to the same extent as any other group of people who propose <Col N="2187" /> to establish an industry in Ireland.</P>
      <P>Senator Brennan urged the installation of what is known as a silent cabinet in the local sub-offices.  Silence cabinets are provided in all the rural sub-offices in which it is possible for the Department to instal them.  They are in a large number of offices at the present time.  The policy is to instal this silence cabinet where it is practically possible.  There are some offices where the accommodation is not there for the cabinet itself.</P>
      <P>Furthermore, in some of the rural offices, the use of the telephone is so limited that it would not pay the Post Office to instal a silence cabinet.  It all depends on the circumstances obtaining in the sub-office.  If Senator Brennan has any particular cases in mind and if he raises the matter with me, I shall have the cases examined and if I find that a silence cabinet is warranted or is necessary or can be installed we shall see the matter is attended to.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill considered in Committee.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 1</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 1 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I even at this late hour delay the House for a few moments?  I am very grateful, indeed, to the Minister for supplying us with stencilled copies of the statement which is very clear but an inference is being drawn from certain figures in it.  This reminds me just a little bit of the famous electricity programme of 1954 when the demand for electricity was to double every five years.  Let us take the figures in paragraph 4 of the Minister's statement where he said that although the number of telephones went up by 50 per cent. between 1956 and 1960, the number of calls went up by only 25 per cent. if I interpret the figures correctly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Similarly, I do not quite follow why <Col N="2188" /> the Minister, on the basis of there being at the moment 4,570 waiting applicants, should conclude that this programme for five years will require provision for the installation of 80,000 extra telephones and 65,000 additional subscribers' lines.  I am not sure about the problem.  Naturally the Minister and his Department have a great deal more information about it but you do reach saturation point with these modern amenities at some stage of the proceedings, particularly with an instrument like the telephone which one can do without.</P>
    <P>If you take the last four years, it seems to me that there is an increase of about 12,000 subscribers' lines a year and the Minister now expects, on top of that, an additional 13,000 lines. Let me be frank about the matter.  This is an enabling Bill and the Minister will not spend the £10 million, if he does not want to.  I just want to sound the note of caution to the Minister that this kind of thing in relation to doubling up every so often just does not go on.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>There is room for half a million more phones and we have only 150,000 so far.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to return again to this matter of the £10 million. I am not really satisfied with the answer given me by the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator could not be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister in his reply said that the telephone service would be so conducted as to provide for interest charges, depreciation and superannuation.  If I or anybody else go by mere amounts and seek nothing else, the bank manager will ask for far more information.  He is interested in the sinking fund.  When are we going to pay back the capital?  Capital with us is a very scarce commodity. We do not want the capital tied up in any State enterprise longer than is necessary.  I should have thought that with the expansion that should result from this big investment and having regard to the activities of the telephone service as reported by the Minister, it <Col N="2189" /> would have been possible for the Minister to state that we are borrowing £10 million now but that the plan is that that should be paid back in a matter of from 15 to 20 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>It is 25 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Subsection (2) refers to the repayment of all or any of it.  In other words, it leaves it at the discretion of the Government whether they will ask for repayment of any of this capital sum.  I want to mention one figure that impressed me very much.  It is the figure in relation to the oil refinery business in Cork.  At present oil refineries everywhere&mdash;I believe there is no exception&mdash;seek to write off their capital in five years. They succeed in doing it and are providing a very valuable public service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should come down to earth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to know something more definite in regard to Government policy about investment. It is not sufficient just to pay interest.  We want to know when the capital is coming back to the pool to do more work for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>The advances of capital for purposes of development of the telephone system are repaid in the form of annuities.  These annuities commence in the financial year next after the calendar year in which the capital has been advanced and are repayable in equal half-yearly instalments of principal and interest combined.  The period of repayment of loans raised under the Telephone Capital Acts, 1924/46 is 20 years, and 25 years in the case of loans subsequent to the 1946 Act.</P>
      <P>I do not think there is any further information I can give to Senator Quinlan in that regard.  Provision is made for principal and interest payments and for superannuation.  It is all accounted for and is all amortised as far as this £10 million is concerned in 25 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I did not follow clearly what exactly Senator O'Donovan meant.  He is basing his calculations on the fact that there are just 4,570 applicants <Col N="2190" /> waiting.  The position really is that that is the number waiting at the end of a year.  The Post Office could have put in 12,000 or 13,000 telephones during that particular year.  New applications would still be coming in during the year.  The figure means that 4,570 applicants are just waiting at the end of a year.  That figure is carried forward into the next year and you still have new applications coming in.  We are finding it very difficult to keep up with the number of applications coming in in any given year.  Even though the rate of installation has increased, we still have at the end of the year a long list of those waiting for the installation of telephones.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make it quite clear that I am not objecting in any way to raising capital for this development, but I am worried about the general policy that sees in State enterprise something that can be governed by very less demanding conditions as regards repayments than private enterprises have to face.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to get clarification of the Minister's statement about the repayments because, as I read this section, it has the phrase &ldquo;the repayment of all or any of the sums issued&rdquo;.  In other words, it does not in any way make it mandatory that the sums must be paid back.  I commend the idea of these terminable annuities.  In fact, that is the very point I made to the Minister for Social Welfare to-night.  It is desirable to provide means by which people with a few hundred pounds or more saved can, when they reach the age when they can no longer work and need a little annuity, have some place to put that money and get that annuity as long as they live.  I take it that this terminable annuity will appeal to that type of investor, but I do not know why the words &ldquo;or any&rdquo; should be included which leaves wide open the <Col N="2191" /> proportion which the Government may decide in future will be paid back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>The phrase in Section 2 referred to by the Senator is just a drafting phrase and nothing more.  The Senator raised a question on subsection (3) which states: &ldquo;All terminable annuities created under this section shall be paid out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas ...&rdquo; They are repaid out of subhead M of the Post Office Vote.  Subsection (3) regulates the method by which money borrowed is paid back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the Minister's statement on that and it is now quite clear that the Government's policy is that this money is to be completely paid back over 20 years so that like T.V., the telephone company is put under an obligation to pay its way.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 and 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without recommendation; received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Diseases of Animals Bill, 1960:" RHead="Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Diseases of Animals Bill, 1960: Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Smith) Patrick Smith">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Smith)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill contains two main provisions. The first provision abolishes a fund which has been in existence since 1878 and which has long since outlived its usefulness.  The general cattle diseases fund was set up in an attempt to spread equitably over all local authorities the cost of dealing with outbreaks of animal disease or, in other words, to prevent all the cost of a local outbreak of disease from falling on one or on a very few local authorities at the time of the outbreak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At the time the fund was set up local bodies had smaller areas to administer than the present counties and they also had functions in relation to diseases such as cattle plague and pleuro-pneumonia which have since <Col N="2192" /> been eradicated, or diseases such as foot-and-mouth disease, swine fever, etc., which are now dealt with directly by the Department of Agriculture. The functions of local authorities in relation to animal diseases are now confined to (1) the appointment of local veterinary inspectors; (2) the administration of the Bovine Tuberculosis Order of 1926; and (3) the enforcement of sheep dipping regulations.</P>
    <P>I should perhaps make it clear that the Bovine Tuberculosis Order of 1926 is not connected with the general bovine tuberculosis eradication scheme. This order deals with clinical or open cases of tuberculosis.  The local authority veterinary inspector visits, inspects and arranges for slaughter in such cases (which are relatively small in number) but the compensation which is now at the full market value is recouped from the Exchequer.  With the development of the bovine tuberculosis eradication scheme generally the need for this Order will diminish in due course.</P>
    <P>Local authorities contribute to the fund by means of a halfpenny in the £ on the rates assessed from time to time. They receive from the fund one-half of their expenses&mdash;that is a total of about £25,000 at present&mdash;for disease control functions, and they pay the other £25,000 directly from their own resources.  I have indicated what these functions are and it will be apparent that the nature and volume of the work and the expenses incurred will be relatively the same in all counties.  The position has been for a number of years that most local authorities received from the fund about the same amount as they contributed to it.  The fund was thus serving no effective purpose and a complicated and rather expensive process of collecting money from local authorities and paying it back to them was being kept up unnecessarily.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides that after the 31st March, 1961, local authorities will meet all their expenses for disease control directly from the rates.  As I have already indicated these expenses total about £50,000 annually which is a <Col N="2193" /> negligible proportion of total local authority revenue expenditure.  The change will mean no additional charge on local authorities as a whole.</P>
    <P>The Fund is now almost exhausted and provision is made for further contributions to enable outstanding claims to be paid.  While provision is made for an overall assessment of 4d. in the £, in fact it is expected that no more than 2d. in the £ will be necessary.  The Fund is being kept open until the 31st March, 1963, so that the outstanding claims and the claims arising up to the 1st April, 1961, can be met.  Any balance on the 31st March, 1963 will be paid to the Exchequer but the last assessment necessary can be fairly closely estimated and so the amount left in the Fund will be very small.  Fines for offences under the Diseases of Animals Acts which were hitherto paid into the Fund will also be paid directly into the Exchequer from that date.  These fines have represented only an insignificant part of the income of the Fund.  To sum up this part of the Bill, I may say it is no more than a change in accountancy procedure made in the interests of simplicity and economy of administration.</P>
    <P>The second main provision in the Bill substitutes the word &ldquo;attested&rdquo; for the word &ldquo;accredited&rdquo; in our Bovine Tuberculosis Eradication Scheme.  What we describe as &ldquo;accredited cattle&rdquo; under our legislation are called &ldquo;attested cattle&rdquo; under the British Regulations.  I have had strong representations both from farmers' representatives and trade interests to adopt the description which has long been used in Britain.  It has been represented to me that describing Irish cattle as &ldquo;accredited&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;attested&rdquo; would have an adverse effect on their sale in Britain since British buyers may wonder whether the difference in description connotes some difference also in status.  In fact, of course, there is no such difference and in view of the representations I received and because of the necessity to ensure that no obstacle is placed in the way of our cattle export trade I thought it well that we should adopt the word &ldquo;attested.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2194" /> When the Diseases of Animals (Bovine Tuberculosis) Bill was before this House in 1957 Senators discussed the relative merits of the words &ldquo;accredited&rdquo; and &ldquo;attested&rdquo; and it was indicated at the time that the change would be made at a later stage if circumstances justified it.  I feel that that time has now come.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Both parts of this Bill are to be welcomed, although I regret the demise of an old friend, the General Cattle Diseases Fund, which as the Minister pointed out originated in relation to pleuro-pneumonia.  If I might ask the Minister a question which is perhaps not strictly relevant to the Bill, and which he may or may not be able to answer&mdash;if he cannot answer it, I will not blame him&mdash;has he or his Department succeeded in persuading the American Government that pleuro-pneumonia is not endemic in our cattle?  I understand it is one of the difficulties which arose when the export trade in beef started here.  Ireland was listed in regulations of the United States as one of the countries in which pleuro-pneumonia was endemic. To the best of my recollection, the last outbreak of pleuro-pneumonia was in 1875 or some time like that.</P>
      <P>In regard to the other part of the Bill, many of these funds were wound up in 1923 and 1924 and those that survived continued for a long time. This was a British method of doing things and it is not in accord with the modern desire for uniformity about which we heard so much in this House recently, although there are occasions when uniformity does not always bring the desired results.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The other part of the Bill is more important.  It is a sensible proposal and I do not want to say anything more about it than that.  Otherwise I might be tempted to make very strong observations.  The Minister said that it had been represented to him that describing Irish cattle as &ldquo;accredited&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;attested&rdquo; would have an adverse effect on their sale in Britain. There is not the slightest doubt that certain deficiencies&mdash;to use a moderate Civil Service kind of word&mdash;have been found in the system that operated <Col N="2195" /> I do not agree with the Minister's attitude in relation to the action which he took.  I do not agree with his refusal to publish the names of the people who do not do their duty in regard to bovine tuberculosis.  The names of such people should be published.  If the State will not point out people who are not doing their duty, who else can do it?  I do not want to say anything more about it, but, as I say, the Bill in both parts is to be welcomed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Seanad will delay discussing this Bill and even if my namesake calls the fund an old friend, I have had some experience of it and I regard it as an old difficulty.  I should like to refer to the Bovine Tuberculosis Order which was originally brought in as a public health measure in the interest of human beings rather than animals. With the eradication of bovine tuberculosis, there is no necessity for the Bovine Tuberculosis Order.  I remember in this House many years ago trying to get an alteration in the Order to make it operate more easily, but the opinion I wish to express now is that in a very short time there will be no necessity for the Bovine Tuberculosis Order, 1956, and the responsibilities of local authorities in connection with contagious diseases of animals will be practically eliminated.</P>
      <P>The fact that we are remarkably clear of any of these major diseases&mdash; and let us hope the country will continue to be clear of them&mdash;means that the necessity for the Central Fund to expend large sums of money on the eradication of cattle diseases will no longer exist.  What we require in this country today is to eradicate bovine tuberculosis and I am sure that everyone, including the veterinary surgeons and those in charge of the animals, will co-operate to the fullest extent in bringing this tuberculosis eradication scheme to a conclusion as quickly as possible.  Even when it is approaching a conclusion, expenditure will be necessitated to safeguard the livestock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Surely it would be all right to change the word &ldquo;accredited&rdquo; to &ldquo;attested&rdquo; simply for the sake of <Col N="2196" /> uniformity.  Those words were discussed in the Seanad before and we accepted the definition &ldquo;accredited&rdquo; here when the definition in England was &ldquo;attested&rdquo;.  They both mean the same thing but I can see that it would be better if we agreed on the term employed in the country to which we export the greater number of cattle in order that the British owner will know that the cattle we are exporting have been tested for tuberculosis and certified as &ldquo;attested&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;accredited&rdquo;.  The fact that the word &ldquo;attested&rdquo; would be associated with the word &ldquo;tested&rdquo; would convey a definite meaning to any British or foreign stock owner more quickly than would the word &ldquo;accredited&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>I hope the House will pass this Bill <i>in toto</i> tonight.  In passing, I should like to make a slightly facetious remark about the fact that I notice in subsection (2) of Section 5 the phrase &ldquo;shall come into operation on such day as the Minister by Order appoints&rdquo;.  I notice that other Senators seem to object to any Minister using Orders for the implementation of legislation.  Surely this Bill becomes a law on the day it is signed by An tUachtaráin?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I notice that the Minister states the local authority is contributing a halfpenny in the £ to the fund and they are receiving half of their expenditure from it.  In other words, at the present time it is costing the local authority a penny in the £. Further on, the Minister states that it was not expected that there would be any increase in claims and he made the statement that:</P>
      <P>While provision is made for an over-all assessment of 4d. in the £, in fact it is expected that no more than 2d. in the £ will be necessary.</P>
      <P>I was just wondering about the jump from a penny to 2d.  Does the State at present make a contribution to this fund we are now abolishing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case my question probably does not arise.  I was wondering was it only in a single <Col N="2197" /> county it would go up to 2d. and that in another it would be a penny.  I was concerned that there would not be any transfer of money or financial responsibility from the central authority to the local authority but I do not think there is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>Most public men are concerned about the same matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I should have hoped that possibly the Minister could have got rid of some of the expenditure under this fund.  I understand from the debate in the Dáil that the only expenditure now which is being met out of the fund is in regard to veterinary inspectors and inspection of slaughter houses. I am not quite sure where the overlapping could occur.  Of course, there is a certain amount of overlapping between county council health inspectors and veterinary inspectors because both are entitled to inspect slaughter houses. Perhaps the Minister would look into that question at some future date.  Inspectors under this Bill can inspect slaughter houses and health inspectors under the Health Acts can inspect slaughter houses also.</P>
      <P>According to what the Minister said in the Dáil veterinary inspectors will inspect slaughter houses.  There was at one time a certain amount of overlapping. I do not know whether there still is.  Sheep-dipping regulations seem to be the only thing which will be left to the fund after 1963.</P>
      <P>There is one other question I should like to ask with regard to the changing of the word &ldquo;accredited&rdquo; to &ldquo;attested&rdquo;. Will that entail any difficulty with regard to cattle in transit when the Bill becomes law?  Will there be any necessity to change forms that might be used in connection with the transport of cattle?  Nothing occurs to me but there might be something.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>According to my information, the disease referred to by Senator O'Donovan, pleuro-pneumonia, last occurred in this country in 1892.  I do not know what the American attitude is or whether they have kept themselves informed as to the progress we have been making since that time.  We were very far away from them then but in fact in some senses.  I <Col N="2198" /> suppose today as in those early times, the Americans are fairly hard to convince in matters&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>Sixty years is a long time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;of disease and perhaps it was that our contacts with them in the cattle trading sense were not of a nature that would produce an understanding of the progress we had made.</P>
      <P>There is no reason, I think, why I should refer to the point made by Senator Quinlan.  The question he addressed to me was in fact one which I asked myself when this matter was first mooted to me by my officials.  I knew well, of course, that if there was any question of breaking up a fund that was designed to assist the local bodies in the State, most Deputies and Senators and public men would take a very poor view of that proposition. It is easy to understand why the fund was created when local bodies were responsible for paying compensation for losses sustained as a result of the outbreak of any of the diseases then controlled by them.  I should also like to say that with the passage of time this payment of compensation was taken over by the State and the need for an arrangement which was a fairly vital matter in those early days did not appear to exist any longer.  Such a fund, created in this cumbersome way, was bound to cause considerable waste of official time at the local authority level and at the central level.  There was, therefore, a very convincing reason for bringing to an end this arrangement and making the local authority directly responsible for meeting whatever costs are incurred in the administration of the Diseases of Animals Acts.  It is not very much.</P>
      <P>Senator Cole made a point about the printing of booklets, and so on.  We are taking power to make an Order to enable us to look after the point to which the Senator referred.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee; reported without amendment; received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Government Bill, 1960&mdash;Second" RHead="and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Local Government Bill, 1960&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2199" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney) Neil T. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this Bill is to enable the corporation of a county borough to provide a concert hall, theatre or opera house themselves or to assist financially a body providing such a building.  Some time ago, the Cork Corporation were given to understand that State assistance, by way of loan, would be provided for the rebuilding of Cork Opera House.  One of the conditions attached to the undertaking was that the Corporation would, if they were given the necessary power to do so, make a grant of £25,000 towards the project.  The Corporation subsequently passed a resolution agreeing in principle to give a grant of £25,000 to the Cork Opera House Trust Fund and requested the Government's permission to do so.  I informed the Corporation that, while existing legislation did not empower them to make the proposed grant, the necessary steps would be taken to enable them to give effect to their resolution.  This Bill fulfils that promise. It is not, however, restricted to Cork Corporation.  It is proposed that the powers set out in the Bill be given to all four county borough corporations.</P>
      <P>In proposing to extend the provisions of the Bill to all county borough corporations the Government had regard to a request from Limerick Corporation that any concession being made to Cork should also be made to Limerick so that the latter corporation might be enabled to assist the executive committee of Féile Luimnighe in the provision of a theatre and concert hall.  While no similar requests have been received from Dublin or Waterford Corporations there have been frequent references to the need for a concert hall of international standard in Dublin and I therefore thought it reasonable that the Bill should apply to all four county borough corporations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The procedure to be followed, where <Col N="2200" /> a corporation wish to put the provisions of the Bill into operation, is set out in subsection (2) of Section 1.  The procedure contemplates the adoption of a resolution by the local authority, who then give notice of the resolution in the newspapers, followed by a waiting period of 60 to 180 days after which it must be confirmed by a further resolution of the local authority. The resolution does not become operative until it has been confirmed by an Order of the Minister for Local Government.  The procedure may appear cumbersome but where expenditure from rates on a project of this nature is contemplated it is desirable that the proposal be given the maximum publicity so that objectors may make representations and have them considered.</P>
    <P>In addition to assisting other bodies in providing a concert hall, theatre or opera house, the Bill enables any of the four corporations to provide such a hall themselves and the purposes for which a hall provided by a corporation may be used are set out in the Bill. Generally the purposes are the holding of concerts, stage plays, operas, meetings, lectures, exhibitions and general recreation or other similar social objects.  Where the building is provided by another body with assistance from a corporation such assistance may be conditional on an agreement between the corporation and the body as to the use and disposal of the building.</P>
    <P>Use, other than that specifically mentioned in the Bill, may be made of any building provided under the Bill, if such use is occasional only or, if continual, is restricted to a part, which is not a substantial part, of the whole building.</P>
    <P>Reference has been made to the desirability of extending the provisions of the Bill to other local authorities. The position is that county councils and county borough corporations have power, under existing legislation, to provide halls for parish councils or to make a grant to a parish council towards the provision of a parish hall. Urban district councils and borough corporations have power to provide town halls which may be used for conferences, <Col N="2201" /> meetings, lectures, dancing, plays etc.  Neither county councils nor county borough councils have availed themselves of these powers in regard to the provision of parish halls.  Neither has there been any general demand from local authorities for the powers in the present Bill.  In fact the only request for such powers, as I mentioned earlier, came from Cork and Limerick Corporations.</P>
    <P>If, however, a general demand does develop for the extension of the powers in the Bill to other categories of local authorities, sympathetic consideration will be given to the question of introducing the necessary amending legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>It is only graceful that I should be the first to welcome this Bill.  Although it makes general provision, it really arises from the desire of the people of Cork to build a theatre.  They know a theatre is barely an economic proposition. Despite that, they raised £75,000 in sums ranging from 1/- to many hundreds of pounds in order to replace the burned theatre.  The State have&mdash;I hope&mdash;agreed to an interest-free loan of £50,000.  This Bill enables the Corporation to contribute another £25,000. Then we shall achieve what we in Cork set out to achieve, namely, the replacement of the Cork Opera House.</P>
      <P>I have always envied continental towns and cities which have municipal theatres.  The theatre, as I say, is not an economic proposition but it is a very desirable asset to the social life of any centre of population.  It is not an asset that can be measured in terms of box-office returns.  It is not even an asset one can measure in terms of the trade the theatre will bring to a large city with a good sized hinterland. It has other rewards and I think these rewards are very important in Ireland to-day.  In any event, the many benefits I see flowing from this will not be measured on a cash register. It is a good thing that out of the ashes of the old Cork theatre, as a result of this piece of legislation, for which I thank the Minister and the Government, we shall be able to ring up the curtain in Cork again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2202" />
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister to consider extending the provisions of this Bill to the borough of Dún Laoghaire.  I believe that Dún Laoghaire has no suitable concert hall of any sort.  It is now the third city in the State and although it may not be classified like the other four cities as a county borough, by reason of its size, its importance and rateable valuation, I suggest that the provisions of the Bill should be extended to Dún Laoghaire.  I understand also that the need in Dún Laoghaire is great.  If the Bill were extended to cover it, probably an application would be received from Dún Laoghaire for the facilities which are available to the four county boroughs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to Senator Burke's request that these powers be extended to Dún Laoghaire, might I say that the situation is that we have since last week, when this Bill was discussed in the Dáil, received a copy of a resolution from the Dún Laoghaire Corporation requesting that these powers should be extended to them?</P>
      <P>In the Dáil last week, I pointed out quite clearly, as I think I did also here to-night, that despite the fact that it was known fairly widely to any and all interested parties and bodies throughout the country that the Government were contemplating such a measure as this to meet the demand from Cork, no representations whatsoever were received from any local authority, with the exception of Limerick.  As I have also pointed out, the history of the express need of a concert hall in Dublin is so well known to everyone that it was not really necessary to hear from the Dublin Corporation that this procedure might be of use to them.  Limerick was added in at its own request.  The facilities which we are giving to Cork we also naturally make available to Dublin.  That left one remaining county borough, Waterford. The Bill was then brought in. Its Title is specific.  It relates to the county boroughs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That then brings us to the position that even if the passing of a resolution at this late stage in the proceedings through both Houses of the Oireachtas <Col N="2203" /> was agreed by all as something that we should accede to, I am afraid it is somewhat beyond us in this respect. Cork really originated the Bill.  They are in the position that they are waiting for the Bill to become law.  If we wanted to add anything to the four county boroughs outlined at the moment in the Bill and in the Long Title, it would mean recasting the Bill as a whole.  This in turn would mean, with the expected adjournment of the Dáil tonight and resumption next October, that no law would be in existence to facilitate Cork between now and next October.  That in itself, without any other argument at all, circumscribes us to the degree that I do not think we can even consider at this stage recasting the Bill to take in anybody.</P>
    <P>However as I said in the other House and here in my introductory speech, if Dún Laoghaire or any other bodies throughout the country show, by resolution or other activity, that they are in fact interested and have a proposition for which the terms of this Bill would be useful, they will be looked on sympathetically by me and I do not think there will be any great difficulty in bringing in a Bill to suit any or all local authorities who would avail of its facilities.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee; reported without amendment; received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Oil Burners (Standards) Bill," RHead="1960&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Oil Burners (Standards) Bill, 1960&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Qustion proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch) Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators will probably remember that, some time ago, there was a certain amount of public disquiet here and in Britain because of the fire hazards associated with particular types of oil heaters. There were, unfortunately, a number of fatal accidents in Britain which <Col N="2204" /> emphasised the necessity to examine this problem at once.  Many of the oil heaters which are in use in this country have been imported from Britain, and some contain features which are recognised as representing a fire hazard in certain conditions of operation.</P>
      <P>I have had under consideration for some time past the action which might best be taken here to deal with the fire hazard associated with oil heaters, and I have had the benefit of discussions with assemblers, importers and distributors of oil heaters.  The action taken in Britain in this matter has, of course, been helpful in our consideration of the problems associated with the use of these heaters.  It will be recalled, perhaps, that a report on oil heaters was furnished to the British Government in March of this year by the British Joint Fire Research Organisation.  Subsequent to this, a British Standard Specification was prescribed for oil heaters, and a Bill is now going through Parliament, the effect of which will be to prohibit the sale of dangerous oil heaters in Britain.</P>
      <P>While the danger attaching to the use of oil heaters can, perhaps, be exaggerated, nevertheless, I think that the situation is one which requires action on the part of the Government. We appear to have had very few accidents resulting from the use of these heaters, but it must be recognised that under certain operating conditions, some of these heaters do represent a serious fire hazard, and the public interest requires that whatever corrective action may be possible ought to be taken as soon as practicable.  A situation is likely to develop in which large numbers of sub-standard oil heaters manufactured in Britain, the sale of which will henceforth be prohibited in Britain, will become available for export markets.  It would be a very unfortunate development if large numbers of defective oil heaters were imported and sold to the public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am sure that the introduction of this Bill will make it clear that the Government intend to take action to deal with the types of oil heaters which represent a fire hazard, and importers <Col N="2205" /> and firms engaged in the manufacture or assembly of oil heaters here will be expected to make sure that the heaters which they are placing on the market are of a safe type and do not incorporate the features which have made some of these heaters a hazard to human life and property.</P>
    <P>The broad effect of the Bill will be to empower the Minister for Industry and Commerce to make regulations requiring that oil heaters which are offered for sale comply with an approved specification which will ensure that the risk of fire will be eliminated as far as possible.  There will be a requirement to attach to oil heaters instructions about their use so that the public will be properly informed about the correct use of these heaters.  There will, also, be a requirement that heaters should have attached to them an indication that they comply with the specification prescribed by the Act.  This will facilitate the purchasing public, since it will be an easy matter for persons to assure themselves that an oil heater which they propose to purchase complies with the approved specification.</P>
    <P>As soon as possible after the enactment of the Bill, I shall arrange that standards of safety will be prepared with the assistance of the Institute for Industrial Research and Standards.  It will be necessary, of course, that manufacturers, assemblers and distributors of oil heaters should be consulted so as to obtain their views on the standards of safety which are proposed and the form which the Regulations to be made under the Bill will take.  I am not in a position to indicate when the preparation of safety standards and consultation with interested parties will have been completed but every effort will be made to expedite matters with a view to <Col N="2206" /> making the Regulations at the earliest possible moment.</P>
    <P>I think that it is important that the dangers associated with the use of oil heaters should not be exaggerated. Indeed, we cannot be unmindful of the fact that accidents are frequently associated with the use of gas fires, electric heaters and coal fires, and they can arise in many other ways as well.  The exercise of reasonable care by everyone is probably the most important factor in accident prevention, and this is especially true in the home where unfortunately so many accidents occur.</P>
    <P>I hope that the proposals contained in this Bill will be acceptable to the House and that there will be general agreement concerning the course of action which is proposed.  It is now almost midnight and would seem an appropriate time to discuss a Bill such as this.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Midnight oil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I trust we shall not have to burn midnight oil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>We give full approval to the Bill and compliment the Minister on not allowing us to burn any midnight oil in respect of it.  He has brought it through very quickly and we shall not object to giving all Stages tonight.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee; reported without amendment; received for final consideration and passed.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 11.45 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 21st July, 1960.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>