<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="17" Month="Feb" Year="1960" Vol="52" No="6" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 17 Feabhra 1960" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 17 February 1960" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="571">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="571" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of Committee" RHead="of Selection">
    <Title>Report of Committee of Selection.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Tuairiscíonn an Coiste Roghnóireachta go bhfuil sé tar éis an Seanadóir Eoin Ó Síthigh Sceimhealtún a ainmniú chun an folúntas a líonadh a tharla sa Rogha-Choiste um Ionstraimí Reachtúla de dheasca an Seanadóir Liam Ó Fearáin, d'fháil bháis.</P>
      <P>The Committee of Selection reports that it has nominated Senator Owen L. Sheehy Skeffington to fill the vacancy in the Select Committee on Statutory Instruments occasioned by the death of Senator William R. Fearon.</P>
      <P>Tairgim:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Go luífidh an Tuarascáil ar an mBord.</P>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Report do lie upon the Table.</P>
      <P>Agreed and ordered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Institution of Civil Engineers of Ireland (Charter" RHead="Amendment) Bill, 1959&mdash;Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Institution of Civil Engineers of Ireland (Charter Amendment) Bill, 1959&mdash;Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the House be agreeable to take the Fifth Stage today?</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That Standing Order No. 111 (Private Business) be suspended for the purpose of enabling the Fifth Stage of the Institution of Civil <Col N="572" /> Engineers of Ireland (Charter Amendment) Bill, 1959, to be taken today.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Ordered: &ldquo;That the Bill be sent to the Dáil&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Broadcasting Authority Bill," RHead="1959&mdash;Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Broadcasting Authority Bill, 1959&mdash;Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 4, line 36, to add at the end of the line:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Notice of action taken under this section shall be notified to both Houses of the Oireachtas.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>We had some discussion on this matter on Committee Stage.  The Government appoint and remove every member of this Authority and have very considerable power over the Authority.  It seems to me that when action is taken under Section 6 to remove a member of the Authority, notification should be given to both Houses of the Oireachtas.  I do not want to labour that point but may I ask the Minister whether such removal from office will be published in any official manner apart from notification to the Houses of the Oireachtas?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Hilliard) Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Hilliard)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Hilliard)</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator Hayes has said, this matter was discussed, to some extent, on Committee Stage.  I should like to say, first of all, that the removal of a member of a statutory body from office is, indeed, a very rare event, and I personally cannot recall any such occurrence.  It would be much easier for the Government or the Minister concerned to await the expiration of the term of office of any member whom they did not wish to have on the Authority, if they have made up their minds at a certain date he should not be there, but if the power given in this section is exercised, there are a number of ways in which the members of the Oireachtas can raise the matter.  In any event, I cannot envisage the Government removing <Col N="573" /> a member of this Authority from office without making a public announcement immediately, unless there was some other overriding reason such as the public interest or something like that that would involve the withholding of the announcement for some time, but in the ordinary normal circumstances in which a member would be removed from office, I cannot envisage such a removal taking place without a public announcement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no obligation to publish it in <i>Iris Oifigiúil.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>There is not&mdash;not that I know of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the Minister that such a removal is unusual. If it took place in any circumstances which excited suspicion, presumably the person himself would be able to bring the matter to the attention of the Dáil or this House.  In the circumstances, I shall not press the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 6, between lines 33 and 34 to insert the following paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;( ) The Minister shall cause notice of the appointment or removal of the Director-General or of the alteration of his remuneration or of his terms and conditions of holding office to be laid before each House of the Oireachtas.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is a matter of greater import, it seems to me.  The Authority has power to appoint a Director-General.  It is also provided that the consent of the Minister is necessary before the Authority appoints or removes the Director-General, or alters his remuneration or his terms and conditions of holding office.  It seems to me quite reasonable that the appointment or removal of the Director-General or the alteration of his remuneration or his terms and conditions of holding office should be laid before each House <Col N="574" /> of the Oireachtas.  The Minister has considerable power.  I think in those circumstances the exercise of the power should be laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree at all with Senator Hayes in what he has just said in relation to how the Director-General's removal from office should be dealt with.  This post of Director-General is, as has already been stated by many Senators, a very important one.  In relation to the method by which we deal with the Director-General in this section, we wish to give it an added importance and place the post of Director-General in an exceptional position among chief executive officers of statutory boards who hold their employment from such boards.</P>
      <P>The Director-General will, in fact, be employed by the Authority.  It is true, of course, that they have to get the consent of the Minister for that employment, but, nevertheless, he is, in fact, an employee of the Authority. I do not think it would be a good principle to have it as in this amendment, obligatory upon the Authority or upon the Minister to cause notice of the appointment or the removal of the Director-General or the alteration of his remuneration or his terms and conditions of holding office laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  I feel that in that matter the Director-General should be dealt with as similar executive officers serving under other authorities of a similar nature.  Therefore, I am opposing this amendment.  I believe it is the proper course to take.  As I said, we wish to have this post placed in an exceptional position among chief executive officers of statutory boards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>What the Minister says he will do can be done.  As long as he retains power to consent to the appointment or removal of the Director-General or alteration in his remuneration or his terms and conditions of holding office, then he is open to a Parliamentary Question.  There is no method by which this person can be appointed and his remuneration or terms of office can be concealed. <Col N="575" /> It will be just as good to put them on the Table of the two Houses as to have the information elicited by question.  What the Minister says about putting him in a special position escapes me.  I do not understand what he means by that.  He is not in a special position at all.  If this method I suggest is not adopted, then there is a method by which all the information necessary can be elicited.  In those circumstances, I shall not go ahead with the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 16.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 8, between lines 6 and 7 to insert the following paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(c) A copy of every licence under this subsection shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after the issue of the licence.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment is proposed to meet, in principle, an amendment moved and subsequently withdrawn by Senator Hayes on Committee Stage.  It proposes to make available for the information of the Oireachtas a copy of any licence issued by me under Section 16 (3) of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that fairly meets the case made about the licence and I should like to thank the Minister for the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 8, line 27, to delete &ldquo;daily&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;hourly&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This amendment simply seeks to make sure that advertisers do not overload certain peak hours of transmission with advertisements.  This has happened in England.  This does affect viewers.  In peak viewing hours, the value of the advertisement is enhanced and the temptation to overload will be there.  Even the Authority itself might succumb to that temptation. This is where the Minister must protect the viewers or the listeners, and I <Col N="576" /> should like him to accept the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think this amendment is necessary at all.  I fully appreciate the Senator's desire to ensure that such advertising as is permitted will be kept to a reasonable level in every programme hour.  That is exactly what the Senator wants to make certain of.  It is my intention to secure that desirable feature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>The British have failed to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>That is why it is proposed that both the total daily time to be given to advertising, and the distribution of that time throughout the programmes, will be subject to the Minister's approval.  As the subsection is drafted, it gives me and any future Minister for Posts and Telegraphs the power to ensure not alone that the total volume of advertising in a day is not excessive but also that the proportion of it in any single hour is reasonable.  This means that I can say: &ldquo;There shall be no more than &ldquo;X&rdquo; hours given to advertising in any one day&rdquo; and also that &ldquo;there shall not be more than so many minutes in any one hour.&rdquo;  I have that power already under the section as it stands.</P>
      <P>I know that this is what the Senator intends.  I shall also bear in mind the recommendation of the Television Commission that there should not be more than six minutes of advertising time per programme hour.  Pending experience and consultation with the Authority I cannot at this stage lay down any hard and fast rule, nevertheless the recommendations made by Senator Barry in this regard will be borne in mind.  The power is already in the section to do what the Senator wants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister is being unfair to himself.  I want to protect him and his successors because there will be that temptation. People may say: &ldquo;My goodness, we can earn another £1,000 in that hour if you give us another ten minutes broadcasting.&rdquo;  The Minister might fall for it or his successor might fall for it and I want to be certain that they will not do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="577" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>This section is operated under the consent of the Minister.  That is the reason the consent of the Minister is inserted in the subsection because the Minister is charged with the responsibility of seeing that the licence payers, the viewers and listeners, get value for their money, independent of what the Authority can earn out of advertising time.  It is for that reason the Minister is in the section, to make certain that there is a fair distribution in the matter of advertisements and the number of hours per day and the number of minutes per hour taken up by advertising time.  There is no other explanation for it and Senator Barry need have no misgivings that the section as drafted will not make certain, and the Minister will not make certain, that the viewers and listeners will get full value for the licence fee paid and will have the greatest possible length of time for entertainment and educational and other classes of programmes.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 10, line 28, to delete &ldquo;Minister, with the consent&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Authority with the approval&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We had a certain amount of discussion on this matter before.  The Minister not only has to consent to the appointment of the Director General but he appoints the whole Authority.  The Authority has to keep its accounts in a particular way and it has to get its accounts audited and the Minister, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, appoints annually an auditor.  I am not able to understand why, and I do not know of any other cases where, the Minister is to appoint the auditor.  If it is intended to set up this body as an independent body, surely it should be left to appoint its own auditor, subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance, just as firms, for example, when appointing an auditor have to keep in mind that if their audited accounts are to be accepted for income tax purposes by the Revenue Commissioners <Col N="578" /> the auditors must be on the Revenue Commissioners' list.</P>
    <P>It seems to me that is reasonable and I do not see why the Minister should be put in here as the person to appoint the auditor.  It simply adds another appointment to the Minister and I see no reason in the world why the auditor should not be appointed by the Authority, subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance.  That, it seems to me, would be quite a reasonable addition to the stature of the Authority itself and is just as practicable as the agreement in the Bill.</P>
    <P>I see no reason why the Minister&mdash; I am talking about the office and not the individual&mdash;should be inserted here.  He has no particular competency in the matter of auditors.  The Minister for Finance has to deal with auditors for other Revenue purposes and I do not see why the Authority should not be allowed to nominate the auditor, subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance.  That is what I put down the amendment for and it seems quite reasonable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>I must continue to oppose this amendment.  As I pointed out during the Committee Stage, the Authority will be getting a very great proportion of its revenue from television fees and will also, in the early years of its life, be in receipt of a non-repayable annual grant direct from State funds.  Therefore, I feel that the taxpayer should have this particular assurance that the money which he puts up will be correctly accounted for.  That is why there must be State responsibility for the selection of the auditor in the first instance.</P>
      <P>I do not in any way accept that that imposes any loss of dignity or independence for the Authority, any more than it does for any other statutory bodies whose accounts are audited either by the Comptroller and Auditor General or commercial auditors appointed by a Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Indeed, I could make a very big case if I wished, and I could have <Col N="579" /> made a provision in the Bill, to have the accounts of this Authority audited by the Comptroller and Auditor General, but I did not do so because I wanted to leave the matter open, and as it is under some other Acts, so that as long as the Minister is responsible for the disbursement of public funds to the Authority, he has a responsibility there.  It is to preserve that responsibility that this section is so drafted, that the auditor is to be appointed by the Authority, with the consent of the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not follow the Minister's line of reasoning at all. Auditing is something that is carried out by a profession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>People have a professional qualification.  They are either chartered accountants or incorporated accountants and it is quite well known that most of these firms are absolutely above board and that consent would be given to a person who might indulge in some sleight-of-hand with regard to the accounts to defraud the taxpayer is quite unthinkable. The Minister by using that kind of argument seems to me to be giving his whole case away.  We are told that this Authority is such that it must have its authority preserved and must have some dignity but we cannot have it both ways.  This is a reasonable amendment.  I am not suggesting that the Authority should have complete authority to appoint its own auditors but the amendment seeks to put in the Authority instead of the Minister.  To put in the Minister and make him appoint the auditor is a quite useless provision.  It has no effect except to put a particular appointment in the hands of the Minister and to allow him to select from the number of highly qualified people on offer a particular person, or a particular firm that he likes.  I do not think he should have that power.  Instead, the Authority should have the power to make that selection but the Minister for Finance should have the power to say: &ldquo;I will not take that person.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="580" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to have it put.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Mr. Hilliard rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The debate is concluded unless the House is agreeable to allow the Minister to clarify some point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The procedure on amendments on Report Stage is that the mover has the right to reply.  I discovered that only lately and I have replied on this occasion.  I am afraid Senators were under the impression that we were in Committee, but, as this will not last very long, perhaps you, Sir, might give some liberty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the House agree?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall follow the usual procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Some other Senators wish to speak as well as the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>If I might say something, I think we should keep to the Standing Orders in this matter. We might get untidy in our debates if we did not.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 6:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 10, line 52, to add at the end of the line:&mdash;&ldquo;The report shall also set out the results of investigation by any viewer or listener research organisation for the period under review.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In this new service we are setting up, it is essential that the consumer, that is, the customer, be continuously consulted about the programmes he receives, and it is equally essential that the results of such consultation be regularly published.  That is the purpose of this amendment.  It is quite probable that listener research will develop independently for the guidance of advertisers, but, concurrently with that, the Authority should <Col N="581" /> conduct its own research and fearlessly publish the results.  Until now, listeners to Radio Éireann, if dissatisfied, could switch over to the B.B.C. but television viewers in four-fifths of the country will not have an alternative programme.  If we want to please most of the people, most of the time, consultation is necessary and we must inform the people themselves of the results of that consultation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment is also not acceptable as it is worded because it would compel the Authority to include in its annual report the results of any investigations into viewer or listener habits, whether carried out with its consent or not, or whether considered reliable or not.  I do not know if that is the Senator's intention, but that is actually what the amendment would do.</P>
      <P>Secondly, sometimes research reports at best can be no more than approximations.  They are based on samples and various general assumptions and there can be wide variations between the ratings given to the same programme by different survey organisations. Moreover, regardless of their statistical accuracy, they purport to measure only the size of the audience which is switched to a certain programme at a certain time, and not the degree of listening or viewing on the part of the audience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This does not mean that I am questioning the usefulness of audience research surveys or the competence of the people engaged in these activities. Such reports would be of particular interest to the advertisers who are interested primarily in the size of the audience who see their advertisements, rather than in the quality of the accompanying programmes and their impact on the people.  The Authority will also be interested in such reports when they have been examined and evaluated.  I have little doubt that the Authority, from time to time, will carry out such surveys itself or arrange with some organisation to have such surveys carried out for it, but I am not inclined to lay too much emphasis or too much importance on such reports <Col N="582" /> or to make of them a yardstick of the Authority's success or lack of success, and there is a danger of doing so if we write such a provision into the Bill.</P>
    <P>Having said that much, I should, at the same time, point out that the Authority will be quite free to include in its annual reports the results of any audience research survey carried out by it, or on its behalf, and I shall be empowered to ask the Authority to do so, but that is quite a different thing from placing a legal obligation on the Authority to publish any results of any surveys submitted to it.  The details of such surveys are open to different interpretations which might be unfair to the artistes concerned and it would be unfair to publish them in an unedited or, indeed, any prescribed form.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>The tenor of what the Minister has said is that we shall be afraid of answers.  It has been said to me that I wanted to get listener reaction to the amount of Irish language programmes televised, and I should like to learn from the listeners what they think about these programmes and whether they listen to them.  I find it difficult to believe that all listeners like to hear the lovesick teddyboys we have in the midday commercial programmes at present, and I want to know if many people listen to them.  We should have this reasearch and know the results of it, but apparently the Minister intends to keep the blinds drawn on that kind of information.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 7 not moved.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 8:</P>
      <P>In page 11, to delete lines 47 to 50 and substitute the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(2) The Minister may direct the Authority in writing to allocate broadcasting time for any announcements by or on behalf of any Minister of State in connection with the functions of that Minister of Sate, and the Authority shall comply with the direction.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="583" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment is proposed to meet the points made by various speakers on Committee Stage, that announcements by Ministers should be expressly limited to announcements within the scope of their functions as such.  The trouble about qualifying the functions of a Minister by adding &ldquo;as such&rdquo; is, I understand, that it would cast doubts on references to Ministers and Ministers' functions, wherever they appear in this Bill and other Acts.  It is different in Britain, I understand, because some of the Ministers there are not corporations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Are not what?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>They are not corporate bodies.  I think the wording now proposed would meet the points Senators wished to have covered and I have gone as far as I could to meet those points.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as my amendment on the last occasion is concerned,&mdash;which is down here as an amendment to the Minister's amendment&mdash;I agree that the Minister has gone a good way to meet us and I do not propose to move my further amendment.  I think the Minister has met the points raised.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 8 not moved.</P>
      <P>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stage today.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill as it now stands is to some extent different from the Bill that came in here. The Minister displayed a very stiff attitude, but relented&mdash;whether under the stress of argument or owing to the charm of certain Senators who proposed amendments, I cannot say&mdash; and in the end agreed to certain types of amendment.  The Bill has been discussed in great detail, and leaves the <Col N="584" /> House with certain amendments, but substantially as it came in.</P>
      <P>There are two things to be said about it.  First, the Bill gives the Minister and the Government complete control over the new television service that is being combined with the old Radio Éireann sound service. It is another step&mdash;we have taken a great many such steps in this State &mdash;towards nationalisation or socialisation, towards giving the State more power.</P>
      <P>The second point is connected with that, and it is that this measure will cost the taxpayers a great deal of money.  It gives the State power, and the State will have to pay, and that means that the taxpayer pays, so that beyond all doubt we have taken another step on the road to socialisation; and it will cost us not only £2,000,000 of a capital sum, but a considerable sum of money for a considerable number of years.</P>
      <P>I do not want to hold up the Bill, or the House, but I should like to develop briefly these two points. There is nobody of opinion in this country, practically speaking, in favour of State control.  Yet, we have in fact a system of government which gives more power to the State than the State has in Britain, where they have had for several periods a Government in office whose policy was, then, at any rate, nationalisation.  We are a highly centralised and socialised State.  Begin anywhere you like-begin with the E.S.B., with Comhlucht Siúicre Éireann.  We have a nationalised transport, we have nationalised our own sources of fuel and power in Bord na Móna; we have Irish Shipping; and we have had a radio service which from the beginning was controlled by a Minister.  We are now combining that radio sound service with a new television service, and we are giving that entirely into State control.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The body to be set up under this Bill as it now stands has much less power than the corresponding body has in Britain.  The State gets more power under this Bill over the new broadcasting Authority than the British Bill of 1954 gives to the <Col N="585" /> British Government.  This body will be more controlled than the similar body in our neighbouring island.  The Authority cannot appoint a Director-General without the consent of the Minister.  As we heard to-day, it cannot appoint an auditor.  It can enter into contracts only with the consent of the Minister.  Under Section 31, it can be prevented from broadcasting certain things and directed to broadcast certain things by the Minister.</P>
    <P>Following the strenuous and continued resistance of the Minister in Committee to amendments, under this Bill as it now stands the new broacasting Authority can be instructed to broadcast certain things or to refrain from doing certain things and can say so only with the consent of the Minister. That is another difference between the broadcasting Authority here and in Britain.  We have here a body set up which the Minister told us at the end of the Second Stage he meant to be independent, but which most certainly is not independent at all.</P>
    <P>Secondly, a commission was set up by the Government to discuss certain proposals from private interests with regard to television.  I am personally entirely without knowledge on this matter, but it would appear that proposals were made which would relieve us from expenditure and, at the same time, set up a television service here under the authority of an Irish State board.  That was entirely rejected in favour of public control and public enterprise, and I think inevitably in favour of the expenditure of public money.  No firm estimate has been made by the Minister in connection with this Bill, as to what the financial returns will be for the money expended.  No firm estimate is possible, apparently, except that in so far as we can discover anything about it in other countries, even in small countries, it is a very expensive service.</P>
    <P>It may very well be that in our national position, we cannot avoid this expenditure, and it would be fairer and clearer, and honester to the taxpayer, if we were to say to him: &ldquo;We cannot avoid having this service; we <Col N="586" /> want to be completely in control of it because we want to maintain certain standards, and in that position, we shall have to pay; that is to say, you, the taxpayer, will have to pay.&rdquo;  It is unfortunate, I am afraid, that we fail to look reality straight in the face.</P>
    <P>We cannot be sure, as Senator Barry has told us this afternoon, what the viewers will want to look at, and the listeners to hear.  There is no method by which we can ensure that.  Advertisers on this very expensive medium can afford to wait and see.  Both viewers and listeners have alternative services which they can easily reach, so that it seems to me that the prospects of this service being a paying one are very slight, and the proper thing to say to our people is: &ldquo;We propose to give you a State controlled broadcasting and television service, and you should pay for that.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Those are the facts, but they are concealed in the section of the Bill which enjoins on the Authority the duty of making broadcasting pay, but which does not in any way ensure that they will be able to make it pay.  All our experience is, that having expended £2,000,000 on capital for setting up a station and several subsidiary stations, having increased expenditure on the provision of broadcasting and television services, and having employed a certain number of people, we shall certainly keep on, whatever it costs.  There is no doubt about that.</P>
    <P>With regard to the Authority itself, I should like to say one final word.  We should have more confidence in them, should select them carefully, and should give them more scope than they get in this Bill.  No matter what adjective the Minister uses, they are cribbed, cabined, and confined at every turn. The Minister is completely in control, and one result of that, whether you think it is good or bad, is that there is complete parliamentary control as well.</P>
    <P>I am glad we have had an opportunity in this House of discussing a Bill of this importance, and that we have been able to do so at some length, and in great detail, without ruffling anybody's feelings.  The Minister should be congratulated on the <Col N="587" /> fact that he certainly has an excellent grip of his own temper, but perhaps he has not got a temper.  In any event, I should like to say, as I said at the beginning, that this is another step towards giving the State more power, and it is an additional burden upon the taxpayer.  On that basis, it will have to be considered in the other House and ultimately again perhaps here.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator Hayes has said, this new experiment of ours will cost the taxpayers a great deal of money, but, as I mentioned in a previous debate, there is some risk that it will deprive some of our citizens of their honest earnings.  In the briefest possible terms, I should like to impress upon the Minister that, by this Bill we are subsidising competition against the cinemas of Ireland.  It will be very difficult for them to pay tax and, at the same time, compete against a form of entertainment which is being subsidised out of taxation.  I suggest there is room for both forms of entertainment: they are both good and desirable.  But in this Bill, we are subsidising one form of entertainment and taking money from the other.  I appeal to the Minister to impress the injustice of this upon the Government before this Bill goes through both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope I shall not be outside the bounds of order in referring to an aspect of the Bill that seems to require some clarification.  If I am out of order, I shall certainly sit down immediately.  In the first place, I wish to repeat what I said on Second Reading about the great educational possibilities of television as a medium.  I hope the Television Authority will attempt to develop these opportunities which are being developed in other countries, and that school programmes will be arranged. I myself am convinced, from personal experience, that it is possible to learn such subjects as history, geography and the political affairs of other countries, better from television than from merely reading books.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill is a compromise between <Col N="588" /> purely private commercial television and a State service.  I entirely agree with what Senator Hayes has said, that possibly the Minister has rather too much control over the Television Authority.  It seems to me that the Bill is a compromise between a State service, in the narrow sense of the word, and commercial television which, so far as I can see, was recommended by the Television Commission. There has been set up, in accordance with many precedents, a more or less independent Authority. As I said on Second Reading, I believe that the success of the experiment will depend on the personnel of that Authority.</P>
    <P>One thing which has emerged from this debate is that the only hope of making Irish television pay is by getting abundant revenue from advertising. I think that in the course of the debate there has been a certain amount of misunderstanding regarding the functions of advertising in a commercial system.  Certain things have been said in the course of discussion which were unfair to the advertising profession and to the people employed by them.</P>
    <P>In the first place, I should like to refer to Section 20 of the Bill which provides that:&mdash;</P>
    <P>The Authority may reject any advertisement presented for broadcast in whole or in part.</P>
    <P>That seems to give to the Authority ample censorship over any advertising matter which may be presented to it. In the course of the debate&mdash;I hope I am not out of order; if I am, the Chair will please tell me&mdash;there were certain discussions about advertising which seemed to indicate that advertising is in some way a social evil, something that ought to be restrained, something of evil rather than of good influence.  I do not want to delay the House but there is a very interesting leading article in <i>The Times</i> of 25th January.  I want to quote just one sentence from that article.  &ldquo;Argument about advertising as a whole or particular manifestations of it is shot through with prejudice.&rdquo;  That is true.  The profession has been gravely misrepresented in the Press and to <Col N="589" /> some extent in the debates in this House.</P>
    <P>As I said, the success of this television service depends on advertising revenue.  The proposal of the Television Commission that it should be entirely handed over to commercial interests was rejected, notwithstanding the fact that the only possibility of reducing losses to some manageable proportions is by advertising on the television service.</P>
    <P>If I am not out of order, I should like to emphasise that advertising has a very positive part to play in a free economic society.  It is an essential condition of progress, in that it brings new products to the notice of the public.  It enables new products to be known and, therefore, it is an essential part of any programme for increasing the standard of living of the population.  The free working of competition cannot take place successfully, unless the public have the fullest information regarding the various products they can, buy.  Advertising provides that sort of information.</P>
    <P>It had been said in the debate that the cost of that advertising must be met in the price of the product and that, therefore, advertising will be expensive to the public.  I admit, of course, that a successful advertiser has to cover the cost of advertising as well as any other cost, but the justification for advertising is that the more efficient producer tends to succeed and the less efficient producer tends to fail.  With the increasing demand caused by advertising&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is going somewhat outside the scope of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of how far I can develop this point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has not gone very far.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 20 is in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>The more efficient producer succeeds and the less efficient producer fails and, therefore, with the increase in the size of <Col N="590" /> the market, the extra costs of advertising provide a more efficient product, a better product and a product that will sell cheaper than it otherwise would without advertising.  That is the case in favour of advertising.  The fact that articles sell cheaper is good, and good for the public.</P>
      <P>What I really want to argue, if I am in order, is that every argument used against television, advertising is equally relevant against all advertising.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The point is that we must keep to advertising on television.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to trespass on the time of the House. I have a lot of notes with me but I shall just go on to the final point in the speech which I have prepared, which I respectfully suggest is relevant to the Bill.  In the case of the Press, the value to the community depends on being able to convey information. In a free democracy, political information is given and information cannot be obtained unless there is a free competitive Press and a free competitive Press cannot exist without advertising revenue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I suggest the same is true of television. The television service will depend on advertising revenue.  We get this curious relationship between the licence fee and advertising revenue.  The power of television for good in the educational field, which I have emphasised, depends on there being a very large number of sets in the community, but the existence of a very large number of sets in the community depends on the licence fee being low.  If the licence fee is low, the Television Authority will have to depend more on advertising than if the licence fee is high.  The other consequence, if the licence fee is low, is that the advertising revenue will not be available, unless the articles advertised are articles which are advertised in such a way as to appeal to the masses.  Therefore, to complain that television advertising in other countries has been debasing public taste seems to be putting the cart before the horse.  The fact of the matter is that in regard to all media of mass <Col N="591" /> communication, it is not the vulgarity of the media which debases the public taste but the vulgarity of the public taste which debases the media.</P>
    <P>There has been a tendency for television in other countries to exhibit certain undesirable qualities&mdash;I could have enlarged upon that if I had proceeded with all the notes I prepared&mdash; but that is an argument, not against television, but in favour of raising the general standard of taste of the community. What we are faced with is that the great mass of the people are not educated up to the point where they appreciate highly cultivated presentation of advertisements, in the Press, on television or otherwise.  I do not wish to exceed the bounds of order.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is quite in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I simply want to repeat&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I draw the attention of the Senator to Section 20? If the Senator keeps to Section 20, I shall consider him fully in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.  If you will permit me to come back to that section, I should like to ask what are the grounds upon which the Television Authority should properly prohibit advertisement matter?  It seems to me that the power in the Bill is entirely unfettered&mdash;entirely at the discretion of the Television Authority. It is a matter of importance for the public to know just precisely what the case will be, what matter is considered undesirable and what, therefore, will be forbidden.  In the first place, any attempt to advertise anything which is illegal will be forbidden.  Also, certain standards of taste will be observed and anything in the nature of gross vulgarity will be forbidden.  In addition, there may be certain types of misleading description of, for instance, patent medicines, which, for public health reasons, may cause the Television Authority to censor certain types of advertisements.  There is one class of television advertising which is criticised a great deal in other countries. <Col N="592" /> It is televising of advertisements which encourage young people, teenagers, to wasteful extravagant expenditure.</P>
      <P>My suggestion is that the Television Authority have such powers to censor that it is most important they should not censor for the wrong reasons.  I should like to refer, without quoting, to a very interesting article in the current number of <i>The Economist</i> at page 624 entitled &ldquo;Consumers' Champions&rdquo;. I suggest to Senators that they could learn a good deal about the censorship of advertising on television by a study of this article.  Shortly, the conclusion is that the main complaints made to the Federal Trade Commission in the U.S.A. were not made on behalf of the consumers of the articles advertised but on behalf of rival producers and that the interests of consumers were rather overlooked.  I do not intend to quote that article.  I should like to refer to it because there are many problems which will confront the Television Authority dealt with in it.</P>
      <P>I should like to say, before concluding, that any censorship of television advertisements, apart from the special considerations such as I have mentioned, could lead to extremely dangerous political results.  If the Television Authority have the power to refuse advertisements for any particular type of thing which they object to on moral grounds, it really is setting up a new moral dictatorship in this country.  If the majority of the Authority were people who had very strong views about drink, they might refuse to permit advertisements in connection with the drink industry to be shown on television. If the Authority had strong views about smoking and tobacco, they might do the same thing.  Certain people might feel that hire purchase is bad for the community, that it runs people into debt and, therefore, they might exercise judgment in that way to prevent the hire purchase of articles being advertised.  I think there is a very real danger when the Television Authority have this complete, unbridled power to refuse to accept certain advertisements.  It is setting up a moral judge over the community if too much power is given to any particular committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="593" /> Politically, of course, as I said, a free capitalist society such as we live in depends upon the utmost freedom in regard to the dissemination of information of all kinds.  Business people and producers are entitled to commend their products.  The alleged line between information and persuasion is one which it is very difficult to draw.  After all, in giving information about one's product, one is entitled, I think, to commend it.  I do not think that anybody should be forbidden from commending his wares to the public.  Doctor Johnston, when he wrote an epitaph on one of his friends, said that anyone who is writing an epitaph is not on affidavit. Equally, those who compose television advertisements are not on affidavit. They should not be put in the dock and accused of perjury and their advertisements should not be refused the next time they come to the screen.</P>
    <P>Every argument that can be used in regard to restricting advertising on television applies equally to the Press. If people who are in favour of strict censorship of television advertising are consistent, they will follow up their campaign by having a strict censorship of advertising in the Press.  If they do that, the Press will find it impossible to pay its way and democracy will be endangered.  We shall be doing something which will have very dangerous consequences.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that Senator Hayes adopted the rôle of banshee on the final Stage of this Bill. I do not want to follow him point by point because most of the points which he made were amply dealt with during the discussion on the Second Stage. His complaint that we are now indulging in a further example of public control and public enterprise in the setting-up of this Authority as against the offers which were made by private people who apparently would have made, in his view, the whole service pay makes me feel that Senator Hayes would prefer to have seen the service operated by private commercial concerns rather than by the type of Authority which we are now setting up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that <Col N="594" /> at all and Senator Ó Maoláin knows that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>However, I feel that what has been accomplished by semi-State concerns, to which I adverted on the Second Stage, such as Aer Lingus, Irish Shipping and Bord na Móna, shows the effectiveness of this type of public authority and that this broadcasting Authority will prove just as effective as a method of achieving the aim in view as these other concerns.  I also feel that the country accepts the decision to set up this type of authority and that it has met with widespread approval.</P>
      <P>Senator Hayes is afraid that nobody can be sure of what the Authority will put on or what the viewers want to see and hear.  I have no doubt that with the directives contained in this Bill, the Authority will take every necessary step to ensure that the programmes and advertisements will be in accordance with the standards which we expect and that in due course, as a consequence of the excellent service which we shall get, the broadcasting and television, service will pay its way.  I do not see any reason for the pessimism Senator Hayes expressed and a few of the smaller countries of Europe just come to mind in that connection.  Surely if they can do it, there is no reason in the world why we cannot do it here. Irish initiative, originality and enterprise has proved sufficient to meet any challenges which were put up to it and I am quite certain that it will meet this challenge of our times too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In Austria, for instance, a small country, newly recovered from the devastations of a great war and years of occupation, there is a television service operating for only three hours daily and there are something like only 10,000 sets in the country. In Finland, also a small country, there are only 50,000 sets; in Portugal, there are only 2,000 sets; in Switzerland, there are some 40,000; while in Denmark, which is highly developed, there are 300,000.  If small countries similar to ours can keep abreast of the times and operate a modern television service and a sound broadcasting service which is a <Col N="595" /> credit to them, there is no reason to be pessimistic about our ability to do the same.  I believe we can do it and that time will prove that the Oireachtas was not wrong and did not act in error in giving power to set up an authority such as we are setting up to control radio and television broadcasting.</P>
    <P>Senator Stanford was worried about the effect which this might have on the cinemas.  I do not think that it will have the detrimental effect which he fears because we have the example of what has happened in the most highly civilised country in the world, the United States of America, where television is the most serious competitor the cinema industry has had and where as a result of the counteraction taken by the film producers, a 10-year slump in cinema attendances has been arrested.  In fact, the attendances last year showed a 20 million increase over the attendances for 1958. That, as I said, was because Hollywood has got into action and is hitting back with quality productions, new methods, such as Cinemascope and Tod-AO, and a better type of production all round.</P>
    <P>I see no reason to fear that it will have the effects which Senator Stanford and others seem to fear it will have. Certainly so long as the cinema is able to put on productions of quality and show a high standard, certainly it will not keep the people out of the cinema.  As far as the theatre is concerined I am convinced that theatre audiences will tend to increase and that the drama will get far more extensive support as a consequence of Irish television than it ever did before, because with television and with, I hope, in due course a Eurovision link, the great dramatists and authors of the world will be brought into the homes of our people and when their works are put on the stage in our theatres people will be more inclined to go to them to see for themselves the actual productions than they would have been before seeing them on the screen.  Television will be a wonderful asset to the theatres and it will not in any catastrophic way damage the attendances in our cinemas.</P>
    <Col N="596" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is going a little wide of the Bill on this Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the point mentioned by Senator O'Brien about advertising, may I say that I should like the Authority to take notice of the danger in regard to advertising which has manifested itself in other countries where advertisements are put in indiscriminately, not at stated times in the programme, at the end of programmes, but at critical moments in the programme.  I should not like to see that happening here.  I hope whatever steps can be taken to avoid it will be taken and that advertisements will be shown either at the end of each feature, or shown altogether at the end of an hour, or whatever way is considered most satisfactory to get over one of the most irritating things in a drama or in a sports-fixture, which is the showing of an advertisement on the screen just when somebody is about to score a goal or do something similarly exciting.</P>
      <P>I do not want to follow Senator Hayes point by point in the dismal picture he painted.  I should like to paint a brighter picture.  We are fortunate that we are now about to pass this Bill in Seanad Éireann, and bring ourselves into line with the other modern and progressive countries which already have this facility.  I am particularly interested that it should happen at this moment, and that Ireland will be in the line of progress because, as Senator O'Brien remarked, of the educational value particularly of the service which the people will get from the television and broadcasting Authority.  I am particularly glad that the Bill is being passed at this time, because of a programme I heard over Radio Éireann on last Thursday night which reminded me of the amazing developments which are taking place now in sound and visual communication.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senators have heard references during this debate to Eurovision which came into operation only some five years ago.  Today its network in Western Europe extends from Finland <Col N="597" /> to Italy; it will soon embrace Spain and Portugal and will cross the Straits into Africa.  Senators may have heard the excellent programme by Philip Rooney on Radio Éireann on February 11th, which marked the 10th anniversary of the foundation of the European Broadcasting Union.  In that programme, General Sir Ian Jacob, President of the Union, referred to further spectacular advances; in other words, the cause of complete continental coverage in which I hope we shall be active participants when we have our television service operating. General Jacob revealed that, in Geneva last week, arrangements were made, and initial steps taken, for a link-up by Eurovision with a similar network behind the Iron Curtain which will, when it is in full operation, give complete European coverage &mdash;continental coverage&mdash;and bring new vistas to the people here in the West and to those in the East.</P>
    <P>More important still, on the authority of such an eminent man, we are within a few years of the completion of the transatlantic link which will bring programmes from the New World into our homes in Ireland and, as we know, colour television is only around the corner.  According to the experts, in a short time, it will be as cheap as black and white television is now.  In the light of these rapid developments, and in view of the importance of this wonderful new medium of education and entertainment, we have no reason to be pessimistic that we are enacting this measure here.  I have no doubt that the taxpayers and the people of this country generally will not want to be left behind in that race, will not want to be left as one of the few untouchable nations which are not keeping pace with modern progress, and they will not grudge whatever licence fee is necessary to ensure that this country will maintain its place in the vanguard of progress.</P>
    <P>I am very glad that the Government saw fit to allow us to discuss this Bill in the Seanad first.  On the whole, I think the Seanad has handled the debate very well and I hope, as a consequence, this Bill will be the forerunner <Col N="598" /> of others introduced in the same manner.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Dr. O'Donovan Dr. O'Donovan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Donovan</NameTxt>
      <P>The statement just made by Senator Ó Maoláin was extremely enjoyable.  It reminded me a bit about that literary piece <i>The Vision of Fair Women</i>, because the emphasis, I think, was on the word &ldquo;vision&rdquo;.  I am not quite sure that this particular vision will come to pass!</P>
      <P>I wish to say a few words about the matter of Ministerial control over the Authority because I feel the Authority will not be free in the sense that other State enterprises and State bodies have been, in their day-to-day operations up to now.  In saying so, I am not making the case for more control of them.  It is a major problem; but specifically I want to refer to two sections in the Bill.  The first is Section 21 which states that committees are to be appointed by the Minister &ldquo;after consultation with the Authority&rdquo;.  &ldquo;After consultation with the Authority&rdquo; has no meaning in this context.  The Minister just writes and says: &ldquo;I propose to appoint a committee to deal with so and so,&rdquo; and they write back and say: &ldquo;We think, Minister, it is a very bad idea.&rdquo;  He then writes back and says: &ldquo;I have considered your views but I am going ahead with the appointment of this committee.&rdquo;  An Act was passed in 1946 dealing with the Racing Board and in it is stipulated that the Racing Board appoints its own committees.  It has the authority to appoint committees, somewhat similar to the committees envisaged here, to do subordinate work and to advise it.</P>
      <P>The other section in this Bill to which I take exception is Section 25 and I believe that subsection (3) of that section is completely out of place in a Bill of this sort.  It states:</P>
      <P>The Minister may, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, appoint the time, place and method of conducting the audit of the accounts of the Authority under this section, and may also appoint the accounts of which copies are to be furnished to the Minister under this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="599" /> I do not mind the second part of the sub-section because it is fairly common practice that State bodies like this publish one set of accounts and furnish a more detailed set to the Minister for Finance.  One example is the Sugar Company.  But the Minister gave us as a reason for the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs having the appointment of the auditors that it was control of State moneys which was involved. That is really not good enough. It may be a good stock Civil Service answer to a difficult problem, but, in fact, it is not correct because commercial auditors are of no significance in the control of money.  They may be of significance arithmetically to see the additions are correct and I can quote an instance in this regard that happened to me a long time ago.</P>
    <P>I had reason to object to the remarks of one of the semi-State companies in relation to the Department in which I was then working, and I thought I would get my own back by approaching the Comptroller and Auditor General because they had defected in a certain serious matter.  He told me: &ldquo;I am only a commercial auditor in this matter,&rdquo; and so I was stymied in my desire for revenge on this organisation for having pilloried my Department publicly.  Therefore, I say that a commercial auditor in the matter is of no significance in relation to the control of expenditure.</P>
    <P>As a second instance, I refer to the Transport Act of 1944, in particular to Section 29, which is the second under which auditors are appointed to audit the accounts of C.I.E., a company with an income at the moment of about £15,000,000 a year.  In passing, I hope this Authority will not run into quite the same astronomical losses as that body, though I am inclined to be less optimistic than the Minister.  Subsection (2) of Section 29 states:</P>
    <P>The Company shall at each ordinary meeting appoint the auditor or auditors and the auditor or auditors so appointed at any ordinary meeting shall hold office until the next ordinary meeting of the Company.</P>
    <P>There is a specific case where a company does not have to accept any <Col N="600" /> intrusion from anybody else and there are other similar cases of which I am aware.  I think the Sugar Company is another good example because auditors are appointed by the company on the nomination of the Minister.  That is a different thing. The company does the appointing. They usually write and say: &ldquo;Our auditors are so and so&rdquo; and the Minister replies saying: &ldquo;I am prepared to nominate them next year.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I do not understand why a change from that procedure was made in Section 25 of this Bill, placing a whole lot of operations into the hands of the Minister which, in my opinion, are quite unnecessary.  In addition to that, I feel there are too many general directions, too many expressions of hope and, indeed, too many sociological propositions in it.</P>
    <P>There is also, I am afraid, too much pretence in the Bill.  For example, we have the section I have already referred to, Section 23, which suggests that the £2,000,000 can be repaid in certain circumstances.  This is literally not feasible, and we should not pretend it to ourselves.  I believe that this service, if it is to be a good second-rate service, will cost a net million pounds a year for some years to come, and I do not think the Minister for Finance will have any million pounds a year available very easily in the next couple of years.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Stanford about the cinemas.  There is undoubtedly an element of subsidising competition with the cinemas.  It may be true that having got over the first impact of television in the U.S.A., as Senator Ó Maoláin says, the cinema is coming back through various arrangements, like drive-in-cinemas, but I am extremely doubtful if people will go as often to the cinema if they can have it in their own homes, which is what television gives them.</P>
    <P>Let me say straight away that all these criticisms are directed towards the nature of the kind of Bill we have got.  I welcome the service very much indeed, and I think that even though I live fairly high on the periphery of Dublin, the reception should be greatly improved.  There was a complete <Col N="601" /> obliteration of a Saxon score last Saturday, which was no great harm, because I could see it coming a long way off. If we had a booster station, we would get more reliable reception, as one does the closer to Belfast one gets.</P>
    <P>I should, like many other Senators, like to express appreciation of the attitude of the Minister personally in the House.  His attitude as a Minister in the House was rather different, if I could split his personality into two in this matter.  He was very patient and very good-humoured; he took the long debate extremely well; but he did not make many concessions. Though he made one significant concession, the sum total of his concessions to the House generally was not very great.  It is only right that we should be grateful to him for his kindness in the detailed way he dealt with the debate on Committee Stage, and if the Minister remains at the Department of Posts and Telegraphs for some years to come, I hope the service will not give him too many headaches.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>The debate on this Bill has been very constructive from many points of view, and if there have been disagreements between us, they have been discussed in a very objective way.  Fundamentally, we are all in agreement that it is right that we should keep abreast of modern developments, and have here a television service that will suit the tastes and needs of our people.</P>
      <P>While, however, we have been more or less in fundamental agreement on the provisions of this Bill, there seems to be a certain undue amount of apprehension as to this question of state control.  Senator Hayes introduced that topic in his final speech on the Bill this evening.  There must, of course, be a certain amount of overriding state control over all these undertakings, and I am sure that if the Minister came in with a Bill setting up a television and sound broadcasting Authority and giving it complete control to do what it liked with the amount of State money and taxpayers' money involved, he would be condemned by Senators for doing so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That being so, the approach of the <Col N="602" /> Minister and the Government to this matter has been the correct one.  It is what I would describe as a middle-of-the-road approach.  The Authority is to be set up under Section 4 of this Bill and given certain duties and responsibilities, in the carrying out of which there will be no interference in the ordinary course of events.  We gave, for instance, subsection (4) of Section 10, which says:</P>
    <P>Every question at a meeting of the Authority shall be determined by a majority of the votes of the members present and voting on the question, and in the case of an equal division of votes, the Chairman of the meeting shall have a second or casting vote.</P>
    <P>That is the usual procedure, and there is no Ministerial interference with that procedure as laid down here.  Then we have subsection (6) which states: &ldquo;subject to the provision of this Act, the Authority shall regulate its procedure by rules.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The only thing, then, is to consider whether the Minister and the Government should wash their hands entirely of the question of television and sound broadcasting.  I do not think they should.  The overriding policy-making control envisaged in the Bill is right and proper, and the Minister and the Government were wise not to divest themselves of that amount of ministerial responsibility.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Donovan gave expression to the view that there were too many sociological directives in this Bill.  I do not know whether that is the case, but I do not think it is. Perhaps it can be argued that there are, but in my opinion, there are not. In a matter of grave national importance&mdash;and this television and sound broadcasting service will be a very important national institution&mdash;it is only right and natural that certain directives should be laid down in this Bill.  As has been said before, the implementation of this measure will have a very great impact on the educational, cultural and social life of the people.  That must be borne in mind by us here, and more especially by the Government.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="603" /> As regards the question of Ministerial control, as I have said, it is right and proper that there should be a certain amount of overriding Ministerial control over an institution of this sort, when there is so much public money, so much of the tax-payer's money, and so much State money, involved.  I do not want to make a long speech because I realise that the debate must be rather circumscribed on Fifth Stage.  I should like to join with other Senators in expressing the view that the debate has been very helpful.  This is the first time we have had a debate of this kind on Second Reading, and I believe the members of the other House will find the discussions here very helpful to them in their approach to the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to echo what other Senators have said in congratulating the Minister and the Government for giving us an opportunity, for once in a while, of considering a Bill before it goes to the Dáil.  I feel that the debate in general has been good.  I said on Second Stage that I felt the Bill was a good one.  Clearly, I must hold the same opinion now because, even after amendment, it remains pretty much the same Bill.  What is in the Bill now, I feel, is very substantially what was there at the beginning.  It seems to me that the number of amendments of a type that might have been legitimate and desirable were few and, therefore, I am pleased that the whole Bill remains pretty well the same as it was when it came to us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to touch very briefly on a point made by two or three Senators on the question of interference with the cinemas.  I feel that Senator Ó Maoláin was right when he suggested that the long-term effect of television, which is only one part of this Bill of course, upon the cinemas and the theatre, may be good, that the general cultural effect of good television may well lead people to read more and go more often to the theatre and the cinema.  If that is true in the long term, it may well be true that the cinemas, by the terms of this Bill and by the action taken under the Bill, <Col N="604" /> may, short term, be hit rather harder than they are now hit.</P>
    <P>In that regard, there is one point I feel I should make on the question of pity for the cinemas and so on. As a consumer, as it were, I remember times when the cinemas seemed to have very little pity for the consumers. Most of us remember days when there were long queues kept in the rain for the purpose of encouraging the consumer to go to the dearer seats.  When one finally got in, the big picture had already started, and one found that there were after all many vacant seats in the cheaper parts of the cinema.  In other words, some cinemas abused the cinema's entertainment monopoly when they had the power to do so. That point should not be entirely forgotten when we are asked now to have pity on the cinemas.  They were not themselves always filled with pity for the consuming public.  Although nobody wants to see them hit, nevertheless we may remember that some abuse was indulged in by the cinemas at the expense of the public.</P>
    <P>This Bill is after all only an instrument, but I think the structure it provides is a good one.  The Minister rightly has been complimented on the way he brought the Bill before the House, on the reasonable way he listened to us&mdash;at some length, I am afraid&mdash;and on his patience.  I feel that perhaps he might have conceded one or two more points.  I notice, for instance, that Section 20 remains unchanged. It stands as it did in the beginning, although he promised that he would look into the matter of this special concession for Irish advertisers and the special concession for people advertising through the medium of Irish.  The Minister promised he would look into that matter but the Bill is as it was.  I think perhaps that that is a little defect in the Bill at the moment. On either of these issues, the provisions of the Bill as it now stands are not wise.  On the one hand, I do not feel that the differential in advertising in favour of Irish Nationals is sound or defensible, and on the other hand, the implication that you must compensate for advertising through the medium of Irish seems a curious Government <Col N="605" /> admission implied by the text of the Bill as it still remains.</P>
    <P>One or two important amendments made by the Government are part of the Bill.  Section 31 was the only section that seemed to me to merit a major change and I should like to express appreciation of the fact that on that point the Minister met some of the objections of the Seanad.  Subsection (2) of Section 31 as it now stands, is a distinct improvement upon the original drafting.  I feel I should apologise to the House for not having been present when an amendment which stood in my name came before the House, but I think the House will recognise that I do not usually sin in that regard&mdash;worse luck, some may add.  I rather regret that the Minister, having said a lot about the necessity for trusting the Authority, and having confidence in it, has found it necessary to retain in the Bill the right to have a complete veto over &ldquo;any particular matter or a matter of any class&rdquo;, if he thinks fit.  Not merely that, but he has the right even to prevent the Authority from telling anybody that he has exercised that veto.</P>
    <P>These are the points in the Bill, as it stands, which I regret, and which I venture to hope will be changed by the Dáil.  I do not want to speak at length, but I should like to say in general terms that I think this Bill, relating to sound broadcasting and television, is potentially an excellent one, and can produce an excellent service in both these media.  My confident hope is that from this good structure, this good Bill, a good service will emerge.  In practice, I believe that the sound broadcasting service will improve.  It has already reached a reasonably high standard, but it is still capable of improvement. I think it will improve under the increased independence given to the Authority, and my hope is that a television service will emerge which will be something of which we can all be proud.</P>
    <P>As I say, I believe this Bill to be good potentially.  I think these services will be good in practice, but that will be the case only if initiative, <Col N="606" /> imagination, and independence are exerted by the new Authority.  Therefore, it falls to the Government to see to it that they give this Bill a chance to fulfil its great promise by appointing a first-class Authority and a first-class Director-General, and then giving them a free hand.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>I just came in at the heel of the hunt this evening.  I am sorry I missed the second half of the debate on Committee Stage last week. It was unavoidable, as I was absent on business in London.  I am glad to have been here in time to say that I wish the Authority every success. I think, as other speakers said, that we had a most interesting debate.  It has been a most stimulating experience for the Seanad to have had this Bill in its first stages in this House. I met a member of the other House recently who said he was very glad to see that the Bill was in the Seanad and he hoped that more would be introduced in the Seanad as it would enable members of the Dáil to read up in advance the views of other people on a Bill.  Up to now, the reverse situation was in operation, but on this occasion we can claim to have made an original contribution to a Bill.</P>
      <P>In view of the many statements, repeated from time to time, about the alleged failure of private enterprise to participate in major schemes of national importance, I cannot refrain from pointing out that this charge cannot be sustained on this occasion. As we know, some nine proposals were actually made to the Commission by private enterprise firms or groups who were willing to risk their money in this venture.  This is in the nature of a major adventure in our national broadcasting system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>These proposals, as I said on the Second Stage, were not only considered but formed, I think, very much the basis upon which many of the decisions were arrived at to set up our broadcasting, and especially our television Authority.  They pave the way for the path they will follow. I think it is only reasonable that somebody should say some time that private enterprise on this occasion certainly <Col N="607" /> has not failed to come forward to undertake a major national task, even though it was with the profit motive in view.</P>
    <P>That being so, I think the Authority should try to keep in mind the necessity to make this service pay and that it should be run on commercial lines. I hope that in a few years' time we shall not find the Authority looking once more to the Exchequer to finance deficits.  I do not say that in any depressing manner.  I think the Authority should be made feel that they must run this service in a commercial way.  That is not to say that they should override the considerations which, in fact, were the ones which decided the Commission to advise that the Authority should be put in complete charge of this and under State control.</P>
    <P>For my own part, I do not find any fault with the decision.  It is probably the best thing to do in the circumstances. If private enterprise had, in fact, been given the task of carrying out this service, I think they would have been very much under fire and criticism&mdash;perhaps, unfair and unjust criticism.  In the long run, for the sake of private enterprise in which I believe so much, I think the best decision has been made in this case.</P>
    <P>I should like to conclude by once again stating that at least on this occasion, it cannot be stated that private enterprise has failed to come forward to carry out this business.  I wish the Authority and the Minister every success in this venture.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>I did, as Senator Sheehy Skeffington pointed out, give an undertaking on Committee Stage to have another look at Section 20, subsection (5).  There were two main criticisms of the subsection.  The first was that there should be no difference in treatment as between Irish and foreign advertisers.  In other words, that the directive in the first part of the subsection should not be given.  I am afraid I cannot accept this.  The subsection, in effect, enjoins the Authority to encourage Irish advertisers <Col N="608" /> to make use of their own service. Many foreign advertisers operate on huge advertising budgets.  Most of them will probably have advertising inserts ready for use, whereas Irish concerns, on much smaller budgets, will have to have them designed and made before they can start advertising.</P>
      <P>Radio Éireann at present grants a certain measure of preference to wholly Irish concerns.  The Authority is, in effect, being asked under the subsection to consider carefully granting a measure of preferential treatment to all Irish advertisers.  In this regard, as Senator Hayes has rightly pointed out, it is very difficult to define what is Irish and I am considering adding a subsection to define what is an Irish advertiser when this Bill goes to the Dáil.  It is not, I should add, intended that the preferences should be restricted to businesses which are wholly Irish-owned&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Preference for the Irish language?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;as is the case in regard to sponsored programmes broadcast by Radio Éireann at present. The second point mentioned was the question of extending the preferential treatment envisaged in subsection (b) of Section 5 for the use of Irish in advertisements to all advertisers.  On reconsidering this matter, I am inclined to agree that a preference in the use of Irish should be given to anybody who uses it.  Here, again, I propose to consider having the subsection amended on Committee Stage in the Dáil.  I could not get this matter cleared in time to have the necessary amendments inserted in the Bill today in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am, indeed, grateful for the reception this Bill has got in the Seanad.  I do not propose to reply in detail to the speeches made on this stage by Senators because I have, in so far as I possibly could, replied definitely to the points raised during the debate on the Committee Stage.  I am also grateful for the usefulness of the debate in this House.  I feel that the more the debate is read by people interested, the more it will be apparent that the debate was in itself a useful contribution <Col N="609" /> to the measure and the method by which the Government should endeavour to see that the Authority is manned by the best possible people, that the Director-General should be the best possible person and that the personnel employed by the Authority, when it is set up, will be the best possible people they can get.</P>
    <P>I felt, and I expressed the view when introducing the Bill, that the Bill was a good Bill and that it was soundly prepared.  I am still convinced, after listening to the debate in the Seanad, that the Bill is a sound Bill, a good Bill and is soundly prepared, and that if the proper people are appointed to the Authority and if the services of the people who are competent and capable to carry out a service of this nature are got, we need have no fear that our broadcasting service will not be of a very high standard and of a very high character, and that it will be of immense service to the people.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Petroleum and other Minerals Development" RHead="Bill, 1959&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Petroleum and other Minerals Development Bill, 1959&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch) Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>Broadly, the purpose of this Bill is to facilitate the carrying out of a comprehensive scheme of exploration for oil and natural gas in Ireland.  There can be no certainty that petroleum deposits exist in this country in quantities that could be worked economically.  At the same time, the benefits that would accrue to the national economy from the discovery of petroleum in worthwhile quantities would be so valuable that it is desirable that a scheme of exploration should be undertaken which would establish whether oil or natural gas occurs in quantities which would be capable of being developed economically.  Exploration for oil is very costly and highly technical, and it is desirable that it be carried out by concerns which have the necessary up-to-date equipment and adequate <Col N="610" /> experience of similar work in other parts of the world.</P>
      <P>Oil and natural gas, which are covered by the term petroleum as used in this Bill, are found in association with sedimentary rock formations. Such formations are fairly extensive and of moderate thickness in Ireland and, although there is no direct evidence, it is possible that oil could occur in these formations unless it has been released by disturbances during their long geological history. The main oil producing areas of the world are in the Middle East and the American Continent, but oil has also been found in Western European countries in quantities somewhat greater than might have been expected, having regard to their geological structure and history.  Holland, France, Western Germany, Austria and Italy have all undertaken oil exploration and development with varying degrees of success.  Great Britain has also carried out extensive oil exploration at considerable cost, but only limited quantities have been discovered up to the present.  A report published in December, 1957, by O.E.E.C. in regard to the development of the oil resources of Western Europe is discouraging in its assessment of the prospects of finding oil in Ireland, but the fact that applications have been made to me for the grant of oil prospecting facilities indicates that in some quarters, at least, the prospects are not regarded as too discouraging.</P>
      <P>The existing legislation relating to petroleum exploration is contained in the Petroleum (Production) Act, 1918, and the Minerals Development Act, 1940.  These Acts were passed at a time when there was little prospect that exploring for petroleum would be undertaken in this country, and they do not provide adequate means for facilitating large-scale exploration programmes.  I am satisfied that new legislation must be enacted to facilitate comprehensive exploration under the most up-to-date conditions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Bill provides for the vesting in the Minister for Industry and Commerce of all petroleum in the State and empowers him, by the grant of licences and leases, to secure that any <Col N="611" /> petroleum deposits that may be discovered will be developed efficiently. There is provision in the Bill for the grant of compensation to the persons who formerly owned the petroleum rights if petroleum is subsequently found and worked, and also to persons whose land may be damaged by operations carried out in searching for and working petroleum deposits.  A number of the provisions of the Bill are already contained in our general legislation relating to minerals, but it is desirable to repeat them in this Bill in order that all the legislation relating to petroleum may be contained in one measure.</P>
    <P>Mineral ownership in Ireland presents a mosaic of holdings varying from 100 to 1,000 acres in extent.  About one half is already in State ownership. The balance is in private ownership but it is frequently difficult to determine who are the legal owners.  It is obvious that oil companies could not be expected to enter into commitments to spend money on oil exploration in Ireland if they were faced with the endless difficulties associated with negotiations for the acquisition of oil rights with a large number of private owners.  It is necessary, therefore, that, subject to the payment of compensation, the State should acquire title to such petroleum rights as are not already vested in it.  If, at any time in the future, petroleum is found and worked, the owners of the petroleum rights which are now being vested in the Minister under this Bill will be entitled to a royalty related to the royalty rent reserved by the lease.</P>
    <P>In oil producing countries, the general practice is that profits earned by oil operators are shared with the Government.  The most common arrangement has been one which provides for profit-sharing roughly on a 50-50 basis, though some of the major oil producing countries are now demanding a higher percentage. Generally speaking, the more favourable the prospects of discovering oil, the higher the percentage of the profits demanded by the State.  The Bill provides for the sharing with the State by way of royalties or similar payments <Col N="612" /> of the profits earned from the sale of any petroleum that may be found here.  Having regard to the relatively poor prospects of discovering oil in economic quantities in Ireland, I am satisfied that it would not be reasonable in present circumstances at any rate, to insist upon a 50-50 profit-sharing arrangement.</P>
    <P>As Senators are aware, I have entered into an agreement with American oil interests for the carrying out of a comprehensive scheme of exploration for petroleum in this country and for the working of any deposits that may be found.  The Agreement, copies of which were laid on the Table of the House, will not come into operation until this Bill is enacted.  I ought, perhaps, to say that I have not had from any Irish interests a satisfactory scheme for the carrying out of a full scale exploration programme for oil.</P>
    <P>The company with which the Agreement has been made is Ambassador Irish Oil Ltd., an Irish registered company which will be a wholly owned subsidiary of Ambassador Oil Corporation, Fort Worth, Texas. Ambassador Oil Corporation are an organisation with extensive practical experience of oil exploration and the working of oil fields and they have the resources necessary for the carrying out of a comprehensive exploration for petroleum in Ireland.  Under the terms of the Agreement, their subsidiary company, Ambassador Irish Oil Ltd., will be given exclusive exploration rights over the whole country for an initial term of five years, and, if they meet their obligations under the Agreement, over 75 per cent of the country for a further 5 years, 50 per cent for a third term of 5 years and 25 per cent for a fourth term of 5 years.  They will be entitled to prospecting licences and mining leases in any area over which they have exploration rights.</P>
    <P>During the first three years of the first five year period, Ambassador Irish Oil will be obliged to spend at least 300,000 dollars on exploration and to drill at least one well to a depth of 5,000 feet.  If they do not meet both these obligations, the unexpended balance <Col N="613" /> of the 300,000 dollars will be forfeited to the Minister, and they will have no right to any further prospecting rights or to any mining leases which may have been granted to them in the period.</P>
    <P>If the company, having met these obligations, does not elect to proceed with further exploration they may retain any leases acquired by them up to that time but will have no further right to leases or to explore further for petroleum.  If they elect to continue exploration after the first three years, they must spend a further 200,000 dollars during the remaining two years of the first five year term.  If they do not spend all that amount of money in the two years, the unexpended balance will be forfeited to the Minister and they will have no further right to exploration licences or mining leases but they will be entitled to retain any leases acquired in the first three years.</P>
    <P>If Ambassador Irish Oil meet all the obligations which I have mentioned, they will retain the right to any leases granted to them during the first five years.  If, however, they spend 1,000,000 dollars in the first five years, they will have, in addition, the right to renewal of their exploration licence for a further period of five years but must surrender to the Minister for Industry and Commerce 25 per cent. of the territory.</P>
    <P>During the second period of five years, Ambassador Irish Oil will be obliged to spend at least 750,000 dollars but, if they actually spend 2,500,000 dollars, they will be entitled to renewal of the exploration licence for a third period of five years over 50 per cent. of our territory.</P>
    <P>During the third five year term, Ambassador Irish Oil will be obliged to spend not less than 750,000 dollars but if they actually spend 4,000,000 dollars, they will be entitled to renewal of the exploration licence for a fourth term of five years over 25 per cent of our territory.</P>
    <P>During the fourth term, Ambassador Irish Oil will be obliged to spend not less than 750,000 dollars but, if they actually spend 5,000,000 dollars, <Col N="614" /> they will have a preferential right over other applicants, other things being equal, for renewal of their concessions. If, in any specified period, Ambassador Irish Oil fail to spend the appropriate minimum amount, then the difference between what they spend and the specified minimum sum is forfeited to the Minister for Industry and Commerce.</P>
    <P>If, during any five year term, Ambassador Irish Oil have spent more than the minimum amount but not the amount which entitles them to automatic renewal, they may &ldquo;purchase&rdquo; such automatic renewal by paying the difference to the Minister for Industry and Commerce.  As I have already indicated the Bill provides, in accordance with normal practice, for the sharing with the State of profits earned on the sale of oil and gas.  The effect of the provisions relating to this matter which are contained in the Agreement is that the contribution payable to the State will never be less than a 7½ per cent. royalty computed on the selling price of the oil or gas or more than 40 per cent. of the company's net income as defined in the Agreement. Having regard to the very speculative nature of any project for seeking and working petroleum deposits in this country, I consider that this arrangement is a reasonable one.</P>
    <P>In addition to the provisions relating to petroleum, the Bill provides for certain amendments to the Minerals Development Act, 1940. These amendments have been found to be necessary as a result of experience gained in the administration of the Act, and it is useful to include them in the present Bill.  At present, for example, the Minister for Industry and Commerce is required, before granting a prospecting licence, to serve one month's notice by registered post on each surface occupier of land in the area covered by the licence.</P>
    <P>When this provision was made in the law, it was not anticipated that prospecting licences would cover large tracts of land.  The present practice, however, is to give prospecting licences for relatively large areas, and this means that formal notice has to be served on hundreds of surface <Col N="615" /> occupiers.  In the circumstances, I feel that, in the interests of administrative convenience, the publication in a local newspaper of notice of intention to grant a prospecting licence should replace the existing arrangement.  A map giving details of the area affected will be made available for inspection in the Geological Survey Office and in the local post office, and, in this way, the interests of surface occupiers will be adequately safeguarded.</P>
    <P>The Act of 1940 provides for compulsory acquisition by the Minister of ancillary rights, e.g., the right to construct roads, the right to a supply of water, the right to cross lands adjoining a leasehold, but I am advised that the Act is defective because, <i>inter alia</i>, it does not empower him to assign such rights to the holder of a State mining lease.  It is desirable that this defect should be remedied in relation to oil and other minerals and this is being done in the present Bill.</P>
    <P>A prospecting licence issued under the Act of 1940 may not be expressed to apply to named minerals but is deemed to apply to all minerals and, in effect, therefore, it confers on the licensee an exclusive authority to search for all minerals in a given area. I propose to amend the Act of 1940 so that, in future, the authority conferred by a prospecting licence may, if necessary, be confined to one or more specified minerals so that the Minister for Industry and Commerce will be in a position to authorise different persons to prospect for different minerals in one area.</P>
    <P>It is my hope that the Bill will commend itself to all Senators, and that there will be general acceptance of the principles of the measure.  On its enactment by the Oireachtas, the first major scheme of petroleum exploration in Ireland will commence. Ambassador Irish Oil Ltd. will apply to me for an exploration licence within three months of the enactment of the Bill, and they will be required within a further three months to make substantial deposits in an Irish Bank of moneys to cover expenditure during the first part of the exploration programme.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="616" /> It will, I am sure, be appreciated that the Bill has been prepared on general lines which will make it possible to facilitate a number of exploration projects for petroleum.  As I explained, the first project will be carried out by Ambassador Irish Oil Ltd., but it is possible that, after the completion of this project, or of such part of it as the company may decide to undertake, other groups may formulate proposals for exploration programmes. The wide basis on which the Bill rests will make it possible to grant any reasonable facilities which may be necessary for the purposes of carrying out a number of successive exploration projects.</P>
    <P>I hope that, on its enactment, the Bill will provide the facilities which are necessary for the exploration and development of whatever oil deposits we may possess.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to welcome this Bill with the minimum of words and, to the Minister's relief, with the minimum of knowledge.  The subject matter of the Bill is one for lawyers and engineers, and I am neither.  In fact, I feel strangely like the boy who once stood on the burning deck because those people whom we had competent to discuss this Bill are not here.  I do not know what the physical results will be on the Irish scene as a result of this legislation, but I hope what will be done will be done neatly and discreetly, and that the Irish scene will not be destroyed thereby.  I also hope that eventually we shall see Irish farmers like Middle East sheiks, driving around in goldplated Cadillacs.  In essence, it is a Committee Stage Bill.  We have had a long television session and I propose that we give the Minister the Second Stage now and deal further with the Bill in Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The principle of this Bill is quite acceptable.  I think there is no other method by which this work could be carried out, but owing to a curious set of circumstances, the person who was to deal with this matter in Committee is not available now.  I should like to ask the Minister to postpone the Committee <Col N="617" /> Stage, on the understanding that certain matters will be raised then. We shall have no objection to his getting all Stages on the next day the Seanad meets.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>For what length of time does the Senator propose that we postpone the Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Until the next meeting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>March 2nd&mdash; this day fortnight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>There appears to be no necessity for any comment from me, except, first of all, to thank the Seanad for the manner in which the Bill has been received.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Do I understand that the Minister is closing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not think anybody else wanted to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say something, if I may?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry; I did not see the Senator rise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I also am sorry that I did not see him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to welcome the general principle of the Bill, which vests a portion of the mineral wealth of the nation in the Government of the State.  When it was suggested by the Professor of Geology in Trinity College that possibly there might be oil in County Clare, it caused a certain amount of excitement to Kilrush Town Commissioners, to the county council of Clare, and in the whole county and indeed the rest of the country.  It was a very tentative statement by Professor Gill, but it was taken up with great enthusiasm in Clare.  It occurred to me, when I saw all this enthusiasm recorded in demands by Clare County Council for action by the Government along the lines now suggested by this Bill, and for immediate attention to be paid to this professor's statement, that I should look up and see whether County Clare was one of these <Col N="618" /> counties which permits its people to hold scholarships in Trinity College. I found that it was not.  Possibly if, finally, oil is struck in Clare, it may have a broadening as well as a deepening effect on the sentiments of the people, reflected not merely in gold Cadillacs, but perhaps in a slightly more liberal outlook also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very doubtful if the Senator is in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not talking about petrolem now.  He is asking for something else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I am adverting to the possibility of oil being struck in Clare along these lines, and the possible effects like gold Cadillacs, which have been suggested.  I am satisfied that equally good spiritual benefits in the way of more liberal thinking might accrue from the striking of oil in such circumstances.</P>
      <P>I am a little surprised, though it will come up no doubt on Committee Stage, that nobody has risen to say that the Minister is taking on behalf of the State very considerable powers to interfere with the rights of the individual, rights of property and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I notice that among the ancillary rights as defined in Section 3 there are all kinds of rights to be given to the holder of various types of licences.  I take one almost at random.  It is paragraph (i) of Section 3.  It gives the holder a right to dam or divert any river or watercourse, including an artificial watercourse.  The same section also gives a right to construct, operate, and maintain roads and railways for access and egress for the purpose of conveying petroleum, and for that purpose to use and occupy land and to exercise any right in or over land, and so on.  You will, if you get one of these leases, be able to go through anybody's lands, road or railway, to divert rivers, and watercourses, and so on.  I am not suggesting that such powers will be abused, but I am adverting to the fact that the Minister is asking for very considerable powers to be conceded to him in this Bill, which, could, if abused, lead to considerable interference with individual <Col N="619" /> rights.  There might even be a question of this not being fully constitutional.</P>
    <P>I notice that in Section 13 there is a subsection which provides that if in the opinion of the Minister it is in the public interest that petroleum under specified land shall be granted by way of lease to any person, the Minister may demise such petroleum to that person by way of lease for such term as the Minister thinks proper.  I should like to ask what exactly is in the Minister's mind when he is thinking of the terms of such a lease.  Possibly it is, as he suggested, along the general lines of the lease granted to the American company, that is, a not very long period, of five or ten or 25 years.  I should hope that such leases would be of short duration, and not of the absurd type granted sometimes in ground leases, and so on, for 500 years and that kind of thing.</P>
    <P>The Minister has adverted to an agreement with an American oil company.  It is quite natural that an outside company with experience of this kind of thing should be allowed to come in to do this, though I do remember that the European Economic Commission of the United National Organisation produced a report upon oil which surveyed the oil and the petrol situation, and one of the conclusions of which was that American interests in oil were artificially keeping the price of oil and petrol at a figure almost double what it would be in Europe, if we were allowed freely to buy oil from the Middle East, without the interference of these controlling companies.</P>
    <P>That is a point that ought to be in the mind of the Minister at any rate in dealing with these companies from Texas, in whose interest is to show that no oil can be produced more cheaply than it can be in Texas, because that is the burden of what this United Nations Committee says, that the price of oil per barrel as produced in the Middle East was very nearly half the price regarded as economic in Texas and so had to be artificially increased.  I hope the Minister will have this in mind, and that <Col N="620" /> possibly Irish oil, if it comes to the surface, may be used to some extent to break that kind of international artificial price rigging.</P>
    <P>I notice that Section 16 covers compensation for damage to the surface of land or to mineral deposits, or to water supplies caused directly or indirectly either by working or doing anything incidental to the working of petroleum, or by exercising the right of entry on and user of land.  Under that section, a person shall be entitled to compensation.  May I take it that that paragraph covers any work resulting from ancillary rights for the purpose of gaining access to or egress from the land?  I am sure that it is comprehensive.</P>
    <P>I notice that the Minister is to bring into being and permit these ancillary rights &ldquo;by order&rdquo;.  The rights are very considerable, and I should like some comment from the Minister as to what shape the order will take, whether it will be laid on the table of the Oireachtas and in any sense be open to question or debate.</P>
    <P>The Minister has also said that notification in the newspapers would be regarded as sufficient in order to safeguard adequately the interests of the people involved.  Perhaps I have read this too hastily, but I do not quite see what people who are dissatisfied with the intention to grant a lease in the locality or to grant ancillary rights can do about it if they are dissatisfied. The Minister has suggested that their interests are adequately safeguarded if they are publicly told that certain of their rights over their property are to be taken from them.  I would ask him if that is really fully safeguarding their interests, unless we say clearly what they can do about it?  It is almost like saying: &ldquo;We are going to take over your farm, and give you one month's or three months' notice, and since we are doing this publicly your interests are adequately safeguarded.&rdquo; There is a <i>non sequitur</i> there, unless I have failed to see some paragraph that shows what they can do about it if dissatisfied with this rather abrupt way of telling them that certain rights that vest in them are no longer to be vested in them by reason of a ministerial order.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="621" /> I do not want to delay the House further.  I think the Minister has been bold in this matter.  He has gone very far in it.  My hope is that it will result in the good of the State and the community.  I am tempted to recall that people like Fintan Lalor suggested that some such idea as this should be applied to the land of Ireland&mdash;that the land of Ireland should be vested in the State and the people, and that the people should hold it by lease from the community, in the precise way the Minister is now suggesting for petroleum.  Perhaps the Minister and the Government are, judging by this Bill, beginning to tread those paths towards socialism along which Fintan Lalor had the hope we might some day be going in this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>There are two points I should like to mention to the Minister which might perhaps be more relevant on Committee Stage but which I shall mention now.  I refer to Section 16 where damage to the surface of the land is dealt with. &ldquo;Damage to the surface of the land&rdquo; is the point with which I want to deal. I do not think that compensation payable to a neighbour is dealt with in the Bill.  Let me deal with it in this way.  Supposing the Minister gives a prospecting licence for a certain area and the Ambassador Oil Company decide to bore on the borders of that area, is there anything in the Bill to compensate the owner of the neighbouring land who is not in the area for damage not so much to his land as to the amenities: the outlook and the enjoyment of the land?  There could be a serious difficulty there in a demand for compensation from a person whose property has been reduced in value by the fact that the company might put, at his front door, a large construction which might be of a permanent nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is one other point I should like to mention to the Minister.  There is a section which compels the company or the Minister, in certain circumstances, after boring, to leave the area, or the bore-hole, in a safe condition only.  I should like to see it left, so far as possible, in the condition in <Col N="622" /> which it was previously.  A &ldquo;safe condition&rdquo; might mean that the bore-hole was left in a safe condition but outside it there might be deposits from excavations.  Those points can be dealt with on Committee Stage but I should like to hear the Minister on them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The points raised by both Senators Sheehy Skeffington and Cole are really Committee Stage points, even though Senator Sheehy Skeffington may have, in fact, touched on some matters which are fundamental. The position as regards the granting of leases is that a person who is in possession of an exploration licence will have a statutory right to a lease, and the giving of a lease will be attended with the greatest possible degree of endeavour to secure that adequate compensation will be given. That will also apply to the giving of ancillary rights.  All ancillary rights which the Minister may acquire must be adequately and fully compensated to the owner of these rights.</P>
      <P>So far as length and conditions of lease are concerned, the conditions will naturally be related to exploration or drilling for oil, and the length will also be related to the life of the oil deposit, which is usually about 20 years, maximum. It is not likely that any of the leases given under the Bill will exceed 20 years, and in most cases they will probably be for less than 20 years.</P>
      <P>On Senator Cole's point about the danger of affecting a neighbour's land in respect of which no rights have been sought or given, I think the answer is that this Bill will not preclude a person from seeking his ordinary civil law remedy in respect of damage done to property not included as part of an exploration or drilling operation.  The Senator need have no fears that anybody who is an innocent victim of these operations will not be properly provided for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The bore-hole difficulty which he mentioned was one which I myself raised in the Dáil.  The manner in which it was met was ample to ensure against any danger or any <Col N="623" /> damage that might occur as a result of leaving a bore-hole in a defective condition.  The owner of the land on which that borehole was opened would be fully compensated for any damage that might be done to his property or to his stock.  He would be fully compensated even after the operators had departed from the scene.  There is a provision whereby the Minister himself would be responsible, in the event of the operator not being available or amenable to the jurisdiction.</P>
    <P>In that case, Senator Cole need entertain no fears about the possibility of bore-holes being left inadequately protected and causing damage.  There is a provision that they must be properly protected and in the event of their not being so protected, the compensation provision will be adequate.</P>
    <P>So far as the oil deposits in county Clare are concerned, as Senator Sheehy Skeffington knows, these deposits proved to be refined oil.  If there were sufficient known deposits of oil throughout the country, it would not be necessary to enter into this agreement with the Ambassador Oil Company.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 2nd March, 1960.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 5.40 p.m. and resumed at 7 o'clock.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Seanad Electoral Law Commission:" RHead="Implementation of Recommendations">
    <Title>Seanad Electoral Law Commission: Implementation of Recommendations.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann is of opinion that the Government should introduce legislation to implement the recommendations of the Seanad Electoral Law Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Perhaps I should first say one or two words about the background to this Commission.  The Commission was appointed by the Government after a debate in the Dáil which took place on 20th November, 27th November <Col N="624" /> and 4th December, 1957, reported in Volume 164 of the Dáil Debates, column 835 and what follows.  The motion was fairly direct. It was simply this: &ldquo;That Dáil Éireann is of opinion that Seanad Éireann as it is at present constituted should be abolished.&rdquo;  Some pretty hard things were said about Seanad Éireann in that debate.  I think it is unnecessary for me to repeat them.  But I shall mention some of the more constructive things that were said.</P>
    <P>First of all, the proposer of the motion, Deputy Noel Browne, did say in connection with the vocational organisation of the Second Chamber: &ldquo;In the vocational bodies, there must be a fund of experience and a special knowledge which would be of great value to us here in formulating legislation, amending legislation and perfecting legislation.&rdquo;  The difficulty as he saw it was how to find a way to enlist this valuable help to the legislature.</P>
    <P>In the course of the debate, Deputy O'Donnell praised the Seanad to some extent and pointed out that Fine Gael had always been on the side of the Seanad.  Later, Deputy McGilligan justified, as he thought and as I think, the expenditure of some £50,000 a year which he reckoned was the cost of the Seanad to the country.  Then towards the end of the debate, the then Taoiseach, Mr. de Valera, spoke. I quote Volume 164, column 1454-5. He was speaking about his aims in 1937 in the new Constitution:</P>
    <P>My hope at that time was that, after a period, we would be sufficiently organised vocationally in the country, and that the panels which were indicated in the Constitution would be such, that the members for these panels could be elected directly by vocational bodies. I still have a hope that that day may come, that it will be possible, after we are organised sufficiently, to allow the vocational bodies to elect members for these panels directly.  I thought that, in the meantime&mdash;and there I have been completely disappointed&mdash;the method of nomination would so <Col N="625" /> limit the number of persons who would be going up for election that, in fact, no matter what the electorate was, as the panels from which the electorate had to select would be definitely of a vocational character, the electorate would not matter very much.  In that I was disappointed, because the tendency has been for the bodies which have the right to nominate the panels to have regard to the electorate in selecting people to represent vocational groups.  They look forward to having persons elected by the electing body, and since these electing bodies comprise members of the Dáil, the county councils and so on, since the electorate is of a political character&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>With great deference, I challenge the use of the word &ldquo;political&rdquo; in that sense; and I shall challenge this later on</P>
    <P>&mdash;&mdash;the names are thought of rather from the political Party angle than the purely vocational one.  It is that that has prevented the aim I had in the Constitution from being achieved.</P>
    <P>He went on to say that he would agree to appoint a commission.  On the basis of that, Deputy Browne withdrew his motion and the debate ended. The Commission was set up shortly afterwards.  Obviously this debate reflected a good deal of public discussion in the country for the past 15 years.  As such, it deserves both the respect due to a debate in the other House and as voicing widespread public opinion.  I think we should keep that in mind clearly in our debate this evening.</P>
    <P>The Commission was appointed on 8th May, 1958 and concluded its work on 26th February, 1959. Here I should emphasise the terms of reference of the Commission.  It will save some unnecessary argumentation this evening, if we keep this closely in mind.  The terms of reference of the Commission were these: to make recommendations regarding any legislative changes within the provision of Article 18 and 19 of the Constitution which the Commission would consider <Col N="626" /> desirable.  Now, those were the terms: &ldquo;within the framework of the Constitution,&rdquo; and although we need not restrict the debate to those terms this evening, in discussing what the Commission did, it is important that they should not be criticised for going outside the terms of the Constitution because in fact they were not entitled to do so.</P>
    <P>In the Report, there was a very large measure of agreement, although it was a varied and representative body.  There were only two dissentients,&mdash;one was Deputy Corish who represented the Labour point of view, that the Republic did not need a second Chamber&mdash;and the other, a point, by Major de Valera I shall refer to later.  The Report is complex in detail.  It would be quite impossible to go into the numerical abstrusities underlying it in our debate this evening.  I think we may get somewhere if we confine ourselves mainly to general principles and to the one chief recommendation.</P>
    <P>Let me first say something about the general principles which are involved. First of all, we are committed in the Report of the Commission to maintaining a second Chamber.  We know that one of our political Parties does not believe that a second Chamber is desirable.  But I would appeal to the members of that Party who are in the House to join the debate on these terms&mdash;I think it is a fair proposition&mdash;to join on the formula that as long as Seanad Éireann remains with us, it should be made as effective as possible for the purpose of promoting good legislation, of influencing public opinion and for the general welfare of the country.  While we have it, let us try to make it as good as it can be.  I do not suppose that anybody, the Labour Party or others, would object to that principle.</P>
    <P>Now we come to the first difficult question.  Supposing we are to continue to have a second Chamber, what is the best kind of second Chamber? It has been much discussed since 1922 and there has been plenty of disagreement, and I imagine there will be some disagreement this evening, but it is fairly widely agreed that the Seanad should not be a kind of second edition <Col N="627" /> of the Dáil.  It should be different not merely in the persons but in the system of election, and a good many people have held the view that it should not be directly controlled by the political Parties.</P>
    <P>Here we come to a crux, and I am well aware of it.  I should like to emphasise my own views&mdash;shared I think by a good many people&mdash;on the political Party system.  It can be a beneficial system; it is the only workable system at present in many countries. It can do harm and it can do good.  Like any machine, it is morally neutral: it depends on how it is driven.  Like a motor car on the roads, sometimes driven recklessly and badly and sometimes driven well. Therefore, I hope that members of the Parties will not take it that because I am an Independent, I am hostile to the political Parties.  I am not.  Our country has been reasonably well governed by them for a very long time.</P>
    <P>I should like to say that I recognise in this House, for example, how often it is that the Party members keep a quorum in the House.  Sometimes the Seanad could not continue, unless the devoted and loyal Party members stayed on until 10.30 or 11 p.m. when many of the less closely involved members tend to go home.  I just wonder whether there might not be a risk that sometimes the House would not be kept if the Party system were not there to keep it.  So I am simply trying to show that the Party system has a very valuable function in the Seanad.  What I argue is this: it is not the only desirable system; it is not the only conceivable system of electing House of this kind.  I am arguing, as many have done, that there is room for independence and room for something like vocationalism.</P>
    <P>Before I return to the Report, may I say something else?  I most deeply deplore the misuse of the word &ldquo;political&rdquo; by the highest in the land to the lowest in the land.  It is constantly used in this House as a term of abuse or depreciation.  People get up and say: &ldquo;I am not being political.&rdquo;  My reaction to that is to <Col N="628" /> feel inclined to get up and say: &ldquo;If you are not being political, go out of this House.&rdquo;'  This is a political body in the noble sense of that word, as well as perhaps in the ignoble sense, and it is really most deplorable for the young people of this country that they hear experienced politicians talking of being political as if necessarily it was a bad thing.  Once again: politics may be good, bad or indifferent, but at its best, it is the noble art, the kingly art.</P>
    <P>Just a few minutes ago, my colleague, Senator O'Brien, reminded me of how Cardinal Newman had praised training for politics, how Cardinal Newman had reminded his hearers that the chief object of a liberal education in Greece was to produce a nobly political man.  So it offends me when I hear that noble word constantly being abused.  We ought to discriminate between politics in the general sense, good or bad, Party politics in the general sense, good or bad, and independent politicians in the general sense, good or bad, and not degrade that noble word.</P>
    <P>Here I should like to quote Deputy Major de Valera's addendum to the Report.  He insists very rightly&mdash;this is on page 25 of the Report&mdash;that the Seanad must be a political body or else it simply does not deserve to exist. He is afraid if the Parties go, sectional interests may increase.  I hope to meet that point of view in a moment or two, but I think we all welcome his insistence that we must all be politicians here.  Our job is to make this House as good a political body as we can and the question is: how can we do it?</P>
    <P>If it is entirely a replica of Dáil Éireann, with different people but thinking in the same way and voting in much the same way, it will not, I think, deserve its place in the nation. Many people have held, and the then Taoiseach emphasised this in the debate in the Dáil, that the best thing to do is to give the vocational system of organisation a chance.  I should say it has had some chance already.  We have in the Seanad men of vocational background who are serving the purposes of the Seanad well.  But there <Col N="629" /> are a good many people in the country who feel that we need to increase that element to increase the vocational slant, so to speak.  Here I imagine a good many people would say: &ldquo;You are wrong; vocationalism is not the answer.&rdquo;  Well, I wait to hear those views expressed later in the debate. For the moment will the House allow me to go on the assumption that vocationalism may be the answer?  What then?</P>
    <P>I now turn to the text of the Report. First of all, I should like to point out that we members of the Commission heard plenty of views on the matter. On page 29, and the following pages, will be found a list of some 34 different recommendations for the reformation of the Seanad.  These were considered well and carefully.  Yet an almost unanimous recommendation emerged.  The essential page in this report is page 27&mdash;&ldquo;Summary of Principal Recommendations&rdquo;.  I do not think I am doing the report an injustice if I say that what really matters in it is this: the recommendation that 23 members of the changed Seanad should be both nominated and elected by the vocational bodies.  In other words, 23 seats will be assured to the vocational panels.</P>
    <P>At the moment there is no such assurance, since the first choices of the vocational bodies may not be elected at all.  In some cases, some very worthwhile vocational bodies have put forward very worthy people and those candidates have not received even one or two votes.  But, under the proposed system, if it comes in, certainly 23 will be both nominated and elected.  Really that is what we should debate to-night.  That is the essential thing.  Would it be better for this Seanad that 23 of us should come directly elected from the vocational bodies instead of being simply nominated by them and elected by the Seanad, Dáil Éireann and the county councils?</P>
    <P>There is one major objection to this which was raised by Deputy Corish on page 24.  This is what he says:</P>
    <P>The franchise is still limited; the method of nomination rests on an <Col N="630" /> unsatisfactory so-called vocational basis and the power of nomination by the Taoiseach is perpetuated in the new proposals.</P>
    <P>We shall leave the second matter out of the count.  I do not propose to dwell on that but I would say the Report of the Commission makes a very good effort to make the electorate from the vocational bodies a genuinely comprehensive electorate.  There will be no question of Senators being elected by one or two small bodies. We have done our very best to do that and the recommendations are in the Report.</P>
    <P>Secondly, I would like to emphasise what appears in the middle of page 23, which states</P>
    <P>These changes...</P>
    <P>that is, the recommended changes&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>...represent a stage, rather than the completion, of a process of evolution towards a Second Chamber composed predominantly of persons who have attained positions of distinction, if not eminence, in their vocations or occupations and we would like to record the wish that after a trial period...</P>
    <P>and this is very important&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>...the development of the Seanad should be further reviewed to see if any further advance along these lines would be of advantage in the administration of the State.</P>
    <P>At this point, I do not think I should go into details.  I simply suggest that if we accept this basic recommendation that 23 members of the Seanad should in future be both nominated and elected by the vocational bodies, it will be an improvement. There will be 23 members nominated and elected vocationally.  There will be six University members who may be taken as, perhaps, vocational.  That makes 29 vocational members in a sense.  There will be 11 of the Taoiseach's nominees, and the remainder remain pretty well under the control of the political Parties.  So, to put it crudely, there will be 31 under the direct control of the political Parties and 29 under the direct control of the vocational bodies.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="631" /> That is a compromise.  It is neither one thing nor the other.  But I do suggest it is a reasonable compromise.  It is a compromise that was agreed to by a very distinguished list of thoughtful people, both political and vocational, and I recommend it to the Seanad.  As a matter of principle, I suggest it is worth while at least to try the effect of increasing the vocational element in the Seanad in the hope of improving its political effectiveness.  It is worth while.</P>
    <P>I suggest, then, that the Report of the Seanad Electoral Law Commission supplies a reasonably good basis for legislation towards that end.  I repeat with emphasis that some of the detailed recommendations will probably have to be changed in the Bill that will come before Parliament, I hope, fairly soon.</P>
    <P>It is no use this evening discussing minor points.  They can be left for emendation in the course of legislation. In fact, if we give approval to this Report this evening, and if the Government decide to bring it before the Houses of the Oireachtas, the Oireachtas may still reject the whole proposal.  We are not committing ourselves to very much this evening. But at least the whole problem will be widely ventilated in the Oireachtas. If, on the other hand, we reject this motion this evening and if the Government do not bring the proposals of the Commission in one form or another before the Oireachtas, I can see no hope of change or improvement in the Seanad for certainly 20 years to come.  This is our chance for good or for evil, and I think it is worth trying.</P>
    <P>Finally, I want to make one aspect of the matter quite clear.  In my belief, we have had a succession of Seanad which have been worthy of respect.  That is my considered opinion based on my experience of the Seanad since 1948.  We already have a valuable amount of vocationalism in the Seanad.  But all human institutions are capable of improvement. Here in this Report, as I see it, there is a definite and promising plan for our improvement.  I hope the <Col N="632" /> Seanad will show both magnanimity &mdash;and it does need some magnanimity to face one's own improvement bravely and frankly&mdash;and wisdom in meeting the challenges and opportunities embodied in the Report.  I look forward to hearing the debate with the greatest interest.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to second this motion.  In doing so, I find myself in the curious position of disagreeing somewhat with the recommendations of the Commission, but for the purpose of having this matter discussed here, I shall proceed over that difficulty as rapidly as I can.  I do, in fact, lean to the view expressed by Deputy de Valera in his reservation to the main Report, that injury may be done to the societies and organisations nominating candidates, if they obtain complete power of election to this House.  I think it is inevitable that interior political stresses would develop inside those organisations, and indeed the House must agree that it would be undesirable.  These stresses would certainly flow from the proposal for direct nomination.</P>
      <P>There is a way of reducing that danger.  My proposal is that the present electorate should be leavened by adding to the voters list in each panel a proportion of special electors from such organisations.  There are roughly 850 of what I would call national electors, the present electorate of this House.  For each panel, you could add, say, 100 to 200 electors selected by the organisation concerned.  The number would depend on the number of seats available in that panel.  These electors could vote only for their particular panels.  This extra proportion of votes would influence the results and would provide a vocational or special interest flavour in the Chamber ultimately elected.  This is as far as we could or should go.  It would certainly prevent complete injury being done by political cleavage inside the nominating bodies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to make a comment about the politicians.  There does seem to be what I can almost describe as an accusation that this is a political Chamber.  No second Chamber in any parliament in the world is non-political. <Col N="633" /> If it were, it would be useless. The kind of woolly assumption that you run into quite a lot outside that the second Chamber should be another kind of Institute of Advanced Studies, for instance, is just impractical.</P>
    <P>By the way, Senator Stanford is completely removed from any comments I make about the Independents in the House.  There is an assumption commonly held by the less literate and encouraged by some of the more literate outside that those who support political Parties diminish in some way the abilities which apparently they would retain, had they remained on the political sidelines.  This is a very naïve viewpoint.  We are governed by the Party system, and those who take part in any capacity in the work of organising and maintaining political Parties are as much a part of our system of government as those who sit on the front benches, and they make a much greater contribution than those who sit on the sidelines.  Because of that contribution, I have more respect for those who oppose me than for those who sit in prim neutrality, unsullied by political tasks.  I hope this House will never be non-political.</P>
    <P>With that, I am afraid, rather dubious benediction on the motion, I hope the House will very fully debate this subject, and if it does so, my purpose in seconding it will have been achieved.  I hope that the watered-down proposal I have made will be acceptable.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>I have much pleasure in supporting this motion.  I should like to say straight away that when I came into this House first, I held the opinion that this should be a vocational Chamber, because up to that time I had spent a lot of my life&mdash;and I have spent a lot more since&mdash;working in vocational bodies, and in fact I have been president of several vocational bodies and in those positions I even made speeches advocating a vocational Seanad.  But I have lived longer since then and I hope that, on this subject at any rate, I am somewhat <Col N="634" /> wiser.  The concept of a non-political Chamber is quite unrealistic in our political situation.</P>
      <P>It seems as a result of constant reiteration to have got into the heads of many people in this country, first of all, that there is no need for a Seanad &mdash;which we are not discussing here tonight&mdash;and, after that, if there is a Seanad at all, it should be a vocational one.  I have now changed my mind&mdash;not that I am changed in any way about my views on the part that vocational groups and vocationalism should play in our national life, or political life&mdash;as to the degree of participation which these groups should, in fact, take in the legislation of our State.</P>
      <P>As this is a political assembly and as our system is a political one, if an attempt were made to create a purely vocational Seanad, I am absolutely certain it would result in a completely chaotic situation.  It would play havoc with our legislation because our legislation, no matter what kind it is, must work from some basic philosophy.  What basic philosophy could you get from a Chamber consisting of 60 people from different walks of life?  No matter how clever or good they are, they are bound, because of their very nature, to have 60 different outlooks on a problem.</P>
      <P>Were you have these 50 or 60 people or whatever the number is, with different outlooks in different spheres coming together in a political Party, that philosophy can be argued out and a policy pursued which is not necessarily a-toe-the line policy.  It comes forth in the form of a political policy.  It is only on such a basis that a Chamber could be run with any sense of decency or order.  If you had 60 Independents representing 60 different vocations, I know that even vocational bodies themselves know what a chaotic position they would be in and what a chaotic situation we would find ourselves in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Incidentally, as Senator Barry said, no such Chamber exists in any other country in the world.  I should hope that in this particular form of life we will not be leaders in such a thing. <Col N="635" /> I think that we would find it unworkable and that it would be held up as a laughing-stock.  Many people who believe in a vocational Seanad do so by reason of the fact that they have not gone into the matter deeply.  They have no experience of how a legislative assembly works.  Our system of government is a political Party one and in our legislative assembly, we have a Government which has been elected as a majority Party who are responsible for legislation.  They have come together on some basic philosophy.  That group is responsible for legislation.</P>
    <P>On the other hand, the system provides for an alternative Government which must either be a Party or a group of Parties.  Therefore, even in the smallest debating society, whether school or university, it has been found absolutely necessary to have speakers for and against whatever the motion is.  They have to pick sides to start with.  The same thing applies in the highest assembly.  We have the Party Government on the one side and on the other, we have the Opposition, which is the alternative Government.  Up to now, we have had that.  We have been rather confined to those.  The Seanad has definitely been divided as between the Government Party and the Opposition Party, with a few Independents thrown in.</P>
    <P>I think that is wrong because the line between the Government Party and the Opposition Party tends to be rigid and hard.  It is desirable, especially in the Seanad and also in the Dáil for that matter, but we are talking about the Seanad, that the hard line between the Government and the Opposition should be blurred. The way to blur that is by having, as is now proposed by this Commission, and as we already have, the six University Independents.</P>
    <P>We are entitled to expect from University representatives a broad and wide vision which is got from university training where people look out in a broad way over life and over the problems of life and the problems of the State.  University representation is necessary.  Up to now, we have had <Col N="636" /> a rather remote form of vocationalism. As we know, the actual election requires another qualification, that is, adherence to a political Party, even for the vocational representative, but under this proposal, it is now proposed to give 23 to the vocational bodies.  I have always been an advocate of making available the advice, help and participation of vocational bodies in the political life of the country, which up to now has been lacking.</P>
    <P>In the recommendation by this Commission, it is proposed that there should be 23 vocational nominees elected to the Seanad.  That is the only change suggested in this recommendation. I think it is a dramatic change, a change which is highly desirable and one that should, and, I have no doubt, will work.  I think that we shall now have the political Parties on which our whole base is built represented to the right degree and in the right strength to maintain the political stability of our Chamber and our legislation.</P>
    <P>All our legislation is political.  It is quite unrealistic to talk about having a Chamber dealing with political legislation that is a non-political body. One thing is a contradiction of the other.  With the eleven nominated by the Taoiseach and the 20 from the existing election to the Oireachtas panels, we have got the right degree of political control, if you like to put it that way, and of our legislative machinery, but with the six University representatives and the 20 coming from the vocational bodies, we have a strong background of independent and expert criticism which can be brought to bear on legislation without the feeling that it is tied to the Party line.  I use the phrase &ldquo;Party line&rdquo;, as I already explained, in its best sense. It is the line that has been decided on, not by any whipping or compulsion, but after debate in another place.</P>
    <P>I feel that under this system we shall now have the very best form of Chamber which will give the right balance to all the elements of the community which should be represented in our Chamber.  Therefore, I have much pleasure in supporting the proposal of Senator Stanford.</P>
    <Col N="637" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that the three speakers who have already addressed the House have not been too enthusiastic in their support of the recommendation embodied in this motion.  Senator Stanford himself was not too enthusiastic about it.  What impressed me certainly was that Senator McGuire spoke mainly against the substance of the motion before the House but finished by saying he would support it.  That is how I interpret his speech.  He said many things in which I should concur entirely.</P>
      <P>I was here from the formation of the first Seanad in 1938 under the vocational system established under the Constitution. Down through the years, there was not until recently a direct political Party sense of opposition in this House.  I distinctly noticed that in recent speeches, especially from the other side of the House, there was this reference to &ldquo;your Party&rdquo; and &ldquo;our Party.&rdquo;  There were always supporters of the Government in power.  I was a supporter of the Fianna Fáil Government but I was nominated by a vocational body.  I always boast of the fact that I probably would never be in this House, if I were not nominated by a vocational body.  I probably would never be in this House, if I were to be elected under the system recommended now.</P>
      <P>Let me try to amplify that statement. Throughout the years, amendments were made to the electoral system of Seanad Éireann and one of the recommendations embodied in the legislation was a screening system to reduce the number of candidates on the panels.  That meant five representatives from each nominating body and the number of candidates nominated by the individual bodies would be reduced. There was a sort of obsession that we should have, step by step, a system of simple vocational nominations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That did not work satisfactorily. Looking at the cultural and educational panel to which there are 14 nominating bodies, I think I am interpreting the recommendations correctly when I say that eight members <Col N="638" /> from each of those nominating bodies, to constitute a number over 100, would be 112.  Those 112 members from those variously constituted bodies with various nomenclatures would have to elect three members to the Seanad.  I doubt if they would do it as satisfactorily as the electorate at present constituted.  You may get a person who is very eminent in his own profession, very well known perhaps throughout Ireland and even possibly abroad, but I want to say boldly that he might not be good as a representative in this Seanad, because politics are current history.  Implying improper motives to representatives is bad, and that is what I deprecate as happening in this House recently. The implication was that one political Party would do such a thing, appoint such a person, and then the other speaker says: &ldquo;If we were in power, we would do the same thing.&rdquo;  That is a bad system, but although I say it is bad, it would be just as unfair to have an eminent surgeon, let him be a veterinary surgeon or other surgeon, an eminent musician or a man eminent in any branch, elected by these 12 nominating bodies.</P>
    <P>I say definitely that I was nominated by a vocational nominating body.  I had to face an electorate and, if you wish, I can claim to be vocational because the various bodies who elected me, county councils or county borough councils, are vocational. There are farmers, Labour people, Independents and there are members of political groups.  However, I had to face them and I was probably nominated because of the fact that I would have appeal.  If you wish to designate it as a political electorate, I had to clear two fences, so to speak.</P>
    <P>On the whole, the present recommendation is not satisfactory.  If I were nominated by the veterinary profession&mdash;the Veterinary Council of Ireland is a nominating body&mdash;I would rather face a political electorate, if you want to call it such.  It is a cross-section of the community who have been elected democratically by the electors of the Republic.  I would rather face that composite wide electorate than the <Col N="639" /> 112 members selected from the 14 nominating bodies on my cultural and educational panel.  I say that boldly. I do not know whether it is a good or a bad thing but I think I would have a better chance of being elected by the wider electorate than I would have by that restricted two-sectional vocational electorate.</P>
    <P>I think I have made my personal position as clear as I can put it to the Seanad.  My personal reaction would be that I would like to see 23 members of the Seanad elected as vocational representatives but I do not think that the system recommended by the Commission is the best system for doing that.  I have indicated why I would not like it operating in respect of the largest panel.  When we come down to the Labour Party, where there are only three nominating bodies, I do not know how it would work at all.  You would get a higher number of electors but it would not be a widespread vocational electorate.  It is simply three trade unions: Cómhar Céard Éireann, the Irish Trade Union Congress and the Irish Conference of Professional and Service Associations. These are three nominating bodies who elect a far greater number to the Seanad on the vocational sub-panel alone than the cultural and educational Panel elect.</P>
    <P>I do not think this is the best system. I have expressed that opinion and I would not like the Seanad to vote tonight on the acceptance of Senator Stanford's motion which he so eloquently proposed to us.  I should like other Senators to express their opinions as I am to express mine.  The Seanad is the Second Chamber set up under the Constitution. It is, to a great extent, a vocational body and it was to a greater extent, a vocational body.  I can imagine that people outside would say: &ldquo;Well, they are all politicians and they are seeking to get representation simply because they are seeking extra direct vocational representation.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I simply want to express an opinion that the introduction of direct vocational representation into the Seanad might not be a good thing.  We must be a political body. <Col N="640" /> Some must support the Government and some undoubtedly must oppose the Government, as is necessary in the democratic government of any democratic country.  We cannot dictate to any Government here and I really think that a slight alteration in the number of vocational members to be elected, that is, 23 vocational nominations against 20 direct Dáil nominations, would be better than this idea which, with the best will in the world, may not be satisfactory. You may get eminent people who would not be the best members of any House of the Oireachtas.  If they come in here, they must act politically. Politics are current history. They must deal with legislation which comes before the Houses of the Oireachtas and in most cases that legislation will have no relationship to the vocation through which they were nominated and elected to the Seanad.</P>
    <P>I can say for myself that it is very seldom that matters of interest to the veterinary profession come before the House.  When they did, however, I think I may boast that I contributed very satisfactorily and secured amendments to Bills of veterinary interest.  I may mention one, the Clean Wool Act. Seven amendments were adopted which are of immense benefit to the wool trade of the country, which has in recent years gone from tens of thousands to well over a million pounds.</P>
    <P>It is very seldom that matters of immediate interest to a vocational representative come up and the other 95 per cent. of the work will not be of immediate interest to him and that would not be the best thing.  It would not be the best thing to have a person here who was not interested in doing work on behalf of the nation, on behalf of the Government of the country, other than what was of immediate interest to him.  I do not think we have had any legislation here so far dealing with the Royal Irish Academy or many of the nominating bodies.  It would not be the best thing to have a person elected to the Seanad because of the <Col N="641" /> publicity gained by having his name before the public.</P>
    <P>The previous Taoiseach, when he nominated what we used sometimes call his soccer team because it constituted 11 players, sought to represent a cross-section of the country and did not nominate people because of their absolute political affiliations.  I could mention names but I shall not mention them here.  When he nominated members of his team of eleven, they represented different vocations, different callings, in the country.</P>
    <P>I would say with Senator McGuire that vocationalism has gone a bit too far maybe at present.  The trade unions are vocations; the veterinary associations are vocations; and they are all looking for a bigger slice of the cake.  We are just going perhaps too far in this idea of vocationalism, and if we have a greater direct entrance to the Seanad Chamber by members as representing the vocation to which they belong, it will not be the best for the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. P. Crowley Mr. P. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>As the elected representative of a vocational interest, I am rather diffident about speaking at all on this question, but as Senator Stanford, I think, quite rightly pointed out, it is the duty of every member of the House at least to express his view on this important question.  We are the people, after all, who have been through the electoral mill, as far as the present system is concerned and we should at least give the Government the benefit of our experience of seeing this system in operation.  I must say right away that I find myself not entirely in agreement with Senator Stanford in his support of the recommendation of this Commission.  I think the recommendation itself is just a little bit simple, an over-simplification in dealing with a very complex and difficult problem.  I am not at all satisfied that the results which may be expected from any system of direct nomination and consequent election to this House would, in themselves, justify the risks obviously inherent in the adoption of that system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I find myself in agreement with <Col N="642" /> Senator Barry: it is clear that you will in fact inject politics, in the undesirable sense in which Senator Stanford used the word already, into the social and economic life of the country in a very undesirable way.  Apart altogether from that, we should also recognise that there are many vocational groups in the country who at the moment have no right of nomination to this House and I do believe that many of them would be found never to have hoped to claim such right.  Yet they are vocational.</P>
    <P>Again&mdash;I think this is too obvious to debate at any great length&mdash;is it not quite apparent that the adoption of the over-simplified system recommended would create a whole lot of other anomalies?  We will have people, many of them associated with one or other vocational group, who would have or be entitled to have duplication of votes in elections.  I do not think the Seanad should debate at any length that aspect because I am sure the defects in such a system must be apparent to anyone with any experience at all of the political life of the country.</P>
    <P>I have experience of two elections to this House and certainly it is rather a task to anybody to have to face the electoral college.  Nevertheless, I can truthfully say, having gone through that experience, that the existing electoral college&mdash;even though it may not be described as perfect; it is in fact unwieldy and a rather unusual system to adopt&mdash;is a body through which we get the nearest thing we can have to a Seanad elected directly by the people. Short of running, so to speak, a second general election for the Seanad or issuing two ballot papers in general elections, one for the Dáil and one for the Seanad, I do not think we could have a body elected that would be more representative of the people.</P>
    <P>The present electoral college has the great merit of being national in character and representative of a very wide section of the people.  Bearing that fact in mind, I rather think that we should not run away with the idea that the defect, if there is a defect, in representation in this House is simply <Col N="643" /> due to the electoral college.  I doubt very much if any suggestion to enlarge the present representative character of the electoral college by adding to it any number of people from the vocational interests about which we have been speaking, would be practical. It might be but I should like to hear it discussed at greater length.</P>
    <P>Finally, I want to say that if we are in earnest about increasing the vocational representation in this House&mdash; and I believe there is such a necessity &mdash;and to make it more vocational in character, it can be done and should be done, but I do not think it is right to condemn the House as it is elected at the moment, or any section, simply because it must operate, in practice, as a political institution.  Clearly, this House is dealing with political problems and although I have stood up here more than once and said that I am not a member of any political Party, nevertheless I realise that if I am called upon to give an opinion or to cast a vote, I must obviously enter politics to do so, and I make no apology to anyone for doing so.  I think the answer to this question is really a lot more simple than the Commission makes out.  If there is a necessity to increase the vocational character of this House, surely there is a simple way of doing it within the existing system of election.</P>
    <P>It is clear at the moment that all that is necessary in fact is to increase the number of seats which ought to be filled from the nominating bodies on each nominating panel.  I think it would be a much better and much more practical way of securing the ends that the Commission was seeking than changing the actual system of election.  I would commend that suggestion to the Minister and to the Government as being the most practical and suitable way of doing that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>The main recommendation in this Report is a very simple one, that 23 out the 60 members of the Seanad should be elected by direct election from the various vocational groups.  The purpose of that, which is quite clear from reading <Col N="644" /> the Report and listening to the debate here, is to make the Seanad less political and more vocational.  What we have to examine here is what exactly does that purpose mean. What do these people who set forth that Report envisage?  They envisage making the Seanad less political, as they say, than it is now and more vocational.  First of all, these two concepts, the political idea and the vocational idea, have been bandied about and people may get the wrong notion that these concepts are contradictory and opposite.  I do not think that is the case at all.  The main function of the Seanad, as one of the Houses of the National Parliament, is surely a political function. Therefore, following on that, the main vocational qualification for entry into this House should be the political qualification.  It is essentially a political House, concerned primarily with the revision of legislation and concerned, as we were recently, with the initiation of legislation.  As such, it is fundamentally a political House, part of the political institutions of our State.</P>
      <P>The Seanad is paralleled by second Chambers in every other democratic country in the world and in none of them do we get the false notion about the necessity for vocational representation or the representation of sectional vocational groups.  This Seanad is a vocational Seanad because most of the people in it are people who have been concerned with the vocation of politics and there is no finer vocation in the world, one that has been regarded by people like Aristotle and Thomas Aquinas back down the years as the principal vocation, dealing with the the art of government and with the art of ruling and the matters which pertain to the government of the State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am very strong in the view that the principal qualification for entry into this House and the other House&mdash; of course, it applies particularly to the other House&mdash;should be the vocational qualification of having been active in and concerned and associated with practical politics.  For that <Col N="645" /> reason, I think the purpose behind this motion, of having this direct representation from vocational groups, is ill-conceived, because the notion seems to attribute to the representatives of vocational groups the practical political knowledge which they may not have and which they can have only through representation and association with politics.</P>
    <P>The present system, which perhaps in certain aspects could be improved, is broadly a good one and any attempt to make the Seanad, as these people say, more vocational&mdash;I do not think the word &ldquo;vocational&rdquo; is the correct one&mdash;would be highly undesirable when this is a House of Parliament dealing with the revision and initiation of legislation and political matters appertaining to Government.  Now, implicit also in this notion that there should be more vocational representation and more direct vocational representation, is a certain condemnation of political Parties.  Far too often in this country today we have this notion that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I point out, Sir, that in proposing the motion, it was made very clear that there was no implicit condemnation of the political Parties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not referring to Senator Stanford who very ably proposed the motion.  I am referring to the sentiments in the Report of the Commission, in <i>Irish Times</i> editorials and as expressed by people throughout the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator quote passages from the Report which imply any antagonism to the political system?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Stanford expressed his awareness of this criticism.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Criticism, but not antagonism.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a very subtle distinction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit that in <Col N="646" /> the majority recommendations, in editorials of the <i>Irish Times</i> and in the utterances of certain people associated with what I call sectional groups, is a condemnation of political Parties and the political Party system.  I know that this is a great field of debate but I should like to say, first of all, that modern democracy cannot work without political Parties.  The political Parties have preserved standards over the years and have served this country well and the political Party Leaders, whether they be Fianna Fáil, Fine Gael or Labour, have, by and large, preserved very high standards of integrity, personal behaviour and competence when in or out of office.  That notion which is abroad that there is something wrong with politics, with a second Chamber composed in a majority way of people from political Parties and that there is something to be condemned in that, is ill founded and not based on the realities in this country today.</P>
      <P>We have responsible political Parties which have grown up and become institutions of the State and I do not see any reason why people prominent in the medical profession, in the legal profession or whatever particular section, trade or commercial group they belong to, cannot become associated with either or any of the main political Parties and through them, project their particular vocational or sectional ideas, have them blunted by criticism from other Party members and eventually work out a common, broad basis which can form part of the Party programme and be presented to the people at election time.  It is most desirable to have political Parties that are broadly based in the community, what could be described as homogeneous political Parties representative of various elements of our society, and have them represented in both Houses of Parliament.  It is through the medium of broadly-based political Parties that a broadly-based programme can be put to the people at election times, and it is under that system that modern democracy works.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under the Constitution, the Seanad has the status of an integral part of the machinery of government.  It is one of the two Houses of Parliament <Col N="647" /> and inevitably, the political Parties must, and should, have a large say in the debates and decisions of this House.  I see nothing whatever wrong in that; I see nothing to be ashamed of in that.  It is admirable, inevitable and perfectly right.</P>
    <P>In regard to the idea of sectional representation in this House, there is one note of warning in the minority reservation made by Deputy de Valera, and I think it might be no harm to mention it.  It is that vocational and sectional groups are in considerable danger of endangering their own interests and their own organisations by having direct election to the Seanad. I do not wish to deal with the whole question of politics as introduced into local authorities, county councils, urban councils, corporations and the like.  Many people think it has not been a good thing that politics on a national scale have been brought into local councils, but we shall have that situation, and one much worse, if these vocational groups have direct election to the Seanad when the Seanad is charged under the Constitution with a political function.  If that is introduced, there will be intrigue and jockeying inside these organisations and it would ruin their foundations and the whole reason for their existence.</P>
    <P>Vocational activity is entirely desirable. It is a helpful sign in our community that in recent years vocational groups have developed, contributed to our welfare and made many public statements on matters which concern them and the community generally.  That is all very good and the free Press we have here gives full publicity to their views.  That is all to the good, and it is also to the good that, in our democracy, political Parties and the Government should pay heed to the views expressed by these groups.  In our society, no Government, for their own sake, will ignore the views of the vocational groups.  Ministers must receive deputations from them and pay heed to their considered views.  Any Government would be very ill-advised not to do so because, due to the marginal <Col N="648" /> nature of politics here, if a Government set out deliberately to override vocational groups, they would find themselves out of office at the next election.  In order to keep in office, Governments have to pay heed to vocational groups and they do so.</P>
    <P>These groups in their turn are performing an admirable service, a social service, and even a service of helping the Government in their various spheres, but the ground could be cut from under such very desirable activities, if these societies and organisations were beset by intrigue and jockeying for the selection of candidates for election to this Chamber. That would take them out of the spheres in which they are doing such good work at the moment and bring them into a sphere for which they have doubtful qualifications.  The medical profession, the legal profession, the trade and farming associations are all different in their own spheres.  They can contribute to the good of the community by advocating the things on which they have expert knowledge, but if they come in here, I think they would be ill-equipped to contribute in the atmosphere that exists here.  The point made by Deputy de Valera in his reservation to the Majority Report is a very valid one and should be borne in mind by the Government when considering the Report.</P>
    <P>There is also a minor aspect of the Report which I thought rather sensible, though, as I say, I do not agree with the major part of the Report. The minor recommendation was that there should be a better system of examining the qualifications of people presenting themselves for election to the Seanad.  Under the Constitution, a person must have a knowledge and practical experience of the particular interests of the panel which he seeks to represent.  At the moment, the Clerk of the Seanad is charged with the duty of examining that.  If we are to have people with a genuine knowledge and experience of a vocational panel, as well as being members of political Parties, it would be no harm if there were a more strict examination of such persons offering themselves for election, and paragraph <Col N="649" /> 43 of the Report on page 21 deals fully with this matter.  It states:&mdash;</P>
    <P>We concluded that the function should be transferred to a Board of Assessors consisting of the Chairman of Dáil Éireann as Chairman, with nine members, one to be appointed, or in the event of disagreement, elected by each of the five electoral colleges appointed by the nominating bodies and two members from each House of the Oireachtas, with the Seanad Returning Officer as Secretary.</P>
    <P>That is an improvement on the present system that might be adopted but in regard to the main principles of the Report, I believe they are badly thought out and are based on a fundamental misconception that politics is not vocational.  Politics is the supreme vocation of all and we, in this House and in the other House, are charged under the Constitution with the duty of pursuing that vocation for the benefit of the people by passing legislation, and by being helpful and critical of the Government when they introduce legislation.  In that, we are exercising the supreme vocational function of society.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I was glad when I saw that Senator Stanford had put down a motion on this subject because I think it is time we, as a Seanad, examined our own conscience and tried to see whether some of the criticisms levelled against us are justified or not and, if so, whether we could improve the Seanad, that is, the present Seanad and future Seanaid.  Senator Stanford, very wisely in presenting his case, made it clear that the implementation of the recommendations of the Commission is naturally conditioned by the fact that the Commission had certain terms of reference outside of which they could not go.  Nevertheless, I think it is legitimate, as some Senators have done&mdash;and as one of the minority signatories has done&mdash;to ask whether a Seanad is necessary?  I think we should ask ourselves that question and see whether we can, as it were, justify ourselves in our own minds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="650" /> I notice that in another minority report which has already been referred to, and with a great deal of which I agree, that is, the minority report of Deputy de Valera, he says:</P>
    <P>On the other hand, if it is merely an Advisory Body and forum for discussion it quickly becomes of little account in public opinion and will have little influence with the Executive.</P>
    <P>In my opinion, a Seanad which is to be nothing more than an advisory, deliberative, consultative assembly would still be serving a very useful function.  That forum for discussion which Deputy de Valera mentions could be a vitally important thing, providing that this sounding board, as it might be termed, was used to draw attention to matters about which it might be important to arouse or inform public opinion.  Therefore I shall depart from this particular point of Deputy de Valera, because I do not think he should have used the adverb &ldquo;merely&rdquo;.  I do not think that it is true either to say that an advisory or consultative, deliberative assembly would not have much weight with the Executive.  That would depend very greatly upon the quality of that body.  I believe that a certain case can be made for a Seanad such as we have, that is, mainly deliberative, that acts as a sounding board, and that is not too close to the Government, too intimately involved in every action and gesture of the Government.</P>
    <P>So much for the question of the necessity for or value of a Seanad in general.  A case can be made for it. I think a case can also be made for our own Seanad, and I believe that our present Seanad has demonstrated itself worthy and shown what can be done in the everyday way of discussing legislation and amendments, and in giving a point of view perhaps, which is not always heard as readily in the Dáil, giving perhaps a slightly more detailed view on matters, whether they be immediate legislation or a point of general public import upon which the Dáil may not even have expressed an opinion.</P>
    <P>It is sometimes said that the Seanad <Col N="651" /> is out of touch with the country, and that the Dáil, which is far more directly elected, has its finger on the pulse of the country and knows what the country is thinking.  There is a tendency to be found indeed among certain Deputies to be a little impatient with the Seanad for daring to have opinions different from that of the Dáil, on the ground that the Dáil, after all, are the realistic people, down to earth, having to go before the electorate, and being in touch with the man in the street.  We in the Seanad realise, however, that sometimes we are demonstrably more in touch with the man in the street than the Dáil itself.</P>
    <P>We remember being told in one of our more stirring debates in recent times on the P.R. question: &ldquo;Why do you not leave it to the country?  Why do you not let the electorate decide?&rdquo;. The answer given by myself, and by several others who shared this view, was that I was quite prepared to leave it to the country, but I thought it our duty to give a lead on the matter to the country, and interpret the views which we thought were the right ones, in order to allow the country to decide in the light of a debate and a vote in the Seanad as well as in the Dáil. Senators know that as it turned out when it was finally left to the country, the country decided that the Seanad was right, and the Dáil wrong.  It would not be right to make too much of that particular instance.  Nevertheless, it is a legitimate answer to make to those who suggest that the Dáil is more intimately in touch with the man in the street, because on that occasion clearly it was not.</P>
    <P>It proves salutary also&mdash;I think the Minister will agree with me&mdash;for Ministers to have to come before the Seanad and justify their policies.  The Seanad has a more intimate atmosphere, and in relation to a particular Bill, Ministers come and listen, generally with patience, and justify the Bill and the Government's attitude in answer to a more intimate form of questioning perhaps than they must submit to in the Dáil.</P>
    <P>Milton was anxious to &ldquo;justify the <Col N="652" /> ways of God to man,&rdquo; and I feel it is a good thing for the Minister occasionally to have to come before the Seanad and justify the ways of the Government to the Seanad.  It helps the Ministers themselves, too, to sort out their own thoughts on particular issues, and the Minister who in the light of a debate in the Upper House decides on amendments or adjustments has gained something for the country, and for himself, by that very flexibility.</P>
    <P>There is another thing that should be said&mdash;nobody outside the Seanad seems to say it or even to notice it, but somebody should say it&mdash;the Seanad is mocked by some newspapers because they think that we do not answer their ideal of what a Seanad should be.  In point of fact, I am prepared to say&mdash;and I have a little experience now of the Seanad, of which I have been a member for nearly six years&mdash;that the way in which it conducts its day-to-day business is in every way comparable with the way in which the Lower House conducts its business.  In particular instances such as the obtaining of a quorum in the House the record of the Seanad is demonstrably far and away ahead of the record of the other House.  I can recall only one occasion in six years on which there was not a quorum in this House.  I doubt if any T.D. can get up and say that with truth, unless he himself has been consistently absent from the time of his election.  In other words, our record in the conduct of debate and the seriousness which we bring to debates can fairly stand comparison with that of the other House.</P>
    <P>The immediate issue here, which was plainly put by Senator Stanford, is whether we should now take steps, in accordance with the recommendations in this Report, to alter the Seanad by increasing the effective vocational representation in the Seanad.  That brings me to this question of vocationalism. Senator McGuire indicated that he had come to the view&mdash;he put it very politely&mdash;that there was a great deal of nonsense talked about vocationalism. Senator Lenihan has much the same view, but he concealed it by saying that he was all in favour of <Col N="653" /> vocationalism and adding in effect that &ldquo;provided, of course, that we do not give it any legislative power;&rdquo; that is to say, you give a pat on the back to vocationalism every time you meet a vocational body, and you say &ldquo;Splendid&rdquo;, but any time they ask for more effective representation, you say: &ldquo;No, it would not be a good thing.&rdquo;  I hope that I am not wronging Senator Lenihan by saying that his attitude too means that there is in fact a lot of nonsense talked about vocationalism.</P>
    <P>One of the fallacies underlying the nonsense seems to be the fact that there is no satisfactory answer to the question as to what vocations shall be represented, and who shall devise the compartments into which you divide vocationalism.  Are the compartments we have in the various panels of the Seanad to-day devised in accordance with some absolute basic law?  What does vocationalism really mean in practice?  A lot of nonsense is talked about it.</P>
    <P>For that reason I have a great deal of sympathy with what Deputy de Valera says on page 25:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Any effective attempt to make it predominantly vocational, in the sense of representing sectional organisations or interests, must import political activity into these vocational groups.  Such moves towards vocationalism would not reduce the &lsquo;non-political&rsquo; Senate which some envisage.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>It is quite clear that there is in fact a lot of self-deception about what is said in this country about vocationalism.</P>
    <P>Again, when Deputy de Valera says on page 26:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;It may well be that a Seanad, openly political in its character and discussions, is to be preferred&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I find myself substantially in agreement with him.  If we were, consequently, to reject this notion of vocationalism, and accept the view that he suggests there, we might as well have a frankly Party political Seanad.  What are the objections?  The usual objection is that the Seanad may <Col N="654" /> find itself in conflict with the Dáil, as if that were some major political sin. The Seanad has in fact no power to hold up legislation for more than a maximum of 90 days.  I never quite understood the fear of successive Governments of being defeated on an issue or an amendment by the Seanad. What harm does it do them to be defeated?  They have their machinery whereby they can get Parliamentary victory later on in the Dáil.  That has been demonstrated before.  We have no real direct power.  What harm then occasionally if in a Party political Seanad, the Government were to be defeated?  I should say that it would do them good.  The humbling process of defeat in the Upper House might well produce a salutary examination of conscience.  Possibly I am being over-optimistic.  I certainly do not see, however, what real harm can be done by an occasional Government defeat in the Seanad.</P>
    <P>The theoretical defeat that we inflict on the Government, if we do defeat the Government in the Seanad, is no more, in fact, in practice, than a guide or warning light which may be important and should be attended to, but which represents no barrier to legislation or Government action.  Personally, I should prefer a Seanad, if a Seanad is necessary&mdash;and I think a case can be made for it&mdash;which is directly elected and unashamedly Party political, because I believe man is a political animal.  There is no use pretending he is not.  I share Senator Stanford's view that there is no shame in being interested in government. Interest in politics is the mark surely of a mature citizen.</P>
    <P>If the Seanad must have some difference from the Dáil, then it could have different periods of election, for instance, or a third of the membership could be renewed periodically or elected for a different period of years, five or seven.  I should be greatly tempted by the suggestion that it could be elected by a more genuinely representative form of proportional representation with constituencies different from the Dáil constituencies, considerably bigger, that is to say, with considerably more <Col N="655" /> seats per constituency and with a smaller number of such constituencies, which would ensure that a finer shading of political and other thought in the country might be presented in the Seanad without any danger to the immediate Party political issues which would still be decided primarily in the Dáil.</P>
    <P>I must add that I should like to retain the right of the Taoiseach to nominate at least some members of the Seanad.  I think that is a good right, though I do not think it has been used to the best possible extent by successive Taoisigh.  Senator Ó Donnabháin mentioned, and, I think, with justice, the way in which it has been used on occasion by the President, Mr. de Valera.  It was very striking to notice the way in which people like the late Sir John Keane were repeatedly appointed by the then Taoiseach, though they differed, as Sir John Keane differed, on almost every issue, from the Government.  It would be a good thing if this method of filling some of the seats in the Seanad were to be retained.  It would also be a good thing if successive Taoisigh would use it far more liberally and with less fear of damaging the Party majority.</P>
    <P>On the question of the present situation, the present circumstance of our Seanad is unfortunately that we make a pretence that we have a vocational Seanad.  There is a myth that vocational bodies are represented in this Seanad.  I think that in circumstances in which the selection of candidates for the Seanad is confined by law to certain vocations, but in which the method of election very often fails to secure the election of the candidates who might be the best and most adequate representatives of their vocations, the system seems to be a bad system, as you get the worst of both worlds.  We have not got the breadth of selection of candidates, and yet you have a political electorate.</P>
    <P>We narrow it down on a vocational basis, and, having narrowed it down, we then proceed to elect on another basis.  That is supremely unsatisfactory. Therefore, I am led to this <Col N="656" /> opinion since we have this stated aim in relation to the Seanad, this vocational aim: ought we not at least try to implement that aim more genuinely for our own sake, for the sake of truth and for the purpose of diminishing political hypocrisy?  Ought we not try to ensure that if we want certain vocational elements to be represented here, they shall as far as possible be represented by their best people, and not just by those from among their number who have the strongest support of the Party political machines?</P>
    <P>Therefore, I should like to put before the Seanad my view, that there are three possibilities for this Upper House.  One is: we should have a Party political Seanad, frankly so, unashamedly so, and that is the one I should prefer.  The second is that we should have a Seanad which would be effectively largely vocational, with the best representatives as far as possible representing each vocation. The third possibility is to have a Seanad pretending to be vocational, but being in reality diminished and hamstrung by being a sort of hybrid version of the first, the Party political Seanad, without being prepared to admit it and to elect it as such.</P>
    <P>I would prefer the first type, the frankly Party political Seanad, but that issue is not before the House this evening.  Under this motion and under the terms of reference of the Commission, we have no power to make a suggestion on those lines.  Therefore, I should like as a second best the implementation of the recommendations of the Report of the Commission as representating at least a step towards the second possibility, that is to say, a Seanad effectively vocational in which, as far as possible, the best elements would represent each vocation. I should like in that connection to quote Deputy de Valera again, when he says on page 26:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I think nevertheless that it would be preferable to try to ensure that those elected to the Senate as vocational representatives have personally, and in all reality, the necessary individual qualifications to represent their calling rather than base the representations wholly on extra-cameral organisations.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="657" /> With that in mind, and with the reservations I have made, I would urge the House to support this motion as a valuable step to our brushing away some of the pretence and getting closer to what is our stated aim, even though that stated aim, as representing only a second best, may not have my wholehearted support.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say at the outset that I could not think of a worse place to discuss this motion than this Seanad because, of necessity, people will speak with their tongues in their cheeks.  Many people will not say what they mean and very few people will say what they really believe.  That is inevitable when one is discussing something which so closely affects oneself.  It is impossible that anything else should occur.</P>
      <P>This whole investigation is a sort of off-shoot of a suggestion that is rampant without a doubt, that the Seanad is a place of retirement for defeated T.D.s.  I am one of such people&mdash;open confession is good for the soul&mdash;so, in saying that, I shall give offence to no one.  It is true that the view is held all over Ireland that while the Seanad should be a place for people with vocational knowledge and, shall we say, with superior experience to members of the Dáil who are more completely and more tightly-bound by the Party Whip, even though there are Party members here, the Seanad is, in fact, a place where people are retired on defeat in a Dáil election, or sent here because they are of use to a political Party.</P>
      <P>I am willing to be judged on that because I am one of those people, and perhaps people down the country would convict me as such, even though they have never met me, because of that fact.  There has been a lot of that sort of talk.  I also say to the Seanad, and Senators may put me in that category if they please, that there are some Senators here because they were good ward heelers rather than as contributors to the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Seanad is a pretty good Seanad. I do not know anything about previous Seanaid and I do not want to criticise <Col N="658" /> those that went before, but I am saying what is true and what the people say. Whether we like it or not, that is what they say, and that is what we have to face up to.  I do not believe we shall get a perfect system.  We can talk about nominating bodies, but at every election, people are nominated and I know of candidates who do not try to be elected but are put forward in order to keep the nomination.  The one I am thinking of concerns a very important industry.  If we were to have an election, this industry would be one of the first&mdash;for obvious reasons, I shall not give names or introduce personalities&mdash;to use its nomination to elect, whereas, in fact, there was no person who wanted to secure election.</P>
    <P>That is an obvious flaw in the suggested system and it should be thought about.  I was amazed at one stage when Senator Lenihan referred to St. Thomas Aquinas.  Perhaps he will bear with me if I use the word Machiavellian.  There are good and bad politicians, just as there are good and bad veterinary surgeons, with apologies to Senator Ó Donnabháin and others.  We cannot say because a fellow is a member of a political Party, he is good, and because he refused to join a political Party, he is bad.  We must get a balance between the two and, in my opinion, the present system of election preserves a fair balance.</P>
    <P>My reason for so saying is, of course, that when you have nomination, by the nominating bodies, election is easier.  After all, we have only to look at the figures, and I am sure Senators, like myself, know them backwards.  It is about twice as easy to be elected if you are nominated by a nominating body than if you are nominated on the Oireachtas sub-panel.  Therefore, that situation weights the system in favour of the vocational people if they want to elect a person who is not a member of a political Party.  At the same time, it achieves a balance, but we must go back to the plain people of Ireland as much as we can even for election to the Seanad.  If we do not go back to the ordinary franchise and a vote for everybody over 21 years, as good <Col N="659" /> a place as another is to go back to the elected local representatives.</P>
    <P>Again, there is the question of whether or not that should be the case for all local elected representatives, or for senior representatives who were elected to vote for the Seanad from the various county councils, corporations and urban councils. When that was the case, I was not in politics, because I was too young, but my father, the Lord rest him, had a vote and I remember all the persuasion, all the pressure, and all the tales.  Let us be truthful about it votes were bought and sold.</P>
    <P>That was a wrong situation and if we create a situation where we have the nominating bodies electing, we may go further back.  There is a danger that we would have the sort of thing we had when there were seven people selected from each county to vote.  We may go back to the stage where one man's vote, or one man's influence on a board, or on a governing body with a particular set-up, or in a particular industry, might mean that a person was elected.</P>
    <P>People like to be called Senator or Deputy and there is a type of person who will go very far indeed to get that honour or to hold on to it if he has already got it, so that if you do not regularise matters you may find that the system of election which you thought was perfection is not perfection, and that it is more imperfect than the system you now have.  That danger is there if you leave the nominating bodies with the right to elect. You may bring in bribery and corruption where the nominating bodies are not as efficiently organised or as virile or as strong as they might be. That is my opinion and it may or may not be correct.</P>
    <P>I hold that a vocational person is, of course, of use in the Upper House. I think he is absolutely necessary in the Upper House, but, even though he is, I think he should be also so well known and so accepted as to be able to be elected on the votes as we have them to-day.  It is right that he should get that little bit of help in that he has <Col N="660" /> only to get approximately half as many votes, but he should be sent back to what I term the plain people of Ireland, through their local authority members.  He must, in fact, be sent back there, and he must gain election under that system.</P>
    <P>We would hope then to get people who are practical as well as people who are vocational because&mdash;let us be honest about it and with apologies to everybody&mdash;I can think of rows and rows of University professors who would be wholly unsuited to Government. The practical man, and the man who had to struggle all his life to show a profit, rather than the man who draws a salary is the man for Government. It is right that those people must, because of a specialised knowledge, be given a number of seats, but they should also be sent back to the ordinary people to be elected to this House.</P>
    <P>If the Seanad was criticised in the past, over the past three or four years &mdash;not because I came here in the past three or four years; I do not think I made any great impact on it&mdash;the Seanad has become important in the minds of the people.  Whether or not that is so because of the superior debate referred to by Senator Sheehy Skeffington, or because of the debate on the referendum, I do not know. Let us forget, so far as this discussion is concerned, who won or who lost. The point is that it was a really good debate and every word of it was read by the people, assimilated by them, and had a very profound effect on them.  Therefore, I think this Seanad at least has justified itself.  The system we have had has justified itself.  If it took a while, if there were criticisms, if it was said that the Seanad was innocuous and of no value at times, the same has been said of the Dáil and of all the eminent institutions we have.  If we have now a Seanad that has justified itself, not only in that debate but in many other debates that I know of, it is a justification of the system of election as it is.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to compliment Senator Stanford on his <Col N="661" /> opening remarks, particularly on his very clear exposition of the nature of politics.  He has done a great service to the country and a great service to democracy.  It has been claimed by sections of the Press and by various youth organisations that there is something ignoble and vile in politics and that people should not touch them.  If that continued, it would constitute a danger to our democratic institutions in the future. In many countries in Europe where that doctrine was propagated it made clear the way for dictatorship.</P>
      <P>The question at issue is whether we should favour having 23 seats of the Seanad filled by the vocational bodies directly.  I would not agree with that recommendation and I certainly agree with Deputy de Valera's objection to that.  First of all, I am sure that the committee has not fully studied the effects their recommendation would have on the vocational bodies themselves. If the idea was that by having vocational bodies elect their representatives directly, we would get a non-political or neutral body of men into the Seanad, then I am afraid it is a very much mistaken idea.</P>
      <P>Let us consider what would happen: a vocational body is constituted of its executive and a number of outside members, let us say, 2,000.  If a number of people, two perhaps, are nominated by that vocational organisation those nominees must be elected on the vote of those 2,000 members. Now since 99.9 per cent of all people are more or less political, political in their prejudices, political in their feelings, as it is only natural they should be, and as those two nominees would be put up for election by the 2,000 members of the organisation, most of whom were affiliated to political Parties, the election would clearly be as political as it is to-day by members of county councils.  It could not be otherwise.  There would be no change.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is equally mistaken to think that we should get the very best men, the highest in their profession, from such an election.  If they were to be selected by vocational bodies, we may be sure that it would become a scramble for nominations and inside <Col N="662" /> a few years you would have people nominated on political considerations.</P>
    <P>It is very clear what would happen; you would not change the representation here as far as political affiliation is concerned, but it would have a very serious effect on the vocational organisation itself.  Politics are good here in their own place, in the Dáil and in the Seanad, but not in vocational bodies.  They have been given a purpose to carry out and they have carried it out very well; it is a very useful purpose and very necessary for the country and for general progress, but politics have no place in those vocational bodies.  They have nothing to do with law-making or with filling the Dáil or the Seanad and to force these things on them will be to split those organisations into different sections.  I am certain that would be the result of allowing those bodies to elect their representatives directly.</P>
    <P>I do not think it would be wise, either, outside that consideration, to allow a certain section, because they happen to be manufacturers, farmers, artisans or anything else, to elect a person to help in the legislature. Really it would not be democratic.</P>
    <P>I am afraid I have an unorthodox view on the whole thing, but I think that we should not be bound by the exact terms of the commission, or even of the Constitution, in considering these matters.  We have a very long experience of the workings of the Seanad and the methods of election. I do not think that our people are inclined to think on vocational lines like the people of some European countries; they always tend to think on political lines and we should remember that in arranging for the future of the Seanad.  I may be wrong, but it is my view that we should elect one Senator for each constituency by means of an older vote, say, by people over 40, or by a family vote on the lines of the old local government vote.  You would get a different type of person and you would find the vocations as well represented as in the proposed Seanad. We should not have any consideration but that of finding the most suitable type of Senator for the future.</P>
    <Col N="663" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>This motion asks us to express the view that the Government should bring in proposals to implement the recommendations of the Seanad Electoral Law Commission. I think we should begin by defining our terms and deciding what precisely we are talking about.  The Commission that sat on the constitution of the Seanad was bound to consider only Articles 18 and 19 of the Constitution; it was concerned only with panel representatives and had no power to deal with the university members, no power to deal with what the number of nominations by the Taoiseach should be.  Also the Commission had no power to make any suggestions regarding the functions of the Seanad as laid down in the Constitution.  They were therefore bound to the Constitution in a number of ways and what they had to recommend was very restricted.</P>
      <P>The first point is the functions of the Seanad.  The Seanad according to the Constitution has to consider legislation from the other House and may itself initiate legislation.  In other words, the Seanad, however it is to be composed, has for its functions the consideration of legislation and it is a part of a parliament.  In other words, it is a place for talking.  It is sometimes said&mdash;it is intended to be said scornfully&mdash;that the Dáil is a talking shop, but that is precisely the kind of government we have.  Democratic parliamentary government is, in effect, government by discussion and both Houses have to be places where we can talk.  In this House, we have to talk about legislation, about public business, and that being so, what kind of person should we have as a member?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let me begin by clearing away one constant misstatement that is made&mdash; and it was made in the quotation given by Senator Stanford when he began this debate with a very reasonable speech.  It is frequently said that the original intention was to have this a vocational, non-political House.  Nothing could be further from the truth. The statement is demonstrably untrue. Anyone who looks at the Constitution, or the Seanad Electoral Act, will see <Col N="664" /> that this House was designed by the previous Taoiseach to be a place where the Government would always have a majority.  Eleven people were to be nominated by the Taoiseach himself after an election.  The universities were to elect six people and the other 43 people were to be elected by individuals who were themselves all, by definition, politicians; the members of the new Dáil fresh from the election, the members of the old Seanad and the members of the county councils.</P>
    <P>The head of the Government which devised this Constitution, and this scheme, was also head of a political Party which had itself as part of its principles and practice the making of the county councils political.  Thus the main body of county councillors were politicians.  Therefore, from the very beginning you had a certain number of people from each county council and borough council nominated but they were nominated on a political basis.  That proved to be unsatisfactory and amending legislation was brought in to extend the electorate to all county councillors, but there is no use in asserting that an electorate which is entirely political could possibly produce anything but a political body.</P>
    <P>The intention was to have this House so constituted that it could never disagree with the other House.  I know that &ldquo;the best laid plans of mice and men gang aft agley&rdquo; and things do not work out as people meant them to work out but that is primarily what was meant.  It was meant to be elected by politicians for a political purpose and from the very beginning, the vocational aspect of the Seanad was to a large extent humbug.</P>
    <P>I do not know what is meant by saying that if we were sufficiently organised, we could have direct vocational elections in the Seanad.  Again, in the arrangements for the election to the Seanad, from the very beginning, it was ordained that there be nominations from the Oireachtas itself to what was called the Oireachtas sub-panel. I know it is a very complicated system but the complication, however you look at it, worked out so that there were always plenty of political <Col N="665" /> candidates and what the nominating bodies often did was to put forward two politicians.</P>
    <P>My friend who has just spoken was himself nominated for a great many years by the I.A.O.S. because he was Fianna Fáil and there sat beside me for many years the late Senator Baxter who was nominated by the same body because he was Fine Gael. There is no doubt that the I.A.O.S. exercised its intelligence in that particular way.  Both their candidates were elected.  The same thing applies to Senator Douglas on this side of the House and to Senator Summerfield on the other side.  There is no doubt that the nominations from the Taoiseach also proved that it was a political operation.</P>
    <P>In regard to the Commission, it was not free to make any general recommendations.  It might be no harm to consider how the Commission was made up.  It was made up of 21 people of whom the chairman was a judge.  We shall leave him out.  Of the 20 others, six were T.D.s; one was a former T.D.; four were Senators; and one was a former Senator.  There were eight others and if I may say, to begin with, they were astonished during the sittings of the Commission.  It was a very irksome body at times for the practising politicians because non-members of the Oireachtas talked about politicians as if the word &ldquo;politician&rdquo; had the same meaning as the word &ldquo;murderer&rdquo; or the word &ldquo;adulterer&rdquo; or some other nasty word.  They were indeed charming people but manifestly they were entirely removed from any notion as to how this State works.  They were astonished that members of the Oireachtas could talk together and agree with one another.  To a member of the Oireachtas, such surprise is fantastic.  One of them expressed to me his surprise that Deputy Haughey sat down beside me and seemed to be a friend of mine, forgetting that he was a student of mine and forgetting a great many other things.  The fact that Deputy McGilligan could make a suggestion with which Deputy Vivion de Valera could agree seemed astounding to them.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="666" /> However, the members of the Commission did a good job in the end. They had various difficulties and one difficulty was in relation to the restrictions which they were under.  The other was the fact that there is no such thing anywhere as a really satisfactory second House of Parliament. The problem has not been solved. One could not go anywhere and say: &ldquo;There is a second Chamber which we shall imitate.&rdquo;  Probably the best second House in the world&mdash;and one may be unpopular for saying so&mdash; is the House of Lords.  If you explained in writing to somebody how the House is elected, he would think it is a lunatic assembly but it is very far from being a lunatic assembly. They are tinkering around with it now and will probably ruin it, but that is another question.  There is no perfect example available, particularly for a unitary State like ours which has no federal problem like the United States of America.</P>
    <P>There are certain requisites for a second House and we should consider them.  I agree with Senator Lenihan, and I think Senator Stanford also said it, that the two Houses should if possible be different.  They should have a different kind of personnel, a different approach to legislation.  In spite of the fact that there are a great many ex-T.D.s in this House, and in spite of all efforts to make this a political House, and in spite of the fact that it is a political House, it does approach legislation in a different way from the Dáil.  Ministers of all Parties have been impressed by that fact.  This House has succeeded in having a different approach and has succeeded at times, with different Ministers of different Parties, in getting them to agree to amendments they would not agree to in the other House.  We had one extraordinary example of that during the recent war.</P>
    <P>I think it should be completely different in its base.  The idea that the two Houses should be elected on adult suffrage is completely wrong.  The second House should be elected in a different way from the other House and have less power.  It should have something to do and what it has to <Col N="667" /> do in this case is to examine legislation or itself to initiate legislation.</P>
    <P>What should we do to improve the situation, if there is something wrong with it?  There are a great many things wrongs with it.  There are people who do not attend the House at all.  There are people who are here in body but not in spirit and who do not bother with the House.  The suggestion is made constantly that this should be made a vocational House. Frankly, I do not understand what that means.  What the Commission recommended was a compromise between the views of those who think it should be entirely a political House and those who think it should be a vocational House.</P>
    <P>Presumably, the idea of vocationalism is that the House should contain specialists.  What is the specialist to do?  I have here in my hand to-day's Dáil Order paper.  It has, I think, 14 Bills on it and we shall get them all in this House.  What is the function of a representative of a vocational body? What is the function of a person who represents the engineers, architects, industrialists or, in particular, trade unions, about all these Bills?  I do not see how he will deal with them unless he is a person who has a general point of view.</P>
    <P>I do not think there is any question of what we are asked to do about these Bills.  It is not, as somebody suggested, to give advice.  It is not getting up to say: &ldquo;I think this Bill is so and so.&rdquo; We are expected to get up and say: &ldquo;I am against this Bill&rdquo; or &ldquo;I am for this Bill&rdquo; or &ldquo;I am going to vote for the whole of this Bill&rdquo; or &ldquo;I am going to put in an amendment to Section 22.&rdquo;  In other words, on every piece of legislation that comes before this House, we have to have an opinion and whether a vocational person would have that and have it better than a politician, I very much doubt.</P>
    <P>There is a completely foolish argument on this in to-day's leading article in the <i>Irish Times</i> that the Seanad consists of a whole lot of morons, with the exception of people who are university <Col N="668" /> representatives.  That, of course, would mean&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of fact, that is really a misrepresentation of the article in the <i>Irish Times.</i>  They certainly do not use the word &ldquo;morons.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>They do not but I use the word &ldquo;morons&rdquo; and I am entitled to use it.  The article states:</P>
      <P>With few exceptions, the candidates are chosen not on their qualifications, but on their political affiliations...</P>
      <P>Remember the words &ldquo;political affiliations&rdquo;. These words are charged with atmospherics.  It is intended to be a dirty, low word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Not necessarily in the leading article in the <i>Irish Times.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>If it means Trinity no; if it means U.C.D., the <i>Irish Times</i> would think it bad, if you had political affiliations there.  It continues:</P>
      <P>...if it were not for the presence of a few Senators of strong character and independent mind &mdash; mainly found among the university representatives and the Taoiseach's eleven...</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Observe the word &ldquo;mainly&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>
      </P>
      <P>...the Senate would be no more than a pallid and ineffectual mimic of the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is the kind of opinion which arises from sheer ignorance and bias combined.  I want to make that quite clear&mdash;sheer ignorance and bias combined. Supposing a Trinity university or other university professor from Dublin or Cork comes into the Seanad through a process of election other than through the university graduates, according to the <i>Irish Times</i>, he is not a good person at all.  He should not get in.  Supposing he is a member of the Fianna Fáil Party, or, as I am, a member of the Fine Gael Party, what is wrong with him then?  Does he <Col N="669" /> cease to have any brains or experience or does it mean that a person who is a university professor and who has experience of politics is not as good as one who has no such experience? I would suggest he is a great deal better than the professor who comes in here fresh and has no experience of politics and who persists in saying that he has no connection with politics.  I have no patience at all with non-political people and I have vast experience of them.</P>
    <P>A non-political person is a person who does not mind what kind of politician helps him.  That is my definition and, mind you, I have met them, male and female, old and young, graduates and undergraduates, educated and uneducated.  They do not mind who you are, if you can help them.  Then there is the other man who tells you quite gratuitously that he does not take an interest in politics. That means he is not Fine Gael; it means I am not to expect anything from him, and he will probably tell a Fianna Fáil supporter the same thing.  Such people do not understand that politicians very often have conversations, and confide in one another.</P>
    <P>Let me come to deal with the Commission's recommendations.  They had a great deal of talk and a great deal of intelligent discussion, as a result of which their decision was that as an experiment out of 43 members to be elected by the panels, they would have 23 elected directly by the vocational bodies.  In order to get agreement, people accepted that generally, though there is a reservation by Deputy Vivion de Valera and there is something in the danger he indicates.  At any rate, in deference to all this agitation, we might try the new system and it would give, as has already been suggested, a certain balance, but there are things in the Commission's Report which I do not think can be of any use at all.</P>
    <P>There are certain words in Article 18 about the qualifications to get on a panel.  These words are quite incapable of being judged by a court, qualifications for example in the national language, culture, art and education.  Apparently anybody with <Col N="670" /> any kind of a degree, or indeed anybody with any kind of training at all, can come in under that definition.</P>
    <P>There is also the qualification about labour, whether organised or unorganised, and there have been literally fantastic decisions under that.  That is not the fault of the people who made those decisions but it is because the definition is far too wide and vague. I am eligible myself on four of these panels and I think that is rather absurd.  The only one on which I am not eligible is the labour panel, though I taught in a secondary school a good many years ago and I do not know of any labour, manual or otherwise, as hard as that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>You are qualified, so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Then there is the qualification for public administration. A person who has been a member of a county council for one month is qualified as is a person who has been a Minister of State for 20 years.  There is no in-between&mdash;everybody is qualified. However, there are all kinds of difficulties.  Senator Stanford touched on some.  There is the specialist who has a special qualification in some particular branch but who is not interested generally and he would be of no use in this House.  I want to stress that point.  He would be no use in doing the job we have to do, particularly if he keeps himself to his own business.  There would be very few opportunities for him to express himself on matters in which he had a special interest.</P>
      <P>The Dáil Order Paper to-day or any day illustrates this point.  The State is taking over more and more functions. We had an example of it here to-day in the Broadcasting Authority Bill. Almost in spite of the Governments themselves, the State is taking over more and more power, the functions of Government are expanding and becoming more complicated and therefore the functions of Parliament and the matters to be discussed and decided in Parliament are multiplying, so that the person with a narrow point of view is not really of much use at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I mentioned some of the people here <Col N="671" /> already.  Senator James Douglas was a businessman, an industrialist who was a member of the Fine Gael Party, and I suggest quite seriously that his experience in business &mdash; the same thing applies to my colleague, Senator McGuire &mdash; was something which was useful because he was prepared to take a particular stand, but, if a person tries to balance himself and says: &ldquo;This is a very bad Bill, or a very good Bill,&rdquo; and yet does not want to vote on it, then he has very little to contribute and he is of very little use.</P>
    <P>That does not mean that I am against vocationalism or Independents, but let me give an example.  A few weeks ago, we met at 11 o'clock in the morning and I was asked by the Leader of the House would I consent to sitting for a couple of hours after six o'clock to finish the Broadcasting Authority Bill.  I said I would not but an Independent Senator said the idea was quite reasonable.  After that, he himself went away.  He could go away if he pleased but I could not.  I was required to answer for a number of people as to whether they would stay here and help to make a House, but he just went away.</P>
    <P>I am not against Independents.  I have said it often before, and it is absolutely true, that there is no Parliament I have heard of since 1922 where Independents get a fairer deal than they do in this House and in the other House.  The independent member gets a better hearing here than anyone else and I welcome him, but I do not know how this House could do the job it has to do under the Constitution in the absence of some kind of political organisation.  Unfortunately, as Senator Stanford indicated, there might be difficulty in getting a House.  Independents exercise their rights to come and go as they please.  Some of us cannot come and go as we please, and we have such people objecting when the programme is announced that they were not consulted.  There is no way to consult them.  I do not know how we could work without some kind of consultation between the Leaders of the Parties.</P>
    <P>The curious thing about the way <Col N="672" /> democracy works is that there is no mention in the Constitution or the Standing Orders of people who do important work.  The Constitution and the Standing Orders of the Dáil make no mention of Whips, and unless there are Whips, the Dáil cannot work.  Only for people here like the Leader of the House and the Leader of the Opposition, I do not think this Seanad would work, either.  I do not know how it is to work if the whole 43 members of these panels are all to come from vocational interests.  The idea is to eliminate politics, as if eliminating politics were the elimination of a virulent contagious disease.  That is not so.</P>
    <P>Senator Stanford told us that politics was a very noble word.  It is a very noble word, although some practitioners of politics are not very noble.  That applies equally to other noble words and professions, as I think Senator Stanford will agree.  You cannot eliminate human nature, and, human nature being what it is, not all the practitioners of any given profession will be up to the highest standards required.</P>
    <P>I feel that the demands made upon people in this House cannot be adequately borne or answered by members of the House who do not take a political view, those who cannot say about a particular problem before them: &ldquo;I am on this side or the other.&rdquo; For example, there is on the Dáil Order paper the Finance (Excise Duties) (Vehicles) (Amendment) Bill, 1959.  I do not know what particular vocation would deal with that.  Perhaps if the lorry owners had a member here, he would say something about it.  Then there are other Bills such as the Health Authority Bill, the Army Pensions Bill, and the Intoxicating Liquor Bill.  There was a Minister who came in here on such a Bill and said that he was peculiarly unfitted to deal with it, and I was obliged to repeat that I was unfitted in the same direction as he was, but we had a member who said that he was not like the Minister or Senator Hayes, that he had a life-long experience of public-houses from both sides of the counter.  We have nobody as good as that now.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="673" /> Then there is the Health (Fluoridation of Water Supplies) Bill.  I should really like to hear specialists on that. We have the Solicitors (Amendment) Bill, the Courts (Establishment and Constitution) Bill, the Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill, and I wonder what suggestions there are for finding people to deal with these.  We are not asked to give anybody any advice.  We are asked to discuss the Bills and to say whether we agree with them or to what extent we do not agree with them.</P>
    <P>That brings me to the concluding point about experts.  I believe in experts, and I have dealt a great deal with them in a great variety of ways, both in politics and government, and outside it.  Experts should be listened to but they should not be allowed to make decisions.  I am perfectly certain of that.  The opinion that this should be a house of 60 people, each of them an expert, is absurd.  If it were to be tried, this House would never make a decision on anything.  It would be reduced to a complete standstill. Experts should be listened to and shown deference in their own departments, and if an expert is able to make practical suggestions he should be listened to, but the notion that the second House of Parliament should be a House of people who have no political beliefs but each one of whom has expert knowledge is entirely foolish.  You would want to change the whole nature of this House to have a scheme of that kind.</P>
    <P>This House has defects.  The defects, particularly in my own Party, very often make me wild, but the older one gets and the more one sees of politics, the calmer one gets about all these things.  The last thing one expects is perfection in human nature. What a very diverse Commission finally agreed to was an experiment, to see how it would work, and if you could go further.  We suggest that of the 43 panel members, 23 should be elected by the nominating bodies themselves. That would not be very simple, and I suggested in order to shorten the proceedings of the Commission. that certain details should be left to the Minister for Local Government <Col N="674" /> to work out, that the Commission should not bother itself working out the details, and that if the principle was accepted, the experts in this kind of thing should work out the details.</P>
    <P>As an experiment and a contribution towards seeing whether the House can be improved, I am prepared to stand over that, but I should like very clearly to say that it seems to me that nobody is any use in this House or in any Parliament, unless he has political views.  He need not be a member of Fianna Fáil or Fine Gael or the Labour Party, but he must have views on current legislation, he must know what he thinks, and be able to say what he thinks, and have the courage to vote for what he thinks.  We had a person getting up here saying that a certain Bill was a political matter, and he was not here to take part in politics. That is an absurd attitude.  We have to take the view that what we are asked to do is a public job of work and you can only do it if you have views, general political views on legislation and on how the country should be governed.  As a step towards improving this House and answering certain criticisms about it, this Commission made certain recommendations and as far as I am concerned, I signed them and I am prepared to agree with them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>One must compliment Senator Stanford on the manner in which he dealt with this motion.  He was strictly fair in his comments, and those of us who have come to know the Senator regard him highly.  Nevertheless, I think that when one comes to speak on this motion, one must have regard to the views expressed by Senator Hayes.  Politics has been defined as the art of the possible.  Its practitioners cannot afford the luxury of anger or certainty.  The Senator who has just spoken has been a long time in the political arena.  He has gained much wisdom, and it is to be hoped that with the passing years, he will become still more mellow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The House must be reserved in dealing with this motion.  The Seanad Commission Report was vague enough in certain ways with regard to the method of election, even as governed by <Col N="675" /> Articles 18 and 19 of the Constitution. However, the Seanad is and must remain a political force, and it seems that it will remain so for at least the foreseeable future.  For that reason, the view expressed by Deputy Vivion de Valera in his reservation written in the Commission Report, is sound, as many speakers have mentioned.</P>
    <P>It is also worthy of some comment, first, because the argument is based upon experience and the view expressed therein is likely to stand the test of time.  Secondly, the aim of electing a Seanad on a vocational basis, whilst praiseworthy, is one which, in my opinion, is not calculated to work out so well in practice.  While it looks well on paper, the House might discover, for example, in the course of time, that if they tried to elect a Seanad on purely vocational lines, as suggested by the terms of this motion, it might have the effect of destroying the very basis upon which it is sought to build the composition of this House.</P>
    <P>For example, by generating active politics inside the vocational groups as to who would be eligible to vote for potential Senators, action of this sort would not produce a purely non-political Seanad.  Again, it could be argued that the aim of a fully vocational Seanad might not work out so well in practice or be wholly in keeping with the work expected from this House.</P>
    <P>It could be assumed, for example, that the Seanad as visualised in this motion, would not attain that degree of detachment necessary to enable Senators so elected to debate the issues before them with a full sense of balance and with due general regard for the common good.  Indeed, election by highly-geared groups can produce a House with a very one-sided point of view.</P>
    <P>Then again, of course, there will always be the danger of Senators elected on a vocational basis regarding themselves as purveyors of sectional interests rather than as public functionaries whose office is to be discharged in a countrywide interest.  We may also take <Col N="676" /> it that if the members of this House, for example, are to be elected on a vocational basis and should each of them represent elements with an overall common interest, it is difficult to see how they can be expected to discharge their duties objectively. The fact that they were elected on this basis could induce them to enter into coalitions of one kind or another which, in the long run, would give rise to sectional strife in the Seanad. In that event, the functions of this House&mdash;and it has some very important functions under Articles 12, 20, 21, 23, 24, 27, 28, 33, 35 and 46 of the Constitution&mdash;would be impaired.</P>
    <P>I submit that there is no animosity, I think, amongst the members of this House to having the various vocational groups represented.  Yet, we must at the same time bear in mind the difficulty of providing for a Seanad which can be effective within the framework of the Constitution which in turn provides for a Cabinet to be elected on a ministerial basis solely responsible to the Dáil.  Therefore, we must always have a care that no matter what people may say who are interested in vocationalism, no matter what their argument, there is the danger they could produce conflict between the Dáil and the Seanad and could lead in the last analysis to a constitutional crisis.</P>
    <P>One last point&mdash;I think the safeguards to which I have referred should not be thrown aside lightly.  While we should all welcome and like to see vocationalism functioning here nevertheless, in our time, I think it will not or cannot dominate the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnSheridan" hpid="Mr. J.D. Sheridan Mr. J.D. Sheridan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.D. Sheridan</NameTxt>
      <P>The hour is late and I just want to say a word or two in commendation of the motion. I think it is a thoroughly intelligent one.  It is well presented.  The Commission has made recommendations and this motion requests that these recommendations should now be implemented.  I think it is a sensible request.  It is quite sound.  We have been treated to several brilliant lectures on the deification of politics.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I listened to Senator Hayes, who is such a brilliant politican that a <Col N="677" /> country-fellow like me dare not challenge him&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>You are not too far behind him at times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnSheridan" hpid="Mr. J.D. Sheridan Mr. J.D. Sheridan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.D. Sheridan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and who has had a lifetime of training and experience&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>You poor man!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnSheridan" hpid="Mr. J.D. Sheridan Mr. J.D. Sheridan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.D. Sheridan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and I heard him castigating some of the members of the vocational bodies in the House. He thinks it is inconceivable that any human being should not be a politician. He quoted from the Irish Agricultural Organisation Society what I think was a rather personal quotation with regard to a Senator who was a member of the House for only a week and the inference was that he was elected primarily because he was a politician.  He said that on the Fine Gael side of the House, Senator Baxter was nominated by the same body and nominated because he was a member of the Fine Gael Party.  I disagree with that.</P>
      <P>(<i>Interruptions.</i>)</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnSheridan" hpid="Mr. J.D. Sheridan Mr. J.D. Sheridan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.D. Sheridan</NameTxt>
      <P>The late Senator Baxter was, to my mind, a very brilliant man, independent of what his politics were, and he was a man who rendered great service to this House. I am a farmer and I am not a politician. I have had no aid from any Party in being elected to this House, and I do not seek it.  When I go to the hustings down in Westmeath, I shall be quite safe&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>(<i>Interruptions.</i>)</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is a member of two Parties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnSheridan" hpid="Mr. J.D. Sheridan Mr. J.D. Sheridan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.D. Sheridan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have never been, a member of any Party.  I defy the Senator to prove that I was.  The Senator may have quite a volume of lung power, but he does not have such a volume of logic or truth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the truth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnSheridan" hpid="Mr. J.D. Sheridan Mr. J.D. Sheridan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.D. Sheridan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am a vocational member and I represent a very important industry in this country, the livestock trade.  I have listened to <Col N="678" /> Senator Hayes delivering judgments on farming, on the livestock trade, and on a hundred and one different subjects connected with farming.  In my opinion, Senator Hayes' knowledge of agriculture would fill a very small volume.  I have heard other professors and legal luminaries discoursing on agricultural interests in this House and yet we have been told that there is no necessity for any vocational members in the House.</P>
      <P>We heard the Government say today that it was up to the country to get itself reorganised.  Every day we take up the papers, we read recommendations from various Ministers saying that Ireland is not sufficiently up-to-date. Yet we are told that the real function we should serve in this House is the provision of a forum for the talking of politics.  Even in the course of discoursing on various subjects, I have heard it said: &ldquo;This has been too long a political issue; I am not speaking politically&rdquo;, but let someone get up on this side of the House and say a bad word about the ex-Minister for Agriculture, Deputy Dillon, and there is an outcry over there.  Let someone on this side of the House get up to praise the present Minister for Agriculture, and there is an outcry on the other side.  This political business does not get us very far.</P>
      <P>Not to confine myself to the Fine Gael side, but to treat a little with the Fianna Fáil side, we had Senator Lenihan preaching a very fine homily on the high virtue of politics.  With Senator Lenihan, politics seems to be a sort of religion.  He has a sublime contempt for anyone who is not a Party man.  If I were to put the farming view with regard to Senator Lenihan's comments, I would put it, ignorantly, if you like, along these lines: There is nothing more beneficial to a rising counsel than to make a name for himself in this House as a brilliant speaker.  That is a great advantage in the legal profession, but I just wonder, in a backward sort of country like this that needs so much effort today, is that also helpful?  Is that political activity of so much value in getting our country into a better position?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Our representatives went across to <Col N="679" /> London last week in an effort to make a better trade agreement.  Politics has reached the stage that if these men brought back a good agreement, the people who do not agree politically with them would pull it to pieces in any case.  I think that is wrong.  I should like to say to Senator Lenihan <Col N="680" /> and to Senator Hayes that we have had a surfeit of politics, and if we gave it a rest for a few years, the country might benefit.  I support the motion.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, March 2nd, 1960.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>