<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="9" Month="Nov" Year="1960" Vol="53" No="1" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 9 Samhain 1960" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 9 November 1960" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Death of Senator. -" RHead="Expression of Sympathy">
    <Title>Death of Senator. - Expression of Sympathy.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is with very deep regret I announce to the House the death, during the Recess, of our friend and colleague, Senator Professor Barniville.  I bhFlaitheas Dé go raibh a anam.</P>
      <P>In the passing of Senator Barniville, Ireland has lost one of her most distinguished sons and the medical profession one of its most prominent surgeons. Over the years his name has become a household legend and many will mourn his loss, particularly those members of the Old I.R.A. who owe their lives to him as a result of his skill, attention and protection during the War of Independence.  His quiet, gentle and charming manner endeared him to all with whom he came in contact. His personality and his sense of humour made him popular with all the members of the Oireachtas, irrespective of their political ties.  For a man who had spent so many years in the public life of this country, the best tribute I could pay to him is to say that some of his greatest friends and admirers were amongst those who differed from him in their political outlook.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The late Senator, after a brilliant academic career, was first appointed in 1911 as Resident Surgeon to the <Col N="2" /> Mater Misericordiae Hospital, Dublin. His long association with the Mater Hospital had become a sort of a tradition, so much so that one could not think of the name Barniville without thinking of it&mdash;they had become almost synonymous.  In 1928 he was appointed to the Chair of Surgery in University College, Dublin, where, as a teacher, he displayed outstanding talents.  The personal interest he took in his students, upon whom he had a profound influence, is reflected in the manner in which he was returned unfailingly to this House, of which he was a member from its inception in 1922.</P>
    <P>To the widow and relatives of the late Senator, I shall convey on your behalf and on my own, our sympathy and appreciation.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Senators rose in their places.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Death of Senator. -" RHead="Election of Senators">
    <Title>Death of Senator. - Election of Senators.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá orm a fhógairt gur toghadh na comhaltaí seo a leannas chun na corrfholúntais i gcomhaltas an tSeanaid lena mbaineann na Rúin a rith Seanad Éireann an 20 Iúil, 1960, a líonadh:</P>
      <P Just="Center">AN ROLLA OIBREACHAIS</P>
      <P Just="Center">
        <i>An Fo-Rolla do Chomhlachtaí Ainmiúcháin</i>
      </P>
      <P Just="Center">Éamon de Brún,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="3" /> AN ROLLA RIARACHÁIN</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>An Fo-Rolla do Chomhlachtaí Ainmiúcháin</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">Gearóid Díolún.</P>
    <P>I have to announce that the following members have been elected to fill the casual vacancies in the membership of the Seanad to which the Resolutions of Seanad Éireann of the 20th July, 1960, have reference:</P>
    <P Just="Center">LABOUR PANEL</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Nominating Bodies Sub-Panel</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">Edward Browne;</P>
    <P Just="Center">ADMINISTRATIVE PANEL</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Nominating Bodies Sub-Panel</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">Gerard B. Dillon.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Senator Browne was introduced to the Cathaoirleach by Senator Murphy and Senator Dillon was introduced to the Cathaoirleach by Senator Carter. The Senators took their seats.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Joint Committee on Electoral" RHead="Law. - Interim Report">
    <Title>Joint Committee on Electoral Law. - Interim Report.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Tairgim:</P>
      <P>Go luífidh an Tuarascáil Eatramhach ar an mBord;</P>
      <P Just="Center">agus</P>
      <P>Go gclóbhuailfear an Tuarascáil Eatramhach.</P>
      <P>D'aontaoidh agus d'ordaoidh dá réir.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Military Service Pensions (Increase) Bill, 1960" RHead="(Certified Money Bill) &mdash; Second Stage">
    <Title>Military Service Pensions (Increase) Bill, 1960    (Certified Money Bill) &mdash;   Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed:  That the Bill be now read a Second Time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Aire Cosanta (Caoimhghín Ó Beoláin) Aire Cosanta (Caoimhghín Ó Beoláin)">
      <NameTxt>Aire Cosanta (Caoimhghín Ó Beoláin)</NameTxt>
      <P>Leis an mBille seo, tugtar údarás reachtúil le hagaidh na méaduithe ar phinsin faoi Achtanna na bPinsean Seirbhise Mileata, 1924 go 1960, i leith fianais sa tréimhse 1916 go 1923, a deonadh le héifeacht ón lú Lúnasa, 1960, ar údarás Meastacháin Bhreise le haghaidh pinsean a ritheadh i nDáil Éireann ar 20ú Iúil, 1960.  Meastar £29,400 mar <Col N="4" /> an gcostas bliantúil agus tá na méaduithe de réir mar a udaraíodh ag an Aire Airgeadais ina Ráiteas ar an gCáinaisnéis in Aibreán, 1960.</P>
      <P>This Bill gives statutory authority for the increases in pensions under the Military Service Pensions Acts, 1924 to 1960, in respect of active service in the period 1916 to 1923, which were granted with effect from 1st August, 1960, on the authority of a Supplementary Estimate for pensions passed in Dáil Éireann on 20th July, 1960. The annual cost is estimated at £29,400 and the increases are in accordance with what was authorised by the Minister for Finance in his Budget Statement in April, 1960.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="An Dochtúir Ó Donnabháin An Dochtúir Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>An Dochtúir Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>Aontaoim leis an mBille.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Military Service Pensions (Increase) Bill," RHead="1960&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Military Service Pensions (Increase) Bill, 1960&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 1 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister, in view of the fact that other pensions are to be increased to-day by seven and a half per cent., why is it that here the military service pensions are being increased by only five per cent.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>This is in accordance with the Budget Statement made by the Minister for Finance.  He announced definitely in that statement that military service pensions would be increased by five per cent. and this gives statutory effect to that undertaking.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 2 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MacSwiney (Pension) (Increase) (No. 2) Bill, 1960 (Certified" RHead="Money Bill) &mdash; Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>MacSwiney (Pension) (Increase) (No. 2) Bill, 1960    (Certified Money Bill) &mdash;   Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="5" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Pensions (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill, 1960 (Certified" RHead="Money Bill) &mdash; Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Pensions (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill, 1960    (Certified Money Bill) &mdash;  Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: That the Bill be now read a Second Time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Aire Cosanta (Caoimhghín Ó Beoláin) Aire Cosanta (Caoimhghín Ó Beoláin)">
      <NameTxt>Aire Cosanta (Caoimhghín Ó Beoláin)</NameTxt>
      <P>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Tá soláthar á dhéanamh leis an <Col N="6" /> mBille seo chun údarás reachtúil a dheonadh do'n mhéadú de seacht-goleith fé'n gcéad i ngach ceann ar leith den dá phinsean de £561 16s. sa bhliain is iníochta le baintreachta Mhichil Uí Cheallacháin agus Sheoirse Mhic Fhlannchadha, ba Mhéaraí Luimnigh tráth.  Tá na méaduithe á íoc ón lú Lúnasa 1960, i leith, ar údarás Meastacháin Bhreise le haghaidh pinsean a ritheadh i nDáil Éireann ar an 20ú Iúil 1960 agus tá siad de réir mar a udaraoidh ag an Aire Airgeadais ina Ráiteas ar an gCáinaisnéis in Aibreán 1960.</P>
    <P>This Bill provides statutory authority for the increase of 7½ per cent. in each of the pensions of £561 16s. per annum payable to the widows of Micheál Ó Ceallacháin and Seoirse Mac Fhlannchadha, former Mayors of Limerick.  The increases are being paid since 1st August, 1960 on the authority of a Supplementary Estimate for pensions which was passed in Dáil Éireann on 20th July, 1960 and they are in accordance with what was authorised by the Minister for Finance in his Budget Statement in April, 1960.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make a point in regard to this Bill on the fact that from the terms of the Bill, it was not quite clear to whom it applies.  I feel that, in a way, it might be better if, as in the Bill which we just had before us, the Title showed to whom it applied.  It looks a bit mysterious this way, although it is, of course, a Bill we all welcome.  There is no point in suggesting an amendment now, but it seems odd that in the case of the Bill which has just been before us, we had the name of the recipient in the Title whereas here it is all left anonymous and there is no mention in the Title or in the Bill of those to whom it applies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>That arose at the time the pensions were granted originally and I cannot accept any personal responsibilities for the fact that there was a difference in regard to the Title.  This is known as the Pensions (No. 2) Bill and the other was known as the MacSwiney (Pension) (Increase) <Col N="7" /> (No. 2) Bill and that was the position which I found.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Solicitors (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1960&mdash; Second Stage">
    <Title>Solicitors (Amendment) Bill, 1960&mdash; Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Justice (Mr. Haughey) Charles J. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Justice (Mr. Haughey)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill, which is a much more comprehensive one, replaces the Solicitors (Amendment) Bill, 1958, which was withdrawn in the Dáil in February last.  The objects of the Bill are threefold.  First, and like the 1958 Bill, it proposes to provide for striking the name of a solicitor off the roll or suspending him from practice or censuring him in any case where he has been found guilty of misconduct. Secondly, it proposes to deal with the Compensation Fund which was set up under the Solicitors Act, 1954, to compensate clients for losses caused to them through the dishonesty of solicitors. Thirdly, it contains certain important miscellaneous provisions in regard to solicitors.</P>
      <P>Part II of the Bill is necessary because of the Supreme Court decision in March, 1958, that Part III of the 1954 Act is unconstitutional in that it meant conferring a judicial power on a non-judicial body, namely, the Disciplinary Committee of the Law Society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 6 of the Bill provides for the new Disciplinary Committee of the Law Society.  This Committee will replace that constituted under the 1954 Act, but they will not exercise any exclusively judicial function.  The scheme of that Act involved a system under which the Disciplinary Committee could strike the name of a solicitor off the roll or suspend him from practice, the solicitor having a right of <Col N="8" /> appeal to the Chief Justice.  The Supreme Court, in the decision in 1958, held that a right of appeal was not sufficient to bring a procedure, otherwise unconstitutional, within the Constitution.</P>
    <P>Under Section 7 the new Committee will have powers of inquiry only, where an allegation of misconduct is made by any person or by the Law Society.  If the Disciplinary Committee are satisfied that there is a <i>prima facie</i> case for an inquiry, they must proceed to hold one and embody their findings in the form of a report to the High Court.  If they find misconduct, the Law Society must bring the report before the High Court.  The report will specify the evidence laid before the Committee and their opinion as to the fitness or otherwise of the solicitor to be a member of the profession.  There is no obligation whatever on the High Court to accept the opinion of the Disciplinary Committee and the Court may accept or reject it, at the Court's discretion.</P>
    <P>The Court, having considered the report of the Disciplinary Committee, may strike the name of the solicitor off the roll, suspend him from practice, censure him or censure him and require him to pay a money penalty. The High Court may also direct the solicitor to make restitution or may freeze his bank account.  On special grounds, the Court may send the case back to the Disciplinary Committee to take further evidence for submission to it and to make a supplementary report.  All this is provided for in Section 8.</P>
    <P>Section 9 is concerned with the removal at his own request of the name of a solicitor from the roll and section 10 with the restoration of the name of a solicitor to the roll.  The Disciplinary Committee may, but only if they think fit, remove a solicitor's name from the roll at his own request. Otherwise, the matter must be referred to the High Court.  Restoration to the roll will be exclusively a matter for the High Court.  It may at first sight seem strange that a solicitor cannot have his name removed from the roll if he so desires.  The vast majority of cases will be perfectly <Col N="9" /> straightforward; but it is necessary to provide against automatic removal from the roll on application if the solicitor desires to have his name removed simply to avoid his obligations. We do not want a person to be able to say: &ldquo;I am no longer a solicitor, and there is nothing you may do to me.  Your Act and your regulations do not apply to me.&rdquo;  Admittedly, under Section 4, &ldquo;solicitor&rdquo;, where the context so permits or requires, includes a former solicitor or a deceased solicitor, but this may not be sufficeint, and Section 9 is necessary in its present form, if only <i>ex abundanti cautela.</i></P>
    <P>Section 11 will cover cases where the former Disciplinary Committee have purported to strike the name of a solicitor off the roll under the unconstitutional provisions of the 1954 Act.  In these cases, the Society may apply by notice of motion to the High Court to have the solicitors concerned properly struck off and the section provides for the procedure to be followed.</P>
    <P>Under Section 12, the orders of the High Court are to be final and not appealable, but an appeal will lie to the Supreme Court on a specified question of law.  We have considered this matter carefully in consultation with the Council of the Law Society and we are satisfied that the provision is fair and reasonable.  The High Court will be deciding on matters of fact in most cases, but if a question of law is involved the rights of the solicitor are being protected by allowing an appeal to the Supreme Court. The Attorney General has no doubt but that the section is constitutional.</P>
    <P>By reason of Section 13, the disciplinary jurisdiction vested in the High Court will be exercised by the President of the High Court or by an ordinary judge of the High Court to be nominated by the President.  This is designed to give uniformity of practice and procedure and conforms with the policy of Section 25 to transfer from the Chief Justice to the President of the High Court certain more or less administrative functions, now performed by the Chief Justice under the 1954 Act.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="10" /> Section 14 of the Bill will clothe with absolute privilege disciplinary proceedings under the 1954 Act and under the proposed Act.  The section will put in statutory form what is the existing law as interpreted by judicial decision.</P>
    <P>The remaining sections in Part II of the Bill are consequential and re-enact, with appropriate amendments, certain sections of the 1954 Act that are listed for repeal in the Schedule.</P>
    <P>Part III of the Bill will set out in a more convenient way the provisions of the 1954 Act concerning the power of the Law Society to deal with the documents of certain solicitors and also the provisions concerning the control of banking accounts of solicitors. In addition, it is proposed in Sections 21 and 22 to put the Compensation Fund on a sound financial footing. This Fund, which will be continued in existence, was set up under the 1954 Act to compensate clients who suffer losses due to the dishonesty of solicitors. The making of grants in respect of losses occurring before the 6th January last and the amounts thereof were in the absolute discretion of the Society.  In respect of losses occurring after that date compensation must in general be in full.</P>
    <P>The annual contribution at present payable by each solicitor is £5, but solicitors in their first three years of practice pay half that amount.  For the 1961 practice year or any practice year thereafter, the contribution may be increased from £5 up to a maximum of £10.  It was hoped in 1954 that after five years the Fund would be able to compensate clients in full and that provision for an additional contribution of up to £5 would be sufficient to keep the Fund solvent.  This hope has not been fulfilled and the Fund is now unable to meet its liabilities. The losses have been much higher than was anticipated and no payments have been made to claimants for some time past.</P>
    <P>Section 22 proposes to raise the contribution to £20 and it will remain at that figure until a reserve of £25,000 has been built up to meet exceptional claims.  After the reserve has been <Col N="11" /> established, the Society may, for any year, reduce the contributions; but in so doing they must have regard to the principle of keeping the reserve at £25,000.  There is no statutory obligation being placed on the Society to increase to contribution but, if they decide to do so, they must have regard to the amount of the reserve; and their powers to increase are limited in this way.</P>
    <P>As I visualise it, the normal contribution will not be more than £20. In fact, the Society hope that they may be able to reduce the contribution after a few years.  The existing liabilities of the Fund under the 1954 Act will be paid off as soon as possible.  To realise that the proposed contribution is double what the Society would have had to impose at the end of this year.  It is, however, less than eight shillings a week, which is small when compared with a solicitor's other expenses in running his office and also when the fall in the value of money since before the war is taken into account.  Other schemes for compensating clients have had to be discarded in favour of what is in fact a compulsory insurance scheme with an adequate annual contribution.</P>
    <P>The solicitors' profession is an honourable and upright one and it is unfortunate that the conduct of a few members is tending to give it a bad name.  This, however, obtains in all professions.  Reputable solicitors, who form the majority, will have to underwrite their dishonest colleagues Unfortunately, no other system will work satisfactorily; and it is necessary because of existing circumstances to impose what I readily admit is a substantial burden.</P>
    <P>Part IV of the Bill contains the miscellaneous provisions.  Three of the sections concerned propose important changes in the law.  These are Section 26, 31 and 32.</P>
    <P>Section 26 proposes to add two new paragraphs to Section 49 (1) of the 1954 Act.  That section provides for the refusal of a practising certificate in certain specified cases listed in subsection (1).  It is proposed to add the case of a solicitor who has failed <Col N="12" /> to comply with an order of the High Court and also the case of a solicitor who has failed to comply with the Solicitors' Accounts Regulations or with regulations as respects professional practice, conduct and discipline. If a solicitor does not conform with the regulations dealing with accounts or with the other regulations I have mentioned, he should not be entitled automatically to the issue of a practising certificate.</P>
    <P>Where, under Section 49 of the 1954 Act, the Society direct the registrar to refuse to issue a practising certificate, the certificate must nevertheless be issued if the applicant satisfies the Society that he has appealed to the Chief Justice.  The President of the High Court is being substituted for the Chief Justice in Section 25 of the Bill.  While it is proposed to add two paragraphs to Section 49 (1) of the 1954 Act, two existing paragraphs, (b) and (c), are listed for repeal in the Schedule to the Bill.  Paragraph (b) is concerned with the case of a solicitor who has been suspended from practice, the period of the suspension having expired.  Paragraph (c) specifies the case of a solicitor whose name has been struck off the roll and then restored.  In both cases, the Society may direct the refusal of a practising certificate.</P>
    <P>Whatever justification there may have been for paragraphs (b) and (c) under the scheme of the 1954 Act, which purported to allow the Disciplinary Committee to suspend from practice and to strike off and restore to the roll, there is no justification now.  Once the period of suspension imposed on a solicitor by the High Court has expired or once the High Court has restored to the roll the name of a solicitor which has been struck off, the solicitor concerned has served his punishment and should not be liable to further punishment.</P>
    <P>Section 31 makes detailed provision for the production each year by every solicitor, to whom the Solicitors' Accounts Regulations apply, of an accountant's certificate stating that the solicitor is keeping the Accounts Regulations.  The regulations, which apply to every solicitor practising on <Col N="13" /> his own or in partnership and receiving clients' moneys, oblige the solicitor to keep a separate client bank account or accounts.  Failure to deliver the annual accountant's certificate will be misconduct for the purpose of the disciplinary provisions contained in Part II of the Bill and, moreover, the registrar is being empowered to withhold the issue of a practising certificate until the solicitor delivers the accountant's certificate.</P>
    <P>Section 66 of the 1954 Act, which made accounts regulations mandatory, provides that the regulations shall make provision for, <i>inter alia,</i> enforcing compliance with them and ascertaining whether they have been complied with.  Under the Solicitors' Accounts Regulations, 1955, the Council of the Law Society may require a solicitor at any time to have his books, bank statements and other appropriate documents produced for examination by an accountant approved or appointed by the Council. The powers of the Council would not normally be exercised until a complaint in regard to the solicitor is made or the Council become aware themselves of some suspected irregularity. By that time, the solicitor will in many cases have already landed himself in trouble.</P>
    <P>The object of Section 31 of the Bill is to keep him out of trouble.  The annual accountant's certificate will protect the public and it will also protect the solicitor himself.  Furthermore, it will help to protect the Compensation Fund so that the profession in general will have a safeguard against those members likely to impose on the Fund substantial liability for their dishonesty.  In this respect, the section is a corollary to a Fund, contributions to which are obligatory for all solicitors though the vast majority of them are honest and careful in the handling of clients' moneys.  Accounts regulations are of little practical value if they are not strictly enforced and the only way to see that they are enforced is by a regular examination.</P>
    <P>A solicitor must be both a professional adviser and a business man.  As a business man he should, if he is prudent, keep proper books and have <Col N="14" /> them regularly examined and audited. The Council have stressed that if appropriate steps are taken before great damage is done, the public and the practitioner will be protected from worse harm.  Admittedly, the accountant's certificate will not be an absolute protection against a solicitor who is deliberately dishonest, but it should save from himself that solicitor who, through carelessness or negligence not amounting, in the beginning at least, to fraudulent intent, would otherwise gradually and inevitably get himself deeper and deeper into trouble.</P>
    <P>The need for an annual accountant's certificate has been demonstrated in England and Scotland.  In England, the obligation was imposed in an enactment of 1941 and rules were made to give effect to that enactment in 1946. A corresponding enactment for Scotland was passed in 1958.  In the Six Counties, proposals for an annual certificate are contained in a Private Member's Bill sponsored by the Northern Law Society.</P>
    <P>Senators will notice that Section 31 of our Bill will, by reason of Section 2, come into operation on a day to be fixed by order of the Minister for Justice made on the request of the Society&mdash;which means the Council of the Society.  The Government have agreed that the section should not be brought into operation immediately so as to allow time for the making of the necessary regulations and to acclimatise the profession to the fact that an annual accountant's certificate will evnetually be required from every solicitor.</P>
    <P>I desire to stress that it is not the intention to have the section enacted and then to do nothing more.  This section is regarded by the Government as one of vital importance which must be brought into operation within a reasonable time.  If it is not, the question of fresh legislation will have to be considered.  In England, one of the rules made in 1946 provides that the accountant shall make a comparison, as at not fewer than two dates selected by him at random, between the liabilities of the solicitor to his clients and the balance standing to the credit of the client account.  This <Col N="15" /> is, of course, a very valuable rule and was obviously intended to see to it that a solicitor is not allowed to evade his obligations simply by having his house in order at the time the accountant makes the examination.</P>
    <P>As Senators are aware, there has been an amount of disquiet at certain cases involving dishonesty by solicitors that have from time to time come to light.  The Council of the Society are very concerned about these cases and are anxious to do all they can in the matter.  Although there is a duty to protect the public, there is also the public's duty to protect itself.  People who have to consult solicitors should be careful to avoid the disreputable members.  Where a client is negligent and loses his money, the compensation Fund will not automatically indemnify him, as payments from the Fund in cases of negligence are in the discretion of the Society and will continue to be so.  Reputable solicitors are in the majority, and a client who exposes himself to fraud with his eyes open has often only himself to blame. I am not, of course, suggesting that innocent clients do not lose their money through the dishonesty of solicitors.  They do.  Nevertheless, loss might, in many instances, be avoided if more thought were given to the solicitor to whom one entrusts one's affairs.</P>
    <P>The last section of the Bill that calls for discussion is Section 32.  This is a technical section which proposes to apply the ordinary bankruptcy rule in respect of the administration of the client account or accounts of bankrupt solicitor or of a solicitor who dies insolvent.  The funds in a client account are treated as trust funds and, as such, do not form part of the estate for the purposes of bankruptcy or inslovency on death.  They are applied in accordance with what is known as the rule in Clayton's Case. This rule lays down that debts must be discharged in order to date or, as is said, &ldquo;first in, first out.&rdquo;  Section 32 of the Bill proposes to exclude the rule by providing that the sum or sums at the credit of the client account or accounts of a bankrupt or <Col N="16" /> deceased insolvent solicitor shall be divisible proportionately amongst the clents of the solicitor according to the respective sums received by the solicitor on their account and remaining due by him to them.</P>
    <P>May I conclude by saying that I hope that this Bill, which is an agreed Bill with the Council of the Law Society, will fulfil its purposes and be of lasting benefit to the solicitors' profession as well as to the public?</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a Committee rather than a Second Reading measure and therefore we do not propose to delay the House on this Stage. As the Parliamentary Secretary has explained to us, it is designed to make rules and regulations for the better ordering and management of the profession, and also to give powers wherby disciplinary measures can be taken, where necessary.</P>
      <P>I was glad to notice that the Parliamentary Secretary, when speaking about this profession, said that as in other walks of life, there may be some black sheep in it from time to time, but that should not be regarded as casting any reflection whatever on the general body of this very honourable profession.  The disciplinary measures will be taken by the profession itself. Most of the sections that appear in this measure appear with the consent of the Incorporated Law Society.</P>
      <P>I do not propose at this juncture to delay the House any longer.  Any amendments or suggestions we have to make relative to the Bill will be made on Committee Stage, as it is more appropriate that it should be done at that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Louis Walsh Mr. Louis Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Louis Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to thank the Parliamentary Secretary and the Senator who has spoken for the kind tributes they have paid to the majority of the members of my profession. I think, however, that the Parliamentary Secretary made an understatement when he said that reputable solicitors are in the majority. In view of the fact that the number of defaulting solicitors is approximately three out of 1,300 or 1,400 in the country, the percentage is extremely low.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="17" /> As a Parliamentary Secretary has pointed out, solicitors deal with the personal affairs and the accounts of many helpless people.  For instance, they deal with very old people who have considerable savings or with young people who are next-ofkin or legatees or who benefit under substantial decrees awarded by a court.  These people must depend on the integrity of solicitors and the guidance which they obtain from them. It is obvious, therefore, that considerable funds pass through solicitors' hands each year for investment or for holding in trust.</P>
    <P>Accordingly, there is a fair amount of temptation placed in the path of solicitors to use such moneys from time to time to tide them over personal difficulties because of over-spending or domestic reasons.  It is right, therefore, that the State should be concerned that the practitioners are worthy of the trust the community places in them and that it should see that that trust is honoured.</P>
    <P>The Council of the Society have been waiting for some considerable time for the introduction of this Bill because of the void created by the decision in the case of O'Farrell &amp; Gorman in the Supreme Court, which resulted in the Disciplinary Committee losing its power to deal with defaulting solicitors and to take the necessary action against such people.  As a consequence of this lack of power, these cases which have been held up may have resulted in some solicitors being more negligent than they would otherwise have been and claims against the Compensation Fund being of considerable size.</P>
    <P>I appreciate the difficulties in dealing with this new legislation owing to the constitutional issue that was raised and the considerable discussions that must have taken place between the Law Society and the Minister, the Parliamentary Secretary, the officials of the Department of Justice and subsequently the Attorney General.  At any rate, it is satisfactory that this Bill has now been brought forward and the Law Society will again be in a position to deal adequately with defaulting members and thus protect and <Col N="18" /> build up the Compensation Fund, the reserve of which must be £25,000 as provided in the Bill.</P>
    <P>The passing of the Bill should undoubtedly add to the prestige of the solicitors' profession and adequately safeguard the interests of the public in dealing with the individual members of the profession.</P>
    <P>It must be appreciated that it was the Law Society themselves that suggested the setting up of this Compensation Fund, and the regulations made under the 1954 Act.  The burden of building up this Fund will undoubtedly impose sacrifices on individual members, particularly in rural areas where practices are fairly small and the funds passing through solicitors' hands are ever so much less than those passing through the hands of solicitors with big practices in the better-off areas.</P>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary has explained and dealt adequately with the provisions of the Bill.  The proposal in Section 31 will undoubtedly tighten up the regulations as to the keeping of adequate accounts and should, as the Parliamentary Secretary stated, save solicitors from themselves and encourage them to keep on the straight and narrow path.  It should also mean that eventually the demands on the Compensation Fund will not be as great as they are at the moment, and that ultimately the premium which the solicitor will be required to pay will be less than the £20 set out in the Bill.  The Society accepted the obligation to establish the Compensation Fund only on the understanding that they would have sufficient control over their members properly to protect the Fund.  For these reasons, I am pleased to be able to recommend the House to pass this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I fully endorse the remarks of speakers in this and the other House with regard to the satisfaction that must follow from the fact that this Bill has the practically unanimous approval of the profession.  As Senator Burke has said, this is more or less a Committee Bill, but I should like to ask the Parliamentary Secretary a few questions about it.  One aspect does slightly disturb me.  I cannot follow what the procedure would be if court <Col N="19" /> proceedings were pending or an action being brought against a solicitor where the Disciplinary Committee might also be inquiring into a claim. Does this committee wait until any proceedings pending in a court are finished or will the committee take action on their own in camera perhaps or in some other way, or would their proceedings be harmful in any way to the solicitor?  There might be some doubt and the solicitor would be entitled to that doubt.  Where does this committee's function come in and where does the court case come in?</P>
      <P>The sections from Section 19 on cover the position where the Society are of opinion that a solicitor has been guilty of dishonesty or misconduct. Would it not be more proper and more in the interests of a solicitor who might, in fact, be accused wrongly if another solicitor, acting on the instructions of the Incorporated Law Society, could be quietly placed in his office with full power to carry on the business, instead of giving power to the Society to take control of trust and other documents, and to give notice to the bank that certain accounts must not be dealt with, which makes the whole thing rather public?  There must be cases where there is no necessity to make the proceedings public at all until further inquiries are made.  These are two aspects in defence of a solicitor who might be wrongly accused on which I should like the Parliamentary Secretary to comment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the £25,000, would it not be better to use that by way of some sort of fidelity bond or something of that nature?  It occurs to me that £25,000 nowadays in a big solicitor's office, particularly a solicitor's office in the city of Dublin, is not a very large sum.  He might easily handle that in one transaction for one client. If a solicitor tended to be dishonest, he would obviously wait until the occasion arose when he would handle some such big sum.  There could be other ways of securing compensation. Each solicitor could insure himself.  I should like to have the Parliamentary Secretary's comment on whether that <Col N="20" /> £25,000 would be adequate at all at the present day.</P>
    <P>Section 32 contains provisions in relation to certain accounts kept by a solicitor at a bank.  Could we not add to that another section to the effect that any further sums in the solicitor's hands could be easy recognisable as clients' funds?  Take the case where a solicitor is going bankrupt.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The bankruptcy rules apply to them, anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we not take that out of it?  Take the case of a solicitor who knows on the day before proceedings are to be taken against him, that some clients' money is to come into his hands.  He lodges that to his own account.  The money in question is a very recognisable sum.  Would it not be possible to include such words in that section as &ldquo;the recognisable sum&rdquo; which could be saved on behalf of a client?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill and I am glad to know that the solicitors' profession, like any other profession, welcomes an effort to lift the general standard.  Much stress has been laid upon the defalcations, dishonesty and loss of clients' money, but I have the impression, from what little dealings I have had with the profession, that perhaps, most of it is not real dishonesty, but rather a lack of business methods.  In the solicitors' profession as such, there seems to be a tradition of old fusty, musty books and the lack of a modern approach in dealing with accounts and business generally.  The Bill cannot obviously do anything for that.  It is a matter for the profession itself&mdash;if my impression is correct&mdash;to try to ensure that standard or give training in this direction to solicitors&mdash;not simply training in law but training in business methods and administration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another aspect of the profession which I think is open to some complaint are the delay and failure to carry out work expeditiously.  We know it is difficult to deal with the law.  We know it is difficult to dispose of estates.  I have had complaints from people with comparatively small <Col N="21" /> estates that the time taken by the solicitor in going through the necessary work is often very alarming. Again, while the Bill cannot do anything about this, the profession as such should, try to encourage expedition in dealing with such work and if the Department can help by streamlining their machinery, then I should hope that it would do so.</P>
    <P>As I said at the outset, I do not think there is very much real dishonesty. There is very little.  Much of the trouble arises from perhaps lack of training in business methods and the fact that things get into a mess because the solicitors do not approach the problem properly, in the first instance.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the other speakers, I welcome this Bill and I welcome it especially because it is presented as a Bill agreed with the Law Society.  Its provisions and the changes from the 1954 Act go a long way towards meeting conditions to-day and this applies especially to the Compensation Fund; but I should like to ask the Parliamentary Secretary about the magnitude of this; £25,000 does seem to be a very small fund to meet liabilities for the whole country. Again, in regard to the charge of £20 &mdash;and of course if the fund is increased or has to be increased in the future, that charge would naturally be increased&mdash;I should have thought that some system of levying the charge on the income of the solicitor, or on his whole turnover, rather than a flat <i>per capita</i> charge, would be more equitable.  For instance, a small country solicitor who is barely making ends meet will apparently be asked to make the same contribution as a solicitor carrying on a prosperous business in a large town.  That is scarcely equitable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary stressed, in regard to Section 12, that the slight curtailment of powers and the recognition of the finality of the decisions of the High Court, except in matters relating to the interpretation of the law, was very fair and reasonable. I should like to know: did the Law Society actually agree to those powers?  Are they in full agreement <Col N="22" /> with Section 12?  Again, in connection with the Compensation Fund, it is essential that the Law Society should have the maximum control of it, since they are the body creating the fund. In regard to Section 31, the Parliamentary Secretary mentioned that two slight powers of the Law Society were whittled down, for instance, that a solicitor has to be automatically admitted by the Law Society when he has carried out his penalty.  Seeing that this admission brings him back as a participant in the fund, I should like to know if the Law Society is in agreement with Section 31?</P>
    <P>I fully endorse what has been said by Senator Murphy and the need for having legal matters dealt with more expeditiously.  I had some experience of that recently, of the length of time it takes to carry out even what appears to be simple transfers, and it is very baffling.  I hope that we may see a big improvement in this and probably the best way to secure it would be the provision of the annual account which will be mandatory in a short time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. P. Crowley Mr. P. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>I also want to welcome this measure and the purpose for which the Bill is introduced, but, like some of the other speakers, I am troubled about one or two aspects which strike me as being contradictory, particularly in the light of the statement made by the Parliamentary Secretary. What troubles me is that we are told the Bill has been made necessary because of a ruling by the Supreme Court which invalidated an order given under the old Act and we are told there is a necessity for putting that right and making the orders of the new Disciplinary Committee, and so on, constitutional.  I think Senator Quinlan, like myself, is a bit troubled about the actual effect of Section 12 which says that&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1) Subject to subsection (2) of this section, an order of the High Court under Section 8 of this Act....</P>
      <P>and so on&mdash;</P>
      <P>...shall be final and not appealable. The section then goes on to say in the second part&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="23" /> By leave of the High Court, an appeal, by the Society or the solicitor concerned, from an order of the High Court under Section 8 of this Act, under that section as applied by Section 11 of this Act or under Section 9 or Section 10 of this Act shall lie to the Supreme Court on a specified question of law.</P>
    <P>That section seems to me to impose a certain restriction, either on the freedom of the individual solicitor or on the Incorporated Law Society itself, to proceed with an appeal from the High Court to the Supreme Court.  As a layman, that strikes me as being restrictive and I should imagine it must in some way be regarded as unconstitutional. I understood the Parliamentary Secretary to say that he had the opinion of the Attorney General that this section was in fact constitutional.  With all due respect to the opinion of the Attorney General, Attorneys General have been held not to be infallible in the past and in fact we have it offered here as a defence of this Bill that an order of the Disciplinary Committee under the old Act was held to be unconstitutional.  That being so, I should like to hear the Parliamentary Secretary further on this section and it would be interesting to know has that section been agreed to by the Law Society.  It seems to me to be restrictive.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Parliamentary Secretary appears to be overwhelmed with welcomes, I might as well add my voice to what has been said by other speakers.  The Bill is necessary from the point of view of the solicitors, their clients and the public.  It provides machinery which it is hoped is now constitutional for dealing with cases of the dishonest solicitor.  I was very glad the Parliamentary Secretary pointed out that clients themselves sometimes contribute to their own undoing and to their own disasters by the way in which they themselves behave and the kind of solicitors they select.  The negligent client is not going to be indemnified under this Bill when it becomes an Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="24" /> Something has been said about the £20 contribution.  It is a minimum figure and although the Law Society hoped it would be reduced, it must be remembered that the Bill contains provisions for allowing it to be increased, and it might be increased, but of course one hopes that that will not happen.  The true story regarding the underlying principles of the Bill is that the solicitors are an honourable profession; they are trusted by the public; and the vast majority of them are worthy of the trust reposed in them. It is the purpose of this Bill that they must pay for the trust which the public places in them and if a person goes to a solicitor who is still on the roll and who is negligent and dishonest, the client will not suffer.  I have to agree with the Parliamentary Secretary that there is no other scheme except the one in this Bill for creating a fund which will accomplish that end.</P>
    <P>There were some points made by Senator Murphy which may very well be true, that the dusty and fusty atmosphere gives an impression of reliability and integrity and is attractive. The Bill contains provisions which will make all solicitors keep their books in an up-to-date manner because they have to be subject to inspection. Although I have not looked at the matter lately, I think at present that, when solicitors are doing their course, they do a certain amount of accountancy, but I have not got much faith, and I am sure the Parliamentary Secretary will agree with me, in the possibility of teaching people accountancy when they are doing law. They get some&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Teach accountants law?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think accountants are lawyers, and I am not sure that lawyers can be accountants, but if it teaches them enough to convince them they cannot do their account themselves, I think that would be a good thing and a good deal of Senator Murphy's complaints will have been eradicated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some people have said that this £25,000 is not sufficient.  I am sure the Parliamentary Secretary has information <Col N="25" /> on that, and it would be a very strange year, I think, in which £25,000 would have to be paid out of the funds.  I should like to go on record as disagreeing with Senator Quinlan when he says that the fund should be on a sliding scale, that the bigger the solicitor, the more he will pay.  Their accounts are already mulcted by way of income tax and should not be mulcted again in this way.  The only way in which it can be done is the way it is being done in the Bill, and one can only hope that the amount will not be increased, that the provision in the Bill for the proper keeping of accounts&mdash;two bank accounts: a personal and a clients' account&mdash;and the inspection of the books will considerably reduce the danger of the clients' account being in any way defrauded.  I can only express the hope that the Bill which is a great improvement from that point of view will work satisfactorily and that it will not break itself upon any constitutional rock in the ocean.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>It appears to me that this Bill is really an attempt to marry principles that are to some extent incompatible.  This Bill seeks to safeguard the public from being defrauded and, at the same time, it hopes to give the rights which the Constitution guarantees to every citizen.  It is not easy to marry those principles and I suppose it was for that reason the previous Bill foundered. With Senator Hayes, I trust that this Bill will not founder.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In dealing with this matter, one must take a common-sense point of view.  It is the duty of the Government, Parliament and the Law Society to safeguard the general public and this Bill attempts to safeguard the interests of the clients who are the general public, even though it may curb the activities of solicitors.  I agree with Senator Murphy and other Senators who maintain that quite a lot of this difficulty could be avoided.  I am convinced it is not sheer dishonesty on the part of solicitors which causes this difficulty.  I think it is carelessness in the method of practising. Many people seem to think that professional men make very bad businessmen&mdash;not <Col N="26" /> necessarily solicitors.  It has been said about other professions; it has been said about University professors, doctors and such people.  If over the years the Law Society had tried to develop a standard method of practising and had got their members to adopt such a standard, some of the difficulty could have been avoided.</P>
    <P>Under this Bill, a solicitor will now have to call in an accountant to do his accounts and certify to the Law Society that his clients' accounts are in order.  If the Law Society had in the past got a firm of accountants or technicians to develop standard or routine methods which the solicitors could adopt in the running of their business, some of the cases of clients finding themselves in difficulty could have been avoided.</P>
    <P>I am speaking from the clients' point of view.  I hold no brief for solicitors, except to be fair to them, but I am satisfied that it is not dishonesty, initially at any rate, but carelessness in their methods which has caused solicitors in many cases to get into difficulty.  In the long run, the duty of the Law Society and of Parliament is to safeguard the interests of the clients and I hope this measure will achieve that purpose.</P>
    <P>It has been suggested by Senator Quinlan and by Senator Hayes, I think, that £25,000 is not sufficient.  I am of the opinion that it is only an iron ration and that the Fund may go much higher than that, but a minimum must be held in reserve to safeguard the interests of clients.  If it is found in the light of experience that the sum is not enough, I am sure the Parliamentary Secretary or some other Parliamentary Secretary, after consultation and agreement with the Law Society, will come before the Dáil and the Seanad and ask that another look be had at the matter.  It is only proper that that should happen, if the sum is found to be inadequate.</P>
    <P>The main point I want to make is that even at this late stage, if the Law Society called in some experts on accountancy to have a look at the whole method of practising on the part of solicitors in dealing with their clients' accounts, it might be possible <Col N="27" /> for them to produce some formula along the broad lines of which solicitors would be compelled to work.  In my view, that would eliminate many of the difficulties and if it were done, it would be a good thing for the Law Society, for clients and for solicitors.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me say, first of all, that I fully agree with what Senator Walsh said as to the use of the word &ldquo;majority&rdquo; in my opening remarks.  I agree wholeheartedly that the overwhelming majority of solicitors are honest and reputable; and, indeed, I would go further and say that when one takes into account the volume of funds which passes through solicitors' hands, the amount of the defalcations is quite negligible when related to the total.</P>
      <P>Senator Cole raised a point about criminal proceedings.  I think there is no doubt that if criminal proceedings in the courts are instituted or pending against a solicitor, then the Law Society will almost certainly await the outcome of such proceedings before taking any action.  The Disciplinary Committee of the Law Society will deal only with misconduct, which is defined in Section 3 of the Bill as including a felony or misdemeanour.</P>
      <P>I do not think the Senator's suggestion that the Law Society should be entitled to put another solicitor into the office of a solicitor about whom they had doubts would be at all feasible.  I cannot see this working out in practice; and I do not imagine it would be very desirable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the size of the Compensation Fund, mentioned by Senator Cole and others, the reserve of £25,000 is a pure reserve; in other words, it is a net figure to be arrived at after providing for all outstanding liabilities.  Taken in that light, it is a fairly adequate reserve.  However, if it proves inadequate, the Council of the Law Society have agreed with me that we consider the matter afresh with a view to providing for a more substantial figure.  There is nothing to prevent the Council of the Law Society permitting a greater amount than £25,000 to accumulate, provided they do not increase the contribution <Col N="28" /> beyond £20 to achieve this.  They may leave the amount at £20 for the required period.  If that brings about a higher reserve, as undoubtedly it should in time, there will be no need to amend the law.</P>
    <P>Senator Cole also asked about insurance bonds for solicitors.  We have considered that matter carefully but we are satisfied that the system in the Bill is a much better one.  In passing, I should point out that the Law Society may invest and undoubtedly will invest any funds in the Compensation Fund as advantageously as possible. We would hope that after a period the income from those investments would go to swell the Fund.</P>
    <P>Where any person, who cannot himself provide against a possible disaster, goes to an insurance company, he joins a group and procures the overall protection of that group.  Why should solicitors not do that for themselves instead of going to an insurance company?  Everybody concerned is within the profession.  In fact, the Compensation Fund is a compulsory insurance scheme, the only difference being that it is run by the Law Society and not by some outside body.  There would be many difficulties in trying to enforce an insurance bond scheme for solicitors. Not the least, I think, would be the fact that the annual premium would undoubtedly be much higher than the annual contribution to the Fund.  We hope that in time that that contribution will be reduced.</P>
    <P>Senator Cole raised, in connection with Section 32, a question as to the administration of the funds of a solicitor who becomes a bankrupt or who dies insolvent.  I think I can assure the Senator that in the type of case he outlined, where a client pays money to a solicitor that is clearly identifiable, that money would undoubtedly be regarded as trust money in that solicitor's hands.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>No matter where it might be lodged?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>No matter where it was lodged.  If the money was clearly identifiable as the client's money, there would, as I see it, be no difficulty. <Col N="29" /> Where a solicitor becomes bankrupt or dies insolvent at the moment, the ordinary bankruptcy rule, which we can agree, I think, are the fairest, apply to all moneys in his possession which are not clients' moneys: but the rule in <i>Clayton's Case</i> applies to the clients' funds.  Section 32 applies the bankruptcy rule to these funds, so that from now on all funds, whether ordinary assets or clients' moneys, will fall to be administered in the same way.</P>
      <P>Senator Murphy dealt with matters which are not, strictly speaking, my concern.  One of the points he touched on was also dealt with by Senator O'Reilly and Senator Hayes.  I refer to the question of business methods in solicitors' offices.  I agree fully that very often the trouble a solicitor gets into arises not from any original dishonest interest but from casual or slipshod methods.  There have been cases of solicitors becoming bankrupt and being struck off the roll, where, if their affairs had been properly managed and all the costs due to them regularly collected, no serious difficulty would probably have arisen.</P>
      <P>I would certainly agree with Senators in this matter of good business methods and I would appeal to these solicitors concerned to be efficient in their office methods.  As Senator Hayes says, it is not possible, I think, or even desirable, to transform all solicitors into first-class accountants. A solicitor is primarily concerned with being a good lawyer and adviser. I am not sure there is not a certain contempt among some solicitors for the bookkeeping profession and books in general.  That may be so.  However, if, as Senator Hayes says, the Law Society, in its educational courses, can succeed in persuading solicitors not to become good bookkeepers but to appreciate the idea of good bookkeeping, the Society will be doing a very good job.  Good bookkeepers are readily available.  A solicitor can have first-class books and excellent accounts without, I would say, his ever looking at them or taking any part in the writing up of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We should all like solicitors, and indeed all the professions, to be more <Col N="30" /> expeditious in carrying out their affairs.  Possibly there is a certain tradition of cautiousness and carefulness in the legal profession.  I think a similar tradition, to some extent, exists in the accountancy profession. If we in the Department of Justice can do anything to facilitate solicitors in the expenditious discharge of their business, we shall do so.</P>
    <P>I could not at all entertain Senator Quinlan's suggestion that the contribution to the Compensation Fund should be based on a solicitor's income.  If, as a mathematician, he examines his suggestion carefully, he will realise that not alone would it be unjust but that it would certainly also be impracticable and most difficult to put into operation.</P>
    <P>Senator P. Crowley gallantly and courageously entered into the realms of constitutional law.  I am not sure that he did not set himself up to be the equal of the Attorney General in this field.  I want, first of all, to point out to him that he is under a slight misconception in thinking that Section 12 relates to the decision of the Supreme Court on the 1954 Act.  As I indicated to him in my interruption, the 1954 Act was found to be unconstitutional, broadly speaking because the Disciplinary Committee of the Law Society were given a power which the Supreme Court held to be a judicial function.  The proposals in Section 12 and in the Bill generally are to the effect that the judicial function of striking the names of solicitors off the roll, etc., is to vest in the High Court, and not in a non-judicial body.</P>
    <P>Furthermore, whatever be the Senator's enthusiasm for constitutional law I should like to point out to him that the constitution specifically provides in so many words that there shall be an appeal to the Supreme Court in all cases, except where otherwise provided by law, that is, of course, excepting constitutional matters where there must always be an appeal.  All we are doing in Section 12 is providing that the decision of the High Court will be final, except on a specified question of law.  I suggest we could, if we so desired, have no appeal at all, even on question of law.  I and my advisers have no doubt but that <Col N="31" /> Section 12 and the provisions of the Bill generally are within the Constitution.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan asked me if the Law Society were satisfied with the provisions of Section 31.  I am not sure exactly what the Senator had in mind. His point escaped me, but I can assure him that on Section 31, as on all other sections of this Bill, the Law Society are quite satisfied.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. P. Crowley Mr. P. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>Including Section 12?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesJHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  We have had long discussions with them and the Bill is an agreed Bill.  At this juncture, I should like to pay a very sincere tribute to the Council of the Law Society for the manner in which they approached the Bill, for their efforts to procure the best possible measure and for the wholehearted co-operation they gave me all along the line.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Reilly mentioned that it should be the job of the Government to look after the interests of the general public.  I agree that that is an obligation of government and of all of us here, but I do not see any conflict between the interests of the general public and the interests of the solicitors' profession.  It is desirable for the community as a whole to have a solicitors' profession that will be respected and trusted.</P>
      <P>I do not think there were any other points raised which call for comment from me.  We shall have an opportunity of going through the Bill in more detail on Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know if I shall be in order in asking for further clarification of one or two points as I do not know whether the Parliamentary Secretary was concluding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No; He was concluding.  This is the Second Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Sometimes a Minister or a Parliamentary Secretary intervenes on the Second Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="32" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>He was not intervening; he was concluding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I shall raise the point on Committee Stage.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, November 16th, 1960.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Irish Steel Holdings Limited Bill, 1960" RHead="&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Irish Steel Holdings Limited Bill, 1960 &mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch) Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. J. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is to provide for an increase in the share capital of Irish Steel Holdings Ltd. to £4,000,000, to be taken up by the Minister for Finance, in order to finance a major expansion of the steel works at Haulbowline Island.</P>
      <P>Irish Steel Holdings Ltd. was incorporated under the Companies Acts in June, 1947, to acquire the assets of Irish Steel Ltd. (in liquidation) and to maintain the steel works at Haulbowline as a going concern.  The nominal share capital is £100 of which three shares have been issued and are held by the Directors.  The Company acquired the assets of Irish Steel Ltd. for £125,000 (of which £69,000 was eventually paid to the Exchequer by the Receiver on foot of a guaranteed loan to Irish Steel Ltd.).  The industry has since been financed by fluctuating bank accommodation, guaranteed in part by the Minister for Finance, by guaranteed loan and by the trading profits of the company since its inception.</P>
      <P>The company operates open hearth furnaces to produce, largely from native scrap, mild steel ingots and billets, which are then converted by rolling into mild steel bars shaped as angles, rounds, flats and squares.  Flat and corrugated galvanized sheets are also produced by the company, the raw materials being imported black sheet and zinc.  The accumulated net profits of the company up to 30th June, 1959, are over £600,000, and the assets of the company were valued by outside valuers at nearly £1 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="33" /> The profits of the company have been fully used to pay taxes, to buy machinery and equipment, to amortize loans, to provide the working capital necessary to maintain stocks, stores, etc. and to finance ordinary trading credits.  In addition to supplying home market requirements of its products, the company has succeeded in exporting in the face of very severe competition.</P>
    <P>A major development scheme put forward by Irish Steel Holdings Ltd. was approved in principle by the Government in March, 1958.  The company was authorised to proceed with the development of its plans on the basis that, if a satisfactory scheme emerged, Government backing would be given.  These expansion proposals were subsequently outlined in the White Paper <i>Economic Development</i> which was laid by the Government before each House of the Oireachtas in November, 1958.  The cost of the developments as then planned was estimated at about £2 million.</P>
    <P>Subsequent investigations, with the help of consultants, have resulted in proposals which in general are similar to those of March, 1958, but which envisages greater increase in output, a wider range of products, and consequently an increase in capital expenditure. Tenders obtained from firms of international standing form the basis of the company's statement of costs.</P>
    <P>Briefly, the main proposals are:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  increase in ingot output to 80,000 tons per annum of ingots of 30 cwt. each by the installation of a new oil-fired furnace of 60 tons capacity and by improvement of the two existing 37 ton furnaces and by extension of scrap handling and casting facilities. Current output is 23,000 tons per annum ingots of 3 cwts. each;</P>
    <P>(b)  installation of a new 750 m.m. blooming mill and a new 650 m.m. large section mill; with the necessary ancillary gear to roll billets, blooms, sheet bars and large sections;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="34" /> (c)  re-arrangement and mechanisation of the existing merchant bar mill to improve its rate of working and to enable it to feed a wire rod mill;</P>
    <P>(d)  installation of a new modern wire rod mill;</P>
    <P>(e)  completion of a sheet mill, which the company acquired in an incomplete condition from its predecessors, Irish Steel Ltd.</P>
    <P>The estimated cost of the development proposals is of the order of £3½ millions.  It is proposed to provide the sum necessary, less £99,000 which the company will provide from its own resources, by the purchase of shares by the Minister for Finance.  In addition, the company will require additional working capital commensurate with its enlarged operations and for this purpose the Bill empowers the Minister for Industry and Commerce, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, to guarantee borrowings by the company not exceeding £500,000 at any one time.  The Bill also empowers the Minister for Finance to dispose of his shares at any time.</P>
    <P>Extra employment for about 200 workers is envisaged which will bring the total number of workers to over 700 at peak periods.</P>
    <P>As at present the main raw material for the industry at Haulbowline will continue to be scrap.  The source of the scrap will be domestic, supplemented by some domestic scrap which is at present exported, scrap arising within the industry, shipbreaking scrap and scrap or pig iron which can be purchased on the world market.</P>
    <P>The scheme is designed to cover the bulk of home requirements for merchant bars, large sections, wire rod, and sheet steel, including galvanized sheet steel.  It is estimated that about 65,000 tons per annum of end products will be produced from the 80,000 tons of ingots.  It is expected that 45,000/50,000 tons will be disposed of on the home market and 15,000/20,000 tons on the export market.  The London agents of the company are confident that they can <Col N="35" /> dispose of much more than this amount on terms which the company has been heretofore able to meet.</P>
    <P>Pending the passing of the necessary legislation, the Dáil has voted Supplementary Estimates totalling £1.5 millions, and practically £1.0 million of this has been issued to the company, to enable it to put the work in hands without delay.</P>
    <P>I believe that the proposal to develop this nationally important industry will meet with the same general welcome in this House as it did in the Dáil.  I have already given figures of the employment which the expanded works will give.  The management of the company are confident that, when the expansion and reorganisation are complete, they will be able to effect important reductions in the price of their products. Increased output will mean an improvement in the balance of trade as a result both of increased exports and diminished imports, and while all these are benefits which we may expect to flow from the Haulbowline undertaking in normal times, we must not lose sight of the fact that in the past, during the Emergency years, the works there made an important contribution to our basic requirements of steel, and the expansion of its capabilities provides the best form of assurance of adequate supplies should imports be interrupted for any reason in the future.  I confidently, therefore, seek the approval of the House for the Bill.</P>
    <P>I shall, if Senators who are not familiar with the technical terms to which I have adverted in the detail of the expansion envisaged, explain what these mean.  I admit that I am not completely familiar with all the activities or technical terms outlined but having taken advantage of a visit to the mill to familiarise myself with the operations, I hope I shall be able to explain any of the points on the technical side upon which Senators might require an explanation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not make any attempt to ask the Minister to explain any technical points.  I do not <Col N="36" /> think there is anybody in the country more ignorant of this kind of thing from the technical point of view than I am.  The Bill is one which deserves support.  It is a Bill for the expansion of Government holdings in capital in an Irish steel company at Haulbowline. It marks not only an extension and an expansion of that company but also an expansion and extension of Government investment in industry.</P>
      <P>As the Minister said, it is very technical, but I suggest to the Minister that it is impossible for Parliamentarians, whether ordinary members of either House or Ministers, really to grasp properly the technical details of a proposal such as this.  The Minister in this instance made an excellent case.  Such a case was made in every instance and the sum of all the cases amounts to a very formidable investment by the State and a very formidable amount of State control.</P>
      <P>Perhaps one of the most convincing things the Minister said was his allusion to the important work done by the project during the Emergency.  It is agreed that such projects are necessary. If private capital is not available for it, then the course the Minister is taking would appear to be the only course available.</P>
      <P>As far as this Bill is concerned, it is worthy of remark that the Dáil has already agreed to it, not only in principle but also in practice.  The sum of £1 million has already been paid.  This Bill in effect, gives legislative sanction <i>post factum</i> to something which has been done already. Parliaments nowadays have to do this kind of thing with no skill or knowledge and, I would suggest, with no opportunity or capacity to acquire either the skill or the knowledge necessary to give a proper judgment on this kind of measure.  As I say, the Minister made an excellent case and I believe the Bill is one with which we should agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this Bill as I welcome any effort to expand industry in this country.  The Minister has made a very reasonable case but if we do a little arithmetic, we <Col N="37" /> find that we are to have 200 more workers employed and the cost is to be an investment of £3½ million; in other words, the cost per worker is £17,500, which puts it into a very high grade cost category.  It is a type of industry in respect of which we cannot afford much of our capital.</P>
      <P>If our primary consideration is to provide increased employment for our people or to hold employment as it is at the moment, I welcome it in the sense that I welcome every new industry which has a prospect of success, even though it does cost us a great deal.  This money is being provided so that we shall get this extra small increment of employment but I cannot let this opportunity pass without pointing out again, as I pointed out on several occasions in this House, the failure of the Government to provide corresponding capital for placing Irishmen and boys on the land of Ireland.</P>
      <P>Let us take the question of land at the moment which is carrying three workers to 250 acres.  Does anybody suggest that it would cost £17,500 to employ another worker in that case? In other words while we are chasing after industry, we are falling down on our primary industry, which is agriculture. We are falling down in the matter of creating employment and holding the employment line.  I hate to think that at present we are allowing what is really only a secondary effort for us, our industrial effort, to divert our attention from our real problems.</P>
      <P>We read of the great industrial expansion which is taking place at the moment and we are thankful for it, but what are the prospects which that holds out&mdash;7,376 new positions when the factories both on the drawing board and otherwise have been completed? That, I take it, is about a two years' expansion effort; in other words, expansion at a rate of something like 3,000 to 4,000 new jobs per annum in industry, while sliding down at the rate of 9,000 per annum in agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As a nation, we have not yet faced up to our responsibilities, to the job of holding the line where it is.  For 9,000 new jobs per annum, we are providing <Col N="38" /> 3,000 or 4,000.  It may be a good thing to think up industries which could profitably and with hope of success, compete in foreign markets and develop that number of new jobs but side by side, we fiddle and play and let agriculture slide into decay. We have waited for four years for the farm apprenticeship scheme and yet there is not the slightest sign of it on the horizon.  I feel that our whole policy is strangely lopsided.  I congratulate the Minister and his Department on what they are doing but I must hold the Government responsible for their failure even to hold the employment line at its present level.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not think that it would be possible within the scope of this Bill to have a discussion on agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, the farm apprenticeship scheme at any rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps at some future date we shall have a legitimate discussion on that.  I think we should all regard the manufacture of steel as a very important industry and I must say that Senator Hayes has already given expression to that view from the opposite side of the House. It proved itself a very worthwhile industry during the emergency years when it was very difficult, if not impossible, to get any material of that kind in here.  One would think from the remarks of Senator Quinlan, when he referred to the cost of this industry, that the amount mentioned, £3,500,000, was being given as a free grant by the Government.  Such is not the case.  Apart from the £99,000 the company itself is putting up, what is happening is that the Minister for Finance will take shares in the business. In other words, it will be an investment and we sincerely hope&mdash; and some of us believe&mdash;that that investment will pay good dividends to the nation in the years to come.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We cannot, of course, have industries of this kind and of this importance established without capital. Everybody knows that and it has always been said that where private industry fails, then it is the duty of <Col N="39" /> the State to step in to supply the needs of our industrial proposals and industrial policy.  Having regard to that, it is right and proper for us to support this Bill and I welcome it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one aspect of this Bill which puzzles me, and perhaps the Minister would help me.  We are going to sink a lot of money in this proposal.  In what way will the policy of the company be controlled, or supervised, or directed, by the Minister?  Is it under Section 4, resulting from the shares which he controls?  What I would have expected would have been something like this: that the Minister would have a representative on the board of directors and a very powerful say in the direction of policy.  Perhaps I have overlooked something in the Bill, but if there is not some control or supervision of that kind, it is rather surprising.  How will the Minister see that this money is properly spent, properly used?  Who at the moment controls the policy?  Presumably, it is the directors.  Are they private persons or are they not?  I should like to go even further and ask how have the profits been distributed in the past?  I am speaking from a good deal of ignorance on the matter.  But there is a large sum of money being transferred, so who is to see that it will be properly expended?  It is a very big outlay.  Unless there are good safeguards, we should be very careful about approving of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraigOSiochfhradha" hpid="Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Ó Siochfhradha</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní dóigh liom-so gur ceart an Rialtas a cháineadh fé mar a dhein cainteoir nó dhó mar gheall ar an Rialtas a bheith ag beartú an gnó seo i Haulbowline a chur i dtreo níos fearr chun an gnó atá beartaithe le déanamh a chur chun slachtmhaire agus cumais.  Ní dóigh liom gur cóir don Seanadóir Ollscoile a labhair bheith ag iarraidh a thabhairt le tuiscint gur ar an gcinéal seo tionscail amháin atá an Rialtas sásta airgead a sholathár agus a chaitheamh nó bheith ag iarraidh go dtuigfí faid atá an Rialtas dhá dhéanamh sin go bhfuil siad ag tabhairt faillí i gcúrsaí eile&mdash;go mór mhór i gcúrsaí talmhaíochta sa tír.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="40" /> Má dheineann an Seanadóir scrúdú ar na cúntaisí agus na Meastacháin, chífídh sé go soiléir nach bhfuil faillí ar bith dhá thabhairt ag an Rialtas i gcúrsaí na talmhaíochta chéanna agus chífidh sé go bhfuil breis agus £8,000,000 curtha i leith a gcaite ar mhaithe le gnóthaí curadóireachta agus talmhaíochta.</P>
    <P>Ach i leith an ghnó seo atá ar siúl i Haulbowline, is ní chomh teicniciúil sin é go bhfuilim féin agus measaim a lán eile Seanadóirí chuid mhaith ar neamheolas ar cad é díreach atá ar siúl san áit sin.  Ba mhaith liomsa fios d'fháil cad iad na hábhair is gá chun an obair sin a choineáil ar siúl agus cad as a thagann na hábhair go dtí an monaracha ann.  Measaim gur fuíoll mhiotail a bhailítear in Éirinn agus a déantar a athleaghadh is mó atá dhá úsáid.  An bhfuil ábhair eile dhá thabhairt isteach sa tír d'aon-ghnó chun úsáid a dhéanamh de in obair na monarchan i Haulbowline?</P>
    <P>Ar mo ghabháil síos ar na Céanna seo i mBaile Átha Cliath is beag lá ná feicim cruacha móra 200 nó 300 slat ar fad de shean-iarsmaí iarainn agus fuíoll mhiotail ar thaobh na gCéanna ann.  An go dtí an monarcha i Haulbowline a bhíonn sé sin ag dul nó an bhfuil cead fós ag daoine an chinéal sin a cheannach i nÉirinn agus a bhreith ar siúl as Éirinn le húsáid i dtíortha eile?  An bhfuil a ndóthain le fáil den cinéal sin sean-mhiotail chun an obair a choimeád ar siúl sa mhonarcha cois béal na Laoi nó an bhfuil gá le hiomportáil ar aon chuid de nua-mhiotal ó dhúthaigh thar lear?</P>
    <P>Ba mhaith linn fós fios níos soiléire a bheith againn ar na haidhmheanna agus na cuspóirí a bhaineann leis an obair sin atá ar siúl i Haulbowline. An é amháin is cuspóir dó ábhair mhiotail chruaidh a sholathár agus a dhíol le monarchain agus lucht tionscail eile nó an gnáthach leo earraí miotail a dhéanamh agus a chríochnú iad féin agus a dhíol i riocht cruthanta chun oibreacha i nÉirinn nó oibreacha thar lear a dhéanamh?</P>
    <P>Séard ba mhaith liom fios d'fháil an ndéanann an mhonarcha i Haulbowline earraí cruthanta críochnaithe ullamh chun úsáide i dtógáil tithe nó <Col N="41" /> gnóthaí poiblí troma nó an é amháin atá á dhéanamh aca fuíoll seanmhiotail a leaghadh agus a dhíol le monarchain eile a tháirgeann miotalóireacht de shaghasanna éagsúla agus chun riachtanaisí áirithe maidir le hinnealltóireacht agus foirgneoireacht?</P>
    <P>Ba mhaith liom, leis, fios d'fháil ar iomlán tonna den mhiotal in aon fhoirm a chríochnaitear sa mhonarchain sin agus fios d'fháil cá mhéad fear oibre a bheidh i gceist tar éis an airgead nua seo a chur ar fáil don tionscal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>The first speaker suggested that there might be some abrogation of the rights of the Oireachtas in introducing a Bill <i>post factum</i> to the extent that the Dáil had already provided £1½ million of the £4 million required for the expansion of the steel mill in Haulbowline. The Dáil, on each of two occasions when making provision, by way of a Supplementary Estimate, for this £1½ million, discussed very fully the requirements of Irish Steel Holdings Limited and the merits of their proposals, and on each occasion, without dissent, the necessary moneys were voted.  That was done for the purpose of enabling the company to proceed, with all expedition, with the plans they had prepared and were, in fact, about to put in hand.  I think the merit of the Dáil taking that course is amply shown by the fact that the company were able to take advantage of tenders at advantageous levels.  Had they waited for the introduction and passing of the Bill through both Houses, the probability is&mdash;in fact, I think it would be a certainty&mdash;that the costs of the development would be much higher than are envisaged in this Bill, and indeed the costs which have already been contracted for with reputable constructional engineering firms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Quinlan also suggested that it appeared to be an undue expenditure of capital to apply an outlay of the order of £17,500 for each additional worker employed.  The simple comment on that is that, in Britain, the new installations for steel-making <Col N="42" /> cost between £10,000 and £20,000 for each additional worker, but I suggest that is not the test that ought to be applied here.  In the first instance, we have in Haulbowline an industry that is gradually becoming obsolete. I am not suggesting that it is, in fact, obsolete but it soon would be obsolete to the extent that its production would become uneconomic and its products would be priced out of the market, with the result that justification for maintaining it on economic grounds would no longer exist.</P>
    <P>It is in the nature of the steel industry that advances in techniques take place and as they arise, unless advantage is taken of them, the possibility is that that industry will lose its place as a viable economic unit on the market.  Therefore, one should apply the £3½ million by way of capital outlay, and the £500,000 for working capital, not to the employment of the 200 extra workers but to the maintenance of work for the 500 men at present employed there and for the 200 extra, making 700 in all.  Without this capital outlay, it is likely that there would not be employment for that number or even for the 500 already working there at peak periods.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan also commented on the fact that if similar capital were made available for the placing of men and boys on the land of Ireland, we might perhaps be doing much better work.  He also referred to the farm apprenticeship scheme.  I think the Senator ought to know&mdash;and I am sure it is accepted by all members of the Oireachtas&mdash;that the first charge on moneys available for the acquisition of land must be, and must continue to be, for the relief of congestion until that problem is solved.  That problem has not yet been solved and as land comes on the market and is available for the relief of congestion, it will be the purpose and indeed the duty of the Government to acquire it without undue interference with the rights of the landowners to free sale.</P>
    <P>The Senator knows, too, that the assistance being given by the Exchequer for agricultural purposes is very considerable.  It runs into several <Col N="43" /> millions per annum by way of subsidies on prices, by way of subsidies on fertilisers and by other means of supporting our agricultural production. That is not a matter for me to deal with in any great detail but I think it right to refer to it as the Senator tried to suggest we were applying an undue proportion of capital to the maintenance in employment of one worker.</P>
    <P>In reply to Senator Stanford, this company was set up as a result of the acquisition by the Minister for Finance of the shares of the original company, Irish Steel, Ltd., which was then a private enterprise company which went into voluntary liquidation.  The mills were lying there for a considerable period without any appearance of private enterprise taking up the steel-making activities down there.  It was only at that stage that the Minister for Industry and Commerce, with the assistance of the Minister for Finance, came in to ensure that this industry would be kept going and kept alive thus ensuring a reasonable supply of essential steel goods during a period when we would probably have found great difficulty and been involved in great expense in procuring them.</P>
    <P>The money having been put up by the Minister for Finance, it was arranged that the directors would be appointed by him.  There still exist three directors appointed by the Minister for Finance, each of whom has been allocated a single £1 share to justify his seat on the board.  At present, the three directors are the chairman, who is a serving civil servant and a senior officer of the Department of Finance, a serving civil servant and a retired civil servant. Replacements to the board, if and when they occur, will be made in similar fashion by nomination.</P>
    <P>Apart altogether from the provivisions in the Schedule for the due operation of the business under the surveillance of the Minister for Industry and Commerce and the Minister for Finance, the directors at present are appointed by the Minister and any replacement of them or expansion <Col N="44" /> of the board which may prove necessary will also be by way of ministerial action.  Therefore, there is full assurance that the interests of the Minister and of the State will be adequately looked after.</P>
    <P>Is main liom a rá leis an Seanadóir Ó Síochfhradha go bhfuil cosc fé láthair ar easportáil dramh-mhiotail as an tír seo.  Ní cheadaítear d'aon duine an miotal d'easportáil gan cead ón Aire Tionscail agus Tráchtála.  Fé mar atá an tionscal anois, gan dramhchruach a chur san áireach, tugtar cead do dhaoine áirithe an fuíleach d'easportáil.  Ach, nuair a bheidh an tionscal nua fé lánseol, ní dóigh liom go mbeidh aon fhuíleach miotail le heasportáil.  Is é is príomh-chúis leis an tionscal ná cruach a sholáthar in Éirinn.  Ins an chlár atá romhainn anois, beidh 65,000 tonna á tháirgeadh. As an méid sin, coimeádfar sa tír idir 45,000 agus 50,000 tonna de chruach agus beidh idir 15,000 agus 20,000 le heasportáil.  Dá bhrí sin, isé an phríomh-aidhm atá romhainn cruach a sholáthar le haghaidh tionscal nua in Éirinn.  Tá súil agam go mbeidh an méid eile a bheidh á dhéanamh sa bhreis acu sa mhonarcha seo saor a dhóthain agus go mbeidh ar a gcumas é a dhíol thar lear.</P>
    <P>I do not think any other points were raised which I am required to answer. I am pleased with the way the House has received and accepted the Second Reading and the principle outlined in the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamAhern" hpid="Mr. Ahern Mr. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a letter here dated 19th October, 1960.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will have to confine himself to a question at this stage.  The Minister has concluded the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamAhern" hpid="Mr. Ahern Mr. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a letter here in regard to the subject of this Bill and I am anxious to hear the Minister's views on it.  I shall pass the letter over to the Minister for his consideration and opinion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="45" /> Bill considered in Committee.</P>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with the taking up by the Minister of an amount not exceeding £4 million, my criticism was not, as implied by Senator Ó Cíosáin, solely because the State was investing in the industry.  I would look equally askance at private enterprise here that would be forced to invest £17,500 per worker.  If the Minister wishes to make allowance for modernisation, it amounts at least to between £8,000 and £10,000 per worker.  A sum of £4 million is asked for here and I am not opposing it in any way.  However, I want to caution that it is a rate of expenditure which we cannot afford, except for a very few projects.  If we are to advance as a nation and increase our employment we shall have to do it through industries that cost far less capital than this type of industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say in reply to that that what this country is short of more than anything else on the industrial side of our economy is basic heavy industry, and if we are to continue to balk at capital expenditure which we believe can be reasonably remunerated, and by reason of the performance of this company in the past can be proven to be remunerative, we shall never progress industrially.  Therefore I do not think the arguments of the Senator are valid, because on such heavy basic industries will depend the emergence and existence of smaller industries, and unless we can proceed in that manner, we cannot hope to have a fully viable industrial economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Therefore, I do not think the Senator should continue to relate the £17,500 capital expenditure to the provision of work for one person.  Even if he did that, having regard to the circumstances, such expenditure is justifiable in our existing circumstances when we are seeking opportunities for employment and must realize that mechanisation on the land <Col N="46" /> will create far less employment on the land and that such industrial employment must be provided to take up the slack, to take up the amount of people in so far as we can, who will, by reason of mechanisation, continue to leave the land.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of the Minister's explanation at the end of the Second Stage, may I ask him if this company is in a special category of its own?  Are there other companies which are completely subsidised and completely controlled by Government nominees in this way?  I should be interested if he could give some examples&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We must confine ourselves to Section 3 of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry; I thought we were on Section 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that Senator Quinlan was quite right in raising this point.  A sum of £17,500 per worker employed is an enormous amount of money.  The Minister and his Department may also, in their wisdom and in the full knowledge of the facts, be right in doing it in this instance, but I think the Minister has misunderstood Senator Quinlan.  The Minister says that what he is suggesting is not the sort of development of capital an economy like this could maintain. That is where the Minister and the Senator are at variance.  I do not think they ought to be, because if there is to be development in Ireland, it is not in the development of heavy industry or in the construction of bridges and so on.  We are not likely to make a success of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We would do very much better if we followed Switzerland or Denmark in their industrial development, where all forms of electronic control gear and automatic equipment control gear are made.  I believe the largest factory in the world manufacturing automatic control gears is at Norburg in Denmark. Much the same type of development is taking place in Switzerland. We could devote our attention very much to that, where there are highly qualified university graduates looking after the technical end of the production <Col N="47" /> of small components that could be moved by air rather than by ship.</P>
    <P>In Britain recently, a great problem was created as to where heavy industries would be sited.  Again, they might not have the international shipping that would allow them to move the goods as they were made.  Some of the big motor corporations were wondering where they would site their developments.  We shall be up against that problem here.  We are not going to compete with Britain in heavy industries or in bridge building.  In this instance, the Minister might be quite right.  Senator Quinlan made it clear that the production of what will be wanted for our own requirements would be necessary, but we are not going to develop our economy and make use of the resources and knowledge of thousands in technology and skills, unless we do it in the way the smaller countries have done it, with small amounts of material and an enormous amount of labour for the amount of the material deployed.</P>
    <P>I have discussed this with many industrialists in Birmingham within the past few months, and some have said that that is the only possible way we could do it.  We cannot compete with somebody like Dorman-Long in building bridges but we ought to be able to do as well as the Swiss and the Austrians&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is going outside the scope of the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to thank Senator Burke for making quite clear again my point in this, which the Minister missed.  I was not critical, but I was performing my duty as a Senator in pointing out the weakness of this type of industry.  We may be justified; the high investment may be necessary; but such high investment of capital per worker is a weakness. Here we are authorising an expenditure of capital up to £4 million of the taxpayers' money.  The Minister and others have recognised that we need at least 20,000 new jobs per annum if we are to take up the present drift from the land and make provision for <Col N="48" /> the increasing numbers, or, as the Taoiseach promised, the provision of 100,000 new jobs in five years.  Take the capital cost of that&mdash;20,000 new jobs per annum at £17,500 per worker.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a completely fallacious argument which the Senator ought not to indulge in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>If you do simple arithmetic, it would be a sum of something in the neighbourhood of £350,000,000 per annum, a type of expenditure we could not possibly face up to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathoirleach An Cathoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator should remember that this is the Committee stage and he must confine himself to Section 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that, but surely we are entitled, in connection with the spending of £4 millions&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathoirleach An Cathoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is not entitled to open up a general topic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator is entitled to discuss this, then I am entitled to answer his arguments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>He was just as pessimistic about Aer Lingus and everything Irish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Quinlan is entitled to make his speech and should not be barracked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Quinlan, to continue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry if this is an example of what we may expect from the leader of the House at the opening of this session, but as an Independent member, I am prepared to state my facts and figures on any section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Section 3 gives power to spend £4 million.  I am in agreement with it but I am pointing out the weakness of what is implied in it.  I am also again raising the question to the Minister.  The Minister mentioned the relief of congestion and I suggest that <Col N="49" /> if £4 million were put into that, it might do something more spectacular.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am intervening only because the attitude of Senator Burke on this section surprised me.  I would expect him to take his usual cue and to suggest that this money should be provided by private enterprise.  It brings back previous occasions in the House when it was said that when private enterprise cannot provide the money, the State has to provide it.  Senator Quinlan's attitude was true to form; Senator Burke's was not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>What is yours?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>You are the cause of half the trouble.  You only came into the House to interrupt.  I should like you, Sir, to keep some of the members over there in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not mind him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to point out that it is not the intention of the firm to make bridges but to make steel to help people to make bridges.  I am glad to inform the Senators that they have made steel to help people in New Zealand to make bridges, and I hope they will continue to do so.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 5 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister referred to the Minister for Finance exercising his power to make certain appointments to the board.</P>
      <P>One of these appointments is listed as a retired civil servant.  There has been an increasing tendency to appoint retired civil servants, and I think that a businessman would be much more likely to make a success of that job.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder might I make my inquiry now?  Are there other firms of this kind in the country completely under the control of the Minister in this way?  I should be interested to know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="50" />
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>Ceimicí Teo., I understand, is a clear parallel.  Other boards by reason of their legislative background are not parallel but they are not unlike; Ceimicí Teo. is parallel.</P>
      <P>Might I say to Senator Quinlan that the retired civil servant in this case is a man who was a member of this board before he retired and whose contribution to its work is very highly valued. It was not because he was a retired civil servant and for no other reason that he was appointed but because when he was a civil servant&mdash;I would not say that he was the direct nominee &mdash;he was more responsible to the Minister for Finance and acquired a knowledge of the working of the company and of steel making and so it was thought prudent to continue him when he retired from the Civil Service.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Dividends are mentioned here, the return on investment. In this case, the question of public and private enterprise has been raised and I should like to know whether the Minister feels that this industry can return, say, the prevailing rate of six per cent. return on capital investment or does he think that a good deal of this must be written off because this is an industry satisfying a very special need or filling a very special place in our economy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>It is hoped, and I believe that it will be possible to show, that this industry will be well able to remunerate itself completely, not perhaps initially at the rate which private enterprise would require, but certainly at the ordinary prevailing rates of borrowing by the Minister for Finance.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 7 to 14, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="51" /> Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Veterinary Surgeons Bill," RHead="1960&mdash; Second Stage">
    <Title>Veterinary Surgeons Bill, 1960&mdash; Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Smith) Patrick Smith">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Smith)</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the Supreme Court's ruling on the Solicitors Act, 1954, the position of the Veterinary Council of Ireland in relation to the exercise of its disciplinary powers has been a most unsatisfactory one.  The council has, in fact, found itself obliged to refrain from the exercise of these powers in any case.  It has expressed to me its deep concern at the present unsatisfactory position and its anxiety to have the position rectified in the interest of the veterinary profession. The Council of the Royal College of Veterinary Surgeons is equally anxious that this should be done so that the reciprocal arrangements in the matter of disciplinary proceedings, as provided for under the Veterinary Agreement with the British Government, should again effectively apply.  It is in these circumstances and for this purpose that this Bill was introduced.</P>
      <P>The existing provisions relating to the Veterinary Council's disciplinary powers are contained in the Veterinary Surgeons Acts, 1931 and 1952.  Section 34 of the Act of 1931 provides that the council may erase from the Register of Veterinary Surgeons persons convicted of crimes.  Section 36 of the same Act provides that the council may, where it finds after due inquiry or investigation that a person has been guilty of professional misconduct, erase the name of such person from the register.  Section 7 of the Act of 1952 provides for suspension of registration on account of professional misconduct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The proposals in the Bill involve the modification of Sections 34 and 36 of the Act of 1931, and of Section 7 of the Act of 1952 to provide that erasures, or suspensions of registration, <Col N="52" /> on account of conviction for crimes or of professional misconduct could be effected by the Veterinary Council only on direction of the High Court.  The council would as heretofore be enabled, after due inquiry, investigation, or consideration of the case as may be required, to decide that appropriate disciplinary action, that is, erasure or suspension of registration, should be taken.  It would be open to the person concerned to apply, within 14 days to the High Court for cancellation of the council's decision and the High Court, on hearing the application, would either cancel the decision, or confirm the decision, and direct the council to take the appropriate disciplinary action, that is, erasure or suspension of registration. Where the person concerned did not within 14 days apply accordingly to the High Court, or where he delayed unduly in proceeding with an application, the council would be enabled to apply to the High Court for confirmation of the decision and the High Court would, unless it saw good reason to the contrary, confirm the decision and direct the council to take the appropriate disciplinary action.</P>
    <P>The construction of the Bill is quite simple.  It substitutes for Section 34 of the Act of 1931, which deals with erasures on account of conviction for crimes, the new section set out in Part I of the First Schedule.  This new section, which is an amended and extended version of the existing section 34, provides for the proposed new procedure I have already explained. The section set out in part II of the First Schedule replaces Section 36 of the Act of 1931 dealing with erasures on account of professional misconduct and, as well, Section 7 of the Act of 1952 dealing with suspensions of registration on account of professional misconduct.  It also provides, of course, for the proposed new procedure.  The Second Schedule to the Bill shows the particular provisions of the 1931 and 1952 Acts which require to be repealed in consequence of the provisions contained in the two new Sections 34 and 36.  These repeals are routine ones.</P>
    <P>The Veterinary Council of Ireland, <Col N="53" /> which has, of course, been fully consulted, welcomes the Bill and has expressed complete agreement with its provisions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>We are in complete agreement with this Bill.  It is undoubtedly, as in the case of the Solicitors (Amendment) Bill, necessary that whatever legal difficulties there are in the way of taking defaulting members of the profession off the register should be overcome.  This Bill is for the purpose of overcoming that difficulty.  As in the case of the Solicitors (Amendment) Bill which we had earlier, the Minister has been in touch with the appropriate authority of the profession&mdash;in this case the Veterinary Council of Ireland.  He tells us&mdash;and I am sure he is correct&mdash; that they are in agreement with the provisions of this Bill.</P>
      <P>This Bill has a further complication which I think makes it important that it should be passed, that is, that there is a reciprocal arrangement between this country and Great Britain which, of course, means that there should be no delay in giving power here to the appropriate authority to deal with people who are behaving in an improper manner professionally.  We are in agreement with the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment of the Veterinary Surgeons Acts is consequent on what happened in connection with the Solicitors (Amendment) Bill but it is much more simple than the Solicitors (Amendment) Bill. There are actually no money questions involved.  The amendments in this Bill are necessary on account of the decision of the Supreme Court in connection with the actions of a similar body, the body governing the solicitors' profession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As Senator Hayes pointed out, it is an agreed measure between the Veterinary Council and the Department of State responsible for the control of the Veterinary College, but I would suggest that the House has some responsibility in checking over the details in the Bill.  The principal point I would ask the Minister to check is the use in Part I of the First Schedule of the <Col N="54" /> words &ldquo;forthwith send by post&rdquo;.  I do not know whether there is an ordinary legal definition of what &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; means but I would interpret it as meaning immediately, having regard to the ordinary everyday use of the word.</P>
    <P>The Veterinary Council usually meet in the evening time and make a decision.  According to this word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo;, that should be sent out that evening.  I suggest to the Minister that there is no necessity for the word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo;, which does not occur in the Solicitors (Amendment) Act.  I suggest that in the cases in which it occurs the words &ldquo;forthwith send by post&rdquo; should be altered to the extent of dropping the word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; and putting in the word &ldquo;registered&rdquo;.  I think that the letter sent by the Registrar of the Veterinary Council should naturally be sent by registered post. It probably would be sent by registered post because if it were not so sent, it would give a delinquent or the person to whom the letter was sent an opportunity of saying he never got the letter or that it was never delivered.</P>
    <P>This word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; is absolutely unnecessary.  There might be some complication if the letter were sent out on the second day afterwards or even the day after.  Some legal person, a solicitor or other, might say it was not sent out forthwith.  I think the word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; is unnecessary and suggest that the word &ldquo;registered&rdquo; be inserted.</P>
    <P>These are small alterations in respect of which I have got sanction from an important member of the Veterinary Council to bring up and I would appeal to the Minister to accept them.  The Bill is an agreed measure between the Veterinary Council and the Department of State concerned but we have a duty still to check on it.  I suggest that the Minister should seriously consider making these alterations in the Bill.  The word occurs in a few sections, apart from appearing in Part I of the First Schedule.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister and previous speaker stated, this is an agreed measure.  We are all glad to know that the Veterinary Council of <Col N="55" /> Ireland were consulted and that they expressed complete agreement with all the provisions of this Bill.  I welcome the Bill and I am glad to see that the Veterinary Council and veterinary surgeons are prepared to help in putting their house in order.</P>
      <P>We all know that reputable veterinary surgeons are in the vast majority in this country and a special tribute is due to the majority of them for their wonderful work in dealing with the bovine tuberculosis eradication scheme but, unfortunately, a small percentage&mdash;and I want to say it is a very small percentage&mdash; do not adhere to the high standards set up by the majority.  That small percentage has done untold harm in this country in the past few years.</P>
      <P>We have discussed the Solicitors (Amendment) Bill.  We know that if a solicitor defaults or if money goes wrong, then the individual suffers, but, unfortunately, if veterinary surgeons are dishonest or do not do their duty, then the whole community can suffer. Unfortunately, that is what has happened. I think it can be truthfully stated that never in the history of this country has such a small minority of people, through their transgressions, done so much harm as has been done to the economy of our country by unscrupulous veterinary surgeons in their work in relation to the bovine tuberculosis eradication scheme.  Because that small majority gave certified figures without examining cattle, there is no doubt that they have done irreparable harm to the export industry, on which to a large extent the prosperity of each and every one of us depends.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We know that due to their mal-practices, the British farmers have lost faith in our store cattle, and I venture to suggest that their mal-practices have cost this country millions of pounds.  We have lost probably something between £5 million and £10 million.  Under the powers which the Minister had, I think he dealt very leniently with them.  Some of them should have got from five to ten years in Mountjoy Prison.  There are people wanted by the law for <Col N="56" /> doing much less harm than they did. I sincerely hope that when this Bill is passed, the Veterinary Council will deal severely and strictly with that very small minority&mdash;and I want to stress that it is a very small minority.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that Senator Ó Donnabháin need have any fear regarding the two points he raised.  I can tell the Seanad that in fact the points were considered in the drafting stage.  So far as I know, the legal meaning attached to the word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; is that once findings of the council have been arrived at, these findings should be conveyed on the date on which they were reached.  That is what is regarded as the meaning of &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The draftsmen also had another matter to consider, that is, what was in the original Act.  The word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; appears in the original Act and as is the case with all draftsmen, they try, when amending an Act, to stay as near as possible to the original.</P>
      <P>As I say, they examined this and found that it was all right.  After all, when you come to look at it, the individual affected by the council's decision has only 14 days in which to appeal to the High Court, if dissatisfied with the general findings.  That being so, the council must convey, with all haste, their decision to the person affected by it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the question of posting by registered post, as every Senator will realise, the council did, I am sure, on all occasions send by registered post, but there are reasons why such a provision should not be contained in the Act.  In this case also, the original Act does not contain what is suggested by the Senator, that is, sending by registered post.  The original Act contains &ldquo;send by post&rdquo;.  It is better that the council should have that freedom and the practice is to send by registered post. These two matters have been considered by the draftsmen and they are satisfied that what is here is safe.  It is what was in the original Act and there was no fault to find with it.  For that reason, I do not think the Seanad need have any fears that any complications <Col N="57" /> of the kind the Senator referred to could possibly arise.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Veterinary Surgeons Bill, 1960&mdash;" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Veterinary Surgeons Bill, 1960&mdash; Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 4, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">FIRST SCHEDULE.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the First Schedule be the First Schedule to the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I was a member of the Veterinary Council and I know that difficulty was anticipated in connection with this matter and from the Minister's explanation, I can see now that what appeared to me to be the more objectionable phrase is now the less objectionable phrase.  The word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; is definitely objectionable because the Council will meet in the evening time&mdash;it once held an investigation in Kerry&mdash;and when the council comes to a decision, it will be very difficult for the registrar to ensure that the message is sent out that evening. I was inclined to interpret &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; as meaning &ldquo;as soon as possible&rdquo; but the Minister's explanation shows that it is very much more restricted.  I would still ask the Minister to consider whether &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; is necessary, because naturally people will want to comply with the decision of the council as quickly as possible and the word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; might afterwards give the legal people an opening for objections and possibly objections that some day might lead to further amendments.  However, if the Minister insists that this is all right, I cannot do anything more than raise the matter and bring it to his notice and hope for the best subsequently.  I think that &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; would be better out than in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. Ryan Mr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is something in what Senator Ó Donnabháin says, but, on balance, I think it would be better to leave the word in.  On the one hand, if &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo; were left out, it means that the council might be able to delay for several days before sending out their decision and that certainly would <Col N="58" /> be a serious matter for the person concerned. It would leave him very little time to prepare a case for the High Court.  If, on the other hand, the word were left in, the very most that can happen is that the person concerned can complain that he did not receive the letter for possibly a day.   He can complain that the council did not comply fully with the word &ldquo;forthwith&rdquo;.  However, I am perfectly sure that any court would take the view that if special circumstances existed which prevented the council from sending the letter on the same day as the meeting was held, that was a reasonable excuse and the council would not suffer in any way for failure to send on the same date. On balance, there is a lot to be said for leaving the word in.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Second schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Government (Temporary Reduction of" RHead="Valuation) Bill, 1960&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Local Government (Temporary Reduction of Valuation) Bill, 1960&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney) Neil T. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. Blaney)</NameTxt>
      <P>The provisions of this Bill relate to the law on rating.  It is proposed to continue for the three years ending on 31st March, 1963, the period in which buildings erected, enlarged or reconstructed during that period may qualify for a seven-year remission of rates under the Local Government (Temporary Reduction of Valuation) Act, 1954.  It is also proposed that farm buildings constructed or improved in that three-year period will qualify for a remission of rates for 20 years instead of the seven-year exemption provided for by existing legislation.  A new method is proposed for calculating the county demand on Buncrana urban district council, providing for the abatement of that demand on a sliding scale over a period of 30 years <Col N="59" /> from 1st April last.  Finally, the Bill makes provision for a reduction by one-half during the next ten years of the rates levied by county councils on half-rents.</P>
      <P>Under the 1954 Act, a remission of two-thirds of the rates was granted for seven years on the valuations of new buildings and on any increase in the valuations of existing buildings that were enlarged or improved, where the constructional work was begun and completed in the three years ended 26th July, 1956.  This three year period was extended up to 31st March last by the Local Government (Temporary Reduction of Valuation) Act, 1956.  The remission applies to all buildings such as hotels, shops, factories, offices, houses and so on, which do not qualify for a remission of rates under any other Statute.  It is estimated that an average of approximately 1,500 buildings newly built or reconstructed, receive this rate remission in each year.  The extension of this remission is intended to encourage building and construction work to which the rate remission provisions of other Statutes do not apply and the execution of which might otherwise be delayed.</P>
      <P>Section 2 proposes to amend Section 14 of the Valuation (Ireland) Act, 1852, which provides that the valuation of a hereditament or tenement shall not by reason of the erection of any farm outhouse or office buildings, be increased for rating purposes for a seven-year period.  This exemption extends to the enlargement or improvement of such farm buildings. Many improvements in farm buildings, particularly in connection with the Bovine Tuberculosis Eradication Scheme, are found to be urgently required at present and the extension of the rating concession from seven to 20 years is introduced in order to encourage farmers to provide the new or improved buildings that are necessary in present circumstances.  The new terms will apply to farm buildings erected, enlarged or improved between the 1st April, 1960, and the 31st March, 1963.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When the Bill was before the Dáil, <Col N="60" /> it was suggested by some Deputies that this longer rates remission might be extended to appropriate works carried out prior to the 1st April last. The effect of any rates remission under legislation such as this is to transfer a certain burden of rates on to other ratepayers.  As I have pointed out, the purpose of the present measure is to encourage the carrying out of constructional work which might not otherwise be undertaken.  This motive is considered to justify the extended remission on farm buildings.  There would, however, be no corresponding justification for awarding in this Bill a gratuitous and retrospective concession in respect of work which was undertaken prior to the current rating period.</P>
    <P>A general re-valuation of all property was carried out in Buncrana urban district in 1950, at the request of the urban council.  As a result, the total valuation of the urban district increased from £7,563 at 1st March, 1950, to £11,445 at 1st March, 1951. This resulted in a corresponding increase in the demand levied on the urban council by Donegal county council.  A provision in the Local Government (Temporary Reduction of Valuation) Act, 1954, was intended to bring the valuation of the urban district for county demand purposes back, in effect, to what it was estimated it would have been if no general revision had occurred and only normal increases had taken place.  That Act provided for an increase of £330 in the valuation in each year from 1954/55 until, in 1963/64, the county demand would be based on a valuation of £11,520, after which the ordinary basis of valuation would apply.  This provision did not secure the intended degree of relief.  The average annual increase in the valuation over the past nine years was only £93 instead of the estimated normal increase of £330 annually.  The result has been that the county demand on Buncrana has been much greater than if the general revision had not taken place.</P>
    <P>The position of Buncrana relative to other districts was further worsened by Section 50 of the Local Government Act, 1955, which provided that the <Col N="61" /> county demand on urban districts should be calculated on the basis of net valuation and not, as hitherto, on gross valuation.  This provision was to the advantage of urban districts generally but the section stipulated that, in the case of Buncrana, the county demand should continue to be assessed on the gross notional valuation as set out in the Schedule to the 1954 Act, thus preventing that urban district from gaining the benefit conferred on other urban districts by the 1955 Act.</P>
    <P>Buncrana urban council have been pressing for amending legislation to relieve the disproportionately heavy county demand on their district and Donegal county council have supported their request.  Section 3 of the Bill accordingly provides that the county demand on Buncrana for the current financial year will be calculated on the basis of .70 of the net produce of a rate of one penny in the £ in that urban area.  It is estimated that this should have the effect of placing Buncrana in the position in regard to the county demand in which it would be if the town had not been completely re-valued in 1950 and only normal increases in valuation resulting from new building and other development had taken place.  The fraction will increase by the one-hundreth of a penny in each subsequent year until, in 30 years' time it will be .99 of a penny.  This arrangement will spread over a period of 30 years the effect on the county demand of the abnormal increase which resulted from the 1950 revision. The immediate effect will be to reduce by approximately £3,700 the county demand on Buncrana for the present year.</P>
    <P>Section 4 provides for the granting of a rate relief on half-rent valuations in county health districts.  Under existing legislation, a person receiving a rent in respect of a hereditament exempt from rating under Section 63 of the Poor Relief (Ireland) Act, 1838, used for charitable or public purposes, is liable to be rated in respect of half the rent or the &ldquo;half-rent&rdquo; as it is called.  In county boroughs, and urban districts, rates are assessed on a fraction only of such &ldquo;half-rents&rdquo;.  Where an owner is liable to pay full rates on <Col N="62" /> the half-rent in a county health district he would, in fact, suffer a loss in cases where the county rate exceeds 40/- in the £.  In a large proportion of cases the tenant, by arrangement, pays the rates but I feel that there is a strong case for granting rate relief on these half-rent valuations.  Section 4 of the Bill accordingly provides that for a period of 10 years from 1st April, 1960, half-rents in county health districts shall be assessed on only half their valuation.  This will bring the position into line with that which applies in urban districts and boroughs. As this Bill is a temporary measure, it would not be appropriate to include in it general provisions to deal in a permanent way with the rating of half-rents. It is hoped, however, that before the 10 year period ends, the general question of the rating of half-rents will have been fully examined.</P>
    <P>Remissions of rates have been given by Local Government Acts in one circumstance or another over the past 40 years and they have always been on a temporary basis.  The Bill proposes to continue the temporary nature of the legislation so that the policy in regard to such remissions can be reviewed from time to time.  I feel that in present circumstances, these rate remissions are giving a desirable impetus to building projects which compensates for the transfer of part of the rates burden on to other ratepayers and I recommend this Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Every member of the Seanad will surely welcome this measure.  I am afraid I cannot be overenthusiastic. The Minister is meeting many of the problems of the day in a piecemeal manner.  He is not getting down to the kernel of the problem which has caused much anxiety for many a long day and will continue to do so until a new measure is introduced which will deal with valuations in a comprehensive manner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am glad the Minister's law officers are present.  They must be aware of the jungle of anomalies that will be created by this type of piecemeal legislation.  I welcome the introduction of this legislation which shows what <Col N="63" /> has happened.  There was a complete revision of valuations in Buncrana, county Donegal, which distorted the exactions imposed on the people of that progressive township in relation to the rest of the county.</P>
    <P>No effort is made to apply the Bill to the rest of the country.  With as much sincerity as I can command, I ask the Minister to have this question examined.  Every day in some town or village the valuation officer inflicts the same type of anomaly, hardship and injustice on some person, as happened the whole township of Buncrana.</P>
    <P>When the law-makers in 1852 conceived these valuation statutes they cannot have foreseen an enormous devaluation in money.  They made the valuation of land static and allowed the valuation of hereditaments to be dynamic.  Many progressive people who have suffered visitations by valuation officers know that the matter has been dynamic.  I do not lay any blame whatsoever on the officers of the Valuation Commissioners.  They are doing their duty.  However, they must be aware of the problem and of the injustices that ensue for anyone who is progressive.</P>
    <P>This Minister has devoted a considerable amount of time to seeing how in some small way he might relieve farmers from the burden of the Valuation Acts.  They are concerned at present with the eradication of bovine tuberculosis and the better housing of their cattle and other animals.  As he sees the justification for putting these provisions into this Bill, he might consider the thousands of other people who, year after year up and down the country, have to face the same problems.</P>
    <P>The Minister should have included all hereditaments in the 20-year period as well as farm buildings. During that period he should have the law in this matter reviewed.  Nothing brings the law into such ill-repute as the feeling that it is not fair or equitable. If any code has brought about that feeling of disrespect for the law, the Valuation Acts have done so.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="64" /> Some years ago, the then Minister for Finance was asked about this matter in this House.  He told us that someone cut a number of pages out of Thom's Directory which referred to properties in North Dublin and sent them in to have all the properties on the pages revalued.  Whether it was done as a sort of appalling practical joke or because of spleen, I do not know.  The only factor that saved the worthy citizens of that part of Dublin was that the job of revaluing the whole of that area would be so colossal that I do not think the money was provided by the Minister for Finance for carrying it out.</P>
    <P>I want to reiterate some of the points I have made.  I approve wholeheartedly of what the Minister is doing for the farming community by allowing them a 20 years' remission of the increase in valuation on all buildings in respect of the next three years.  He has also extended the provisions of the 1954 Act for another seven years.  He is not out of season in giving a rebate to the people of Buncrana who suffered an increase of valuation amounting in round figures to between £7,500 and £11,500.  I believe that if he examines the points, he will admit that, to be fair to all the other sections of the community, this 20 years' remission should be extended to any person who builds a house or factory or improves a shop or any other hereditament.</P>
    <P>If this is not done, it will increase the sense of grievance we hear given expression to at our urban councils and discussed every year by the Municipal Authorities Association.  It is even discussed at our trade councils, where they say that shopkeepers are afraid to do up their shops because if they put in a new front which might be worth 10 per cent. of the value of the building, they might get a 200 per cent. increase in their valuation.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to consider seriously these points.  I should like him to charge the law officers of his Department with the responsibility of drawing up a new code of valuation procedure on the existing valuation of the whole country, to take some arbitary standard and fix it at that so that <Col N="65" /> the valuations for all time will be based on that.  You cannot base valuations on changing values of money.  The letting value which was the criterion for years changes from day to day, from week to week and from district to district.  It is very often grossly unfair to the citizen who has his premises valued in that archaic manner. It is not to the credit of the intelligence of our people that we should have this body of laws which, in my view, impeded the progress we would like to see in our country towns and rural areas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrady2" hpid="Mr. Brady Mr. Brady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make a small contribution to what Senator Burke has said on this question of valuations.  He is quite right.  I know a shopkeeper who, on his own initiative, put a new roof on his house in a small village.  He applied for no grant, but had a few pounds to spare and did it with his own money.  The poor law valuation of that house was £8 and the reviser came along and fixed the valuation at £20.  That man came to me and of course I advised him to appeal. He had to go to Ennis, to pay a solicitor and get a barrister to appear for him in the circuit court, and there the valuation was fixed at £18.  That man is paying the full rate of £2 in the £. He is paying £36 rates on that house. He is also paying rent to a landlord in Limerick.  I cannot understand how these revisers arrive at their decisions.</P>
      <P>At one time, Ennis urban council was abolished and its affairs administered by a commissioner.  The people were very pleased with him, with the result that they nominated no candidates at the next triennial election. Then the commissioner was appointed for a further period.  What did he do? He carried out a general revaluation of the town.  He sent up the gross poor law valuation, something like Buncrana, and of course, reduced the rates on paper.  He is now a county manager.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We know that in the town of Ennis, there are houses unoccupied where the urban council sued.  One man who had a pretty big shop and owed £120 rates defeated them in the circuit court.  He said that he had made every reasonable effort by advertisement, by <Col N="66" /> negotiation and in every way to find a tenant for the house but could not, with the rates and charges that were on it.</P>
    <P>I have a thorough knowledge over 36 years of this problem and I have great sympathy for the borough of Ennis and for Kilrush and for the people who have been instanced in Buncrana, because I understand their position.</P>
    <P>The man I mention whose valuation was increased from £8 to £20 was enterprising enough to put a roof on his own house and to plaster the front of it.  There was no increase in the measurements, and the structure was not touched in any way.  I think it is terrible the way the valuers are carrying on.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>There is more than one Buncrana.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrady2" hpid="Mr. Brady Mr. Brady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
      <P>We talk about progress. Is that progress?  This man said that he would not borrow or apply for a loan.  We have land in our county from Ennis to Limerick valued at about 50/- an acre.  I know a farm of about 180 acres of land and the valuation is something like £465 15 0.  I see all the books and I know everything about it.  I cannot understand how some of these revisers work.  I would like to see some of those fellows put on a 24-acre holding, given a wife and a few children, and told to try to make a living on it.  That would give them some conception of their duty to the rural population of this country. These excessive valuations have come before the county council and no words of mine could condemn them sufficiently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is designed to amend the Valuations (Ireland) Act, 1952.  Under that Act, a farmer who erected a farm building had a remission for seven years.  Under this Bill, it is proposed that if a farmer erects a building between April, 1960 and March, 1963, he will get a remission for 20 years.  Senator Burke spoke about the sense of grievance; but there will be a sense of grievance and very unhappy feelings between neighbours if this Bill is passed, because <Col N="67" /> there is no denying that the enterprising farmer is the man who will suffer under it.</P>
      <P>Take any enterprising farmer who answered the call to increase production, to build new farm buildings, to help eradicate the scourge of T.B. and to adopt modern byres, during the past seven, eight or ten years.  Such a farmer has now passed the remission period and is paying the full rate.  For others, the seven years will be up shortly and they will be paying full rates.  The man who has been hanging back, who did not answer the call as a duty, is to be rewarded under the Bill by getting a rates remission up to 20 years.</P>
      <P>The farmers are supposed to be conservative and lacking in initiative.  Here we have a Minister of State bringing in a Bill which is definitely rewarding the farmers who proved themselves both conservative and lacking in initiative, while the people who built over the past 10 years are being victimised. Anybody who did any building since the war or who does it within the next few years should have this rates remission up to 20 years because he is a man who must dig into his capital, get loans or grants, go to the bank to borrow money.  It is very unfair that immediately he does that work, his valuation and his rates are increased.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Brady has given an illustration of what has happened in Ennis. What happened there is happening all over the country but it is unfair to blame those in the Valuation Office. Those people are only doing their duty. The time has come when the Government should say that people who have built since the war should get 20 years' remission and anybody who puts up any building or improves his shop, factory or any other building in the next six, eight or 10 years should also get 20 years' remission of rates.  Is what is going on at the present time progressive? Senator Brady is unfair to blame the valuation officer.  Let him blame his Government and his Taoiseach who suggested that they are the progressive Party.  If they want to be progressive, let them agree with the suggestion some of us are making or <Col N="68" /> with those made in the Dáil when the Bill was before the Dáil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I take the view that this is intended to be an incentive to the entire people to do things that should be done anyway and I welcome the Bill in so far as it does create an incentive to farmers, particularly dairy farmers who must have more extensive housing than any other type of farmer. It is an incentive to farmers to improve their premises and in so far as the Bill goes in that direction, I welcome it.</P>
      <P>It may be argued that it should be retrospective, that the people who built prior to its coming into operation should be indemnified because they were a bit too soon.  If this case could be made, then grants under the Housing Acts, say, the Housing (Financial and Miscellaneous Provisions) Act of 1932, should be increased when grants are increased under the 1952 or 1954 Acts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>You could build a house for £350 in 1932, and it takes more than £1,000 now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot go back all the time.  We must legislate for the future, not for the past.  That is why we always have to bring amending Bills of one type or another into Parliament&mdash;so that legislation can be changed with changing times and changing circumstances.  While it might be possible to make a case along Senator L'Estrange's lines, to create this position of equity between man and man in everything, I think, is impossible, because if you want equity between man and man in everything, you have to take one individual by another and relate one individual to another.  It would not be possible under any legislative system in any country.  It never was possible and it was not practicable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should mention the contribution of Senator Burke.  Mind you, I am inclined to say that he is a very brave man and very sincere in the views he expressed.  It could be argued by some people that there would be no reasonable equity between valuations until <Col N="69" /> there was a readjustment between all the valuations of the country.  But who is brave enough, apart from Senator Burke, to implement that?  If we on this side of the House were to take direction and advice from Senator Burke, many of his colleagues would repudiate him in a very short time.  We would be sitting ducks for attack by any of the people who might feel like making political capital out of such a situation.</P>
    <P>These matters are not easy to solve. This solution, if reasonable agreements could be got, might be a good thing or it might have very bad effects, too. I am not prepared to go all the way with Senator Burke in this matter but there should be some method of levelling up.</P>
    <P>I take Senator Brady's word for his facts in the example he gave but I might suggest to him that some other person who built a new house, not a business premises but a residential premises, might have as high a valuation on that residence adjacent to a business premises.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrady2" hpid="Mr. Brady Mr. Brady">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
      <P>The man did not object to £3 or £4&mdash;put it up to £12.  He knew there would be some little increase and the man was quite reasonable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not disputing the case.  The Senator has not heard me out.  An abnormally high valuation could be set on a new premises&mdash; though the owner would be indemnified on a sliding scale.  The Valuation Office has no regard for adjacent valuations and the State has to step in to indemnify such people against the full impact of the increase in valuation. Take a reconstruction of premises such as that mentioned by Senator Brady. When these premises are re-valued in the light of and in proportion to adjacent premises, then the valuation could go up.  I often wished that something could be done to ensure that in valuing any premises, reconstructed or new, the Valuation Office should have regard to the all-over position in that townland, village or parish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange says that the Valuation Office have done <Col N="70" /> the job very well.  I am not prepared to agree with him.  I agree with Senator Burke and Senator Brady.  They have not succeeded in keeping equity and justice between existing valuations and people unfortunate enough to be re-valued have been very unjustly treated.  Those who built better premises and escaped re-valuation are getting away with it and not paying a due share of the local rates.  As far as the Bill goes, I welcome it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like briefly to add my voice to the comments made about the injustice in valuations and the necessity to improve on the system.  The only improvement I can see on this system that would be just is to abolish it altogether.  The first task in raising the moneys involved is that they should be raised with some relation to income.  A commission in the past few days showed how income tax could be lowered and that lowering could be very well used to abolish this iniquitous system of rates based on valuation altogether.  The most iniquitous of all is concerned with agricultural land and claims made down through the years have treated of that.</P>
      <P>If the Minister is reconsidering valuation, the time has come to reconsider the whole basis of the raising of this money from agricultural land. If he wants the same amount&mdash;I am not saying that he will have it or that he should not have it&mdash; it should be raised by some progressive method, by a progressive land tax that would encourage the good farmer and not by rates as they are arranged at the moment that hit the good farmer and the bad farmer alike.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>One thing emerged in varying degrees from the five speakers who contributed and that was somewhat a condemnation of the present system of valuation and the manner in which the revisions are carried out and, in general, a call for a change of method&mdash;a change of system, or as the last speaker said, the abolishing of the system altogether and the putting in its place of some form of tax that would raise the same amount of money, some form of a land tax or something such as that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="71" /> What I want to put to the House is this: While I have views&mdash;they could be as valuable as the next&mdash;quite strong views on the valuation system, as we know it, the fact is that it is not my Department at all and I do not propose to impose those views on Senators here tonight.  I shall merely deal, not with the general arguments made by practically every speaker but with those others which are immediately concerned with the Bill before us.</P>
    <P>In that regard, I think Senator L'Estrange took the view that we should have retrospective remission of rates under this Bill and that, in fact, by giving the remission we now propose of 20 years on new, improved or reconstructed farm buildings, we are not giving encouragement to those who deserve it but rather that we are penalising those who were enterprising enough in the past to have built new farm buildings or improved or reconstructed their existing buildings.</P>
    <P>I want, as I did in the Dáil, to reiterate that circumstances today are such, due in particular to the bovine tuberculosis eradication scheme, that in many cases, particularly in the dairying areas, that will arise in the very near future, certain farm buildings must, of necessity, be improved, reconstructed or renewed.  It is to encourage and to help those who must in such circumstances do this renewal or reconstruction; it is to try in some way to alleviate the burden they may have to carry in regard to this building that we bring in this remission.  It is to help and encourage them to do something which, without this remission, they might not do, which in itself would be not only a loss to the farmer in question but could also be detrimental to the whole bovine tuberculosis eradication scheme.</P>
    <P>May I also say that this idea of making it retrospective to those who built in the past five, six, seven or 12 years does not really meet the point intended to be covered by the remission for the future, in that those people, obviously enterprising though they may have been, must have been in possession of sufficient material goods or <Col N="72" /> gains to enable them to build.  It may also be that a number of those described as unenterprising were unenterprising for the very simple reason that many of them in those years were unable to provide the wherewithal for these repairs or renewals.  Surely, those people were in need of encouragement? This encouragement, we hope, will be of some value to them in present day circumstances.</P>
    <P>Again, one other point in regard to this whole matter of rates remissions &mdash;they are and have been over the years intended to encourage building. There is no encouragement surely in giving a remission of rates to somebody who has the building up and enjoying its worth over the past five or ten years?  We ought to encourage building for the future.  That is the intention, in addition to the other reasons I have already given.</P>
    <P>The question of penalising, I think, does not arise.  The question of encouraging those who have not yet built or who must build in the future is not, I think, payment for not doing their business in the past.  Rather is it a further encouragement to help them to do it in the future, if they were not in a position to do it in the past. Having commented on the items which were mentioned specifically in relation to the measure before the House, were I to say any more I would have to start discussing the general arguments on the valuation system as a whole, which is not the responsibility of my Department.  It is a matter which is not relevant to the discussion here tonight.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is no objection, could we have the remaining stages now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>There may be amendments. Are we not meeting next week?</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 16th November, 1960.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 6.50 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 16th November, 1960.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>