<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="27" Month="Oct" Year="2005" Vol="181" No="12" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 27 Deireadh Fómhair 2005" DateEnglish="Thursday, 27 October 2005" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" LastSrc="4" cnum="989">
  <Col N="989"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar<?oasys _jy?>10.30 a.m.</P>
    <Line />
    <P Italics="Y" Just="Center">Paidir.<br />
  Prayer.</P>
    <Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have received notice from Senator Kitt that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to give an update on the present position on water and sewerage schemes in Ballygar, County Galway, in light of the health considerations of the people of Ballygar.</P>
      <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator<?oasys _jy?>Cummins of the following matter:</P>
      <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to address the cessation of farm plastic collections and ensure adequate funding is put in place to enable the recycling of this waste.</P>
      <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order, the Cathaoirleach is blessed as he did not hear the Ranelagh version of the Gettysburg address during the course of Private Members&rsquo; business last night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>My point of order relates to Standing Order 31. A ruling was given by the Leas-Chathaoirleach that no limitation is placed on the length of time a member of the Government can address the Seanad during Private Members&rsquo; time. I read Standing Order 31 this morning and, as the Cathaoirleach is well aware, it contains no such ruling. There was a gross abuse of Private Members&rsquo; time last night, which is a matter of concern for all Members of this House.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="990"/>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We will not discuss this matter. A meeting of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges will be held today and this matter would be more appropriate to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>Could the Cathaoirleach clarify the issue and state whether there is a time limitation? It is quite clear from the Standing Order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I cannot clarify that at this time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>Standing Order 31 makes it abundantly clear that the Cathaoirleach has absolute discretion in informing Members of this House and Members of the Lower House about the length of time for which they should speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Today&rsquo;s meeting of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges would be a more appropriate forum in which to discuss this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>A total of 40 minutes of repetition was unfair, not just to the House but to the many people who wanted to contribute to the debate and could not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should resume his seat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>This issue must be clarified by the Committee on Procedure and Privileges today in order that all members of the Government are aware that rules apply to everybody speaking in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>As I have explained, this is a matter for the CPP.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The Order of Business is No. 1, Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005 &mdash; Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business and to conclude not later than 1 p.m. &mdash; spokespersons have 12 minutes each and other Senators have eight minutes, with the Minister to be called on to reply not later than five minutes before the conclusion of Second Stage; and No. 2, Prisons Bill 2005 &mdash; Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 2 p.m. until 5 p.m. &mdash; spokespersons have 15 minutes each and other Senators have ten minutes, with the Minister to be called on to reply not later than ten minutes before the conclusion of Second Stage. There will be a sos from 1 p.m. until 2 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>I will refer to the other matter later. All of us on this side of the House wish to congratulate Senator Cox on the mini-revolt she led last night.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="991"/>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>This is not a matter for the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not see the Senator here this morning but I wonder whether she will appear behind me at any minute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Yesterday&rsquo;s business cannot be discussed on today&rsquo;s Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>I suspect it is very much current business. Now that Fianna F&aacute;il has broken ranks with a Progressive Democrats Minister, I wonder whether the reverse applies. I rather hope that it does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>On the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>This week, Senators Norris and Quinn raised the issue of 1916 and the announcement made at the Fianna F&aacute;il Ard-Fheis by the Taoiseach last weekend. I assumed all party leaders were consulted and cleared this matter in advance of the Taoiseach&rsquo;s speech but I was informed yesterday that this had not happened. Two serious points stem from this decision. First, it was inappropriate to make an announcement on a national day of commemoration at what was a political rally. Second, there is a serious issue concerning the role of the Army. I would have preferred if a decision had been made in consultation with all of the party leaders. Where we commit the Army to a national day of commemoration, it should not be used in a partisan party political way by one party in attempting to show its neo-national credentials against another. It is a serious matter in terms of respect for the Army. I ask that future decisions of this nature be taken with all party leaders in both Houses.</P>
      <P>I do not for one moment reject the fact that the 1916 Rising was an important staging post towards Irish independence. However, many other events have not been commemorated such as the establishment of the Irish Free State and the Irish Republic, both of which had democratic legitimacy. The Government should not use the Army as a pawn. We must reconsider this issue and the way in which we commemorate our history in an all-party way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree with Senator Brian Hayes. The notion of a 1916 commemorative military parade was launched at a party rally. That is regrettable because it makes it the possession of one section rather than the entire community. Children will enjoy it as a day out. However, I remember the nasty exclusive sabre-rattling that occurred in 1966. As somebody who claims the right to be an Irishman just like everybody else, it did not make me comfortable. I will state again <Col N="992"/>what I stated last week, that to me Easter Sunday is about the resurrection of Jesus Christ, not the insurrection of Padraig Pearse.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I will make a couple of positive points. I have just come from the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Transport which had a meeting with the Railway Procurement Agency and other bodies. The implementation of a proposal for a metro system in Dublin received unanimous support. We urged the Cabinet, in light of its ten year transport infrastructure plans, to include it. We also referred to the study commissioned by professional consultants which strongly recommends a metro system for the capital that would not only connect the city to the airport, but also onwards to Swords. Everybody is on board. It is appropriate that we discuss the issue in this House because of the significant role played by the Leader of the House when Minister for Transport. She had more guts than her two male predecessors in examining the proposal for a metro system logically and clearly, and in not having a closed mind. In those circumstances it would be right for this Chamber to discuss the issue. I hope the Leader agrees with me and that the strongest possible message that we need a metro system will be sent from this House to the Cabinet. I will not be negative about Luas. However, it was an expensive bauble which had no impact on traffic levels. It made people comfortable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>It is an excellent facility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>It had no impact whatsoever, statistically.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>That is completely wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>It is nice for the people who live along it but let us have the real solution at last.</P>
      <P>As I am in positive mode, we should congratulate Mr. Niall Mellon who was in the House recently&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not in order as it would set a precedent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I would like the Leader to give as much support as possible, through the appropriate Ministers, to the wonderful work done by Mr. Mellon in building houses in South Africa and taking decent Irish builders out to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We cannot set a precedent for such requests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I would not dream of doing so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>It would happen on the Order of Business every day if they were allowed.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="993"/>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I was merely asking the Leader to be positive and speak to the Ministers involved and give encouragement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>I assume the rules of this House are applied in the same way to everybody who speaks here and that we will be left with no uncertainty about this in the future.</P>
      <P>I ask the Leader for a debate on workers&rsquo; protection legislation for a number of reasons, including the apparent stalemate on whether we will have a further partnership agreement. While this stalemate crystalised around one issue, it developed from the frustration of the trade union movement at the inertia of the Government on issues such as the expansion of the industrial inspectorate. It was agreed it would be expanded dramatically. However, the expansion has not been fully completed. A group of Polish workers made serious allegations about being grossly underpaid. Six months later the inspectors had still not begun their investigations. They stated they did not have the numbers. Unfortunately, one of this country&rsquo;s characteristics is that we are far better at introducing new legislation than enforcing it. This week five people died in industrial accidents. The two issues concern the environment in which people work. Everybody accepts employees must operate safely. However, it is ultimately an employer&rsquo;s responsibility to provide a safe working environment. We must examine all of the legislation in place. The Minister should come in to the House to discuss all of these issues and how we can provide people with a proper, safe and non-exploitative work environment.</P>
      <P>We need a debate on the Ferns report. A Minister should come to the House and respond to it. I do not want to blame the Government. This is not a matter on which I wish to create a political conflict. However, we must discuss some of the issues involved. The Roman Catholic Church has discussed at length the framework document which is supposed to create guidelines. Nobody told me the church had submitted the framework to Rome nine years ago. I did not know this until I saw the report. It is in the gift of the authorities in Rome to make the framework obligatory under Canon Law but nine years on it has still not done so. Only the Vatican can compel a bishop to implement the framework. I find it extraordinary that after nine of the most traumatic years in the history of the Catholic Church, the authorities in Rome are still shy in insisting that every bishop in Ireland operates according to best practice. We should not discuss the failures of the State. We should discuss the degree to which a large institution within the State seems unwilling to take what everybody else now knows to be the right action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis"><NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
	<P>As one who is not a member of the political party which held a so-called rally in <Col N="994"/>Killarney at the weekend, I defend the right of the Taoiseach to make an announcement there or anywhere else on the issue of a 1916 Rising commemoration. I live near the Curragh and it is interesting to note that the barracks there are named after the leaders of the 1916 rebellion such as Ceannt and Pearse. It is standard practice in a democracy to have military involvement in commemorations and State ceremonies. It is not unusual. In our case, we have &Oacute;glaigh na h&Eacute;ireann. Many would be willing to hold overt military parades to mark the anniversary of the rising. For that and other reasons, it is entirely appropriate that the Army which is the inheritor of the 1916 tradition and underpins our democracy be present at any State occasion commemorating the event.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>On that subject, I support the comments of Senator Brian Hayes. While no one is against the idea &mdash; personally I am in favour of it &mdash; our great republican democracy would be better served if there was consultation. We are anxious to ensure the participation of all parties. This could become &mdash; properly so &mdash; a great national day, to which I look forward. I encourage the Leader and the Taoiseach to consult, as Senator Hayes said, with all party leaders because every right thinking citizen is anxious to honour the memory of those involved in 1916 and our history.</P>
      <P>In view of the importance of child care and how strongly Members on both sides feel about it, I encourage the Leader who will be anxious to oblige to arrange a further early debate on the issue as many did not have an opportunity to speak yesterday.</P>
      <P>I asked previously about the defeated stage payments Bill and referred to the promise made by the then Minister of State, Deputy Noel Ahern, that the Government would introduce its own measure. As it is not included in the proposed legislative programme, I am anxious to hear if the Leader knows anything about it and what is being proposed, about which I heard a rumour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator was not at the Fianna F&aacute;il Ard-Fheis in Killarney.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I was but I do not know where the Leader was.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The matter of Killarney is not appropriate to the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>It is right and fitting that we commemorate the rising of 1916. In Killarney the Taoiseach said it was not triumphalist, but a matter of recognising the sacrifice, valour and <Col N="995"/>humanity of those who fought in the rising which was a watershed on the road to independence. As I recall, in 1966 there was a whole year of commemorations of sports, cultural and literary activities. The Taoiseach made the point in Killarney that the commemoration would not be confined to one day. He also said the Government would set up a national committee to oversee the commemoration. This will rightly ensure the consultation to which Senator Brian Hayes referred. I hope there will be no division. The Seanad can play a role in this respect; it is a time for unity.</P>
      <P>It is right that the Army should participate. As has been said, it is the inheritor in respect of the sacrifice made by the great people concerned. The people also want this. I had never seen such an outpouring of emotion as at the State funerals for the forgotten ten volunteers, in spite of adverse advance criticism.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is looking into his own heart.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>The Taoiseach is acting in the best interests of the people. I appeal to everyone in this Chamber and throughout the country to unite in this commemoration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not disagree with anything said in the House about the 1916 Rising. Nobody has a problem with celebrating or commemorating it. As Senator Brian Hayes said, it is a &ldquo;staging post&rdquo; in our history which should be recognised but there is a problem with the Taoiseach announcing it at a tribal rally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>Party, not tribal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Come on, it is a tribe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Ross could have chosen better words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>The House is becoming very prim these days.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The House must respect all political parties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>The words stand. It is clear that in this House it has already become a political football. Political parties should not compete for possession of this part of our history. That is the problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>If we are genuine about it being a national commemorative event &mdash; I believe <Col N="996"/>Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; is genuine &mdash; let us not allow Sinn F&eacute;in and Fianna F&aacute;il to compete for possession of this part of our history, as occurred last weekend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Exactly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>If the Taoiseach was genuine, he would have announced it in the D&aacute;il, not at that event which the Cathaoirleach does not want me to call a tribal rally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Italics="Y">(Interruptions).</P>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>From the wigwam in Killarney.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>I make a special plea to the Leader of the House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I might have to defend the Killarney structures yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>What happened in Killarney is not appropriate to the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;that the Fianna F&aacute;il Party, in a spirit of consensus and mercy, has compassion on Senator Cox when it comes to consider her case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not relevant to the Order of Business. That is not a matter for this House but for the Fianna F&aacute;il Party, of which Senator Ross is not a member.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>He might be one day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>It is a long held aspiration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>We are not all sure about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>Startling figures showing our high rate of personal credit, consumption and borrowing were issued yesterday by a company of stockbrokers owned by a bank. The ratio of personal debt to average income will rise from 120% to 160% in the next three years and we are now rated third highest in the euro zone. It is a source of alarm to international observers and the Central Bank that individuals are borrowing so much money for personal consumption. The main problem is the banks&rsquo; lending for mortgages and credit cards. As the Central Bank will issue a statement next week, I ask that we debate this matter at an early date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The Leader favours a further splurge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">In light of the comments made on the weekend&rsquo;s announcement, it is sad that there is division on what should be a great national cel<Col N="997"/>ebration. The Taoiseach is entitled to make public announcements wherever he sees fit; there is a precedent. It is ironic that last weekend our neighbours in Great Britain celebrated a military event of 200 years ago, the Battle of Trafalgar, in which Lord Nelson who passed away in that battle defeated the French and the Spanish. Nobody suggested there was an element of triumphalism about it. It is part of the fabric of its history and traditions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>It was not announced at the British Labour Party conference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P>Anybody who has observed the British penchant for commemoration will know that, in common with other large powers, militarism forms a great part. This is more about pique on the part of those who feel they were not consulted. In a spirit of reconciliation, solidarity and empathy with all shades of opinion on this island and in this House, will the Leader consider holding a debate early in the new year on the 90th anniversary of the 1916 Rising?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Excellent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P>That would allow all sides of the House to join in supporting this great national celebration.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">11 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
      <P>In news that broke overnight the democratically elected President of Iran was quoted last night as saying he believed the state of Israel should be wiped off the map. Irrespective of one&rsquo;s views about Israeli foreign policy and its policy towards the Palestinians, and I believe most Members of this House support the Palestinian cause, I support the right of the people of Israel to exist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P>In that context the international outcry against the Iranian President is such that I have some faith in international morality. I ask the Leader to request the Minister for Foreign Affairs to make a statement at the earliest opportunity on Ireland&rsquo;s response to this unacceptable and outrageous attack on another country which is, although it is sometimes forgotten, a democratic country. The President of Iran went way over the mark in making that statement. I ask that there be an early statement in response.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SheilaTerry"><NameTxt>Ms Terry</NameTxt>
	<P>What is the situation with Seanad reform?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator will have to speak to Senator Brian Hayes.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="998"/>
    <Speaker pid="SheilaTerry"><NameTxt>Ms Terry</NameTxt>
	<P>I seek a debate on that issue. It was suggested previously that Senators should be enabled to put down parliamentary questions to Ministers. Recently, I put down a parliamentary question through a Deputy, as that is the only way we can do it, about a health issue in my constituency. The reply was that it was not a matter for the Minister for Health and Children but that the new parliamentary queries division in the HSE would answer the question. If that is the way we intend to proceed, we should impose timeframes on the HSE for replies to questions. We should not have to wait two or three weeks for a reply from the HSE when the reply should come from the Minister&rsquo;s office. Why was that parliamentary queries division, if that is the correct name for it, not put in the Minister&rsquo;s office instead of the HSE? It is time to examine these issues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>The 1916 Rising marks the foundation of the State and the Proclamation is its founding charter. There is no question of it being a party occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcCarthy"><NameTxt>Mr. McCarthy</NameTxt>
	<P>It was at the Ard-Fheis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>It is a national occasion. I will not repeat arguments already made on this side of the House. I also strongly endorse Senator Mooney&rsquo;s comments about the intolerable statement by the President of Iran. The Minister for Foreign Affairs should protest against what is an invitation to genocide and terrorism of every kind. Many of us have been critical of Israeli foreign policy. We have also been critical in this House of President Bush&rsquo;s foreign policy. However, we must be realistic. A clear message must be sent by the community of nations, including Ireland, that this type of statement is simply not acceptable. It is also an illustration of the dangers of theocratic government anywhere in the world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Absolutely. Well said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcCarthy"><NameTxt>Mr. McCarthy</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the sentiments expressed by Senator Brian Hayes. Nobody doubts that the anniversary in 2016 will be a significant historical event. The manner in which the announcement was made and the lack of all-party consultation are the real issues. I speak as a member of the only political party that existed in 1916. Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael did not exist then. The Army is the Army of the State, not the Army of Government. The fact that the announcement was made in the wigwam in Killarney when the Taoiseach was putting on his warpaint&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question?</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="999"/>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcCarthy"><NameTxt>Mr. McCarthy</NameTxt>
	<P>That make up costs the State a great deal of money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>The cowboys are on that side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGerardHanafin"><NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
	<P>I support Senator Mooney and Senator Mansergh. The world is a more dangerous place today. The President of Iran speaking of Israel in those terms and given our knowledge that Iran is pursuing a nuclear programme, there is a strong probability that Israel will defend its interests prior to any other eventuality. The situation is very serious.</P>
      <P>Will the Leader arrange a debate on transport? A number of people objected vociferously to taxpayers&rsquo; money being used to provide a new terminal at Dublin Airport. However, it appears that at least one company is using taxpayers&rsquo; money for its bottom line. If a company raises taxes, it does so on behalf of the State and it is incumbent on that company to pass that money to the State. There is no basis for telling people that because they paid money to the company, it will not return it. That is the pirate&rsquo;s charter &mdash; take everything and give nothing back. It is unacceptable. If landing fees and taxes have been paid but the people do not fly, the money either belongs to the people concerned or the taxpayer, not the company.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Having read the Ferns report, it is apparent that we must legislate to protect children. People have not acted properly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Mr. Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>Last week, I put down a matter for discussion on the Adjournment but, due to time constraints and the significant number of other matters on the agenda, the Cathaoirleach was unable to facilitate it. The motion I put down called on the Government to assemble an all-party committee to begin preparations for an inclusive celebration of the 1916 Rising. It is important that we commemorate 1916 in an appropriate, inclusive fashion. It is a fact of history that 1916 occurred and it will be commemorated 11 short years hence. It will be a great occasion for the Irish people and we must ensure that it is a celebration in which everybody can participate and feel welcome.</P>
      <P>All-party involvement in organising that commemoration is the most appropriate approach. The majority of people involved in politics today, both in Government and in Opposition, will not be the players in 2016 when there will be a new generation of politicians. However, we must set the tone now by ensuring that in 11 years there will be an appropriate recognition of the men and women of 1916.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The other issue I wish to raise arises from Senator Ryan&rsquo;s comments on social partnership. The continuation of social partnership is now being debated by the trade union movement and, obviously, different opinions will be voiced. It has <Col N="1000"/>occasionally been said in this House that the major economic and social decisions are taken outside the House and that parliamentarians, apart from Government Ministers, are no longer playing a significant role in that regard. It is important that this House has a debate on social partnership. All Members agree it has played a major role in turning our economic performance round.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>Rubbish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Mr. Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>If the trade unions and employers can discuss the future of social partnership, so can politicians. I ask the Leader to arrange a debate in the Seanad on the merits of social partnership, how it can be driven forward and how we can ensure it continues to play a role in developing and strengthening the economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Brian Hayes brought up a matter about last night but the Cathaoirleach ruled it out of order. The Senator then raised the issue of 1916 again in the House and said the Army should not be used in a party political manner. There was a discussion about this on Tuesday and we strongly made the point that the Army is provided for in the Constitution. I do not recall it but I am aware that Mr. Costello went to Canada and announced an Irish Republic. One can talk about consultation with others but he was in<?oasys _jy?>Canada when he announced it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcCarthy"><NameTxt>Mr. McCarthy</NameTxt>
	<P>There was no Ard-Fheis there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis"><NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
	<P>He was in a wigwam.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>He was in a very small wigwam.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>He was an elected Head of Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P>It had far reaching implications that are still with us today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Indeed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader to reply without interruptions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Unlike the Leader, I do not remember that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Order, the Leader to reply without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I spoke quite clearly. Senator Hayes thinks he is frightfully funny. He is not a bit funny; he is an ass. At least, that is the kind&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Italics="Y">(Interruptions).</P><Col N="1001"/>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I am sorry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Leader, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I am sorry I said it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>If that is not calling the kettle black I do not know what is, but I will not take that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not think&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I apologise and withdraw the remark.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Thank you. That is acceptable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I will not run to anyone to take it off the record; it is on the record and will stay on the record.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>I note Senator O&rsquo;Rourke&rsquo;s fulsome apology.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I do apologise but I am not going to beat myself on the ground.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianHayes"><NameTxt>Mr. B. Hayes</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader never has.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader, without interruption, on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I will speak to Senator Hayes again about his remarks.</P>
      <P>Senator Norris agreed with Senator Brian Hayes on the proposed 1916 commemoration. Senator Norris was the first to raise it in this House on Tuesday. He asked us to give full robust support to the metro idea and we will be glad to do so. He then decried the Luas but he should stop people coming off the Luas and ask them whether they enjoy using it; they love it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Absolutely, but it has no effect on the traffic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
	<P>Rubbish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Ryan spoke of the stalemate on social partnership and sought a debate on legislation referring to worker exploitation, immigrant workers, health and safety and all worker related issues. That is what the head of SIPTU is worried about and would like to see debated. Perhaps it would be a good idea. He also correctly stated the guidelines have not been given the Vatican <i>imprimatur </i>and that is stated in the report.</P><Col N="1002"/>
      <P>Senator Dardis stoutly defended the Taoiseach&rsquo;s right to make a statement &mdash; I would agree fully with him that it was a highly appropriate statement.</P>
      <P>Senator Coghlan, whom I am glad to see but who never came near me in Killarney,&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>We must have been mixing in different wigwams.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Order, please.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Coghlan was not in mine anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Mr. Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I was.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I asked about Senator Coghlan&rsquo;s whereabouts in the hotel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>On the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Coghlan supported Senator Hayes and called for another debate on child care &mdash; we have had enough of them. He also asked the position on his Housing (Stage Payments) Bill 2004 and I will inquire about it.</P>
      <P>Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; also spoke about the proposed commemoration of 1916, that we commemorate the valour and the courage of those who fought in 1916 and agreed with Army participation.</P>
      <P>Senator Ross agreed with the sentiments expressed on all sides in this House about commemorating 1916 but I gathered he thought it was announced in the wrong <i>milieu</i>. We think otherwise. He then raised the increase in personal debt <i>per capita</i> in Ireland to 160% and sought a debate on the matter.</P>
      <P>Senator Mooney thought that it was out of a sense of pique that this debate about 1916 was being carried on by some people in the House. He then raised the statement about wiping out Israel, which we are told was made by the Iranian President, and asked that the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Dermot Ahern, make a strong statement about it.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Senator Terry asked the position on Seanad reform. We have had our meeting with the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Roche, and the next one is scheduled. She put it against the background of questions to Ministers, which, as she will be aware, would require a constitutional referendum. If one reads the Constitution, Ministers are not accountable to the Seanad; they are to the D&aacute;il. They come here when requested. I find the Adjournment debate, where one can get answers, is good. Introducing a process of questions to Ministers would require a constitutional amendment.</P><Col N="1003"/>
      <P>Senator Mansergh also spoke of commemorating 1916 and the intolerable statement by the President of Iran.</P>
      <P>I agree with Senator McCarthy that the Labour Party is the oldest political party in Ireland and that is well recognised. He stated that the lack of all-party consultation was one of the real issues. Deputy Bertie Ahern is the Taoiseach of the country and he is the president of my party. He chose the occasion, therefore, to make that statement.</P>
      <P>I did not understand Senator Hanafin&rsquo;s point. Maybe I was not listening sufficiently closely. He raised the need for legislation on child abuse and he is correct. He raised another matter, which I could not follow. As this is my fault not his, I will speak to him afterwards about it.</P>
      <P>I did not know Senator Bradford tabled an Adjournment debate last week but he was prescient.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>Visionary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Senator Bradford called for a debate on social partnership. It would be a good idea to debate social partnership. This follows on from the debate sought by Senator Ryan on all of the legislation which affects workers and workers&rsquo; rights. We will see if we can do something on that. By chance, I happened to hear Mr. David Begg on the radio yesterday. He cited one of the measures in Seanad reform which related to scrutiny of social partnership and he was in admiration of it. We will see about organising a debate. I do not know who would take it &mdash; the Minister for Finance, I suppose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Mr. Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Taoiseach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>No, the Taoiseach has twice been into this wigwam.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005:" RHead="Order for Second Stage">
    <Title>Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005: Order for Second Stage.</Title>
    <P LI="1">Bill entitled an Act to make provision for the granting of indemnities to air navigation undertakings by the Minister for Transport and to make provision for matters related thereto.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke"><NameTxt>Ms O&rsquo;Rourke</NameTxt>
	<P>I move: &ldquo;That Second Stage be taken today.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P><Col N="1004"/>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Transport</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank you, a Chathaoirligh, and the House for accommodating this Bill. Many people have asked me what the Bill is all about. In brief, the Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005 is all about improving and modernising Eurocontrol in air traffic management. The benefits to the commuter should be the prevention of airline delay, improved safety and integration with other European players. The main purpose of this Bill is to give effect to the International Convention relating to Co-operation for the Safety of Air Navigation signed at Brussels on 13 December 1960, as consolidated by the protocol signed at Brussels on 27 June 1997.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Eurocontrol, the European organisation for the safety of air navigation, was established by an international convention in 1960. The provisions of the 1960 convention were given effect in the Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Act 1963. The formal accession of Ireland to the Eurocontrol organisation came into force on 1 January 1965. Membership of the organisation has continued to grow and has now reached 35 states, including all EU member states except Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania. The accession of the European Community to Eurocontrol took place on 8 October 2002.</P>
      <P>Eurocontrol is the European organisation for the safety of air navigation. It currently numbers 35 member states and has as its primary objective the development of a seamless, pan-European air traffic management system. The achievement of this objective is a key element to the present and future challenges facing the aviation community, which are to cope with the forecast growth in air traffic, while maintaining a high level of safety, reducing costs and respecting the environment.</P>
      <P>Eurocontrol develops, co-ordinates and plans for the implementation of short, medium and long-term pan-European air traffic management strategies, and their associated action plans, on a collaborative basis. It is a collective effort involving national authorities, air navigation service providers, civil and military airspace users, airports, industry, professional organisations and relevant European institutions. Its core activities span the entire range of gate-to-gate air navigation service operations, from strategic and tactical flow management to controller training, from regional control of airspace to the development of leading edge technologies and procedures, and the collection of air navigation charges.</P>
      <P>Since the 1960 convention a number of protocols have been adopted. Two of these dealt with tax provisions while the third protocol of 12 February 1981 was a multilateral agreement on route charges. This provided for a common policy and joint system for the establishment and collection by Eurocontrol, on behalf of the contracting <Col N="1005"/>parties, of en-route air traffic control charges in European airspace covered by the agreement.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The convention provisions and its subsequent protocols were given effect in Irish legislation by the Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Acts 1963 to 1983. These Acts were subsequently repealed and the provisions of the convention and subsequent protocols given effect in the Irish Aviation Authority Act 1993. The Irish Aviation Authority is required under that Act to implement specific provisions of the Eurocontrol convention.</P>
      <P Just="Left">A revised Eurocontrol convention was concluded following several years of negotiation. The changes represent a major revision of the convention and are designed to update it to take into account progress made in the area of air navigation services. The final Act to the convention and the protocols amending and consolidating the text of the Eurocontrol international convention were signed by Ireland, subject to ratification, on 27 June 1997. The revised convention will come fully into force when it is ratified by all member states. To date 26 of the 35 member states have ratified it.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The amendments are designed to strengthen the co-operation between contracting parties via joint activities in the field of air navigation. These objectives do not prejudice the principle that every state has complete and exclusive sovereignty over the airspace above its territory, nor the capacity of each state to exercise its prerogatives with regard to security and defence in its national airspace.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The main provisions of the revised convention include the following: an updating of the objectives of the organisation, commensurate with its current and possible future activities; a new institutional structure for formulating and implementing the organisation&rsquo;s policy; an expansion of the tasks of the organisation to achieve a European air traffic management system; more effective decision making based on majority voting; and an enabling provision for European Community membership of Eurocontrol. At approximately the same time as the signature of the revised convention, EU member states agreed in principle to Community membership of Eurocontrol as the most appropriate way for the Community to exercise its competence in air traffic management. Negotiations between the European Commission and EurocontroI subsequently resulted in the text of an agreed accession protocol in 2002.</P>
      <P>Signature of the accession protocol took place at a diplomatic conference held on 8 October 2002. Signature of the final Act and the protocol on the accession of the European Community by Ireland was approved by Government at a meeting held on 11 June 2002. This Bill contains a reference to the protocol in the definition of the Eurocontrol convention, which will allow Ireland to ratify the accession protocol. The accession of <Col N="1006"/>the European Community to Eurocontrol was the culmination of negotiations aimed at ensuring consistency between the two organisations as they work together to develop the European air traffic management system. This move was followed by the conclusion of a memorandum of co-operation between the two organisations in December 2003, establishing a framework for mutual co-operation and support in five areas, namely, the implementation of the single European sky, research and development, data collection and analysis in the areas of air traffic and environmental statistics, satellite navigation and international co-operation in the field of aviation.</P>
      <P>It is important to explain what is meant in this context by the single European sky. The European Union&rsquo;s single sky and the revised Eurocontrol convention are deeply interlinked initiatives designed to tackle structural inefficiencies in European air traffic management. The approach represents, in many respects, a marriage of the technical expertise of Eurocontrol with the political and legal wherewithal of the Union. In the late 1990s the sharp rise in European air traffic led to substantial air traffic control delays. People here may have experienced such delays, but we hope to avoid them in the future. We manage traffic on the ground. Therefore, it is only right that we manage the growth in air traffic with our partners to avoid delays so that air passengers can travel safely without delay.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The delays experienced prompted the European Commission to launch its own initiative, with the issue in December 1999 of its communication on the creation of the single European sky. Significant progress has been made on the move towards implementing the single European sky policy, which attempts to reform the current air traffic management system. Air traffic management in Europe, with 73 air traffic control centres operating in the pan-European airspace, is fragmented and faces capacity constraints. An estimated 350,000 flight hours a year are wasted due to inefficient air traffic management and airport delays.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The European Commission has proposed a regulatory approach in the area of air traffic management with the objective of achieving a harmonised approach to safety, the regulation of air traffic services, technical interoperability of systems and airspace design and management at a European level. A key element of the institutional arrangements is the single sky committee which provides a mechanism for collaboration between member states&rsquo; civil and military authorities on airspace allocation and use. The single sky is the best means of overcoming the current institutional and structural problems that exist in the European air traffic management system and offers an effective process for securing member states&rsquo; compliance with agreed system improvements.</P><Col N="1007"/>
      <P>The single European sky initiative marks the beginning of a new dramatic and exciting chapter in European air traffic control. The development of the proposals is both a challenge and an opportunity for air navigation service providers to demonstrate in a practical way the greater efficiencies that can be obtained through the integration and development of services on a European scale while ensuring uniformly high safety standards throughout Europe. A single sky committee, chaired by the Commission, will oversee the preparation of implementing measures to establish the appropriate regulatory framework.</P>
      <P>These proposals envisage Eurocontrol acting as the technical advisor to the single sky committee and playing a significant role in defining and developing rules in accordance with mandates given by the European Union. The Commission sees Eurocontrol reflecting the single European sky rules across its membership and therefore achieving some of the single sky objectives in the wider European sphere. At the same time, the intention is that the single sky committee would adopt Eurocontrol&rsquo;s own rules when these were considered appropriate. In this way, the synergies between the two organisations can be meaningfully developed.</P>
      <P>The single European sky legislation has implications for the organisation and management of air traffic control services in Ireland and will require changes to the Irish Aviation Authority as service provider and regulatory authority for air navigation services. These developments and other evolving policies at international level give rise to the need for a critical examination of the structure and functions of the IAA, with a view to ensuring continuation of the highest safety standards, maximising organisational and operational efficiency and ensuring alignment with international and European air navigation and safety policies.</P>
      <P>The single European sky regulations require that all air navigation service providers be certified. Certification encompasses air traffic services, meteorological services for air navigation, aeronautical information services and communications, navigation and surveillance services. Common requirements for the certification of air navigation service providers, when adopted, will cover a range of criteria including technical and operational issues. Air navigation service providers will also be required to demonstrate suitability in the areas of ownership and organisational structure and human resources, including adequate staffing plans and security.</P>
      <P>These criteria provide the foundation for national supervisory authorities to certify service providers. Only validly certified air navigation service providers can then be designated to provide air traffic services on an exclusive basis within specified, constituent airspace blocks of <Col N="1008"/>the national airspace. The safety regulation division of the Irish Aviation Authority has been nominated as Ireland&rsquo;s interim national supervisory authority.</P>
      <P Just="Left">While Eurocontrol was previously almost exclusively concerned with air traffic management activities for the <i>en route</i> segment, the revised convention has considerably extended the scope of its activities to include the entire spectrum of air traffic services. These changes enable the following: the introduction of independent performance review and target setting; improvements to safety regulation; strengthened policy and planning for the airport air traffic system interface as part of the gate-to-gate concept; improved airspace design processes; improved standards making; the provision for common design and procurement of systems; enhanced research, development, trials and evaluation and more effective introduction of new technology; enhanced user consultation and/or involvement; and enhanced global co-operation and influence.</P>
      <P>With the growth in air traffic and the expansion in membership, it was recognised that the previous unanimous decision-making structure was unwieldy. Under the revised convention, most decisions can be taken by a majority vote. The revised convention will enable Eurocontrol to pass binding decisions on contracting parties in the fields of air safety, which is seen as a significant step in the right direction towards a more harmonised and safer European air traffic management system.</P>
      <P>Even though the revised convention will not come into force until all contracting parties have individually ratified it, contracting parties agreed to implement certain provisions of the revised convention early. These have included the expansion of the scope of the organisation&rsquo;s activities, establishment of the provisional council and advisory bodies to it and delegation of broader executive powers to Eurocontrol and its director general for the day-to-day running of the organisation. These important developments have enabled Eurocontrol to function more effectively.</P>
      <P>The Commission sees Eurocontrol reflecting the single sky rules across its membership and therefore achieving some of the single sky objectives in the wider European sphere. At the same time, the intention is that the single sky committee would adopt Eurocontrol&rsquo;s own rules when these were considered appropriate. In this way, the synergies between the two organisations can be developed, which is the correct way to move forward. Eurocontrol can play an important role in bridging the gap between EU states, under the new ATM regulatory structure being devised under single sky, and the non-EU contracting parties and will also continue to act as the main technical support body for Europe&rsquo;s air traffic management industry.</P><Col N="1009"/>
      <P>The Bill amends the Irish Aviation Authority Act 1993 and also makes provision for related matters. Specifically, the Bill reflects changes in the management structure of Eurocontrol and provides for the making of regulations requiring the Irish Aviation Authority to comply with any conditions laid down for the operation of a common European air traffic flow management system at a common international centre. Eurocontrol already operates such a centre, the central flow management unit based in Brussels, which has worked well with national air traffic service providers over a number of years. Furthermore, the Bill provides that Eurocontrol officers may give evidence in Irish courts and also provides for such officers to carry out on-the-spot inspections.</P>
      <P>Government policy on air navigation services is designed to ensure that Irish-controlled airspace is operated safely with maximum efficiency and effectiveness and that the highest internationally set and agreed safety standards are applied to the operations of Irish airspace and those using it. This policy is based on standards that are set internationally, mainly through the International Civil Aviation Organization convention to which Ireland is a signatory. Effect is given to this policy through the Air Transport and Navigation Acts and the Irish Aviation Authority Act 1993. Both Government policy and the development of these standards are designed to ensure continuing acceptable passenger and aircraft safety levels.</P>
      <P>Having regard to the largely executive nature of air navigation and safety regulatory functions, the requirement to ensure that these remain responsive to market needs and the desirability of capitalising on its potential for additional commercial and employment opportunities, the Government assigned these functions to the Irish Aviation Authority in 1994. The Irish Aviation Authority has responsibility for regulating the technical and safety aspects of civil aviation and the provision of air traffic standards. In its regulatory capacity, it oversees the safety standards in the operation, maintenance and airworthiness of Irish registered aircraft, the Irish air navigation services, Irish airlines and aircraft maintenance organisations, the competency of Irish pilots and aircraft maintenance engineers and the operation of Irish aerodromes. In fulfilling its role, the Irish Aviation Authority operates to international safety standards and procedures as laid down by the International Civil Aviation Organization and all other European and international regulatory organisations.</P>
      <P>I now turn to the main provisions of the Bill. Section 1 defines the 1993 Act as the Irish Aviation Authority Act 1993, while section 2 provides for miscellaneous amendments to the 1993 Act reflecting the new and more streamlined organisational arrangements within Eurocontrol and updating the penalties contained in section <Col N="1010"/>74 of the 1993 Act. Section 3 provides for amendment of Part III (Eurocontrol Convention) of the 1993 Act to delete references to the statute of the agency and the multilateral agreement on route charges, which are incorporated into the new convention. This section also empowers the Minister to make regulations for the purpose of giving effect to the common European air traffic flow management system at a common international centre, specified in Articles 2(<i>e</i>), 7.2(<i>d</i>) and 19 of the new convention, and ensuring compliance with that system by way of random checks and inspections and evidence in proceedings. Eurocontrol already operates such a centre, the central flow management unit based in Brussels, which has worked well with national air traffic service providers over a number of years.</P>
      <P>Section 4 repeals section 67 of the 1993 Act on detention of aircraft. Subsections (<i>a</i>), (<i>b</i>) and (<i>c</i>) of section 67 relate to the transfer of powers from the Minister to the Irish Aviation Authority set out in section 32 of the Air Navigation and Transport Act 1988. Section 32 was repealed by the Air Navigation and Transport Act 1998 so these subsections are already in fact redundant. Subsections (<i>d</i>) and (<i>e</i>) of section 67 of the 1993 Act comprise textual amendments to section 41 of the 1988 Act, which also relates to the transfer of powers from the Minister to the Irish Aviation Authority. I am advised that the repeal of section 67 of the Act of 1993 in its entirety does not now affect the status of section 41 of the 1988 Act, as amended by section 67. I hope Senators have been able to follow all of that. Section 5 is a standard legislative provision that provides for the Short Title while the Schedule reproduces the text of the consolidated Eurocontrol Convention.</P>
      <P>I have been advised that the Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005 represents a progressive and pragmatic way of managing the European air traffic control network in an efficient manner. It will reduce journey times, increase efficiency and improve safety. I am happy to commend the Bill to the House. I look forward to the contributions and comments of Senators.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Callely, to the House. He has been here quite often in recent weeks. I welcome the opportunity to speak on the important Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005, which for the most part I support. Its many positive aspects include its efforts to modernise air traffic management systems throughout Europe. It is crucial that we increase co-ordination between all Eurocontrol member states, not least because of the massive increase in the number of flights since the advent of low-cost air travel and the consequent increase in the numbers of landings and take-offs from airports across Europe.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Eurocontrol, which is the European organisation for the safety of air navigation, has a long <Col N="1011"/>history and has served Europe well in co-ordinating air traffic for over 40 years. It has 35 member states at present. Its primary objective is the development of European air traffic management. Eurocontrol develops, co-ordinates and plans the implementation of short, medium and long-term pan-European air traffic management strategies and associated action plans. It partakes in a collective effort that involves national authorities, air navigation service providers, civil and military airspace users, airports, industry, professional organisations and the relevant European institutions.</P>
      <P>One of the most significant changes to the convention that is being made in the revised convention before the House is provided for in the article that allows for the expansion of Eurocontrol&rsquo;s authority to include airport taxiways and runways, as well as the areas which are <i>en route.</i> The article also provides for increased research and improved co-ordination of elements of air traffic management. The revised convention before the House will permit greater co-operation between Eurocontrol and other European institutions. It will introduce European air traffic management performance review and target-setting systems. It also strives to create a more efficient decision-making process within the Eurocontrol commission, based on majority voting and the reinforcement of co-operation between civil and military authorities. Eurocontrol has made important changes to its administrative and deliberative structures by allowing for the establishment of a provisional council, which will be the organisation&rsquo;s central deliberative body. The council will be instrumental in implementing the expanded activities permitted under the revised convention.</P>
      <P>The Common Market was established and expanded with the aim of creating a unified trading area within Europe. Similarly, Eurocontrol has attempted from its earliest days to unify Europe&rsquo;s air traffic management system. This positive development corresponds with the European ideal of encouraging closer co-operation in all aspects of life. The revised convention significantly expands the powers of Eurocontrol in many key areas. It will allow the organisation to improve its co-ordination of the actions of its contracting parties in crucial areas of air traffic management and to impose binding decisions on them. It is clear that this power of enforcement is one of Eurocontrol&rsquo;s most important powers, particularly when one considers the importance of ensuring that the safety of air travel is the paramount consideration and having a powerful watchdog to protect the flying public.</P>
      <P>I hope the increased powers that the revised convention will give to Eurocontrol to assist it in its key role as the co-ordinator of European air traffic control will help to address Europe&rsquo;s <Col N="1012"/>worsening air traffic problems. Senators are familiar with the delays which are often encountered at this country&rsquo;s airports. We have not been helped in that regard by the Government&rsquo;s delay in making a decision on the construction of a second terminal at Dublin Airport. Air traffic delays are a tiresome burden for passengers, frustrate the expansion and efficient operation of airlines, lead to additional costs for airlines and create losses for the national economy. I welcome any legislation that helps to address such problems by facilitating better and more effective pan-European co-operation in air traffic management.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The unprecedented expansion in the business of low-cost carriers in recent years seems to have made air traffic problems worse. The European Commission has argued that some air traffic delays can be attributed to the manner in which airspace is organised in Europe. The Commission has argued that the problem is linked to European fragmentation along the lines of national boundaries. Such divisions make air traffic delays and air traffic congestion much worse than they need to be, thereby highlighting the need for better co-ordination and forward planning, services which Eurocontrol is best placed to provide. I agree with the Commission&rsquo;s statement that Europe cannot retain frontiers in the sky, given that it has abolished them on the ground in areas like free movement and free trade.</P>
      <P>I would like to raise the broader but related issue of the EU&rsquo;s open skies deal with the US, which has been the subject of a great deal of discussion in recent months. I urge the Minister for Transport to make progress in respect of the deal and the renegotiation of the bilateral agreement with the US, which offers tremendous opportunities for Ireland. I do not believe we should lose out to other European states in that regard. I recognise that Shannon Airport is a particularly sensitive issue that has been discussed for some time. The problems in that respect need to be resolved to the benefit of Irish aviation growth.</P>
      <P>I am very supportive of the broad outline, aims and objectives of the enabling legislation before the House. It has come to my attention, however, that the Bill in its present form raises concerns for some people within the aviation industry. I will endeavour to point out to the Minister of State the complicated problems encapsulated within the Bill. The main difficulty in the legislation relates to the collection of Eurocontrol charges, which are levied by the organisation if a member state airline breaches a regulation. The arrangements for the payment of such charges are set out in a 1981 agreement, which Ireland has signed. Ireland appears to have gone beyond what is required under the agreement, however, for reasons which I do not understand.</P>
      <P>The 1981 agreement provides that if an operator fails to pay the Eurocontrol charges, each member state will give Eurocontrol the power to <Col N="1013"/>sue the operator to obtain the full payment. Ireland appears to have gone beyond the normal regulations by permitting Eurocontrol, under its enabling legislation, to detain or sell aircraft to enforce the payment of the charge. It also provides that Eurocontrol can seek payment from non-operators and allows preference to be given to outstanding Eurocontrol charges over other debts in the event of an operator becoming insolvent.</P>
      <P>People within the Irish aviation sector have pointed out to me that the Irish Aviation Authority Act 1993 conflicts with the common collection process that was adopted by other Eurocontrol member states. They have argued that it distorts competition to the detriment of Irish interests, which seems arbitrary and unfair to Irish operators. I ask the Minister of State to explain the rationale behind the Irish provisions, which seem severe given that Eurocontrol has a 98% rate of recovery of such charges. Ireland is equally compliant with other countries so it does not explain why we have chosen to go beyond what is necessary under our convention obligations.</P>
      <P>Indeed, Ireland has an almost exemplary record in regard to complying with Eurocontrol requirements. Since the introduction of the State Airports Bill 2004, we have gone further and permitted each of the State airport authorities to detain aircraft and sell them, regardless of ownership, to pay Eurocontrol in preference to other interests. This policy does not take into account that the operator and owner of aircraft are not the same in most cases.</P>
      <P>We need to be careful to get the balance right and not unfairly penalise innocent parties to the detriment of the development of the Irish aviation sector. It could be off-putting to potential international investors in Irish aviation if we were to operate requirements more rigid than our European counterparts, when it is clearly not necessitated by our membership of Eurocontrol. Irish law as it currently stands permits Eurocontrol to take charges from innocent third parties, irrespective of guilt or innocence, either by way of the detention or sale of aircraft, which may only be leased by the operator. Such operators are not the party which takes the hit if the aircraft is ultimately sold to recoup the Eurocontrol charge.</P>
      <P>There may even be constitutional issues in regard to the protection of property rights enshrined in Bunreacht na h&Eacute;ireann. Until the enactment of the State Airports Bill in 2004, the Irish Aviation Authority exercised such powers on behalf of Eurocontrol. However, it rarely went so far as to seize the property of innocent third parties. This power of seizure and detention has now transferred to the three State airport authorities based in Dublin, Cork and Shannon, and there is a fear within the aviation sector that such <Col N="1014"/>reserve might not be so willingly exercised by these authorities in the future.</P>
      <P>This is a complicated issue which I have done little more than briefly outline. However, I am sure the Minister&rsquo;s officials in the Department are well aware of this discrepancy in Irish law. To my knowledge Eurocontrol can bring proceedings to hold aircraft owners as well as operators liable, whichever is the most appropriate in the circumstances. This would appear to reduce the necessity for detention and seizure. Will the Minister of State explain why he believes this difference between Irish law and the method adopted by other Eurocontrol members is necessary? Will he consider amending the legislation to place the Irish aviation industry on a level playing field with other member states, who are also signatories of the Eurocontrol convention?</P>
      <P>I welcome the Bill. I hope the Minister of State will address this issue on Committee Stage, if not today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>I will be happy to respond to the Senator on that issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimDooley"><NameTxt>Mr. Dooley</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and welcome the introduction of the Bill in the Seanad. From my reading, the Bill is of a technical nature but, nonetheless, it is important and should come into force without delay. Any Bill dealing with safety is obviously of paramount importance and should be dealt with by the Legislature with the utmost speed.</P>
      <P>The Bill will allow Ireland to ratify certain changes to the international convention which effectively established the European Organisation for the Safety of Air Navigation in 1960. As Senator Paddy Burke stated, it is not surprising that the convention would need to be updated because significant changes have occurred in the air transport and navigation sector in that period, particularly in terms of the growth of the industry, the greater number of aircraft in Europe, the increased number of flights and the increased number of passengers travelling. This growth in aviation is due to the significant growth of the economies of Europe, which makes us all better off, while globalisation has been a further significant factor.</P>
      <P Just="Left">While this growth is welcome, it brings certain difficulties for those organisations charged with the responsibility for ensuring that air navigation is carried out in a safe manner. The Minister of State clearly indicated to the House the wastage that takes place at present and the inability to get the best from the available airspace and air slots. However, if we ensure the Bill is put in place, we can move to a point where we can &mdash; I do not like to use the phrase &mdash; sweat the asset a little more. Despite what is thought about the size and scope of our skies, the number of flight paths is limited. It is important that proper management <Col N="1015"/>systems that cross individual state boundaries are utilised in an effective and efficient manner to ensure we continue to grow this sector in line with the growth of the economies across Europe and the world, and in particular to allow the continued globalisation to which we all refer.</P>
      <P Just="Left">It is agreed that safety is of paramount importance. Despite the large increase in aircraft movements and passengers travelling, air transport is thankfully the safest method of transport. This is highlighted by the carnage on our roads. If the numbers travelling on land are compared with those travelling by air, it is clear that, despite the complexities associated with aviation, air travel is safer than road travel. It is important that the highest standards are maintained to ensure that air travel remains at the top with regard to safety standards.</P>
      <?oasys _dc20-?><P Just="Left">As an island nation, our dependence on air connectivity is of vital economic importance. Therefore, safety standards are essential. Real challenges are potentially emerging as more airlines compete for business. We know of the changes in the market, particularly in the past ten years but more specifically in the past three to five years, due to the emergence of the low-cost carriers, to which Senator Paddy Burke referred. However, low-cost cannot mean low safety standards. We must be clear on this point. The Government has a particular role to ensure through national legislation that safety standards are maintained despite the necessity to force down prices, costs and charges. This is being achieved through the aviation authority, Eurocontrol.</P>
      <?oasys _dc0-?><TimeSt down="4" idown="4">12 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
      <P Just="Left">It is important the State does not facilitate a race to the bottom. In other sectors, we have heard the language used with regard to jobs. While we have lower costs and cheaper air fares, we must not force the industry to a point where safety is compromised. There are recent examples, with regard to which the Minister of State may be able to provide technical detail. The Greek carrier Helios regularly flies to and from Cyprus and operates charter flights to and from Ireland. Its passengers had real concerns about the safety of the airline for some weeks before one of its aircraft was involved in a crash. It is important that the desire of low-cost carriers to facilitate lower charges and ensure competition does not force them into a compromised position. While the outcome of the Helios investigation may not yet be known, if lessons are to be learned, the matter must be investigated, whether through Eurocontrol or the European Commission, to ensure that this race to the bottom in terms of cost does not mean a race to the bottom in terms of safety standards.</P>
      <P>To deviate slightly, as a result of the lowering of costs, there is a desire to allow aircraft to land in a less expensive environment. This has led to <Col N="1016"/>a desire among some of our airport authorities to reduce the conditions of workers by outsourcing certain functions within airports. This is neither helpful nor necessary. There is still a capacity for airports, while reducing costs in line with the expectations of workers, to at the same time maintain a level of standards and quality of employment for all involved. Outsourcing is a quick fix solution which has serious repercussions for the future of employment. Cost-cutting must be also examined in how it affects the social fabric of the local community and region. Yellow pack jobs are in no way helpful for the morale or the wealth of a community. What is needed is a workforce open to real change. In recognition of changes in the aviation sector, the trade unions have a role in co-operating with management to ensure a reduction in cost bases. They must be prepared to enter negotiations to bring about cost reduction. However, management cannot force a situation of cost reduction through outsourcing. In co-operation with union representatives, bringing about changes in work practices will resolve some of the problems. In return, employees must take on these changes. Employers, in recognition of this, must pay a decent wage for a decent day&rsquo;s work. I ask the Minister of State to take an active role in defining policy in this regard, particularly with the recent establishment of the airport authorities in Dublin, Cork and Shannon.</P>
      <P>I am familiar with these issues at Shannon Airport and I understand the same has arisen in the other airports. Management at Shannon Airport is proposing cost-cutting measures by outsourcing the catering division, effectively creating yellow pack jobs. Costs can be cut without doing this. The Government must carefully monitor this process to ensure a situation similar to that at Irish Ferries does not arise. While I accept Irish Ferries is not a State company, lessons can be learned from that experience.</P>
      <P Just="Left">All Members welcome low-cost carriers with the capacity to travel more freely and cheaply. However, the knock-on effects are significant. Carriers are making more profits in the lower cost environment. However, I do not want to see the workers carry the can for changes taking place across Europe. While the Bill does not specifically address the impact of these changes on employment, any legislation which deals with the aviation sector has the capacity to lead to changes in lifestyle of those providing the service. We must ensure there is no negative impact on their existence.</P>
      <P>Eurocontrol does provide a good framework in which co-operation can take place across Europe. Senator Paddy Burke already mentioned that the European Commission is dealing with the open skies policy. Media reports indicate that the dual gateway policy is about to be changed. While Senator Paddy Burke would like this to happen sooner, I certainly do not want to see it <Col N="1017"/>expedited. I want to see it delayed, if possible, because it will have a significant impact on Shannon Airport. Some claim the only way to deal with this is when it occurs. Leaving the dual gateway status is the only way to deal with it. The incremental gain in tourism from transatlantic flights from a change to the dual gateway status will be of a limited nature. It will not compensate for the significant loss to the western seaboard. While there may be a small gain in passenger numbers on the east coast, the west will lose out. The Government will then have to put in place other measures to prop up the west&rsquo;s tourism industry. This will not be cost effective in the long term.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I want an economic impact study to be carried out on the ending of the dual gateway status, as has been proposed by several businesses in the mid-west region. I am not saying the outcome will be negative. Instead, it will set out the challenges from the drop in passenger numbers. It is then a matter of how we work back from that and put in place measures to ensure a decline in business in the region does not happen. The Government has good policies for decentralisation and balanced regional development. The dual gateway status provides for balanced regional development by ensuring direct transatlantic connectivity on a daily basis. It ensures the business community and the tourism services in the Shannon region are catered for. If the dual gateway piece is taken out of the jigsaw, the carriers will want to consolidate their efforts in one airport, namely, Dublin Airport. I would welcome any initiatives the Minister of State, Deputy Callely, can bring to bear on this matter.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Bill, the speedy passage of which will be of immense benefit. It introduces an important framework for the delivery of a safe environment in air travel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Deputy Callely, and the Bill to the House. However, an issue I wish to raise is not covered in the Bill and I do not know if it can be included in its provisions. I have had complaints from individuals, which is the reason all politicians must act, about the use of private helicopters in suburban areas. There seems to be little in the way of legislation to control their use. The statutory instrument covering their use is Irish Aviation Authority (Aerodromes And Visual Ground Aids) Order 2000. On places of take-off and landing of aircraft, section 5(1)(<i>d</i>) states &ldquo;in the case of a rotorcraft or balloon, not being used for public transport, any place where the aircraft may take-off or land without undue hazard to persons or property and in respect of which the owner or occupier shall have given permission;&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>When this order was introduced, there were only about a dozen private helicopters but now <Col N="1018"/>there are over 200. A few years ago, private helicopters were used by a few rich people and were not a public nuisance or hazard. Now, it is much more of a problem. Will the Minister of State address this matter in his reply? I realise it is only loosely connected with the Bill but it is an area that will become increasingly important. More and more people believe that a private helicopter is one of the most suitable methods of transport around the country, despite the splendid work you are doing, Minister, on the roads.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>That is a valid point. I thank the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I remind Senators that remarks should be addressed through the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>I join my colleagues in welcoming the Minister of State to the House and thank him for outlining in great detail the provisions of the Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005. I compliment Senator Henry on raising the important issue of the increasing number of helicopters using our airspace.</P>
      <P>The Bill amends the Irish Aviation Authority Act 1993 and makes provision for related matters. Specifically, the Bill reflects changes in the management structure of Eurocontrol and provides for the making of regulations requiring the Irish Aviation Authority to comply with any conditions laid down for the operation of a common European air traffic flow management system at a common international centre. Eurocontrol, the European organisation for the safety of air navigation was established by an international convention in 1960. The provisions of the convention were given effect in the Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Act 1963. The formal accession of Ireland to the Eurocontrol organisation came into force on 1 January 1965, which was also a momentous year for other reasons, which I will mention to the Minister in private. Membership of the organisation has continued to grow and now numbers 34 states, including all EU member states except Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania.</P>
      <P>The accession of the European Union to Eurocontrol took place on 8 October 2002. As the Minister of State outlined, since the 1960 convention a number of further protocols have been adopted. An additional protocol of 6 July 1970 concerned tax provisions. A protocol of 21 November 1978 amended the 1970 protocol. An amending protocol was adopted on 12 February on a multilateral agreement on route changes which provided for a common policy and joint system for the establishment and collection by Eurocontrol, on behalf of the contracting parties, of <i>en route</i> air traffic control changes in European air space covered by the agreement.</P><Col N="1019"/>
      <P>The provisions of the convention and its subsequent protocols were given effect in legislation under the Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Acts 1963 to 1983. These Acts were subsequently repealed by the provisions of the convention and subsequent protocols given effect in the Irish Aviation Authority Act 1993, which the Minister referred to in detail. The final Act giving effect to the convention and the protocols amended and consolidated the text of the Eurocontrol convention and were signed by Ireland subject to ratification on 27 June 1996. The revised convention will fully come into force when it is ratified by all member states. To date 22 of the 34 member states have done so.</P>
      <P>The revised Eurocontrol convention was concluded following several years of negotiation. The changes represent a major revision of the convention and were designed to update it to take account of progress made in the area of air navigational services. The main new provisions of the revised convention include an updating of the objectives of the organisation, a new institutional structure for formulating and implementing its policy, an expansion of the tasks of the organisation to achieve a European air traffic management system, more effective decision making based on majority voting and an enabling power for European Union membership of Eurocontrol. Many of the provisions of the revised convention do not require legislative changes as they are already provided for in existing legislation or relate to administrative arrangements for the operation of the Eurocontrol agency.</P>
      <P Just="Left">In the late 1990s the sharp rise in European air traffic led to substantial air traffic control related delays, to which the Minister of State referred. Some colleagues have experienced such delays recently. This prompted the European Commission to launch its own initiative in December 1999 with a communication entitled The Creation of the Single European Sky. This proposal envisaged Eurocontrol acting as a technical adviser to the single sky committee and playing a significant role in defining and developing the rules.</P>
      <P>I will raise two points with the Minister of State. First, what additional costs will arise to the State from the passing of this legislation? Second, we do not have an airport in Cavan so we must use the airport in Dublin. To get there we have to use the road. I thank the Minister of State for the work he and Minister for Transport, Deputy Cullen, are doing on progressing the N3. This road is very important to the people living in Cavan, Meath and north Leitrim who need to get to Dublin, whether for the airport or for work. I urge him to keep pressing to get this road under construction as quickly as possible. We will discuss the rail link to Cavan at a later date.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="1020"/>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>If the road is wide enough it might serve as a runway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State and compliment him on bringing the Air Navigation (Eurocontrol) Bill 2005 before this House. I commend him on his presentation of the Bill which will receive the full support of the House, because it is of vital importance. We have a proud record on air navigation and the work carried out by his officials is effective. They provide a wonderful service.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I will outline developments at the former Knock Airport, now called Ireland West Airport, Knock, having been rebranded last Monday. The first flight landed at and took off from the airport 20 years ago, with Rome its destination. It was a historic occasion which I wish to put on record in this House. May 2006 will be the 20th anniversary of the official opening of Knock Airport by the then Taoiseach Mr. Charles J. Haughey. A combination of the leadership of Mr. Haughey and Monsignor James Horan brought about one of the greatest infrastructural developments in the west of Ireland and indeed the country.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The fact that we have an international airport of the standard and quality of Ireland West Airport, Knock, has contributed enormously to the economy of the west. Some 500,000 passengers are now recorded annually, which is a marvellous achievement in such a short time. Projections for the future are substantial. At present, users of the airport contribute an inbound tourism spend in the region of &euro;7.1 million. There was a direct contribution of &euro;6.5 million by Knock to the GDP of 2004 and a contribution of &euro;30 million from the tourism spend in the region. The Exchequer received &euro;5.4 million in income tax and PRSI and there were 500,000 tourism bed-nights in 2004. Some 110 people are directly employed and 580 jobs are supported in the wider local economy. Those represent impressive progress for the airport.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I ask the Minister of State for further investment in the airport. The management estimates it requires some &euro;22.9 million for navigational aids and ATC, runway and apron upgrades, terminal works, fire and ramp services, baggage and security, catering and retail services, car parks, IT and CCTV cameras. The CAT 11 navigation aid provides the means to land aircraft in lower levels of visibility. It is a navigational aid for the airport itself. Navigation status is not available in the Border, midlands and west region and if the region is to reverse its deficiency in direct airport access then CAT 11 or CAT 111 status in the region is vital. Knock Airport represents the most viable and realistic opportunity to achieve that. The cost of the perimeter fencing and all other requirements will be included in the estimates.</P>
      <P>The extension of the apron to the end of the runway, the significance of which the officials <Col N="1021"/>present will realise, will also provide additional safety. The apron is part of the aerodrome where aircraft park and passengers disembark. Currently there are two official aircraft parking stands at the airport. The airport currently suffers from acute ramp congestion with scheduled aircraft such as Easyjet regularly having to hold in the air or on the runway as it waits its turn for a stand on the apron. The funding referred to above would provide the airport with four aircraft parking stands. I was in the Minister of State&rsquo;s Department for a short period of nine months around the time when Knock Airport, or Ireland West Airport as it is now known, was being built. I was delegated responsibilities by Mr. John Wilson, who was a Minister at the time, and I concentrated on the post office services.</P>
      <P>We are very proud of Ireland West Airport, Knock, a flagship project in the region. A programme on its history was shown a few days ago on television. Some Opposition Members must cringe when they remember the foggy and boggy site.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>It was one of the more damaging political decisions made by that Government at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>We put the money into the project. We hope the present Government will carry out its aims and secure the money that is now required.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Mr. Paddy O&rsquo;Toole, a Minister at the time, paid the price in Ballina, and Senator Jim Higgins, now an MEP, was rewarded with a seat in Leinster House. The decision had many repercussions. When I attended the rebranding of the airport, there was a great feeling of satisfaction from Fianna F&aacute;il in that the party was part of this particular history.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>The party has let the same people down in the past number of years. They are seeking money and it is not being provided.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>People such as P&aacute;draig Flynn, Albert Reynolds and Charles J. Haughey played their part.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Leyden had some part in it also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I was present the day the invitation arrived from Monsignor James Horan to the then Leader of the Opposition. The invitation <Col N="1022"/>stated that Monsignor Horan would yield to nobody but the Pope in Rome. The Pope had visited the country in 1979. Our party was in Opposition at the time, and I was the spokesman for posts and telegraphs. We have a very proud record&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator was all talk. No money was provided at the time and no money is being provided now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Burke needs somewhere to land a helicopter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I will park it at the Minister&rsquo;s door.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Minister of State and his officials to take on board this submission. We have his goodwill and that of the Minister for Transport, Deputy Cullen, and the Taoiseach. The Minister for Community, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs, Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, has brought his Department to Knock, which is a great achievement for the Government. We should announce it more often as due recognition is not being received.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Government has got enough already. It is on a merry-go-round.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome this Bill and will use this opportunity to explain a personal interest in it. The last time an air navigation Bill came before this House I was a spokesman on transport. I broadly welcomed the Bill because it increased passengers&rsquo; rights, etc. Last June I returned from a wedding in Rome, flying with Aer Lingus. The aircraft&rsquo;s departure was delayed, and my experience of complaint since has been a nightmare. I have received no compensation apart from a &euro;100 Aer Lingus voucher. The aeroplane that was coming from Dublin was diverted to Gatwick Airport for safety reasons, as there was a smell of gas on it. It later transpired that the smell was from sweets being consumed. The aeroplane was delayed in Gatwick which led to a delay in it arriving in Rome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Is this relevant to the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">It is relevant from the perspective of air navigation, and it is at least as relevant as a discussion on Knock Airport. When the last air navigation Bill was in the Seanad, it promised better rights for passengers. This has not come about, and there is no co-operation between flight operators and passengers.</P>
      <P>Returning to my experience, the aeroplane was due to fly out at 7 p.m. on a Saturday evening but <Col N="1023"/>we finally returned to Ireland at 2 p.m. on the Sunday. There was chaos in between, with no accommodation being offered. It did not affect me that much as I am quite young and can take some rough and tumble. If I can survive political life here I can survive sleeping on the floor of an airport for a few hours. However, some affected people were in their 70s. Even worse, mothers with young children were also affected, and I do not know how they did not crack up completely.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Those affected were given no information to begin with and any information that was received afterwards was complete misinformation. It was akin to a scene from &ldquo;Fawlty Towers&rdquo; as nobody was in charge or knew what was happening. Being entitled to compensation, I should have received a full refund of my fare and compensation of &euro;400. This has not occurred. When I telephoned the Department of Transport I received some helpful advice. I wrote to the customer care section of Aer Lingus, which in my experience is an oxymoronic description. No policy seems to exist for customer care in the company. At the moment one cannot telephone Aer Lingus to complain as it will not take calls. The company will not reply to letters. This is a point that the Minister of State should take up with the head of Aer Lingus. There is nothing more unsatisfactory and frustrating for a customer than being unable to get a reply from a company.</P>
      <P>As Aer Lingus did not acknowledge my letters, I contacted the Department to get information on the relevant Bill and the increased rights for consumers. I was told that my complaint must be registered with the country in which the incident happened. I wrote to the air navigation section in Rome Airport and still have not received a reply. So far, all I have received is a voucher from the incident, and I have had no other acknowledgement of my case. This should not happen.</P>
      <P>If customers travel by aeroplane, they should receive what they are promised. I am only highlighting my own personal case because I am familiar with it. It applies to other people, and there were 300 or 400 other people on the aeroplane journey I described. Some of these people have not received compensation. We wonder why the public is so sceptical about the European Union, but what I have described is a case in point. The aeroplane was diverted, the airline was liable and compensation should have been paid accordingly. This never happened.</P>
      <P>I ask the Minister of State to take the case up with Aer Lingus. At this stage the monetary compensation is not relevant, but the principle is. It is ridiculous that I had to wait almost 24 hours at that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>I have some good news for the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="1024"/>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>It is well and good passing these Bills, but if the legislation is not put into practice we are merely wasting time. I am not sure if more amendments are being brought forward but the Minister of State should bear in mind my comments. If talks are to be held at EU level, questions should be asked about how legislation is working in practice. It has not worked, and I can give the Minister of State the documentation from my experience as proof.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Transport</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senators contributing to this debate and I have carefully noted the issues raised. I hope I will be able to respond adequately. If I do not, I invite the Senators to write directly to me on any issue which I do not have sufficient time to clarify now.</P>
      <P>It is important to understand the stage we are now at and the manner in which we are moving forward on the issue. For example, over the past decade air traffic growth has topped 50%. It is clear this trend will continue. Europe has close to 9 million flights per year, and there are up to 30,000 flights on busier days. Eurocontrol expects that current traffic will double by 2020. Current systems, with ongoing improvements, should be able to handle this increased load until approximately the middle of the next decade. After this more radical measures will be called for to avoid serious congestion.</P>
      <P>I have visited a number of our own centres under the control of IAA. I have been impressed with the level of technology now in place within these centres, and we are able to accommodate today&rsquo;s capacity. Other measures may be required in future.</P>
      <P>The single European sky initiative is expected to lay the foundations of a unified system which will be able to cater for the anticipated growth as well as bringing other benefits arising from the positive aspects of such a unified system. The initiative launched by the European Commission aims to restructure European airspace as a function of air traffic flows, rather than according to national borders. Hence, it will designed to facilitate air traffic to get from A to Z in a much quicker and seamless system. Instead of being obliged to deal with the 73 air traffic control centres mentioned, a seamless system will be in operation.</P>
      <P>The initiative&rsquo;s purpose is also to create additional capacity and increase the overall efficiency of the air traffic management system. Eurocontrol has considerable expertise and experience in these fields which will be applied to make the single European sky initiative a reality. The revised convention seeks to provide a more effective air traffic management institutional policy and decision-making structure for Europe, with the overall objective of increasing airspace <Col N="1025"/>capacity and, as I have noted, reducing air traffic control delays.</P>
      <P>The pressure for change came from a number of sources, particularly airlines&rsquo; dissatisfaction with the failure to unify and centralise air traffic management in Europe. When implemented, the convention will provide for the necessary institutional reforms required to achieve a uniform European air traffic management system for the control of general air traffic in European airspace as well as in and around airports.</P>
      <P>I will try to deal with the issues raised by Members. My good friend Senator Browne referred to an issue that is of concern to many passengers whose experiences have been similar to his. I understand a number of the Senator&rsquo;s colleagues in the Fine Gael Party have also had this experience. The Senator might mention to Deputy Deasy that he made a great mistake. If I had been invited to the Deputy&rsquo;s wedding in Rome, I would have ensured none of my colleagues in Fine Gael would have experienced any chaos, as the Senator put it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister of State must wait for the next wedding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Minister of State bring the Government jet with him?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>I am unsure whether Senator Browne was referring to the chaos at the wedding or the airport.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>It is hot air.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>It is the chaos within Fine Gael. However, I am happy to extend an olive branch to Fine Gael Members. If they can secure an invitation to such functions for me, I will be happy to attend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>There were 400 people on the flight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Paddy Burke should note that, if necessary, I might even arrange to use the jet. It would be great if I could call on it to bring me to a wedding.</P>
      <P>On a more serious note, since February, passengers have been automatically entitled to compensation from an airline in the event of delay, cancellation or denied boarding. In the first instance, it is a matter for the airline to fulfil its obligations to passengers regarding compensation and passengers should apply directly to the airline concerned for compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>That is a waste of time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Equally, we have a Commission for Aviation Regulation, CAR. The statutory instrument which designated the commission was <Col N="1026"/>made in May. It designates the CAR as the authority responsible for enforcing the European regulation and receiving complaints from passengers who feel an airline has failed to meet its obligations under the regulations. I am in favour of user-friendly systems. In light of Senator Browne&rsquo;s contribution, I will ask my departmental officials to take up the issue with the CAR. One should not be obliged to take the course of action outlined by the Senator. Air passengers who experience problems on their journey and who feel their right to compensation has not been met by the relevant airline or tour operator should forward their complaint to the CAR or call the commission at (01) 6611700. That should resolve the matter. I am unsure whether the Senator did so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>I did that also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>If he did and it has failed, as Minister of State at the Department of Transport, I am disappointed, as is my Department. I will ask the CAR to respond. I ask in this House that a response be laid on my desk within three to five days on the issues raised by the Senator. This is not simply because the matter has been raised by him&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FeargalBrowne"><NameTxt>Mr. Browne</NameTxt>
	<P>No. There is a principle involved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;or because I mentioned Deputy Deasy&rsquo;s wedding in jest. In earnest, passengers should not be bounced from one authority to another and then asked to write to the authorities in Rome and so on.</P>
      <P>As for Senator Leyden&rsquo;s comments in respect of Ireland West Airport, Knock, I welcome the successful development by the Knock authorities. It is a key infrastructural asset for economic and tourism development in the west. I travelled to the airport earlier this year and had the opportunity of meeting its general manager and chairman who brought some issues for which they had sought funding to my attention. I was happy that these were followed up and that within a couple of months they received the required moneys. I acknowledge that the need for major investment at the airport to promote growth has been identified. That is being proactive and how things should be.</P>
      <P>I am a strong supporter of market-driven airport development, not only in Ireland West Airport, Knock, but in all our regional airports. I congratulate all the airport authorities which have developed their facilities. I fly on a regular basis to an airport in my own base of north Dublin, namely, the premier airport, Dublin International Airport. Equally, I congratulate the Cork Airport Authority which is undertaking an enormous investment programme.</P><Col N="1027"/>
      <P>I was asked about the cost of this measure and can state the passage of this Bill will not involve any additional costs. We contribute approximately &euro;6 million to Eurocontrol which is recovered from the Irish Aviation Authority.</P>
      <P>Senator Henry raised an interesting question, for which I thank her, about the operation of private helicopters. I raised the issue with my departmental officials before coming into the House. Senator Wilson has also raised the issue. A stringent and structured regime for the control of helicopters and their pilots is in place. Certain restrictions apply to the flight paths of helicopters. Equally, I understand there are exemptions as to when helicopters or light aircraft are obliged to communicate and obtain flight clearance, etc. I will ask my officials to note Senator Henry&rsquo;s comments &mdash; I know they have done so already &mdash; and to communicate the criteria that apply in respect of the use of helicopters to her. I agree with her observation that helicopters have become a regular mode of transport for a greater number. The Irish Aviation Authority is the responsible body regarding the operation of helicopters and applies the highest possible safety standards. I wish to discuss the issue of safety later, in respect of light aircraft and helicopters.</P>
      <P>Senator Dooley touched on a number of subjects. I have noted his comments, particularly on outsourcing by aviation companies and the position of Shannon Airport. If one examines Shannon and some of its competing demands, such as the developments in Cork, to which I have alluded, Knock, Sligo, a number of other regional airports and Dublin Airport, there is an opportunity for it to develop on a regional basis in line with the others and attract its own market. Good work is being carried out in this regard. People such as Senator Dooley have great roles to play in leading the potential of likely developments.</P>
      <P Just="Left">With regard to safety regulation being a case of one size fits all, there is no question of low-cost carriers having lower standards of safety as stringent criteria are applied across the board. I will be unequivocal in this regard as I do not wish people to have a view that there is a difference in safety standards. I also wish to congratulate everyone involved in our aviation industry as, excusing the pun, they fly a tremendous flag for it, whether they are the operators in the sky or on the ground. We have a significant safety record due to the stringent protocols and procedures and very strict safety criteria in place. In international terms, we rank very well in this respect and, as such, I wish to congratulate the individual players, namely, the operators, pilots, hostesses and other staff involved in putting planes into the sky and the mechanical, technical, airport authority, ground and support staff involved, whether one is discussing anything from <Col N="1028"/>light aircraft or helicopters to companies such as Aer Lingus, Ryanair, Aer Arann and other Irish operators. The small number of cargo companies operating out of Ireland also have good safety records.</P>
      <P>As such, safety is paramount in aviation and a central element of the revised convention is ensuring the highest practical safety standards are maintained while maximising the capacity of the air traffic management, ATM, system. The implementation of safety standards in Ireland is clearly the responsibility of the Irish Aviation Authority, IAA, which falls under my responsibility as the Minister of State at the Department of Transport. I meet with the IAA whenever it deems suitable. It knows that my door is always open and I have a good rapport with it. I congratulate Mr. Eamonn Brennan of the IAA and his staff, as I am impressed with their commitment, dedication and enthusiasm in going about their business. I have visited a number of the IAA&rsquo;s centres and have been impressed at every level.</P>
      <P>Senator Paddy Burke referred to the delay in the decision on the second terminal for Dublin Airport. The Government took a number of key decisions in May of this year concerning future aviation policy, including a possible third party investment in Aer Lingus and the building of a second terminal. These decisions will provide a secure foundation for the development of Irish aviation. The Dublin Airport Authority is highly conscious of the need to avoid any slippage in the timetable for the second terminal, which will allow for growth in passenger traffic. Just under 20 million passengers per annum fly through Dublin Airport. Based on the information given to me by my officials, this level of investment will allow the airport to accommodate approximately 30 million passengers, a full 50% increase.</P>
      <P>If one examines what the Government is doing in Cork, Shannon, Knock, Sligo and all of the other regional airports, one will be impressed when flying over Dublin Airport or Cork Airport. We are discussing new terminal buildings and a level of investment that is unprecedented in Irish aviation. I am particularly pleased and proud to be a member of a Government that is taking the aviation business so seriously and putting in that level of investment.</P>
      <P>Senator Paddy Burke raised another issue, namely, the retention and sale of aircraft under the revised convention. Ireland is under no compulsion to legislate for the creation of liens or joint and several liabilities as an operator and owner of aircraft and has not made provision for it in this Bill. By not introducing the creation of a lien and joint and several liability, it cannot be said that Ireland is not discharging its obligations under the new Eurocontrol convention. It is a matter of choice for a contracting party to introduce domestic law to this effect. I will ask my Department officials to communicate with the <Col N="1029"/>Senator on this issue. He will be satisfied with the Irish position as I have outlined it.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I thank Senator Wilson for his kind comments and clear, broad understanding of the Bill. He is one of several Senators who have been in regular contact with me about a number of issues relating to aviation. He referred to the pressure on our infrastructure, in particular the road network in County Cavan. The Government is making significant investments in our roads building projects. We are spending approximately &euro;115 million each month and will continue to do so in order to achieve what the Senator has indicated is important, namely, an appropriate infrastructure network, whether it is road, rail, air or any other method of transport, including new modes. I am pleased to inform the House that our ten-year investment framework will be announced in detail within the coming days. Some of what Senator Wilson has asked me to deliver for the people of the BMW region will be included and he will be impressed by and satisfied with it, as will every Member of this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>We will all be retired by that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Senator going that soon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>We are examining ways of developing projects on time, within budget and as quickly as possible as we recognise there are issues to be addressed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>The Government has only one year left to address them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>The Government will be refreshed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Mr. Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>I may not be in a position to make the announcement of a Cavan airport that Senator Wilson would like but will be able to announce some other good initiatives. I wish to express my appreciation to the House for accommodating the Bill and to my officials, Mr. Fintan Towey and Mr. Kevin Dunne.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>Next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 2 November 2005.</P>
    <P Italics="Y">Sitting suspended at 12.50 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <Col N="1030"/><MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prisons Bill 2005:" RHead="Order for Second Stage">
    <Title>Prisons Bill 2005: Order for Second Stage.</Title>
    <P LI="1">Bill entitled an Act to enable the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to enter into agreements for the provision of certain services relating to the custody of prisoners by persons who are parties to such agreements; to provide for the certification of persons who will perform functions under this Act pursuant to such agreements; to provide for the giving of evidence by prisoners in certain types of proceedings before the courts by live television link; to amend the Prisons Act 1933; and to provide for matters connected therewith.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I move: &ldquo;That Second Stage be taken today.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prisons Bill 2005:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Prisons Bill 2005: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><TitleTxt>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I am pleased to have this opportunity to open the debate in the House on the Prisons Bill 2005. The purpose of the Bill is to provide for contracting out certain prisoner escort services; the closure of Mountjoy Prison, and prisoners participating in certain court hearings by means of a live television link from prison. The measures provided for in the Bill are intended to provide for a more efficient and effective running of the Prison Service.</P>
      <P>Since becoming Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform in June 2002, I have been committed to introducing measures to reform and modernise the prison system. While much has been achieved in recent years, we must continue to strive to ensure the State has a modern, humane and cost effective prison service that meets the highest international standards.</P>
      <P>I recognised from the beginning that the target I had set for myself was ambitious. It would require major changes in how the prisons operated and significant capital expenditure. In seeking to modernise our prison system I have the full support of the Government in securing the necessary capital investment, for which I am grateful. I am satisfied that the modernisation programme completed and under way will serve us well into the future. It is never easy to bring about change. However, as legislators and policymakers, we must be prepared to look to what is in the overall national interest and beyond narrow local sectional interests.</P>
      <P Just="Left">On examining the prison system, one is confronted with two main challenges. These are the poor physical standards in some of our prisons, most notably Mountjoy and Cork, and the need <Col N="1031"/>to ensure our prisons are run efficiently and in a cost-effective manner. That said, I acknowledge other improvements in the prison system are also required and I will address these issues in a proactive way.</P>
      <P>The rules governing our prisons date back to 1947. Successive Ministers with responsibility for justice chose to leave the substantive rules as they were. I was determined to ensure that, in tandem with improving and replacing our existing prison infrastructure, the governance of prisons would be set out in modern rules. To that end, last June I published draft prison rules on my Department&rsquo;s website. I intend to bring these rules into use at the earliest possible stage.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The House will be aware that the Government approved a series of measures in November 2003 in the event of failure to reach agreement with the Prison Officers  Association on organisational change. Of these measures, the outsourcing of the prisoner escort service is relevant to this Bill. I stress that it has always been my preferred option that organisational change in the Prison Service be achieved through negotiation and with the co-operation of the Prison Officers Association. I am pleased that the proposal for organisational change has been accepted and is now being implemented, allowing for greater certainty in the allocation of resources. In previous years capital investment was curtailed by the constant drain on finances for overtime requirements. Following long and protracted negotiations, a comprehensive proposal for organisational change in the Prison Service was accepted in a second ballot of members of the Prison Officers Association last August. A majority of more than two to one favoured accepting the deal and I welcomed its acceptance. The revised working arrangements stand to benefit both management and staff.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The arrangements agreed in the revised proposal represent one of the most significant change programmes undertaken in the Prison Service in recent years, opening the way for greater flexibility, efficiency and cost effectiveness in every operational area of the State&rsquo;s prisons. Key measures agreed include the replacement of overtime with a new annual &ldquo;additional hours&rdquo; system which effectively caps the level of extra attendance costs in the service; the introduction of more efficient staffing and working arrangements backed by new agreed rosters; the establishment of a new Prison Service escort corps, PSEC, which will manage Prison Service escorts more efficiently and effectively through better co-ordination and the use of cellular vehicles; the rationalisation of prison stores and maintenance arrangements; the introduction of a new recruit prison officer grade with modified conditions of service and the elimination of static posts through the use of technology such as electronic gates and <Col N="1032"/>closed circuit television to allow the redeployment of staff.</P>
      <P>The main benefits to the taxpayer will be greater control of costs, predictable future costs and a more effective service in the future. At the same time, staff will secure attractive, stable and predictable overall rates of remuneration. I am pleased to inform the House that the implementation of the agreed arrangements is proceeding apace. The timeframe for implementation is extremely challenging. Roll-out of the additional hours system which will replace the existing overtime system will begin next month and be completed by February 2006. A co-ordinated prisoner escort service utilising cellular vans will also be activated for all Dublin prisons by mid-November, extending across the service nationally early in the new year.</P>
      <P>In accordance with the terms of the agreed proposal, phased payments to staff will be linked to progress on the change agenda. To date, progress has been sufficient to merit payment of an initial lump sum payment and progress is well advanced for the roll-out of the first phase of an annual hours system to replace overtime which will trigger payment of a new operational allowance to staff in the institutions concerned.</P>
      <P>Provision has been made for a joint national monitoring and review committee, comprising representatives of management and staff with an agreed independent chairperson nominated by the Labour Relations Commission. It will decide, among other matters, on issues regarding the interpretation of the agreement where consensus cannot be reached. Local monitoring and review arrangements will also be put in place at each institution to oversee the work of the new system and address locally any difficulties that may arise, with recourse to the national committee if required.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Successful implementation of these measures will deliver savings to the Exchequer of &euro;25 million per annum. I have made it clear on several occasions in this House and elsewhere that these savings are essential in bringing order to the cost base of our prisons. I am determined that these savings will be achieved as the roll-out of the change programme proceeds. The new working arrangements will take advantage of technological developments in prison design such as electronic locking systems. The use of video links is addressed in section 11 of the Bill, as well as in relation to visits for prisoners in the new prison rules.</P>
      <P>Sections 2 to 7 of the Bill relate to the provision of prisoner escort services. When the Bill was published, it appeared that the proposal for organisational change would be rejected by prison officers. In those circumstances I would have had no choice but to contract out prisoner escort services if the Prison Service was ever to be viable. Fortunately, after further negotiations <Col N="1033"/>and a second ballot, we have now progressed to a stage where the proposal for organisational change has been accepted and it incorporates a co-ordinated prisoner escort service operated from within the Prison Service. As this is my preferred approach, I have no plans to contract out the service for the foreseeable future. Agreement is one thing; delivery is another matter. I, therefore, propose to retain sections 2 to 7 in the Bill, although I hope they will never have to be brought into force.</P>
      <P>I will give the House a concise outline of the provisions dealing with the escort of prisoners. For the purpose of the Bill, a prisoner is a person in respect of whom an order of a court committing that person to prison is in force. It includes persons remanded in custody or sentenced to imprisonment from the moment the court has ordered their detention. Section 2 provides that the Minister may, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, enter into an agreement with a contractor to provide prisoner escort services. Such services would cover the transfer of prisoners to and from prison, their production in court and holding them in detention for those purposes. The service must be provided using persons certified by the Minister to be prisoner custody officers. Under section 3, an individual may apply for a certificate which will be granted only if the Minister is satisfied that the applicant is of good character, has been properly trained and is capable of performing the functions of the position. An applicant who is refused may appeal to the court against the refusal. Conditions may be attached to the issue of a certificate which will be valid for a period not exceeding five years.</P>
      <P>Section 5 provides that a prisoner custody officer shall have the same powers as a prison officer, including the power to use reasonable force where necessary. Certain limitations on the power to search are imposed. Prisoner custody officers are obliged to prevent escapes, maintain order, comply with any court order relating to a prisoner and comply generally with the relevant prison rules.</P>
      <P>Section 6 makes it an offence for a prisoner custody officer to disclose unauthorised information. Section 7 provides for the appointment of an officer to monitor the performance of contractors and submit a report to the Minister each year relating to the activities of the previous year. If the Minister is of the view that a particular individual, because of his or her behaviour or otherwise, is no longer fit to be a prisoner custody officer, the certificate may be revoked pursuant to section 4. A person who is not properly certified and purports to perform the functions of a prisoner custody officer shall be guilty of an offence.</P>
      <P>In section 8 I am providing for the closure of Mountjoy Prison. This is linked to my plans to modernise the stock of prison accommodation. <Col N="1034"/>The section amends the Prisons Act 1933 by deleting the provision that excludes Mountjoy Male Prison and Mountjoy Female Prison from its scope. The effect will be to give the Minister the power to close Mountjoy Prison in the future by an order pursuant to section 2 of the Prisons Act 1933 which enabled the Minister to close a prison by order, but was expressed not to apply to Mountjoy Prison. While the effect and motive of this are not completely clear, one interpretation is that in 1933 there was no need to create a statutory power of closure in respect of Mountjoy Prison. Another interpretation is that under current law Mountjoy Prison cannot be closed. This amendment will remove any legal doubt as to whether that is possible. On its own, this measure might be regarded as almost a technical amendment but its importance relates to my determination to provide modern and humane prison facilities for all prisoners and staff.</P>
      <P>Senators may be interested to note that Mountjoy Prison was the first purpose built prison in the State. Before its completion in 1850, prisons in Ireland were provided and operated by grand juries, the precursors to county councils. The Prisons Act 1933 originated from the need for legislation to validate an order made in November 1920 closing Tralee Prison. The Circuit Court found in 1932 that the legislative provisions available at the time under the Prisons (Ireland) Act 1877 were not sufficient to allow the prison to be closed and the premises transferred to Kerry County Council. The Prisons Act 1933 was to amend the statutory provisions governing the closing of local prisons and their subsequent disposal which had been contained in sections 30 and 31 of the 1877 Act. Difficulty had been experienced in the interpretation and application of these sections and as a result, there was considerable doubt as to the legal position of some closed prisons, portions of which were retransferred to county councils and others used for public purposes such as police barracks. These doubts were confirmed by a decision in 1932 in the High Court in relation to a prison in Kilkenny. The 1933 Act was to clarify the position for the future. Sections 30 and 31 of the Act of 1877 were repealed and replaced by more explicit provisions. The Attorney General of the time, introducing the Bill on Second Stage, specifically mentioned that Mountjoy Male Prison and Mountjoy Female Prison were excluded from the Bill as there was no reversionary interest in the prison vested in any local authority. The prison was exclusively State property.</P>
      <P>Today we need new purpose built prison facilities to provide the range of facilities needed to cater for the type and range of prisoner population accommodated in, for example, the extended Mountjoy Prison campus. Today there are 855 inmates in the Mountjoy Prison complex divided between Mountjoy Male Prison with 499 <Col N="1035"/>inmates, St. Patrick&rsquo;s Institution with 184 and the Training Unit with 90, as well as 82 female inmates in the D&oacute;chas Centre. The Mountjoy complex contains some 28% of the total national prison population.</P>
      <P Just="Left">It is neither operationally feasible nor economically sensible to redevelop the 20 acre site at Mountjoy at an estimated cost in excess of &euro;400 million. New prisons will have reduced operational and maintenance costs. The Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform, with the Prison Service and the OPW, set about acquiring a greenfield site in the greater Dublin area in an open and transparent manner. Up to 30 sites were offered and considered, averaging a per acre price of &euro;200,000 with some sites having a price as high as &euro;500,000 per acre. Despite the protestations of some, nobody has identified to me a 150 acre site within ten miles of Dublin city centre which is suitable for a prison site and which would be available to the Department at a lower price than that which has been agreed for the lands at Thornton near Dublin. Five acres of land with planning permission which formed part of the Thornton farm and which were  retained by the owner have been priced at &euro;1 million per acre by Deputy Jim O&rsquo;Keeffe, the Fine Gael spokesperson on justice. Does anyone seriously suggest the remaining 150 acres could be purchased for &euro;6 million? That suggestion has been made. A local estate agent confirmed recently on the RTE radio programme &ldquo;Five Seven Live&rdquo; that the price paid by the Department was what he would have expected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister is clutching at straws.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>The development of the 150 acre Thornton site will produce a modern prison campus with the appropriate range of facilities and with room for future expansion. It will end the unacceptable practice of &ldquo;slopping out&rdquo; which the inmates of Mountjoy endure. It will prevent drugs being catapulted over the prison walls into the exercise yards. It will make it possible to have a drug-free prison system, which is very difficult at Mountjoy.</P>
      <P>The sale of the valuable Mountjoy site, 20 acres abutting the Royal Canal site in Dublin, could bring in anything up to &euro;100 million. It will go a substantial way towards delivering a modern new prison campus at Thornton. The north inner city will benefit from the redevelopment of the Mountjoy site. There is massive potential for the redevelopment and rejuvenation of this part of our capital city once the new prison campus is up and running.</P>
      <P>I am also moving ahead with plans to develop a new modern prison for the Munster region on Spike Island. As with the Thornton development, <Col N="1036"/>the new prison will provide the range of facilities best suited to meet modern requirements. This prison building programme is aimed at moving us to a situation where, by and large, we will have single cell occupancy within the prison system. I am also extending capacity at the open prisons in Loughan House and Shelton Abbey. As many prisoners as possible should be accommodated in such institutions. I am extending the definition of &ldquo;prison officer&rdquo; in section 9 to allow for the definition to apply to a prisoner custody officer and I am providing for technical amendments in section 10 dealing with prison rules.</P>
      <P Just="Left">With regard to drugs, the replacement of the Mountjoy complex provides a long overdue opportunity to focus on designing drugs out of the prison environment. In line with the drugs policy for the Prison Service, which I will publish shortly, there will be an intensification of efforts in the prison system to prevent the availability of illicit drugs within prisons. This will involve the traditional means of effecting supply reduction and elimination &mdash; staff vigilance, physical searches and supervision of persons entering prisons &mdash; continuing to be reinforced by means of improved facilities and procedures for searches, as well as use of video surveillance and screening in visiting rooms, prison yards and other areas where drugs are likely to change hands.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I will bring forward legislative proposals through the Criminal Justice Bill, this Bill and the new prison rules which will underpin the physical structures being planned for the new prisons. Central to supporting future supply and demand reduction will be the introduction of mandatory drug testing as envisaged in the programme for Government. The new prison rules include specific provision for mandatory drug testing and, in this context, it is intended that later in the year, the Prison Service will commence implementation of a new strategy of mandatory drug testing, addiction counselling and treatment and increased measures to prevent drug usage to provide for a more complete system of rehabilitation.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Drugs in prison are a disaster. There is no point having people in prison if they have access to drugs, other than to protect the public from their presence on the street. There is no rehabilitation if hard drugs are present in prisons and no chance that people will go straight after prison if they emerge from prison with a hard drug usage problem. To those who suggest needle exchanges and sterilising fluid as part of the prison regime I respond with an emphatic &ldquo;No&rdquo;. One can only stop drugs in prison by doing just that, not by tolerating them or having prison officers handing out needles to prisoners in the interests of the prisoners&rsquo; health. That is confused thinking on a moral and practical plane. I wholly oppose it and will not countenance it.</P><Col N="1037"/>
      <P>The introduction of mandatory drug testing or MDT has a number of purposes, namely, to deter drug usage, to identify and treat those who misuse drugs and to provide information on the level and type of drug usage in prisons. That will demonstrate to governors their responsibility and performance targets. It is the responsibility of governors to ensure drugs are not in their prisons. It is a crime if there are drugs in a prison and it is an important part of the function of governors to keep their prisoners safe. Safe in this context means safe from drugs, not safe on drugs.</P>
      <P>In January 2003, I established a committee on video conferencing, chaired by Mrs. Justice Susan Denham, to examine its potential for use for the conduct of trials. An interim report was completed in February 2004 and the final report became available in January 2005. In its interim report, the committee was of the view that the use of a live television link could be of value and that a number of pilot projects should be introduced. However, the committee was satisfied that legislation was required to enable the use of video conferencing facilities in the Irish criminal courts.</P>
      <P>This legislation was prepared on the basis of the committee&rsquo;s interim report which only envisaged its use for pre-trial applications. As currently drafted, section 11 of the Bill provides that a court may direct that specified pre-trial hearings may proceed with the accused not physically present in the court but who may participate by means of a live television link to the prison where the accused is in custody. The court may not proceed with such televised hearings if it would be unfair to the accused or in certain other circumstances where it would not be appropriate, such as proper facilities not being available or issues being too complex.</P>
      <P>The committee in its final report drew attention to the financial benefits of using video conferencing and also pointed to the advantages that had been identified in other jurisdictions, namely, the elimination of the security problems associated with prisoner transportation; the reduction in prisoner transportation costs; a reduction in tension at courtroom precincts by eliminating prisoner movement and waiting in holding cells; allowing prisoners to be released more quickly after a court hearing and the potential to improve the management of court hearings. In the final report the committee recommended that the scope for the use of video conferencing be expanded to include applications during a trial and after a trial.</P>
      <P>The issue of the use of video conferencing in civil proceedings was also addressed in the final report. My officials are in consultation with the Attorney General&rsquo;s office on the additional matters raised in the final report and I intend to bring forward appropriate amendments to the Bill on Committee Stage to reflect those consultations. I wish to signal now, lest anyone thinks I <Col N="1038"/>am ignoring the final report of the Denham committee, that I will expand the terms of this Bill to take full account of it to the extent possible.</P>
      <P>In conclusion, I wish to underline the importance I attach to the provision of modern and humane conditions for both prisoners and staff. For young men &mdash; and they are most frequently sent to prison &mdash; going to prison is a disaster in their lives. Incarceration should be a last resort and should only be used where no other way of dealing with an offender is practical, reasonable and consistent with the maintenance of the rule of law. However, with an expanding population there will be a requirement for a substantial prison estate in Ireland. There is no reason that it should not be of the highest quality. There should be, for example, athletics facilities, football pitches and the like so prisoners can have a rehabilitative experience. There should be space for educational facilities in our prisons. Prisons should not be Victorian hellholes but modern places which are, in so far as is consistent with security, uplifting and enlightening for inmates rather than depressing and dehumanising. If we put the necessary investment in place, we will achieve such standards.</P>
      <P>This Bill, together with the new prison rules and the prison officers&rsquo; agreement on revised work practices, are part of a huge reforming process. We will change the way prisons are run, where they are located and the results that are achieved from the point of view of prisoners. I look forward to hearing Senators&rsquo; views on the Bill and will give careful consideration to the points raised in the debate. I look forward to any proposals in respect of amendments on Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister after his marathon here last night. There will be no objection from this side of the House to the provision of a modern and humane prison service. Many of our prisons urgently require demolition, which will happen in the case of Mountjoy.</P>
      <P>I share the Minister&rsquo;s views on drug free prisons. However, there must be proper rehabilitation and modern medical facilities in the prisons. By all means let there be drug free prisons but the other facilities must also be put in place. There will not be a drug free prison unless that is done.</P>
      <P>The Bill is short and has three objectives, namely, to privatise certain prison escort services, to provide for live video links for pre-trial hearings and to allow the State to close Mountjoy Prison. I am generally in agreement with the Minister on the provision of live video links for hearings. This measure is primarily designed to reduce the number of prisoner transfers to and from the courts, thereby reducing the cost to the State through the use of video conferencing for certain preliminary court hearings. Instead of <Col N="1039"/>being physically brought to court and incurring the necessary expense and security risks, a prisoner can interact with the court by video or television link. We support this provision.</P>
      <P>The use of new technology, especially where it has a proven track record, is welcome. However, it is essential that the prisoner be able to interact with the court, that is, to hear and be heard and to consult confidentially with his lawyer. These matters must be catered for as well. This provision should result in significant cost savings, which is welcome.</P>
      <P>That is more than can be said for the Minister&rsquo;s aim to privatise certain prison escort services. I am glad that agreement was reached eventually with the Prison Officers Association and that the deal incorporates a co-ordinated prisoner escort service, but the Minister&rsquo;s response to privatise the system in his row with the Prison Officers Association was the result of the high overtime bill. His answer was to reduce the prison officers&rsquo; hours by outsourcing prisoner escort services. This has been done in other jurisdictions and no doubt it can save money &mdash; the Minister mentioned a figure of &euro;25 million &mdash; but it could also cost more eventually. What the Minister was suggesting on outsourcing goes directly against the interdepartmental report on staffing and the operation review team, dated July 2002, which states that privatisation of these services will not save money. According to the remarks made by the Minister at the time of publication of the Bill, his motivation in bringing it before the Oireachtas was to allow for a more cost effective and efficient system within the Prison Service, but there is no basis for this belief and the opposite may happen. The bigger problem with this outsourcing and privatising is that the quality of service could decrease when a private company gets its hands on it. Profit will become the primary motive in a situation like that.</P>
      <P>Sections 2 to 7, inclusive, deal with the provision of the prisoner escort service, the certification of prisoner custody officers and their functions, etc. I have grave reservations that the level of security could decrease if this ever happens. As we are dealing with the Bill, as published, we must speak about it. I wonder what will satisfy the Minister as regards the suitability and fitness of the prison custody officer to carry out his or her duties. What checks will be put in place to ensure these people are properly trained and have relevant experience? There is also the intention to issue a certificate of fitness for five years for a prison custody officer. Who is the arbiter on fitness, training, good character, etc.? Will the private contractor or the State be responsible if officers commit human rights violation? Not enough thought has been put into this system. If the Minister could not handle his fight with the Prison Officers Association, he should not have <Col N="1040"/>started it because the taxpayer should not have to pay for the high price solutions. If it comes to that, it could be a high price solution and it is of the Minister&rsquo;s making.</P>
      <P>There is an inherent contradiction in the Minister&rsquo;s actions on the proposed move of Mountjoy Prison to north Dublin, where the prison will be further away from the courts and prisoner transfers will be more expensive and probably more dangerous. Is it intended to provide for a court building near the new prison? Would it make sense to provide for a court building adjacent to the new prison? That could possibly save money in the long run.</P>
      <P>My party has consistently stated that the conditions in Mountjoy Prison are untenable and we have repeatedly called for something to be done about them, but the Minister&rsquo;s responses on the issue have been disjointed and inconsistent. The women&rsquo;s prison, which cost over &euro;18 million and is a good facility, will be knocked down and the State will spend a fortune on Thornton Hall.</P>
      <P>I could speak about Thornton Hall for the next half hour but I have no intention of doing so. The site at Thornton Hall was bought by the Department at considerable cost to the taxpayer. Serious questions were raised about the suitability of the site and the manner of the purchase thereof. The Minister has doggedly stuck to his decision &mdash; he did so again here today &mdash; to purchase this particular site despite the availability of potentially more suitable sites which would be less expensive. No matter what he states, that is the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>Where are they?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>He has also rejected a call for an investigation of the matter to be carried out by the Comptroller and Auditor General. Of what is he afraid? If he is so doggedly pursuing this and making statements like he did today, he should have nothing to fear from an investigation carried out by the Comptroller and Auditor General. We welcome the closure of Mountjoy because the conditions there are appalling but it is a pity that its proposed replacement should be shrouded in such controversy.</P>
      <P>In general, we will be supporting the area of advances in technology and video conferencing. We have reservations about other areas, as I have outlined. I will not dwell any longer on the Thornton Hall issue because the Minister knows my party&rsquo;s position on that matter. We all are in favour of a more modern and humane prison system in the country and we will support the efforts of the Minister and the Government in that regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I, too, welcome the Minister to the House. I am sure he will be relieved to hear that I am supporting the Bill here today.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="1041"/>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>That is a change.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>It is a short Bill. While much more voluminous legislation has come before us, the Bill will make quite an impact due to the changes contained therein. The three issues, which have been outlined by the Minister and supported by Senator Cummins, will have a considerable impact on the operation of prison services.</P>
      <P>The appointment of contractors, which has been discussed here previously, is a good idea. While the Minister has said he does not intend using this provision in the short term, nonetheless it should be in the Bill. In that regard, I note that it was prompted because of difficulties within the Prison Service.</P>
      <P>I would take a different view from Senator Cummins. Within the public services there is an adherence to bad practice, which is often supported by the unions and which is totally at variance with what has happened in the private sector. Unions in the private sector, because of high unemployment and all that occurred during the 1970s and 1980s, in particular, saw that it was only through partnership, working together with companies, that they could ensure the long-term well-being, employment security and improvements in conditions and wages of their own members. Unfortunately, that has been slow in coming to the public service. As a consequence there are headline areas of bad practice. In fact, it is fairly endemic in the public service.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The Prison Service was one of those areas and I compliment the Minister on taking it on. It is not easy. Obviously the nature of politics is that the Minister has the Opposition criticising him for the fact that there is a problem when he is doing his best to ensure that future practice is founded on a more realistic and sensible basis than was the case in the past.</P>
      <P>Undoubtedly the Prison Service had many such difficulties. In fairness to prison officers, who may have been sheltered because of this and may have been beneficiaries of bad practice, it takes a little courage and enlightenment on their part to recognise that and I welcome their support of the changes through the ballot, by two to one. In many ways, it is an example of what can be done in other sectors within the public sector.</P>
      <P>The prison custody officers provision is a good innovation. I note that the Bill includes a provision that certification by the Minister is essential in order to engage people by contractors, who are authorised to do this work. That is a reasonable and prudent precaution. I am not convinced an applicant who is refused would take the appeal course through the courts as that might be too cumbersome. Will the Minister consider the possibility of an appeals officer rather than involve the courts? The courts trundle on and they are just as typical of outdated or bad prac<Col N="1042"/>tice. They need improvement and the removal of any extra workload from them is a step in the right direction.</P>
      <P>The Minister intends that the functions would be in accord with those of prison officers, which makes sense. The person must be capable of performing the duties, undergo training and be a fit person. It is proper that he has built into the legislation a system whereby an officer will be appointed to monitor the contracting arrangements and how they function and to report annually to the Minister in this regard. The purpose of this is to make the system more cost effective. I hope the new procedures within the Prison Service will obviate the need to use this provision, but if it is more cost effective, it should be used.</P>
      <P>It is good to see excessive levels of overtime removed and rationalisation of stores and maintenance arrangements. This is worthwhile and will achieve a saving of &euro;25 million. The elimination of static posts through the use of technology which will allow the redeployment of staff is also welcome. In this regard, it is regrettable that recently our general practitioners, who are extremely well rewarded for spending in some cases just a matter of minutes with patients, obstructed the introduction of the new general practitioner-only medical cards. When the issue was resolved, the IMPACT trade union suggested that because of the increased workload the change involved, it should enter the fray to extract further moneys from taxpayers for its subscribers. That shows a level of detachment from the real world.</P>
      <P>This economy would never have progressed were that type of mentality predominant. That attitude was with us in the private sector in the 1960s and 1970s, but it evaporated because people saw it was counterproductive. The same modern thinking must be introduced into the public service. It is extraordinary that after 16 or 17 years of partnership this has not happened. If it is not provided for in the next partnership arrangement, we should not enter into such an agreement. We must modernise public services and they must be productive. The provision of a computer or extra equipment is no reason for extra payment for public service workers. That does not happen in the private sector nor in any competitive economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I am glad the Senator has changed his views in that regard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>My views on this have been consistent throughout my political life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator&rsquo;s party is not very consistent on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Jim Walsh, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="1043"/>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I recall taking issue with a county manager of some standing 20 years ago with regard to reducing the level of expenditure within the county. I suggested a saving of £100,000 and identified and itemised how that could be done. He took me to task and said that the service to the community in the county would collapse as a consequence of my suggestions. The following year when Fianna F&aacute;il came to power &mdash; when because of the profligacy of the Labour-Fine Gael Government of the time the country was almost bankrupt and the IMF was threatening to come in and take over &mdash; it took strong steps to reduce expenditure. That county council had its expenditure cut by £1 million. I did not have to make any suggestions then about where savings could be made as the county manager was quite happy to identify where they could be made, despite the fact that the previous year the £100,000 saving I suggested would have collapsed the whole service. This discipline must be imposed within the service because it is simply not there.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I welcome the provisions in the Bill that will lead to the probable and earliest possible closure of Mountjoy Prison. Without doubt, it is an outdated, Victorian institution which should not be part of our prison services. People should not be put into the type of situation where slopping-out is part of the daily environment. It is difficult to get people in such conditions to concentrate on rehabilitation. These conditions are demeaning. There is a stark contrast between visits to Mountjoy and visits to the D&oacute;chas Centre, which is a fine modern institution for the retention of offenders.</P>
      <P>I agree fully with the Minister that incarceration should be a last resort. Unfortunately, all too often we see people emerge from prisons, often after relatively minor offences, well equipped to progress to more serious crime. Within prison they have made contact with a network that brings them into a more serious crime regime. We must avoid this. Community service, fines, suspended sentences, restorative justice and court orders restricting movement are alternatives that should be used to make people recompense society and rehabilitate offenders. Prison should be a last resort. The amount of drugs available in prisons must also be counterproductive to achieving any success in rehabilitation of prisoners. The Minister recognises that and I am glad he intends to take more stringent steps in that regard. Hopefully, the construction of a new prison will assist that process.</P>
      <P>I am glad that, arising from the most recent report, the Minister intends to extend the trial use of video links in pre-trial court hearings. I agree with him that video linking should be used to the maximum extent possible. I have some concern with regard to a construction in the Bill which states a court &ldquo;may&rdquo; direct, thereby making the <Col N="1044"/>provision discretionary. I fear interpretation of this by a court will err on the side of caution towards the prisoner. The idea that something is unfair to the accused could be widely interpreted. Will the Minister consider tightening that provision as the Bill proceeds? In a situation where video linking could prejudice the defence of the prisoner, there is sufficient reason it should not be used. If, however, a prisoner just wants to be able to eyeball or intimidate a witness, it is not necessary that he or she is present in the court and a video link would suffice.</P>
      <P Just="Left">There are accompanying costs to the presence of prisoners in court, for example, Garda time. We have had much debate here on Garda resources. Any local superintendent can tell us that on court days large numbers of garda&iacute; are tied up with the courts. Also, because of the inefficiencies within the court system and how it operates, garda&iacute; can be tied up indefinitely and may have to go back on a second day on the same case. This is wasteful of manpower and something must be done in this regard. I compliment the Minister because the use of video-link evidence in trials is a step in the right direction. However, it may not be utilised to its proper extent so I believe that the avoidance of its use should be the exception rather than the rule. Video-link evidence can lead to considerable savings and has been used successfully in other countries.</P>
      <P>I welcome the provisions of the Bill, which will have an impact. The Bill is another step in the essential task of improving the operation, efficiency and cost-effectiveness of the Prison Service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House. This Bill is very interesting. I, like Senator Cummins, will start by examining the use of video-link evidence, which comprises the final part of the Bill. I have witnessed the operation of video-link evidence and read the interim report of Mrs. Justice Susan Denham in respect thereof. I have not read the final report but I believe video-link evidence could be extremely useful.</P>
      <P>Many people have a consultation with their legal advisers before their court appearance. Will these prisoners be able to receive visits from their legal advisers at the prison before giving evidence via video-link? The Minister is nodding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>Teleconferencing visits will also be allowed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
	<P>The physical presence of a legal adviser at the prison where the video-link evidence is to be given is very important. I am not happy with the scenario of the solicitor sitting in his or her office consulting via video-link with the prisoner in prison. Will it entail a considerable amount of travelling by the legal profession? Will lawyers, as opposed to prisoners, be forced to <Col N="1045"/>spend a considerable amount of time travelling around the country in vans? I am sure this matter can be sorted out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I cannot see the legal profession travelling in vans.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
	<P>I am sure the Minister will explain when he replies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>If Senator Cummins had his way, many lawyers might be forced to travel in vans.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
	<P>It is very important that prisoners are able to talk to their legal advisers in person before they give evidence by video link because face-to-face communication is not the same as talking to someone via video link. It is certainly not the same when one is having a medical consultation with someone. I am sure the Minister will give us further information.</P>
      <P>I have no problem, in principle, with private firms running prison escort services but I am anxious that we do not do so simply because it is cheaper. A large proportion of prisoners are violent and dangerous individuals. One prisoner escaped from a hospital at gunpoint recently. The general public should not be put in danger by plans to cut the costs of the prison escort service. Under the new system proposed in the Bill, prison custody officers are to receive training, the amount of which has not been specified. However, we know that prison officers&rsquo; training is not very long. I would like more details regarding the kind of training prison custody officers will receive because they will be involved with violent and dangerous individuals. They will rarely escort those accused of petty crimes.</P>
      <P>Under the terms of the Bill, prisoners can be escorted to places other than prison so violent, dangerous and psychotic prisoners could be escorted to the Central Mental Hospital or other hospitals. Will there be any gradation in cases of which prison officers or prison custody officers will be in charge? It appears from the Bill that both groups will do the same kind of work. There should be a thorough examination of the kind of people prison custody officers will be escorting because I am sure the Minister does not wish to see the public put in danger.</P>
      <P>I can understand the Minister&rsquo;s reason for moving Mountjoy Prison; it is very valuable property. The prisoners will be moved to a site that has been likened to outer Mongolia by some people. I am sure a better prison will be built on the new site; it could not be worse than the current prison. I recently brought some Italian visitors around the current prison and nearly died of shame when we visited the basement. I have visited Italian prisons and one would not see anything like Mountjoy Prison in the Italian system, apart from <Col N="1046"/>the oldest prisons which are kept as ancient monuments. It is a disgraceful prison. I will not address the rights or wrongs of the property that has been acquired for the new prison because I know little about real estate.</P>
      <P>There is a severe shortage of hostels for people released from prison. People frequently object when released prisoners are given houses in their areas. In light of the very large proportion of prisoners incarcerated in Mountjoy Prison, will the Minister promise to build a few hostels for both men and women near the site of the new prison? Some people leave prison and have nowhere to go but the streets. I see that I am making progress on this Bill.</P>
      <P>Under the terms of the Bill, Loughan House and Shelton Abbey will apparently become private prisons. I am not sure if Spike Island will be reopened as a private institution. I was concerned about a report by the prisons inspectorate which recommended privatising some prisons. I do not have a deep-rooted objection to privatising prisons; it would be excellent if it was the better option. However, I have never read a piece of good academic research which examined the merits of private and public prisons thoroughly. Private prisons must be run for profit and it is very difficult when one is looking at the cost per prisoner to find out whether the prisoners were in the same category, given the same treatment or had a lower or higher recidivism rate.</P>
      <P>I am grateful to the Irish Penal Reform Trust for supplying me with information and my researcher, Kasey Cleary, who has carried out research into the US prison service. We must discover the best course of action before we start privatising prisons. If one looks at the US prison service, where there is a considerable amount of privatisation, the costs of running private and public prisons in Iowa are much higher than those in Colorado. One then discovers that pay rates are lower in Colorado and that medical facilities in the state&rsquo;s private prisons are not licensed by the state&rsquo;s Department of Public Health and the Environment. None of us wants to end up with substandard prisons simply because they are cheaper.</P>
      <P>The Minister is aware from my contributions to other debates that I am less than enthusiastic about expanding the Prison Service, which is incredibly costly and has a recidivism rate of nearly 90%. At the same time, our probation and welfare service is pathetically starved of funds. A ridiculous state of affairs exists whereby people are repeatedly given very short prison sentences, which only seem to train them for their return to prison. I query the value of building more prisons. We would be better off using international developments in restorative justice and drugs courts, both of which have been successful in Ireland, rather than developing an enthusiasm for building very expensive prisons. It makes no difference <Col N="1047"/>if they are public or private prisons because private operators must be given subsidies to build prisons so the money must come from the public purse. Public prisons are built directly by the State. I have little enthusiasm for further prison building.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">3 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
      <P Just="Left">The technological improvements in prisons like Cloverhill, such as electronic locking and the use of handprints to facilitate access, have helped to improve the conditions of prison staff. I am glad the Minister came to an agreement with the prison officers, who do a job, especially in Mountjoy Prison, that would not be the choice of many people. I agree with the Minister that the conditions in Mountjoy Prison are outrageous. It is extraordinary to think there was in-cell sanitation in the prison until the 1930s, when someone decided it should be taken away as part of an economy drive. We should be careful when deciding to pursue economy drives. The Minister spoke earlier about confused moral thinking about drug-free prisons. I am sure I was being paranoid when I thought the Minister was looking at me when he made those remarks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I was not referring to the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
	<P>The level of drug abuse in prisons is outrageous. On several occasions, prisoners or their relations have spoken to me about prisoners who did not have any involvement in drug abuse until they went to jail, which is really terrible. I have visited drug-free prisons in other countries, including Maiano Prison in Spoleto, the highest security prison in Italy. Some of the prisoners in that jail have been given sentences of 25 or 30 years. I did not ask what they are in prison for because I did not want to find out. The Minister has placed great emphasis on surveillance and mandatory drug testing, which is all very well, but I am informed that diversion programmes are the most successful way of keeping prisoners away from drugs. I wish the Minister had mentioned education, which is terribly important, in that context. The Minister, for whose support I am grateful, is aware that I am an enthusiastic advocate of the dramatic productions which take place in Mountjoy Prison. Prisoners are keen to point out that those who are involved in such productions, including those who have a history of drug-taking, do not take drugs. We can help to reduce the level of drug-taking in our prisons by getting prisoners involved in more diversionary programmes.</P>
      <P>The last time I visited Mountjoy Prison, prisoners were using machines to sew towels and jeans, etc. We have not returned to the days of sewing mail bags by hand. The prisoners improved their sewing skills when they completed <Col N="1048"/>the big project of making 85,000 flags for the Special Olympics World Summer Games in 2003. If one talks to prisoners, most of whom are so young it is pathetic, they will tell one they would do anything to get out of their prison cells. They are happy to do any kind of work or participate in any form of education. If one goes around the back of the prison, one will see prisoners making paving stones. If one goes to the metal workshop, one will see prisoners working on various metal appliances, such as the frames for park benches. It is somewhat facile, which is a dreadful word to use, simply to talk about mandatory urine testing and surveillance, etc. It is extremely important to encourage prisoners to want to stop taking drugs. Prisoners will give up drugs if they are told they cannot help out with the play, which all of them want to do, if they continue to take drugs. Carrots are frequently more effective than sticks in such circumstances.</P>
      <P>I wish the Minister, Deputy McDowell, well with his proposals in this Bill. It is regrettable that our prisons have been sorely neglected for so long. I do not think the best thing to do is to build more prisons so that we have more prison places. The experience of other jurisdictions should teach us that no matter how many prison spaces are provided, they will get filled. I would like far more money to be invested in the probation and welfare service. I urge caution in respect of some of the Minister&rsquo;s proposals which may mean that things are cheaper, as we have to ensure that things are safer as well. I am sure the Minister would not wish to make any progress without taking safety considerations into account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyKett"><NameTxt>Mr. Kett</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to the House. Like my colleague, Senator Jim Walsh, I assure the Minister that I support his proposals in this legislation. Senator Walsh did not mention that we can hold him responsible in many ways for what happened last night because his substitute during that debate was Senator Cox.</P>
      <P>I welcome the practical Bill that is before the House. As Senator Cummins said, there are three main planks to the legislation. The Minister has chosen to contract out the prison escort service. I applaud the position taken by the Minister on that issue throughout the discussions with the prison officers. He tackled the immoral and unsustainable system that meant that a small number of prison officers could accrue overtime earnings which were greater than their gross pay. I agree that contracting out the escort service to reduce overtime payments is the best way forward. I am sure it will lead to severe cost reductions, thereby benefitting taxpayers. I agree with the Minister&rsquo;s decision to allow for the possible sale of the Mountjoy Prison complex, as provided for in this Bill. The introduction of video conferencing is another laudable and desirable <Col N="1049"/>development that will save the taxpayer considerable amounts of money. It is right that it will entitle prisoners to participate in an orderly way in a decent and humane situation, to develop their potential while they are in prison and to prepare to return to society.</P>
      <P>Mountjoy Prison is located in a part of Dublin that I represented for 17 years on Dublin City Council. My former colleague in this house, Deputy Costello, who also represents that part of Dublin, is an ardent supporter and defender of prisoners&rsquo; rights. When I listened to the D&aacute;il debate on this issue, I was slightly confused to hear Deputy Costello trying to lambaste the Minister. Nobody succeeds in lambasting Deputy McDowell. I found it hard to reconcile Deputy Costello&rsquo;s comments on the possible sale of Mountjoy Prison with his reputation. He spoke about possible archaeological finds as a means of preventing the sale of the prison. I found it odd that the Deputy, who has defended prisoners over the years, was trying to block the Minister&rsquo;s attempts to develop state-of-the-art facilities for prisoners in Thornton Hall. That is the way I looked at it, in any event, and that is the way it came across. Nobody can make a legitimate case against the Minister&rsquo;s proposal to sell Mountjoy Prison, which is an outdated Victorian complex, as the Minister and Senator Jim Walsh have said. The ability of the prison to serve the purpose for which it is used has passed. It is overcrowded and in poor condition. It is badly equipped to deal with the problems which need to be addressed in the prisons system. Anyone who has visited Mountjoy Prison recently will agree that it is depressing and inhumane. I am sure people will argue that the Minister is throwing good money after bad because some necessary improvements have been made to it.</P>
      <P>The people of this country, which has a young population, have much more money in their pockets than ever before. They encounter many opportunities to end up on the wrong side of the law. The Government is dealing with the problems in the justice system by putting more garda&iacute; on the streets and by offering those who end up on the wrong side of the law the humanity of serving their time in decent surroundings. Mountjoy Prison has been criticised by the Council of Europe&rsquo;s Committee for the Prevention of Torture and Inhuman and Degrading Treatment and by the Inspector of Prisons and Places of Detention. People are slopping out in Mountjoy Prison, just as people in ordinary houses had to do at the start of the 20th century.</P>
      <P>Anyone who visits Mountjoy Prison is aware that drugs are freely available there. There are many ways and means of getting drugs into the complex. Prisoners can use their mobile telephones to arrange for drugs to be thrown over the wall of the prison, which is set right against the street. People do not have to use cars or buses <Col N="1050"/>to get to the prison, as they will have to do, more or less, when the prisoners move to their new surroundings, so they can walk to the prison to supply drugs to prisoners. The people of the area around Mountjoy Prison have grown up and lived with the prison without having too many problems with it. The worst thing to happen in the locality was probably the shooting of a prisoner earlier this year.</P>
      <P>A young man was released from prison and shot half an hour later in broad daylight in front of shopkeepers and members of the public going about their business.</P>
      <P>However, by and large, for a complex set in a built-up area in the heart of the city, there were few problems. This should be some comfort to the residents of the Thornton Hall area because few people live close to the site. Its sale will bring about a regeneration of the area which I represented and of which I am very fond. I hope that when the planners develop and regenerate that area, they allow for the building of fewer of the skyscrapers that have begun to appear throughout the city. I am sure Senator Brady, who also represents the area, will be shoulder to shoulder with me in ensuring this does not happen.</P>
      <P>The Mountjoy Prison complex is incapable of serving as a centre of rehabilitation &mdash; it probably never was. Prisoners should no longer have to put up with the conditions there. No more money should be spent on it because that would be financial suicide and the Minister could rightly be held up to ridicule if he did so. The idea of moving the prison makes good sense.</P>
      <P>I understand the concerns of local residents at Thornton Hall. Members have experienced similar local objections in inner cities in regard to the opening of drugs rehabilitation centres by the health boards. We have all attended public meetings at which residents threw their hands in the air and cried wolf. However, they eventually settled down despite the centres being located closer to their homes than the Thornton site will be to residents there. Local residents came around and in the end became quite friendly with some of the individuals being rehabilitated.</P>
      <P>Video conferencing is a terrific idea, so much so that on reading the explanatory information on it, I wondered why it had taken so long to happen. If video conferencing works to an optimum level, it will almost render the first element of the Bill unnecessary, which would be wonderful. I realise it will not be possible to video conference on all occasions and that it will be necessary to take some people to court. However, it will remove the security element, the financial element and other elements that remain a cause of concern.</P>
      <P>This is a fine, practical Bill and I look forward to its implementation.</P>
    </Speaker><Col N="1051"/>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House and wish him well with the Bill. Like Senator Cummins, I will raise several issues which I hope the Minister will clarify.</P>
      <P>Why does the Minister not envisage court services being provided at the proposed site at Thornton Hall? It is a large, 150 acre site with much room for expansion. I would have thought court services would be provided to alleviate some of the issues with regard to the escort of prisoners to and from courthouses that will no doubt arise when the Bill is enacted.</P>
      <P>Will the Minister expand on the contracting out of prisoner escort services? He stated:</P>
      <P LI="1">The proposal for organisational change has been accepted and it incorporates a co-ordinated prisoner escort service operated from within the Prison Service. As this is my preferred approach, I have no plans to contract out the service for the foreseeable future.</P>
      <P FLI="0">However, the Minister proposes to retain sections 2 to 7 of the Bill in case there is a problem. I presume this is in case the Prison Service falls down in its duty and is unable to undertake the service, in which case it would be contracted out. What would happen in the meantime given that prisoners would still have to be taken to court? Would the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na have to take over the service? From my reading of the Bill, I thought contracts would be awarded and that we would have competition for this service. It is clear there will be no competition and that the service will be carried out within the Prison Service. Many prison officers who do not wish to work overtime must do so at present. This will be another function for the Prison Service and additional prison officers will have to be employed to carry it out.</P>
      <P>I agree with the Minister that there is no place for drugs in prisons. Some years ago, the Minister attacked a former Minister for Justice, Mrs. Nora Owen, when he stated she should be able to rid prisons of drugs within six weeks and that if he took over as Minister, he would achieve this within six weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>He did not achieve it in six years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>At least he is trying to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>Since that time, the Minister served a five-year period as Attorney General.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I did not serve as Attorney General for five years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Mr. P. Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>Since then, he has served as Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform for three and half years. I presume that as the Minister gets more familiar with the north side of Dublin, he has come to understand it is not easy <Col N="1052"/>to get rid of drugs, particularly from Mountjoy Prison. Nonetheless, I agree with the Minister that there should be no drugs in prisons. He would have the full backing of almost all persons in the State in his efforts to achieve this end. I would like the Minister to clarify the points I have made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House and welcome the publication of the Bill, which, as Senator Kett noted, has been awaited for some time in our area. I welcome the proposed contracting out of prisoner escorts. Anyone who has visited the accident and emergency unit in the Mater Hospital will know that prisoners being escorted in and out of the hospital in handcuffs and chains are a regular sight. This can be quite intimidating for members of the public, particularly children. I welcome the savings that will accrue from this change, which I hope will come into operation.</P>
      <P>It is in everybody&rsquo;s interest, including that of prisoners, that video conferencing is introduced because it will provide a clear record. I realise that certain questions remain as to its legality but it will certainly be in the interests of the courts, lawyers in particular, because it will save much time and energy which is wasted at present. With the courts and prisons in close proximity in my area, droves of prison officers and garda&iacute; are regularly seen travelling to and from the courts when they could be on other duties. It is a serious waste of Garda time but it also takes two or three prison officers to escort one prisoner for what might be a ten-minute or a full day hearing. Video conferencing is to be greatly welcomed.</P>
      <P>I remember the first time I visited Mountjoy Prison. The atmosphere made it the most intimidating place in which I had ever been. All Members will agree that it was a good idea when it was built in the 1800s. Unfortunately, it has not kept up with the times. Prisoners are still slopping out and padded cells continue to be in use.</P>
      <P>Whatever about the prison&rsquo;s historical element, for many Dublin people it has a sentimental value. Most mornings I meet a man in Drumcondra who tells me about his cousin who is buried in Mountjoy and what he had done in the Rising and the Civil War. However, there are others who will be glad to see the back of it, including its clients. The transfer can be achieved if it is handled sensitively and planned properly.</P>
      <P>Hangman&rsquo;s house has a particular historical significance. Yet many who remember it are passing on and the connections are being lost. In Dublin, there is a strong tradition of handing down stories and family history. As Senator Kett said, Mountjoy Prison plays a large part in the Dublin Central constituency, whether it is through local business, staff using local facilities, vans coming and going or people who attend our clinics visiting relatives there.</P><Col N="1053"/>
      <P>I have visited Mountjoy Prison many times and have several friends on the staff. The work done there is exceptional but much of it goes unrecognised. For example, through the training unit, the inmates supply the children in Temple Street Hospital and others with top quality toys every Christmas. I had the pleasure of seeing a garden for senior citizens produced by the community working parties in a nursing home on the Navan Road. These are the activities we do not hear about. Many of the staff are dedicated to the welfare of their clients. It will be good if this can be maintained in the transfer of the prison. The ethos that has emerged in Mountjoy over the years under many governors, particularly Mr. Lonergan, must be maintained and nurtured.</P>
      <P>I have met the St. Margaret&rsquo;s-Rolestown Action Group and I am aware of the legal and other issues about the proposed site. The group has valid concerns but, if it is dealt with sensitively, the site chosen will be ideal. Some consideration must be given to the location of the mental hospital on the site and the other facilities to be put on the prison campus. The immediate residents have some concerns but with proper and rational consultation these can be addressed.</P>
      <P>We have been anticipating the Bill&rsquo;s publication. As Senator Kett said, it is of particular significance for those of us from the Dublin Central constituency. The Minister and his officials have put much work into properly framing the Bill. If it needs to be tweaked here and there, it can be done on Committee Stage. I wish it every success.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform and the Bill to the House. His predecessor, the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy O&rsquo;Donoghue, began a modernisation programme for prisons and got so far. I am glad the Minister is carrying it forward and is determined to establish humane and modern conditions in our prisons. No Member wants prisoners living in Victorian institutions which, every year, are criticised by prison visiting committees as being substandard. This programme is part of an important reform process.</P>
      <P Just="Left">Until I heard the Minister&rsquo;s speech, I had reservations about the Bill. I would not have been happy if prisoner escorts were to be outsourced and not done by the Prison Service. However, the Minister said his negotiations, although long and protracted, with the Prison Officers Association have been successfully concluded and it is not his intention to activate that provision, provided agreements are carried out in the future.</P>
      <P>The Minister has grasped the nettle of prison officers&rsquo; work practices, conditions, and overtime pay. It was necessary and I am glad that, with the tacit support of most parties in this House, he has brought this to a successful conclusion. It is more efficient for short hearings to be done by video <Col N="1054"/>conferencing without the paraphernalia associated with bringing people under escort from Portlaoise for a several minute hearing in Dublin. This obviously uses up an enormous amount of resources. For proper court hearings such escorts are necessary but they are not for brief formal hearings.</P>
      <P>I applaud the Minister&rsquo;s aspiration to remove drugs from prisons while accepting the practicality of such an exercise will be extremely difficult. There are two attitudes to this question. I pick up, subliminally, an attitude that there should be a liberal tolerance towards drugs in prisons. I am not of that view and agree with the Minister. We have been somewhat lax on this matter over several years, allowing the problem to grow. This matter is part of the justification for a greenfield site.</P>
      <P>I endorse Senator Brady&rsquo;s comments on ensuring the historical dimensions of Mountjoy Prison are catered for. One of the greatest visitor attractions in Dublin is Kilmainham Gaol, a well run site. I draw the Minister&rsquo;s attention to the fact that Spike Island also has significant historical connotations. A few pages in John Mitchel&rsquo;s <i>Jail Journal</i> are given over to it. I ask him to ensure its historic parts are preserved in some way.</P>
      <P>The only regrettable thing about the move away from Mountjoy is that there is a modern women&rsquo;s prison there which cost a significant amount in Government funding. I am sure the Minister and the Government have taken this into account in making a balanced decision to move to a new site. The value of the land is such that the State will not lose money in real terms but it is a matter of some regret that a modern facility built so recently may be discarded.</P>
      <P>There has been much controversy involving the Minister and RTE about the value of the new site being &euro;30 million for 260 acres.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>It is 150 acres.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>I accept that is the market value. I question more generally how we have got ourselves into the position where we have to pay such vast compensation for farmland, be it for a prison or any other public purpose, over and above its normal agricultural value. I was equally shocked that the Railway Procurement Agency had to pay &euro;3 million acquiring back gardens along the southern Luas line. We have a remarkably skewed interpretation of Article 43 of the Constitution, which acknowledges the right to private property, but also states: &ldquo;The State recognises, however, that the exercise of the rights mentioned in the foregoing provisions of this Article ought, in civil society, to be regulated by the principles of social justice.&rdquo; It goes on: &ldquo;The State, accordingly, may as occasion requires delimit by law the exercise of the said rights with <Col N="1055"/>a view to reconciling their exercise with the exigencies of the common good.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Land values 30, 40 or 50 years ago were not remotely what they are today but there was a much more robust interpretation by the State of the public good and social justice. We all remember the Land Commission, which bought good agricultural land in return for land bonds. Some questioned the justice of that policy but I defend it as it represented social justice at the time. If land was required for roads, bog development or agricultural cottages the landowner in question certainly would not have made a profit on it. If anything he would make a loss.</P>
      <P>The courts have got us into a position where having once had a robust notion of the relationship between private property and the social good, we now have an almost unlimited worship of property to the extent that if something is wanted for a public purpose it is worth tens if not hundreds of millions of euro. There is something wrong with these huge windfall profits, and I probably do not represent the views of my would-be constituents on this matter. The Government and the legal profession need to examine this as the balance has shifted dramatically. The Minister has encountered some criticism because we have pushed the rights of private property beyond all notions of sanity and we need to return to a saner view of the public good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><TitleTxt>Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree with Senator Mansergh that private property is sometimes put on a pedestal and the rights of private property are sometimes given too much weight over the public good. As Attorney General I fought over the constitutionality of the social and affordable housing provision in the Supreme Court. The Supreme Court made it clear that the rights of private property were not sacrosanct. There were other rights as well and the Constitution clearly authorised a balanced view on these matters to be taken.</P>
      <P>I could have sent people out to bid at the back of a hall to purchase suitable farms on the sly for the prison I wanted to build. If I had done that I would immediately have been assailed by the community having a prison visited on them for not looking at or asking for anywhere else, instead sending a man in a dirty mackintosh to raise his newspaper at the back of an auction room. The Department impressed upon me that I had to go through a public procurement process, which altered the terms of trade against me.</P>
      <P Just="Left">It has been argued that I could have come before this House and the other House and given myself compulsory purchase powers, in which case I would have been able to identify a piece of land somewhere near Dublin and serve notice in a newspaper that I was taking it. Let us remember <Col N="1056"/>the political realities. It is bad enough to visit a prison on a community but worse still to knock on the door of some farmer in north Dublin and tell him to leave because, in a year&rsquo;s time, I would come and take his farm, his lifestyle and his home in the public interest. If I had gone down that road I would have provoked immense hostility on behalf of a family being thrown out with their possessions on the road saying they were getting agricultural prices for a property I was going to use for non-agricultural purposes, namely, to build a prison.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CyprianBrady"><NameTxt>Mr. Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>They would have to go to the south side.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>It would not be easy to do. I wish to put on the record of this House that of all the land that was offered in that process and adjudged suitable the cheapest was bought. Whatever way one looks at it that is the case although different impressions have been given. If another option had been chosen would this House have congratulated me for saving a lot of money by putting a farming family out on the side of the road by a CPO process? Would this House have congratulated me if I came in here and declared that the only reason I was building a prison in a particular community was that the land came up at the right time for the official I sent out in disguise to purchase it on the sly? Would I have received brownie points for that?</P>
      <P>I was recently in Belfield for a PSNI students Gaelic football match and I reflected on the money that my distinguished uncle by marriage, Mr. Michael Tierney, put into the acquisition of that site. It was a significant sum at the time. The campus in UCD was built and the money spent on it seems worthwhile when one looks at it now. Similarly, the Irish Embassy in Paris on the Avenue Foch is a beautiful building in which I have been lucky enough to stay a few nights. There was an outcry when the building was purchased, although it is worth many multiples of its purchase value now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Dr. Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>It should not be so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I aspire to staying a few more nights there at some stage. I agree with Senator Mansergh in that it is a pity that public procurement of land, especially when there is no CPO power attached to it, and even when there is, ends up with the taxpayer paying top dollar. That is the society in which we live. There is no easy alternative way of doing business without causing much reaction.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The D&oacute;chas Centre is a fine prison building but is already overcrowded. As Minister, I know people are being released early because there is a lack of space. All medical bays, etc., are being used by prisoners already there. Some rooms not <Col N="1057"/>intended for the accommodation of prisoners are already being used. The building is too small. Unfortunately, drugs are introduced into the D&oacute;chas Centre over the wall. As enlightened as the building&rsquo;s architecture may be, its location allows drugs to be thrown over the wall into fine open spaces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>That is another example of bad planning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMcDowellPD"><NameTxt>Mr. M. McDowell</NameTxt>
	<P>I hope whatever replaces the prison will be of an equivalent if not better architectural standard. Those who lament the building&rsquo;s demolition should remember that what I propose to have built in north Dublin at Thornton Hall will be of a similar standard for both men and women, and young people currently in St. Patrick&rsquo;s Institution. That is good news.</P>
      <P>Senator Brady mentioned padded cells. Regardless of what detention facilities are being kept, a programme has been put in place to replace padded cells with modern observation units. By the end of March 2006 padded cells will be eliminated. I have not spoken on this issue in public before, but I witnessed a padded cell on my first visit to an Irish prison. The cell is about four ft. by four ft. or five ft. by five ft., dark and with grey rubber lining and matting on the floor. A pink light gives subdued lighting. In this instance an adult in his 40s was lying in the foetal position wearing only underpants in the cell. The only other item in the room was a plastic pot. The prisoner had been in the position for days as an argument occurred over whether he should be transferred to Dundrum.</P>
      <P>It was a shocking sight to behold. The committee on torture has warned us many times of how wrong these cases are, and I am pleased that such occurrences will be eliminated by March of next year, even in Mountjoy Prison. I am allocating extra funding to that prison to ensure these cells are phased out. No matter what occurs with Thornton Hall, Mountjoy Prison will remain for a number of years yet. No human being should be kept in padded cell conditions.</P>
      <P>Historical points were raised by Senators Brady and Mansergh with regard to Spike Island and Mountjoy Prisons. I am conscious of these matters. Some features of Mountjoy Prison are well worth preserving in an architectural treatment. There are some fine examples of stonework which could enhance a replacement development. The execution shed, colloquially known as the hang house, is a national monument in my opinion even though it is not designated as such. Many of our patriots died on those gallows, and I intend to have them removed to Kilmainham Gaol where they can be erected again and preserved. They are examples of places where people paid the supreme sacrifice for Irish freedom, and <Col N="1058"/>they should not be forgotten or discarded as part of prison modernisation. We recently removed some bodies of the 1916 to 1921 period from Mountjoy Prison to Glasnevin, but remaining graves and monuments will have to be dealt with appropriately.</P>
      <P>The same conditions will apply to Spike Island, which has a graveyard also. It was a place for transportation, and the journals of John Mitchel describe it. A magnificent fortress exists in the centre of the island with impressive architectural features, and there are some interesting Second World War gun emplacements and passageways. There is a range of buildings inside the fortress, some of which have become derelict and roofless, and these must be restored as part of a regeneration project for Spike Island.</P>
      <P>The issue of drugs was briefly mentioned and I thank Senators for their comments. There is a notion abroad, although it is rarely articulated, that prisons are easier to run if a certain amount of drug abuse is tolerated. This is very wrong. New policy in this area will be announced in the near future.</P>
      <P>With regard to escorts, my preference is for a continuation of the present situation, that is, that prison officers as public servants should carry it out. If this becomes economically impossible I must be in a position to provide a legal alternative means. As Senator Mansergh stated, I will put this proposal forward in Bill form while hoping that I will not be forced to use it and that it will be economically viable to provide prisoner transport using public servants.</P>
      <P>We should use CCTV as much as possible. I will not delay the House with the details as we all have a weekend to prepare for, but there is an elaborate plan for a CCTV network. This will involve soundproof cells for consultations between lawyers and clients, and locations from which people can testify and take in what is occurring in court. It makes sense that if a surgeon in Dublin, for example, was required to testify in a personal injuries case in Cork or <i>vice versa</i>, he or she should be able to appear via a televised link to testify before a judge and jury in another place, provided that the interests of justice are properly looked after.</P>
      <P>Such a system will be an essential part of how we develop the criminal justice system. It will also minimise costs from transporting people unnecessarily. For example, a remand prisoner in Portlaoise Prison who is a high security risk might be transported from Portlaoise to Green Street in Dublin, along with a large escort, for a hearing that lasts a short time. If he is remanded for another three weeks, he is driven back, with a colossal amount of money having been spent on the operation. It does not have to be spent.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I agree with the point by Senator Cummins that there should be a courthouse at the new campus. The courthouse in Cloverhill deals with many <Col N="1059"/>procedural cases. One very frequently comes across cases where a prisoner who may be serving two years for burglary, for example, may be in court for unauthorised interference with a mechanically propelled vehicle. Such a person must go with prison officers to the local District Court where the case is pending for a remand hearing, an adjournment or whatever. As that is not a good way in which to do business, it makes sense to bring the courts system to the prisoners for such applications, in so far as possible. As I noted earlier, there is such a facility at Cloverhill Prison.</P>
      <P>I want to thank all the Members for their thoughtful and eloquent contributions to this debate. As far as the comments of Senators Brady and Kett concerning north inner city Dublin are concerned, I believe the end of Mountjoy as a prison facility provides an enormous opportunity. Twenty acres of prime land will become available for a landmark development which will improve north inner city Dublin dramatically. Given the possibility of installing water features on the site which will connect directly to the Royal Canal, architects will drool at the possibilities of developing it. One must also remember that the site value will be colossal compared to the money spent at Thornton.</P>
      <P>Senator Jim Walsh raised the procedure regarding the certification of contractors as suitable people and queried whether the appeals procedure should be conducted through the courts. While an appeal to the courts is a cumbersome method to achieve a result, if one denies people their livelihoods, under the European Convention on Human Rights and as a matter of justice, one must have some form of appeal system. I agree that loading extra work onto the courts system is undesirable. However, we must have some form of independent appeal for people whose livelihoods might be at risk.</P>
      <P>As for the points raised by Senator Henry, I want to assure her that I was not looking in her direction when I raised the point about moral confusion. I take it as certain that someone of the Senator&rsquo;s professional background would regard prisoners having easy access to hard drugs as a complete catastrophe. It is an unspeakable proposition. Whatever the purpose of prison may be, it is not to have people entering the system without a drug habit but emerging with one. That is certainly not one of society&rsquo;s goals for its prison system.</P>
      <P Just="Left">I share the view strongly expressed by a number of Members that we must always regard imprisonment as a last resort &mdash; in particular, because in the main, it is visited upon marginalised young men in our society. As Governor Lonergan has noted, one can examine their postal addresses and almost predict where they will end up from childhood, because of their family circumstances, educational difficulties, bad luck and <Col N="1060"/>the like. It behoves us to have a criminal justice system in which, if possible, people are not sent for short periods into a system which consequently brands them as being unsuitable for many jobs and puts them on the back foot for the rest of their lives. However, we have an expanding population and within 30 years, between 6 and 8 million people will live on this island again, as they did before the Famine. It is naive to believe that we can cut back on our current number of prison spaces.</P>
      <P>The revolving door was a cause of enormous public concern when it existed in the mid-1990s. I accept the Judiciary must play its part in ensuring that people are not inappropriately imprisoned and society must be willing to fund the alternatives, such as probation, supervision, restorative justice, community service and the like. Nevertheless, once public sentiment comes to the point, as it did in the mid-1990s, where it no longer believes that people serve sentences imposed by the courts due to incompetence on the State&rsquo;s part and an unwillingness to run a decent service, the people&rsquo;s sense of well-being implodes. Once the subliminal attitude that people walk out of prison without serving their sentences because of a lack of space takes hold of public opinion, there is enormous cynicism, a sense of desperation and a complete lack of faith in the rule of law as an end in itself.</P>
      <P>I thank the Members for their thoughtful contributions to today&rsquo;s debate. I look forward to Committee Stage, when undoubtedly, this Bill will be improved by a careful line by line analysis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Dr. Henry</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>D&eacute; C&eacute;adaoin seo chugainn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 2 November 2005.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHenry"><NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Mr. J. Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>Ar 2.30 p.m., D&eacute; C&eacute;adaoin seo chugainn.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters">
    <Title>Adjournment Matters.</Title>
  </MainHeading>
  <Line />
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Water and" RHead="Sewerage Schemes">
    <Title>Water and Sewerage Schemes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelKitt"><NameTxt>Mr. Kitt</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank the Cathaoirleach for selecting this matter and the Minister of State for coming before the House. I refer to two issues concerning the town of Ballygar, County Galway, that have been raised with me by many people in <Col N="1061"/>the town and its surrounding areas, namely its water supply and sewerage system.</P>
      <P>As far as the water supply is concerned, major concerns have been expressed about its quality, colour, taste and content. Concerns have also been expressed about the amount of chlorine and other additives in the public water supply. As far as the reserve supply is concerned, the pumps are not working. What plans are there to upgrade the water system? I understand the proposed scheme will require a new source and note from my discussion with Galway County Council that the scheme is listed in eighth place on the council&rsquo;s assessment of needs in respect of water schemes. It is not actually included at all in the water services investment programme. Perhaps the Minister can confirm my hope that it can be included in the next rolling programme from the Department.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">4 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
      <P>As for the sewerage system, it is difficult to envisage any development in this town given its sewerage scheme is so poor. There have been many complaints about the smell from the treatment plant and one cannot have development without adequate sewerage and water supply. Hence, I want to see some progress on this matter. According to the county council&rsquo;s assessment of needs in respect of sewerage schemes, the scheme is in 17th position, but is not included in the water services investment programme. These two issues are very important and I hope the Minister of State will indicate what will happen regarding the water and sewerage schemes in Ballygar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelAhern"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Mr. N. Ahern</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank the Senator for raising this issue. The provision of modern environmental infrastructure to support social and economic objectives has been a major focus of Government spending over the past number of years. Towards this end there has been unprecedented investment by the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government under the national development plan on water and sewerage schemes, which has made a key contribution to the economic growth that has benefited every part of Ireland.</P>
      <P>My Department&rsquo;s Water Services Investment Programme 2004-2006 was published in May 2004 and includes over 60 different schemes for County Galway with a value of over &euro;445 million. Towns and villages such as Athenry, Ballinasloe, Barna, Carraroe, Clifden, Glenamaddy, Headford, Milltown, Oughterard and Tuam can all look forward to new and upgraded sewerage schemes. Many areas have also benefited from improved water supplies, such as Carna-Kilkieran, Tuam and Headford. There are new regional water supply schemes for Gort, Ballin<Col N="1062"/>asloe, Clifden, Loughrea, Dunmore-Glenamaddy and Portumna.</P>
      <P Just="Left">When selecting individual projects for approval in the water services investment programme, my Department takes into account the priorities identified by Galway County Council. Ballygar was in eighth position on the list of water schemes and 16th on the list of sewerage schemes submitted by the county council in response to the Department&rsquo;s 2003 request for local authorities to produce updated and prioritised assessments of new infrastructural needs in their areas. These assessments are the main input in the approval of individual schemes by my Department for Exchequer funding. Given the prioritisation made by the council, along with the high level of competing demand for the available funding, it was not possible to include the Ballygar proposal in the current water services investment programme.</P>
      <P Just="Left">However, the current programme is part of an ongoing three-year strategy that has rolled forward at regular intervals. Further schemes will be added to future phases of the programme in line with the prevailing priorities identified by the local authorities. In light of what Senator Kitt has said about health considerations, colour, taste and content, Galway County Council may review the current priority ratings of the Ballygar schemes with a view to moving them further up the lists. If this were to happen, it would improve their prospects of being included in the investment programme. Senator Kitt can be assured that the points he made this evening will be taken into account in this context.</P>
      <P>The future of these proposals in Ballygar is very much in the hands of Galway County Council. If it decides that they should be given greater emphasis within its overall list of priorities, their prospects of securing funding under the water services investment programme will be correspondingly enhanced. Perhaps the concerns raised by the Senator regarding content and colour are new. While the Department may make the final decision, it depends on the list of priorities sent forward by the county council. As of the last time it was asked for a list, Ballygar did not feature very highly. I am sure the Senator will use his good offices at county council level to make these points. If it reprioritises, the Department will do its best to allocate funding.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Waste" RHead="Management">
    <Title>Waste Management.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Mr. Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State for attending the House. The Irish Farm Films Producer Group, IFFPG, collected over 12,500 tonnes of plastic farm film from farmers in the first eight months of 2004. There is a great demand from farmers for these collections but the scheme has ceased until next year due to insufficient funding. The volume of plastic film <Col N="1063"/>collected last year represented an increase of 47% over the previous year and 50% above the Government agreed target for 2005. The total amount forecast for 2005 is double the 2004 figure of 8,500 tonnes and there is a great response from the farming community, which is anxious to deal in a responsible way with its used film. Its members must be complimented on this.</P>
      <P>The IFFPG has exceeded its budgeted targets and suspended collections in September. Farmers must now store the waste plastic film until collections resume. The industry must receive credit for its efforts to eliminate pollution and protect the environment and it is essential that these collections resume as a matter of urgency as a backlog currently exists. From an environmental point of view, this is unacceptable and I ask that the Minister of State does his utmost to ensure this problem is dealt with soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelAhern"><NameTxt>Mr. N. Ahern</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator Cummins for raising this issue. The Waste Management (Farm Plastics) Regulations 2001 require manufacturers and importers of farm plastics to take steps to recover farm plastic waste they have placed on the market or contribute to and participate in compliance schemes to recover the waste in question. A farm plastics recovery scheme has been operated by the IFFPG since 1997, which is currently the sole approved body in Ireland for the purposes of implementing a compliance scheme for the recovery of farm plastic waste. Established with the support of the Irish Farmers Association and comprising representatives of film manufacturers and importers, the IFFPG has achieved significant success in the recovery of waste farm plastics.</P>
      <P>The 2001 regulations, which replaced the previous regulations made in 1997, reinforce the operation of the scheme by imposing various obligations on manufacturers and suppliers in respect of the collection and recovery of farm plastics placed on the market, such as bale or silage wrap. Under the regulations, a producer of farm plastics has the choice of either complying with the regulations directly or participating in the approved scheme. Under the IFFPG scheme, producers <Col N="1064"/>currently pay a levy of &euro;127 per tonne on the sale of farm plastics, which in turn is transferred to the IFFPG for use in funding the collection and recovery of farm plastics waste. Manufacturers and importers who do not participate in the approved scheme are required under the regulations to operate a deposit and refund scheme equating to a deposit or refund of &euro;254 per tonne of farm plastic purchased and returned for the collection and recovery of waste plastics as well as comply with other onerous reporting requirements to local authorities.</P>
      <P>The IFFPG is a not-for-profit organisation and it is a matter for the company to set a rate of levy that will cover its operational costs under the terms of this producer responsibility initiative and in accordance with the polluter pays principle. The scheme has operated successfully to date and I note the Senator&rsquo;s comments that he and the farming community are generally happy with it. It is estimated that approximately 8,500 tonnes, some 55% of farm plastics placed on the market in 2004, were collected for recycling. An estimated 55,000 farmers availed of the collection service in 2004 and the IFFPG estimated that over 12,500 tonnes of farm plastics have been collected in 2005.</P>
      <P Just="Left">The IFFPG estimates that more than 12,500 tonnes of plastics have been collected this year. Responsibility for the collection and recovery of farm plastics rests with the compliance scheme, which my Department monitors on an ongoing basis. The Department is aware of the specific issue raised, as it is in regular contact with the IFFPG and is anxious to preserve and continue the success of the farm plastics scheme. These discussions continue to explore options for improving the scheme, and a resolution of this and other outstanding issues. I understand the Department met the group recently and suggestions were made on how to deal with this matter. Perhaps a large amount of imported plastics, which may not fully pay the levy, came onto the market. The group proposed some ideas which will be examined in an effort to make the fund self-sufficient next year.</P>
      <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 4.05 p.m. until<?oasys _jy?>2.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 2 November 2005.</adjournment><Col N="1063"/>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <?oasys _te?>
</Debate>
