<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="3" Month="May" Year="1935" Vol="56" No="3" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 3 Bealtaine 1935" DateEnglish="Friday, 3 May 1935" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="325">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="325" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business of" RHead="the Dáil">
    <Title>Business of the Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Ruttledge) Minister for Justice (Mr. Ruttledge)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Ruttledge)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Items 6 (Pigs and Bacon Bill, 1934) and 7 (Estimates, omitting 52 to 62, inclusive), and 8 (Local Government (Temporary Provisions) (Amendment) Bill).  There will be no private business at 12 o'clock. It is proposed to adjourn at 2 p.m. until 5 p.m. on Tuesday, 7th inst., and to meet on Wednesday, 8th inst., and Thursday, 9th inst., at 5 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it proposed to meet on Friday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>I think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The statement has been made that Private Deputies' time will not be allowed to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That Public Business be not interrupted at 12 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that by agreement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the President (Mr. Little) Parliamentary Secretary to the President (Mr. Little)">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the President (Mr. Little)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is always done at this time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Why does the Minister say that Private Deputies' time will not be allowed?  Surely he ought to propose that it be not allowed?  The Minister, so far as I know, does not order the procedure of the House.  I want to know if there is agreement between the Whips as to taking Private Deputies' time?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government orders the business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="326" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government propose the business, and the Dail disposes.  We could have a division on this question but I do not want to have it.  I merely want procedure to be attended to.  The Government does not order the business.  That should be understood.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has been counting the members of his Party on his fingers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall make a surplus out of a non-existent thing if the Minister likes.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Bank of Ireland Bill," RHead="1935&mdash;Report of Joint Committee">
    <Title>Private Business. - Bank of Ireland Bill, 1935&mdash;Report of Joint Committee.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I move&mdash;&ldquo;That the Report do lie upon the Table.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Ordered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I move&mdash;&ldquo;That the Report and Minutes of Proceedings be printed.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Ordered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Pigs and Bacon" RHead="Bill, 1934&mdash;Fifth Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Pigs and Bacon Bill, 1934&mdash;Fifth Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has not seen fit at this stage to make any further comment on the Bill than move that it do now pass.  It is right that the House should consider for a moment the situation created by this Bill.  Admittedly, under the situation created by British quotas, it has been necessary to produce some legislation in this country to organise our industry for the new trade conditions that obtain.  As a provisional measure, I think that this Bill is worth a trial, though, if the quota system continues in Great Britain, the Minister will find, as I told him on the Second Reading, that, whether he likes it or not, he will be driven a step further and find himself under an obligation to register all pig producers and to control the supplies of pigs.  That suggestion <Col N="327" /> naturally raises the question of why that necessity should arise.  It arises for the reason to which Deputy Smith referred last night.  It arises for the reason about which Deputy Smith got hysterical last night.  If production is to be regulated, it must follow that the obligation will devolve upon the Government of providing an economic price for the producer.  If there is an economic price for pigs at the present time, as Deputy Smith pointed out, every man in the country, engaged in agriculture, will get into the production of pigs.  Deputy Smith, however, does not seem to have gone on to ask himself why would an economic price for pigs at this juncture drive every farmer in the country into the production of pigs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Because it would be the only thing that would be economic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Exactly&mdash;because it would be the only thing that would be economic&mdash;and that is what Deputy Smith forgot.  The Minister for Agriculture and Deputy Smith explained that it was unthinkable to fix an economic price for pigs; that it was highly desirable, nay, essential, that from time to time there should be an uneconomic price for pigs in order to prevent people from producing.  Both of them forgot that, in stating that, they were admitting that between them they had rendered every other branch of agriculture uneconomic, with the result that if you present an opportunity to a farmer of making money with certainty in any branch of agriculture, every farmer in the country is going to go into that particular branch.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Is not that a nice commentary on three years' agricultural administration by Fianna Fáil? In 1931 there was no restriction on the price of pigs, nor was there any restriction on the production of pigs.  There was no restriction on the production of cattle and no restriction on the production of sheep.  There was no restriction on the production of any crop&mdash;roots, cereals, or anything else.  Every farmer was free to engage in whatever branch of agriculture he found most suitable to his own particular district. <Col N="328" /> Every man was free to make money out of whatever particular branch of agriculture he wanted to engage in. But now Deputy Smith and the Minister for Agriculture have come to the conclusion that if you provide an economic price for the farmers of this country in the production of pigs, every farmer in the country will go into that line of production, and, as Deputy Smith said, it is highly desirable that from time to time farmers will not be able to get an economic price&mdash;that the principle of this Bill is that from time to time they will not get an economic price.  It is only when the full significance of that admission began to dawn upon his own mind that he lost his temper and began to threaten physical violence against any Deputy in the House who dared to refer to it. I do not blame him.  It is a damaging admission.  It is one of the most striking and sensational admissions that has been made from the Fianna Fáil Benches since the full horror of their own disruptive policy has begun to dawn upon them.</P>
    <P>The sooner Fianna Fáil make up their minds to face facts, the better it will be for the country and the better it will be for themselves.  They have got to mend their hand in such a way that farmers in this country can earn a livelihood by their own exertions, without subsidies or doles from the Central Fund of the State.  In the meantime, if they are going to regulate an industry such as the pig industry by a Bill such as the Pigs and Bacon Bill, they have got to make up their minds to this: that justice demands that if industries are to be subsidised indirectly by tariffs, if certain branches of agriculture suitable to certain districts in the country are to be subsidised, such as beet and wheat, then a duty devolves upon the Government which is responsible for these subsidies to guarantee for the farmers who are engaged in the production of pigs, not an exorbitant price, but a mere economic price; in other words, the cost of production plus the barest margin of profit that will enable the farmers to carry on.  In so far as they fail to do that in this Bill, this Bill falls <Col N="329" /> short of what the agricultural community are entitled to expect.</P>
    <P>I have not the slightest doubt that after the lapse of a very short time they will find themselves forced by the strength of public opinion to provide the economic price that I have urged them to provide in that amendment of mine which was rejected yesterday. In the meantime, however, let them learn the lesson which emerges from their own apprehensions.  Their present fear is that if you provide an economic price for pigs, that is, the cost of production plus the barest margin of profit, all the year round, for pig producers, every farmer, in the country will go into the production of pigs and there will be such an enormous production that it will be wholly impossible to handle it.  They realise that the reason why that apprehension is well-founded is because they themselves have bankrupted every other branch of agriculture and that to-day there is no branch of agriculture in which a farmer can earn a decent livelihood except those branches which are directly subsidised by the Government. Admittedly, by increasing the subsidy on beet, or wheat, you can make it profitable for anyone to produce it.  You can make it profitable to produce pineapples or grapes by the same methods.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Or tea.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Or tea. Yes, you can grow tea here if you raise the subsidy high enough to permit every farmer to erect glass-houses and grow the tea under the same conditions as you would be able to grow it in, say, the Botanical Gardens.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Deputy relate tea-growing to pig production?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, Sir, because the prudent and perspicacious Minister for Agriculture in the Fianna Fáil Government seems to think that crops analogous to tea are very much better for our farmers than the crops that the natural resources of this country make it possible to produce.  The Minister <Col N="330" /> seems to prefer any kind of subsidised crop to the ordinary products of the Irish agricultural industry and it is being suggested to us by the Fianna Fáil Party that these subsidised crops &mdash;these artificial products&mdash;are preferable to the natural products of the Irish agricultural industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>And pig production?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Precisely.  It is the realisation, the slow dawning of a realisation on the minds of Fianna Fáil that they are running the whole agricultural industry into bankruptcy, that makes Deputies like Deputy Smith hysterical when he suddenly discovers it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, now, that is not what makes Deputy Smith hysterical. He is naturally that way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, it makes his hysteria bubble over, and when he realises what he has done his remedy, instead of thinking and trying to apply his mind to the problem and realise what his duty is in order to remedy the damage he has done, is to get up and threaten to knock the heads off his colleagues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>Was it heads you said?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That reflects little credit on the public life of the country and it reflects little credit on Deputy Smith himself, but the Deputy is silly himself, because he does not know how to remedy his own shortcomings.  My suggestion to Deputy Smith to-day is that, instead of talking about knocking the heads off his colleagues, he should go home to Cavan and consult his neighbours&mdash;sensible men earning their living on the land every day&mdash;who would give him a little commonsense instruction in the ordinary fundamentals of agricultural economy.  They will tell him that there is no branch of agriculture in which they can earn their living to-day unless they get some kind of dole or subsidy from the central Government. That is the reason why he rightly apprehends that if an economic price <Col N="331" /> is paid for pigs every farmer in the country will go in for the production of them.  Let the Fianna Fáil Party dwell on that question and, when they have realised what the measure of the disaster is that they themselves have brought on the agricultural industry, let them mend their hand and get markets for our people where they can dispose of their agricultural surplus profitably.  If they do that they need not be one bit uneasy about ensuring an economic price for pigs because the ordinary rules of economics will operate, and only those farmers who cannot make a better profit out of some other branch of agriculture will go in for the production of pigs.  If they do that, then we will be back on the sound economic ground that every farmer will produce economically the crop that he is best able to produce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Set that to music.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And you will croon it for him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>He will dance to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>When we have established that system we will be back again on solid ground and to a line of policy that will make it possible for the people of this country to live decently and not to be paupers begging from the Government the right to live, and begging Government doles in order to make it possible for them to make ends meet.  Until we get on to that solid ground there is no use bawling about a republic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has referred to the three years agricultural policy of the Government.  The agricultural policy of the Government is not under review.  The question is: That the Bill before the House do now pass.  The Deputy must relate his remarks to that Bill which, he must realise, is far removed from the question of a republic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>He cannot because he has to let off the gas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Fianna Fáil have argued that you cannot give an economic price for pigs because, they say, if you do <Col N="332" /> every farmer in the country will go in for the production of pigs.  I think they are right at the moment because every other branch of agriculture fails to yield a profit.  If every other branch of agriculture did yield a profit there would be no danger of everyone going in for the production of pigs because many farmers would much prefer to engage in other branches of it.  My concluding submission is that there is no use talking about political independence or any other form of independence unless men have economic independence and the ability to make a living on their own land, and while we are bawling about a republic we at the same time&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Chair decides that the question of a republic or other form of government is not relevant then it is not relevant, and the Deputy should not endeavour to come around to that question by some other form of words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall eschew further reference to the republic.  I say that you are sapping the economic independence of the country and that you are making it impossible for any man to earn a living on his own land without going hat in hand to the Government asking for doles and assistance.  I say that is demoralising our people.  I say that that system of universal pauperism that you are forcing on our people is destroying the morale which they have built up during the last 50 years since they became the proprietors of their land.  I think that the Government ought to realise, and address themselves to the task of restoring that economic independence to our people that the Land League got for them.  The only way you can do that is by making it possible for them to earn a living by their own exertions without doles and assistance from the Government.  When the Government have wakened up to that fact they will realise that Government subsidies are no remedy for destroying markets in which our people could earn a living without any subsidy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The curer gets his profit on bacon under this Bill; the jobber gets his <Col N="333" /> profit on the sale of pigs, and the retailer gets his profit on the bacon he sells.  That is all provided for in the Bill.  There is provision for the jobber's allowance, for the curer's allowance and for the retailer's allowance. The only individual in this Bill for whom no provision is made in the way of an economic price is the man who produces the pig.  Surely that is a paradox.  I leave it to Deputy Smith and to the Minister for Agriculture to explain why it is that it is safe and prudent to provide for a profit for the curer, the jobber and the retailer, but that it would be a desperately dangerous thing to ensure that the producers of pigs should get an economic price all the year round.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot compliment the Minister on the quickness of a right decision.  Even though we pulled him a bit of the way yesterday&mdash;he acknowledged it himself&mdash;I am sorry that he was not quicker in coming to the decision, which I am sure he will come to later, of granting the substance of the amendment that was put forward yesterday.  But I must compliment him on the speed with which he got out this huge Bill and had it in our hands this morning.  It shows that in the opinion of the Minister there is great urgency in this matter.  I wonder. I think it is common ground that it was the British quota system that prompted the regulation of the pig industry here as well as in Holland and Denmark.  Is there need for such violent expedition to rush this Bill through in face of the generally accepted statement in Britain that they are going to reverse their policy as regards quotas and substitute levies instead?  It will be agreed, I think, that if the British were to say &ldquo;No more quotas but levies on pigs&rdquo; there will be very little need for the machinery that is to be set up under this Bill.  However, I will pass away from that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under this Bill you have certain people classified as minor curers.  That is to say, curers no matter how long they have been in business and no matter how efficiently they have worked <Col N="334" /> their little businesses, if for any reason they are not in a position to expand their business, then they will go out of business in two years' time. That will be their position if their business does not exceed the curing of bacon of, I think, 2,000 pigs a year. At the Special Committee a strong case was endeavoured to be made for compensation for those minor curers who will have to go out of business. Of course they will have two years, and during that period they are going to have an opportunity of expanding their business beyond the boundary line that classifies them as small curers under this Bill.  If they do succeed in expanding their business beyond that line they will be allowed to carry on. I hope that whoever will be dealing with the matter two years hence, if at that time there is any need to have this measure in operation, will endeavour to keep those minor curers in business.  After all, they filled a useful purpose in the past.  Some of them, I know, are 30 years in the business and if you put them out of that business, you might as well put them on the dole.  It cannot be written into the Bill&mdash;it would not be fair from the plan of the Bill to have it in&mdash;but I hope the Minister will create an atmosphere in his Department by which in respect of those who will not qualify as small curers at the expiration of the period of two years, some other means&mdash;perhaps a lower qualifying standerd &mdash; might be devised to keep them in business.  We have all got literature from one small curer in particular and I have got his entire case firsthand. It is really a case of a very industrious man who cannot get any further in the business owing to various circumstances over which he has no control, and I dare say that as good a case could be made for others.</P>
    <P>I was sorry the Minister could not make up his mind on having one board, or, at least, the Pigs Marketing Board, which for all practical purposes is a joint board and that he did not give that Joint Board the function of making an order for a production period or for the production of bacon. <Col N="335" /> We had enough to say about that yesterday, without taking up too much time to-day, but I want to make this quite clear, as I think it is the position that no matter who argued for or against the Pigs Marketing Board having the right to make this order, nobody made the case that the making of the production order does not affect the price of pigs.  It was accepted all round that it does affect the price of pigs.  I think the Minister has accepted it&mdash;I am sure that, as an intelligent man, he must accept it.  Having accepted that, I have no doubt that when he considers the position finally and before this Bill is disposed of in the Seanad, he will see the justice of giving the Pigs Marketing Board the right to decide on the production order. He will find that it is good policy to do it, because even though there are what might be termed safeguards in the Bill, in the case of the Bacon Marketing Board, they have the right under the Bill to go into the manufacture of bacon as a Board and so have the Pigs Marketing Board.</P>
    <P>I think the Minister does not intend the exercise of such right by either of the two Boards by way of correcting the policy of either or both Boards or correcting the policy of the bacon curers or pig producers.  It is, I take it, only machinery devised as auxiliary machinery in case such auxiliary machinery is necessary.  The Minister has said&mdash;I do not know if he has said it here, but he said it in the Special Committee&mdash;that that right of the Pigs Marketing Board to go into the business of curing bacon would be necessary in case any bacon factory had been burned down and the other factories had enough to do to handle their own quotas.  That is a good precaution, but I think it would be very bad if the Pigs Marketing Board, in order, so to speak, to give one in the eye to the Bacon Marketing Board, set up in the business themselves.  The way to avoid any hostility between the two Boards or between the pig producers and the bacon curers is, in my opinion, to have all interests represented where <Col N="336" /> business concerning all interests is being done.</P>
    <P>If the Minister acts on that principle and looks on those sections that give the Bacon Marketing Board and the Pigs Marketing Board the right to manufacture bacon, as useful only as auxiliaries to the whole industry rather than as a corrective of a wrong policy by some other board, he will at once see the justice, the feasibility and the efficiency of giving the Pigs Marketing Board the right to make a production order.  There is another matter he might consider in relation to Section 98, sub-section (4), which says:&mdash;</P>
    <P>In making a production order the Board shall have regard to the following matters, namely...</P>
    <P>(d) the supply of pigs likely to be available.</P>
    <P>This Bill is handicapped right from the beginning, because that supply is the pivot of the whole Bill.  I submit the Minister has provided himself with no machinery in this Bill, or anywhere else that I am aware of, that would be any way reliable in fixing the production order.  He will want to have a fairly close idea of the number of pigs maturing within the production period, and if he does not know that number of pigs, how can he make a production order that is of any use?  Unless he has a method of counting those things, he will not know how many he must make provision for.</P>
    <P>I suggest to him that is the pivotal paragraph of the whole Bill.  It affects the amount of bacon that is to be cured and the price to be fixed for pigs.  I really do not see any way out of registration, but, however, it is past the time for suggesting what should be in the Bill.  I understand we are confined to discussing what is in the Bill. Deputy McGovern is terribly afraid that if you register pig producers they will be conscripted, or something like that.  What harm is it? No man is ashamed to have his name down as feeding 20 or 30 pigs.  If this machinery is to be of any use, it should be as near perfection as possible, and unless we have that detail fairly accurate, I do not see how the machine can be very well worked.  Surely if one county <Col N="337" /> feeds 100,000 pigs in the year, and the other county 20,000, the 100,000 county has a right to a bigger voice in the industry.  The only way the other county can knock it out is by beating it in pig production.</P>
    <P>I agree with the arguments used by Deputy Dillon about an economic price. I also agree that if an economic price were fixed we would all run into pig production.  I have peculiar notions of my own about prices.  I work for as good a price as I can get, but work would not have half the fascination for me if I knew exactly the price I was going to get.  I do not agree with fixing prices at all.  I like an element of sport about working for prices.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Something like 6 to 4 or 5 to 1.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not bet.  I never put a bob on a horse in my life.  But if you know exactly where you are going it takes the whole spice out of life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>The farmers cannot afford to be sportsmen in existing circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I want conditions that are potentially economic, but I do not want conditions where it can be said: &ldquo;Go on, produce pigs, you will get £3 apiece for them at a certain weight.&rdquo; You are sure of that and you will eventually get fed up with it and get sick of running in a straight line like that.  There is nothing like an element of risk.  That is the only thing that is worth having in life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a bad phrase for a politician&mdash;getting tired of running in a straight line.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>There are not many straight political lines in this country. I do not think Euclid was a politician.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have a mathematical President at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Euclid was not a politician because if he were he would never define what a straight line was.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Deputy a question with regard to his view on fixed prices, with which I largely sympathise? If the Deputy says he does <Col N="338" /> not want to produce to a fixed price, I sympathise with him.  But, suppose he is told that the raw materials of his industry are going to have their price fixed by another man&mdash;for instance, under the Cereals Act the price of the raw materials of the pig industry are fixed by the Minister from time to time &mdash;surely then he would feel inclined to say: &ldquo;If you are fixing the price of raw materials you must also fix the price of my finished product in order to secure that my profit will not be taken from me in the event of your raising the price of the raw materials.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy refers to the debates on the Cereals Bill he will find that I laboured that point more than all the other Deputies in the House put together.  The raw material dictates the price of the finished article. The price of corn used for pig feeding is being regulated in the machinery we are now passing and it does not matter what price the Minister by Order may fix.  We pass the pig through the machinery provided by this Bill and what we get for the article when it comes out of that machine will regulate the price down the whole line.  Let us take things as they are.  The Minister supported the other policy, but the Minister is not responsible; the whole Government is responsible.  It is the Minister's duty to put up the Pigs and Bacon Bill.  He must produce it in the circumstances in which he finds himself. I am not defending the Minister, but I am looking at this as if I were given the job, circumscribed as he is and considering what I would have to do in those circumstances.  Let me put this to the Deputy.  Should the Minister fix an economic price, knowing that if he did our markets will be oversaturated with pigs in six months and that, though you had nominally an economic price for your pig, you had in fact no price at all?  Is not that the position we would reach?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If we had an unlimited market for pigs I agree that you should fix an economic price.  Let us take the British quota.  If we exceed that, what will we do with our pigs?  We come up against a barrier.  We can pile up our pigs until they cross that <Col N="339" /> barrier and when they cross that barrier they are lost.  What is before the Minister, as I see it, is that if you fix an economic price you may be sure that in six months' time we will be producing too many pigs. Then he has no alternative but to issue cards as in Denmark and Holland and each potential feeder will apply for a licence to feed so many pigs.  Allocations would then have to be made.  In Denmark a farmer is feeding so many pigs under licence at a fixed price and he is feeding other pigs under licence at nowhere near that price at all, merely taking his chance.  Where prices are fixed on the basis of getting a quota in the British market they are three or four times higher than the prices in the case of other pigs.  There is no difference whatever in the pigs and the only point is that there is a market for one pig and no market for the other.</P>
    <P>We will have plenty of time on the External Affairs Vote and the President's Vote to say all we like about the economic war, and I intend to say a good deal about it.  What is before us now is the question whether it is better to have an economic price with over-production practically immediately, the card system and limitation of production, or is it better to fix a price, bearing in mind the considerations set out in Sections 98, 139 and 140?  It is better to fix a price according to them.  If the number of pigs grows or if the outlet for bacon is diminished, then prices will have to be scaled down and you will come to a point where the working of the economic law, restricted a bit here I admit, will operate.  Which are we going to have?  Personally, I prefer what is in the Bill.  I agree with what the Deputy has said, that if we get an economic price for the production of pigs we will rush into that because nothing else is economic.  I agree also that you cannot fix the raw material of an article at an inflated price and expect to sell the finished article in competition.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOLeary" hpid="Mr. O'Leary Mr. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be educating the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="340" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing that educates a man like an empty stomach, and we are travelling pretty fast on that road.  Frankly, I prefer the machinery in relation to price fixing that is in the Bill, for the simple reason that we cannot pay an economic price. At the Pig Tribunal I think the Minister was drawn a bit to attach too much importance to this point, that is, that one season of the year&mdash;dividing, as he did, the year into two parts&mdash;there are more pigs produced than in the other part, and that in that period in which the greater number of pigs is produced the price is low.  I submit for the Minister's consideration that even if the price is low, that price gives a better return to the feeders than at the other period when the price is high. The <i>prima facie</i> proof of that is in the fact that even though that price has been regularly low in the past and in the present, people will continue to feed more pigs during that season knowing well that they will also continue to sell their pigs at a lower price than in the other season.  But even though pigs are sold at a lower price in this season the fact is that the economic price is actually higher than in the season when pigs are fetching a higher price.  The proposal in this Bill giving power to the Pigs Marketing Board, which is, in fact, a Pigs and Bacon Marketing Board, to correct what are really economic forces will not work.  This is called a Pigs Marketing Board, but, as I said, it is a Pigs and Bacon Marketing Board. This deludes people into calling it a Pigs Marketing Board.  There are Pigs and Bacon men on it.  It is really a Joint Board.  The Bill would be a better Bill if it had not that power at all.  I hope if the Minister does not see his way to cut that power out of the Bill he will discourage its use, because he has the power to do so.  In conclusion, I wish to say that I hope the Bill will be a success, but I have my doubts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to say that Deputy Belton has very effectively replied&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;to the Deputy's very gentlemanly comment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="341" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;to the statement and misrepresentation made by Deputy Dillon both yesterday evening and to-day. He has made a great plea in connection with the fixing of an economic price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Knock your feeders' heads off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Belton has quite rightly pointed out that this House and those who want to consider this proposition seriously and those who wish to leave out of consideration on this matter mere Party propaganda, have got two means of facing this problem. We have got, as Deputy Belton pointed out, to accept the machinery in this Bill, and we have got to resort to the card system in order to control production. I think the attempt of Deputy Dillon yesterday and to-day to misrepresent anything that was said on this side in favour of the Bill in relation to that matter was uncalled for. There is only another matter that I would like to ask the Minister to keep in mind, and that is the question of minor curers.  If at the end of any time hardship may be imposed on any of those who may have to go out of business then, if the Minister feels inclined to come forward with other proposals, I am sure every Party in the House will give him any assistance they can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy mean to say that he is asking for compensation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSmith" hpid="Mr. Smith Mr. Smith">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Smith</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not mention the word compensation.  My statement was perfectly safe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, perfectly safe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>Like Deputy Belton, my chief interest in the Bill has lapsed with the failure of the Minister to provide an economic price for pigs.  I was interested in Deputy Belton's argument and in Deputy Smith's argument that at intervals there should be uneconomic prices&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say that we should work for uneconomic prices.  If <Col N="342" /> Deputy Bennett wants to argue on that line let him have a show down on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well, I accept that Deputy Belton did not argue on that line.  Deputy Smith did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I gave too much of my time to this Bill to be misrepresented on it to this House now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>I will say this for the Bill at least that it does provide for the fixing at times of uneconomic prices.  I will admit that that is the position at present&mdash;that there are at intervals in the pig trade periods when the price is not economic.  If the Bill can do no better than continue that state of affairs then we are better off without the Bill and let the farmers be guided by their own common sense and the chance of the market as Deputy Belton said.  If the Government interferes in trade of any description they should make it a cardinal principle that the people engaged in the carrying on of that trade are ensured a profit. Otherwise they should not interfere at all.  In this Bill every interest is made secure except one.  The curer is made secure, the handler is made secure, the retailer is made secure and the worker is made secure for a fair wage under the Bill.  But the primary producer is to be left to the tender mercies of chance as to whether he gets a fair economic price or not.  But when we, on this side of the House, speak on these lines we are accused by Deputies on the Government Benches of making political speeches. It is part of our job to try to interpret what our constituents sent us here to do.  If I do that I am not laying myself open to be called a politician and I should not be charged with making political speeches any more than Deputies on the Government side. I have been sent here by the farmers of Limerick to interpret their wishes as well as I can.  That is what I want to do.  The wishes of the farmers are that if the Government interfere in a matter like this, they should pay the piper and produce a price for the farmer.  There is no use in losing tempers over this Bill.  I do not want to insult anyone but neither will I take insults.  This Bill has been <Col N="343" /> brought about by circumstances which the Minister cannot control or which Deputy Smith cannot control but he might help.  We are powerless to interfere in the dispute&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>The economic war again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, Deputy Donnelly has asked if I will suggest any way out of the matter.  I suggest that if we cannot provide an economic price to the farmer, then it is as well that we start at once on an armistice.  The present situation does not give the men in the front line trenches any chance. These men should be given some chance by the Government or else the Government should maintain them in the fight.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with that if you got the public outside to say &ldquo;we will have an armistice&rdquo;, but the public said &ldquo;we won't&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>When did they say that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps in coming to an armistice or in the subsequent settlement we might arrive at a stage when we would make it a cardinal condition that a quota would not be necessary for pigs, that all our pigs would be taken in exchange for some other goods, just as we made an arrangement, possibly favourable for Great Britain, under the Coal-Cattle Pact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Or as the Minister made with reference to butter&mdash;that they would take all the butter we have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGovern" hpid="Mr. McGovern Mr. McGovern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGovern</NameTxt>
      <P>The greatest blot on this Bill is the failure of the Minister to accept Deputy Dillon's amendment to fix an economic price.  Upon that depended whether the Bill would be any good so far as the producers were concerned.  It is all very well for Fianna Fáil Deputies to tell us that it is political propaganda on the part of the Opposition when we claim that the producers of pigs should get an economic price the same as the producers of anything else.  Every producer of an industrial commodity in this country is getting an economic price, no matter what the cost may be to the consumers <Col N="344" /> of that commodity.  That is the policy of Fianna Fáil.  The Minister for Industry and Commerce makes sure that all industrial producers get an economic price.</P>
      <P>The Minister for Agriculture has gone a bit of the way in that direction with regard to the production of some agricultural commodities, such as butter and grain, but he has lost sight of some very important matters affecting certain areas.  There are areas in this country in which those who go in for pig production have to buy grain to feed the pigs, and the Minister has left these out of consideration altogether. He has increased the price of the raw material without putting an economic price upon the finished article.  Pigs and bacon are the finished articles. Owing to the Minister's policy of making the raw material dearer and by keeping down the price of the finished article, pig producers in these areas who have to depend upon buying grain from the grain-growing areas are hit both ways.  The price of feeding stuffs goes up and the price of the finished article goes down.  That is the principal objection to this scheme.  It is going to injure the pig trade very much in counties like Cavan and districts in the West of Ireland where they cannot go in economically for grain growing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>What about Section 140 &mdash;the cost of the production of pigs and particularly the cost of feeding stuffs for the previous four months during which the pigs were being fattened?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGovern" hpid="Mr. McGovern Mr. McGovern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGovern</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not say that is going to give an economic price.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>You are going to have your representatives on the Board and what are they going to do?  They are to consider the cost of feeding-stuffs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGovern" hpid="Mr. McGovern Mr. McGovern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGovern</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Belton is quite satisfied because his amendment has been accepted but I would much prefer Deputy Dillon's proposal, because that would ensure an economic price.  I had an amendment down something similar to Deputy Belton's, but I would prefer Deputy Dillon's amendment to my own or to Deputy <Col N="345" /> Belton's.  I think there was no reason why Deputy Belton's amendment should have been accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Would you not prefer to either of these an amendment guaranteeing £5 per cwt.?  There are things you can get and things you cannot get.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGovern" hpid="Mr. McGovern Mr. McGovern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGovern</NameTxt>
      <P>You could not fix one price for all time and all seasons.  The price must go up and down with the times and circumstances and with the feeding costs, etc.  If you had an economic price and related the price of the finished article to the price of feeding-stuffs that would be an equitable arrangement for all parties.  Another proposal in this Bill is that by fixing the price of bacon you will regulate the production of pigs.  That might be so if there was at least six months' notice given.  By right you would want to give 12 months' notice.  There is only to be one week's notice given of the price of pigs in the next period.  How are the producers to know then what pigs they are to produce?  Pig producers are not conjurers and cannot produce pigs out of a hat over-night. They have to get time to do it.  It will take at least 12 months before people can make up their minds to increase the production if they want to.  The fixing of the price a week in advance by the Bacon Marketing Board is simply taking advantage of the people who have a supply of pigs ready for the market.  They must sell them at the fixed price, which may be half the cost of production.  The effect will be, perhaps, that when the Minister wants an increase in production the production of pigs will go down by half.  I wanted the Minister to accept the amendment to give at least six months' notice of what the price will be&mdash;that the people producing pigs should know six months in advance.  If he wanted to regulate the price that would have some effect.  It is not fair to them to be led on blindfolded until they have the pigs ready for the market and only then know the price they are going to get.  There is no use in fixing a price in that way.  It would be much better if the price was fixed for the whole <Col N="346" /> year round beforehand and let all parties know what it is likely to be. Fixing the price a week before is no use at all.</P>
      <P>My principal objection is that in the County Cavan, and especially the part I come from, it will knock them out of production altogether unless the price is an economic one and has some relation to the price of feeding stuffs. They go in there extensively for pig feeding and have to feed the pigs on meal or grain from elsewhere in order to augment their own supplies, as it is not a tillage county.  County Leitrim is in a similar position and so are other counties in the West.  Naturally I am concerned with the district I come from myself, and I believe that this is going to be a very bad Bill so far as the people there are concerned and is going to drive a large number of small farmers out of production.  I hope the Minister will consider making some amendment to this Bill or make some effort to improve it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexHaslett" hpid="Mr. Haslett Mr. Haslett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haslett</NameTxt>
      <P>The need for some Bill of this kind has long ago forced itself on the people of the country.  The fluctuations in the price of pigs have been really maddening.  I speak as a representative of the pig feeders and am a pig feeder myself.  As long as I can remember there have been fluctuations taking place within a day of from 5/- to 10/- per cwt. in the price of pigs and pork.  The people have been looking forward to this Bill in the hope that that would be remedied to some extent.  I do not agree with a good many of the statements made, because I realise that the Minister's powers in regard to this Bill are limited.  He may achieve stabilisation of prices.  He has power to do that under the Bill but, at the present time, I do not see how anyone in this House, or anyone outside it, can force the Minister to the point where he can guarantee an economic price for the production of pigs.  Talk like that is pure moonshine. The Minister's powers are circumscribed. I do not want to travel into other realms.  I am speaking of things as they are, and what the Minister is up against in this Bill.  He is in a circle and out of that circle he cannot <Col N="347" /> get at present.  He cannot force a higher price for bacon.  He can only get for the people of this country what is going, less the charges against that price.  I take the long view in regard to the Bill.  Any experience I have had I have tried to give to the Committee and to the consideration of the Bill, on the ground that sooner or later the line that circumscribes the Minister will be removed.  It cannot go on.  It is impossible.  This Bill will be a start, and if it does not achieve what we want now, we will have machinery ready when, as we are all optimists, I hope and trust, we will emerge from the gloom, and that some Minister for Agriculture will have more freedom to get what pig producers want.  I disagree somewhat with Deputy Belton in his definition of what he would like as a pig producer.  I do not know whether to call them gamesters or tricksters.  I cannot subscribe to his idea, or to put it the reverse way: &ldquo;heads you win and tails you lose.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not play that game.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexHaslett" hpid="Mr. Haslett Mr. Haslett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haslett</NameTxt>
      <P>In a country which is very near us they fixed a price and they are better satisfied, because people know what they are working to compared with the time when they did not know what was going to happen next day or within a few weeks.  The result of that has been that pig production has increased more than 25 per cent., perhaps by nearly 50 per cent., because of the price fixed ahead, so that producers know what they are working to.  I supported Deputy Dillon in that idea, but if it had the same effect with us as it had in the Northern province, the question arises, where would we be unless the Minister could get other markets and get them very quickly for our bacon? Otherwise it would be impossible to deal with the surplus.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>If he does not get markets what does it matter how many pigs are produced?  Will we not have to sell them at a loss?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexHaslett" hpid="Mr. Haslett Mr. Haslett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haslett</NameTxt>
      <P>I am tired selling at a loss.  I do not want to have that intensified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="348" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexHaslett" hpid="Mr. Haslett Mr. Haslett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haslett</NameTxt>
      <P>I am producing cattle and beef and selling them at a loss for the last two years.  I am tired of that, and do not want to continue doing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill provides that you are to sell pigs at a loss at a certain period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexHaslett" hpid="Mr. Haslett Mr. Haslett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haslett</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister did that, provision would have to be made for a surplus, which I realise is impossible. It was calculated that roughly 2,000 pigs was the minimum for a curer.  If we are to have any measure of supervision under this Bill, I think that is a fairly low minimum.  It works out at 38 pigs a week or a little over 6 pigs a day.  Surely, if a factory is doing any business it should deal with at least six pigs a day, if the staff was to be kept economically employed.  Deputy McGovern referred to feeding stuffs, and argued that a county into which feeding-stuffs are moved from another county is in a worse position than a county that produces for itself. I always calculate that whether feeding stuff is raised or fed it is worth a certain price as feeding, and if we are going to relate the cost we must allow the producer just the same price as the purchaser for that stuff.  In this Bill we achieve stabilisation of prices.  I have no hope that we will have increased prices at present, because we cannot have this machinery, with the levies it brings for the working of that machinery, for nothing.  Except we have a market where prices are expanding we cannot have much hope for an improvement in prices.  As far as my interests are concerned, I consider that we are legislating now for times ahead rather than for the immediate future.  I hope that this Bill will go some length in bringing home to the people just what we are up against in the way of getting an economic price for our produce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>There has been a great deal about the variety of interests that are likely to be prejudiced by this Bill, but, so far, nothing has been said about one small class on which I would like to have the Minister's views as to the likely repercussions of this <Col N="349" /> measure, and how he intends to prevent any undesirable outcome on their business.  I refer to urban wholesalers. There is a section which almost prevents their being recognised or expanding their business in a certain way.  The situation with regard to them is this, that as a matter of necessity, in the ordinary division of economic effort in relation to production, as between the primary producer of the pig and its appearance on the breakfast table, these urban wholesalers achieved a certain very influential position. There are about eight in this city. I do not think they number more than that.  They have, in fact, served the retailers very well.  They have also served the curers.  I have seen it stated in the report of the Special Committee that the Minister for Agriculture, in answer to a plea made on behalf of these people, said that they were not being interfered with.</P>
      <P>In a sense that is true.  They are not in a sense being specifically interfered with in the Bill, but under Section 40, sub-section (4)&mdash;or it used to be that sub-section; it may have been changed owing to changes in Committee&mdash;there is a reaction on them.  The Minister's argument is that they are not hampered.  They are hampered in this way, that at the moment their defence against any attacks made against them by the curers is that they can amalgamate and go into the curing business on their own.  As a matter of fact one wholesaler did that.  They are to be prohibited in the future from that resort.  That was their one defence. One of the curers has opened an establishment in this town.  That curer has, in fact, done what Deputy Dillon and the Special Committee forecast might be done.  In other words, the curer, when applied to by those wholesalers for consignments of stuff, has given it to them at 2/- a unit more than the price at which he supplies to the retailers.  Obviously, a wholesaler cannot continue in business if the men whom he is going to supply are to get supplies at a less price than he can get them.  The Minister has taken away their only resort by way of defence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="350" /> The Minister's second suggestion was that they never were really in that business at all, and used to handle only imported bacon.  If he will turn to the report of the Commission which dealt with prices he will find that there was evidence given by curers, retailers, and the wholesalers themselves.  The evidence quoted by the Commission was to the effect that the wholesalers handled 77 per cent. of what was cured at home, only 23 per cent. being distributed direct as between curer and retailer.  That, therefore, has grown up as an important and almost essential part of the business.  It was found impossible under the conditions of trading in the city that the curer should supply direct to the retailer, and the further proof of the necessity of these people in the economic scheme of things is that since the measure was anticipated and since the measure has been published the reaction of the curers has been not to attempt to supply direct from their curing establishment to the retailer, but to come to town and open up, thus showing that they cannot do without some intermediary. They have been described as an unnecessary intermediary.  I put it that first of all the growth of this part of the business has made them a necessary intermediary, and the fact that the reaction is for the curer to come to town and open a wholesale establishment himself.  I think proves the necessity for the establishment which those people have. Supposing they are unnecessary, does it mean that we are faced with this, that even an individual curer will find it necessary to open a sort of wholesale distribution premises in the city? If so, instead of having eight people with a long tradition, plenty of experience, and with about 300 employees, we will have each curer&mdash;and there are about 300 of them&mdash;opening in the town.  Is it considered desirable that the reactions of this measure should be so harsh upon a particular group of people who have grown up in the business? I suggest to the Minister that his statement that the Bill does not interfere with those people should be further analysed, and his view which he put forward as an argument that <Col N="351" /> they did not handle any part of the Irish business but only imported American bacon, should be further looked into.  The truth can be got from the report of the Prices Commission.</P>
    <P>There is a further point which the Minister should remember, that those eight wholesalers include in each separate establishment brands of bacon as cured by the different curers throughout the country, whereas of course if we get into the new system each curer will now establish his own premises and sell to the retailer only one brand&mdash;his own particular brand. You have here obviously an economic unit of distribution which has grown up.  Taking the final argument which might be brought up against them it cannot be said that their disappearance will either add a halfpenny extra to what the producer gets or cheapen by a halfpenny the product as it goes to the consumer.  If there is any gain either to the producer or the consumer, and if they are, as I assert they are, an economic necessity and a necessary intermediary in this business, I think the Minister should be very careful as to the reactions upon this natural growth of business.  I may stress as a last point that it is not desirable that those eight people, with well known establishments, plenty of connections, an established trade, and giving credit to the retailers for a minimum, of, I understand, five weeks, should be crushed out of the business.  The Minister should make some attempt to meet them, and if he cannot meet them personally he should at any rate make some attempt to meet their arguments which have already been furnished to him.  That is the special and individual point about which I wanted to speak on this measure.</P>
    <P>Outside of that, there are a few general economic matters which have been raised in relation to and in the atmosphere of this Bill.  Very briefly, I should like to get one or two points clear.  Deputy Haslett hopes that we will come to a better stage of optimism than we have reached at the moment. I do not see how we can be more optimistic than we are at present.  We have won the economic war.  The war <Col N="352" /> is over.  We have been so assured by the Minister for Industry and Commerce several times.  His statements with regard to more intimate matters in the City of Dublin are a little bit more doubtful, a little bit more suspect than they used to be, but he has said with great vehemence and an appearance of belief that the war is over.  We are now in normal peace times, and are settling our establishment under those conditions.  I think it was Deputy Haslett, or possibly Deputy McGovern, who said that the Minister for Industry and Commerce has guaranteed an economic price to the industrial producer.  I want to question that.  I am going on to the analogy of this Bill.  I do not see how it can be said that he has.  He certainly raised the price of certain commodities in the country, and raised the price of certain manufactured goods.  I wonder would most of the wage-earning people of this country, and they would class themselves amongst the industrial producers, say they are better off now than they were, or that their wages are, in purchasing power, equal to what they were three years ago?  If they are not, it is a narrow view that just because certain employers are benefited by tariffs we can adduce from that a statement of principle to the effect that the Minister for Industry and Commerce has guaranteed industrial producers an economic price.  We are approaching&mdash;and this is only another step in the same direction&mdash;a peculiar position in the country.  There was a time when, by virtue of a few legal decisions operating under a particular Act, certain business houses which had been a rather ordinary type of property in the country got an artificially enhanced value put upon them; a certain judicial decision was given that a new licence could not be given until the old licence was abolished.  We are getting into that situation with regard to numerous things at the moment.  Take, for instance, reserved commodities.  Suddenly we find people who are not in a certain business at all deciding to go into that business.  They are protected from competition not merely against outsiders but even against other <Col N="353" /> nationals of the country; their establishments are getting an artificially enhanced value and we are interfering at every moment with the ordinary swing of economics.  I remember being asked in this House, I think by a Labour Deputy, when I was so often boasting about the sovereignty of this Dáil, why did I not get it to repeal some of those economic laws that seem to be hampering our progress; why did I not get it to repeal the law of supply and demand.  That is the attempt which is on at the moment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Or what the economic price is to be now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Possibly.  It would depend upon how far arrangements were made, or whether we get definitely to the point whether the Minister was an expert in all the multifarious matters dealt with by a Government Department, or whether he is relying upon his civil servant experts to guide him.  What is happening is that instead of the producer who grew up in the business, and whose ancestors before him grew up in it and handed on their experience to him, operating under the ordinary laws and guiding and governing his own business, he is to be directed by civil servants who never were in business, but who have a passion for tidiness and cleaning up, and who insist upon interfering in matters of which they have no practical experience.  It would seem that the whole country is eventually going to be run&mdash;and we see effects of it at the present moment&mdash;by complete bureaucratic machinery.  The Pigs and Bacon Bill is another drift in that direction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Someone said one of the values of such a measure as this is its educative effect upon the people.  That appears to be sound.  Deputy Smith has learned a lot on what he is pleased to call the process of thinking inside himself, and there suddenly emerges from him the thought that it is a desirable thing, and not merely possible but probable that this Bill should put certain people out of the production of pigs by fixing an economic price.  One would think that that might be done by the <Col N="354" /> ordinary laws of supply and demand, but once you start handling and mishandling production and getting into a position in which you are shifting your basis it is a different matter.  You are not then merely putting all your eggs into one basket but you are shifting them from basket to basket and these of a very flimsy character.  Deputy Smith now agrees that it is a desirable thing to drive people out of production and that that can now be done by civil servants operating through the Minister. Deputy Haslett thinks that this Bill, so far as prices are concerned, might be a good thing if it stops fluctuations.  Will it?  Is it likely to? There may be found in it something analogous to what was contained in the Cattle Bill and the Butter Bill of some years ago.  In other words, you are looking to selling your produce in England. You want to stabilise the marketable commodity that you are sending to England.  You find out what the tastes of the people in England are and you cater for them.  And so far as this Bill will bring about standardisation of bacon to suit the English palate it is a good thing, and that is what the Fianna Fáil Party are now getting enthusiastic about.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a long time coming.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh no, I got to the economic war quite early.  I am now talking about the friendly relationships you are establishing and I say it is good business.  I do not like Deputy Smith not to hope that England will first get the bacon that they want and I do not want to keep him rolling on his pillow when thinking whether the farmers have to be driven out of production by the lowering of prices.  Now he has a weapon in his hand.  He can no longer console himself by referring to cycles of trade.  All he need do now is to come and see the Minister for Agriculture and get some people put out of production.  It looks a very fantastic business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have got here an interesting quotation from a paper called <i>The Miller.</i> It indicates the point to which all this insanity and scatter-brain business can come.  I tack this on to the insane <Col N="355" /> notion of Deputy Smith for driving people out of production.  This is a quotation which relates to what is happening in America.  An American wrote to an American newspaper to say that a friend had recently received a cheque for 1,000 dollars for not raising hogs.  He now proposes to get a farm and to go into the prosperous business of not raising hogs.  And he wrote to the editor of this paper to find out his opinion as to the best kind of farm not to raise hogs on, the best strain of hogs not to raise and how best to keep an inventory of the hogs you are not raising and he went on to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;My friend who got 1,000 dollars got it for not raising 500 hogs.  Now, we figure we might easily not raise 1,500 hogs or even 2,000 hogs, so you see the possible profits are only limited by the number of hogs we do not raise.  My friend who received the 1,000 dollar cheque has been hog-raising for 40 years, and the best he made was 400 dollars a year.  Kind of pathetic to think how he wasted his life raising hogs when not raising them would have been so much more profitable.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="StephenJordan" hpid="Mr. S. Jordan Mr. S. Jordan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Jordan</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the name of that paper?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>The Miller.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="StephenJordan" hpid="Mr. S. Jordan Mr. S. Jordan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Jordan</NameTxt>
      <P>Whang the Miller?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>No; not even Mick the Miller.  The paper wound up by saying that this was an example of curious economics.  We in this State are tinged slightly with that sort of economic insanity.  Undoubtedly there will come a time when it will come to a question of the destruction of the live stock of the country, but it will be a little less fantastically done.  It will be done by civil servants acting through the Minister for Agriculture.  Deputy Smith will have to face the fact that deliberately prices will be lowered, so as to drive certain people out of production. Deputy Smith has now reached the point where, by some reason or other, he thinks that that which was done by nature is wrong but that which is done by the Minister for Agriculture is correct.  He should <Col N="356" /> think further and let us know deliberately why he thinks it is right that these things should be mishandled by the Minister for Agriculture, and not dealt with by ordinary economic courses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the point raised by Deputy McGilligan in reference to the wholesale trade, I may say I did meet the wholesalers when this Bill was first drafted.  I pointed out to them that I did not see how they were interfered with in this Bill.  The point was made that in the past they, at least, had the weapon that if the curers did not deal with them they could go into the curing business themselves. Section 40, sub-section (4) of this Bill is certainly for the benefit of the wholesaler.  In other words, if they smoke only, they are trading without actually being curers.  I made the point, it is true, that they were dealing to a great extent in imported bacon, and the reason I made that point was that their grievance was due to the tariff on bacon or the stoppage of imports, but not to this Bill.  All the bacon imported came through their class.  Take the Dublin people on the list of wholesalers.  They had that business, certainly, but when the import of bacon was stopped it was not so certain that the home curers would deal through them.  I agree with Deputy McGilligan that their disappearance will not benefit either the producer or the consumer.  I know that proprietors of some very large factories take that view also.  I have heard them express the opinion that it would be better for them to continue to deal through the wholesaler than to set up machinery to retail their own bacon. Some of the other factories may take a different view, but I hold that we are not interfering with that trade in this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>You do realise that you are taking away their defensive weapon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to that point, I should say that it is still possible for a factory to be licensed. If they had a genuine grievance they might be prepared to start a factory of their own.  As the Industries <Col N="357" /> Tribunal pointed out, it would be advisable to have at least one more factory in the Free State, so that there is an opening in that direction if they wish to avail of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister does not intend to bring in a provision of any type to meet that problem?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>He is just going to leave it to chance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Does not the Minister appreciate that there is a danger?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that I can be accused of being unjust to that particular class.  I think Deputies will agree that when these people were really hit was when the import of bacon was stopped.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us agree that they were hit by the tariff on bacon. Is that any reason for saying that, because they are so weak now, we can hit them as often as we like?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures are given in the Tribunal report.  The percentages were 77 to 23.  Seventy-seven per cent. of the Irish business was done by the wholesalers&mdash;I do not say the eight Dublin men&mdash;and 23 per cent. directly with retailers.  Surely that is a position worth keeping?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot see how this Bill interferes with them except that they have not got that threat any longer.  I wonder if the curers regarded it in the past as a threat.  I do not agree with Deputy McGovern that this Bill is following on the lines of the dairy produce or fresh meat legislation. Those measures were brought in solely to regulate export.  Deputy McGilligan said that Deputy Smith might not lie awake with the fear that the British people would not get good bacon.  Our predecessors could be accused of that attitude.  They were very anxious to give a good article to the British consumer but they did not cater for the <Col N="358" /> consumer at home.  Under this Bill, all bacon, whether intended for home consumption or for export, is subject to veterinary inspection.  There is no distinction as regards inspection between the article intended for export and the article to be consumed at home.  I may say that the greater part of the bacon is consumed at home and, therefore, this is a much more important market than the export market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister remember the comparative percentages?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot give the exact figures but it would represent about 35 per cent. or 40 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought the export was rather more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>My figures may not be exact, but the export does not come near one-half.  Two or three years ago it was one third.  It has increased somewhat.  Deputy McGovern suggested that we should give six months' notice of the fixing of prices. It would be extremely difficult for the Board to fix firm prices six months ahead.  However, I think the Board ought to give an indication, if possible, six months or twelve months ahead of the probable position.  They probably will give that indication.  They may be able to see, with the trend of production and the expected market, that there is likely to be a crisis in nine or ten months if production continued to increase as it is increasing at the moment. The Board will probably be able to give their opinion in that way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is not entirely due to the British quota that this Bill is necessary. Deputy Haslett pointed out how disconcerting and disappointing it is to the farmer to find, when he brings his pigs to market, that the price has fallen from 56/- to 51/- or 50/-.  That is one thing which we have to stop.  When dealing with the Second Reading of this Bill, I gave prices at two factories on that particular day.  On that day, if a farmer brought a 12 stone pig to one factory he would get 24/- more than if he brought it to another factory.  To stop these variations from day to day and between factory and factory, I <Col N="359" /> think that we would be quite justified in bringing in this Bill.  It is obvious that, in the case I mentioned, one factory was not losing 24/- per pig.  It might be losing part of that sum.  It may have been forced to buy pigs for somewhat more than their value.  It is equally obvious that the other factory was making much more than could be justified as a profit.</P>
    <P>Apart from that day-to-day fluctuation, everybody looking at the prices in the daily papers will have noticed that a week seldom passes in which there is not some change in the prices as regards the different weights.  A 10½ or 13 stone pig will sometimes command a better price than a lighter pig, but the following week the other pig may jump up in price.  All these sudden changes will be stopped under this Bill and the farmer will know, at least a few weeks ahead, what the price will be.  Probably, when the Bill is working normally, the Board will be able to give a fair idea, perhaps six months ahead, of what the price will be.  There were also violent fluctuations which were more or less seasonal.  These were probably more exaggerated than was necessary.  As this Bill is constructed, it will not be possible to prevent some fluctuation.  As I have pointed out so often, the whole basis of the Bill is to follow the law of supply and demand.  Deputy Dillon pointed out that there was no restriction on exports in 1931, that we could have sent all the pigs and sheep we liked to Great Britain then.  Perhaps Deputy Dillon would examine the prices we got in 1931.  If he does, he will find that the price of pigs was never so low since as it was in the end of that year. He will find that the same thing applied to sheep&mdash;the two animals he mentioned.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the Minister deduce from that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to know what the Deputy was going to deduce from his statement and from his attempt to bring us back to the conditions of 1931, when there was an unlimited market in Britain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="360" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister deny that the British market is now a profitable market in which to sell bacon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not that a red herring?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Dillon, in his oratorical excitement, appealed to us to remember 1931, when we could send all the pigs and sheep we liked into the British market.  I advise him to get the prices for that period and he will find that, towards the end of 1931, the graph for sheep and pigs was lower than it has ever been since.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeating" hpid="Mr. Keating Mr. Keating">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keating</NameTxt>
      <P>Pigs were lower in November, 1932, than ever.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>In 1931?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does not the Minister admit that the British market is now a profitable market in which to sell bacon, no matter how much they take from us?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy allow me to deal with his argument as he put it first?  I shall deal with the rest later. He was appealing to us to remember this unlimited market, and his argument evidently was that there was an unlimited market there and that we should send in our stuff to it.  The result was that pigs and sheep came in to Britain in large quantities, not only from the Free State, but from the rest of the world, and prices came down in Britain.  In other words the economic law of supply and demand operated, but Deputy Dillon does not want it to operate now.  At the Special Committee, Deputy Dillon had an amendment which had that effect, and when it was pointed out to him that this Bill was based on supply and demand, he said, &ldquo;Well, I had better withdraw my amendment; there is no use in talking politics here at the Special Committee.&rdquo; The Deputy felt that there was no use in talking politics at the Special Committee, because the public Press was not represented there.  Accordingly, he re-introduced his amendment here on the Report Stage in order that he could talk politics here where the Press was represented.  Deputy McGovern was on that Committee also, but he never said a single word there <Col N="361" /> to the effect that this economic price should be fixed.  Deputy Bennett was also there, and neither did he mention it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Bennett was not at the Special Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, I am sorry.  Deputy Bennett was not there.  But Deputy Dillon did not pursue his argument there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Was not Deputy McGilligan on that Committee also?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy McGilligan did not attend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This has been mentioned twice.  I explained that I am one of those horny-handed sons of toil and could not attend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand.  As a matter of fact, I said that in order to excuse Deputy McGilligan, not to blame him.  But, as I was saying, Deputy Dillon withdrew his amendment with regard to the economic price, saying that there was no use in talking politics at the Special Committee. There was no use in talking politics there, because the Press was not present, but he took the opportunity of re-introducing the amendment on the Report Stage when he knew that the Press would be present, and he would have an opportunity of talking politics to advantage.  As a result, we have lost hours talking about an economic price merely to give Deputy Dillon an opportunity to talk politics for the benefit of the public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is now deliberately&mdash;well, perhaps not deliberately&mdash;stating what is not true.  The amendment that was standing in my name on the Report Stage is entirely different from the amendment standing in my name for the Special Committee, and differs with regard to those elements which I thought were unreasonable to ask from the Minister. In the amendment standing in my name on the Report Stage these elements are withdrawn from my proposal, and the proposal now stands in what I said, at <Col N="362" /> the Special Committee, I thought to be the reasonable form.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment dealt with the economic price, and Deputy Dillon now wants to try to delude us into believing that he wanted to leave out rents and rates from the calculation. That is the reason why he was willing to leave out politics at the Special Committee, but not here in the House where the Press is present.  Deputy McGovern also served on the Special Committee, and he never raised the slightest protest when Deputy Dillon withdrew his amendment.  Deputy McGovern also had the good sense to realise that the Press was not represented at the Special Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>He was reading Columbcille then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I said that prices were bad in 1931, and so they were.  They were very bad in 1931.  The result was that the numbers of pigs and sheep went down in this country during the following year and until 1933.  Our output and exports, both of pigs and bacon, have been increased in the last three years.  Deputy Haslett, I think, mentioned the North of Ireland having a big benefit in the bacon trade.  If Deputy Haslett will look at yesterday's <i>Evening Herald</i>, he will find that for the last three years both the production and the export of bacon in the Free State and Northern Ireland have gone up by an exactly equal percentage. He will see that we increased our output just to the very same figure as in Northern Ireland during the last three years.  It was the same in both places.  These are the figures I saw in the <i>Evening Herald</i> yesterday evening and the Deputy can read them for himself.  They are probably in to-day's paper also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexHaslett" hpid="Mr. Haslett Mr. Haslett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haslett</NameTxt>
      <P>My point was that the fixed price had the effect of raising it definitely in Northern Ireland.  I was not making any comparison between the two places.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that.  Of course, it would be very easy to fix an economic price for bacon here if we could accept Deputy Dillon's figure <Col N="363" /> that 4 lbs. of a meal ration would produce 1 lb. of meat.  If we could take that formula, I would not have the slightest hesitation about fixing an economic price in this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister challenge the conclusions of the Lane-Fox report in that regard?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>If Deputy Dillon had any experience of pig raising, he would not take that figure.  No Deputy here, who has raised pigs, would take that figure, because, if you take 4lbs. of a meal ration to 1 lb. of meat, there would be no difficulty at all about making pigs pay.  The price of meal here for pig feeding has not been increased as a result of our cereals legislation.  Deputy Dillon may believe that we feed nothing but maize meal mixture to pigs, but we do not, and no good farmer would think of feeding a whole ration of maize meal mixture to pigs.  Any good farmer will balance his ration, and he will have six or eight cwts. of wheat offals.  These offals, as a result of our legislation, are lower than they otherwise would be because the flour was produced in this country. Formerly, we were importing the offals, and the price of them here was the Liverpool price plus freight.  The prices are lower now than the Liverpool prices, and putting that against the increase on the maize meal that would be contained in the ration, I think he would find, if he took some pains to inquire into it or if he asked a practical farmer, that the ration has not increased in price as a result of that legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does not the Minister know that he is talking through his hat when he says that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, it is a compliment if the Deputy thinks that, because there is a good chance that I am talking sense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexHaslett" hpid="Mr. Haslett Mr. Haslett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haslett</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the offal sold more cheaply to anybody else than the Free State feeders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>There has been no offal exported from this country since last <Col N="364" /> May, with the exception of 800 tons. There is a prohibition against the export of offals from this country. Deputies are extremely out of touch with facts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlexHaslett" hpid="Mr. Haslett Mr. Haslett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haslett</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, we shall get the figures for the Minister at a later stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister know the price of pollard at present?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do, because I am buying it myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the Minister paying for it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>About 6/-.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is very cheap.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it is.  It is good value.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister say what mill is supplying him?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am getting it from a merchant, not from a mill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>At 6/-?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>For white pollard?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, brown pollard.  I do not know what the price of white pollard is, because I do not buy it. Deputy Dillon made a very strong speech here against Government subsidies. He said there was going to be no success in farming until all Government subsidies were cut out.  It is a pity the Deputy would not turn his argument to Deputy Bennett who wants to get 120/- per cwt, for butter while the world price is 70/- and wants to get it done out of Government subsidies. Deputy Bennett does not want it taken by means of a levy from the farmer.  The Party opposite advocate Government subsidies when it suits them and they are against them when it suits Deputy Dillon to make an oratorical outburst.  Would Deputy Dillon point out to me where in this Bill the curer is guaranteed a profit?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>When he fixes the price of bacon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The curer does not fix the price of bacon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="365" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Who fixes the price of bacon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The other Board can give him pigs at a non-paying rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Who fixes the price of pigs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The curer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The price of pigs is fixed by the curers and if the producers do not like it the curers can block it.  Then it is handed over to the chairman.  When he fixes the price of pigs the curers can apply to the Marketing Board and change the price of bacon again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>And the other people can change the price of pigs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister tell us where the curer fixes the price of bacon in this Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Dillon has not read the Bill.  I would like to know where the curer or retailer is guaranteed a profit under this Bill. Where is the producer not guaranteed a profit any more than the rest of them?  Deputy Dillon, of course, was followed by Deputy Bennett and by Deputy McGovern&mdash;the two lieutenants. They all say the same thing: that the curer and the retailer are guaranteed a profit under the Bill but that the other fellow is not.  Where is a distinction made between any of the classes under this Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGovern" hpid="Mr. McGovern Mr. McGovern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGovern</NameTxt>
      <P>The curer has it in his own hands, but the producer is left to take what he gets.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardSidneyAnthony" hpid="Mr. Anthony Mr. Anthony">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Anthony</NameTxt>
      <P>And the poor consumer is going to pay.  He will have to suffer between the lot of them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No one spoke for him at all.  Deputy Belton more or less accused me of rushing this Bill.  I think he was hardly justified in what he said, because this Bill has been before the House for a long time. Deputy Belton referred to the fact that the Bill was in the hands of Deputies this morning.  The compliment <Col N="366" /> that Deputy Belton paid me is hardly due to me.  I think it is the Ceann Comhairle who should receive the thanks for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Minister will not forget to deal with the few suggestions I made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>No. The Deputy, as well as some other Deputies, made a plea for the minor curers.  They will go out after two years unless they qualify.  I have taken the view that it is much better that we should make it easy for them to qualify than put them out and compensate them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree with compensation for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment that I brought in yesterday will have the effect of making it easier for them to qualify, and I hope they will qualify. If we were to talk of compensation for them, then we might have a situation somewhat like the one Deputy McGilligan spoke about in the case of the American hogs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I hold the view, because of the monopoly that will be created in the bacon curing business, that the assets of the minor curers have been enhanced by this Bill, and that if they were to sell out they would probably get more for their business to-day than they would have got, say, two years ago.  There is no case, I think, for compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>The difference between curing ten and 40 pigs a week presents an insuperable difficulty to numbers of these establishments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know, but I think Deputy Belton has struck the right note.  It is probably going to be a valuable business, and I do not believe they will have any difficulty in getting the necessary financial help from some quarter when they want to qualify. We have reliable data on which to forecast the number of pigs coming on the market.  We have been acting on these data for the last few years.  On the whole, the Department of Agriculture has been very successful in <Col N="367" /> giving a forecast of the number of pigs that will be available each month of the year.  The Deputy knows that we have very strict regulations now with regard to the registration of boars.  We get returns, and we are able to give a good forecast.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that information reliable enough for the fixing of prices?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It has proved to be very reliable in the last 12 months with regard to the number of pigs expected to come on the market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>For bacon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>For sale, whether exported alive or used for bacon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Minister reply to the point raised by Deputy McGilligan as regards wholesalers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>He did, by saying that they are not affected by the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very important that these traders should be granted a little indulgence.  There is only one question that I want to ask the Minister, and it is this.  Would he consider providing facilities for traders who have not chain stores?  I think there should be some sort of a central depot where they could go and make their selections, not of one cure but of all cures.  As the Minister knows, some customers prefer O'Mara's bacon and others Denny's bacon.  Whether it is so or not, they think that one is better than the other.  These small traders may want to select a bit of each cure. It would be very expensive on them if they had to get a small consignment from each curer.  The transport charges would be high.  On the other hand, if there was a central depot to which they could go and make a selection of the bacon cured by half a dozen curers, and get all sent to them in one consignment, the freight charges would be small.  Their position should be considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not see how that question can arise now.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Estimates" RHead="for Public Services">
    <Title>Public Business. - Estimates for Public Services.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="368" /> The Dáil, according to order, resumed the consideration of Estimates for Public Services in Committee on Finance.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Vote 32&mdash;Office" RHead="of the Minister for Justice (Resumed)">
    <Title>Public Business. - Vote 32&mdash;Office of the Minister for Justice (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That the Estimate be referred back for reconsideration.&rdquo;&mdash;(Risteárd Ua Maolchatha.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I was referring last night to the amazing blunder made when the detective establishment of this State set out to arrest a man who was apparently notable for rather revolutionary activities and who was subsequently charged for them.  They found themselves, having apparently taken up a telephone directory and looked up a house and a particular name, at the house of an ordinary law-abiding citizen of this State.  Their attitude that night, of course, caused that gentleman annoyance.  I might even say it put upon him a certain amount of fear which, I think, no ordinary law-abiding citizen ought to have thrust upon him unless there is good reason. I want the Minister to consider if, in circumstances in which a man's house had to be raided at 2 o'clock in the morning and if a man represents himself to be an ordinary law-abiding citizen, these forces of his should not think it a reasonable request to be put by him that they should state their authority even from outside the halldoor, because the Minister must know that there have been outrages committed in the country, in which people have disguised themselves as members of the force, and there have been other outrages in which people have announced themselves, without disguising themselves, as members of the force.  Surely it is a reasonable matter that a citizen should be entitled to ask, from behind the security of his own halldoor, what is the authority for raiding his house; what he is supposed to have done; what is going to be looked for; who has signed the search warrant; and who has sworn the <Col N="369" /> necessary information and belief before the required District Justice.</P>
      <P>I alluded last night to the fact that these men, on a police whistle being blown from an upper window, broke and ran.  I do not want to be contemptuous in using the word &ldquo;ran.&rdquo;  If they thought the house was that of a man who belonged to an avowedly military body and if they had a reasonable apprehension that the blowing of the police whistle was the signal for others to come upon them, they were not merely correct in their attitude, but they were sane in taking cover, but the Minister must realise the apprehension that would be caused in the mind of a peaceful citizen surveying that particular performance from his upper window.  Men come along and announce themselves as police; they refuse to state their authority; and at the first blast on an ordinary police whistle, which is rather easily recognised, these men break up and hide themselves along the street and then, of course, come along some time later to renew their attempt to get into this man's house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I suggest that that incident reveals a situation which the Minister ought to deal with.  I think it is incomprehensible that, at this stage, a member of the detective division, and a rather well-known member of the detective division, should find it possible to swear or to state&mdash;I do not know what the phrase in the Firearms Act or the Treasonable Offences Act is&mdash;or to indicate his belief that there are arms or treasonable documents to be found in a particular house.  How can a reputable man of the Headquarters Branch of the police force find it possible to swear that, in a particular house, he has reason to believe certain things are to be got, when, in fact, it turns out to be the house of a man who is not wanted at all?  The Minister knows that a gross blunder was made on that occasion.  The Minister has apologised, but I suggest that that is not enough. Citizens are entitled to feel secure against a repetition of such a blunder and the Minister ought to give some public reassurance by indicating how that blunder took place; whether it <Col N="370" /> was a sudden order rushed upon this unfortunate detective; whether, in fact, he had a document put into his hands and was simply told to pedal off to the District Justice's house and get it sworn as quickly as possible; or, at any rate, give some explanation of the circumstances in which this particular matter took the shape it did take.</P>
    <P>I suggest further that the Minister might consider whether it should not be left as a matter of discretion to the detective officers, when requested so to do, to state from outside the door who sent them there; what they are supposed to be getting in the house; what is their authority; what District Justice has signed, and so on.  That will induce, at any rate, a better-belief and better security and confidence in people's minds.  I am not going to suggest at all that that should, and could, be done in every case.  If there are dangerous men, or people who are thought to be dangerous, about to be apprehended, and if it is thought that the best way to get these people is by going to the house at an early hour of the morning, in order to bring about the element of surprise, I quite agree that it would be impossible to have that element of surprise, and even that element of security for the raiding force, if there was to be an insistence on every occasion upon following such a procedure as I have suggested, but in certain cases it is quite possible. At any rate, we are again in the dilemma that the peaceful citizen should not be put in such a position.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>They were often put in that position during the régime of the late Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to have examples.  I am giving an absolutely specific case.  The Deputy would not always have liked to be described as a peaceful, law-abiding citizen.  I notice that he rather pats himself on the chest for it at the moment but there was a time when it was not so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>And there were others in Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="371" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Mulcahy could give all the information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I could tell you a lot about yourself and your colleagues.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope that Deputy Mulcahy will not anticipate me because I have a lot to say about the Deputy and his colleagues to-day.  At any rate, peaceful citizens should not be put in that position.  I have given the Minister an example.  The Minister knows about it because he has written to the person involved and I know that he has so written.  It is agreed as between us that it did happen.  The gentleman for whom this man was mistaken was eventually apprehended.  I do not know whether he was also raided at two o'clock, three o'clock or four o'clock in the morning, but unless they had two persons of the same name in the Bridewell, his raid could only have started about four o'clock when the mistake was found out.</P>
      <P>Whether this second person was raided in the early hours of the morning and whether this performance was gone through again, I cannot say&mdash;I have no touch with him&mdash;but he was eventually paraded before the Tribunal with a group of others.  I am not making any particular note of his case. The situation we find ourselves in, apparently, in the last three weeks is that the Government have decided that the I.R.A. have got to be met in some way.  If the Government were going to meet them as what the President described them&mdash;an avowedly military organisation&mdash;and if they were going to be put down as such, they would get 100 per cent. support for anything they do in regard to them from this side, but they are not treating them as such. They are treating them as rather obnoxious political opponents at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Awkward opponents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>As awkward opponents.  The Minister for Justice, when speaking in Ballina over a year ago, said that complaints had been made that they had not pursued the I.R.A., and he asked &ldquo;Why should we? We know the I.R.A.; we know the type <Col N="372" /> of organisation they are; and we know their ideals,&rdquo; and he tailed off into nothingness and certainly tailed off into inactivity so far as the I.R.A. were concerned.  He did tell us on another occasion at Bonniconlon that there was not a thing that happened at an I.R.A. meeting of which he had not information within 24 hours, and he went on to say that he did not act on such information.  At least, he has not been in the habit of acting on it.  We get, at any rate, the change in words.  The President has recently described the I.R.A. as an avowedly military organisation, with the use of arms as one of its methods, and the President decided that action must be taken. What that action was and what it has led to is another chapter in the discussion, but, at some point, the decision was taken that the I.R.A. are to be regarded as an avowedly military body, with the use of arms as one of its methods.</P>
      <P>Round about that time, some of the detective officers of the force were sent to the newspapers in the city, and, I think, elsewhere, to warn them that they are not to publish any information emanating from any unlawful associations. The President or the Minister for Justice was asked here if he could tie up these two things together and say that a body which was an avowedly military organisation, with the use of arms as one of its methods, was one of the unlawful associations referred to in the communication made by the detective officers to the Press and there was a definite refusal to link these two things together&mdash;the avowedly military body with the bodies vaguely described to the newspapers as unlawful associations. There was, in fact, a very peculiar series of events to which Deputy Mulcahy referred briefly yesterday. We get, coming up to the Easter celebrations, an editorial in the <i>Irish Press</i> on April 3rd, with the rather cynical heading: &ldquo;For honest thought.&rdquo;  A Mr. Russell had written to the editor of the <i>Irish Press</i> bitterly commenting on certain proposals of the President, and at a certain point in the editorial it says:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Mr. Russell's second point is&mdash; we think the word is not too strong <Col N="373" />&mdash;a grotesque misrepresentation of the national commemoration organised by the largest Republican movement in Ireland&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That means yourselves, if you do not know it.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;He pretends that O'Connell Street is to be held against his Party's commemoration ceremony by &lsquo;the Free State Army and police&rsquo;.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>However, Mr. Russell was mild there. What was it you people used to call them?  You used to call them Imperial troops.  Do you remember that?  He merely said by &ldquo;the Free State Army and police&rdquo;; that is his manner of describing the tribute that was paid by the Government to the memory of the 1916 leaders.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Finally Mr. Russell condemns the decision of Fianna Fáil to have its own method and emblem of honour for the Republican dead.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>This is the part I want to stress:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We understand, and Mr. Russell must know, that the proceeds of the sale of Easter lilies go, at least in part, to the I.R.A., some of whose leaders have declared that they will use arms against the majority's Republican representatives.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>It does not say against the Government. They are not sanctified in this article as the Government; they are the alleged majority representatives of an alleged Republican movement in the country.  As a matter of fact they are the Government, and I read the Government into this.  This paper, with its editorial authority, says that the proceeds of the sale of Easter lilies go, at least in part, to the Irish Republican Army, some of whose leaders have declared that they will use arms against the Government.  I hope the advertisement was paid for.</P>
    <P>On the next day, Thursday, April 4th, the same paper printed an advertisement for the sale of Easter lilies.  In other words, it helped to advertise the sale of an emblem, and portion of the proceeds was to go to the I.R.A. for the purpose of purchasing arms to be used against the Government of the country.</P>
    <Col N="374" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Did any other paper publish that advertisement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy tells me that any other paper did so, I will accept his statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Other papers did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.  But why was it allowed?  That is what I am at. There is in this country a military organisation, and an advertisement is issued for the sale of a certain emblem, and part of the proceeds of that sale is to be devoted to the purpose of getting arms that will be used against the Government of the country.  And that is allowed!  I do not care what paper published it, that should not be allowed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Why single out that particular paper?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Give me the names of the others, and I will read them too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>It is singled out because it is, according to the Deputy, the Ministerial paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>All this matter to which I am referring is commented on editorially in that paper.  Will Deputy Donnelly tell me if any other paper commented editorially that they knew part of the proceeds of the sale would be devoted to that purpose?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>And yet the paper that knew that part of the proceeds of the sale would be used to get arms for use against the Government published that advertisement!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>My point is that it took some hunting and a bit of ingenuity to get this advertisement in the <i>Irish Press</i> and relate it to the leading article.  Why not take the advertisements in all the other papers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Somebody did give me that editorial and that advertisement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure Deputy Mulcahy read it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="375" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Deputy Donnelly say why any paper should be allowed to publish an advertisement for the purpose of collecting funds to buy arms to fight the Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Other papers published the advertisement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not see it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We will hear Deputy McGilligan without further interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked if any other paper had editorially announced that it knew that part of the proceeds of the sale of these emblems was to get arms to fight and overthrow the Government, and I wanted to know why that advertisement was allowed. On the 11th April a question was asked in the House.  It was addressed to the Minister for Justice.  He was asked if he had any information that moneys or any part of same derived from the sale of Easter lilies were to be used in the purchase of arms for unlawful purposes.  He said that he had no such information.  The Minister, who knows everything that happens at an I.R.A. meeting within 24 hours, has not the information that the editor of the <i>Irish Press</i> was able to put in his editorial on the 3rd April.  The editor is very precise in his information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think anybody is going to deny that the I.R.A. were collecting for the purpose of getting arms to defeat the Government.  That was not the first occasion on which that was said.  Senator David Robinson, when some point was raised about the sale of poppies, said that the people at any rate knew what the proceeds of the sale of poppies would be devoted to, but nobody knew what the proceeds of the sale of Easter lilies were going to be devoted to, and there was a most aggrieved reply from Cumann na mBan stating that the purpose of the sale of Easter lilies was to buy arms.  They did not put a tooth in it.  I asked the Minister on the 11th April if any permit for the sale of such emblems had been sought or granted, and I was told no permit had been sought or granted. <Col N="376" /> I asked what action it was intended to take against the publication of advertisements for the sale of the emblems, and I was told that it was not proposed to take any action.  We know that an avowedly military organisation, which has the use of arms as one of its methods, published an advertisement about the sale of certain emblems, and the editorial column indicated that it was known that portion of the proceeds would be used to purchase arms, and the Minister for Justice is not concerned to see that that advertisement will not be repeated, and he does not care whether they get arms or not.  I assume that there was not a permit granted.  Is the law with regard to the flag-day type of collection repealed?  Is it going to be allowed to lapse?  May every organisation, whether with a peaceful or warlike aim, collect and will there be any police activity against the people who collect?</P>
    <P>Now we come on to Easter week itself.  Deputy Mulcahy said yesterday, and Deputy Kelly seemed to contradict him, that the President of this country found it necessary in his procession to the ceremonial that morning to go by an unannounced route and mainly by back streets, although he was preceded by an impressive military, detective and police force.  All of which was quite proper; the only thing improper about that whole morning was that the President of this country, no matter who he would be, should find it necessary to proceed by a circuitous route unannounced and with a heavy squad of military and police protecting him. It is a shocking state of things that in 1935 this country has come to the point when the President&mdash;I do not care what his personality is&mdash;should have to be protected and should have to change the route announced going to a particular ceremonial.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy suggesting that it is nonsense to say that that state of things could be described as monstrous or that what I have stated is not a fact?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="377" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>He had not to be protected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Justice will answer that.  Is the President being protected at the moment; if so, against whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the point&mdash;is he or is he not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister for Industry and Commerce being protected at the moment, and if so, against whom?  Is the Minister for Finance under protective guard and against whom is he being protected?  Is it the I.R.A., the avowedly military body with the use of arms as one of its methods, or is it not?</P>
      <P>There should be no evasion of that. The President either has these Guards around him as a matter of ceremonial and honour or else as a safeguard against attempts upon his personal security or against his life. Let us know what it is.  I used to be guarded.  It was because the police officers said that I should that I was guarded. I never knew what it was for.  I never was conscious of any reason why anybody should attack me but, at any rate, it was clear that I was guarded, and so were my colleagues guarded by the police against parties and organisations who used arms.  Is that the situation at the moment?  I will have to probe a little bit deeper into this matter of the Easter ceremonials.  In this Hourse there was a motion put down to discuss a meeting of engineers or persons purporting to act in that capacity as members of the organisation styling itself the Irish Republican Army, and as to whether such a meeting was held on Saturday, 10th February, 1934, at or near Parnell Square or anywhere else in the City of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to say with regard to that episode that I regard it, and the releasing of one Gerald Dempsey under peculiar circumstances as the two points upon which will pivot the breaking down of law and order and the morale of the police force in this country.  And I hold, no matter what position may be held here by these <Col N="378" /> people, when the inquiry into the action of the men who set free Gerald Dempsey or into the action of the people in connection with the episode of the 10th February, 1934, in Parnell Square is held, that irrespective of the dignity of any people in the business we will have this inquiry and have the facts out.  We know that the meeting took place.  We know it took place near Parnell Square and it was observed.  No further action was taken.  The Minister says it was necessary to observe it.  We know that people entered No. 5 Parnell Square and with field-glasses looked down upon the meeting that was held in the other premises across the Square.  The Minister did not deny that it was known by the police that that meeting was to take place, and it was known that the object of that meeting was instruction in mine-laying and the preparation of landmines.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That took place over 12 months ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but when we first raised it the Minister said he was making inquiries.  The period during which these inquiries were being made was within the last 12 months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but I think there was a decision in this House about the motion, and the decision was that no inquiry was to be held.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not pleading that the inquiry should be held.  What I am stating is that there was a meeting in Parnell Square to give instruction in mine-laying and the preparation of landmines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not admit that at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister admitted it, but he said that he was certain there was no connection between that meeting and what took place the following day in Dundalk.  He never denied the meeting was held.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>I never admitted the meeting was held.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="379" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has never denied that people were observed by the police at that meeting being given instruction in landmines and mine-laying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>I deny it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister does not agree that they were kept under observation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>No, they were not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say that people entered premises in Parnell Square, and that they were given instruction in landmines and mine-laying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the statement. I will deal with the matter in replying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well.  The Minister, when first questioned on the matter, told us that the meeting was held.  First of all (a) there was a meeting; (b) that the police knew of it; and (c) that they had almost an agenda for the meeting.  We know that at that meeting instruction was given in landmines and mine-laying.  The Minister further told us that there are certain occasions when the only thing called for on the part of the police is observation and that it was not incumbent on the police to raid or arrest.  That is a dictum that is perfectly sound.  In the circumstances, the Minister decided that observation was all that was necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will now take up this matter of the Easter activities this year.  I heard rumours before Easter that an avowedly militaristic organisation had become very active.  We know that the organisation has been attacked in a certain mild way, that the premises of certain men known to be in that organisation were raided and that certain information had been secured by the Government. One heard this information was under three heads: (1) That there was an order that arms and ammunition should be brought to the City for Easter; (2) that documents had been discovered in which the movements of Ministers outside working hours had been very carefully scrutinised and noted down.  These matters have <Col N="380" /> come out in the course of the trials of the prisoners before the Military Tribunal.  It has been stated there in evidence that memoranda had been discovered showing the movements of Ministers and also ex-Ministers; showing that these had been carefully scrutinised, marked and recorded: that plans of at least two military barracks had been discovered.  The first of these things has not come out yet as part of the evidence at the State prosecutions but the other points have always been indicated in any report we got.  I suggest that the three are true.  What is the result of all that?  Is it as a result of all that that the President and the Ministers of the State have to go to the Easter ceremonial by an unannounced route and mainly by back streets strongly guarded by an impressive military guard?  O'Connell Street was held that day by a strong military guard and quite properly if these be the circumstances. I suggest that was not so much for the purpose of memorial to the people who had died but for the purpose of a display of a sufficiently strong force of military to overawe any avowedly militaristic body.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>That is far-fetched. Read the President's speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not far-fetched. This is a deliberative Assembly.  We do know that certain documents, indicating that a certain organisation were taking a not very sympathetic interest in the Minister's movements, have been discovered and put in evidence in charges against prisoners before the Military Tribunal.  We also know that plans and maps of barracks were got and we are assured that it is a fact that the President went to the Easter ceremonial by an unannounced route. There was a route announced previously and that was changed.  We do know that the President went to this ceremonial mainly through the back streets and that he was very heavily guarded and so were the Ministers.  I suggest, too, as the President is guarded at the moment and as some of his Ministers are guarded and quite properly so, that the country should <Col N="381" /> know why they are guarded and against whom.  Is it thought proper to have these guards surrounding the representatives of the Government in this country?  I think it a monstrous thing that in the year 1935 any member of the Government should be guarded. The fact that the Ministers of this country in the year 1935 can be so guarded must be only regarded as unusual, abnormal and monstrous.  The Minister should tell us why they are guarded and against whom these guards are provided.  The Minister tells us he knows all about the I.R.A. We have it from his own statement that within 24 hours he knows all that happens at their secret meetings.  He told us in that statement that he was not going to inquire after them.  The President has burst and upset that statement as put forward by the Minister for Justice.  The Minister for Industry and Commerce has exactly the same view.  In the course of his speech reported in the Press on the 12th March last he saw fit to attempt to soothe the minds of some of his supporters. On that occasion the Minister said:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Members of Fianna Fáil were sometimes disturbed by the fact that the Government had to take action against individuals and organisations who had not accepted the national policy and who took forcible measures to defeat the Government plans.  Everybody had, of course, the right of freedom of opinion and freedom of speech and association within the law, but no minority had the right to try to defeat national policy or to try to defeat Government plans by force or the threat of arms.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is a perfectly sound statement.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;If the Government did not take measures against those who attempted such things, not merely would it fail in its duties as a Government, but it would be failing in its duty as the chosen leaders of the Republican movement operating a policy approved of by the majority of Republicans, who wanted to see that policy fairly tried.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="382" /> His mind is not running so much on the sanctity of government as on the majority of the Republican movement and the Party.  His anxiety is not about the people who are against the Government, the people of anarchical views, as the people who are rather awkward political opponents at the moment.</P>
    <P>When some of these prisoners came to be tried we have again a rather amusing situation revealed.  The counsel briefed for the State, as reported in the <i>Evening Herald</i> of April 26th, said, in regard to one of them:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;This man must have a sense of humour.  He must, in his private moments, his kindly moments, be tickled to consider that he can come here and describe an Act as a Coercion Act, and can, the same man, call upon his men to arm and organise themselves for the purpose, presumably, of making the civilian population accept his views on matters political.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>If that man had a sense of humour he must also have a sense of grievance that a man briefed by the present Government could come to court and tell him that it was illogical for him to describe as a Coercion Act the Act which established the Military Tribunal.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister for Justice responsible for briefing counsel?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going to assert that he is responsible for the events which this prisoner was protesting against.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not responsible for briefing counsel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>He is responsible, I understand, for the members of the force who appeared to give evidence in this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not responsible for the opinion of counsel or for briefing counsel in a particular case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall leave the opinion of counsel.  I want to show <Col N="383" /> that this man, who did in fact protest in this court against what he described as a Coercion Act, had been training and arming people.  That was an allegation which apparently the Military Tribunal believed.  I say it is an aggravation for a prisoner to be faced with that particular set of arguments when he knows that the man who is operating the Act against him has also described that very Act as a Coercion Act while he himself about three years earlier had been trying to instruct these people to arm in order to overthrow a Government.  When these prisoners, who were found with these movements of Ministers detailed and with plans of barracks, were being charged, sergeant after sergeant and superintendent after superintendent was produced, to swear about certain activities of theirs and certain documents found in their possession.  What did the whole evidence boil down to? A statement was made in one case that if these men had only had sense to recognise a particular court they undoubtedly would have put up an argument.  What was it?  That they would have claimed to be the inheritors and the lawful successors of the volunteers of 1916 to 1920.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think it was proper that that should have been suggested as their argument, as I do not think that that would have been their argument &mdash;at least it would not be at one remove.  They would not claim directly to be the successors of the volunteers of 1916 to 1920.  They claimed that they were the successors of the men who claimed to be the successors of the volunteers of 1916 to 1920.  They claimed to be the successors of the men who, when they came into this House here, stated that whatever authority they had previously and whatever continuity they had, the men they left outside could claim the same. Deputy Donnelly must admit that under these circumstances these men can certainly still, on the expression of opinion of President de Valera and his Ministers, claim that they have the continuity which the President had and that they have the same rights as the President claimed to have against <Col N="384" /> a lawfully appointed Government.  I referred to this matter before.  There was a White Paper&mdash;No. P.202&mdash;published which, in the year 1926&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is going very far back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The whole atmosphere of this is that certain people are being arrested by the Minister for Justice and they are putting up a certain defence.  I do not want to defend them, but I want to say with regard to them that until this Government makes its position clear&mdash;I do not care what its past has been&mdash;even starting from to-day, that they have no moral authority against these men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot discuss that on the administration of the Minister for Justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the administration of the Minister for Justice I am speaking about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot discuss a document issued in 1926 on the administration of the Minister for Justice for the financial year which has ended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I put this to you. Speaking on 14th March, 1929, the President, then Deputy de Valera, said:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Those who continued on the organisation we have left can claim the same continuity that we claimed up to 1925.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>He gave them there his seal and authority when speaking in 1929, and they claim to have it still.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing the President's statements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall give you some statements made by the Minister for Justice.  Surely the administration of justice does not depend on what an individual Minister states, but on the Government policy in relation to the administration of justice?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing the administration of the Minister for Justice for the financial <Col N="385" /> year which has closed and the Deputy proposes to discuss a document issued in 1926.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am discussing certain Military Tribunal trials which took place three or four weeks ago, and the evidence then referred to and the relevant matters to that evidence.  These men are being charged at present for certain military activities.  There was a certain military activity which was ordered by the man who is now Minister for Industry and Commerce, and he asked with amazement did anyone suggest that that action of his was invalid?  Surely prisoners can say the same thing.  They can quote the President, who stated that they could claim the continuity that he claimed to have up to 1925.  That is not the only point. There has been produced against these prisoners and made a serious item in the charge that one of them was found with a thing called &ldquo;Governmental Policy and Constitution of Oglaigh na h-Eireann adopted by General Army Convention in March, 1933.&rdquo;  I think there is what is called a fourth impression of this out.  It is really an impressionistic study in a certain type of abnormality of mind that should be noted.  It is an abnormality of mind which was the Minister for Justice's not long ago.  These prisoners when that is produced say: &ldquo;That is Deputy Frank Aiken's Constitution of Oglaigh na h-Eireann,&rdquo; and so it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That is the constitution as amended in 1924-25.  I have compared it&mdash;I cannot say literally&mdash;and it is almost word for word with the one dated 1933, brought in evidence against certain persons, that the present Minister for Defence passed.  The Minister for Defence does not believe that.  Let me remind him of an incident.  Remember that you are charging men at present with breaking the laws of the State; with being an avowedly military body; with the use of arms as one of their methods. Will the Minister for Defence let his mind run back to the time, long after the &ldquo;cease fire,&rdquo; when we were supposed to be getting into constitutional activities, when the courtmartial of the O.C. of the Dublin Brigade was <Col N="386" /> ordered?  For what?  For endeavouring, if you please, contrary to general orders, to start a war without the sanction of the Army authorities, or without even notifying them.  It is shocking play-acting.  That happened. I do not think the man paraded.  He was probably dismissed in ignominy in his absence.  It was alleged in 1925 that he had broken a certain general order by endeavouring to start a war without the sanction of the Army authorities and without notifying them.  Is it not ludicrous to have that said here in daylight of the man who was up to recently Deputy Frank Aiken, and who is now Minister for Defence, by people with their records who, in 1925, got a man court-martialed for endeavouring to start a war without the authority of the military authorities and without notifying them?  There was a second charge which was more serious, that by mishandling the arrangements for this particular little war, that he wanted to start on his own, he had spoiled the chance of success of a similar venture later.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>There were some queer happenings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That was one that did not come off, when a man was courtmartialed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>That will never happen to the Deputy.  He will never be responsible for starting a war.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will never do so against a Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Or against anything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will compare my record day by day with that of the Deputy in Belfast, Dublin and Derry. I am no hero, I am no rebel against authority and do not pretend to be.  I will speak against rebels to authority.  There was the situation of this man, and unfortunate sergeants and members of the Civic Guard find themselves paraded against prisoners who, when faced with the charges, can reply that that is what Deputy Frank Aiken did.  In addition, when one man was charged he said that he would not recognise the court. <Col N="387" /> Surely, the Minister for Defence realises that he also issued another general order, in which he forbade recognition of any judicial tribunal, ordinary or military, by anyone except under three conditions (1) that they had carried out an authorised military act; (2) that the penalty was death; and (3) that General Headquarters had allowed it.  There was that saving clause.</P>
      <P>The President is aggrieved because the use of arms is one of the methods of this avowedly military organisation, but the <i>Irish Press</i> published an advertisement about the Easter Lily, although they wrote editorially that the proceeds were to go ultimately towards the purchase of arms.  Surely, Ministers must know, as the prisoners have hinted, that they could be faced with their own records; that the Vice-President of this country, when writing home on a particular occasion said that it was better to keep the name, Election Fund, over the moneys collected because it added to the belief that the moneys were to be used for constitutional activities, but that privately he propagated the idea that they were to be used &ldquo;for purposes which I need not specify in this letter.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is difficult to know if Ministers have at this moment definitely turned their backs upon their past, and are to get after people who are following in their footsteps, people whom they have described to-day as being misguided. There is the situation I find developing and that I have tried to focus attention on for the last two months, with the historic past evidence in the background.  I want to know what is&mdash;I do not say feared, because I hope they are not feared&mdash;the organisation that is being guarded against. What information has the Minister from his police, secret police or ordinary police, or other agents, as to the strength of certain people and their potentialities for danger?  Are these people going to be definitely countered at last as an avowedly military organisation?  Is the Minister in the future, if there is any sort of I.R.A. meeting, as the man administering justice in this country going to take action?  He should.  If there <Col N="388" /> occurs again an incident such as I investigated in a Parliamentary Question previously, where a certain man was tried by general courtmartial, found guilty and sentenced, will the Minister take action against the people who held this pretence at courtmartial or will he leave them alone? Has the Government definitely decided now, irrespective of what they said at any time, or of whatever their excuses may have been, that there is a changed attitude?</P>
    <P>Are they now in favour of having one Government only in the country and one military organisation?  Will they keep to that for the future?  Or, are the police forces just to be used against people because they are awkward political opponents?  Are they really to be encouraged and to be kept in reserve against those who want a change of Government?  Have Ministers definitely cast off their old skins?  Are they constitutional now?  Can we have any security that courts that have been misused will, even now, be directed against military organisations, and that people will not be paraded on futile charges for refusing to answer questions, when there is apparently available in the files in Government Buildings information that these bodies are out to overthrow the Government by force of arms, and out to collect money for the purchase of arms?  Then we will know where we are.  The Government will want to do that.  Whatever may have been their hopelessness in the past and however much that past may be regarded as weakening their moral authority to take action against old-time colleagues, they will get our full support if we can only get it clear that their past is wiped out, and that they are going to work along different lines in the future.  I have my doubts. about that.  I still think it is only going to be a question of hammering at organisations that are a political danger, that there are not going to be any root and branch methods, or any attack on the principle of getting after these people, because they are, as the President described them, an avowedly military body.</P>
    <P>If it is clear that they are going to <Col N="389" /> act they have immense opportunities and they can get the arms.  The Government could have prosecuted people long ago if, from documents and tabulated returns they have, they thought there was a conspiracy against Ministers.  If they thought there was anything in that, they could have put forward serious charges against them instead of this nonsensical business&mdash;saving their own face and trying to palaver the prisoners at the same time by charges involving not more than three months' imprisonment.  It is time that the Government should take serious notice of the more serious activities of this avowedly militaristic body.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>There was one question which Deputy McGilligan put to the Minister for Justice to-day, and on which I wish to throw emphasis. President de Valera is at present going round this city and country heavily guarded.  There are 10 or 15 men constantly vigilant to protect him from something.  The Minister for Justice is heavily guarded. The Minister for Industry and Commerce is heavily guarded.  Against whom?  It is very necessary that this country should know who it is that constitutes a threat to the lives or safety of the President of the Executive Council and the Ministers of State. It is pertinent for the public to make that inquiry, because if the Government know that the lives and safety of those men are threatened they must know or suspect from what source they are threatened.  Do they intend to tolerate the continued existence in this country of a body of men who they believe would murder the President of the Executive Council if he was not adequately protected by the forces of the State?  If they do intend to tolerate the continuation of such a situation, then we have reverted to barbarism; society has completely broken down.  If the Government has allowed itself to be manipulated into a position in which it tolerates the continued existence of a body which it has reasonable ground to apprehend intends to murder or make a violent assault upon the President or <Col N="390" /> Ministers of State, then the Government has, in fact, abrogated its functions.  In my submission it is a deplorable confession of futility that the Government should submit the President and Ministers of State to the manifest inconvenience of going about surrounded by armed guards, unless at the same time they take active measures to put an end to the threat which makes such armed guards necessary.</P>
      <P>I think the time has very definitely come for the Government to make it clear to all parties in this country that, no matter what their own past may have been, they are not going to tolerate any armed minority in this country attempting to overthrow the elected Government of the majority of the people, nor are they going to tolerate for a single moment any armed minority conspiring to assault or to murder members of the Executive Council, or other persons in the public life of the country; and that while in the interregnum they are prepared to give the necessary protection to prevent murder being done, they look forward to maintaining that protection only so long as it may take them to make a definite end of the organisation which issues the threat that makes that protection necessary. Deputy McGilligan has covered the ground pretty thoroughly, but I think this much must be said, that it is out of evil sometimes cometh good.  I can well remember a great many of the Deputies on those benches protesting at one time that any disorder, violence, or intimidation that was practised against the members of our organisation was really nothing more than the natural indignation of outraged citizens.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Perfectly true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>They have since seen the Minister for Defence pelted with rotten eggs off the streets of Tralee when he was going down about his legitimate business&mdash;conducting a military review on St. Patrick's Day. They have seen the President of the Executive Council hooted and jeered in the streets of Dublin, grossly affronted as he was driving perfectly <Col N="391" /> legitimately through the streets of Dublin, when his passage should have been attended with all the ordinary marks of respect.  They have seen turned against themselves the very self-same methods of insolence, aggression and intimidation that they rejoiced to see turned against us in the past.  They have come to realise that the toleration of such outrage on the persons of citizens is something that is not consistent with the maintenance of Government in this country.  What I regret is that the same indignation was not evinced by the Government when insult and intimidation were offered to a humble citizen as is now being evinced when they are offered to the President of the Executive Council and to the Minister for Defence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The humblest citizen in this State has as much right to go about his legitimate business as has the President of the Executive Council, and he ought to get the same protection. But he did not.  On the contrary, the blackguard and the intimidator were clearly shown that they had the sympathy of the Government so long as they confined their activities to attacking ordinary citizens who were members of our organisation.  It was not until the Minister for Defence was pelted with rotten eggs in Tralee, and until the President of the Executive Council was insulted on the streets of Dublin, that the Fianna Fáil Government began to sit up and take notice. If they had been guided by us when this kind of blackguardism began, those insults need never have been undergone by Ministers of State, because it would have been made clear right from the very beginning that the Government would not tolerate anybody being subjected to insults of that kind when they were offering no provocation to their neighbours.  My mind goes back to an occasion in the town of Ballina, the Minister for Justice's own native town, when his own neighbours came out and conducted themselves like wild animals on the streets. They sought to prevent the holding of a perfectly peaceable meeting, precipitated a riot, threatened me and a <Col N="392" /> large number of other citizens with violence and attacked us physically. For some reason best known to the Minister for Justice, the Civic Guards appeared to be absolutely paralysed in the discharge of their duty.  On that occasion we were well able to defend ourselves.  We did so, and took such steps as were necessary to secure our free passage through the streets, and to disperse the persons who had attacked us.</P>
    <P>As I explained to this House, we forebore to do that until it became perfectly clear that unless we took our defence into our own hands we would be driven off the streets, because the Civic Guards were determined not to extend to us the protection which we were entitled to expect from them.  My friends and myself had good grounds for personal complaint on that occasion, but our personal grievance was trivial compared to the general impression that was created upon the minds of the young people and upon the minds of the Minister's own friends in Ballina that day, because they got the idea into their heads that you can attack and insult persons who are politically opposed to you, and if they happen at the same time to be political opponents of the Minister for Justice you can do it with impunity&mdash;nothing will happen.  No Civic Guard will be allowed to touch you and if there is any subsequent prosecution strings will be pulled and the harm will be taken out of the matter.  Now you are reaping the whirlwind you yourselves sowed in the last couple of years.  Now you have the President of the Executive Council going round with a heavy guard; you have the Minister for Industry and Commerce going round with a heavy guard.  You are suffering from all that because you did not make it clear from the very start that you would not allow anyone, great or humble, in the State to be intimidated. The present situation is one profoundly to be deplored.  It is a relief and a satisfaction to know that whatever steps are necessary to protect the person of the President from insult or injury are being taken.  I think the Minister for Justice is perfectly right in taking every precaution to secure that <Col N="393" /> no assault or insult is offered to his person or to anyone else.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody in the country wants to do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>At the same time the Minister is not doing his duty unless, in addition to providing all the protection necessary, he is taking active steps to make an end of the threat, and to secure that no body of persons shall indulge in such conduct now or hereafter.</P>
      <P>There are some Departmental questions, in addition to the general question of policy, that I want to address to the Minister.  The Minister recently recruited a very considerable number of Guards.  It did seem to me that after all the talk we heard about the supreme importance of the Gaeltacht, and so forth, that greater consideration might have been given to the Gaeltacht in this matter.  I know certain preference was shown, but I have no doubt that the Minister could have drawn more recruits from the Gaeltacht and could have secured that Gaelic-speaking Guards would be sent to the Gaeltacht instead of having English-speaking Guards in Irish-speaking districts.  I think he might have recruited them for the Fíor-Ghaeltacht and insisted on having Irish speakers.  I believe, indeed, he could, without difficulty, have secured a couple of hundred more Irish-speaking Guards, and thereby made sure of having more Irish-speaking Guards in the Fíor-Ghaeltacht and the Breac-Ghaeltacht.  In doing that I believe the Minister would have materially assisted in the development of the language throughout the country as a whole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want now to ask the Minister another question.  I have always been jealous of the reputation and good standing of the Gárda Síochána as a whole in the country.  I think the Minister will agree with me that since he formed a special branch, and took in a number of recruits for that branch some very regrettable things took place.  I am not now calling for very severe discipline upon his part, but I think he has found that some of the new members have not measured up to <Col N="394" /> the standard of discipline expected from the Guards.  I think the Minister has been precipitate in allowing them to undertake public duty without being sufficiently trained in the discipline required for members of the branch.  I have always tried to be scrupulous in talking about the Guards, and not to reflect upon them except where I was able to substantiate the charge, and to make it possible for the Minister to remove the cause of complaint, and not leave it there to be a reflection upon the whole body.</P>
    <P>I referred recently to an incident which occurred at Keadue in County Roscommon.  I mentioned that an outrage was committed there by way of an explosion and that there was a uniformed Guard present when the explosion took place, and that he either took part, or allowed it to pass with his full knowledge.  The Minister said that was the first he heard of it.  But he must have heard since of this explosion which broke a number of windows and damaged the gable of a house.  He must also have heard of the rumour that was circulated in regard to it, and I should be glad that the Minister took advantage of this Estimate and gave us full particulars of what happened.</P>
    <P>I trust when he does so he will confirm what I have said.  There was a rumour circulated very widely throughout the whole district on the lines that I brought to the attention of the House.  I think it is highly desirable that when a case of this character gets the publicity that this got locally, that a full statement should be made to clear the matter up and to satisfy the public mind that whatever disciplinary action is necessary to rectify the matter has been taken and that no continuing scandal exists.  Now, as I conceive it, the Minister for Justice is bound to defend in this.  House every branch of the Department for which he is responsible.</P>
    <P>Recently in the <i>Irish Press</i> newspaper there has been started a hypocritical and fraudulent sort of agitation about indecent films.  Somebody was persuaded to get a county council to start a resolution congratulating the <Col N="395" /><i>Irish Press</i> upon the manly stand it took upon this matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy must know that the Minister for Justice is not responsible for the policy of the <i>Irish Press.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I know, but I think the Minister is bound to see that the film censor for whom he is responsible is doing his work.  If not, the Minister would want to know the reason why and would resent the suggestion of the hypocritical slush which appeared in the <i>Irish Press</i> that the film censor is deliberately allowing indecent films to appear.  Every film that appears must first be submitted to the film censor. If the film censor condemns a film there is a right of appeal to the Board to review his decision.  I believe the common experience of every responsible person in this country is that the general standard of the films shown in regard to indecency or impropriety of any sort is above reproach.  Few of us will agree with the philosophy underlying many cinema dramas or comedies as philosophy but the same would apply to books or novels; but no one suggests because of disagreement with their philosophy that they are in conflict with the ordinary standards of decency or propriety, and that is not for the Government to say either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>Nor for the Chairman of the General Council of the County Councils.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am coming to that.  It is the duty of any body charged with governmental responsibility to see that no public indecency or impropriety shall occur through their administration. As Deputy Coburn interjects, it is a gross insult on the part of the Chairman of the General Council of County Councils or of the <i>Irish Press</i> to start a mare's nest of the kind for which they made themselves responsible, unless they are prepared to go further and say to the Minister for Justice &ldquo;We indict the film censor. He is allowing films to be shown to our young people which are a public scandal.&rdquo;  They would have a perfect right to do that.  But what they have <Col N="396" /> not a right to do is, simply for the purpose of getting a little popular kudos and ranging themselves on the side of the angels as super-purists, to start a reckless and uninformed agitation of a hypocritical and morbid character which prejudices that highly respected public servant who has shown scrupulous zeal in the very delicate task entrusted to his care and implies that he is an incompetent or negligent person.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>It implied nothing of the kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>What else does it imply?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonnDonnelly" hpid="Mr. Donnelly Mr. Donnelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnelly</NameTxt>
      <P>It simply expressed its own opinion on what is a world-wide problem to-day.  In other countries there are pickets out before the picture houses and if a paper deals with that world-wide problem and gives its opinion, it is straining language for the Deputy to suggest that it is looking for kudos.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That exactly explains the confused and silly mentality that is behind all this business.  In the United States you have cinematograph films being thrown on the screens which would bring a blush of shame to the most sophisticated individual in this country, because there is no restriction of any kind there.  The result is that in respect of a certain type of cinematograph film there has been a competition in indecency.  The consequence was that certain public-spirited individuals rose up and said: &ldquo;If the State will do nothing to control this business we shall have to go out and do it ourselves.&rdquo;  They started a League of Decency to bring pressure to bear on the cinematograph proprietors to put an end to this competition in indecency which meant that every actress appearing in musical comedy parts on the screen was stripping naked and that there was no chance of films being taken by a certain circuit of cinema theatres unless half the women in them were skipping round with nothing on them.  That was what was happening and the League of Decency came out and said that must stop.  No provision had been made <Col N="397" /> by the State to check it at all.  Here the Minister for Justice is responsible for the film censorship and every precaution is being taken.  Either the film censor is not doing his job or the <i>Irish Press</i> is talking through its hat. It is talking through its hat simply for the purpose of masquerading as the pious, good, zealous paper that ought to be in the hands of every &ldquo;dacent&rdquo; Catholic man.  The same tripe was started about a Christian Government&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The policy of the <i>Irish Press</i> is not under discussion on this Estimate.  The Deputy has related one matter to the Vote before the House, but he cannot pass on to a general review of the policy of any newspaper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely I am entitled to criticise a critic of the Minister for Justice, and say that far from that criticism being justified, it is the critics themselves who are wrong.  I am pointing out that this same hypocritical business underlies the policy of Fianna Fáil&mdash;the idea of setting themselves up as the only patriots, as the only angels, as the only persons of virtue in the country, everybody who does not subscribe to their view being outside the pale.  I am trying to point out where that kind of policy can bring them. It can lead them into a morass of gross and dishonest misrepresentation and, further into irresponsible attacks, by implication, on public servants who are doing their job and doing it well. These people allow themselves, by their passion for hypocritical fraud, to be carried beyond self-aggrandisement into libellous and slanderous attacks by imputation upon a public official who is doing his work to the satisfaction of the whole community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want the Minister to take up the cudgels on behalf of that public official and to join with me in telling the <i>Irish Press</i> that their campaign is a fraudulent one, done for the purpose of promoting circulation amongst the more ignorant elements of the community, and that we are not impressed by the machined, snowball resolutions sent around with a view to creating <Col N="398" /> this dilemma on the councils: &ldquo;Are you on the side of indecent films or are you not?  If you vote against this resolution praising the <i>Irish Press</i>, you must be in favour of dirty films, and it is a shame for you.&rdquo;  That is what I am agitating for, because that kind of nauseating, hypocritical, slushy fraud is eating the very soul out of this country and we are all afraid to oppose it lest somebody get up and say: &ldquo;He voted against the resolution; therefore he must be for dirty films.&rdquo;  There is not a Deputy on the opposite benches who would not say that but for the fact that I forestalled them and warned them that, if they did, they would be exposed wherever they said it.  I have opened up that ulcer, and I hope the Minister will complete the cleansing operation and make it clear that that kind of fraud impresses nobody.  There is another matter to which I should like to refer&mdash;the arrears in the Circuit Courts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not like to interrupt the Deputy but, on a motion to refer back, it is customary to discuss only general policy.  If the Deputy desires to discuss details now, I take it that the other Votes will not be discussed separately.  It would not be desirable to have duplication of discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>Last year, all the Votes were discussed on this Vote and I understood that the same practice was being followed this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJohnMarcusOSulli" hpid="Professor O'Sullivan Professor O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what was done last year but I know that, when I was on the opposite benches, the general policy underlying all the Minister's activities, so to speak, was discussed on the Vote for the Minister's Office and there was merely a short discussion on the other Estimates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The usual procedure is to have the main discussion on the Vote for the Office of the Minister, questions of detail being dealt with briefly on the other Votes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I shall waive the details and obtain the information I <Col N="399" /> want by way of question to the Minister when we are dealing with the subheads. The general policy has been adequately discussed, and any other matters I desire to raise I shall raise by way of question and answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="400" />
    <Speaker pid="ProfJohnMarcusOSulli" hpid="Professor O'Sullivan Professor O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move to report progress.</P>
      <P>Progress reported.  The Committee to sit again on Tuesday, 7th May.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 2 p.m. until Tuesday, 7th May, at 5 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>