<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="7" Month="Nov" Year="1935" Vol="59" No="4" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 7 Samhain 1935" DateEnglish="Thursday, 7 November 1935" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="595">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="595" /> Do chuaidh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Fair Wages Clause">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Fair Wages Clause.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government and Public Health whether he can state if a fair wages clause is inserted in contracts entered into under the combined purchasing scheme, and whether he will indicate the normal practice of his Department in relation to the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O Ceallaigh) Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O Ceallaigh)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government and Public Health (Mr. O Ceallaigh)</NameTxt>
      <P>The practice of the Department is to ensure that conditions as regards fair wages are observed in these contracts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government and Public Health if he will indicate the local authorities which in practice insert a fair wages clause in contracts entered into by them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTOKelly" hpid="Mr. O Ceallaigh Mr. O Ceallaigh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O Ceallaigh</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as I am aware fair wages conditions are included in contracts of local authorities. If the Deputy will inform me of any contracts to which exception is taken in this respect I will look into the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Town Tenants' Commission">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Town Tenants' Commission.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Justice whether he can state if a decision has been taken to implement any or all of the recommendations of the Town Tenants' Commission appointed in January, 1927.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Ruttledge) Minister for Justice (Mr. Ruttledge)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Ruttledge)</NameTxt>
      <P>The majority of the recommendations <Col N="596" /> of the Town Tenants' Commission appointed in 1927 have been implemented by the Landlord and Tenant Act, 1931.  In so far as the question relates to such of those recommendations as were not implemented by that Act, the answer is in the negative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Does that mean that the Minister or the Government refuses to consider the advisability of setting up a Fair Rents Court?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not mean anything of the kind.  It means that a decision has not yet been reached.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any hope that a decision will be reached inside seven years?</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Kilkenny Gárda Station">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Kilkenny Gárda Station.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesPPattison" hpid="Mr. Pattison Mr. Pattison">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Pattison</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Justice whether he is aware that the existing Gárda station in Kilkenny City has been condemned by the medical officer of health as being unsuitable for its present purpose; whether it is a fact that proposals regarding the renovation of these premises are under consideration by his Department; and, if so, whether having regard to the cost of repairing and reconstructing the building, he will consider the advisability of providing a new building designed especially for the purpose of a Gárda station.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware that the premises occupied by the Gárda Síochána in Kilkenny are very unsuitable, and I have urged on the Board of Works, who are responsible for the provision of barracks for the Gárda, the desirability of providing suitable accommodation as soon as possible.  I have been informed by the Board that no suitable alternative premises are available and that as a suitable site has not yet been acquired some time must elapse before a new building can be provided.  The Board state that they propose to carry out certain works in order to make the present premises as suitable as possible in the meantime.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Armistice Day Celebrations">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Armistice Day Celebrations.</Title>
    <Col N="597" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Justice whether he is aware that at least one daily newspaper has been called upon, by resolution passed at a meeting of the Federation of old I.R.A. Associations and sent to the newspaper, not to publish pictures of Armistice Day celebrations, and what, if any, action he proposes to take in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJosephRuttled" hpid="Mr. Ruttledge Mr. Ruttledge">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ruttledge</NameTxt>
      <P>The information in my possession as regards this matter does not disclose anything calling for Government action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>As I am not satisfied with the Minister's reply, I intend to raise this matter on the adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Prices Commission">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Prices Commission.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether he is aware that as now constituted the Prices Commission is unable to deal expeditiously with the investigation of matters referred to them, and if he is prepared to introduce proposals for establishing the Commission on such basis that a proportion of its members will be required to devote their whole time to the work of the Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that the Prices Commission as at present constituted is unable to deal as expeditiously with the investigation of matters referred to them as could be expected having regard to the nature of such investigations.  I am not satisfied that existing circumstances warrant the adoption of the suggestion that a proportion of the members of the Prices Commission might be asked to devote their whole time to the work of the Commission.  Consideration is at present being given to the question of the amendment of the Control of Prices Act in certain respects having regard to the experience gained from its operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>In what respect is it proposed to amend the Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="598" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Wait and see.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Air Services in Saorstát">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Air Services in Saorstát.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarSeanDoyle" hpid="Mr. P.S. Doyle (for Mr. O'Neill) Mr. P.S. Doyle (for Mr. O'Neill)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.S. Doyle (for Mr. O'Neill)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if it is contemplated in the near future to inaugurate, through departmental action, air services (1) between centres in the Irish Free State, and (2) between such centres in the Irish Free State and Great Britain and Northern Ireland; and if he will indicate when such services will come into operation, and if pending such departmental action he will be prepared to sanction the operation of air services in the Irish Free State by private or public companies worked in conjunction with existing services in Great Britain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It is contemplated that commercial air services will be established in the near future.  The details of the scheme under consideration are not sufficiently complete for a definite announcement.  In the meantime it is not practicable to consider other schemes.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Tobacco Manufacture Rebate">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Tobacco Manufacture Rebate.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state the total amount of rebate (1) at the rate of 7d. per lb. under Section 20, sub-section (3) of the Finance Act (No. 20), 1932; and (2) at the rate of 3½d. per lb. under Section 18 of the Finance Act (No. 31), 1934, paid to licensed manufacturers of tobacco during the year ended 31st March, 1935.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee) Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. MacEntee)</NameTxt>
      <P>The information requested by the Deputy is as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  £13,183 4s. 5d.</P>
      <P>(2)  £38,654 17s. 7d.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that that means that a total of £178,000 has been paid out of the Treasury to certain Irish manufacturers in this case, and that during the same period the total number of wage earners employed in the manufacture of tobacco fell by 108?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="599" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of it.  I have no doubt that I would be if the Deputy had put that question.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Repayment of Income-Tax">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Repayment of Income-Tax.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state the total amount of income-tax repaid under Section 7 of the Finance Act (No. 20), 1932, to holders of certain Saorstát Eireann securities during the years ended (1) 31st March, 1933; (2) 31st March, 1934; and (3) 31st March, 1935.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I would refer the Deputy to the reply which I gave to a similar question by Deputy Norton on the 28th May, 1935 (Official Report, Column 1842).  As I pointed out on that occasion, the first issue of capital in respect of which a certificate under Section 7 of the Finance Act, 1932, was granted was not made until July, 1933, and there were only two such issues, both of them small, prior to December, 1933.  Prior to December, 1934, there were nine such issues.  It must be remembered, however, that in the case of stocks, shares, or securities issued for public subscription a considerable period normally elapses between the date of the prospectus and the first payment of dividends or interest on the issue.  As I stated before, the cost of the relief was nil for 1932/33 and was negligible for 1933/34.  As regards the financial year 1934/35, relief under Section 7 of the Finance Act, 1932, was allowed by repayment or otherwise during that year to the extent of approximately £15.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>When the Minister says that the amount paid in relief in respect of the year 1934 was negligible, are we to understand that it was less than £15?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what the Deputy would regard as negligible, but I think I should regard something less than £15 as negligible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that the Minister gives us the figure for 1935, can we take it that the figure for 1934 which he describes as negligible was less than that amount?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="600" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy may take that if he so wishes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Without being misled by myself or the Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The difficulty is that Deputies do not ask the questions they really want answered. As the Deputy is no doubt aware, claims in respect of this concession may be made any time within six years after tax has been deducted in respect of any of these dividends, and, therefore, the amount of the repayments made during the years I have referred to do not represent the value of the concession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked the Minister for exactly what I wanted&mdash; the amount of money actually paid out.  Is the Minister in a position to state the amount of claims made in respect of these years?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputy may take it that all the claims made have been met.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Unemployment Relief Moneys">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Unemployment Relief Moneys.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether he can make available for the informatiion of Deputies details of his proposals for the expenditure of the sum it is proposed to expend on the relief of unemployment and distress and indicate the sum which will be allocated for this purpose in the area of each local authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. H. Flinn) Hugo Victor Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. H. Flinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>In my statement on the introduction of the Supplementary Vote for the relief of unemployment and distress, yesterday evening, I informed the Dáil of the proposed distribution of the Vote as between different subheads of expenditure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Information on the subject of the allocation of the Vote county by county will be made available for Deputies as soon as possible after final sanctions for individual schemes have been given; but statistics are <Col N="601" /> not collected to show the distribution of the Vote as between the areas of local authorities.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Parliamentary Secretary whether the sum provided in yesterday's Supplementary Estimates is the total sum of money which will be available in the current financial year for the purpose of coping with the serious unemployment problem which exists?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be a matter of prophecy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Some people think the Parliamentary Secretary is a prophet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The whole Front Bench.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary is not included in that number.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Government then ceased to prophesy?</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Damage by Rabbits">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Damage by Rabbits.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarSeanDoyle" hpid="Mr. P.S. Doyle (for Mr. O'Neill) Mr. P.S. Doyle (for Mr. O'Neill)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.S. Doyle (for Mr. O'Neill)</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture if he is aware that the granting of 3d. per head bounty on rabbits exported has not achieved any satisfactory results in the matter of materially lessening the number of these pests; and if he has under consideration any further or better scheme for the protection of crops against the widespread damage caused by the ever increasing number of rabbits in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>There was practically no export of rabbits during the summer months. Since September, however, there has been a considerable increase in the export of rabbits, and a large number of claims for payment of bounty are now being received.  It is yet too early to express a definite opinion as to whether the bounty will effect the desired object.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My Department is keeping in touch with the experiments which are being carried out with the object of destroying rabbits by poisonous gases, but <Col N="602" /> these experiments have not yet been concluded.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister in a position to inform the House if there is any form of quadruped in this country now that it is not the Minister's policy to destroy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We should include bipeds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>You did your best.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Pensions for Connaught Rangers">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Pensions for Connaught Rangers.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is in a position to state the provisions now being made to provide pensions or gratuities for the men of the Connaught Rangers who participated in the pro-republican mutiny in India.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Aiken) Minister for Defence (Mr. Aiken)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Aiken)</NameTxt>
      <P>Proposals are at the moment the subject of consideration and will, without undue delay, be embodied in a Bill to be laid before the Oireachtas.  It is not opportune at this Stage to state what these proposals are in detail.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Scéim do Leathnú">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Scéim do Leathnú.</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraiú</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOgMcFadden" hpid="Micheál Og Mac Pháidin Micheál Og Mac Pháidin">
      <NameTxt>Micheál Og Mac Pháidin</NameTxt>
      <P>den Aire Tailte an feasach do go bhfuil scéim faoi n-a Roinn i dTír Chonaill a dtig le feirmeoirí aol d'fhagháil faoi laigse agus an dtabharfaidh se caoi don mhuinntir atá ag tógáil toighthe faoi Acht na Gaelhealtacht an buntáisde céadna d'fhagháil ón scéim seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasDerrig" hpid="Tomás O Deirg (ar son Aire Tailte) Tomás O Deirg (ar son Aire Tailte)">
      <NameTxt>Tomás O Deirg (ar son Aire Tailte)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is cosúil gurab é an scéim atá luaidhte ag an dTeachta ná an scéim atá ceaduithe ag an Aire Talmhaíochta fé n-a dtugtar deontaisí speisíalta dos na Coistí Talmhaíochta ionnus go gcuirfí ar chumas feirmeóirí aol do cheannach i gcóir talmhaíochta ar phraghasanna laghduithe.  Níor fritheadh aon ghearán im Roinn a rá go raibh sé deacair aol dfháil le hagha tithe do thógaint.</P>
      <P>Níl sé beartuithe buntáistí scéim na gCoistí Talmhaíochta do chur ar fáil d'iarratasóirí fé Achtanna na dTithe (Gaeltacht) óir dá ndeintí sin b'ionann é agus an deontais tógála do mhéadú, rud nach ceaduithe do dhéanamh gan reachtúchán nua.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Col N="603" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>The business will be taken as on the Order Paper from item 8 to item 12 inclusive, omitting Estimate No. 25&mdash;Supplementary Agricultural Grants&mdash;and then items 4 to 6.  If item No. 11 be not reached by 6 o'clock business will be interrupted to take it at that hour.  If the business as ordered be finished, the Dáil will adjourn at 10.30 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 13th November.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the President say when it is proposed to take Estimate No. 25?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the President (Mr. Little) Parliamentary Secretary to the President (Mr. Little)">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the President (Mr. Little)</NameTxt>
      <P>Next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>On Wednesday or Thursday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>That will be a matter for the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we get an answer from the Minister as to what day it will be taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>He could arrange that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we to take it that it will be taken on Wednesday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJLittle" hpid="Mr. Little Mr. Little">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Little</NameTxt>
      <P>We can arrange that afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="League of Nations (Obligations of Membership)" RHead="Bill, 1935&mdash;Committee Stage">
    <Title>League of Nations (Obligations of Membership) Bill, 1935&mdash;Committee Stage.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 2 stand Part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>This, I presume, is the operative section in respect of the Schedule.  I expect that when we come to the Schedule, the ruling will be that the matter is already decided or something equivalent to it.  There are financial measures proposed in the Schedule, under the heading of proposal 2, and the term &ldquo;intermemediaries&rdquo; occurs in paragraph 6.  I should like to know whether any arrangements have been made with banking houses or financial houses, if <Col N="604" /> there are financial houses in this country, as to co-operation in the working of this Bill.  There are in Section 5, some rather severe penalties to which persons who infringe this Act may be liable.  There is a fine in one case not exceeding £100 on summary conviction or imprisonment for any term not exceeding six months or both such fine and imprisonment.  Paragraph (b) says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>On conviction thereof on indictment, to a fine of such amount as the court shall think proper, or at the discretion of the court to imprisonment for any term not exceeding two years or to penal servitude for any term not exceeding seven years, or to both such fine and such imprisonment or penal servitude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As to whether it is the intention to carry out the provisions of the Act and to convict and inflict the penalty for any offence against the Act, we are not given any information and we would like some.  If the intention be to effect the purposes for which the Bill has been passed, then obviously some co-operation or arrangement should be arrived at by persons who are engaged in the particular classes of business, commerce or finance, involved in these cases.  I think the House is entitled to know whether, in the first place, an examination of the problem has been made, whether arrangements have been made to facilitate the working of this Bill when it becomes an Act, and if steps have been taken to avoid prosecutions by perfecting the machinery that will be put into operation so as to prevent any evasion.  Section 4, which we have not yet reached, deals with religious and humanitarian bodies or organisations. Now in another country there have been prosecutions against religious bodies.  It is quite possible that in that country the intention was to have prosecutions.  It is equally probable that the persons who have been prosecuted knew nothing of these Acts of Parliament.  The passing of Acts of Parliament is a very onerous and very responsible task for those engaged in it, and it is not likely that the ordinary man in business takes particular note of the ramifications of <Col N="605" /> Acts of Parliament, particularly such as these.</P>
    <P>I would like to know whether any special precautions have been taken to ensure that innocent persons will not render themselves liable in these cases.  The word &ldquo;intermediaries&rdquo; which, I suppose, is necessary in order to have perfect legislation is a very simple word to insert in a Bill, but does it follow that every bank manager or trader in the country must take precautions to know the exact destination of every commercial transaction that goes through to ensure that, by no possible devious method, no moneys will flow out of this country into the hands of Italians.  I understand that there is a bank in this country which apparently has either the title or may be owned by Italians.  Now, have any arrangements been come to in connection with that particular bank?  I dislike very much the passing of legislation which imposes restrictions on business and which gives no notice to the persons concerned that these restrictions are being imposed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>What does Deputy Cosgrave mean by saying a bank which has either the title or may be owned by Italian citizens?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact that it is so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>What is so?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>That a bank, or a branch of a bank, is owned in this country by Italians, or is under Italian names.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>There is such bank in this country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>That is my information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the President some questions about this section.  I would like to have a clear statement from him for the information of the House and the country, because I would like to tell him that the country is not at all behind this measure.  I would like the President to give the House an idea of what he <Col N="606" /> had in mind when drafting Section 2. If the President has any doubt that the country is not behind this measure. I challenge him and the leader of the Opposition to take off the whips and put this to a free vote of the House. This was done by a convention over 17 years ago when conscription was threatening this country.  Now it is to be run through and imposed on this country under the tyranny of the Party whips.  Sub-section (1) of Section 2 sets out:&mdash;</P>
      <P>For the purpose of giving effect to the scheduled proposals, so far as the same are to be carried out by the Government of Saorstát Eireann, the Executive Council may by order take all such measures, impose all such prohibitions and restrictions, and do all such things as shall, in the opinion of the Executive Council, be necessary in order to carry into effective execution all or any of the measures mentioned in the scheduled proposals.</P>
      <P>Will the President give the House an indication of the measures that he thinks are necessary to do all the things set out in that sub-section? Sub-section (2) of the section says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Whenever the Executive Council makes an Order under the foregoing sub-section of this section the Executive Council may, by the same or any subsequent Order, provide for all such matters and do all such things as shall, in the opinion of the Executive Council, be ancillary or incidental to or necessary for the enforcement of all or any of the provisions of the said Order so made under the said sub-section.</P>
      <P>I would like to know if the President, when submitting these two sub-sections to the House, had his mind made up that if necessary he would conscript the youth of this country?  The President laughs, but it is no laughing matter for the youth of this country to be sold by the President at Geneva who then brings in his bargain to be ratified by this House.  I think I would be in order in quoting the President's speech at Geneva.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="607" />
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy would relate the matter to any of the schedules concerned he would remove the Chair's doubt as to whether he is in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>The President has scheduled in this Bill a number of things that he wants done at the request of Geneva.  I had thought that all authority came from the Irish people, through them from God alone. I do not know whether if what takes place in Geneva comes before or after God in the opinion of the President. It comes in somewhere, but Geneva has ordered the President to do certain things, and he says in these sub-sections that he will take all such measures as are necessary to do these things.  The President is very reticent on this matter.  He laughs when there is a suggestion of conscription.  He is still laughing, beaming, in fact, like the rising moon. He wired from Geneva to Ennis to say that he was going to tell the people of County Clare what he would not tell anyone else in Ireland, but when he went there he did not tell them.  I submit that the President's speech in Geneva is the pledge that he has given.  It is reported by the <i>Daily Express</i> in its issue of the 7th September.  The speech was reported under glaring headlines.  The newspaper report states:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Mr. de Valera, Ireland's delegate to Geneva, yesterday placed his country on the side of Britain in a stirring speech to the League Assembly.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Three cheers for President de Valera&rdquo; and &ldquo;Up the Republic.&rdquo;  I think in this case the President is trying to conceal his mind and to slip through these two sub-sections. Perhaps it would be of interest to Deputies if I read for them what the President said at Geneva.  It would be of interest to members who have not read it or who, having read it, have forgotten it.  It will do no harm to read it for them again to remind them of what he said, and particularly my friend Deputy Norton who offered labour for the shambles in Europe.  &ldquo;We have given our <Col N="608" /> word,&rdquo; the President said, &ldquo;and we will keep it.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="StephenJordan" hpid="Mr. Jordan Mr. Jordan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jordan</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>The report goes on:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;We have given our word, and we will keep it,&rdquo; he said of the League Covenant&mdash;emphasising that should the League act against an aggressor the Free State will find its promise more exacting than most nations.  &ldquo;I come to this tribune with a feeling of deep sadness,&rdquo; began Mr. de Valera.  &ldquo;The speakers who preceded me doubtless have had the same feeling.  For no one can avoid being affected by the contrast between the high ideals and lofty purposes enunciated from this platform&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
      <P>We could say &ldquo;from platforms in this country too.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;&mdash;in former years and the atmosphere of despair which surrounds it to-day.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Look at the Fianna Fáil Party to-day and yesterday and the gloom that is over the benches.  The President went on to say:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;To-day the cynic is our teacher.  Yesterday, when aggressive national policy had been outlawed, our thoughts were busy with the possibility of a union of Europe.  To-day, before the mangled bodies of the youth of this Continent&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is where the President wants to send Irish youth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is making a Second Reading speech. This section deals with the powers of the Executive Council relative to the scheduled proposals.  The Deputy must confine his remarks to the scheduled proposals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we send the Deputy to Geneva to make his own speech there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit to your ruling, Sir, but I want to know what was in the President's mind in moving this sub-section.  I wanted to know how far the President desires this country to go in those matters.  I wanted to show <Col N="609" /> from this speech of the President at Geneva that he had at that time weighed up the whole situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is limited to the proposals scheduled at the end of this Bill.  He may not deal now with the President's speech at Geneva.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall just put my view to you, and if I am not in order you can say so and I shall pass away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy will pass away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Labour Party will have passed away long before I pass away.  The Executive Council are empowered to impose all such prohibitions and restrictions and do all such things as in their opinion are necessary to carry out the proposals mentioned in the Schedule.  By sub-section 2</P>
      <P>the Executive Council may, by the same or any subsequent Order, provide for all such matters and do all such things as shall, in the opinion of the Executive Council, be ancillary or incidental to or necessary for the enforcement of all or any of the provisions of the said Order so made under the said sub-section.</P>
      <P>My interpretation of &ldquo;ancillary or incidental to&rdquo; is that the Executive Council are taking powers to enforce any steps that, in their opinion, are necessary to punish Italy.  If that is not the case, the President has only to say so and I shall accept his statement. I shall not touch on the President's speech further, but it is an extraordinary power for any Executive Council to seek&mdash;the power of life and death&mdash;without coming back to the Parliament.  I think that the two sub-sections should be opposed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>With reference to the negotiations with the banks, as, I think, I indicated yesterday, there have been discussions with the banks. The position was that, almost without legislation, we could be assured that the financial measures set out in the <Col N="610" /> Schedule could be made effective. The contention that every person who may break a law should be warned about the law is a contention that could be made much more effectively in regard to other matters than in regard to this Bill because there is not the slightest doubt that there is machinery in this particular case for spreading information which is not available in other cases.  The banks and banking corporations have been informed of the passage of this measure and they will see that their servants are similarly warned regarding Orders made under the measure.</P>
      <P>This is not a Bill of the type which is passed in a few minutes without previous public discussion of the matters involved.  I do not think that there is anybody in the country who will be affected by the Bill who has not got due warning.  The very fact that this Bill is passed and that its provisions will be available to anybody engaged in operations of this kind must be regarded as sufficient.  The corporations concerned have got notice and I am perfectly satisfied that that notice will be passed on to the officers of these organisations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As to Deputy Belton's contentions. I do not know what he is driving at at all.  If he were a new member coming into the House for the first time I could understand his obvious misreading of the section.  The Deputy has been telling other Deputies that they should read this Bill.  I have very grave doubts that the Deputy has read the Bill because, if he had read the Bill, he would not be making the mistakes he is making.  All we are doing here is taking power to make orders which will render it possible to give effect to these scheduled proposals. The only way I could see conscription looming in any direction whatever from proposals like these would be if we had to conscript young people in order to make the banks carry out their legal obligations when necessary Orders are made.  This is domestic legislation to see that our citizens do certain things.  The only power asked for is power to make these proposals effective as against <Col N="611" /> our own citizens.  I hope the Deputy is relieved of his anxiety about the conscripting of young people.  The banks were consulted in regard to the financial proposals before the question of legislation was decided, and the view was that, even without legislation, we could give effect to practically all these proposals.  The exemptions might, however, be difficult and it was thought better that we should have legislation.  Some unforeseen legal difficulties might arise, and to provide against any such possibility, it was thought better to have the whole thing dealt with by legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The statement has been made that the banks were consulted about these proposals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Were any of the financial houses in this country consulted, or does the term &ldquo;banks&rdquo; denote all the financial institutions? Has any private bank been consulted?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot get into touch with every banking and other institution to consult them in matters of this sort.  There is a Standing Committee of the banks of which the Deputy knows, and they were consulted as well as the Currency Commission, and the question of the application of these measures was discussed with them.  No difficulty was apprehended about the carrying out of these measures.  In the orders that will be issued matters of detail will arise, and these orders will be before the House in due course; it is in the drawing up of the several orders in detail that the point the Deputy raised now might probably be considered. The point is that in general, the people who have been dealing with transactions of this kind have assured the Government that there will be no real difficulty in carrying them out, and that in fact by an arrangement these measures could have been made effective without legislation at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the President consulted the Minister for Agriculture <Col N="612" /> as to whether there are any seeds imported from Italy that cannot be procured elsewhere, and if provision has been made for a supply of these seeds?  I do not know where they could be got.  Is any arrangement to be made whereby these seeds can be procured from Italy after sanctions are enforced?  I am referring to seeds for onions, rye grass, cauliflowers, broccoli, carrots and parsnips.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Which section is the Deputy dealing with now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to know if it is in relation to this section I should raise the matter.  I should like to have some order in connection with the discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, the Schedule to this Bill is in a somewhat unprecedented form.  Will we be in order in discussing this Schedule at all, or will we be called upon to divide?  As far as I can see, after a careful perusal of the Bill, it is purely informative and not supposed to be incorporated in legislation at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Leader of the Opposition said in passing that if questions raised in the Schedules were not debated on Section 2, the Committee might be precluded from discussing them later.  Possibly he had in mind a ruling given by the Chair with reference to a finance measure. On that occasion the matter of the Schedule was fully contained in the section.  If the Deputy cares to consult the records he will find that the ruling was given in reference to one section only.  Discussion of the Schedules to this Bill would be in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair will observe that the Schedule of this Bill is in quite an unprecedented form.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>And that it will arise on five proposals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Each proposal may be discussed separately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="613" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it your ruling, sir, that the question I put to the President is in order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It would more properly arise on the Schedule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>If I raise it on Proposal No. 3 will I be in order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>That proposal deals with the importation of Italian goods?</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 3 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I should be glad if the Minister for External Affairs would indicate exactly what &ldquo;humanitarian body&rdquo; is indicated.  Will that term be confined strictly to charitable organisations doing work analogous to that of the Red Cross, or will it include learned institutions and such other bodies as are engaged in educational activities?  Will it include such bodies as the National Museum, the National Gallery or the Royal Irish Academy?  Is it the intention of the Government to make an order setting out by name the bodies in this country which it is proposed to exclude under this section, or is it rather the intention to set out a series of bodies and allow each case to come up for consideration as to whether it belongs to the scheduled classes, with their obligations?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>This exception only refers to two bodies.  The Deputy appreciates that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the question as to what is covered by the word &ldquo;humanitarian&rdquo; I do not know that there is any very strict definition which would enable us to determine straight off what exactly the term includes.  I know that in Geneva the example given us was the Red Cross, and it was in that connection I raised the question of religious bodies.  We felt that <Col N="614" /> religious bodies at any rate would not ordinarily be covered by the term &ldquo;humanitarian,&rdquo; and it was decided therefore in connection with this matter that it should.  That is in regard to proposals in general that were accepted in Geneva.  What particular activity might be strictly classed as &ldquo;humanitarian&rdquo; here will be a question I am afraid for later decision.  The intention at any rate was to refer to charitable organisations like the Red Cross.  Then when you come to charitable organisations, you have a wide question to determine what &ldquo;charitable&rdquo; is.  If there is any doubt the matter can be made clear in the orders that will be issued.  The general intention is that &ldquo;humanitarian&rdquo; should cover the Red Cross and the activities of organisations of that sort of charitable character.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true that the extent of the section is not very alarming, because it purports to exonerate humanitarian and religious bodies from obligations under Section 2 (1) which would arise largely on the issue of a loan to the Italian Government. I think the Minister for External Affairs will agree with me that it is a very undesirable principle to carry into legislation that we should exempt or even risk exempting any body of persons without having secured knowledge of what that body represents.  We are now asked to exclude religious and humanitarian bodies, but no Deputy knows what these words mean.  I recognise that the list was prepared pretty quickly, but I suggest that in its present form, it is a very undesirable legislative departure, and that the Government should take steps at an early date to prepare a schedule, defining clearly what is meant or what they desire by these two terms, and later to lay that list on the Table of the House for discussion, if necessary, within the 21 days prescribed in a later section.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 5 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="615" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to get some information about this section. Take it that there is a person in this country who feels strongly in connection with this matter, and who is desirous of assisting, as far as he can, one of the two nations now engaged in hostilities.  He might send a subscription of £5 to an Italian National Loan that might be on the market.  He is liable, if he is prosecuted and convicted on indictment, to a fine of such amount as the court shall think proper or to seven years' penal servitude. That appears on the face of it to be a rather serious liability for an offence of that sort.  I am prepared to admit at once that if this is the law it should be subscribed to but I do think that there should be some measure of justice in apportioning a penalty of that sort.  I do not quite understand what is the reason for setting out in paragraph (a) the punishment on summary conviction, and in (b) the punishment on conviction on indictment.  It is not explained what particular offence might be dealt with under summary jurisdiction.  On the other hand, it is not set out what are the offences that are likely to be dealt with on indictment.  We have in this country I think a number of persons who have Italian blood in their veins. Perhaps their grandfathers were Italian.  They might feel strongly on this matter and they might send out a subscription to a national loan.  I think that most people would agree, even though they were disobeying the law by doing that, that it is rather severe to render them liable to a penalty of seven years' penal servitude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>There is an additional point to that put forward by Deputy Cosgrave, which arise in an entirely different sphere.  Many people in this country had the experience, when the condition of Austria and Germany was very bad as a result of the war, that they had friends there who were in very needy circumstances. It happened at that time that very many learned people there were very glad to take assistance from outside people, so as to enable them to continue either at their studies or at their work.  That might happen again in <Col N="616" /> connection with friends of Irish people in Italy or in connection with Irish students in Italy.  I should like to ask the President if sub-section (4) of Proposal No. 2 would mean that it is an offence punishable under the terms of Section 5, to send a £1, a £5 or a £20 note to Italy to a personal friend of somebody in this country who was in very needy circumstances brought on by the operation of these sanctions, or whether it would operate in the case of an Irish student studying in Rome to whom remittances might be sent from this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>By way of loan?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Sub-section (4) states:&mdash;</P>
      <P>All banking or other credits to or for any public authority, person or corporation in Italian territory.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Credits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>If you send a postal order or send a draft on a bank to a person in Rome it mdy be called a credit.  I want to know whether for the purposes of this section it is a credit.  If it is sent by money order, by cheque, or in any other way, will a person who sends a friend in Rome £5, whether he be an Italian or an Irish person, be liable to conviction and punishment under Section 5?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>The question that has been raised is rather interesting. That matter did occur to me before, but my view of that is that that would not be a credit transaction and would not come within the intention of these proposals at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not so much concerned with the intention as to what the actual wording means in point of law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Deputy knows, the fact that we here say that is the intention does not make it so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as I can interpret the terms here, I would interpret them as meaning that such transactions, which I would regard as direct cash transactions, would not <Col N="617" /> come under this proposal.  I do not know if it would be so decided in court.  That is the difficulty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>From the point of view of being skilled in law, the legal institutions of the country would regard myself and the President as being on the same level in interpreting this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I take a different view from that of the President and I cannot help feeling when I read here of &ldquo;all banking or other credits to or for any public authority, person or corporation in Italian territory&rdquo; that that means any kind of transmission of money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I put it to the President that, if it does not mean that, the whole thing is inoperative, because if it does not mean that, instead of carrying out the transaction by creating a credit in favour of an Italian corporation or person, all we need do is to get a roll of bank notes, send them to Italy and thus avoid the creation of a credit and avoid coming within Proposal No. 2 of the sanctions. Surely the sanction must mean that we are to suspend financial relations with Italian corporations, persons and institutions.  To do that we must suspend every kind of financial relationship or else loopholes will arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I can only tell you that in the minutes and discussions, it was made clear that the type of transaction to which Deputy Mulcahy referred was not to be covered here. I take credit as meaning money loans in one form or another, and this is to prevent loans being made or credits established.  In regard to a transaction such as the sending of money from this country to a student, I do not think such a transaction would be covered by the terms of it at all. It might be advisable to make it clearer but one cannot define every term. We have to work on the usual connotation of words and it would be <Col N="618" /> altogether impossible to make any progress if we had completely and absolutely to define at every step the full content of every word we use. Credits and loans arc used in a certain sense, and my opinion in connection with all this&mdash;and as I say the minutes and discussions will prove that the view I am expressing would be the general intention of the committee which passed these proposals&mdash;is that these words do not cover transactions such as referred to by the Deputy. In the orders we shall attempt to make it clearer than in the general terms of the statute what class of transactions are referred to.  The orders will be the operative part. Power is being given here to make orders to get certain things done.  The provisions here indicate the general intention, and in the orders an effort will be made to indicate the type of transaction that is forbidden.  We are not here to define these things.  We are giving powers to make orders, and if there is any objection taken to any of the orders, it can be dealt with here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Has this Section 5, dealing with offences and penalties, been adopted by every other State member?  Are these the penalties that are imposed in other countries or are they in excess of them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>They are less.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not deal with that question.  I only dealt with the meaning of credits and the class of transactions we intended to be covered and forbidden.  With regard to the penalties, the penalties in their nature have to be substantial because you may be dealing with offences here which might run up, say, to a loan of £1,000,000 or something like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>We can dismiss that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot dismiss that.  That is exactly the type of transaction which one has to look after.  I do not see how the Deputy can say we can dismiss it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="619" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Because we are not going to lend £1,000,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Because the Deputy knows nothing about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I am a child in these matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>You are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>And the man who is talking is a younger child.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Some of us sat in places where we were able to form an opinion of the wisdom or childishness of certain Deputies.  We need not go into that.  The point is that there are transactions forbidden here of such a character that very substantial penalties must be available.  I have said that transactions like the loan of £1,000,000 could very well take place which we might have to deal with if we did not have substantial penalties available.  That is the reason that the penalty is left at the discretion of the court.  No maximum is laid down because nobody can definitely state what is the amount that might be involved in an offence against this Bill when it becomes an Act.  The amount of the fine, therefore, is left at the discretion of the court.  There can be a fine of any amount in the discretion of the court in the case of an indictment and imprisonment for two years or penal servitude for seven years.  We have to depend upon the court to assess the punishment or the penalty in accordance with the offence when it is an indictable one.  In regard to a case dealt with by summary conviction, the fine will also be at the discretion of the court, but not exceeding £100 or imprisonment for six months.  That is, I am informed, less than the penalties laid down in other countries in regard to the same proposals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>The President has not answered a rather interesting point raised by Deputy Dillon&mdash;is there anything under this Bill to stop, shall we say, Deputy Esmonde from sending Signer Mussolini a present of £10,000 in currency notes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>While the President is digesting that one, I will ask the <Col N="620" /> Attorney-General if he will lend a hand and let us know if there arc any precedents in legislation for giving a court the power to impose an indeterminate line, or would the precedents not indicate that the fine should be measured by so many times the amount of the profit that might have accrued from the transaction, or something like that? I do not care to give any court the power to impose an unlimited fine.  It seems to me to be a loose kind of way of legislating.  I will be interested to know from the Attorney-General if he has any precedents to lay before the House for that form of penalty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>There are several precedents leaving the amount of the fine indeterminate.  That difficulty was considered when this particular section was being drafted and, after consultation with the Minister for External Affairs and his Department, it was decided that the only satisfactory way of dealing with a case which might arise is to leave the amount of the fine open.  That is made clear.  In the Order in Council made on the other side of the water in connection with this particular type of legislation the amount of the fine is also left open.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any precedent in Irish legislation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>There are precedents in plenty in legislation which applies here.  Deputy Cosgrave asked a question about making the punishment fit the crime and instanced a transaction in which a £5 note or £5 in value was involved.  His difficulty is answered by sub-section (a) which leaves it to the district justice to treat the offence as a minor one.  The maximum penalty in that case is £100, and the district justice can deal with it as leniently as he wishes.  The indication is given that the maximum fine is to be £100 and the maximum imprisonment six months for a minor offence.  The Order in Council made in England with regard to this type of offence allows, on summary conviction, imprisonment for 12 months, or a fine not exceeding £500, or both such imprisonment and fine, <Col N="621" /> so that the measure of the penalty which the district justice can impose on summary conviction is on a lower scale here.  If the charge is a sufficiently serious one to have it preferred on indictment, the maximum penalty is seven years.  Deputy Cosgrave seemed to suggest that the section fixed seven years as the penalty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>No, seven years is the maximum.  I know that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="The Attorney-General The Attorney-General">
      <NameTxt>The Attorney-General</NameTxt>
      <P>The amount of the fine is left open.  As the President indicated, there is no way of measuring what may be the amount involved in breaches of orders made under the Act.  They may amount to a very large sum.  We can only leave the matter entirely at the discretion of the court, and I do not see any reasonable objection to that being done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Personally, I think the whole thing is far too elaborate. The British scheme says £500 fine for a lower court and imprisonment for 12 months.  Whatever likelihood there is of a prosecution over there, there is very little likelihood of a prosecution here.  A look at the Schedules would satisfy one that, so far as the first one is concerned, unless the goods come from England, they are not going to be exported from here. We have not the means of producing these goods here.  In fact, they are produced in very few countries.  As regards borrowing £1,000,000, nobody-outside a lunatic asylum would ever think that Italy could borrow £1,000,000 from this country.  The Dublin Corporation wants £1,000,000 very badly.  Here we have £1,000,000 handed out.  It is almost going.  In order to prevent its going we must impose a penalty of seven years' penal servitude.  That is a joke.  No person who would get seven years would do it.  The thing will be over before that time.  We ought not to put ourselves in a ridiculous position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I suppose it is no use replying to the Deputy in matters of that kind.  He will come up with the same simplicity and pretence of <Col N="622" /> wisdom.  The fact is that, if it were not for this Schedule a number of these transactions, which the Deputy says could not be carried out, would be carried out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Including the £1,000,000 loan?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  If a country in a state of war wants credit very badly and if there is on the part of those who have the money sufficient inducement in the way of interest and the possibility of repayment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Two very important items.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>But they have occurred.  There have been loans to States which have won and to States which have been defeated in war.  I think the Deputy is making himself ridiculous by suggesting that you might not have loans of that amount. In regard to the other question of goods that we would have to import, they could be re-exported if it were not for this Schedule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as the loans are concerned, in the first place, no country which took part in the war and borrowed money paid back the money they borrowed.  No country did so.  Take the best of them.  Take France.  France borrowed money from England and from other countries in 1916 when the franc was 19 to the £ and is paying it back when it has been up to 120 in the £. Now people want their money back and their interest on their money also, and I suggest that the idea of a transaction, involving £1,000,000, with Italy in such circumstances, is absolutely nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>All the financial experts at Geneva were simpletons, if so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Money is not got as simply as the President seems to think, and to suggest that £1,000,000 could be got so easily for such a purpose as this, in my opinion, is the greatest joke the President has yet attempted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="623" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Apart from that, the President has not yet told us how he proposes to stop a benevolent citizen of Saorstát Eireann from presenting Signer Mussolini with a note from his roll of notes, or to stop an anxious mother from sending her son in Italy some money for his studies, or to prevent a devoted friend from sending a subscription to an embarrassed friend in Italy suffering from the sanctions already imposed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Dillon should ask Deputy Cosgrave where this generous friend, with the indeterminate roll of notes, is to be got.  At any rate, I do not think that a sum of money, given as a gift, is covered, in fact, by this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it the intention of the President to cover it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>His intention is, simply, to cover the resolutions that have been passed by the representatives at Geneva and to see that powers are given to the Executive Council to implement these proposals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot believe that it was the intention of the Minister for External Affairs, or of the other Ministers at Geneva, to do something which is manifestly ineffective.  What is the use of prohibiting anybody from lending money to any Italian if a perfect defence to the indictment or charge of lending money is to say: &ldquo;Not at all, I gave it to him as a gift&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>All right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That seems to be the President's idea.  I wish to assure the President that I have no desire to embarrass him.  I have taken the view already that this Bill, in itself, is all right.  I only want to clarify the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that, perhaps, Deputy Cosgrave can answer Deputy Dillon's point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no need to get excited about it.  I only want to clarify the point, but I suggest <Col N="624" /> that an early consideration should be given to the difference between a loan, a credit, and a gift; and that urgent steps should be taken to ensure that a gift made for the purpose of circumventing these sanctions should be brought within the scope of the Bill; and that, if needs be, a licensing system should be established&mdash;that is a thing I do not often advocate in this House.  I am prepared to advocate a licensing system&mdash;from which the Minister for Industry and Commerce will be strictly excluded&mdash;in order to provide for the necessary gifts that must be made to such people as ecclesiastical students in Rome and certain other persons similarly circumstanced in the normal course.  I am sure that that is the intention of the Government, but it is a matter to be considered calmly.  If the President does not get vexed and shake his locks at me, it will probably be considered better and the solution of it will more readily come to hand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy not aware that if a gift is a disguised credit it will be dealt with as such, and will be covered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>With a view to clearing up the point, I take it that it is not intended to cut off such Irish charities as there might be existing at present in Italy or as might be in the habit of passing to Italian friends; nor, I take it, is it desired, at this particular moment, that we shall cut ourselves off from Italian culture and influences.  There are bound to be Irish people carrying out studies of one kind or another in Italy.  Section 4 says that:</P>
      <P>No Order made by the Executive Council under this Act prohibiting or restricting any of the transactions mentioned in Proposal 2 of the Scheduled Proposals shall apply to or affect any transaction with or for the benefit of any religious or humanitarian body or organisation.</P>
      <P>I will ask the President, on Report, to take an amendment to that, which would make it read as follows:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That it shall not apply to or affect any transaction with or for <Col N="625" /> the benefit of any religious or humanitarian body or organisation, or any private transaction with a charitable or humanitarian purpose.</P>
    <P>I am accepting the President's outlook as to what is meant here with regard to the word &ldquo;humanitarian,&rdquo; which might be educational or anything else which it might be necessary to cover.  If the President would accept an amendment such as I have suggested, I think that it would set the minds of people at rest and would make it perfectly clear that none of the orders to be issued would prevent or interfere with a transaction of the type I have mentioned.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with that, the President might also consider what would happen supposing somebody in Italy should win £30,000 in the next Hospitals Sweepstake. Would he be able to collect the money, supposing the sending of money to Italy was prohibited by law?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems that Italians will buy no sweep tickets.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Deputy Mulcahy's suggested amendment, I do not think it is necessary. I think that is a matter that can be dealt with in the orders.  After all, this is only an enabling Bill, the purpose of which is to enable us to make certain orders and we will have these suggestions carefully considered in the making of the orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, it must be remembered that the President was not able to assure us in the beginning whether such a transaction would be covered by Proposal No. 2 or not, whatever about the Order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but the whole question will be a matter of the interpretation of these proposals so as to make them effective.  I was able to give the Deputy, so far as my recollection of the minutes goes, what was the intention, and we will endeavour to carry them out that way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Personally, I am satisfied with the President's assurance <Col N="626" /> that it is not the intention to include any such transaction in such an Order as would render the people taking part in such a transaction liable for the punishments under Section 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, that is so.</P>
      <P>Section 5 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make a point in connection with Section 6 before we leave it.  Section 5 provides penalties upon any person who may commit any act which is a contravention of an Order made by the Executive Council, and Section 6 here makes provision that where an Order made by the Executive Council is objected to by either House of the Oireachtas within the next subsequent 21 days, the Order shall be annulled. In the meantime, it is possible that a person may have been charged and convicted under the Order.  When you are dealing with a situation like this, there is, no doubt, a desire and, perhaps, a necessity on the part of the Executive Council to proceed with speed where offences against any of these orders are found, and there is a possibility that a person may be convicted of an act in contravention of the Order, before the period of 21 days had passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy will excuse me for a moment, has the President got a copy of the proposal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Therefore, I think it necessary to make provision in a Bill such as this to meet that point. My point would be met by the insertion of a new section after Section 6, and I therefore move, with your permission, Sir, the following amendment:&mdash;</P>
      <P>On page 3, after Section 6, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Where a person has been convicted of any act under Section 5 which is a contravention of an Order of the Executive Council under this Act and such Order is annulled under the previous foregoing section, such conviction shall be forthwith quashed and any sums paid by way of fine <Col N="627" /> refunded, together with the amount of any costs incurred in connection with his trial by the person so convicted.</P>
    <P>Under Section 6 as it is it seems to me that a person who had been fined and whose fine had been paid would not be able to recover the amount of the fine paid for the section says that:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Such Order shall be annulled accordingly but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under such Order.</P>
    <P>I do not wish to oppose Section 6 because I think it is necessary that the Order should be presented to the House, but before passing from Section 6 I would ask whether the President would not see the necessity of passing this new section so as to enable a refund of any sums paid by way of fine in cases where it was afterwards found that the Oireachtas had not approved of the Order under which the fine was imposed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>From one point of view it is hard to resist the amendment proposed by the Deputy.  On the other hand, I would rather this amendment was not inserted in the Bill, because the Order would be in force at the time of the offence at any rate.  It is not for a private citizen to assume that an Order that has been legally made will be revoked by the Oireachtas.  I do not think it is right that because it happened that his view coincided with the view of the Oireachtas afterwards &mdash;that such an Order should not have been made&mdash;that he should be released from the obligation to obey the Order. I think that the proper way to deal with this would be to assume that if such an Order had been issued and annulled the Executive Council would exercise its prerogative to deal with the case.  I think from the general point of view that would be much better.  As regards validity, the point is that afterwards if the Orders were not held as valid&mdash;say they were revoked subsequently&mdash;there would be a question of looking for an indemnity and making claims for compensation and so on.  I admit that the Deputy can <Col N="628" /> make a case for the amendment, but I think on the whole it is better from the point of view of practical principles that a case like that, such as the Deputy has in mind, should be left to the Executive Council to deal with it.  I am sure the Executive Council would consider the pros and cons of the case.  One of the things that would have to be borne in mind in coming to any such decision would be &mdash;what right had a person who committed the offence named to assume that the Order under which he was fined was not going to be concurred in by the Oireachtas&mdash;that, in fact, that Order was going to be ended by the Oireachtas?  I do not think it is right to suggest to any citizen that he has a right to make such an assumption. I think on the whole that if I have to give a decision I would say &ldquo;No.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The President has admitted that he has taken very extraordinary powers under this Bill. This is a case where the court can fine the person any particular sum.  I quite see the President's point, but I feel that this is a bigger danger to run, in times of heat or anything else like that, than to accept the amendment. We would have the Executive Council standing over the withholding from a person the amount he was fined and that because his case had been conducted in such a spirit as brought about a certain amount of feeling in the Oireachtas.  If a person is guilty of a crime like this, or an offence against an Order like this, and that Order is afterwards found to be invalid why should not the fine be refunded?  The President, I think, contemplates the starting of a political agitation that would get some House of the Oireachtas to turn against the Executive Council and I quite see the objection to that; but I also see that the case could be conducted in court in such a way as would have the same effect.  The Executive Council would be, I think, almost morally bound to return the fine as well as the costs of the case. I think it is better to have it definitely set down in legislation that this House is not going to hold a very substantial fine from a person under an Order <Col N="629" /> with which the House itself had decided it did not agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I can only put the other principle against the point of view expressed by the Deputy&mdash;that the citizen in question will have been adjudged to have broken the law as it existed at a particular time, and that the citizen had no right to assume that this Order, under which he was convicted would be annulled by the Oireachtas.  He had, in fact, committed an offence and would have been punished for the offence.  If there had been no law against that particular thing there would be no offence, but laws are made and offences thereby created.  Sometimes the laws are repealed, and what may be an offence under a statute, when that statute is repealed may not be an offence at all. While I appreciate the point the Deputy has made, I must resist the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I think really the question is somewhat an abstract one because the liability arising is not very great.  I take it from what the President has said that if the Oireachtas did, in fact, reverse an Order made by the Executive Council and if some person suffered because of a breach of that Order the Government, unless there was an intention to create a public scandal by his action, would introduce proposals to give him back his fine and indemnify him against any loss suffered.  I understand that was the President's view &mdash;that that was the proper way to do it rather than to hold out a standing invitation to anybody to set the law at defiance in the hope that the Oireachtas would support him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>In all the circumstances I would not feel like saying what the Executive Council would do. The whole circumstances would have to be considered.  The point that has been made by Deputy Mulcahy and which has also been referred to by Deputy Dillon is a point which would naturally be taken into consideration by the Executive Council.  If there was clearly a case where an injustice would be done that injustice would be <Col N="630" /> remedied in so far as it was possible to do it by the Executive Council.</P>
      <P>Amendment withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 6 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to raise one point on Section 7.  It will be necessary to introduce a repealing measure when the necessity for this Act no longer arises.  Of course, it would not be advisable to have it permanently on the Statute Book.  Has that been considered?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>That matter has been considered.  Obviously there is a difficulty in determining the whole question of the duration of this matter That is a thing that cannot definitely be foreseen and we think it is better to leave this matter quite indefinite and not to put in any date or anything of that kind.  This will lapse, I will not say automatically, but so far as its effect is concerned it will lapse.  When the need for applying this Act disappears, if it is necessary to bring in a repealing Bill, that will be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It surely is the intention of the Government to repeal this Act when the necessity for it passes and not leave it permanently on the Statute Book?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>No definite term can be set for the operation of this Act. We cannot know at the moment when it is likely to cease to operate.  When the occasion for it disappears, then a Bill can be brought in repealing this Act, or the Orders can be immediately revoked.  We can revoke the operative part.  of the Orders or repeal the Act altogether.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>The Act will have to be repealed.  If it were allowed to remain on our Statute Book, would it not make a show of us?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>There are a number of obsolete things already on the Statute Book, I am afraid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>But this is sufficiently fresh to warrant some attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the President accept an amendment setting out that this Act will operate for three years and then cease?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="631" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think we should set any definite term at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the President expect it to last long?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not say.  I hope it will not last a month.  I hope the occasion for this will disappear at once, but we cannot tell.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>If it lasts longer than three years the President will not be over there to repeal it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we should consider putting in a clause that, if the necessity arises, the Executive Council can, by Order, which would be laid on the Table of the House, cause the Act to lapse.  There would be no necessity for a repealing Bill then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think there is any need for that.  There will be no difficulty in bringing in a short Bill ending this.</P>
      <P>Section 7 and Proposals 1 and 2 of the Schedule agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>On Proposal 3, I would like to repeat the question I put on an earlier stage, whether the President has consulted with the Minister for Agriculture as to where farm and garden seeds, so far procurable only from Italy, can be got in the event of this portion of the Schedule being adopted?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Aiken) Minister for Defence (Mr. Aiken)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Aiken)</NameTxt>
      <P>What are they?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Certain kinds of rye grass.  Does the Minister suggest there are no seeds imported from Italy that cannot be obtained elsewhere?  I think the Minister knows as much about this as he does about making a watch.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We will grow grass, anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I merely ask the President if he has consulted the Minister <Col N="632" /> for Agriculture on the subject.  I am sure the President will see that it would be worth his while to consult on the matter with the Minister for Agriculture. If my statement is found to be wrong, then that is all there is to it.  I happen, however, to know there is substance in my question; otherwise I would not have asked it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankMacDermot" hpid="Mr. MacDermot Mr. MacDermot">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacDermot</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it relevant on this Bill to consider where, in the future, we will get the types of articles that in the past we have been getting from Italy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid not.  That is a matter for the Minister for Agriculture on another occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>When the introduction of this Bill was arranged, we approached the various Departments of Government, including Industry and Commerce, Agriculture, Justice and Defence.  All these Departments were notified and memoranda were submitted from them with regard to the effect on the sections of the community with which they were associated. All these things were carefully considered.  I have here a memorandum dealing with the imports from Italy.  I can tell the Deputy that anything indicated here in connection with seeds is almost negligible&mdash;the amount down here is negligible.  With regard to Deputy MacDermot's statement, he must remember that if there are hardships imposed as a result of the passing of this, it is our duty to bear them.  That is one of the difficulties about these things &mdash; certain hardships have to be borne.  Other countries have to put up with similar hardships.  An effort is being made to try to minimise the hardships by co-operation amongst the countries concurring in the imposition of the sanctions.  It is vain to think that you can completely avoid any hardships. You cannot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It so happens in this case that the amount of hardships we will be suffering will be comparatively small compared with the hardships other countries will have to face.  With regard to articles imported from Italy, a certain amount of inconvenience will <Col N="633" /> have to be borne by members of the community, but this is one of the things we have to suffer for the security that is in the League of Nations, to the extent that it is in the League of Nations.  That is what membership of the League of Nations means. It means that to achieve a certain good, a certain object, nations are prepared to stand together and, if needs be, each one of them will put up with a certain amount of inconvenience and hardship in order to provide the security which the League is intended to provide.  You cannot get out of all hardships in connection with this, but I think the amount that we will suffer here will be comparatively slight in contrast with other countries. With regard to agricultural imports, on looking through the list I find that in the case of seeds for feeding purposes the amount is almost negligible.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I mentioned seeds for seeding purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>Evidently that is so small that it did not merit mention at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>Then the position is this, that if there are types of seeds that we have been importing from Italy and we cannot get them anywhere else we will have to do without them&mdash;is that it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The President The President">
      <NameTxt>The President</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a complete answer and I am sure that is some information for the Minister for Defence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is the absence of rye grass seeds from Italy that breaks the Irish farmer's back, we can give up talking about the last straw.</P>
      <P>Proposals 3, 4, and 5 of the Schedule agreed to.  Schedule and Title agreed to.  Bill reported without amendment.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="634" /> Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.  Message to be sent to the Seanad accordingly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickBelton1927" hpid="Mr. Belton Mr. Belton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Belton</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to be recorded as opposing the final passage of this Bill, as I opposed the Second Reading of it yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WillianRKent" hpid="Mr. Kent Mr. Kent">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kent</NameTxt>
      <P>As I, also, opposed the Second Reading of the Sanctions Bill yesterday I wish to record my dissent from its passage now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Both Deputies will be recorded as dissenting.  But, the Bill having now passed, there can be no further discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Conditions of Employment" RHead="Bill, 1935&mdash;Recommittal">
    <Title>Conditions of Employment Bill, 1935&mdash;Recommittal.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 87:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 17, Section 42 (2), in line 53 and also in line 57, to delete the words &ldquo;purporting or claiming to be.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is one of a number of amendments to Section 42 and they all hang together.  This is really a drafting amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 88:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 17, Section 42 (2), line 54, to delete the word &ldquo;concerned&rdquo; and substitute the word &ldquo;interested.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>This appears to be an alteration of Section 42.  I am really referring to amendment No. 87 but the same remark applies to amendment No. 88.  I thought there was an entirely new section coming along.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No, the new amendment relates to sub-section (4) of Section 42.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>The following amendment was agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>89.  In page 18, Section 42 (2) line 1, to delete the word &ldquo;employed&rdquo; and substitute the word &ldquo;interested&rdquo;.&mdash;(Aire Tionnscail agus Tráchtála.)</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="635" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I have here an amendment&mdash;amendment No. 90:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 18, Section 42 (2), line 6, to delete the words &ldquo;one or more of&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This is to require that any agreement to be registered must be registered at the request of both parties to it.  Previously the Bill provided the Minister could register at the request of one of the parties.  Arising out of the discussion in Committee, I agreed to amend the section so that the consent of both parties would be required.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>What does the Minister say is the purpose of this amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite prepared to withdraw it if there is any objection to it.  I am not very keen on it.  I introduced it because I thought it was urged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>By whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>By the Labour Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no enthusiasm for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Bill is better without it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Then I am prepared to withdraw it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Does it still mean agreement amongst the parties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment being moved?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not moving it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Then we cannot discuss it.  The Minister must have the consent of the House to withdraw it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment withdrawn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It has not been moved.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 91 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 91a.:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In page 18, to delete Section 42 (4) <Col N="636" /> and substitute a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(4)  Whenever an agreement is registered in the register, the following provisions shall, on and after the date on which such agreement is so registered and for so long thereafter as it continues to be binding on the parties thereto, have effect in relation to such agreement, that is to say:</P>
    <P>(a)  such agreement shall be binding on every employer concerned in the form of industrial work in the area to which such agreement relates and on every worker or, where such agreement relates only to a class of workers, every worker in such class employed in the said form of industrial work in the said area;</P>
    <P>(b)  it shall not be lawful for any such employer to employ or pay any such worker at a rate of salary, wages or other reward which is less than the rate provided by such agreement and applicable to such worker;</P>
    <P>(c)  if any such employer employs or pays any such worker in contravention to the next preceding paragraph of this sub-section, such employer shall be guilty of an offence under this section;</P>
    <P>(d)  subject to the provisions of the next following paragraph of this sub-section, every such worker shall, notwithstanding any contract to the contrary, be entitled to demand from and be paid by and to recover from his employer salary, wages, or other reward at the rate provided by such agreement and applicable to such worker;</P>
    <P>(e)  nothing contained in this sub-section shall operate to prevent any such employer from employing or paying any such worker salary, wages or other reward at a rate greater or more beneficial to such worker than the rate provided by such agreement and applicable to such worker, or operate to prevent any such worker who is so employed at such greater <Col N="637" /> or more beneficial rate of salary, wages, or other reward from recovering from his employer salary, wages or other reward at such greater or more beneficial rate.</P>
    <P>The amendment is one which caused considerable difficulty, not merely in the drafting but, also, in the minds of certain people interested who read into the sub-section what was not intended to be there.  Whether in fact it was there or not is another question.  The purpose of the whole section is to ensure that when an organisation, of employers, representing a majority of the employers, in a particular industry, and an organisation of workers, representing the majority of the workers in the same industry, come to an agreement as to the rates of wages that should operate, then that agreement may be presented to the Minister for Industry and Commerce for registration. If accepted by him and registered, the wages specified in the agreement become enforceable throughout the whole industry; and a minority of employers, not already in the agreement, become liable to pay those rates of wages to their workers, or at any rate liable to pay not less than those rates of wages to their workers.  Three attempts have been made to get the agreement into a form to which no objection would be taken.  The difficulty, I frankly admit, was due to my desire that the enforcement of the agreed rate of wages should not be the obligation of the Department of Industry and Commerce.  All the difficulty in framing the new section was due to the fact that I was anxious to provide that the enforcement of the agreed rate would be something the worker himself would have to undertake without the assistance of the Department.</P>
    <P>I have come to the conclusion that it is not practicable and that the ways by which an agreed rate could be evaded are so many, that unless it is made an offence by law, in the ordinary way, the whole scheme could not be operated. The significance of the new amendment is that it proposes to make it an offence for the employer to pay less than the registered rate of wages. There is one possible further amendment <Col N="638" /> required and it is on a matter upon which opinions may differ.  The new sub-section (4) proposes to provide that when an agreement was registered the following things may happen: First, all such agreements shall be binding for every employer in the class of work to which the agreement relates, and secondly, binding upon every worker as well.  It is in relation to the second paragraph that I think a further amendment would be necessary, because, as Deputies who read the amendment will notice, there is no penalty provided for the worker if he accepts less than the agreed rate.  Of course, the prospect of the increased rates of wages being evaded arises from the possibility of collusion between the employer and employee. It is not inconceivable, in certain circumstances. It is considered that it shall not be lawful for any employer in any industry concerned, to pay less than the agreed rate.  If he pays lees than the agreed rate he is guilty of an offence, and the worker is entitled, on his own behalf, to go to the courts and recover the amount that he is being underpaid.  And it is provided that nothing in the section shall operate to prevent an employer paying a higher rate, or of making it impossible for the worker to recover the agreed higher rates through the courts in the event of the employer not following up his contract.  I think this section is now completely operative. I think it gets over the objections which were raised to the original sub-section, and the only query in my mind in that connection is whether it is necessary or desirable that we should have another paragraph providing that it would be an offence for the worker to take less than the agreed rate.  I think it would be a safeguard to have that, although it looks rather strange to enforce by legal penalties on the worker his obligation to get the registered rate of wages.  At the same time one cannot ignore the possibility of that situation arising in particular circumstances. I think this amendment is a decided improvement on the original sub-section (4), whereas the amendment which I proposed originally, and which is embodied in the sheet of amendments, is open to a possible <Col N="639" /> interpretation which would nullify it altogether in so far as it does not appear to make it invalid or illegal for an employer to pay less than the agreed rate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesWalterBeckett" hpid="Mr. Beckett Mr. Beckett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beckett</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister mentioned in his explanation the term, &ldquo;if accepted and registered.&rdquo;  What is the implication of that?  Is the Minister going to accept in some cases and not accept in others?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite possibly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesWalterBeckett" hpid="Mr. Beckett Mr. Beckett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beckett</NameTxt>
      <P>On what lines will he exercise his discretion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot say that now. There may be circumstances in which the Minister would refuse to register an agreement.  I will give you an example.  Assuming that there was an organisation of employers which was acting in competition with a number of other employers in another part of the country where different circumstances prevailed.  The agreed rate, although applicable to the factories of the organisation of employers, and although they were an actual majority of the total number of employers in the industry, might nevertheless be unfair to those outside the association.  I do not say that will happen often.  The only circumstance in which I can see it might happen is where a prevailing practice to recognise a lower standard rate in rural districts as against city districts was to be wiped out by the proposed agreement, and it was considered desirable to preserve it.  That not infrequently happens even under the Trades Board Act at the present time. Very frequently, a trade board unanimously recommends rates of wages for the trade with which it is concerned, and on those recommendations coming to me, as Minister for Industry and Commerce, I refer them back, pointing to particular parts of the proposals to which I take objection, and asking them to reconsider those proposals.  Not infrequently the proposals are reconsidered, and sometimes amended, to meet legitimate objections put up to them.  Precisely the same circumstances might arise in <Col N="640" /> relation to the agreed rate of wages. The third party coming in might see something objectionable which the parties to the agreement had not observed, but might be prepared to rectify if brought to their attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesWalterBeckett" hpid="Mr. Beckett Mr. Beckett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beckett</NameTxt>
      <P>An agreement would not, therefore, be a legitimate agreement until it had the Minister's imprimatur?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>An agreement, if made, is an agreement, the same as an agreement between employers and workers at the present time is an agreement which is acted upon.  The only difference between the present-day agreement, if I may call it that, and an agreement which is registered, is that the rate of wages specified in the registered agreement becomes legally enforceable upon everybody engaged in that form of work, whether or not they are parties to the agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister stated that he was considering whether he would impose a penalty on the worker for accepting less wages.  I do not know when he proposes to come to a decision on that point, because in other parts of the Bill it seems to be the practice that where it is an offence for the employer to do a particular act in conjunction with the worker it is also an offence on the part of the worker.  I do not know when he proposes to let us know his decision on that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another matter about this wages register agreement which is not quite clear from the Minister's remarks.  Of course we can all understand that there might be some minor points in the agreement between two bodies to which some exception might be taken by the Minister, possibly very properly, and which might be amended.  From the Minister's remarks on this section previously it appears as if he were contemplating merely to take the wages rates out of the existing agreement, and to enforce those.  I do not know what he proposes to do with the rest of the agreement. Does he propose to ask the employers and workers, in a case where they have both agreed, or where one of them agreed in other instances, <Col N="641" /> to merely forward an agreement as to wages?  When this Bill was previously under discussion the Minister said, as reported at Column 406 of the Official Debates:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The purpose of the Agreements Register is to ensure that, where agreements are made between a majority of employers and representatives of the workers, the minority of employers will have to conform to them.  That is the purpose of the register.  It relates only to rates of wages and not to conditions of employment, which would be a more difficult thing to enforce.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That, to my mind, opens an extraordinary door to evasions of this section, because the Minister can quite easily conceive that the workers, in return for a concession in one direction, might accept a lower rate of wages, and, in return for some other condition, look for higher wages.  To illustrate what I mean, take for instance the various boundaries of the City that the workers have to be on at a certain hour of the morning. Everybody who is conversant with those trade agreements knows that bargaining goes on, in which possibly a smaller boundary might be considered in some way in the wages or some other concession.  I should like to ask the Minister whether he proposes merely to take the wages out and abandon everything else, because I think then it will not be very long until he finds that various sections of employers are working under entirely different conditions.  Another matter which the Minister will readily understand is that in a trade agreement demarcation lines for various trades are drawn.  Does he propose to abandon those, because, if so, he may find himself confronted with a worker who demands a rate of pay in respect of which somebody else would contend &ldquo;You are not allowed to do that class of work under an agreement&rdquo;?  I cannot see how he is going to pick what he wants out of the agreement and throw the rest there.  I can quite understand that there might be some clauses which he will take objection to and ask to have reconsidered, but if <Col N="642" /> he proposes merely to take the wages rates out of an agreement between two bodies, employers and employees, and throw the rest there, I am afraid he will find confusion worse confounded in industry.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am trying to explain the position to the Deputy.  So far as Section 42 is concerned, and it is the only section of the Bill which relates to wage rates, there is this essential difference between it and the other sections of the Bill, that nothing can happen under it on the initiative of the Minister for Industry and Commerce.  The initiative must be taken by the representatives of the employers and of the workers, and until they have agreed, either to the rates of wages or to request reconsideration of the agreement, nothing happens.  It is only when they have, or one of them has, come with an agreement to the Department dealing with rates of wages and it is registered, that anything happens under the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So far as the rest of the Bill is concerned, it deals with conditions of employment in respect of which action can be taken on the initiative of the Minister for Industry and Commerce irrespective of whether the parties, one or both, in any trade want him to do it.  The desires of the Minister for Industry and Commerce, implemented by regulations, deal with the things specified in the Bill, such as hours, of work, holidays and so forth.  There may be other things, and frequently are other things, mentioned in trade agreements between workers and employers which are not dealt with in this Bill and which do not relate to rates of wages.  In so far as there are, the position in respect to them is being left unchanged.  These agreements are operating at the present time, but they are not legally enforceable and the position in respect of them will be precisely the same in the future as it was in the past.  When this Bill is law there will be power to implement agreed rates of wages under Section 42 and power in the Minister for Industry and Commerce to impose conditions relating to all the <Col N="643" /> other things mentioned in the Bill, but no power to interfere with things not mentioned in the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Minister has not answered my difficulty. I quite agree with him that, as he has pointed out, his functions do not begin until an agreement which has been, in the first instance, come to between employers and employees is presented to him and, very possibly, presented to him jointly by employers and employees, but I should like to point out to the Minister that apparently&mdash;and he has not answered tho point&mdash;he proposes to take only rates of wages out of those agreements and make them enforceable on other bodies of employers and possibly employees also.  I would point out to him that that could be reduced to a farce, if you do not take into consideration the other conditions.  I mentioned, for instance, the case of a city boundary. Suppose, for the sake of argument, a body of workers were paid 1/6 per hour on the basis of an agreement reached jointly and that the Minister found that certain other employers were not paying that rate and says, &ldquo;You will have to pay that rate, 1/6,&rdquo; and then discovered that they had imposed conditions compelling a man to be in Bray at 8.30 in the morning to work for 1/6 an hour.  I submit that that would make a farce of the wages rate.</P>
      <P>There are a number of other conditions of the same sort, and once the Minister takes the wage rates into consideration, I cannot see how he can avoid taking the other conditions into consideration.  Certainly in bargains with regard to rates of wages, one frequently hears that a boundary can be cashed for a halfpenny or a penny and that other considerations have a cash value and I submit to the Minister that if he leaves this section in this state he is going to make a farce of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely these are all matters that will be dealt with in the agreement presented for registration?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but are they going to be enforceable on the people <Col N="644" /> to whom the Minister refers&mdash;the new comers&mdash;or are merely the rates of wages to be enforced?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has not mentioned anything that does not seem to me to relate to rates of wages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I have mentioned a boundary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Even in respect to that matter, an agreement could provide for the payment of different rates in different areas and in different circumstances and that agreement would be enforceable in that respect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Will all those conditions of labour be enforceable?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>In so far as they have a bearing on the rates of wages, yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will appreciate that those effects on the wages will become more and more shadowy.  There are some things which would have a cash value and others which will merely have a bearing. I do not see how the Minister is going to pick a certain set of conditions out of that register and make them enforceable on newcomers and leave the rest out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister felt-that an agreement was not sufficiently specific and, therefore, not capable of effective enforcement, he presumably would refuse to register it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure the Minister that, on the contrary, he will find quite the opposite in a lot of instances, although he may find that some are not very clear.  In the case of registers that are perfectly clear, I would suggest to the Minister that his interpretation and his own words on an earlier section are too narrow a definition of this section to make it workable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that under this section, if it is provided that a rate of wages of 1/6 per hour is to be paid and certain other conditions to be fulfilled, that portion of the agreement relating to wages would be something which must be adverted <Col N="645" /> to in ascertaining whether that rate is being paid by other employers in industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>And while I think that, so long as this section stands in its present form, it would be easier if the rate stood independent of the conditions, you will probably have experience of the section if a position is created where there will be a desire on the part of both workers and employers to make the wage rates as far as possible independent of any other conditions upon which at present these rates are based.  I think it is clear from the section that the only thing that would be registered is the portion of the agreement relating to wages and such other conditions as directly relate to the payment of that rate of wages.  There may be, of course, as Deputy Dockrell has said, a case for some more extensive codification of conditions which might be registered and be enforceable.  But, at all events, this section is limited in its activities to wages, and I think Deputy Dockrell will admit, even looking at the matter from the employer's side, that that is one of the features of industrial activity in which unfair rates of wages imposed by one employer are not only harmful to workers but definitely harmful to employers who endeavour to pay a reasonable rate of wages to their employees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister on producing this amendment and on the conversion which it indicates.  He can now look Stalin straight in the face, feeling convinced that he has not enshrined in our legislation here a bourgeois subterfuge of the standard wage which he looked in grave danger of enthroning in our legislation if the section, as previously introduced, stood.  My objection to it then was based on the fact that it seemed to tie workers down to a standard rate of wages.  Now, I am glad that the Minister is providing that it ties them down just to a minimum rate of wages and the tying is mainly in respect of the employer, not even in respect of the good employer, but in respect of <Col N="646" /> the bad employer, because in the section, as now drafted, there would be an agreement negotiated between the workers on the one hand and the employers on the other.  When that agreement is registered, all the employers in that form of industrial activity will be required to pay the rates of wages provided in the agreement as the minimum.  There will be nothing in the agreement compelling a worker to accept that rate of wages if he can get a higher rate.  That makes the Bill much more beneficial than it would have been if the Minister had not moved in the direction of the terms of his amendment.</P>
    <P>I think that the section, as now amended, is a very valuable one.  It is a valuable contribution towards making the Bill effective.  It is valuable, also, in the sense that it puts into legislation the intentions indicated by the Minister in his Second Reading speech, namely, the intentions underlying Section 42 and, in the main, the whole Bill.  I think this amendment will overcome all the objections which, I know, the Minister has heard from the workers' side during the discussion on this Bill.  It will also be much easier to administer the Bill as amended.</P>
    <P>On the point as to whether a penalty should not be imposed on a worker who conspires with an employer to accept a lower rate of wages than that provided for in the agreement, I think that most people who stand for fair conditions of labour would accept an amendment of that kind.  As Deputy Dockrell and Deputy Good probably know, the building industry is one of the industries where, very frequently, small employers employ workers under conditions which do not at all compare favourably with the conditions recognised by big employers in the industry: where there is a certain amount of secrecy imposed upon the workers not to disclose to other workers, even in the same industry, the rates of wages which they are being paid.  All that secrecy is enforced not for the purpose of assisting the worker, but rather of concealing from an employer's trade rivals the low rates of wages which are being paid on contracte which, in many cases have been tendered for on <Col N="647" /> the assumption that better rates of wages would be paid.  I think anything that would prevent a conspiracy of that undesirable kind between workers and employers is all to the good, and I would encourage the Minister to present an amendment on the Report Stage making it an offence for workers to engage in such a conspiracy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesWalterBeckett" hpid="Mr. Beckett Mr. Beckett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beckett</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister, on considering the matter further, will see the necessity for dealing on very broad lines with agreements come to between employers and employees.  In the trades which have these agreements they are the outcome of long years of negotiation.  They have gradually developed down through our own time.  In the case of any big trade there is no agreement which does not take in the conditions of employment as well as the question of wages. Deputy Dockrell, when speaking a short time ago, referred to the various provisions in these agreements.  You have provisions relating to demarcation and so on.  If these provisions are not to be recognised in the registered agreement, diffisulties will arise that it will be no easy matter to settle.  New industries may spring up and the demarcation clauses will not be enforceable on them.  That will immediately handicap, through unfair competition, those in certain trades who are bound by agreements.  At present employers and employees may not depart from the terms of their agreements except by mutual agreement. What is to be the position if a new entity comes into the market, a new employer of labour, and that he is doing the same work under completely different conditions from those bound by the agreements?  If the whole agreement was registered that would be impossible.  If, however, only the portion of the agreement relating to wages is to be registered, very great difficulties will be created.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Minister has not considered the effect of his reply on certain trades.  Deputy Beckett and I know a good deal about particular trade, a trade in which <Col N="648" /> there are quite a number of agreements. I think there are 11 or 12. Those agreements only apply to the City of Dublin, so far as that trade is concerned.  Different agreements apply in other districts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Any area can be specified in the agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister would want to define the area.  It has been pointed out already that in the case of those agreements relating to Dublin there is a line drawn around Dublin so that any man working inside that line gets a certain rate of wages.  If he is sent to work outside that line he gets walking time, if no other means of locomotion is provided.  The Minister, therefore, can see that in a particular area there may be a very considerable difference in the rates of wages paid.  The Minister says that he will take wages out.  In the case of those agreements if you take wages out of the context they have no meaning. Take, again, the position with regard to the City of Dublin.  There is a certain wages paid inside the city and there is a certain wage paid outside the area, which is an agreed area.  The further a man goes outside that area a different wage operates. The rate with regard to walking time is different.  That, in effect, amounts to a different wage, so that if you take the wages laid down in the agreement out of the context chaos will immediately be created.  The only way to get over that difficulty is to register the whole agreement or register none, because all these other points to which I have adverted turn on the question of wages.  There are wages of apprentices, depending on the different years in which they are.  These will all be important matters.  There are tribunals set up for dealing with the point to which Deputy Beckett referred &mdash;the demarcation of labour and the encroachment of one trade upon another trade.  These arrangements are all essential.  Every other day points arise upon them.  It is essential to have them for the proper working of the trade.  I ask the Minister either to take the agreements as a whole&mdash;I do not see any advantage in registering <Col N="649" /> them, but if there be an advantage let them be registered as a whole&mdash;or not register them at all.  Certainly one part should not be taken out of its context and registered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will register the agreement presented to him.  If there is a question of splitting up an existing agreement into two parts&mdash;one dealing with rates of wages and the other with other conditions&mdash;the splitting up has to be done, not by the Minister for Industry and Commerce, but by the parties to the agreement.  They may present for registration a complete agreement dealing with wages and matters having a bearing upon wages.  As Deputies know, frequently matters are included in agreements which have no relation at all to rates of wages. Probably the most common clause&mdash;a very useful one&mdash;is that which requires employers to employ only members of named trade unions or of a named group of trade unions.  That particular provision in the agreement has nothing whatever to do with rates of wages, but it is not at all uncommon. I do not think we should undertake the obligation of enforcing these clauses by statute.  Yet they are part and parcel of many of these agreements. There are frequently other clauses relating to matters which do not bear directly upon wages.  A number of these will be covered by regulations made under the Bill.  These regulations may deal with hours of work, holidays or any of the other matters mentioned in the Bill. Although these particular items in the agreement may not be implemented under Section 42, it is not merely possible but very probable that when the agreement relating to wages is registered under Section 42 simultaneous registration under the sections dealing with these other matters will be brought into operation, so that the maximum amount of registration desired by the parties concerned in the industry can be effected.  I agree that most of the matters you find in these agreements relate to rates of wages, and in so far as they do, they can be covered by the agreement that is registered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="650" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Minister is speaking with want of experience.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I have seen a fairly large number of these agreements&mdash; and disagreements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>I have seen a fair number, too.  If you take all the items, wages are a very small part of the agreement.  I strongly urge that the wages item should not be taken out separately.  These agreements are of vast importance.  They are essential to the working of the trade and they should be taken as a whole or not at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree&mdash;the wages items.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>No, not the wages items. The wages are only part of the agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>They are the only part we can enforce.  May I mention another type of clause which you get in these agreements&mdash;the clause which lays down the procedure to be followed before a man can be dismissed, his appeal from the immediate boss to the factory manager or works manager. Again, I could not undertake the responsibility of seeing that these particular clauses were enforced.  That will have to be done in the way it is done at present&mdash;by representatives of the unions and employers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>I am endeavouring to assist the Minister to make this Bill workable.  The line on which he is now proceeding will create chaos.  If you register an agreement, it should be taken as a whole.  Then, the different clauses under it will be enforceable.  Otherwise, it should not be registered at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I could not agree to that.  I could not undertake to enforce clauses other than clauses relating to rates of wages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister will look into the matter, he will, I think, find that what I suggest is essential to the working of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>If we were to undertake to enforce trade union clauses, <Col N="651" /> the obligations that would arise would be very considerable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister is going to take one clause out of an agreement and enforce it, he is going to have trouble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to take any clause out of any agreement.  The only agreements considered for registration will be those presented complete by the parties.  They can have separate agreements on other matters if they like.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Then, the Minister is going to proceed to cut the agreements up?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  The agreement will be registered as a whole or it will be refused.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>What is enforceable on the other employer or what is the object of all this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Whatever is in the agreement.  If the agreement deals with matters other than rates of wages or matters that have a bearing on rates of wages, then it is not capable of registration at all under the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Minister will find that there is nothing in these agreements but what is of vital interest to the two parties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>They can deal with matters other than rates of wages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite so.  I can conceive that there are certain questions with which the Minister may not want to interfere.  At the same time, the Minister is leaving this section very much in the air.  His own words seem to suggest that wages and nothing else are to be taken into consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Under Section 42, that is correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>It relates only to rates of wages and not to conditions of employment, which would be more difficult to enforce.  There are a lot of other items to be considered&mdash;demarcation of the boundary, country money, walking money, and various other matters.  I do not see how, if your contention is to prevail, there are not <Col N="652" /> going to be two sets of employers&mdash; the employers who are parties to the wages agreement and the employers who respect the agreement, so far as wage rates are concerned, in the spirit only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Most of the matters the Deputy has mentioned appear to me to relate to rates of wages, even though they may be rates which would prevail only in exceptional circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Minister comes to a decision I think he should look into the matter.  I can clearly see that there will be chaos in the building trade if he goes ahead with his proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Deputy, or Deputy Beckett, would send me samples of the type of clauses which appear in these agreements which they would like to have enforceable in this way.  We could then discuss the matter with greater knowledge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>I undertake that we shall bring the whole matter of these agreements before the Minister and show him the difficulties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That will enable us to understand precisely what the trouble is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesWalterBeckett" hpid="Mr. Beckett Mr. Beckett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beckett</NameTxt>
      <P>We will give a clause with pleasure right away.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 92 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 93:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 18, Section 42 (6), line 53, after the word &ldquo;register&rdquo; to insert the words and letter &ldquo;the following provisions shall have effect, that is to say:&mdash;(a)&rdquo;, and in line 57, after the word &ldquo;registered&rdquo; to add two paragraphs as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(b)  the Minister shall cause notice of the registration of such agreement in the register (with such particulars of such agreement and such registration as the Minister shall think proper) to be published in the <i>Iris Oifigiúil</i>;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(c)  any person may obtain from the Minister, on applying therefor <Col N="653" /> in the prescribed manner and paying the prescribed fee, a copy of the copy of such agreement retained by the Minister under this section.</P>
    <P>This amendment and the next one hang together and are designed to meet a particular objection voiced on the Committee Stage, that there was some danger that the Minister might accept as an organisation representative of employers, or more particularly of the workers, one which was not properly acceptable as such.  Consequently, we are proposing to provide that where the agreement is registered it shall be open to any person to object to its registration in the High Courts, on the ground that the employers' signatories were not substantially representative of the employers, or that the workers' signatories were not substantially representative of the workers.  The purpose is to give the right to object in the High Courts to any person who feels that something has been done which should not be done, on the grounds that the parties were not properly representative.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say what fee he has in mind to be paid for a copy of the agreement that has been registered?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be hard to say.  I think it will not be very much, just sufficient to cover the expenses of providing a copy of the agreement.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 94:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 19, before Section 42 (8), to insert a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(8)  Whenever an agreement has been registered in the register, any person may, within one month after the publication in the <i>Iris Oifigiúil</i> of notice of such registration, apply to the High Court in a summary manner for the annulment of such registration, and on the hearing of such application the High Court may, if it is satisfied of either or both of the following matters, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="654" /> (a)  that the employer signatories to such agreement were not, at the date of such agreement, substantially representative of the employers interested in the form of industrial work to which such agreement relates in Saorstát Eireann or, where such agreement applies to part only of Saorstát Eireann, in such part of Saorstát Eireann; or</P>
    <P>(b)  that the worker signatories to such agreement were not, at the date of such agreement, substantially representative of the workers or the particular class of workers to which such agreement relates employed in the form of industrial work to which such agreement relates in Saorstát Eireann or, where such agreement applies to part only of Saorstát Eireann, in such part of Saoratát Eireann,</P>
    <P>the High Court may annul the registration of such agreement in the register.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 95:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 19, Section 43 (1), paragraph (b), line 35, to delete the words &ldquo;rate of salary, wages, or other reward payable &rdquo; and substitute the words &ldquo;average weekly earnings payable in a normal full working week.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This amendment deals with Section 43 and is designed to correct an error in drafting.  The purpose of Section 43 was to provide that where the hours of work were reduced, either automatically on the passing of the Bill or in consequence of regulations, the reduction in hours shall not operate to reduce the earnings of workers.  The phrase used in the Bill is &ldquo;rate of salary, wages, or other reward payable.&rdquo; That is obviously a different thing from what we had in mind in framing the section.  What we had in mind was the average weekly earnings rather than the rate.  You could have the rate maintained but the actual earnings reduced if the hours were reduced and, consequently, this substitute has been brought forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="655" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesWalterBeckett" hpid="Mr. Beckett Mr. Beckett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beckett</NameTxt>
      <P>This is taking 48 hours as the standard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  If a worker has been paid, say, 50/- a week for a 48-hour week and if an order is made reducing the working hours to 44, it is proposed that he will still continue to get 50/- weekly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesWalterBeckett" hpid="Mr. Beckett Mr. Beckett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beckett</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that there is no power taken to change the minimum.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>For young persons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There is power in Section 44 to effect reductions in the 48-hour week for particular trades.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Some trades work a longer period in summer than in winter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That can be provided for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister understands that workers in these trades do not get the same money in winter as in summer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We are merely providing that whatever is normal will continue despite a reduction in the normal working hours.  That will be taken to include the normal position, having regard to all the circumstances, the time of the year, and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>But we will not know the total weekly rate for the summer months or for the winter months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is a reduction I think the normal for that period will determine the calculation under Section 43.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>That will be understood, then, in accepting this amendment. On reading it, it would appear that the Minister intended to reduce the hours in winter, but that the wages would be as in summer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment only relates to the section in which the hours are reduced by an order made in the Bill.  If they are reduced for any other reason this section has no relation. It is only when a specific order is made that the section comes into operation, or when the Bill by automatic <Col N="656" /> operation effects a reduction.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 96:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 19, Section 43 (1), paragraph (b), line 36, to delete the words &ldquo;remain unchanged&rdquo; and substitute the words &ldquo;not be reduced&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 97:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 20, Section 44 (2), to delete all from the word &ldquo;rate&rdquo; in line 36 to the end of the sub-section and substitute the words &ldquo;average weekly earnings payable in a normal full working week to any person whose hours of work are reduced by such regulations shall not be reduced merely because of such reduction in his hours of work&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This is also a substitute for the same type of phrase that has been referred to in other parts of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>The following amendments were agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 20, Section 44 (3), lines 43 and 44, to delete the words &ldquo;persons who are in his opinion representative&rdquo; and substitute the word &ldquo;representatives&rdquo;. &mdash; (Aire Tionnscail agus Tráchtála.)</P>
      <P>In page 20, Section 44 (3), lines 45 and 46, to delete the words &ldquo;persons who are in his opinion representative&rdquo; and substitute the word &ldquo;representatives&rdquo;. &mdash; (Aire Tionnscail agus Tráchtála.)</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 100:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 20, Section 44 (4), line 50, after the word &ldquo;section&rdquo; to add the words &ldquo;and such worker shall also be guilty of an offence under this section.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This section puts an obligation on the worker as well as the employer.  It is the same as was effected throughout the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 101:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="657" /> In page 21, Section 45 (1), line 6, to add at the end of the sub-section a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(e) notice of every agreement registered in the Wages Agreement Register which affects any workers doing industrial work on such premises.</P>
    <P>This is a new provision which provides that among the notices which must be displayed by the employer is the agreement in relation to rates of wages, if such agreement has been registered.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 102:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 21, Section 46, line 16, to delete the word &ldquo;by&rdquo; and substitute the words &ldquo;or reasonably proper by the actual occurrence or the threat or reasonable anticipation of&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This is an amplification of the definition of emergency circumstances in which a departure from the provisions of the Bill is permitted without a penalty.  It was represented that it was not merely sufficient to provide that the provisions of the Bill should be departed from owing to fire, storm, breakdown of machinery or any other emergency, but also that the work done was required.  It is agreed that the definition of &ldquo;emergency&rdquo; is now sufficiently wide to cover all possible contingencies.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 103:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 21, Section 46, to add at the end of the section a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(2)  A certificate signed by any Minister that an act done by or in relation to any person employed by such Minister was rendered necessary by an emergency shall be conclusive evidence that such act was so rendered necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This is to provide that the certificate of another Minister relating to persons employed by him as to the circumstances of the emergency will be sufficient in order to avoid the spectacle <Col N="658" /> of one Minister having to prosecute another.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 104:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 21 before Section 48, but in Part IV, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  Where a contract for the execution of any work or the manufacture or production of any article or substance or the doing of any other form of industrial work was entered into before the commencement of this Part of this Act and is at such commencement not fully carried out, and the person liable under such contract to execute such work, manufacture or produce such article or substance or do such other industrial work claims either or both of the following things, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  that, by reason of the obligations imposed on employers by this Act, a limitation of time contained in such contract for the doing of any particular thing has become unreasonable and should be extended, or</P>
      <P>(b)  that, by reason of the said obligations, any particular price or other payment fixed by such contract has become unreasonable and should be increased,</P>
      <P>then and in every such case, such claim shall, in default of agreement between the parties concerned, be referred, on the demand of any such party, to arbitration under this section.</P>
      <P>(2)  Where a claim is referred under this section to arbitration, the following provisions shall have effect, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  such arbitration shall be heard and determined by one arbitrator who, in default of agreement between the parties concerned, shall be appointed by the Minister on the application of any such party;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(b)  in the case of a claim for the extension of a limitation of time, the arbitrator shall determine whether such extension should or should not be made and (if he <Col N="659" /> determines that such extension should be made) the amount of such extension;</P>
    <P>(c)  in the case of a claim for the increase of a price or other payment, the arbitrator shall determine whether such increase should or should not be made, and (if he determines that such increase should be made) the amount of such increase;</P>
    <P>(d)  the arbitrator shall be paid such fee for acting as arbitrator as shall, in default of agreement, be fixed by the Minister, and such fee and all other general costs and expenses of the arbitration shall be paid by such one or more of the parties to the arbitration and, if by more than one of such parties, in such proportion as the arbitrator shall direct;</P>
    <P>(e)  the arbitrator shall determine how the costs and expenses incurred by each of the parties to the arbitration of or incidental to appearing and being heard thereat shall be borne;</P>
    <P>(f)  if the arbitrator determines that a limitation of time should be extended or that a price should be increased, the arbitrator shall amend the contract which is the subject of the arbitration, in such manner as he shall think proper in order to give effect to such determination;</P>
    <P>(g)  the determination of the arbitrator shall be final and conclusive and shall be binding on all parties concerned.</P>
    <P>This is a new section designed to meet representations which were made as to the possible effect of the Bill on contracts.  It provides for the alteration of the terms of the contract either by agreement or by arbitration whenever it is contended by one party thereto that because of the limitations imposed by the Bill either the time in which the contract had to be performed or the price to be paid should be varied.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Col N="660" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 105:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 21, before Section 49, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  The Minister may by order, if and whenever he so thinks fit on the application of an employer carrying on an industrial undertaking, declare that any one or more of the departments, branches, or other parts of such undertaking shall, for all the purposes or any specified purposes of this Act, be deemed to be separate industrial undertakings, and that this Act shall apply and have effect in relation to such undertaking accordingly.</P>
      <P>(2)  The Minister may by order, whenever he so thinks fit, revoke or amend an order previously made by him under this section, including an order made under this sub-section.</P>
      <P>(3)  Whenever and so long as an order made under this section is in force in respect of an industrial undertaking, this Act shall apply and have effect in relation to such undertaking subject to and in accordance with such order.</P>
      <P>It was suggested and is obviously desirable that there should be power to regard separate parts of industrial undertakings as separate factories in certain circumstances.  This amendment proposes to give power to the Minister, by order to declare separate parts of the same undertaking to be separate factories for the purposes of the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that that is not done for the purposes of exclusion but also for the purpose of inclusion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 106:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 22, Section 51, lines 2/4, to delete the words &ldquo;on the grounds that they are members of the family of the person carrying on such industrial undertaking or any other grounds.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Is the Minister accepting this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="661" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I prefer the Bill as it stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>This section provides that &ldquo;where industrial work in any industrial undertaking is done wholly or partly by persons who, on the grounds that they are members of the family of the person carrying on such industrial undertaking or on any other grounds, do not receive any salary or wages in respect of their work, the person carrying on such industrial undertaking shall for the purposes of this Act be deemed to be the employer of such persons doing such industrial work and such persons shall, for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to be workers in the employment of such persons.&rdquo;  I think this section would be immensely better if you did not have these illustrative conditions injected into it.  What is the need for putting in the words &ldquo;on the grounds that they are members of the family of the person carrying on such industrial undertaking or on any other grounds&rdquo;?  If there is any significance in those words at all, it is a limiting significance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>It is, but it limits it to the type of case we contemplate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>What other type of case has the Minister in mind?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>None; but there might possibly be something included in the scope of the section of which possibly we are not aware, if the illustrating words are not in.  The illustrating words are undoubtedly limited, but they only limit the scope of the section in so far as they illustrate the type of person the section proposes to deal with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am rather afraid that the courts may hold, in construing this Bill, that you are tied to the central pivot of &ldquo;on the grounds that they are members of the family of the person carrying on such industrial undertaking&rdquo;. I think that the other few words, &ldquo;or on any other ground&rdquo;, may under the well-known legal process of <i>sui generis</i> be regarded as relating to members of the family.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="662" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Clearly institutions would be covered?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>They are covered specifically in another section.  It would be better, I think, to leave out those qualifying words.  When this Bill becomes an Act it is not the Minister who is going to interpret it but the courts.  I think, firstly, that the section is better without these words, but my objection would be less vigorous if the Minister could say, fortified with legal opinion, that &ldquo;or on any other grounds&rdquo; would not be construed in relation to members of the family.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall get that opinion if it will satisfy the Deputy.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 107:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 22, Section 52 (2), line 19, after the word &ldquo;prison&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;a borstal institute&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 108:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 22, before Section 53, to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  The Minister may by order make regulations for all or any of the following purposes, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  requiring persons carrying on industrial undertakings to make and furnish to the Minister statistical returns;</P>
      <P>(b)  prescribing the class or classes of industrial undertakings in respect of which such returns are to be made;</P>
      <P>(c)  prescribing the subjects and matters in respect of which such returns are to be made;</P>
      <P>(d)  prescribing the forms in which and the times at which such returns are to be made.</P>
      <P>(2)  Every person, required by regulations made under this section to make statistical returns, who fails to make such returns in accordance with such regulations shall be guilty of an offence under this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="663" /> This section is designed to give us power to require statistical returns in relation to the various matters that may be specified from time to time in respect to it.  There is no power to require the furnishing of these statistics at the present time.  As Deputies are aware, in relation to some matters dealing with industry we are dependent on voluntary information given to us by employers.  It is considered more desirable that this Bill should be availed of in order to get power to require by order the making of these statistical returns to the Department.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Are they very onerous returns?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>They would be reports relating to persons employed, distinguishing between the sexes&mdash;in other words, information that it would be necessary to have in order to enable the obligations of the Department under the Bill to be carried out, wherever such obligations require a limitation in the employment of young persons or in some other way impose restrictions.  Obviously, to enable us to review the position, it is desirable that we should have this power to get returns from employers.  Generally it is desirable&mdash;and I think most Parties in the House have stressed it from time to time&mdash;that we should have a more effective method of requiring information as to the employment provided in the different trades than we have at present.  At present we are practically dependent on voluntary returns apart from the information secured by the periodical census.  The great majority of employers give us these returns at the present time, and for them there will obviously be no difficulty in future.  Even in those cases, however, our difficulty at present is that we do not know whether we have got complete returns or not, whereas if this section is passed and the returns are obtained under it, we shall be able to use these statistics with more confidence than at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>The reason I have asked the question is that the Minister for Finance uses employers for the purpose of collecting the income-tax of <Col N="664" /> employees.  That is a considerable burden on employers.  I have had lists with as many as 40 names on them directing me to collect certain sums off certain men.  If we are going to increase lists of that character we are going to increase the burdens of employers very considerably.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to take responsibility for the sins of the income tax authorities.  All I can say about the returns required under this section is that we are getting them voluntarily at present from most employers.  They will not impose any considerable burden on them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>Employers are not without burdens at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>They have advantages, too.</P>
      <P>Bill, as further amended, reported to the House.  Report agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the Report Stage be taken on next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we have the Minister's amendments circulated before that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>And in time to enable Deputies to put down further amendments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I think so.  There will not be very many.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesWalterBeckett" hpid="Mr. Beckett Mr. Beckett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beckett</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the Report Stage be left over until Wednesday week.  This is not a Bill that any Party in the House wants to rush through.  We all desire to make it a good Bill, and the amendments will have to be considered very carefully.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of fact, most of those that I contemplate bringing forward are already prepared. There will be only few in number, arising out of points put forward on the Second or Committee Stage.  I could probably have these in the hands of Deputies by the week-end.  I suggest, therefore, that we fix the Report Stage for next week.  Having regard to the state of the Dáil programme, we may find it better to take it next week than <Col N="665" /> on the following week, in which the pressure of business may be greater. If, however, any Deputies interested in the Bill raise any objection to taking it on next Wednesday, I would be only too happy to put it back further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the Minister's amendments be in the hands of Deputies?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall try to get them into their hands at the week-end.  In so far as we have covered the Bill up to date, I think the amendments are ready, but there may be some more arising out of the discussion to-day which may take a little time to prepare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Shall we have them on Saturday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall try to arrange that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>That will leave us very little time to get in amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Then we can object to the Bill being taken on Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I should have said next Monday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Then you ought to postpone the Bill until Wednesday week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Postpone it until Thursday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>If we do not get the amendments until Monday there will be very little time to prepare amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be perhaps only one amendment out of to-day's discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryMDockrell" hpid="Mr. Dockrell Mr. Dockrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dockrell</NameTxt>
      <P>We will want to read the Bill intelligently when it is reprinted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>All right, we will put it back until Wednesday 20th.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesWalterBeckett" hpid="Mr. Beckett Mr. Beckett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Beckett</NameTxt>
      <P>When will we have this Bill as amended?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>We will have the Bill as amended to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister still have his amendments ready on Monday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="666" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>If we are going to put it back until Wednesday week, I should like to take an extra day myself.</P>
      <P>Report Stage fixed for Wednesday, 20th November.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Railways Bill," RHead="1935&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Railways Bill, 1935&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill be now read a Second Time.  This is a Bill to amend the Railways Act of 1933. That Act was designed to effect, amongst a number of other things, the reconstruction of the capital of the Great Southern Railways Company and to assist the reorganisation of the company's entire undertaking, in common with that of other railway companies, which was made possible under the Road Transport Act of the same year passed about the same time. It was realised that the period of reorganisation would involve for the company abnormal financial difficulties for which some special financial provision should be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It was accordingly provided by Section 4 of the Railways Act, 1933, that such of the company's capital stocks as were on 1st December, 1932, securities in which trustees were authorised by the Trustee Act of 1893 to invest trust moneys, or under which funds in any court might, under the Rules of the Court, be invested, should continue until the 31st December, 1935, to be so available for the investment of trust or court moneys or funds, whether the company did or did not pay on its ordinary stock a dividend at the rate of 3 per cent. per annum, or any dividend, as required by the Trustee Act and the Rules of Court respectively sub-section (2) of Section 4 provided that, for the purposes of the application, on or after the 1st day of January, 1936, of the provisions of the Trustee Act, 1893, or the Rules of Court, relating to securities in which trust or court funds might be invested, the company should be deemed to have paid a dividend at the rate of one per cent. per annum on its ordinary stock in respect of every financial year of the company which ended after the 30th day of November, 1932, and before the 1st day of January, 1936, and for which <Col N="667" /> the company in fact paid no dividend on its ordinary stock or a dividend less than one per cent.</P>
    <P>As Deputies will remember, certain administrative difficulties necessitating amending legislation dealing with road transport, operated to postpone the date for the coming into effective operation of the Road Transport Act, 1933, and these, together with other difficulties inseparable from the reorganisation, contributed to defer the realisation of the position originally contemplated, with the result that it becomes, in our opinion, necessary and desirable to extend by two years the period during which the trustee status of the company's capital stocks shall be maintained.  It is not anticipated that it will be necessary to seek any further extension of this period; nor is the introduction of this Bill to be taken as any indication of our opinion as to whether or not it will be possible for the company to pay a dividend on its ordinary stock during that period.  The Bill is being introduced as a safeguard in the event of its not being found possible.</P>
    <P>The amendment we are proposing to effect is to substitute the date, 31st December, 1937, for the date, 31st December, 1935, and the date, 1st January, 1938, for the date, 1st January, 1936, where they occur in the relevant section of the Railways Act. The necessity for it is, in our opinion, entirely due to the fact that the reorganisation of the transport system, consequent on the passage of the Road Transport Act and the Railways Act of 1933, did not really become effective until this year because of the delay in bringing the Road Transport Act into operation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>In other words, you want to continue these stocks as trustee securities?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, until the period of reorganisation is over.  These stocks would lose their trustee status if a dividend of 1 per cent. was not paid on the ordinary shares.  That has not been paid for the last two years, and may not be paid for the next two years because of the financial difficulties arising out of the reorganisation, <Col N="668" /> and it is desirable, in the interests of the company generally and the interests of the people who invested in these stocks, that the position should remain unchanged until the full reorganisation is completed.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, November 13, 1935.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Supplementary" RHead="Estimates">
    <Title>Supplementary Estimates.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil, according to Order, went into Committee on Finance and resumed the consideration of Supplementary Estimates for the service of the financial year ending 31st March, 1936.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Vote" RHead="69&mdash;Relief Schemes (Resumed)">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Vote 69&mdash;Relief Schemes (Resumed).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKelly" hpid="Mr. T. Kelly Mr. T. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to direct the Parliamentary Secretary's attention to the necessity for spending some of this money on the employment of extra painters.  As we all know, the painting industry is dependent more or less on the weather and winter time is a time more or less of unemployment.  Probably this matter should be brought up on the Estimate for the Office of Public Works, but I cannot afford to let the painting situation wait until next March.  I should like if some of this money could be devoted to the painting of depots and other institutions directly under the control of the Office of Public Works. I have one place in my mind's eye for a long time.  I do not know if the Parliamentary Secretary ever passes through College Street.  Opposite one of the classical buildings of Dublin there is in that street a building which was used for generations as a police station.  I was there last week, and I must say that that building is now one of the most disreputable buildings in Dublin.  It was a police station as long as I can recollect, and a police station long before I can recollect.  I just glanced inside it, and I do not think it has been painted since it ceased to be a police station.  It is now used as a sort of soldiers' recreation room, but its position, right outside that splendid building of the Provincial Bank, on which a great deal of money <Col N="669" /> was spent some years ago in having the whole place renovated, is an eyesore. I thought the Minister might have had some money to spend there with a view to putting some sort of an appearance on it.  Personally, I think it would be better to remove it altogether and place a decent building on the site.</P>
      <P>There is another building in charge of the Minister, I think, that I frequent regularly, or very often at least, and that is the Labour Exchange building in Lord Edward Street.  Exteriorly, it is all right; but inside I think it has not been painted for a very long time.  It is a very disappointing building inside.  As a matter of fact, I think it is no credit to the architects who planned it.  It is quite probable that the space to be disposed of at the time was small, and they may therefore have been confined in their plans, but the interior, at any rate, needs doing up.  I do not know whether the University buildings in Earlsfort Terrace would look the better for a coat of paint.  I must admit that my eyesight was a bit blurred the last time I passed up there, but it seems to me that it needed some attention, and I am only taking the opportunity of drawing the Parliamentary Secretary's attention to it. There are other places I might speak about, but I feel that these are three places on which additional money might be spent before Christmas in order that some of the painters, who might otherwise be idle, might be enabled to provide themselves with the usual Christmas fare that, in every workingman's home in Dublin, is expected and wished for.  That is all I have to say in connection with this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Flinn) Hugo Victor Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Flinn)</NameTxt>
      <P>One of the great advantages, Sir, in one sense, of a debate of this kind is that those who have asked questions, which, presumably, they expect to be answered, have generally departed into the shades of a better land and into a more comfortable and pleasanter occupation when the time for answering their inquiries has come.  Consequently, I am afraid that I will find that those whose comments <Col N="670" /> I have to answer are not here to listen to my replies.  Deputy Brennan discussed the whole agricultural situation, which does not come under this Vote.  He did ask a certain question in relation to how money was being expended, and why it was being expended, on turf development.  It is being spent for the purpose of enabling our natural fuel here to be used and to be available throughout the whole country for domestic and, I hope, for industrial purposes.  Certain difficulties have arisen, as the House knows, in relation to the uniformity of the supplies coming up from hand-won turf, and, for certain purposes, uniformity in the nature and quality of turf is very important.  For that reason, arrangements are being made to provide for those purposes a more uniform quality of turf in the form of machine-made turf, but that will not interfere with the production and development of turf by other means.</P>
      <P>Deputy Brennan also said that there had been a lot of complaints.  All I can say is that they are the most silent complaints that I have ever heard. The ears of my Department are probably wider open to complaints than, perhaps, those of any other Government Department that ever existed; and I can say that this year there have been no complaints &mdash;no complaints which brought to our knowledge matters of importance of which we were not already aware and with which we had not already dealt.  Deputy Brennan also complained that money was being spent on non-productive schemes.  I have searched the records&mdash;the archives that were handed over to me from all Departments&mdash;to find that mass of productive schemes that were left there by my predecessors.  I have not found them.  What they may be perfectly sure about, at the present moment, is that in every area the best scheme which is available in that area to deal with unemployment, at the time at which unemployment exists, is being used.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think I have rather avoided telling the secrets of my prison house, or telling tales out of school, but anything more impudent than for men to get up from the Front Benches opposite and speak of lots of complaints, and <Col N="671" /> unproductive schemes, and all the rest of it, having regard to their own record in the matter, I cannot imagine.  We took over a very bad job.  We have made that a clean job and an efficient job.  We have done that with the cooperation&mdash;and I want to bear that testimony&mdash;of all members of all Parties in the House in bringing forward to us complaints to be dealt with; and now, at the end of that period, when the House is universally conscious that this money, which was given in trust to be spent for the benefit of the poor, is being efficiently and honestly spent for that purpose, it is an outrage that men should so irresponsibly get up and attempt to leave behind them a trail of insinuation of that kind when they know that there is no basis whatever for it.  Deputy Brennan then went on&mdash;like a sort of male Cassandra&mdash;to tell us all the terrible things, which he imagined existed, which were bound to have their reaction.  Well, at least that is better than the phrase that we were going to be bankrupt in a fortnight.  I do not think Deputy Brennan said anything else.</P>
    <P>Deputy O'Leary wants a commission. set up to investigate the farming position; but, surely, not on a Supplementary Vote for £150,000 for unemployment. With that genial courtesy and meticulously generous choice of adjective which is a distinction of speeches delivered sometimes from the opposite side, he informed us that we were the greatest pack of hypocrites unhung.  That also is a contribution to a solution of the unemployment question.  He then wanted a little general election in East Cork.  That is all that Deputy O'Leary has to say on the subject of this Vote.</P>
    <P>Deputy Haslett apologised for being in order.  He made the only suggestion up to that which had any relation whatever to the subject, and it was a valuable suggestion, one which, I think, is in the minds of men of all Parties in this House and which is emphatically in the minds of the electors of all parties in the country. That is that some method should be found by which those people who are <Col N="672" /> now receiving the new unemployment assistance and are not working for it, but who are anxious to work for it, should have an opportunity of doing so.  All I can say is that that ambition of Deputy Haslett &mdash;that ambition of the electors of this country&mdash;has very cordial sympathy over here.  Deputy Davin said the amount was inadequate.  No amount that could possibly be put forward would, in my opinion, be treated in any other terms.  You have to define what you mean by inadequate.  You will have to settle down to some standard by which you think it is the business and the duty of the State, by artificial means, to raise the whole body of the State.  I would be very glad to hear a discussion of that kind.  I would be very glad if somebody would formulate some standard under which the State, as a whole, would give to every willing worker a decent standard of comfort.  But until somebody does lay down a standard of that kind. mere phrases such as the inadequacy of the amount are no use.  I remember when we introduced a Vote of £2,000,000 it also was stated to be inadequate.</P>
    <P>It is the wildest illusion to imagine that the only money which is being provided for unemployment relief at the moment is this £150,000, or the £350,000 which preceded it.  There is being supplied by the State a sum of, roughly speaking, £1,500,000 under the name of Unemployment Assistance for the purpose of relieving distress without work. If the State were to provide that £1,500,000 for the purpose of relieving distress by work everybody would be of the opinion that the State was meeting, or at any rate beginning to meet, its obligations adequately.  Take, for instance, the City of Dublin in relation to which there is being, and there is going to be, a considerable amount of interested propaganda for the purpose of increasing the Relief Vote.  If we were to provide them with £50,000 as a Relief Vote it would be considered a generous gesture.  But as a matter of fact under Unemployment Assistance at the present moment the City of Dublin is being provided with £350,000 a year approximately, and the only acknowledgment of that is to make a <Col N="673" /> grievance of the number of people which that artificial provision is bringing on to and making visible on the rates.  At the present moment the Government in the City of Dublin is paying for the relief of distress an amount of money which would keep employed at full wages all the year round somewhere about 2,500 men.  But no acknowledgment of that is made, and it is the same right through the country.  I do hope that some arrangement will be made by which these people will be put in employment and will cease to be an artificial reproach upon the register.</P>
    <P>Deputy Davin asked whether or not the position in the country in relation to unemployment had improved. He asked me to tell him whether or not it had improved in his own constituency.  It is quite impossible for me, with the statistical information now at my disposal, to be able to answer the latter of these questions though in the unemployment register there is being set up machinery which will enable us in future years to check up very accurately on this matter.  One of the great advantages of the Unemployment Assistance Act was that it brought for the first time into view on the statutory register, the degree of economic distress existing in any part of the country. As far as the country in general is concerned it is possible to answer precisely the question which was asked.  A committee was set up by the Department of Industry and Commerce to examine the whole of the figures available and the trend of employment and unemployment in the Saorstát.  I do not know how many members of the House have read the report but, as one who is rather closely familiar with the figures, I will say that it is a difficult document to read.  It is, in my opinion, an extremely competent document.  The statistical information which is available in very few cases is directed to the point which it is desired to examine.  Sometimes it has been necessary to examine two or three sets of related statistics in order to get the final indication of the trend.  That <Col N="674" /> committee has reported on page 31, paragraph 44, under the heading &ldquo;Conclusion as to employment,&rdquo; as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;All the available evidence goes to show that employment in the aggregate was considerably greater in 1934 than in either 1926, 1931 or 1933.  Even in Agriculture, employment has shown an improvement.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Paragraph 45 says&mdash;and this is the result of expert examination of all the available figures in relation to the trend of employment and unemployment:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The examination of the facts and figures readily available relative to unemployment which have been made in this memorandum makes it apparent that there is no evidence of an increase in unemployment during recent years.  At the same time it has been shown that there is a great increase in the volume of employment, especially in the volume of industrial employment.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is the best answer which I can give to the question which Deputy Davin has asked.  I will go further and say that the investigation which has been there started, and which has been brought up to 1934, has in the process of investigation created the machinery and standards by which it will be possible to keep tally in future on trends of that kind.  I believe that to be very valuable work.  Personally, I think you cannot exaggerate the value of careful, systematic and impartial investigation of that kind of social and other trends.</P>
    <P>Deputy Davin raised one question which, curiously enough, had been raised entirely from the opposite point of view by those speakers who spoke in the previous debate.  He objected strongly to the doing of relief work by stages.  That was a practice which we have adopted only in the last two years.  Personally, I think it is not merely a thoroughly defensible thing, but a thing essentially desirable in itself.  Whatever system of distribution or administration of a limited sum is used for dealing with unemployment or distress it will involve the allocation to particular bodies of people, to areas containing numbers of people of <Col N="675" /> particular degrees of distress, of a certain amount of money out of that total fund and the basis which we have adopted, in relation especially to minor relief works, has been to take the 3,000 electoral areas in Ireland and estimate for each of them the amount of the total sum which those particular areas would be entitled to.</P>
    <P>You may find that there is to be given to a particular area the sum of £100, and you may find in connection with the five or six schemes which are competing in that district to be done, that the schemes which can be done in one year for £100 are inferior in permanent value to a scheme which would cost £200 or £300.  In all those cases, so long as a reasonable advantage will immediately accrue from the first expenditure of money upon that scheme, we deliberately choose the better scheme and, even if it does take two or three years to complete, even if it takes the quotas of two or three years in order to get that scheme completed, we think it a better and wiser method.  That has been applied to schemes running into thousands.  Often a link road wants to be done, but you could not justly, having regard to your duties to other areas, find the whole of the money in one particular year.  In those cases they have teen properly spread over a series of years and I think Deputy Davin will agree with that, if he examines the relative schemes which have been accepted or rejected for purposes of that kind.</P>
    <P>Deputy Davin also was strongly in favour of public health works in towns and villages, and so are we.  I do say that of public health works generally the ones in the smaller towns and villages are really the ones of the highest social value and anything that can be done in ration to them ought to be done.  But you must remember we are dealing with a limited sum of money and that sum has to be divided over all the different claims, not merely in all the different areas but under all the different departmental and other heads.  Of the £370,000 which is the net grant up to the present for this year, £100,000 has been allocated to the Department of Local Government <Col N="676" /> and Public Health for the purpose of energising local government and public health works.  In addition to that, they carried over unspent from last year in the re-vote about £66,000, giving a total of £166,000 which they could use for the purpose of giving grants to local authorities to induce them to borrow the remainder of the money to enable public health works to be done.  That is what is being done.</P>
    <P>Broadly speaking, you may fake it that the average grant would be about 40 per cent.  It varies entirely with the conditions of the district.  On the basis of 40 per cent., it means that £166,000 of a grant will energise a total expenditure of over £400,000, and it is in that way the grant for public health, for unemployment assistance, is being made, not merely up to the extent of its own amount, but to the extent of two-and-a-half times the total amount which appears in the Vote to help to bring on public health works.  Deputy Davin alluded to the fact that the Parliamentary Secretary sometimes perambulated into strange places for the purpose of inspecting works.  Experience has shown that that is a very valuable thing.  It is not always a comfortable thing, but there is no question as to its actual value.  It does encourage carrying out good work to know that someone will see the good work which has been done, and it helps to prevent things being left undone.</P>
    <P>Now we come to housing as a relief to unemployment.  At the present moment there are probably between 20,000 and 30,000 people engaged in housing work.  The actual amount of labour on a house has certainly turned out to be discouraging.  When I first came to tackle this job, I had illusions of five or six or ten men engaged on a house. When I was told there were only one-and-a-half men per annum on a house I began to feel somebody must be dreaming.  Now we have every reason to believe that the actual employment over the whole year on a house is considerably less than one-and-a-half men.  At the same time, owing to the number of houses that have been built, it is at the present moment a very real and solid contributory to the employment position in the State.</P>
    <Col N="677" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Kelly Mr. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you include clearance of the site?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>No. Clearance of the site would probably be exclusive of that.  That, I think, is a line upon which some employment in the cities might possibly be given in anticipation. If plans were made for housing schemes well ahead of the time at which they would come to fruition, I think it would be possible largely to use labour on that.  In fact, it is in the boroughs and in the big towns that the problem of using the available unemployed men usefully is going to be most difficult.  The number of people represented by borough unemployment is relatively small compared with the total.  We have been accustomed in this House, unfortunately, to use the phrase &ldquo;unemployment relief&rdquo; when, as a matter of fact, the problem in Ireland is not by any means so much unemployment distress as ordinary economic distress.  Of the 150,000 people who came on to the unemployment assistance register, the proportion who are unemployed, in a real sense, is relatively small.  Most of the people who have come on, have been people who are small farmers, whose general economic condition has been below the level set up by the Government in the Unemployment Assistance Act as the level at which relief should be given.</P>
      <P>There are very many illusions, I am afraid, on the subject of the real meaning of those vast totals which are now in existence upon the register.  There is a sort of feeling that when you have 150,000 people on the register you have 150,000 units of unemployment.  As a matter of fact, you have nothing of the kind.  We took out a return for two agricultural counties, which were different in characteristics, so that we could average these counties.  We took the County of Louth and the County of Mayo.  There were 8,775 people on the register; 3,000 of these were under 2/-. In other words, these 3,000 were people who were fully qualified for the register, and there were 1,670 people in addition, of 3/- and under, making a total of 4,600 people out of 8,000 under 3/-.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Where was that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="678" />
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>In Louth and Mayo.  I can give the figures separately for each county some other time.  We took these two because they were counties of very different characteristics, and I gave the average of the two.  If I gave the figures for Mayo alone, it would leave a wrong impression on the Home. The vast majority of people en the unemployment assistance register, at the present moment, are not unemployed persons at all in that sense.  We had one rather curious opportunity of testing this.  In this year there were two &ldquo;Employment Period Orders.&rdquo; The first removed farmers of £4 valuation from the unemployment assistance register for a period of a month.  In the second &ldquo;Employment Period,&rdquo; in addition to the class of farmers referred to above, unmarried men in the rural districts, without dependents, were put off the register.  Forty-two thousand people came off the register at that time.  The register is made up of three separate compartments, each making a total.  First there are people entitled to unemployment insurance benefit, and that total has not varied to any considerable extent throughout the whole of the operation.  As a matter of fact, at present it is probably as low as it was in 1931.  The second figure is of people on the register because they want unemployment assistance; and you reckon up the balance between the sum of these two, and the total of what is called &ldquo;others.&rdquo;  When those 42,000 people went off the unemployment assistance register if they had been seeking employment they would have been classified in the returns as &ldquo;others.&rdquo;  As a matter of fact, the &ldquo;others&rdquo; register only increased by 4,000 people and this proves that they were taken from the same people, as immediately the Employment Period was over, they were again found on the register for unemployment assistance. Deputy Bennett said I was an honest man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKelly" hpid="Mr. T. Kelly Mr. T. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>He was not far out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>He also said that at the present moment the unemployment <Col N="679" /> schemes were being fairly and honestly, administered and not to the advantage of any particular man or school of thought.  I am taking the opportunity of repeating that, not merely because it is a very nice thing to hear said but because the fact that it has been said now, after all that was said in the earlier debates, means that the House now recognises that the whole scheme is being administered as a trust.  Anyone who knows the amount of trouble and difficulty and the administrative difficulties that we had to put up with at the beginning for the purpose of making sure that this position would come about will now greatly appreciate the fact that that is recognised.  The fact that the House does recognise that these grants are now being administered in that spirit, is going to make it possible to have a cheaper and more efficient administration of unemployment grants in the future.</P>
      <P>Deputy Corish raised the question of public health works, which I think I dealt with to his satisfaction.  I was rather surprised when he said that owing to anonymous letters sent to the labour exchange men had been automatically removed from their jobs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am rather surprised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Anonymous, vindictive and spiteful letters!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am rather surprised, but you have to separate two things here.  It is the duty of everybody to clean up the register and to keep people not entitled to the money from getting it.  That being clear, it is entirely wrong that any man, for vindictive or political purposes, should write an anonymous letter to injure a worker.  These are two different lines of country.  While I think the position ought to be safeguarded, and that it is the right and duty of every citizen in the State, to-day, to do all in his power to clean up these registers&mdash; just as we held it was the duty of every man who knew that anything was wrong in connection with relief works to bring <Col N="680" /> the matter up&mdash;the position referred to by the Deputy has to be cleared, up and will be looked into.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Anonymous, letters should not be acted upon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very much inclined to agree.  I would be very glad indeed to see that moral courage developed in the public mind so that each man would do his duty over his own name. I would be very glad indeed to see these conditions prevailing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy MacFadden asked some questions in relation to Tír Conail. He was particularly interested in works for the purpose of dealing with a big flood due to a cloudburst in Glencolumbcille. I do not often allude to particular items, but I am personally aware of that case, and I should be surprised to know that everything possible was not done.  I went into the matter personally, and I know that a considerable number of roads and so on were dealt with, but it very often happens in cases of that kind where there has been a cloudburst or something of that nature that a series of demands are put in which would mean the reconstitution of a province. I had cases where the actual total of damage done was estimated, when we came down to brass tacks, at 16 acres. of arable land, and having regard to the representations which were received from the most responsible people in the most categoric fashion, I certainly thought that at least a province had been wiped out.  I do think that in the case of Glencolumbeille everything possible was done.  I will certainly look into the matter, because that district and the whole of that western Donegal, district is one which, from the point of view of the industry of the people, the courage of the people, and the way in which they face up to the difficulties of their lives, deserves every possible assistance that can be given to it.  That is true of a great portion of the western seaboard. Anyone who travels that western seaboard cannot but be proud to remember that he belongs to a people who have the courage, the tenacity, the resolution, and the love of their own sod, which are displayed by the poor <Col N="681" /> people all along that western seaboard. Certainly no appeal in relation to that portion of the country falls on deaf ears in our Department.</P>
    <P>Deputy Norton told us that all those schemes were utterly inadequate.  He wanted us to take our courage in both hands and face the problem.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesPPattison" hpid="Mr. Pattison Mr. Pattison">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Pattison</NameTxt>
      <P>Keep your promise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>We are keeping our promise, and when we go to the people they will send us back here again because we have kept our promise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>To relieve unemployment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  We are doing more than any Government has attempted to do here, and we intend to do more than any Government that can be substituted for us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the 103,000?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>We must take them one by one.  I like the story of taking your courage in both hands&mdash;in other words, put up schemes costing a lot of money? Is not that it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>And when the Minister for Finance stands here on Budget day and asks for the money to do it they go into the lobby and vote against him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>You can push them into the lobby if you like.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Until the people in this House, are prepared to take the responsibility of voting for unpopular taxes&mdash;derived from the only sources from which large sums of money can be got, these people are not entitled to come to us or to anybody else and use a phrase like &ldquo;taking your courage in both hands&rdquo; in putting forward large schemes.  I am reminding the Labour Party, that at the next Budget, when we do bring forward demands for money, when we do bring forward demands for the sinews of war, when we do ask for the means of accomplishing the things which they say we should do, they should take their courage in both their feet and walk into the right lobby in favour of providing <Col N="682" /> the resources necessary to energise the schemes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>To tax food and wipe out income tax?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Whatever you like. Unless the Deputies opposite are prepared to find for us, as we asked on a previous occasion, a series of taxes which would enable the social services &mdash;both those existing and those they demand&mdash;to be put into operation without the taxing of food, then they have either got to say that they prefer to do without the services, or vote for the taxes on the food.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>Where is the £200,000 which the Minister raised for the Widows' and Orphans' Pension Fund?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the name of Queen Anne's grandmother?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>Where is the £200,000 that was raised for the widows' and orphans' pensions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is time we came down to brass tacks on this matter&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I have the greatest possible sympathy with what the Labour members say when they make demands of that kind, but I have no sympathy whatever with them when they refuse to take the responsibility of having to provide the means by which those demands might be met.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesPPattison" hpid="Mr. Pattison Mr. Pattison">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Pattison</NameTxt>
      <P>When did they do it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Unless someone is going to produce to us new series of taxes, no single portion of which will fall upon the working people&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>We gave you particulars of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Anyone who believes that you can, over a period of years, beginning now, finance a heavy scheme of public works out of an increase in income tax is simply a lunatic.  Let them come forward with schemes for finding the money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="683" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>What about a tax on ground rents?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKelly" hpid="Mr. T. Kelly Mr. T. Kelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Kelly</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought you had a plan?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>How much would that provide?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Look up the figures.  It is an increasing sum anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Norton said yesterday that all we were providing was £1 for every person on the unemployment register.  How much does he want provided?  Tell us the taxes you are prepared to impose for the purpose of providing that money.  You will then be taking your courage in both your hands, and hot merely talking about it.  It is time we had the help of the Labour Party in facing the unpopularity of providing the means of doing the things which they demand should be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcMenamin" hpid="Mr. McMenamin Mr. McMenamin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMenamin</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Parliamentary Secretary two questions. One arises out of the balance of £66,000 which was unspent by the Local Government Department last year.  That is practically one-third of the total amount.  Should not some steps be taken to ensure that the money is spent in the year in which it is voted? Should not the Local Government Department be asked for an estimate as to how much they can spend in any current year, and is it not right that they should not get a larger sum than that?  The second question arises out of Deputy Davin's suggestion that only a portion of those larger schemes should be carried out in any one year. I agree with the principle of spreading the money over a number of years, but in the case of a £300 or £400 job it would make a laughing-stock of the whole thing if only £100 were spent. It would look very miserable&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought the Deputy was asking a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcMenamin" hpid="Mr. McMenamin Mr. McMenamin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMenamin</NameTxt>
      <P>While I agree in principle with doing the thing by stages, I think the matter should be looked into.  I suggest also that the Local Government Department should not get one-third of this money and not <Col N="684" /> spend it.  There is plenty of work to be done and the money should be spent in the year when it is voted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>In so far as that is a question, I will answer it.  I already answered it on a previous occasion. What happened was this: When the Government first made a grant of £2,000,000 in the first year we did not find the necessity in that particular year to spend that £2,000,000.  We decided to reserve £150,000 of it for the purpose of enabling schemes which took a considerable time in gestation, in the preparation of plans and so on to be prepared for a future year. It would be quite impossible in practice, and experience has certainly shown it, for the Local Government-Department to be held responsible for completing in any particular year a scheme for which the demand for money was first made in that year. Until the grant is available for a local authority, you cannot get the local authority to move and it is necessary that this money should be provided. If, in fact, we had not had that fortunate opportunity in the £2,000,000 grant, I should have had to go to the Minister for Finance on the ground of the efficient administration of the schemes and ask him to provide some such fund as would enable me to energise schemes of that kind from year to year.  It is probably the most efficient piece of financial machinery at present in the possession of the Government and it came into existence in the way I have told the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcMenamin" hpid="Mr. McMenamin Mr. McMenamin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMenamin</NameTxt>
      <P>But last year they spent only £40,000 out of £100,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is dreaming.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcMenamin" hpid="Mr. McMenamin Mr. McMenamin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMenamin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quoting your own figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>You are not quoting any of my figures.  They carried over on the previous year £84,000 which they had not spent.  They got £100,000 which made it £184,000 and they carried over this year £66,000, which means that they had spent £118,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to prolong the debate or to ask ridiculous questions, but I should like to know from <Col N="685" /> the Parliamentary Secretary whether he gives encouragement to anonymous correspondents by investigating charges, vicious and vindictive in some cases, made by such anonymous correspondents.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I think anonymous correspondents should be discouraged in the most strict and rigorous fashion. I am not going to answer a general question of that kind.  I am telling you what I think in exactly the same way as the State Solicitor or the head of the Civic Guards would tell you he regards anonymous statements as objectionable.  They should not be encouraged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you investigate them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>That question I am not going to answer at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. Davin Mr. Davin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I know and it is quite easy to ask such a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Parliamentary Secretary responsible for that at all?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughVFlinn" hpid="Mr. Flinn Mr. Flinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Flinn</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  Deputy Corish raised a question in relation to a particular road in Wexford.  As a matter of fact, I was dealing with that matter just before I came in and it will save me the trouble of writing to him about it if I reply to it now. It is not possible at the moment to do that particular thing.  As he knows, there is rather a difficult legal question involved between two or three Departments but it is a matter which has merits and it will be considered.</P>
      <P>Vote agreed to.</P>
      <P>Resolution reported and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Control of Imports:" RHead="Quota Orders: Motions of Approval">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Control of Imports: Quota Orders: Motions of Approval.</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following Motion:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Go gceaduíonn Dáil Eireann leis seo an tOrdú chun Iomportálanna do Rialú (Quota Uimh. 23), 1935, do rinne an Ard-Chomhairle an 2adh lá de Lúnasa, 1935, fén Acht chun <Col N="686" /> Iomportálanna do Rialú, 1934 (Uimh. 12 de 1934).</P>
    <P>That Dáil Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 23) Order, 1935, made on the 2nd day of August, 1935, by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).&mdash;(Minister for Industry and Commerce.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Minister for industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Minister for industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have nothing further to say on this matter.  I explained on the previous day upon which this Resolution was under discussion, the nature of the Order, which deals with onions, and the necessity for the restriction of imports during the season in which home supplies are available. That season has passed for this year, and will not come again until June or July next, and, in the meantime, there is no restriction upon importation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>As we are back on the subject, will the Minister say if he has been able to ascertain in the meantime why it is a quota is fixed for the next six months substantially higher&mdash;I think the quota allows for the import of 34,000 more cwts. of raw onions than were imported during the same period last year&mdash;than the quantity imported in the same period last year?  Can the Minister tell us why it has been fixed at such an amount, and whether imports of that size are contemplated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>There are two answers. One is that only 75 per cent. of a quota is allocated, except in emergency circumstances.  When a quota is fixed, only 75 per cent. is allocated, and the other 25 per cent. is held against possible contingencies.  The second is that there is no reason in this case, during the present quota period, to restrict in any way the importation of onions, and, consequently, the quota has been fixed as large as is convenient to administer. in order to ensure that every person on the register of importers will get whatever licences he seeks without restriction.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="687" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass) Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Lemass)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Go gceaduíonn Dáil Eireann leis seo an tOrdú chun Iomportálanna do Rialú (Quota Uimh. 24), 1935 do rinne an Ard-Chomhairle an 13adh lá de Mheán Fhómhair, 1935, fén Acht chun Iomportálanna do Rialú, 1934 (Uimh. 12 de 1934).</P>
      <P>That Dáil Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 24) Order, 1935, made on the 13th day of September, 1935, by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
      <P>This relates to Quota Order No. 24, which deals with perambulators and, under it, the importation of complete bodies and complete chassis for perambulators is prohibited save under licence.  Considerable progress has been made in the development of the perambulator assembling industry and there are some half-dozen firms now engaged in it.  It was found, however, for a variety of reasons, that further progress would be slow so long as the importation of complete bodies and complete chassis was taking place freely, and the Order is designed to transfer, not at present the whole, but a substantial part of the home market for perambulators of the types covered by the Order to the native assembling firms.</P>
      <P>The quota fixed for the present quota period, which extends to 31st January next, is 200.  That number is, of course, largely experimental, because there are no separate statistics relating to imports of these articles and, consequently, no reliable information.  Because, however, of the experimental nature of the quota, the period fixed is a short one, and whatever adjustments may be necessary, arising out of the experience gained during that period, can be effected without undue delay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I endeavoured by Parliamentary Question the other day to get some information on this matter from the Minister.  I got very little and he certainly has not added to it now.  He has told us, however, in reply to a Parliamentary Question, that the <Col N="688" /> imposition of this Quota Order was for the purpose of assisting in the development of the industry and providing increased employment.  He told us that the total number of persons employed, on the last day fur which he had information, 1st September, 1934, was 77; but he had no information for, say, March, 1935, so that we have here a proposal practically to shut down the import of articles, 16,000 of which were imported during the last calendar year. If the Minister applies the 75 per cent. in respect of the quota on these articles, a quota at the rate implied in this Quota Order is going to allow in only about 600 of these articles in 12 months.  Sixteen thousand were imported last year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy cannot assume that, because not all classes are covered by the Quota Order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>We would at least expect the Minister to tell us what percentage this quota is of the amount that normally comes in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I explained that I could not do that because we have not got separate figures.  They are not available to anybody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The way it presents itself to me is that the Minister is shutting down, to the equivalent of an import of 600 articles, the type of article which was imported to the extent of 16,000 last year; that 75 or 77 people were employed on this type of manufacture before; but that he can give us no information as to the amount of employment that is going to be given in this respect.  Apparently, we cannot get from the Minister any information as to how tins quota is going to assist the development of industry here.  He simply tells us that he has not got the information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>But there is another aspect of it to which I would like to draw the attention of the House.  The cost of perambulators imported last year was £17,700. They are used, I suppose, by the less wealthy class of people, the class of people who have on them the responsibility and the cost of rearing young families.  These people had to pay <Col N="689" /> £8,800 in Customs duties on the import of these articles last year.  Judging by the number of persons employed, the number of these articles that are being produced in the country is less than the number that is being imported. The price of the manufactured article is obviously measured by the price of the imported article.  If, on the import of £17,000 worth of perambulators, the buyers of them had to pay the equivalent of more than £8,000 in Customs duties, it gives one an idea of the amount of the additional cost that these persons have to bear by reason of the tariff.  I submit to the Minister that they will have to bear more by the reason of the putting on of this particular quota.</P>
    <P>The Minister explained when the tomato quota order was imposed that, because of the shortage of tomatoes, the sellers of tomatoes in this country made abnormal profits.  It is undoubtedly the fact that, in the case of boots and other articles in respect of which quota orders have been made, the issuing of the quota order brought about a rise in the prices paid.  The Minister must be not only blind but deaf if he does not understand that his quota order in respect of boots raised the price, of boots in the country. Now, we are going to have the price of these perambulators raised if we consider the amount of duty alone paid in respect of imported perambulators last year, amounting, as I have said, to £8,800.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Where did the Deputy get that figure?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I got it from the reply of the Minister for Finance quoted on page 60 of the Dáil debates for the 30th October last.  We have got the figure of £117 or so for every person employed in this country in the manufacture or assembly of perambulators. That is according to the figure of the Minister for Industry and Commerce. If the Minister, takes it that the production of perambulators in the country is equal to what comes in, we set an idea of the amount of money that has to be borne by the particular class of persons purchasing them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there not another explanation of that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="690" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>We would be glad to hear any explanation that the Minister has to give.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The duty was being paid by the exporters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister explain that to us?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>That is why the quota order had to be made because the duty was non-effective.  The exporters were paying the duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister would stand over his proposal and tell us what he has found out by his examination of the situation as to what is happening in the country, as to what he thinks and what he hopes is going to happen as the result of it, we would not be led into these misconceptions. I am not prepared to take an interjection like that from a Minister who will not, in a systematic way, give the House an explanation of what the position is industrially or from the point of view of cost or taxation.  The Minister, in putting these quota orders before us, should give us a somewhat systematic <i>exposé</i> of what the effect of producing additional employment is going to be here.  He should also give us a more systematic explanation of the price of these things as a result both of the taxation that is imposed and of these quota orders.  To anyone who simply looks at the facts as they are, the purchasers of these articles, before ever a quota order was imposed, had as a result of the 75 per cent. tariff with the preferential rate of 50 per cent., paid these huge sums of money that I speak of on the imported article alone, and an equivalent sum over the normal cost of manufacture on the produced article here.  But, when we relate the additional cost paid by reason of the Customs duty to the number of people employed, the facts that emerge are sufficient to warrant a deeper examination of the situation than the Minister has apparently given to it, with a more complete explanation to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister says that this order is going to increase employment here. It is put in such a way that, I suggest to him, it reduces in a very blunt way <Col N="691" /> the number of these articles that are being imported.  At the rate that is quoted in the quota order, there are only 600 of these articles going to be imported in the 12 months as against 16,000 imported last year.  The whole thing, in my opinion, is very irresponsible. If we are to believe the Minister it seems to me that he is only taking a shot in the dark as to what may happen.  Surely, the Minister with the assistance of his Department and with the contacts that he has, both with manufacturers and the commercial community both in the city send through the country, should be able to give us a somewhat more satisfactory explanation with regard to the real effects of this quota order.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister says that this quota order will have the effect of increasing the number of people employed in this particular industry.  We should like to have more definite information on that than we have got from the Minister.  According to his figures, in the previous year the number of these articles imported was 16,000.  The tariff on them amounted to £8,800 odd.  The Minister said it was paid by the exporters of the articles.  I would like to have some more definite information on that from the Minister.  Is he in a position to produce tables showing the price of these articles in England, where the articles were manufactured, and the price charged here?  According to the figures that the Minister gave this evening, we gather that the purchasers of these perambulators, in tariffs, alone are contributing the sum of £115 each in wages to the 77 men employed.  There has to be added to that the profit of the protected manufacturers here, and that is going to amount to something.  We have no means of knowing what that profit amounts to.  Judging by our experience of other tariffed goods, we know that manufacturers are able to obtain a handsome profit for themselves on these already highly tariffed goods.  It is probably true that the mere putting into employment of 77 men costs the purchasers of these perambulators a <Col N="692" /> good deal more than the sum paid in-wages to them.  This particular tariff will bear severely on people who are not in a position to bear it, people with family responsibilities, people who are working desperately to maintain themselves and their little growing families. I should like to have very clear and definite information on the whole subject.  I, myself, shall not be purchasing any of these articles, but I have sympathy for the 16,000 odd purchasers of perambulators, many of whom, I know, are in a position in which they can ill afford to buy any kind of propelled vehicle to carry child.  This particular tariff is an illustration, which can easily be converted into figures, of what is happening all over.  In many instances, the whole result of a tariff, particularly where it is excessive, falls on the unfortunate consumers.  Unless we get some figures to prove that the exporters are bearing some portion of this tariff, there is definite evidence in, this case that almost the whole cost of putting these few men or women into work is borne by the consumer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcMenamin" hpid="Mr. McMenamin Mr. McMenamin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMenamin</NameTxt>
      <P>Are the bodies of these things being built in the country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  Deputy Bennett seems to be suffering from a lapse of memory.  He has forgotten that his Party has changed its policy since he last spoke in the same strain.  He is likely to move east, like certain other members of his Party, unless he remembers that they have a new policy now and that they are in favour of tariffs.  All that free trade jargon which Deputy Bennett has given us is now out of date with members of his Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you sure?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Unless they have run away from the new policy published a fortnight ago and have changed again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>I spoke of excessive tariffs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy read the policy of his Party?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="693" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCBennett" hpid="Mr. Bennett Mr. Bennett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bennett</NameTxt>
      <P>I did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy does not seem to have understood it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GearoidOSullivan" hpid="Mr. G. O'Sullivan Mr. G. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a tariff on babies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I have often warned Deputy Mulcahy to keep as far away as he can from statistics.  They are a source of perpetual danger to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has done his best to keep me far away from them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Without success.  He has managed to escape my care and has consumed statistics to an extent that is causing him considerable indigestion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not blame the Minister for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to tell the Deputy that he must never be certain of the accuracy of his deductions from a limited number of statistics.  I said already that a possible interpretation of the yield from the Customs duty on perambulators is that the exporters of these goods were subsidising their sale in this country to the extent of paying the duty.  I do not say that that is the whole explanation, but I know, from investigations made otherwise, that, to some extent, that must be an explanation, because considerable reductions in price were being offered to importers by those formerly engaged in supplying the markets here.  It was that situation, in which the <i>ad valorem</i> duty did not appear to be effective, that led us to deal with the problem by Order under the Control of Imports Act.  If that situation were not present, if the Customs duty were effective, as we intended it to be, this Order would not be required.  Secondly, I told Deputy Mulcahy that there were no statistics as to the imports in any period of the classes of perambulators covered by this Order.  The figures which he got from the Trade and Shipping Statistics relate to a much wider range of articles.  The articles covered by the Order represent much less than half the total import figure for baby carriages <Col N="694" /> generally.  The great majority of imported baby carriages are of the folding type which, I understand, are also the cheapest and sold in greatest quantity.  The only perambulators covered by the Order are those of the fixed-body type, and they are being manufactured by a number of concerns here&mdash;and manufactured very well.  I cannot tell Deputy Mulcahy what is the average employment given in their production, because that information is not available.  As he mentioned, on the 1st September, 1934, there were from 70 to 80 employed, and by the 1st April, 1935, that figure had risen to 103.  Presumably, the figure is now higher, because production in the industry has increased.  The import quota fixed for the first quota period is, as I have said, experimental, because of the absence of definite information as to the quantities required. The experience gained in that period will enable us to fix the quota for ensuing periods with greater accuracy. It is unwise for Deputy Mulcahy to assume that if the quota for three months is fixed at 200, the quota figure over the year will be 800.  That may or may not be so, but there are no grounds for the deduction the Deputy has made.  The operation of the Quota Order affords effective protection for the industry and defeats certain efforts that were being made to defeat the <i>ad valorem</i> Customs duty which could be nullified, and was nullified, by various devices adopted by importers. The quota was placed not merely on the completed articles but on the component parts of it.  Consequently, it is effective against any devices for its evasion that may be adopted.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Dáil Eireann hereby approves of Control of Imports (Quota No. 25) Order, 1935, made on the 4th day of October, 1935, by the Executive Council under the Control of Imports Act, 1934 (No. 12 of 1934).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This Quota Order deals with certain assembled parts of motor car bodies. That is, an assembly consisting of the back part of a motor car with the end <Col N="695" /> part and the side or roof attached thereto.  The importation of motor body shells is already prohibited under Quota Order 10, and the intention of that prohibition was to secure the greatest degree of assembly in the production of motor bodies within, the Free State.  The most difficult part of the body assembly and the part which provides most employment is the joining, together of the back part and the side panels.  It appears that such assemblies could be imported notwithstanding the Quota Order prohibiting the importation of body shells.  In order to prevent the position being abused by extensive importation of such assemblies, this Quota Order No. 25 was made.  A purely nominal quota has been fixed for the first quota period.  During the preliminary period, licences for limited quantities only were issued, such licences being confined to firms who had been doing assembly work on the basis of importation of back and side parts.  The intention is that these assemblies shall not be importer.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall agree to this Quota Order, but, on the general question of quota orders, I want to make an application to the Minister.  In connection with these Control of Imports Quota Orders, would he be good enough to arrange that there be inserted in parenthesis, after the quota number, a short description of the Quota order itself?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>You mean in the Resolutions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>No, documents issued to merchants in connection with them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>And also in this Resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am dealing with the point of view of the commercial community. If one is importing three or four commodities to which different Quota Orders apply it is comparatively difficult to know to which commodity a particular set of documents applies, because all the information you have is Quota Order No. 25 or Quota Order <Col N="696" /> No. 14.  It would be of material assistance to the commercial community if a rule was made where a quota is referred to by number in parenthesis that thereafter will appear a statement that it refers, say, to boots.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy appreciates the difficulty.  Surely the difficulty is one of definition, where you might, in fact, mislead someone by putting in an entirely inadequate definition for the purpose of giving information of that kind.  Take the case that we discussed. It refers not merely to baby carriages and perambulators as being the subject of the Quota Order, but to a certain class defined in the Order, so that a brief description of that class of perambulators would not be possible, The description perambulators or baby carriages would be misleading, because the Order only relates to certain classes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the difficulty might be overcome by describing, say, Quota Order No. 25 as referring to certain classes of perambulators. To take another instance, supposing there was an order referring to certain classes of boots, it would be practicable to state that Quota Order No. 14 applied to certain classes of boots only, thus drawing the attention of merchants to the fact that it was a very limited and a clearly inadequate description.  The Minister will readily recognise that if a person is habitually importing under quotas, he must be a registered importer, and therefore would import a certain amount under every Quota Order.  All the merchant wants to know is to which of the Quota Orders that he habitually uses these documents refer.  I suggest that a circular might be sent to registered importers asking them to note that this description was merely for convenience and did not purport accurately to describe the Quota Order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>At the present time all the persons concerned get a copy of the Quota Order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>My suggestion is that a circular or handbill should be sent for the convenience of importers with a <Col N="697" /> description of the Quota Order appended stating that it is not meant to be an exhaustive description, but merely a help to merchants to differentiate between sets of documents. I admit that if you go through these documents carefully you can get the requisite information, but it is a tedious process, and where you have to handle them in the course of business, particularly if you have not a large staff devoted exclusively to that work, it involves a good deal of unnecessary trouble.  The Minister will recognise that in this country we have a very large number of very small importers who have not the highly-trained staff that large importers would have.  I have had personal experience of that difficulty, and I heard it mentioned by a number of other merchants similarly circumstanced, and I suggest to the Minister that for an experimental period in any case he might try it.  If he finds that misapprehension arises he can easily abandon it and revert to the original method.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFLemass" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I will have the suggestion considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will find that Section 3 of the last Quota Order that we dealt with says: &ldquo;The period beginning on the 6th day of November, 1935, and ending on the 30th day of June, 1936, is hereby appointed to be the first quota period under the Control of Imports (Quota No. 24) Order, 1935, which relates to certain motor car body parts.&rdquo;  It is the same dealing with perambulators &ldquo;under the Control of Imports (Quota No. 24) Order 1935 (which relates to certain perambulators and chassis, bodies and body shells of certain perambulators.&rdquo;  What seems to be required is that on the front of the Order there should be a parenthetical statement.  Deputies are frightfully confused when they simply see Quota No. 35 Order.  It should be possible to make the Orders read that Dáil Eireann had approved of Quota No. 35 Order relating to so and so, and that it was made on a certain date. It would be of considerable convenience to Deputies and to the commercial <Col N="698" /> community if that could be done. If the commercial community have the same difficulty about these Quota Orders that Deputies have, I pity the commercial community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGood" hpid="Mr. Good Mr. Good">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Good</NameTxt>
      <P>I heard continual complaints of the same character.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Customs" RHead="Duties Orders&mdash;Fruit In Water">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Customs Duties Orders&mdash;Fruit In Water.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan) Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Dáil Eireann hereby approves of Customs Duties (Preferential Rates) (Fruit in Water) Order, 1938, made on the 4th day of, October, 1935, by the Executive Council under the Customs Duties (Preferential Rates) Act, 1934 (No. 19 of 1934).</P>
      <P>In the last Finance Act there was a duty of 3d. per lb. imposed on fruit in water with a preferential rate of 2½d. The preferential rate was definitely for the purposes of the Customs duty. Under our treaty with South Africa we are bound to give them a preference of one-sixth of whatever duty may be imposed on any fruit coming into this country.  Therefore, this Order made by the Executive Council is to carry out the undertaking with regard to South Africa.  Our treaties with both Australia and Canada compel us to give them the equal treatment that we give to any other countries in the Commonwealth and this Order gives a preference to South Africa, Canada and Australia.  The amount that is expected to be imposed will be extremely small, in fact negligible, so that the loss to the Exchequer under this Order will not amount to more than a few shillings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister inform the House what is &ldquo;fruit in water&rdquo;? Is it a commodity imported by jam manufacturers exclusively?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, exclusively, as opposed to fruit in syrup, which is known as tinned fruit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister sive the value of the last annual imports?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="699" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not say now.  The imports were rather considerable until about three years ago when we imposed duties on fruit and pulp coming to this country.  The result of the imposition of these duties was that we had some meetings with the jam manufacturers, and we agreed to give them a licence for a certain amount, which has been reduced year by year. The amount this year is 40 per cent. of what came in in 1932.  As far as I remember it amounted to something between £30,000 and £40,000, but I would not like to be tied to these figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="700" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. -" RHead="Question on Adjournment">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Question on Adjournment.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="FrankFahy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Frank Fahy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy MacDermot gave notice that he intended to raise a question on the Adjournment arising out of question No. 5 on the Order Paper.  The Deputy is apparently not in the House now.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 7.30 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, November the 13th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>