<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="22" Month="May" Year="2012" Vol="215" No="10" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 22 Bealtaine 2012" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 22 May 2012" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="543">
    <HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead=""> 
    <Title></Title>
        <P Just="Center">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Machnamh agus Paidir.</i></P>
        <P Just="Center"><i>Reflection and Prayer.</i></P>
        <Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad"> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad</Title>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have received notice from Senator Martin Conway that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to indicate when she intends to commence the missing children&rsquo;s hotline number 116000.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Mark Daly of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to outline the reasons the Gaeltacht area of west Kerry has not been incorporated in the Leader scheme.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Deirdre Clune of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to outline the changes he intends to make at Cork Airport and the timeframe for such changes.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business."> 
    <Title>Order of Business</Title>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>It is proposed to take No. 1, Animal Health and Welfare Bill 2012 &mdash; Committee Stage, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business and adjourn not later than 5.45 p.m., if not previously concluded.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Leader back to the House and wish him well.  Perhaps the Deputy Leader might take a few notes to make it easier for him, if she would not mind.</P>
        <P>Last Wednesday on the Order of Business I raised the issue of the mortgage crisis, as I have done consistently since the end of last September.  We had a decent debate last week with the Minister of State at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform when I stated that I, in no way, shape or form, questioned his personal commitment to resolving the issue.</P>
        <P>Last week I predicted that the quarter one figures in respect of mortgage arrears and distressed mortgages will be substantially worse than those for the fourth quarter of 2011.  Data released by the Central Bank and the Financial Regulator yesterday indicate that 10.5% of mortgages are in arrears of 90 or more days and, which is perhaps worse, that 25% of all mortgages are either restructured or in arrears of 30 days or more.  What we are facing here is not a crisis but a catastrophe and one, moreover, that continues to deteriorate.  As the Financial Regulator observed, the banks are overwhelmed by it.</P>
        <P>The only explanation that comes to mind for the Government&rsquo;s lack of action in this regard is that it has been paralysed into inaction.  I was greatly concerned last week when the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Brian Hayes, for whom I have immense personal regard, referred to the forthcoming personal insolvency Bill as a game changer for the mortgage crisis.  It will be no such thing.  As I said, one quarter of households are already in mortgage difficulties and even where their loan is restructured, people continue to fall into arrears.  The Family Home Bill 2011, which would at least have afforded protection to family homes, was defeated in this House by three votes.  The problem is getting worse because rather than freezing interest payments for mortgage holders in arrears, their interest bills are rising exponentially.  I look forward to meeting representatives of Allied Irish Banks at tomorrow&rsquo;s meeting in Buswells Hotel to discuss this matter.  However, it is only one element of the catastrophe.</P>
        <P>What we need is a mortgage arrears implementation strategy which includes timelines for implementing the necessary actions.  It was good to see the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, in the Chamber last week, but that debate took place only after ten successive weeks of requests by me to that end.  The Minister of State &mdash; we noted the senior Minister&rsquo;s failure to attend &mdash; was apologetic and chastened in response to the serious issues raised by Members on all sides of the House.  The Government must delay no longer in seeking to address this issue as best it can.  No government can provide a total solution, but there are simple steps which would offer relief to those concerned.  These steps must include a suspension of the application of interest where a mortgage holder is in arrears.  A policy of extension of mortgage terms would also be helpful for those seeking to free up some cash in the short term.  Most of those affected fall into the 25 to 40 age bracket and are struggling to make large mortgage repayments on reduced incomes.  The tens of thousands of people affected by this issue are not worried about the fiscal treaty referendum or what is happening in Europe.  What chiefly concerns them is putting food on the table and keeping a roof over their head.</P>
        <P>In this regard, and with apologies to the Leader, I am obliged to propose an amendment to the Order of Business that the Minister for Finance come to the House today to set forward a timeframe for action by the Government.  The personal insolvency Bill is a welcome part of the jigsaw but will not be sufficient to address all of the difficulties.  The Minister must outline in detail the Government&rsquo;s response to the catastrophic data on mortgage arrears that were announced to the media yesterday and will be published next week.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank colleagues for their courtesy towards me in my role as Deputy Leader during recent Orders of Business.  There were requests for debates on several issues which, although not immediately urgent, the Leader might do well to facilitate in the coming weeks.  For example, a debate on the rights of children and young people might encompass a range of issues put forward by Senators.  In addition, several colleagues called last week for a debate on third level access and youth unemployment, issues which have become particularly topical.  For example, there was significant media commentary at the weekend on the comparable rates of youth unemployment in various European countries.  A substantial difference in northern countries such as Germany, Sweden and Denmark, where we see lower rates, is the greater emphasis on apprenticeship and vocational training as opposed to focusing solely on university education.  This is of particular interest and something to which German policymakers point as a factor in keeping rates of youth unemployment low.  Being conscious of our own high rate of youth unemployment, we should look at different ways to tackle it.  In that regard, I very much welcome the announcement made by the Minister for Education and Skills yesterday of 6,000 extra places under the Springboard programme because that is the kind of programme which has been successful in other countries in keeping youth unemployment rates down.</P>
        <P>I thank the Leader for facilitating a debate tomorrow on the agreement between the European Union and the United States on the use and transfer of passenger name records.  The Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality debated the motion last week and I was one of the members who raised certain issues with the Minister.  It will be a short debate, but it should provide enough time for justice spokespersons to put any questions they may have to the Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JillianVanTurnhout"><NameTxt>Senator Jillian van Turnhout</NameTxt>
	<P>Yesterday the Irish Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children published the Childline annual statistics for 2011.  The importance of listening to children cannot be overstated and in the past 23 years Childline has been providing this invaluable service for children.  It is a service which is trusted and recognised by young people.  In 2011, for example, it received more than 800,000 calls, including 54,000 relating to some level of emotional abuse and 11,000 relating to bullying.  Childline not only listens to and supports young people but it also saves lives.  Yesterday I heard a prime example of this from the ISPCC spokesperson who relayed the story of a teenage girl who had taken an overdose, contacted Childline and shared with the operator her feelings of worthlessness and how everyone was right that she was a waste of space.  During the 45 minute call she eventually told the Childline operator where she lived and an ambulance was sent to take her to hospital and save her life.  I shudder to think what would have happened if her telephone call was one of the 800 telephone calls that go unanswered each day because of insufficient funding and resources.  Childline in the United Kingdom, which is run by the NSPCC, receives &pound;11 million for its continued development.  The Department of Education in Northern Ireland makes contributions to Childline Northern Ireland.  In Ireland Childline operates without Government funding or support.  In fact, it raises &euro;4 million thanks to the generosity of the public and Eircom.  The lack of funding seriously undermines the capacity of the service to meet the needs of children.  Some 38% of calls go unanswered.  These are the voices of 800 vulnerable children and young people which are not heard each day.  Will the Leader invite the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to the House to discuss how the Department and the Government can better support the exceptional work being done by Childline to ensure all children are heard and valued?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>I support what Senator Jillian van Turnhout said and draw attention to the need to care for another section of the community.  It is distressing to note the rise in the number of cases of elder abuse being reported.  The HSE attributes the rise in the number of referral of approximately 9% in 2011 as compared to the figure for 2010 to factors such as increased public awareness of the issue and how to report cases of abuse.  That may well be true, but I hope we are not at the same time failing to draw attention to the fact that there are pressures in society which may be leading to an increase in cases of psychological and financial abuse.  It would be appropriate to have a debate on that issue in early course or incorporate it into one of the debates already planned because it is not one we should ignore.</P>
        <P>A number of weeks ago, with other Members of the Houses, I heard a woman by the name of Reggie Littlejohn of Women&rsquo;s Rights without Frontiers speak about her work in exposing forced abortions and sterilisation in China.  She mentioned to us the plight of Chen Guangcheng  who I have mentioned in the House on a number of occasions in the past year and who has now reached a very high level of prominence in our society because of his recent high profile escape from China.  While being rightly supportive of the Government&rsquo;s efforts to promote strong economic ties with China, a number of us in the House are also anxious that we do not overlook the issue of human rights.  For his work in exposing forced abortions and sterilisation in China, Mr. Chen and his family were put under house arrest.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>He and his wife released a video on the Internet last year about their imprisonment and were then beaten by local officials.  There are concerns, even now that he has arrived in the United States, about the fate of his family members, particularly his nephew, Chen Kegui, who is in a prison in Shandong province accused of attempted murder for threatening three government agents who broke into his home after his uncle&rsquo;s escape.  I do not want to hear general platitudes about how the Government will find some channel to raise human rights issues with China.  What, precisely, is this small country going to do in its conversations with Chinese officials?  Are we going to raise issues such as the fate of Chen Guangcheng&rsquo;s family?  It would be a shame if we did not.</P>
        <P>I mention in passing the victory for freedom of religion that occurred at the European Court of Human Rights in the form of its decision in the case of Fernandez-Mart&iacute;nez <i>v.</i> Spain, which has been recently reported.  This touches on issues we have discussed in the House with regard to section 37, namely the right of freedom of religion even in State-run and State-funded schools.  A helpful decision has come from the European Court of Human Rights, and I urge our Government &mdash; and Fianna F&aacute;il, which introduced a Private Members&rsquo; Bill on this issue &mdash; to take note of this movement in the direction of protecting freedom of religion.</P>
      <Speaker pid="TerryBrennan"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Brennan</NameTxt>
	<P>The past weekend has been a momentous and historic one for Irish sports people from different walks of life.  I congratulate Katie Taylor on the magnificent achievement of winning her fourth world title in Shanghai and wish her continued success in the forthcoming Olympic Games.  I also congratulate my neighbours, Rob and Dave Kearney, who live just a couple of miles away from me and who played their part in the magnificent Heineken Cup final with Leinster.  These young people are ambassadors for our country in all corners of the world and should be acknowledged for their achievements.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Senator seeking a debate on sport?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryBrennan"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Brennan</NameTxt>
	<P>I will mention this again during the debate on sport on Thursday.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the Leader&rsquo;s proposal on the Order of Business.  I ask the Leader to ask the Minister for Defence, Deputy Shatter, to come to the House to allay the fears expressed to me by a former Minister and Leader of this House, Mary O&rsquo;Rourke, and Councillor Aengus O&rsquo;Rourke about the future of Custume Barracks in Athlone, the headquarters of the 4th Western Brigade, incorporating the Engineer Corps, the Ordnance Corps, the Medical Corps and the Military Police Corps.  Rumours abound in Athlone that the Government proposes to move these to Cathal Brugha Barracks in Dublin.  This would be a major blow to Athlone, especially in view of the transfer of troops from Mullingar and Longford to Athlone.  These may be only rumours, but rumours should be allayed as quickly as possible by the Minister.</P>
        <P>I welcome yesterday&rsquo;s launch of an air ambulance service for the Athlone region, based in Custume Barracks.  However, the Minister vetoed my attendance and that of all other Fianna F&aacute;il and non-Government Deputies, Senators and councillors.  It was the first time this has happened in my memory.  As a former Minister of State, I invited every Fine Gael and Labour Party member to such events.  This is a boycott.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>That is disgraceful.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>As the longest serving Member of this House from County Roscommon, I want to lodge a protest about this veto that prevented me from dealing with an issue that affects the people of my area, namely, the launch of an air ambulance service at Custume Barracks.  I can now verify the Minister gave instructions to his office to ensure no Fianna F&aacute;il person should attend under any circumstances.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Do you have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I am making a protest, a Chathaoirligh.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator, do you have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I want the Minister hauled in here to answer to me and explain why he established this boycott.  The county council members in Athlone, who are elected representatives living in the vicinity of the barracks, were vetoed.  I can state for a fact that I was not invited.  I do not care how the Minister denies it.  I was not invited because he&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator may make that point when the Minister is present.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;is an arrogant Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator may make that point when the Minister is present.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>He has become more arrogant in one year than others in ten years.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Senator proposing an amendment to the Order of Business?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I am going to go further.  I am submitting a motion for the Adjournment tomorrow evening and I ask the Cathaoirleach to accept it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome back the Leader, Senator Cummins.</P>
        <P>I agree fully with Senator O&rsquo;Brien on mortgages.  I listened this morning to people outlining their difficulties on the Pat Kenny show.  It is a nationwide issue, not just one that arises in rural and urban areas.  People are affected drastically and suffer at the end of the month.</P>
        <P>The one point I heard today that I did not understand is that some financial institutions are refusing to move people&rsquo;s direct debit dates.  One individual said his account was debited on the 20th day of the month although he did not receive his pay at that time.  The man&rsquo;s bank flatly refused to move the date to the end of the month when he asked it to do so.  I cannot understand how an institution should be so defiant and illogical.  I ask that the Minister or an official talk to the bank and ask whether individuals such as the man in question could not be accommodated.  It is a very simple matter.  The mortgage issue is the biggest issue in the country at present.  I hope we can have a resolution as quickly as possible.</P>
        <P>My question for the Leader is similar to that of Senator Brennan.  I concerns the European championships in two weeks, to which 40,000 Irish fans may travel.  I am going myself.  I have spoken to many who are going and am told about the roaming charges that will be incurred in Poland and, if the team is successful, the Ukraine.  Eircom and O<sub>2</sub> should come forward and say that for the first ten days of the championship, Irish supporters travelling to Europe will have free texts.  The companies will make a lot of money from fans ringing their wives, whom they will miss, at 10 p.m.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Has the Senator a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>The wives, who will miss their husbands, will be ringing home from Poland also.  When the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport is present on Thursday, could he consider calling on Vodafone and O<sub>2</sub> to reduce their roaming charges during the championships or eliminate the charge for texts?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask for a debate on the economy.  This is a war situation.  As I predicted, we are experiencing the slow-motion disintegration of capitalism as we know it.  I ask the Leader to ask the Government to call for the establishment of the international financial court to try individuals and groups for economic crimes against humanity.  This happened after the Nuremberg trials in Germany in the 1940s.  I. G. Farben, Krupp and Thyssen, in addition to senior managerial staff from these and other companies, were arraigned, tried, indicted and convicted before the court.</P>
        <P>The ratings agencies and groups such as Goldman Sachs have conspired internationally to create, or have created, the circumstances I describe.  They are responsible and should be held responsible for the misery that has been inflicted.  It has been very widely suggested and academic papers have been written to suggest some of the agencies have deliberately helped to foster circumstances in which famine will become prevalent in order to increase their financial reward.  We must take this on, particularly in light of the treaty we are being asked to sign up to.  I wonder how many people have read Article 32.  Paragraph 3 states, &ldquo;The ESM, its property, funding and assets, wherever located and by whomsoever held, shall enjoy immunity from every form of judicial process . . .&rdquo;  Paragraph 4 states, &ldquo;The property, funding and assets of the ESM shall, wherever located and by whomsoever held, be immune from search, requisition, confiscation, expropriation or any other form of seizure, taking or foreclosure by executive, judicial, administrative or legislative action.&rdquo;  Paragraph 5 states, &ldquo;The archives of the ESM and all documents belonging to the ESM or held by it, shall be inviolable.&rdquo;  Paragraph 6 states, &ldquo;The premises of the ESM shall be inviolable.&rdquo;  What does that sound like to those present?  It sounds very much like dictatorship.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>We know from where it is coming.  We know from which part of Europe it is emerging.  I am asking for a debate on the economy in order that we can make a small move to correct the disaster facing us which some of us were able to predict, which has not been tackled in a radical fashion and which the signing of the treaty will make worse.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>I wholeheartedly share the sentiments expressed by Senators R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen and Jillian van Turnhout about human rights and the abuse of both the elderly and young children.  It is regrettable that we are looking at a 9% increase in the number of cases reported of abuse against older persons.  This House has led the way in the debate on this issue.  It is astonishing that Childline does not receive one penny of State support.  It is appalling to think that &euro;4 million a year must be raised through the kindness of others in a country which calls itself a democracy and portrays itself as a society that cares about young people and children and that 38% of calls go unanswered because of a lack of resources.  It is a disgrace and a shame that 800 calls a day are not answered from children who need help and at least are prepared to make a telephone call to look for help.  I ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to come to the House for a debate on the funding of Childline because this is a matter which needs to be addressed urgently.  I thank the Cathaoirleach for accepting my matter for discussion on the Adjournment on the missing children&rsquo;s hotline.  The Minister has led the way in ensuring all of the stakeholders will be brought together to provide this service and I hope she will have good news for me this evening, but the position on Childline is serious.  We need to deal with the matter urgently.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Leader back to the House.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">3 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>Our history and heritage are important to us all.  In the next few days the D&aacute;il will discuss a motion seeking to protect the national monument at 14-17 Moore Street.  The motion has been supported by 50 Members of the D&aacute;il and was part-crafted by the families of the signatories to the 1916 Proclamation.  It would be appropriate and worthwhile for this House to have a debate on national monuments and areas of historical significance.  The signing of the 1916 Proclamation was a seminal moment in the creation of the State.  How ironic would it be, when one would considers it was the relationship between politicians, developers and bankers that destroyed the economy and caused us to lose our sovereignty for which the people mentioned died, if a development on this historical site damaged the ability of Dublin City Council to turn the area into a 1916 historical quarter, which is what it should be?  These are not unimportant issues.  It is important that we remember and protect our history and heritage as much as possible.  I, therefore, ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the broader issue of protecting national monuments and areas of historical significance in such a way that we can use them to attract visitors and tourists to the country.  Many of those who come to Dublin and travel to various parts of the country visit historical sites which we should preserve and protect.  I ask all parties in the House to support the motion that will be debated in the D&aacute;il in the next few days, but we could also play our part by having a debate on this important issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarieMoloney"><NameTxt>Senator Marie Moloney</NameTxt>
	<P>I am disgusted to read in the newspapers today that the former Minister of State, Mr. Ivor Callely, is unlikely to be pursued for the sum over &euro;6,000 that he was paid in expenses.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I inform the Senator that the former Senator mentioned is now a private individual.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarieMoloney"><NameTxt>Senator Marie Moloney</NameTxt>
	<P>The point I am coming to is that officials in the Department have been advised that they had no legal basis on which to pursue him for the money because the error was made by the Department.  I raise this issue because day in, day out I deal with claimants who have been overpaid by the Department of Social Protection and are pursued by it for every last penny.  Why is there one law for one Department and one law for another?</P>
        <P>I just do not accept that.  If people are pursued in respect of social welfare overpayments, then the same should happen in this case.  Why is it not possible to take the money from the former Senator&rsquo;s pension?  I want someone to come before the House to explain why people on social welfare are obliged to repay moneys they have been overpaid while others do not have to do this.  It is no wonder that people have lost faith in politicians, particularly when they read about cases of this nature in the newspapers.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Well said.  The Senator is quite entitled to ask that question.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>I support Senator Moloney in her request.  It is important that justice should be seen to apply right across the board.</P>
        <P>I wish to voice my concerns regarding a matter that arose while I was out canvassing in favour of the treaty.  History shows that many crises which are not resolved end in wars.  It has come to my attention that many social welfare recipients intend to vote &ldquo;No&rdquo;.  This gives rise to a major concern on my part, especially in light of these people&rsquo;s needs, the size of the social welfare budget &mdash; &euro;20 billion or two thirds of all moneys we take in &mdash; and the fact that we are not exactly sure how we will fund our country into the future.  It is quite reckless and irresponsible of certain politicians to advise social welfare recipients to vote &ldquo;No&rdquo; on the basis that we may not need the ESM or access thereto.  I am of the view that at this point it would be safer to proceed on the basis that we will need access to a second bailout.  If we do not&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>And a third, a fourth and a fifth and they will have to be accounted for.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;need a second bailout, then it will be a bonus.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>And the ESM is inviolable.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Healy Eames, without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask that the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, make a statement on the likelihood of the need for a second bailout.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>He stated a few weeks ago that such an eventuality was ludicrous.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>The second issue about which I am concerned, and to which several previous speakers referred, is the crisis relating to mortgage debt.  Last week, Senators indicated that there is a need for urgency to find a resolution in respect of this matter.  I am of the opinion that there is one great possibility for families and individuals who are in trouble.  I refer to one of the solutions to which the Keane report refers, namely, the split-mortgage model.  The latter would allow families or individuals to requalify&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;in the context of the amounts they can afford to repay.  I am concerned about reports this morning to the effect that the Central Bank is exerting pressure on lenders to resolve this matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Senator supporting the calls for a debate on mortgage debt?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.  It is important that the Minister for Finance should clarify how lenders can resolve this matter &mdash; they will obviously pass the pressure on to homeowners &mdash; until the necessary solutions are put in place.  Both of my questions are for the Minister and I request that he offer clarification in respect of both the ESM and mortgage debt.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AideenHayden"><NameTxt>Senator Aideen Hayden</NameTxt>
	<P>I support Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien&rsquo;s comments on the situation with regard to mortgage debt.  This is going to be one of the great sources of division in our society going forward.  I am not completely <i>ad idem</i> with the Senator in respect of the insolvency legislation because I am of the view that the latter will make a significant difference.  However, I am concerned that there is currently a campaign to subvert the inclusion of mortgage debt under that legislation.  We have all read newspaper reports to the effect that 25% of people who are in mortgage arrears are deliberately withholding their repayments.  The Central Bank recently stated that this is absolutely incorrect and untrue.  However, it is symptomatic of a campaign being conducted in the media and in the wider economic sphere to ensure that mortgage debt will not be covered under the insolvency legislation.  If such debt is not covered, it will be an absolute disaster.</P>
        <P>I wish to bring to the attention of the House the fact that the Central Bank will not publish figures for arrears relating to buy-to-let mortgages until later in the year.  The position in this regard is much worse than that which obtains in respect of residential mortgages.  One of the difficulties we face is that all buy-to-let mortgages are ultimately secured on family homes.  If we do not know the very significant extent of the arrears relating to such mortgages, then we have no idea with regard to the scale of this entire problem.  I support the call to the effect that the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, should come before the House.  On a previous occasion I requested that he do so.  It is time the Minister explained to the Seanad where we stand in respect of mortgage debt.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>And the ESM.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AideenHayden"><NameTxt>Senator Aideen Hayden</NameTxt>
	<P>I am deeply unhappy that we do not know the extent of the buy-to-let mortgage debt in this country.  We must find that out as a matter of urgency.</P>
        <P>Senator Conway referred to statistics on the abuse of older people.  It is horrifying that the figures have increased by 9%.  I put it to the Leader that we should have a further debate on the situation of older people.  I was shocked to hear recently that there is some mention of the fact that social workers are being diverted away from care of the elderly and into children&rsquo;s services.  While I imagine as a group of Senators we would support every care for children, it cannot be at the expense of older people in our society.  We must put in place on a statutory basis legislation to protect older people.  As in the case of Childline, we must have a fully funded 24 hour call service for children and vulnerable older people.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CatherineNoone"><NameTxt>Senator Catherine Noone</NameTxt>
	<P>I enjoin the comments of previous speakers.  The figures in respect of elder abuse are astonishing.  There were 2,302 allegations of abuse made to the HSE last year according to the figures published today.  As other speakers have noted, this represents a 9% increase.  God only knows how many cases have occurred which have gone unreported, which is usually the case with these statistics.  This is one frightening aspect of the figures.</P>
        <P>Alleged perpetrators of abuse tend to be related to the abused and this makes it all the more easy for it to be concealed.  Some 44% of all cases reported were sons or daughters, and a further 18% were partners.  This makes it difficult for the abused person to report.  We need to work to remove the stigma that older people may feel in reporting these serous matters.  I agree with Senator Hayden.  Not only do we need a fully funded Childline service in the country but something similar for older people, especially given the economic environment in which we are living today.  It may not seem like a substantial expense to make a telephone call but it should be made as easy as possible for people to report these hideous happenings.</P>
        <P>I enjoin other speakers in calling for the Minister for Finance to come to the House to discuss the plan of action to deal with the potential lost generation in the country with mortgages, the whole mortgage area, those with mortgage arrears and those in negative equity.  Everyone is discussing it.  There are many ideas but we must hear exactly what the Government, as our stakeholder in the banks, will tell them about what needs to be done with mortgage arrears and the effects this is having on our citizens.  I call on the Leader to ask the Minister of Finance to come to the House as a matter of urgency.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomSheahan"><NameTxt>Senator Tom Sheahan</NameTxt>
	<P>I support my colleagues who raised the issue of elder abuse.  As an addendum I am keen for the Minister of State with responsibility for older people to be brought before the House to discuss the issue of ageism and elder discrimination.  Recently, I was contacted by a constituent who works as a private contractor and who has a contract with Bus &Eacute;ireann.  The fact he is 70 years of age means he can no longer collect children and bring them to school.  He has a private indemnity arrangement and public liability insurance but because he is 70 years of age, he cannot drive the school bus.  Nevertheless, he can sit into a 53 seater coach and drive it to Dublin.  He spends one hour in the morning collecting children, as he has done for the past 50 years without any tarnish on his licence or otherwise.  I believe this is ageism of the worst type and, coming from a semi-State body, it is wrong, incorrect and should be rectified.  If this is a matter of policy, we need to change it.  The person in question provides his own indemnity and public liability arrangements.  This is a matter of elder discrimination.  I call for the Minister of State responsible to be brought before the House to have a debate on ageism and elder discrimination.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>As ever, I note with interest Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien&rsquo;s comments.  We should have a little patience in this matter because we are aware of the plans the Central Bank is devising to deal the with the issue of mortgages which&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader is back.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate that and I join my colleagues in welcoming him back.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>He should watch his back.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader knows that he is very safe with me standing behind him.  The issue of mortgages is serious, as attested to by all Senators, but the banks are being flexible with those who are up front with them.  I make a distinction in that regard.  We have compassion and sympathy for those who got themselves into an intolerable position and are now unable to meet their repayments, but buy-to-let merchants are in a different category.  I agree with the Central Bank that the banks are not doing enough in this regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>I never mentioned those who bought to let.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>They should be appointing receivers and collecting rents because the people concerned obtained money, perhaps under false pretences, for buy-to-let properties.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>I am glad the Senator is not running one of the banks.  He would have half of the number of people out on the road.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I am talking about buy-to-let merchants.  I am making that distinction.  I agree, as my colleague stated, that we need to see the figures for all categories.  This is an important matter which I am sure the Leader will address.</P>
        <P Just="Left">People on social welfare benefits who intend to vote &ldquo;No&rdquo; in the referendum are disregarding the need for that insurance policy.  We are very dependent on the funding provided and will be for the years of the programme in which we are involved.  It is what we will pay those on social welfare benefits, pensions and working in the Civil Service with.  That will be the position for years, regardless of who is in government.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should not single people out.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator knows all about it because it was his party which signed up to it in the first instance.  The Government is honouring the agreement made with thetroika.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Do social welfare recipients not have the right to take part in a free ballot?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Paul Coghlan is over time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Of course, they have a right to take part in a free ballot.  I acknowledge their right to do wrong, if that is their wish.  I am just talking about the stupidity of it, as I see it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>Why would the Senator single out social welfare recipients?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>There are others, too.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader of the Opposition, Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien, as well as Senators Fidelma Healy Eames, Aideen Hayden, Catherine Noone, Paul Coghlan and others raised the question of mortgage arrears.  As Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien mentioned, the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, was in the House last week.  There is no doubt that rising mortgage arrears present the biggest challenge to the Government and Ireland and that we must put in place a new framework of laws and banking practices to give as many families as possible the opportunity and the incentive to work their way out of their debt difficulties while staying in their homes.  That is what everybody in the House wants.  With that in mind, the Government has taken a number of actions to help families.  It has increased mortgage interest relief for those who bought their first home at the height of the boom and are, therefore, most vulnerable to mortgage debt distress.  It has increased the budget for mortgage interest supplement to help those who have lost their jobs with their mortgage repayments.  The Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government and the Housing Agency have been working with the banks to roll out the mortgage-to-rent initiative which is under way, but I agree that much more needs to be done.  The Taoiseach and the T&aacute;naiste have stated there has not been as much progress as they would have liked.  As a result and as I informed the House previously, the Taoiseach has set up a Cabinet sub-committee on mortgage arrears to bring a new focus to the issue and drive further action on it.  The Cabinet sub-committee has met four times to date to oversee implementation of a series of additional measures.  The Personal Insolvency Bill to encourage banks to give borrowers a real chance to work their way out of their debt problems will be published by the end of June.  The Minister for Justice and Equality has also indicated that he intends to commence Second Stage of the Bill before the summer recess.  The Government will ensure the banks introduce, with Central Bank oversight, a range of new solutions, including split mortgages, to deal with genuinely distressed mortgage holders, with a determined distinction between those who cannot pay and those will not pay, as Senator Hayden mentioned.  These will be set out in the new mortgage arrears resolution strategies that are being finalised with each mortgage lender.  The Central Bank is engaging with these new banks.  The Government is not standing idly by on this issue.  The Government is acting firmly, and I will inquire whether the Minister for Finance is able to come to the House at a later stage to discuss the issue.  We had a discussion on it only last week, but I will inquire whether the Minister will come in personally to deal with the same subject.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Bacik called for a debate on the rights of children and young people, as well as a debate on third level education and youth unemployment.  Senator van Turnhout and others spoke about the lack of government support for Childline, which carries out such important work in Ireland.  We will invite the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs in here to address these issues.  She has been to the House on several occasions and I am sure she will accede to that request in early course.</P>
        <P>Senator Mullen and other Members spoke about elder abuse and called for a debate on the issue.  We have a debate programmed for 13 June, when the Minister of State, Deputy Lynch, will come to the House to discuss the public consultation report which we embarked upon.  It was a very fine report and Members will have an opportunity to address this report and to deal with elder abuse and the issue of ageism, which was raised by Senator Sheahan.  There will be an opportunity on 13 June to discuss all these items with the Minister of State, who has agreed to come into the House.</P>
        <P>Senator Brennan congratulated our sporting heroes, Katie Taylor and Rob Kearney.  I am sure we would all like to congratulate them.</P>
        <P>Senator Leyden spoke about Custume Barracks in Athlone and welcomed the launch of the air ambulance service for the west at the barracks.  As he a motion on the Adjournment on the subject, I do not propose to respond further on the matter.</P>
        <P>Senator Harte raised the issue of mobile phone roaming charges during the European championships.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport will be here on Thursday to deal with the capital programme, but I am sure the Senator will get the opportunity to raise that issue as well.  Senator Norris called for a debate on the economy.  We will try to get the Minister for Finance in soon to discuss that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>A general debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.  Senator Conway spoke about children&rsquo;s rights and Childline, which I have already addressed.  Senator Cullinane spoke about a D&aacute;il motion on the development of a historical quarter in Moore Street.  The Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht will be in the House on 7 June to discuss the decade of commemorations, so the Senator will have an opportunity to raise those points with him.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In respect of the issue raised by Senator Moloney, I would be very surprised if the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport would forgo any moneys owed to it.  I empathise with the issue raised by the Senator regarding social welfare claimants in receipt of overpayments.  The money should be deducted over a period.  I do not expect social welfare recipients to be treated differently from anybody else.  I will relay her comments to the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.</P>
        <P>Senator Healy Eames also asked for the Minister for Finance to come to the House and I will endeavour to arrange that.</P>
        <P>I have addressed the issues raised by Senators Hayden, Noone, Sheahan and Coghlan.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, &ldquo;That a debate with the Minister for Finance on the worsening situation in the mortgage arrears crisis be taken today.&rdquo;  Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>It is.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 13; N&iacute;l, 32.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading>
        <YesVote pid="DavidCullinane">Cullinane, David.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarkDaly">Daly, Mark.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="TerryLeyden">Leyden, Terry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaschalMooney">Mooney, Paschal.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="RonanMullen">Mullen, R&oacute;n&aacute;n.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DavidNorris">Norris, David.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianODomhnaill">&Oacute; Domhnaill, Brian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DarraghOBrien">O&rsquo;Brien, Darragh.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DennisODonovan">O&rsquo;Donovan, Denis.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="NedOSullivan">O&rsquo;Sullivan, Ned.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MaryMWhite">White, Mary M.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</YesVote>
        <NHeading>N&iacute;l</NHeading>
        <NoVote pid="IvanaBacik">Bacik, Ivana.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulBradford">Bradford, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TerryBrennan">Brennan, Terry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="ColmBurke">Burke, Colm.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DeirdreClune">Clune, Deirdre.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="EamonnCoghlan">Coghlan, Eamonn.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulCoghlan">Coghlan, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelComiskey">Comiskey, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MartinConway">Conway, Martin.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MauriceCummins">Cummins, Maurice.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JimDarcy">D&rsquo;Arcy, Jim.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelWDArcy">D&rsquo;Arcy, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnGilroy">Gilroy, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JimmyHarte">Harte, Jimmy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="AideenHayden">Hayden, Aideen.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FidelmaHealyEames">Healy Eames, Fidelma.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="ImeldaHenry">Henry, Imelda.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="LorraineHiggins">Higgins, Lorraine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CaitKeane">Keane, C&aacute;it.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnKelly">Kelly, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DenisLandy">Landy, Denis.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FiachMacConghail">Mac Conghail, Fiach.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MarieMoloney">Moloney, Marie.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MaryMoran">Moran, Mary.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TonyMulcahy">Mulcahy, Tony.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelMullins">Mullins, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CatherineNoone">Noone, Catherine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="SusanOKeeffe">O&rsquo;Keeffe, Susan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PatONeill">O&rsquo;Neill, Pat.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TomSheahan">Sheahan, Tom.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JillianVanTurnhout">van Turnhout, Jillian.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="KatherineZappone">Zappone, Katherine.</NoVote>
        <Tellers>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson; N&iacute;l, Senators Paul Coghlan and Susan O&rsquo;Keeffe.</Tellers>
        <Decision>Amendment declared lost.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P>Question, &ldquo;That the Order of Business be agreed to,&rdquo; put and declared carried.</P>
        <P><i>Sitting suspended at 3.35 p.m. and resumed at 3.45 p.m.</i></P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Visit of Delegation" RHead="from Bosnia-Herzegovina"> 
    <Title>Visit of Delegation from Bosnia-Herzegovina</Title>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I am sure Members will join me in welcoming a parliamentary delegation from Bosnia-Herzegovina.  On my own behalf and that of all my colleagues in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, I extend a very warm welcome to our guests.  I hope they will have a very successful visit to Ireland.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Animal Health and Welfare" RHead="Bill 2012: Committee Stage."> 
    <Title>Animal Health and Welfare Bill 2012: Committee Stage</Title>
        <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 2</P>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Minister clarify whether wild animals are included in the definition of what constitutes an animal under this section?  I refer, for example, to wild birds and fish.  The Bill may be in conflict with certain aspects of the Wildlife Act on which hunters rely to validate their sports activities.  I wish to suggest a wording which might be included in respect of wild animals, namely, &ldquo;Animals, birds or fish living and sustaining themselves at both an individual and a population level in the wild for their requirements&rdquo;.  I ask the Minister to consider drafting an amendment containing this wording before Report Stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister.  I am seeking clarification of a number of matters.  Section 2(1) deals with definitions.  Will the Minister provide clarification of what is meant by an intensive unit?  Are automated scrapers, automatic feeders and so on included in the definition in this regard?</P>
        <P>I have been approached on the definition of what constitutes a farm animal.  When one reads the section, it is obvious that the definition in this regard is clear.  Some of the farming organisations are of the view that there must be a clear distinction between animals kept for farming purposes and those used for sport, recreation and breeding which are not associated with the production of food, etc.  Will the Minister indicate whether sufficient clarification is provided in the Bill of this matter?</P>
        <P>Is it safe to assume that under the definition of what constitutes a premises, a farm dwelling house is exempt?  I have also been asked to seek clarification of the definition of protected animals.  Does the definition distinguish between animals kept for farming purposes and those kept for other purposes?  I accept that this is probably covered by the definition of a farm animal to which I have referred.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><TitleTxt>Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>We are trying to cover all animals, including farm animals, in the legislation.  However, we make a distinction in respect of farm animals in the context of farming practices and so forth.  We also make a distinction in respect of the treatment of some animals which are hunted in the course of normal hunting or fishing practices &mdash; this is covered later in the Bill &mdash; although some requirements need to be met in terms of acceptable standards and so on.  We have tried to make a distinction between animals which are farmed and other animals, whether they are kept for domestic purposes, pets or whether they are wild animals.  It may be somewhat dangerous to get into terminology such as &ldquo;self-sustaining animals&rdquo;.  Certain animals are at risk of extinction if we do not act to protect them, for example, the red squirrel.  This may be because of other animals encroaching on their territory or because of human activity.</P>
        <P>We have deliberately tried to keep &ldquo;animal&rdquo; as a broadly defined word.  Moreover, we have deliberately referred to &ldquo;farm animals&rdquo; because they are in a different category in many ways with regard to acceptable practices in the normal course of farming and so on.  Some of the amendments are attempts to deal with this issue and we can discuss them and try to accommodate the Senator&rsquo;s concerns.  We will take it amendment by amendment.</P>
        <P>I have received a note in respect of the matter of premises and a farm dwelling.  The latter is distinct and requires a separate warrant.  The broader definition of a &ldquo;premises&rdquo; includes a farm dwelling as well.  If an animal is being kept within a farm dwelling and is being abused, it should apply whether it is a farm dwelling or another dwelling.  If animals are being abused something should be done about it.  There is a distinction between human dwelling places and other premises in terms of the need for a warrant to send someone in to examine them.  In other words, there will not be authorised officers walking into people&rsquo;s homes because they have heard something or because they have some evidence of cruelty.  That would require a warrant whether it is a farm dwelling or an urban dwelling.  There is a distinction in terms of the required warrant for entering a person&rsquo;s dwelling.  Farm families can and should be reassured in this regard.  That is not to say that if there is evidence or a reason to believe there is significant cruelty going on within a house an authorised officer could not get a warrant to knock on the door.  I hope the questions have been addressed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister has clarified the position on the question I asked about wild animals.  I meant to include a reference to &ldquo;and includes (but is not limited to)&rdquo; in page 9 at line 6.  This is followed by a list of bovine and other animals.  The Minister has clarified it but I presume it includes hounds, working dogs and sporting horses.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is by way of clarification.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
        <P>Section 3 to 7, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 8</P>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 1 and 6 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed to?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 11, subsection (1), lines 10 and 11, to delete &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This amendment relates to the wording &ldquo;take necessary measures to ensure that&rdquo;.  Sections 8(1)(<i>a</i>) and 8(1)(<i>b</i>) follow.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">4 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>It refers to taking all necessary measures to ensure the animal is unable to stray from the land, that all buildings, gates, fences, hedges, boundary walls and other structures used to contain the animal are constructed and maintained in a manner that minimises the risk the animal will stray and the risk or spread of disease.  My amendment seeks to replace the word &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; with &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo;.  I seek to do the same in amendment No. 6 on section 11.  The word &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; has the potential to create difficulties for farm holdings and farmers.  I would like to hear whether the Minister agrees with the amendment and, if not, I would have no difficulty with him proposing an alternative wording.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>It is not an unreasonable suggestion, particularly in regard to section 8, but if I accept an amendment I want to make sure it is legally sound.  I want to explain the difference between these two amendments.  Section 8 is about preventing animals straying by putting up fencing and developing an environment that ensures animals do not stray.  The Senator is suggesting that all reasonable measures, rather than all necessary measures, should be taken to do that.  I do not have a strong view on which word should be used, and I would not be against accepting his amendment, but I would like to check that with our legal people.</P>
        <P>I have a problem with amendment No. 6 because it is about the duty to protect animal welfare, which is at the heart of this legislation.  It is important to have absolute clarity in terms of what we are requiring of people.  I want people to take necessary steps to protect animal welfare as opposed to reasonable steps, which is ambiguous.  When we are talking about ensuring animals do not stray, the word &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo; may not be as vital.  If the Senator is happy to withdraw these amendments, I will consider introducing the word &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo; if it makes sense legally to do that.  If there is a problem with it, I will let the Senator know but I would like to leave the word &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; in section 11, if he is happy to agree that.  That is as far as I can go on that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>That is acceptable.  I thank the Minister for being so forthright.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>On Fianna F&aacute;il&rsquo;s amendment No. 1 to replace the word &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; with &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo;, will the Minister clarify the matter on Report Stage?  He said he would consider replacing &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; with &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo;, as is suggested in amendment No. 1, because it relates to control of disease, but regarding amendment No. 6, which deals with protecting animal welfare, the word &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo; should be inserted because the section states: &ldquo;Where a person having possession or control of a farm animal fails to comply with <i>subsection (1) </i>and that person is not the owner of the farm animal, then the owner of the animal shall also have committed an offence under <i>subsection (3)</i>&rdquo;.  Section 8&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>That is a separate amendment.  We will come to that shortly.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>I will come back in at that stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SusanOKeeffe"><NameTxt>Senator Susan O&rsquo;Keeffe</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the retention of the word &ldquo;necessary&rdquo;.  I believe that in both cases, the word &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; is what gives this Bill its strength and makes it stand out from where we have been.  Most farmers will assume the reasonable thing, but to make it necessary is at the heart of what this Bill is about.  I appreciate the Minister will obviously look at it, but I would like to see the word &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; retained in both cases.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>In fairness, the Minister has expressed a willingness to look at this before Report Stage.  Will Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill withdraw his amendment?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I will withdraw it.  I accept totally what the Minister has said.  I would just like to clarify the reasoning behind the words &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; and &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo;.  If a farmer has put up fencing, and for one reason or another, people break those fences and animals stray, then the question of &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; versus &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo; comes into play, as well as the potential of fines and whether they are class A or otherwise.  I wanted to bring in a little bit of common sense thinking on the issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The matter will be put on hold until Report Stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 11, subsection (1)(<i>b</i>)(ii), line 19, after &ldquo;kept&rdquo; to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;having regard to the potential of wind borne spread of disease or of protected or other species of wildlife spreading disease&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This amendment again deals with section 8(1) and the risk or spread of disease onto farmland or premises on which the animal is kept.  The potential of wind borne spread of disease, or of protected or other species of wildlife spreading disease, is obviously outside the control of a farmer.  There has not been a low incidence of the spread of wind borne disease in this country, although it certainly has happened in other countries.  I do not want farmers to be left exposed if that line in my amendment is not put in.  I would like to hear the Minister&rsquo;s thoughts.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>Ironically, we are asking farmers to do a little bit more here, but it is not necessarily a bad thing to do.  Disease is often spread by wind borne spores or else by wild animals.  For example, the badger culling programme, which nobody likes but is very necessary in my view, has produced significant results in reducing the incidence of TB in Irish herds.  They have not taken a similar approach in the UK, and they have had much more difficulty in reducing TB levels in British herds.  There is clear evidence to suggest that wildlife can spread diseases.  We had a recent incidence of this in respect of bird flu.  There is also evidence on wind borne diseases.</P>
        <P>If we were to introduce this amendment, it would reinforce the idea that we change the word &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; to &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo;, as per amendment No. 1.  If we are asking farmers to take account of the spread of disease through wildlife when they are putting up fencing or housing, I do not think we can be unreasonable to them if a badger gets through the gap and people can make a connection between that and a TB reactor in the herd.  I do not think people should be taken to court for that, but we should be encouraging farmers to think about the spread of disease in its fullest sense, such as through wind borne diseases or wild animals.</P>
        <P>I would like to look at this amendment and try to improve it a bit.  I hope the Senator will not take offence to that.  I told my officials that I think this is a useful suggestion, but I am not sure about the actual legal terminology used.  I cannot accept the amendment as it is, because I would not want to have to delete it on Report Stage.  I would, however, like to accept the spirit of the amendment.  As with amendment No. 1, would Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill be happy for me to have a look at it and come back with a proposal on Report Stage?  The Senator may also table the amendment again on Report Stage.  If I do not accept it then he may press the amendment at that stage if he wishes.  If he gives me a chance to have a look at the proposal I will try to incorporate the spirit of what he proposes into the section.  His proposal is a useful addition.  I would like to talk to some of the farming organisations to make sure that what we are putting in is reasonable.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I will withdraw the amendment.  This is a matter of practicality.  A farmer should not be legally liable if a wind borne disease is present on his or her land.  If the Minister or his officials have an opportunity to speak to some of the farm organisations that would be welcome.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 11, subsection (2), line 20, after &ldquo;excuse&rdquo;, to insert &ldquo;or without right of way&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I welcome the Minister to the House.  Senator Reilly, who represented Sinn F&eacute;in during the debate on Second Stage of the Bill, is, unfortunately, sick at present.  I am stepping in for her today.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 3 deals with rights of way.  All public representatives deal with issues of right of way on a regular basis.  I am dealing with two such issues in my own county of Waterford at present.  I know the importance of rights of way, how they are valued by people, the purpose they serve and the frustration caused if they are removed.  A right of way can lead to a beach or a source of water or provide access across a field.  Blocking a right of way can be seen as a breach of property rights.</P>
        <P>I fully support the main thrust of the Bill.  It is important legislation which my party fully supports.  It is important, however, that the intent of the Bill in this area is not misunderstood.  We have no difficulty with what the Bill is trying to achieve with regard to ensuring that people do not open gates or entrances or do anything that would harm animals.  We are concerned that confusion might arise if our amendment is not accepted and the words we propose are not added.  It is important that confusion does not reign in issues as important as this.  Right of way disputes can lead to unnecessary tensions, and dialogue is the best way of dealing with them.  I fear the wording of the section might be misunderstood by some and I look forward to the Minister&rsquo;s response to the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I hope Senators do not get the wrong impression.  I will not be able to accept every amendment.  I will try to accept the spirit of a number of them.</P>
        <P>I know what the Senator is saying here.  However, the section is not, in fact, about right of way.  It, essentially, says a person shall not damage or interfere with a building, gate, fence, hedge, boundary wall or other structure used to contain farm animals unless the person has a lawful excuse to do so.  This includes, potentially, right of way.  Even if a right of way goes through a person&rsquo;s farm, we must, nevertheless, try to ensure that people close gates after themselves and do not damage walls.  A person who is walking on a right of way may, occasionally, have to climb over a hedge or another obstacle.  The existence of a right of way does not limit our responsibility for animal safety while using the right of way.  We are always obliged to close gates behind us, and so on.</P>
        <P>The terminology in line 20, page 11, which says, &ldquo;without lawful excuse&rdquo; should cover a myriad of things, including right of way.  I cannot accept the Senator&rsquo;s amendment which excuses people from damaging or interfering with a building, gate, fence or hedge because it is part of a right of way.   That is sending a signal that people who are walking along or using a right of way do not have to be conscious of the fact that there may be an animal next door.  It is a fair point to raise rights of way but this section does not preclude people from walking along a right of way.  If a farmer decides to put a gate across a walkway where there is a legal right of way, there is nothing to stop someone taking a legal case against him or her, but if there are cattle in the field and someone opens the gate and walks through because they see it as a right of way, they have a responsibility to ensure the cattle do not go out the gate.  It is likewise if there was a sheep pen or something else of that nature.  The aim of the measure is to ensure that as people walk across the countryside, they do not deliberately open gates or release animals.  It is about making people conscious of the fact that if there are animals kept either in a pen, a shed or a field, everyone has a responsibility to ensure that if they are enclosed they remain enclosed if that is appropriate.  I cannot accept the amendment because I do not want a person to make a case in a court of law, having left a gate open and where an accident ensued, to say in his or her defence that it was a right of way and therefore there was no need to close the gate.  I am trying to give a practical example of what might happen.  &ldquo;Without lawful excuse&rdquo; should cover rights of way as it is and that is probably as far as we should go.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>Our amendment was not to excuse people who have access or right of way through a farmer&rsquo;s land from not doing what he or she should do, namely, close gates and refrain from damaging hedges, for example.  Our concern was that this provision could be misunderstood and abused by some people who might erect gates on rights of way to frustrate people from gaining access.  I am mindful of the Minister&rsquo;s response.  Perhaps we could examine the matter further on Report Stage.  As I am somewhat persuaded by the Minister&rsquo;s response, I will withdraw the amendment with a view to examining the matter again on Report Stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I will examine the matter again to see whether the amendment adds to the Bill.  If that is the case, I do not have a problem with it, but I suspect it is probably not necessary.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 8 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>This is a matter that concerns Senator O&rsquo;Neill and which he has partially addressed.  The Minister indicated there could be a response down the line.  Will the Minister clarify section 8(4), which relates to where a person having possession or control of a farm animal fails to comply with subsection (1) and that person is not the owner of the farm animal, then the owner shall also have committed an offence?  There is probably a reasonable explanation for it but it would seem to me that where a person operating an animal feed lot or livery stable does not conduct his or her business properly under the law, the owner of the animal could also be prosecuted.  Perhaps there is an explanation but it appears that if the person is not the owner of the farm animal, the owner shall also be deemed to have committed an offence.</P>
        <P>In layman&rsquo;s terms it appears to me that if I am the owner of a horse and the horse is in livery in a stable where, unknown to me, things are not operating as they should and there is some sort of inspection, it is not just the operator who is liable to prosecution but I, as the owner of the animal, could also be considered responsible for the difficulty.  The way the provision is written would appear to indicate the owner of the animal shall also have a liability.  Where a person who is not the owner of an animal but is in possession of it fails to comply with the section, the owner shall also have committed an offence.  Perhaps the Minister might reflect on this provision.  There may be an explanation, but it is not jumping off the page for any of us.  Senator O&rsquo;Neill brought this matter to my attention and I am sure that he will contribute.  In particular, I have in mind people in the equine business.  Livery is an important part of the care of horses.  As the Senator mentioned to me, a horse might break out of a livery yard or stable where the owner of said stable does not have matters fully in order.  That person is not the animal&rsquo;s owner, yet this provision seems to indicate that the owner would also be guilty of an offence.  A little clarification might be required.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree with Senator Bradford.  He has pointed out a matter that might require further discussion.  This issue has to do with section 8 on animals straying.  According to the wording of subsection (4), if a person is in possession of an animal, for example, someone in a contract rearing or bed and breakfast arrangement who looks after animals, and the animal strays, the owner is culpable even though he or she had no knowledge of or played no part in breaking a fence or the fact that a shed is capable of being escaped from.  The owner is seen as having committed an offence.  I am unsure.  Perhaps I am reading the Bill incorrectly, but this provision seems to leave the owner in a difficult position despite having had nothing to do with the animal going astray.  There may be a logical explanation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senators Bradford and &Oacute; Domhnaill for raising this matter.  Senator Bradford has read out the subsection starting on line 25.  This matter has to do with Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill&rsquo;s amendment on deleting the words &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; and &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo;.  Although I am jumping around the Bill, this subsection is tied to section 11(3), as both read exactly alike.  As the Minister pointed out, these two provisions might apply in different circumstances.  One relates to the control of disease by prohibiting animals from straying and the other relates to animal welfare.</P>
        <P>What reasonable and necessary steps can an owner take if his or her horse, for example, is in a livery yard or a feed lot?  What would happen to the owner who sent a horse to a farrier or vet or a dog to a boarding kennel?  Will the Minister examine the wording in these two subsections?  They will have implications for the rights of owners.  An owner may take reasonable steps to ensure that his or her animal is looked after well and give that animal to someone else in good faith.  Perhaps the word &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; needs to be changed.  The subsections&rsquo; wording needs to be changed, given the differences between livery yards, feed lots, farriers, vets and boarding kennels.  There is too great an onus on the owner.  If a person hires someone to look after an animal, the onus is on the latter to do his or her job.  I will make excuses for no one, but an owner might not be in a position to inspect his or her animal even once per day, week or month.  He or she has handed that animal over to be cared for in good faith.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I will provide the reasoning behind the wording as is.  We are trying to ensure that the owner of an animal does not hide behind an employee working in the yard, on the farm or in the livery if that animal is being abused, subjected to cruelty or whatever.  For this reason, the Bill&rsquo;s wording is, &ldquo;unless the owner shows that he or she took all reasonable steps to ensure that all necessary measures in the circumstances were taken to comply with subsection (1)&rdquo;, which is on the prohibition of farm animals straying.  This section is not about cruelty to animals broadly.  Section 8(1) states:</P>
        <P LI="1">A person who has in his or her possession or under his or her control a farm animal shall, having regard to the animal&rsquo;s nature, type, species, breed, development and environment, take all necessary measures to ensure that&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>a</i>) the animal is unable to stray from the land or premises where it is kept, and</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>b</i>) all buildings, gates, fences, hedges, boundary walls and other structures used to contain the animal are constructed and maintained in a manner that minimises</P>
        <P LI="3">(i) the risk that the animal will stray...</P>
        <P FLI="0">I will think about the concerns expressed by Senators.  I have good practical experience of what it is like to have a horse 40 miles from where I am living which is being looked after by a friend.  Likewise, an owner of a suckler herd may be sharing grazing facilities with another farmer.  There could also be the case of a dog placed in kennels when his or her owner goes on holiday which escapes.  There are many cases of people who, for whatever reason, may arrange for their animals to be in the possession, control or responsibility of somebody else.  We do not want people to be prosecuted because of the irresponsibility of somebody else while minding their animals.  At the same time, I want to ensure there is a responsibility on an owner to ensure good care is taken of his or her animals if they are being looked after by someone else.  It is about getting the balance right between the responsibility that comes with ownership of an animal and the practical realities of farming.  The Department&rsquo;s view is that this issue is covered by the provision &ldquo;he or she took all reasonable steps to ensure that all necessary measures . . .&rdquo;.  I will examine this provision before Report Stage to see if it can be improved.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>The wording of section 8(4) should be different from that of section 11(3) as they cover different circumstances, namely, the straying of animals and welfare issues.  Welfare is much more important in that somebody should take the necessary rather than reasonable steps.  However, this wording should not be used in section 8(4).</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I call Senator Paul Bradford.  In fairness the Minister has said he will reflect on this issue before Report Stage.  He is not shutting the door.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate the Minister&rsquo;s consideration of the issue.  The section should read, &ldquo;the owner shall have reason to believe all necessary measures are taken&rdquo;.  That would provide for a reasonable balance.  Under the current wording, the owner would almost have to have an audit undertaken of the place where his or her animal is kept.  It would be better if the obligation on the owner was to have a reasonable belief matters were in order.  Owners would not give their animals to people who would not look after them properly.  How can an owner take all reasonable steps to monitor someone else&rsquo;s property?  I look forward to the Minister coming back to us on this issue.  We are all at one in that we want to ensure every animal, be it a farm or domestic animal, is properly looked after and cared for, but we do not want too many difficulties to arise from genuine mistakes.  Perhaps we can arrive at a working compromise.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>This is a genuine issue.  What we do not want is prosecutions being taken against owners in circumstances where they may be paying for and have reason to believe, as the Senator said, that everything should be right and proper with a housing facility, livery or whatever.  I will examine the issue and will try to arrive at a wording that is fair without absolving people of the responsibility that comes with owning an animal, which is what the legislation is about.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
        <P>Section 9 agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 10</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 12, lines 19 to 21, to delete subsection (4) and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;(4) The Minister may for the purposed of <i>subsection (3)</i> issue a permit and may attach such terms and conditions to it as he or she considers appropriate.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This amendment concerns authorised officers, who are defined in section 2 as a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, an officer of Customs and Excise, or a person appointed under <i>section 37</i> during the period of his or her appointment.  Section 10(4) states:</P>
        <P LI="1">An authorised officer may for the purposes of <i>subsection (3) </i>issue a permit and may attach such terms and conditions to it as he or she considers appropriate.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Without questioning the role or functions of an authorised officer, the subsection gives him or her much latitude.  It would be more appropriate for the Minister to have the power to issue a permit and attach such terms and conditions as he or she considers appropriate, following consultation with an authorised officer, rather than give an authorised officer on the ground the responsibility to attach such terms and conditions as he or she sees fit.  The subsection appears to be very wide-ranging.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>The reality is that such a permit would be issued by a qualified person on the ground who may be an employee of a local authority and, therefore, the term &ldquo;Minister&rdquo; is inappropriate.  In the past this terminology has been used as a basis for litigation by those who have worked on the assumption that all permits must be issued by the Minister personally and not by one of his or her officers.  This is an important section.  It is about ensuring that we can enforce the rules in regard to the deliberate spread of disease.  If a person has an animal which he or she knows to be infected and is trying to get rid of it from the farmyard and sell it, we need to be able to act quickly.  That is the reason for authorised officers, whether at local authority level or working from my Department.  We do not need a process whereby the Minister would have to personally authorise the actions of an authorised officer for the purpose of inspections or appropriate action on freezing the movement of animals.  We have a set of rules for authorised officers governing the appropriate response when they have reason to believe something like this is happening under section 10(3).  I would like to place some trust in these officers to behave as they see fit.  If their response is over the top, the Minister may have to intervene, but it is important to place some trust in them.  The authorised officers will be qualified.  Perhaps we might discuss this issue later in the debate.</P>
        <P>There was a concern, particularly among farming organisations, that many new officers who might not have much experience of farming but who might be connected to animal welfare organisations would be appointed.  Authorised officers need to be qualified.  Predominantly, they should be veterinarians or veterinary nurses who understand animals and the complexity of animal welfare issues as opposed to individuals who may well be well meaning but who are not qualified or informed to make the necessary decisions.  I am not sure there will be a change to the current group of authorised officers who undertake farm inspections.  Experience of how farms work is important to the authorised officer&rsquo;s role.  Local authorities, as well as my Department, have a responsibility to put such officers in place in certain instances.  Involving the Minister in sanctioning these appointments would probably be too restrictive in the context of getting the job done quickly.  Therefore, I cannot accept the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I fully appreciate the Minister&rsquo;s comments and accept his reference to making the system too unwieldy.  If there was an issue in every county on a particular day and everything had to go through the Minister, I appreciate it would take more time to deal with it.  The authorised officers will be professional staff, but they can be members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and Customs officers.  In this case, they will not have the knowledge or expertise to address specific agriculture queries, but I assume they will work with a veterinarian or a veterinary nurse.  Will the Minister attach to the legislation a list of the terms and conditions the officers can apply?  This would help authorised officers also.  I am not trying to confine the terms and conditions they can apply where there is a breach.  Would it be appropriate to have prescriptive terms and conditions attached to the legislation in order that where an authorised officer has a query, he or she could deal with it using black and white terms and conditions?  The farming organisations and farmers in general would then also be well aware of the consequences of a breach.  The expression &ldquo;such terms and conditions as they may consider appropriate&rdquo; is vague.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>The vagueness of the reference is its strength because it gives authorised officers the flexibility they need in responding to any situation.  The requirement is that authorised officers be of a high standard, but I would like to provide them with the flexibility they need to respond according to need.  The Senator is correct that some officers may well be garda&iacute; or Customs officials because we do not know where an incident will occur.  It could happen in a port, mart or at the horse sales, but, more than likely, it will happen on a farm.  I will examine this issue again, given that the Deputy has raised it, but we are trying to be flexible in the legislation to allow authorised officers to do their business as they see fit.  If there is a problem, we can follow up on it, but that is the intention.  Having in place authorised officers who are properly qualified and informed in their work is the best approach to take.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I will withdraw the amendment on the basis of the Minister&rsquo;s undertaking to review the matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 5:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 12, subsection (5), line 22, to delete &ldquo;This section does&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;This section and <i>section 12 </i>do&rdquo;.</P>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>This is a technical amendment to include section 12 in the exemption contained in this section in respect of activities authorised in accordance with the Cruelty to Animals Act 1876, the Animal Remedies Act 1993 and the Irish Medicines Board Act 1995.  The exemption relates to experiments conducted in laboratories, predominantly for the purpose of testing for human health reasons.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Section 10, as amended, agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 11</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 6:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 13, subsection (1), line 5, to delete &ldquo;necessary&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;reasonable&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">In light of the Minister&rsquo;s offer to review the proposal before Report Stage, I will withdraw the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 7:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 13, subsection (1)(<i>b</i>), lines 23 and 24, to delete all words from and including &ldquo;that&rdquo; in line 23 down to and including &ldquo;suffering&rdquo; in line 24 and substitute &ldquo;appropriate to the animal species&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Subsection (1)(<i>b</i>) states:</P>
        <P LI="1">having regard to the animal&rsquo;s nature, type, species, breed, development and environment, ensure that all buildings, gates, fences, hedges, boundary walls and other structures used to contain the animal are constructed and maintained in a manner that the animal is not caused injury or unnecessary suffering.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have no difficulty with these provisions.  However, the amendment arises from the fact that various forms of fencing may not be suitable for all species.  For example, sheep netting would not be suitable for cattle just as barbed wire fencing would not be suitable for sheep.  As it stands, a farmer who, in the course of loading cattle into a trailer, finds that one of them has injured itself on barbed wire fencing would be negligent under the legislation even though that type of wiring has been used for generations to contain cattle.  I appreciate that the Minister may consider the amendment too broad, in which case I would have no difficulty if he were to come back to the issue on Report Stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I am not satisfied with the Deputy&rsquo;s wording in this amendment.  The difficulty is that the phrase &ldquo;appropriate to the animal species&rdquo; does not deal with suffering or welfare issues.  One certainly might make the assumption that it does do so, but we are striving for the utmost clarity in terms of the requirements on farmers and other animal owners.  Specifically, we must ensure they have regard to the animal&rsquo;s nature, type, species and so on and that they ensure all buildings used to contain animals are constructed and maintained in a manner conducive to the welfare of those animals.  We need to ensure animal owners have regard to the animal&rsquo;s nature, type, species and so on and to ensure all buildings used to contain the animal are constructed and maintained in a manner that ensures the animal is not caused injury or unnecessary suffering rather than just say &ldquo;appropriate to the animal species&rdquo;, because that could be appropriate in terms of efficiency as regards stocking rates, for example, or appropriate as regards access to water, feed or whatever.  The section specifically states: &ldquo;in a manner that the animal is not caused injury or unnecessary suffering&rdquo;.  In other words, there must be adequate space.  Animals need to be able to move around.  They should not fall through slatted floors.  Likewise, it is not always cattle.  It could be some other form of housing that ensures animals are not causing themselves injury by simply trying to move around.  For me, this is quite an important section on which we need to be very clear in terms of people&rsquo;s responsibility in terms of the housing of animals and ensuring animals do not cause themselves unnecessary suffering.  I mention sharp objects on the ground or sticking out of the wall and so on.  That is not really covered by the words &ldquo;appropriate to the animal species&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>I know what the Senator is getting at and I will take a look at it but we need a much stronger wording than what he proposes.  Perhaps there is something we could include which recognises that different types of housing are required for different types of species.  I do not have a problem with that.  If the Senator wants to come back with an amendment on Report Stage, I will look at it but I want the words &ldquo;that the animal is not caused injury or unnecessary suffering&rdquo; and that we have a practical approach towards the housing of animals which will not lead to unnecessary injury.  I am afraid I will stick with my wording on this.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I listened carefully to the Minister and accept everything he said.  Perhaps the wording in the amendment is not ideal.  We will have another look at it.  This side of the House supports fully anything which would ensure animals suffer less or ensure there is no undue suffering.  Perhaps the wording of the amendment did not encapsulate that.  We will have a look at it and maybe come back.</P>
        <P>The point we are making is probably from a farming point of view.  Barbed wire fences are one example but there are probably others as well.  We will have a look at the amendment and come back on Report Stage.  The Minister might want to reflect on it as well.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>If the Senator comes back with something that adds to it, I will look at it.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Section 11 agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 12</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 8:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 13, subsection (1)(<i>a</i>), line 35, before &ldquo;do,&rdquo; where it firstly occurs to insert &ldquo;intentionally&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This is the prohibition on animal cruelty section.  It states: &ldquo;A person shall not &mdash; (<i>a</i>) do, or fail to do, anything or cause or permit anything to be done to an animal that causes injury (including disfigurement) or unnecessary suffering to, or endanger the health or welfare of, an animal&rdquo;.  We seek to add the word &ldquo;intentionally&rdquo;.  If a farmer or pet owner does something intentionally, it is a crime.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I will give the legalistic answer and then my view on it.  The proposed amendment weakens the welfare thrust of this Bill.  We have worked hard to achieve a fine balance between the rights of the individual and the need for the State to have the power to intervene where offences have occurred.  The Attorney General and the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel have been closely involved in the drafting of this Bill and have been very active in ensuring civil liberties and constitutional rights are upheld.  The reason we have sought legal advice on this is that we do not want a situation in which people go to court and say in their defence that they did not mean to do it.  If an animal is abused when someone comes home with too much drink taken or if a person flicks a cigarette into a barn and it goes up in flames, killing or burning animals, the person should not be able to defend himself or herself by saying it was not on purpose.  In the normal course of law, a person will have a natural defence, if something goes to court, that there were reasons that were outside his or her control.  I know exactly what the Senator is saying, and it is not unreasonable.  However, according to my legal advice, if we put in the word &ldquo;intentionally&rdquo; to obtain the phrase &ldquo;A person shall not . . . intentionally do, or fail to do, anything or cause or permit anything to be done to an animal that causes injury (including disfigurement) or unnecessary suffering to, or endanger the health or welfare of, an animal&rdquo;, it will severely weaken the capacity to achieve prosecutions where appropriate.  I can drop the Senators a note on our understanding of that, if they wish.</P>
        <P>I can understand why farming organisations have concerns in this regard.  Sometimes there are reasons, such as mental health problems, for a person behaving out of character or doing something unintentionally to cause suffering to animals in his or her ownership or control, but those circumstances would be taken account of anyway in a court of law, even if it were not put in as an excuse in the legislation.  Such an amendment would weaken the Bill.  In every case, solicitors and barristers would try to base their cases around whether the act was intentional.  To be fair, much of the cruelty that takes place in Ireland is probably not intentional.  Nevertheless, it may be significant, and we need to try to act on that to ensure behaviour changes.</P>
        <P>I am told that section 61 provides for mental health problems, so there is another section that deals with that particular issue.  I know there have been cases in which severe depression or other challenges may have led people &mdash; especially those living in isolation &mdash; to behave as they would not normally behave, and we need to take account of such things.  That type of person does not belong in prison, and should not be fined; they need help.</P>
        <P>In essence, this amendment weakens what we are trying to do, and I am not in a position to accept it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I will explain where I am coming from.  What about animal sports, or even, by a further extension, pest control?  There are sports such as stag hunting that we are not too used to up in Donegal, but there are many other sports such as hare coursing.  Where does that fall with regard to section 12?  The section states: &ldquo;A person shall not . . . do, or fail to do, anything or cause or permit anything to be done to an animal that causes injury.&rdquo;  Where does that leave the area of sports?  Does it have any effect?  I know there is other legislation dealing with sports, but where does it leave horse racing, for example?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>We went to great lengths to ensure we were not doing anything that would prevent people from continuing to participate in field sports as they would have in the past, as long as that is in a way that is consistent with the codes of conduct enshrined in those sports, including coursing, hunting and fishing.  The measure applies only if there is undue cruelty such as the digging out of animals when they have gone to ground, which is unacceptable.  In the legislation I am not banning coursing and hunting through the back door.  We are trying to get the balance right between facilitating field sports and ensuring the codes of practice agreed for those sports are respected.  If people begin to operate outside these codes, that is a different issue.  The legislation states:</P>
        <P LI="1">Nothing in this section applies in relation to anything which occurs in the ordinary course of&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>a</i>) fishing,</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>b</i>) lawfully hunting an animal, unless the animal is released in an injured, mutilated or exhausted condition, or</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>c</i>) lawfully coursing a hare, unless the hare is hunted or coursed in a space from which it does not have a reasonable chance of escape.</P>
        <P FLI="0">We have spoken to individuals involved in field sports to try to recognise what constitutes lawful hunting.  If there is behaviour outside this definition, we need to act on it legislatively.  The balance is about right on these issues.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Minister to clarify a few points on section 12.  On page 14&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>There are a number of amendments to section 12.  Normally we deal with the amendments first, after which we discuss the section.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Okay.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>It makes matters easier.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 9:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 14, subsection (2), lines 4 to 7, to delete paragraph (<i>b</i>).</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">5 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P FLI="0">Section 12(2)(<i>b</i>) reads, &ldquo;cruelly treat or beat, kick, ill-treat, over-work, over-drive, over-load, over-burden, torture, mutilate, infuriate or terrify an animal, or cause, procure or permit an animal to be so treated, infuriated or terrified&rdquo;.  My amendment is to draw attention to this paragraph which is over-descriptive.  There is nothing in it about normal agricultural practices.  The definition appears to cover all agricultural practices because very often normal farming practices, even when conducted professionally, can include infuriating animals.  Examples include trying to put a bull into a trailer and practices where animals are dealt with in close confines such as sheep dipping, dosing and tail docking and the de-horning of animals.  Many everyday farming practices appear to fall under the definition in section 12.  While I propose the deletion of paragraph (<i>b</i>), I would be willing to accept a prescriptive definition exempting normal farming practices.</P>
        <P>In other words, there should be a distinction made between &ldquo;cruelly treat&rdquo; or intentional cruelty, which the Bill which we support is trying to minimise or eradicate, and normal farming practices which we do not want to see included in those few lines, between lines 4 and 7.  That is where we are coming from.  We are willing to work with the Minister on the creation of that definition of farming practices, if that can be done on Report Stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I understand why Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill raised this issue.  In some ways, this is language of another time.  This subsection is based upon language included in the 1911 Protection of Animals Act.</P>
        <P>I can see no reason to remove this section.  It states that a person shall not beat, kick, over-work, torture, mutilate, terrify an animal, etc.  I can see no reason that such actions, which are clearly against all principles of animal welfare and which are currently illegal and have been so for the past 100 years, should now be made legal by this Bill.</P>
        <P>Having said that, the purpose of this legislation is to modernise both the legislation and the terminology used around animal welfare.  I do not want to legalise anything that is currently illegal around abusing animals, over-working them or over-driving them, and certainly not terrifying or infuriating them unnecessarily.  Section 16 deals with castration and other exemptions, and Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill might take a look at that while he is listening.</P>
        <P>I do not want to delete this until I have something better with which to replace it.  If Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill wants to come up with a wording for Report Stage that essentially sums up these practices but puts them in a more modern but acceptably legalistic language for the Bill, I will certainly look at accepting it.</P>
        <P>I do not want to start legalising practices that have been illegal for 100 years unless there is a reason to do so.  Essentially, we have maintained the wording in terms of beating, kicking, ill-treating and over-working animals.  In some ways, this paragraph sums up what this legislation is all about in terms of protecting animals, including wild animals, that may interact with human beings.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>On farm animals, I understand from where the Minister is coming.</P>
        <P>He might clarify the meaning of &ldquo;over-work&rdquo; and &ldquo;over-drive&rdquo;.  In what way will this apply to a man out hunting with a dog and a hunt out with a pack of hounds?  There may be unsubstantiated and malicious complaints made.  The Minister will be aware that there is an anti-hunt lobby in this country.  Who will follow-up on such a complaint?  Who will determine whether a dog is over-worked or over-driven, or a horse is over-ridden in a hunt?</P>
        <P Just="Left">I ask the Minister to clarify this.  Will there be a register kept of those who continuously make complaints because they may make these complaints for a nuisance factor rather than for the good of the animals?</P>
        <P>I would say nobody was aware there was a 1911 Act that contained this wording.  Who determines &ldquo;over-drive&rdquo; and &ldquo;over-work&rdquo; where it is one person&rsquo;s view against another&rsquo;s?  Somebody may telephone a section of the Department stating that a hunt has over-worked its hounds.  Who will determine that?  By the time the inspector gets there, the hounds would most likely have recovered.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>Hunting is dealt with in subsection (12).</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>It states, &ldquo;normal&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>Subsection (12) states anything which occurs in the ordinary course of lawfully hunting an animal, unless the animal is released in an injured, mutilated or exhausted condition.  We are trying to outlaw catching a fox that has been injured or mutilated and then releasing it again, in other words, throwing it to the hounds.  We are not condoning that type of activity for one second.</P>
        <P>On the point Senator O&rsquo;Neill makes, subsection (2)(<i>b</i>), in terms of hunting anyway, should be covered by subsection (12).  In other words, the normal course of hunting is not being outlawed in this Bill &mdash; not by a long shot.  Dogs and horses, as anyone who has been to a hunt will be aware, get very excited and over-exert themselves, but that is not what we are trying to stamp out here.</P>
        <P>Subsection (2)(<i>b</i>) is about laying down the rules, that the idea that one would beat, kick, ill-treat, over-work or over-drive an animal is not acceptable in law.  In fairness, a normal hunt will not be affected by that paragraph.</P>
        <P>In terms of the person who makes the judgment on it, I assume, if it is an authorised officer following up on a report of cruelty, there must be a judgment made in that regard but, ultimately, as with all of these matters, it is a court of law that decides in the end, if it goes that far.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Is Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill pressing the amendment?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>No.  I am willing to accept what the Minister has said and the assurance he has given that he is willing to look at a revised wording on the amendment on Report Stage.</P>
        <P>I agree that the 1911 Act was a long time ago.  None of the Minister&rsquo;s officials would remember that far back.  It shows the real need for updating the legislation when one sees that it is 101 years since that legislation.  I agree with the Minister.  How can he justify removing it, if it was there previously?  Coming up with a more sensible form of words might be the option.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>If this was a problem for hunts or for farmers, it has been there for 100 years in law and I would have thought it would have been a problem by now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Nobody knew it was available.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I am not aware that it has been an issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>Something must have happened last week.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I am not aware that it has been an issue, in the early 1900s or in the past couple of years.  As it was not an issue, we felt that to weaken the wording on it would send out the wrong signal.  If we can use better or more accurate language that reflects modern Ireland, I have no difficulty with looking at that.  At present, I do not want to weaken the wording.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 10 and 30 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 10:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 14, subsection (5)(<i>b</i>), line 21, to delete &ldquo;or a code of practice&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Amendment No. 10 relates to the code of practice and amendment No. 30 relates to the functions under the Bill on the establishment of a code of practice.</P>
        <P>In general terms, a code of practice would be good, particularly for pet owners.  For those obtaining their first animal as a pet, it would be good and responsible for them to adopt a code of practice.</P>
        <P>However, on extending it to the care and husbandry of farm animals, the farming organisations have raised queries on the code of practice and the implementation of a code of practice in respect of the keeping and rearing of farm animals for the production of food.</P>
        <P>No one knows how to rear animals better than a farmer and no one will give more attention to the rearing of animals than a farmer.  The farming organisations have raised issues about this section, section 25 and the introduction of a code of practice.  The introduction of a code of practice relating to the keeping, protection and husbandry of pets would be an excellent step.  As there may be a logical reason for what is being proposed, perhaps the Minister will provide reassurance in that regard.  We are seeking clarification as to whether the deletions proposed in the two amendments are necessary.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>Codes of practice are useful.  Other jurisdictions have been utilising them for decades.  The purpose of allowing the Minister of the day to adopt a code of practice from another state or organisation relates to administrative simplicity.  There is a provision in the Bill which requires public consultation to take place before the adoption of a new code of practice.  In a farming context, this type of process works well.  Prior to the adoption of codes of practice, for example, there is input from both farming bodies and welfare organisations through the Farm Animal Welfare Advisory Council.  The purpose of section 12(5) is to give an indicative, not exhaustive, list of considerations to be borne in mind when examining whether suffering is taking place.  Codes of practice are an obvious aid in this regard.  Some actions which might be deemed cruel could, in fact, be in accordance with a code of practice and this may speak in the animal keeper&rsquo;s defence.  Codes of practice could be used by the courts, even if they are not mentioned in the legislation.  It is more straightforward and fairer to everyone involved to retain the reference to a code of practice.</P>
        <P>We are trying to ensure people understand what is acceptable practice.  A code of practice is not necessarily legally enforceable.  It is actually a set of guidelines to which there should be adherence.  A code of practice can be used as an example or as evidence in court.  If a person is not abiding by an acceptable code of conduct, that can be a measurement of whether he or she is behaving in a cruel way.  I have been driving the agenda on codes of practice, particularly in the context of animal welfare organisations.  There are many well meaning individuals involved with such organisations who, in some instances, are taking on more than they can cope with, both financially and, in the context of space, from a resources point of view.  I refer to those who may be keeping horses, dogs or cats.  It is probably good that we should seek to put in place codes of conduct which make clear to those involved with animal welfare organisations, farmers, etc. what is or is not acceptable.  Codes of practice are not law, but they are recognised in law.  There is a difference in that regard.</P>
        <P>I wish to reassure people, particularly those in the farming community, that I have no intention of introducing a series of new codes of practice for how farmyards or cattle sheds should be run.  However, we are using codes of practice as a tool.  Last Christmas we introduced such a code for animal welfare organisations for the care of animals, re-homing, neutering, spaying and all of the other matters related to the responsible keeping of rescue animals.  There must be standards, codes of conduct and acceptable forms of behaviour when it comes to the care of such animals.  We have linked this with the grant aid available from my Department to support these organisations.  If such organisations reach a certain standard in the codes of conduct we are setting, we will support them financially.  However, if they do not reach the standard, we will not be in a position to provide such support.</P>
        <P>I understand why farming organisations would be concerned about discussions on new codes of conduct.  They are already concerned about the number of farmyard inspections which take place.  They do not want more form-filling, red tape and rules.  In many ways, farmers are the ones who understand, in most detail, how to care for animals because they do it for a living.  There is not going to be a raft of new codes of conduct.  If we were to consider the introduction of a code, we would be obliged to do so in consultation with farming organisations.  The last thing I want is the creation of a new enforcement nightmare in the implementation of codes of conduct on farms.  Any action we take in this area will occur in consultation and co-operation with farmers in order to ensure, from their point of view and that of the Department,that there will potentially be a better understanding of the appropriate ways to care for animals, whether they be farm animals or domestic pets.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>Section 25 does not state that before a code of practice or conduct is introduced, consultation must take place with the farming organisations.  Would it be possible to amend the section in order that reference would be made to a consultation process?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>This is covered under section 25(5)(<i>b</i>).</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>That paragraph states &ldquo;may, having considered any representations received, establish or adopt the draft code&rdquo;.  It does not state consultation shall take place.  Section 25 also states:</P>
        <P LI="1">(5) Before establishing or adopting a code of practice, the Minister&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>a</i>) shall publish on the website of his or her Department of State a draft of the proposed code...</P>
        <P FLI="0">Perhaps the Minister might consider including a reference to prior consultation taking place with the relevant organisations.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I will examine the position in that regard.  Such a reference would not be unreasonable, particularly as that is our intention.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>That might satisfy the farming organisations.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 11 and 12 are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 11:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 14, subsection (6), line 30, to delete &ldquo;reasonable grounds&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;evidence&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This is similar to a previous amendment and relates to the issue of authorised officers.  Section 12(6) refers to &ldquo;An authorised officer who has reasonable grounds for believing that a person is offending against this section&rdquo;.  I am seeking to have the term &ldquo;reasonable grounds&rdquo; removed and replaced with the word &ldquo;evidence&rdquo;.  The subsection would then read &ldquo;An authorised officer who has evidence for believing that a person is offending against this section&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 12 is to section 12(8) in which the phrase &ldquo;Where an authorised officer has reasonable grounds&rdquo; is used.  I am again suggesting the term &ldquo;reasonable grounds&rdquo; be replaced with the word &ldquo;evidence&rdquo; in this instance.  The term &ldquo;reasonable grounds&rdquo; is vague.  I am not for one moment questioning the professionalism of authorised officers, but I am concerned that the provision is overly vague.  Again, subsection (6) states &ldquo;An authorised officer who has reasonable grounds for believing that a person is offending against this section, in relation to an animal...&rdquo;.  If authorised officers are given the powers they rightly deserve, in exercising such powers they should be able to substantiate evidence, not just establish reasonable grounds.  As stated, the term &ldquo;reasonable grounds&rdquo; is vague, whereas &ldquo;evidence&rdquo; is much more concrete.  If garda&iacute; are entering a premises to seize drugs or deal with a complaint, they must have evidence before doing so.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>In some ways, this goes to the essence of what we are trying to change in law.  Much of the existing legislation which is outdated requires animal cruelty to take place before an authorised officer can act.  In other words, there must be evidence of cruelty before action can be taken or a prosecution pursued.  What we are trying to do is intervene at an earlier stage, particularly, as discussed, in the context of disease control.  If there is a suspicion that animals are being cruelly treated we want authorised officers to be able to act on it if they have reasonable grounds to do so.  This is the terminology we are using.  If a neighbour sees that animals are been repeatedly abused but he does not have photographic evidence, he may report it to the Department or the local authority.  At that stage we want authorised officers to be able to go in and make clear that they have received a report and that until they get to the bottom of it they want X, Y or Z to be done.  We are issuing a warning through this legislation to people who have committed offences.  We have no wish to take people to court unnecessarily.  We want the flexibility for early intervention when there are reasonable grounds for it in the case of suspected cruelty.  This can only happen through authorised officers.  This point is important; it is not the case that anyone can do it.  There is no point in having a hotline for the public to report instances of cruelty if one cannot act on those reports.  If the onus of proof is such that one must provide evidence before an authorised officer can intervene, then the cruelty has taken place before one can prevent it.  The purpose is to ensure that authorised officers can react to situations, reports or evidence that cruelty is taking place.  If they have reasonable grounds to believe that a person is offending against this section of the Bill, then they can take action.  We need to give them the appropriate powers.  Otherwise, there is a problem with the onus of proof and the gathering of evidence before an authorised officer can act.  I have no wish to go down the route where people are hiding behind a hedge with cameras trying to take photographs of others, whether they are farmers, huntsmen or whoever, and then going to authorised officers with photographic proof of certain things.  We are trying to ensure that if there are reasonable grounds for believing that cruelty is taking place, then authorised officers can act and respond quickly and in a way in which they deem appropriate.  To change the reasonable grounds to a requirement to have full evidence would significantly limit what authorised officers can do.  It would be a retrograde step for the Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I am keen to make some progress.  Are you satisfied with the proposed wording?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I have listened carefully to the Minister.  I accept the explanation he has given.  I had planned to push both of these amendments to a vote because I believe the reasonable evidence of proof for authorised officers is very wide.  Anyway, I appreciate where the Minister is coming from.  As public representatives, we have all experienced issues in our constituencies involving animal cruelty.  I appreciate the Minister&rsquo;s remarks and that authorised officers will be professional people who will react only on sound, reasonable grounds.  I am unsure, therefore, whether there should be any further clarification of the Bill at this point.  Perhaps not.  I am willing to accept what the Minister has said.  We are all aware of instances &mdash; the Minister referred to them as well &mdash; involving people who have too much alcohol consumed or who have mental health problems.  Other people have pets but cannot look after them.  Some farmers mistreat their animals by not feeding them properly and so on.  I accept on merit the comments of the Minister.  It probably makes sense to give the Bill teeth.  I accept his remarks on this basis and I will not press the moment.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 12 not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendment No. 13 is out of order since it involves a potential charge on the Revenue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to explain why.  I can understand why people may have been lobbied on this issue.  If an amendment has a cost to the Exchequer then it is automatically ruled out of order and, apparently, I am unable to say anything on it.  That is probably convenient from my point of view.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>It is out of order because it involves a charge on the Revenue.  The decision is self-explanatory.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment No. 13 not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 14:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 15, subsection (12), between lines 12 and 13, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;(<i>d</i>) normal farming or agricultural practices.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Section 12(12)(<i>c</i>) states &ldquo;lawfully coursing a hare, unless the hare is hunted or coursed in a space from which it does not have a reasonable chance of escape&rdquo;.  I propose to include a further subsection with the phrase &ldquo;normal farming or agricultural practices&rdquo;.  The beginning of section 12(12) states: &ldquo;Nothing in this section applies in relation to anything which occurs in the ordinary course of&rdquo;.  This relates to a previous discussion on hare coursing and the hunting of an animal and so on.  The matter is covered earlier in any event.  It answers a previous query raised.  Normal farming or agricultural practices should apply in this case as well.  This will lend a distinction and a definition to farming practices under that section.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>In its submission, the IFA stated that the vast majority of farmers treat animals according to the highest welfare standards.  I fully endorse this point and, as someone who has grown up with farming for a long time, I have personal experience of this.  Farm animals are well provided for by the Animal Health and Welfare act generally.  The exceptions listed in this section relate to wild animals as opposed to farm animals.  There is a similar provision in the Northern Ireland Act.  That was the basis for this part of the section and I do not propose to accept the amendment.  The main reason is that I have no wish to put normal farming practices in the same category as lawful hunting, coursing and fishing.  The reason we make an exception for fishing, hunting and coursing is that everyone accepts that there is a level of stress and animal suffering in fishing, hunting and coursing but that this is a part of these activities.  To put farming in this category suggests all the wrong things about farming.</P>
        <P>The majority of farmers in the country treat animals very well.  In the case of dairy herds many farmers know their animals by name.  Most farmers would be comfortable with the fact that this Bill applies to them as it does.  It recognises the status of farmed animals and the issues around farming and so on.  There is no need to make an exception for farming to put farm animals in the same category as hunting and coursing because they are in an altogether different category.  In many ways farming and farm practices are the best example of how animals should be looked after.  I am comfortable, as are the farm organisations, that farm animals should not be in the section since it would suggest in some way that farming, coursing and hunting are all part of the same type of activity.  They are very different.  I am satisfied that section 12(12) ensures that we do not disrupt lawful field sports.  This should not, however, apply to farming generally.  That would say something about farming that we have no wish to say in the Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator wish to press the amendment?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>No.  I accept what the Minister has said.  What I am trying to achieve, following consultation with the farming organisations, is that there would be a differentiation between other sports, for want of a better term, husbandry, caring for pets and so on and farming.  I want that distinction in respect of farming.  If a code of practice is introduced farmers will abide by that because they are looking for a return on their investment.  Given what farmers are trying to achieve and the role they will play in the development of Food Harvest 2020 I want that distinction for farmers because they are not covered exclusively under the animal cruelty section of the Bill.</P>
        <P>I tabled this amendment following discussions with the farming organisations which wanted it.  Fishing is included in the subsection also.  I am not making a distinction between farming and hunting or coarsing, and it is entirely different from fishing.  The reason behind this amendment, and the Minister can insert it elsewhere in the Bill if he wishes, is to make proper farming practices separate from the animal cruelty aspect of this section.  I appreciate the Minister may not be able to accept that because while 99.9% of farmers are responsible for the manner in which they farm and care for their animals, as in any profession a small number of them may engage in elements of animal cruelty.  That distinction could possibly be covered under the code of practice the Minister is proposing to introduce under the legislation.  That is the distinction I am endeavouring to make.  I was not trying to put it into a similar category.  Following the consultations with the organisations we felt this was the best section on which to table an amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>This is at the heart of the Bill, namely, prohibition of animal cruelty.  Many of the animals we have here are on farms.  If we decide to insert into this section wording to the effect that nothing in the section applies in regard to anything which occurs in the ordinary course of farming, what are we at here?  That is the reason the Bill contains sections which state that a person shall not cruelly beat, kick, ill-treat, over-work, over-drive, over-load, over-burden, torture or mutilate an animal.  That must apply on a farm as well as in a person&rsquo;s back garden.  This legislation is not just about eradicating dog fighting or cock fighting or dealing with people who go to work and leave their dog starving in the porch.  It must be about the majority of animals in the country, and I do not believe farmers have a difficulty with that as long as what we are asking them to do is not unreasonable.  As I have said repeatedly in the context of this legislation, farmers understand the importance of animal welfare probably better than anyone else.  They make their living out of it.  The healthier and happier their animals are generally, the more commercially successful are farmers.  I do not suspect that commercial return is the sole driver behind farming in terms of the relationship between farmers and animals.  The idea that we would exclude from the section on prohibition of animal cruelty the entire farming sector is not credible.  However, I understand the Senator&rsquo;s point about the need to respect commercial farm practice and make exceptions on issues such as tail docking, castration and dehorning, when appropriate, and all of the other practices a farmer must do with farm animals to control disease, infection and so on.  We are covered on that score.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The Minister might clarify two points.  First, on subsection (12) and the three opt-outs, I listened to what the Minister said about an element of risk or where pain etc. is involved in terms of fishing, lawful hunting an animal, and lawfully coursing a hare.  It may be covered elsewhere in the Bill through the use of other language but does the Minister see any reason to have horse racing and show jumping added to that list?</P>
        <P>Second, subsection (11) states: &ldquo;Nothing in this section applies to the destruction of an animal in an appropriate and humane manner.&rdquo;  The Bill makes provision in respect of veterinary officers, authorised officers etc. yet this subsection states that nothing in this section applies to the destruction of an animal in an appropriate and humane manner.  What if people out shooting or hunting, or someone who is alone, come upon a wounded animal or bird that has been shot and not killed, in other words, a dying animal, and they do not have immediate access to a veterinary officer or an authorised officer?  How does this subsection apply?  Why is it necessary if we are already making provision in respect of authorised officers and veterinary officers?  Is some flexibility not necessary in that regard?  I refer to people out hunting, fishing or shooting who may come upon a dying animal and where it would be in the interest of the animal to put it down.  An authorised officer or veterinary officer is not present in those circumstances.  Does this section provide for that?  I am confused in that regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I hope the Minister found us satisfactory at the races in Roscommon yesterday.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I did, yes.  We had a very enjoyable day in Roscommon yesterday.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Good.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>Section 23 deals with the humane destruction of an animal.  In amendment No. 26 I am improving that section in respect of some of the issues the Senator is concerned about.  If somebody comes across a dying animal it is often a charitable act to put it down if one has the expertise to be able to do that.  We do not want to unnecessarily prolong the suffering of an animal that may have been knocked down by a jeep, but I will deal with that section shortly.</P>
        <P>On the question of horse racing, my note indicates that horse racing is not mentioned but that section 12 would apply.  I am not sure what that means because if it is not mentioned I am not sure how it can apply.  I do not believe there is much cruelty attached to horse racing or show jumping but if somebody is mistreating an animal under any of the other subsections of section 12, whether it be cattle or horses, then it should apply.  If an animal is being rapped to make it jump a little higher, if a horse&rsquo;s legs are being damaged as a way of training it or if a series of unacceptable practices are being used in an effort to try to get a better performance from animals, there should be consequences on foot of that.  The same would apply in the case of the downright mistreatment of animals that were being beaten, kicked, not fed properly or appropriately housed.  That should apply too horses as much as it applies to any other farm animal.</P>
        <P>We are on section 12 but I think the Senator was referring to subsection (12) of thesection.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>We will deal with the section later.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I am sorry.  I was doing my adviser a disservice.  I do not believe we need to specifically name sports horses or horse racing.  Every now and again horses tragically die or are injured while racing; this is not something that will result in a prosecution.  Similarly, if an animal falls and breaks its leg in a field, it will not result in a prosecution either, as it is something that happens in the normal course of events.  Accidents sometimes happen, but when there is cruelty in the conditions outlined in section 12, whether in the racehorse or show jumping industry, we have to act.  If I am missing something, the Senator can talk to me later and we will do something about it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister&rsquo;s clarification.  The first line of section 12 rightly states a &ldquo;person shall not do, or fail to do, anything or cause or permit anything to be done to an animal that causes injury&rdquo;.  It does not include the words &ldquo;deliberately causes injury&rdquo;.  I am just thinking and trying to be protective of the horse racing and show jumping industries.  Unfortunately, an injury can occur at times when a horse jumps during a competition or during a race.  The legalistic definition included provides that a person shall not do anything that causes injury&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is dealing with the section.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>I am.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>We have not come to it yet; we are still dealing with amendment No. 14 in the name of Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>I thought we had moved on.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Unfortunately, we have not.  Does Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill intend to press the amendment?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>No.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 12 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>Perhaps the Minister might look at this issue with his officials and interested bodies.  The racing industry has strong representative organisations.  There might be a necessity to insert an opt-out clause because of the language used in the first part of section 12 which states a person shall not do anything that causes injury.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P>Do the exemptions listed in section 12 &mdash; fishing and hunting &mdash; match the sentiments behind the Bill, where they apply?  I appreciate that I am asking a question about the broad thrust of the legislation, but is it case that where the welfare of an animal is called into question, the Minister is unilaterally exempting fishing and hunting?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SimonCoveney"><NameTxt>Deputy Simon Coveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I will check the answers to Senator Paul Bradford&rsquo;s queries.  The last thing I want to do is to prevent a gymkhana in Mallow from going ahead because one would be breaking the law by participating in show jumping.  That is certainly not the intention, as I think people realise.  We will take a look at the issue and make sure we are not doing anything that will cause something we are not expecting.</P>
        <P>It is important to clarify the issue in respect of fishing, hunting and coursing.  We are talking about the act of fishing, hunting an animal or coursing a hare lawfully.  If somebody is keeping dogs to do this but is not feeding them or is abusing the hounds, that person is not exempt from the legislation.  Section 12oo(12) states, &ldquo;Nothing in this section applies in relation to anything which occurs in the ordinary course of . . . fishing . . . hunting . . . lawfully coursing&rdquo; and so on.  I accept Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill&rsquo;s comment that fishing is very different from the other two activities.  We are essentially providing for the distress or cruelty caused to animals in the course of hunting or coursing lawfully to ensure we can act if cruelty is inflicted by the owner on the animals used in the activity.  I hope I have made the distinction clear.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
        <P>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</P>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Ar 10.30 maidin am&aacute;rach.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters</Title>
    <Sect LHead="Missing" RHead="Persons"> 
      <sTitle>Missing Persons</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State.  This is the first time I have spoken in his presence.  He is someone for whom I have always had tremendous regard and it is great to see him in the House.  </P>
        <P>I submitted the same Adjournment matter last July.  At the time the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs was very positive about the commencement date of the missing persons&rsquo; hotline.  This is a pan-European number which many of our European colleagues have already set in motion, but this country has not yet put it in place.</P>
        <P>In her reply last July, the Minister said she was at an advanced stage in negotiating with a number of non-governmental organisations, NGOs, telecommunications operators and other voluntary groups involved in providing helplines to distressed people and it appeared that the service would be rolled out in Ireland in a matter of months.</P>
        <P>Given that students in Cork won a national competition for the Forget Me Not campaign, whose purpose is to ensure that people do not forget missing persons, the benefits of such a hotline are already agreed by all stakeholders.  It would provide a mechanism for members of the public who may have information that could facilitate Garda investigations.  Visitors to Ireland might observe something that an Irish person might not see as relevant.  The service would establish a relationship with our European colleagues who could share information.  In the age of communication, where social media are put to very good use, our society has an obligation to provide such a telephone number.  It has been agreed internationally and at European level.</P>
        <P>The service will not be cost-prohibitive.  It will not break the bank.  I know we are in a difficult economic climate and every penny must be accounted for.  We learned today from our colleague, Senator van Turnhout, that Childline receives no State funding, which is an issue for another day.  However, we have signed up to the hotline service and it is part of the European project.  I hope the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Fitzgerald, through her colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy McGinley, will give us some news and firm dates this evening.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DinnyMcGinley"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Dinny McGinley</NameTxt>
	<P>I am taking this Adjournment debate on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald.  I thank the Senator for raising this matter, which is obviously of concern to him and to all of us.</P>
        <P>I am pleased to be here to address the Seanad on the 116000 hotline.  I hope to update Members on progress that has been made on this issue.</P>
        <P>In Ireland the incidence of children going missing is fortunately low and we have witnessed a decrease in these figures year-on-year.  Any incident of a missing child is deeply traumatic and is a life changing event for any family.  We all share in the sense of unease and panic that surrounds accidents and misadventures involving children but to live with the reality of a missing child for one&rsquo;s whole life is a burden too great to contemplate.</P>
        <P>From the outset the Minister felt that there is a need to refocus and to ensure that a child-centred approach informs and shapes the way in which the 116000 hotline will be implemented and operate in Ireland.  The Minister for Children and Youth Affairs has taken a particular interest in this issue since her appointment.  Deputy Fitzgerald is especially pleased that the Irish Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, ISPCC, which has a proven track record in the delivery of child-centred services, has recently been allocated responsibility for the operation of the 116000 hotline number.</P>
        <P Just="Left">While support and services for children when they go missing and for the families of missing children are vital, the first action which should be taken when a child goes missing is to alert the relevant local authorities, which in the case of a child going missing in Ireland, is An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The investigation of the child&rsquo;s disappearance is the responsibility of the Garda, and their structures in this regard include not just the local garda&iacute; who will have primary responsibility for the investigation, but also its missing persons bureau.</P>
        <P>It is of paramount importance that any arrangements which are put in place to operationalise the 116000 hotline recognise that the first and foremost contact to be made is to notify the Garda so the investigation can commence without delay.</P>
        <P>In essence, the purpose of the 116000 telephone number is to provide a contact number to families if children go missing.  The setting up of the hotline has been overseen by an interdepartmental project team which was established in January of this year and which is chaired by the Department of Children and Youth Affairs.  The project team is cross-sectoral involving a number of Departments and agencies.</P>
        <P>The current position is that ComReg, following cross-departmental consultation and an examination of the issues involved by the project team, has now allocated the 116000 hotline number for Ireland to the ISPCC.  The operation of 116000 hotline is now a matter for the ISPCC which, I understand, has made an application for funding to the European Commission and a decision on this application is pending.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In the coming months the project team will be working to ensure that the hotline becomes operational in a timely manner and operates in a way that supports and augments existing arrangements to secure child protection.  To this end the ISPCC will develop interagency protocols with the HSE and the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</P>
        <P>Last week, the 116000 hotline number went live, with an interim message advising callers of appropriate action dependent on individual circumstances.  The ISPCC has indicated its preferred timescale of September 2012 for the hotline to be fully operational.</P>
        <P>In conclusion, I would like to thank Senator Conway for giving me an opportunity to address the Seanad on the 116000 hotline.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>This is very good news, with regard to missing children.  The ISPCC is the appropriate NGO to be responsible for this operation.  We now have a firm date of September 2012.  When the Minister of State, Deputy McGinley, walked in the door of the Seanad Chamber, I knew he would have good news.  I have not been disappointed in that regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DinnyMcGinley"><NameTxt>Deputy Dinny McGinley</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator very much.  Go raibh m&iacute;le maith aige.</P>
      </Speaker>
    </Sect>
  <Sect LHead="Leader" RHead="Programmes"> 
    <sTitle>Leader Programmes</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I have a simple question and, coming from his part of the country, he will be aware of the issue I raise.</P>
        <P>When will the west Kerry Gaeltacht be incorporated into the Leader scheme?  It is not clear whether it will be included with South Kerry Development Partnership or with North and East Kerry Development.  The matter has not been finalised and applications are awaited.  There seems to be a state of indecision.  I hope the Minister of State can clarify the position.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DinnyMcGinley"><NameTxt>Deputy Dinny McGinley</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  It affects my own constituency, being a Gaeltacht area.</P>
        <P>The Leader initiative was established by the European Commission in 1991.  It was designed to aid the development of sustainable rural communities following the reforms of the Common Agricultural Policy.</P>
        <P>Leader II commenced in 1994.  It extended the programme to all rural areas in Ireland and was delivered by 34 groups. While Leader I had been a pilot initiative, Leader II was designed to complement the strategy for rural areas in the National Development Plan 1994-99.  In addition to increased funding and coverage of all rural areas, emphasis was placed on the development of the acquisition of skills and improvements to the animation and capacity building levels to ensure delivery of the business plan for the area.</P>
        <P>Leader continued in the 2000-2006 round of EU funding and is currently operational in the 2007-2013 Rural Development Programme, RDP.</P>
        <P>Groups operated in all rural areas in the 2000 to 2006 programming period, while 35 groups are delivering the Leader element of the rural development programme 2007 to 2013 in all rural areas.  Since 1994, therefore, all rural areas, including all Gaeltacht areas, have been included in the Leader elements of successive rural development programmes.  The west Kerry Gaeltacht has also been included in successive rural development programmes since 1994 and there is no question of any Gaeltacht area being excluded from the Leader element of the programme.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">6 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>Meitheal Forbartha na Gaeltachta, the group contracted by the Department to deliver Axes 3 and 4, the Leader element, of the rural development programme in Gaeltacht areas, went into liquidation on 7 September 2011, leaving Gaeltacht areas without access to the programme temporarily.  Progress in the legal winding up of Meitheal Forbartha na Gaeltachta is ongoing.  The process of identifying those promoters whose projects are at an advanced stage of development and most likely to be ready to make a claim for payment is well advanced and an interim system, in co-operation with local development companies contiguous to Gaeltacht areas, including west Kerry, is in place to facilitate payment to these projects in the short term.  Many of these files have been sent to the relevant local development companies which will be in touch directly with the promoters to arrange payment in the very near future.</P>
        <P>In the context of delivery of Axes 3 and 4 of the rural development programme in Gaeltacht areas in the longer term, the Department is examining the submissions submitted as part of an overall process commenced in March which requested expressions of interest from established local development companies to deliver the Leader elements of the rural development programme in MFG areas for the remainder of the programming period.  In that context, an alternative delivery mechanism will be identified for all Gaeltacht areas formerly serviced by Meitheal Forbartha na Gaeltachta, including the west Kerry Gaeltacht.  Some further work has to be done to finalise this process.  However, I envisage its completion shortly.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryBrennan"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Brennan</NameTxt>
	<P>An bhfuil t&uacute; l&aacute;n s&aacute;sta leis an freagra sin?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  I understand the issue relating to payments, but, as is evident from his reply, there is no mechanism in place for new applicants.  People who have business plans and with ideas have nowhere to go.  The Minister of State has referred to a mechanism in place for those who have made applications for development which are at an advanced stage and and can claims payments, but it is clearly stated in the final paragraph of his reply that there is no mechanism in place for persons in the west Kerry Gaeltacht who have contacted me to make an application for Leader funding.  It is stated further work must be done to finalise the process and that it will be completed shortly.  We are nearly in the middle of the year; as the Minister of State is aware, the Leader programme operates from the beginning to the end of the year and it will be a long time before people can make applications.  I accept he might have similar issues with which to deal in his area, but in west Kerry people with ideas have nowhere to apply for Leader funding.  They are told the responsible bodies are the East Kerry Development Partnership and Sliabh Luachra Development.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryBrennan"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Terry Brennan</NameTxt>
	<P>Ceist ghearr le do thoil.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>They are supposed to be in charge of the process, but it has not been formally handed over and no one has been told to send applications to them, or where they should go if they have a business idea.  Perhaps the Minister of State might examine the matter again as the people concerned must have a place to make applications for Leader funding.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DinnyMcGinley"><NameTxt>Deputy Dinny McGinley</NameTxt>
	<P>I am in regular contact with the Minister on the matter because a Gaeltacht area forms a significant part of my constituency and is dependent on the programme.  Unfortunately, the structure in place for delivering the programme to Gaeltacht areas, Meitheal Forbartha na Gaeltachta, encountered difficulties and we are in the process of establishing a new structure.  There is EU involvement also because of the co-funding element.  I understand the process is at an advanced stage.  Expressions of interest have been sought and are being considered.  As far as I know, the issue will be resolved shortly.  The Minister has indicated that this is the case.  I would like to be able to say it will be done today, but it takes a while to dot the i&rsquo;s and cross the t&rsquo;s to make sure a structure will be in place for the delivery of the Leader programme in Gaeltacht areas up to 2013.  I am assured by all involved that Gaeltacht areas will be covered as soon as the new structure is operational.</P>
      </Speaker>
	  </Sect>
  <Sect LHead="State" RHead="Airports"> 
    <sTitle>State Airports</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdreClune"><NameTxt>Senator Deirdre Clune</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for coming to the House to respond to this issue as it affects Cork Airport.  It arises in the context of the Minister&rsquo;s announcement approximately two weeks ago on Shannon Airport, which was welcomed.  It has raised issues about Cork Airport and there is concern about when the same will happen there, being the next step in the restructuring of airports.  The matter is, therefore, urgent.</P>
        <P>Cork Airport is extremely important to the region.  It is one of the reasons for the high level of foreign direct investment in the Cork area, including in pharmaceutical and IT companies.  The connections to such strong hubs such as London and Amsterdam are vital to the region.  I have read the Booz report and believe the reporting on Cork Airport is positive.  Booz considers the outlook for the airport is positive.  While passenger numbers have dropped considerably, this is in line with the fall in passenger numbers internationally.  They have fallen in Dublin Airport also.  Booz considers that the economic outlook for Cork Airport is sound, based on its business plan and realistic projections.  The report recommends that Cork and Dublin Airports have separate authorities under a national aviation board.  The Minister has agreed with the recommendation that Cork Airport should have its own board and be autonomous; make its own decisions; develop its own routes and business plan.  That is important and what stakeholders want.</P>
        <P>Recently the chamber of commerce had a meeting on the subject.  Having spoken to airport management, worker directors, board members and the business community as a whole, I am aware that they want Cork Airport to have its own autonomous board and, as recommended in the Booz report, to make decisions for itself and not to be under the thumb of Dublin Airport.  To date, Cork Airport has been treated as an appendage in that it does not have its own decision-making process, which is what is wanted and needed.  The reason I raise the issue is that I would like the Minister to outline what is the next step for Cork Airport, his plans for it and the timeframe envisaged for its restructuring.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LeoVaradkar"><TitleTxt>Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Leo Varadkar</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  Following on from the Booz report on the future ownership and operation of Cork and Shannon Airports, the Government decided in principle to separate Shannon Airport from the Dublin Airport Authority and merge it with a restructured Shannon Development to form a new entity in public ownership.  It was also decided that the existing ownership of Cork Airport by the Dublin Airport Authority, DAA, would be maintained and that the DAA would be renamed to reflect the fact that there would be two airports in the group structure and an international business.</P>
        <P>The Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, and I will establish a steering group which will bring forward proposals for the implementation of the Government&rsquo;s decision.  Questions on the structural changes for Dublin and Cork Airports are to be considered by the steering group in the first instance.  However, the Government is strongly of the view that the future of Cork Airport is best served by it remaining within the DAA group.</P>
        <P>Central to the work of the steering group will be the preparation of proposals for the separation of Shannon Airport from the DAA and, in conjunction with the DAA, to agree a business plan for the Cork and Dublin State airports.  The group will also identify the optimum organisational structure for the merged entity to best suit the future development of the Shannon area, including a detailed business plan.  The Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation and I look forward to working with the key stakeholders to progress the many issues relating to the Government&rsquo;s decision and particularly the future of the three State airports.  Clearly, changes lie ahead for the airports, but it is in all of our interests to work together to ensure the future sustainability of all three State airports.</P>
        <P>When the steering group has finalised its recommendations later this year, the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, and I will revert to the Government with detailed proposals for the implementation of the Government decision.  These will include business plans for the restructured Dublin Airport Authority, DAA, as well as an implementation strategy for the establishment of the new entity at Shannon.  It is envisaged that this will include a plan setting out how the entity will contribute to achieving strong regional development while ensuring the highest standard of enterprise and support in the region.</P>
        <P>I am pleased to note that, while passenger numbers at Cork Airport have fallen continuously in recent years since its peak of 3.3 million in 2008, recent statistics show that the number of international passengers going through the airport is increasing.  I am hopeful that, with all stakeholders working together, this trend will continue for the remainder of the year and into 2013 when we will have the Gathering.  All of the events being planned around the country, including in Cork, will attract more than 300,000 additional visitors to Ireland next year.  The DAA and Cork Airport will actively support and engage with the event to ensure it reaches its full potential.</P>
        <P>I will address some of the direct matters raised by the Senator.  According to this year&rsquo;s figures to date, the number of international passengers using Cork Airport has increased every month.  This is encouraging.  Passenger numbers decreased last year, but it seems that they will increase this year.  A major change for the airport is the fact that there are no domestic flights anymore.  They will not return, given improvements in the road network.  What really matters is the number of international passengers, which is on the rise.  The recovery in international passenger numbers is more encouraging in Cork than it is in Dublin.  The recovery is non-existent in Shannon.</P>
        <P>There are different opinions on the airport&rsquo;s future.  Some members of Cork&rsquo;s business community take the view that separation or privatisation would be the best option.  Others take the view that the <i>status quo</i> or the <i>status quo</i> with more autonomy should obtain.  This is the outcome that I currently favour.  Unlike Shannon, Cork carries a considerable debt, largely related to the recent capital investment, that it will not be able to pay down on its own.  It will take quite some time for the large passenger volumes passing through Dublin Airport to raise enough funds to pay down the debt.  Only at that point could separation be considered, but it is some time away.  I could not put a timeframe on it.</P>
        <P>The other issue that arises in the case of Cork is that it is a different airport than Shannon.  Cork Airport is centred in a heavily populated region and beside a city of real scale.  Its future will primarily be led by increasing passenger numbers and passenger services as well as ancillary business.  The future of Shannon is probably more the other way around, with a greater emphasis on the aviation industry as well as passengers.  The airports are different beasts.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdreClune"><NameTxt>Senator Deirdre Clune</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister&rsquo;s favoured option is the <i>status quo</i> with more autonomy.  Are we awaiting the steering group&rsquo;s decision or is it a Government decision?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LeoVaradkar"><NameTxt>Deputy Leo Varadkar</NameTxt>
	<P>That is one of the recommendations in the Booz report, but the Government decision does not address it directly.  Rather, the Government decision addresses the fact that Cork will remain a part of the DAA group, with the DAA to be renamed and restructured to reflect the fact that it will become a different body.  The steering group will make recommendations on the structure of the new DAA or whatever it happens to be called.  The situation remains unclear.</P>
        <P>I take a strong view on Cork Airport.  If it does not have a separate, autonomous board, it should have significant representation on the main board.  It would not be acceptable for there to be only one or two representatives from Cork.  The view put forward by Booz is a strong one, namely, each of the sub-entities &mdash; Dublin, Cork and Aer Rianta International, ARI &mdash; should have its own board.  There are pluses and minuses to this suggestion.  Some people refer to the CIE model, which does not always work well.  The matter requires further consideration.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdreClune"><NameTxt>Senator Deirdre Clune</NameTxt>
	<P>Is there a timeframe?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LeoVaradkar"><NameTxt>Deputy Leo Varadkar</NameTxt>
	<P>We want to have all of this sorted this year so that there is no confusion or uncertainty.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdreClune"><NameTxt>Senator Deirdre Clune</NameTxt>
	<P>That is important.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LeoVaradkar"><NameTxt>Deputy Leo Varadkar</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.  However, it is not always possible to avoid either.  Although legislation might not be required, it could complicate matters further if it was.  Uncertainty creates problems, particularly when one is trying to attract businesses to an airport zone or to get airlines to start new routes.  They want clear answers to questions.  For this reason, a great deal of political capital and time is being spent on this matter to drive it forward and to ensure that, if possible, it is concluded within this calendar year.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdreClune"><NameTxt>Senator Deirdre Clune</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 6.15 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 23 May 2012.</adjournment>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" />
	</Sect>
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
