<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="6" Month="Jun" Year="2012" Vol="215" No="13" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 6 Meitheamh 2012" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 6 June 2012" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="725">
    <HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead=""> 
    <Title></Title>
        <P Just="Center">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Machnamh agus Paidir.</i></P>
        <P Just="Center"><i>Reflection and Prayer.</i></P>
        <Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad."> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad</Title>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have received notice from Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">Go dtabharfaidh an tAire Coimirce S&oacute;isiala&iacute; soil&eacute;iri&uacute; maidir leis na crit&eacute;ir lena nglacfar le hachomharc ar di&uacute;lt&uacute; don Forl&iacute;onadh C&iacute;ose faoi na tairs&iacute; nua at&aacute; tugtha isteach, m&aacute; t&aacute; an suim &oacute;s cionn an teorainn a cheada&iacute;tear, n&oacute; m&aacute; t&aacute; l&eacute;as fadt&eacute;armach ag na tion&oacute;int&iacute; at&aacute; ag d&eacute;anamh an achomharc.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Mark Daly that he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Social Protection to make a statement and detail any evaluation carried out by the Government prior to introducing the new redundancy arrangements.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re proposal for a directive on the freezing and confiscating of proceeds of crime in the European Union &mdash; referral to the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality and Defence, to be taken without debate; No. 23, motion re access to the committee papers of the Joint Committee on Finance and the Public Service, to be referred to the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, to be taken without debate; No. 2, Local Government (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2012 &mdash; Second Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1 and to conclude not later than 5.45 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and the contributions of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be called on to reply to the debate not later than 5.35 p.m.; and No. 3, Private Members&rsquo; business, to be taken at 5.45 p.m. and to conclude not later than 7.45 p.m.  The Minister for Finance will be in the House to take that business.  I confirm for the House also that the Minister for Finance has indicated that he will be in the House to take a general debate on the economy and mortgage arrears which has been scheduled for Tuesday, 3 July, following the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader has just dealt with one of my questions which he will be glad to hear will shorten my contribution.  I have raised this matter on a few occasions.  I welcome that we have a date now for the Minister to come into the House for a debate on mortgages, even if it is a month from now.  The ongoing mortgage crisis is an important issue on which there was agreement across the House on the part of the many Members who contributed to that debate.</P>
        <P>Is there any news as to when the community employment scheme review is due?  A number of reports are pending but they were not published in the past week and I wonder if that was one of them.  When that report is published I ask the Leader to afford time for it to be debated.</P>
        <P>Regarding the pyrite committee report, in her role as Deputy Leader, Senator Bacik said that the Government had hoped to get that report published by the end of May.  We are only a week past that but we had a target date originally of the end of March.  As I said previously, approximately 72,000 houses are potentially affected, mainly on the east coast.  I visited many people in my constituency whose houses are in a desperate state of disrepair and who have had the legs cut from under them, so to speak, by HomeBond, which now says it has no liability in this regard.  Does the Leader have a date for the publication of that report?  When we have had an opportunity to examine that report it is important that we have a debate on how we will assist hundreds of thousands of people across this country who have no safety net in this regard and who are living in houses that are unsafe and will continue to pay mortgages on houses that are effectively valueless.  That is a major challenge for all of us across the House in terms of the way the State deals with that issue.</P>
        <P>I record my support for the call by the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, last Sunday that Sinn F&eacute;in would pay for the cost of the High Court challenge to the Referendum Commission&rsquo;s comments, the public relations stunt it engaged in two days before polling that will cost the taxpayer in the region of &euro;200,000.  I ask the Leader to ask our colleagues in Sinn F&eacute;in whether Sinn F&eacute;in can confirm that it will leave that bill with the taxpayers or&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator and his lot left plenty, and so did those on that side of the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>We know that Sinn F&eacute;in is well versed at fund-raising not just in this jurisdiction but in Britain and in the United States of America&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>I would like the Leader to afford some time next week to discuss the referendum, the role of the Referendum Commission and the High Court challenge brought by Sinn F&eacute;in over comments made by the Referendum Commission.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Would the Cathaoirleach advise my learned friend that we have no role whatever in discussing these kinds of judicial decisions?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>I thought we had one in this House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader might consider affording some time next week to discuss the referendum.  My party is very pleased that the &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote was carried.  We were pleased to play a positive role in ensuring that an important step was taken by the Irish people in passing the fiscal treaty.  It is one part of the jigsaw but there are many challenges Government will face, and we will support it in seeking a write-down on debt and in examining the banking debt.  That is something that should be discussed.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to afford us some time next week to discuss the referendum now that it is over, to see what were the positive aspects of the campaign and what could be done better should future referendums come down the track.  Perhaps my colleagues in Sinn F&eacute;in will use this opportunity to confirm that they will pay for the cost of the High Court challenge to the Referendum Commission two days before polling.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to congratulate everyone involved in carrying the Olympic torch through the streets of Dublin today.  I had the privilege of watching it going down Clanbrassil Street through the south east inner city.  It was a moving ceremony in both senses of the word because it moved very fast through the city.  It was also moving to see children and adults turning out in large numbers to watch it go by.</P>
        <P>I also wish to send best wishes to the 120,000 sitting the junior and leaving certificate examinations today.  We all wish them well.</P>
        <P>I join with Senator O&rsquo;Brien in welcoming the result of the referendum last Thursday.  All of us who were canvassing on the ground were quite worried and concerned about the possible result, but in the end it was more decisive than some of us had anticipated.  We certainly heard a good deal of frustration on the ground but also an acceptance that this was the better option and that, in particular, access to the ESM was essential to help this country in its recovery.</P>
        <P>I support Senator O&rsquo;Brien in calling for a debate on the aftermath of the referendum and looking ahead to where we go from here.  We might debate two issues, perhaps without a Minister.  The first is the need to pursue the growth agenda and support President Hollande&rsquo;s efforts to try to ensure there is a growth package at EU level alongside the fiscal stability treaty.  Second, we should see some way forward in the settlement of the bank debt, which is the big issue.  I know negotiations are ongoing but we could usefully debate that in the aftermath of the referendum.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader for a debate on the role of the Seanad in the constitutional convention.  I welcome today&rsquo;s announcement that the convention has been established and that it will be proceeding along the lines the Labour Party has proposed &mdash; that we will see a two-thirds and one-third split between members of the public and elected representatives.  It needs a tight timeframe for it to be effective.  It would be welcome to see more contentious issues taken on alongside the first two issues in the first stage of the convention.  We might well debate the Seanad&rsquo;s role in examining constitutional change and the work the constitutional convention will do.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JillianVanTurnhout"><NameTxt>Senator Jillian van Turnhout</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree with Senator Bacik&rsquo;s proposal for a debate on the future of the Seanad in light of the announcement concerning the constitutional convention.</P>
        <P>I also send my best wishes to those sitting the junior and leaving certificate examinations.  I would not swap places with them but I wish them the very best, having dropped my nephew to his first exam today.</P>
        <P>I warmly welcome the announcement by the EU for funding for the missing children hotline on Missing Children&rsquo;s Day.  This House played a strong role on that matter by having an all-party, all-group motion seeking the hotline to be up and running.  This funding has now been announced by the EU but the ISPCC, which has been awarded the hotline and the funding, will need additional funding from the Government.  I therefore repeat my call of 22 May, asking the Leader to invite the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, to the House to discuss her Department&rsquo;s plans to provide the necessary funding and support for Ireland&rsquo;s missing children&rsquo;s hotline, so we can have it operational in the coming months.</P>
        <P>We should also discuss with the Minister, Deputy Fitzgerald, how her Department and the Government can support the exceptional work done by the ISPCC through its Childline service.  I also ask the Leader to seek from the Minister a date for the publication of the report into child deaths.  She should give a commitment to attend the House shortly after it is published so that we can discuss it with her.</P>
        <P>I commend the joint policing operation between the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the PSNI into organised prostitution, brothel keeping and money laundering.  On Tuesday last, 29 May, searches were carried out at over 120 houses, apartments and flats on both sides of the Border under Operation Quest, which led to a number of arrests.  I particularly welcome the fact that three suspected victims of human trafficking were rescued during the course of these searches.  I welcome the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na&rsquo;s recognition of the link between prostitution, organised crime and money laundering, as well as the additional link between prostitution and human trafficking, which this case demonstrates.  I commend the garda&iacute; for their approach.</P>
        <P>The Minister for Justice and Equality has advised us that he will shortly publish his public consultation document.  I am disappointed, however, that the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland has banned a radio advertisement campaign by &ldquo;Turn off the Red Light&rdquo;, which seeks to highlight abuses in the Irish sex trade.  That is very disappointing.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>A question for the Leader, Senator.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JillianVanTurnhout"><NameTxt>Senator Jillian van Turnhout</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader ask the Minister for Justice and Equality to give us a date for publishing the consultation document?</P>
        <P>On 24 May, we raised the Government&rsquo;s arm&rsquo;s length policy on our cultural institutions which are being eroded.  I am a keen family historian and on 1 June a notice appeared on the National Archives&rsquo; website stating that its genealogy service has been temporarily suspended and that it is hoped to reinstate the service as soon as possible.  When we are promoting a year of Gathering next year, is it greatly remiss of the authorities to suspend such a service.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I have frequently spoken in this House against the horrible trade of human trafficking for whatever purpose.  I would have to say, however, that if in 100 busts North and South of the Border, which involved multiple arrests, the fact that only three people appear to have been trafficked suggests that the link is not quite as strong as has just been suggested.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I usually agree with the Leader of the Opposition, Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien, who is a very courteous and honourable man.  I do take issue, however, with the idea that we should discuss court judgments in this House in this manner.  The point raised by Sinn F&eacute;in was in fact an intricate one and this was recognised in the judgment of Mr. Justice Hogan.  I believe it is appropriate that any person &mdash; I speak as somebody who has benefited from this situation myself &mdash; should have the costs paid when they raise a very important constitutional point.  Fianna F&aacute;il obviously feels rather touchy on the subject because it is threatened by Sinn F&eacute;in.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>Most certainly not.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I can understand their difficulties.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>No shinners in north Dublin.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>When we have this debate, which I believe we should have, I hope they will realise the seriousness of the situation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.  I am supporting the call for such a debate because we are facing a really serious situation.  I do not think we realise exactly how serious it is.  Where are all the promises we heard before the referendum now?  What response did the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, get from the spokesman for Wolfgang Sch&auml;uble, who is the paymaster?  He was given the brush-off, which he did not expect.  We have been the best boys in the class, yet all we do is get slapped for it all the time and it will not get better.  Therefore I will wait to see if all the promises produced by the &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; side are right.  I hope so.  I have never had any problems being wrong if it is for the benefit of other people, but I very much doubt it.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I am also seeking a debate on homophobia.  We did not have much to say about this on the recent international day against homophobia.  The campaign against homophobic bullying was largely subverted &mdash; even though the Government won &mdash; by being diluted into a general debate on bullying which we have all the time.  However, the statistics from the National Office for Suicide Prevention are stark.  Some 59% of young gay people experience homophobic bullying in school; 25% are physically threatened; 34% hear homophobia from teachers; 27% have self-harmed; 50% have seriously thought of ending their own lives; and 20% have attempted suicide.  It is time we did something about it, particularly in light of the kind of international situation we have where people are being murdered because of their sexual orientation.</P>
        <P>Recently, in North Carolina &mdash; of which, curiously enough, I am the honorary attorney general &mdash; one pastor called for lesbians to be corralled into a 100-km diameter concentration camp.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I am seeking a debate on homophobia and am giving the reasons.  The pastor said no food should be dropped in to them because they would then die out.  Another pastor said that if a boy was showing what he called &ldquo;a limp wrist&rdquo;, he should be given a good punch.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We are not discussing it today.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>We have also had the cowardly and disgusting attitude at the Anglican synod recently.  I am urging that we should take this issue seriously.  On most occasions when I raise these issues in the House, nobody speaks against them but I do not get a lot of support.  I would welcome it if we showed a bit of solidarity in this area instead of always taking the soft, easy options which everybody is comfortable with.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdreClune"><NameTxt>Senator Deirdre Clune</NameTxt>
	<P>This morning, Pfizer announced that it was to shed 177 jobs in two plants in Cork.  Pfizer employs 4,000 people in this country.  This decision will affect the lives of those who will lose their jobs and the lives of their families and it will cause devastation and shock.  I extend my sympathies and that of all Senators to those people.  That announcement shines a light on the pharmaceutical industry and the way it is changing worldwide.  The reason for these job losses is that Pfizer&rsquo;s blockbuster drug Lipitor has come off patent.  Other drugs will also come off patent.  We see mergers and acquisitions take place on an international basis.  It is important that this House examines the pharmaceutical industry and employment it provides here.  I ask the leader to invite the Minister to come to the House to explain the discussions he is having with the pharmaceutical companies and what the IDA has planned in this area.  While much of this is out of our control we must have a strategic plan for this area which is an important employer across the pharmaceutical life sciences.  I ask the Leader to arrange a discussion on the future of the pharmaceutical industry, which is an important industry that is changing internationally, and the implications that has for this country.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to arrange for the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly, to come to the House to discuss health matters and to have a question and answer session on it which is always useful.</P>
        <P>The new emergency aeromedical service commenced operation on 4 June.  It is a pilot scheme based at Custume Barracks, Athlone.  It is a national ambulance service and this is the first time it has been introduced.  The service responded to a young lady who had a farm accident in Castleplunkett, Castlerea, on Monday and she was brought to University College Hospital, Galway, within approximately 30 minutes of the helicopter being summoned.  It has been extremely useful and initially it has proved to be very successful but it is no substitute for the active accident and emergency department we had in Roscommon County Hospital.  It is all very well having accident and emergency departments in Portiuncula, Castlebar, Mullingar, Tullamore and Galway but the excellent accident and emergency department we had in Roscommon was a far better service where an ambulance brought a patient to the hospital rather than having to rely even on an air ambulance service which can be called in emergencies.  The provision of an air ambulance service and accident and emergency department plus the ambulance service is an excellent combination and I commend Minister, Deputy Reilly, on bringing it forward with the Minister, Deputy Shatter, in Custume Barracks, Athlone, even though its launch was very secretive.  Nevertheless, that is fine as it is operating now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>They will evaluate the position but it is an exaggeration to say that the service was provided for Roscommon County Hospital because this is a national service.  It could be provided in Cork or elsewhere in the State, and it is based in Custume Barracks in Athlone.  If Fine Gael thinks it is off the hook as far as Roscommon is concerned it can forget about it.  Sone 60% of the people were generous in voting &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; in the referendum on the treaty.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>They will never forgive and they will never forget&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>A Senator</NameTxt>
	<P>They are forgetting.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;the activities of the current Government.  They have been misled so much&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is over time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome what happened during the week in regard to this service but I still believe that the restoration of the accident and emergency department there is vital.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMoran"><NameTxt>Senator Mary Moran</NameTxt>
	<P>I send my good wishes to the 116,774 students who began the State examinations this morning.  From my teaching experience I understand how stressful examination time can be for students but we need to send them out the message to keep calm and remind them that they always know more than they think they know.</P>
        <P Just="Left">As a mother of two children who are sitting State examinations this year - one is sitting the junior certificate and the other the leaving certificate - this is my third year in a row when I have had a child sitting State examinations.  I am well aware of the pressure students can place on themselves but students should see this as an opportunity to demonstrate their talents and to look on the positive side.  It is a showcase for the culmination of all their hard work.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I welcome the junior certificate cycle review which will come into place in 2014 whereby State examinations will not just depend on a student&rsquo;s performance on a particular day.</P>
        <P>There are changes to two of the leaving certificate subjects &mdash; Irish and mathematics &mdash; this year.  For the first time higher level mathematics will carry 25 bonus CAO points, which is to be very much welcomed, to encourage students to take higher level mathematics.  In addition, in the oral part of the Irish paper there will be a picture section.  I call for a debate on the taking of Irish as a subject at leaving certificate and the alarming drop in the number of students who take Irish at second level.</P>
        <P>I welcome the arrival of the Olympic torch to Ireland today.  It was symbolically passed over at the Border north of Dundalk this morning and it was a fitting gesture that it was handed over by a Protestant sporting hero to a Catholic sporting hero on the Border.  I reiterate President Higgins&rsquo;s words this morning that the flame&rsquo;s arrival in Ireland symbolised the growing closeness between Ireland and the United Kingdom, no doubt heightened by the visit of the Queen last year.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMoran"><NameTxt>Senator Mary Moran</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Bacik said it was a fantastic moment to witness.  I was fortunate this morning to be able to go to Merrion Street where I saw the torch being carried.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I can confirm that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Was it a Protestant or a Catholic&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMoran"><NameTxt>Senator Mary Moran</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and not only to see it but to touch it and to hold it with Katie Taylor&rsquo;s mother who was carrying it on behalf of all the mothers of Ireland.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should have run herself.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P>Here&rsquo;s to Katie Taylor.  I am in solidarity with Senator Norris calling for a debate on homophobic bullying.  The Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality heard evidence from many groups against homophobic and transphobic bullying on 17 May but I am in solidarity with the Senator.</P>
        <P>I welcome the publication of the heads of the Bill on the establishment of the human rights and equality commission that the Minister, Deputy Shatter, published earlier this week and his commitment to put in place a new body that will be strengthened in its ability to respect the human rights and equal status of everyone in our society.  He has moved swiftly in response to the working group&rsquo;s report which reflects the public consultation process that fed into it.  I am sure all Members would agree that now more than ever before within the context of our vulnerable Irish society and economy we need to get it right in terms of the way equality and human rights can be delivered side by side.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I have some questions I would like the Leader to ask of the Minister, Deputy Shatter.  Of primary concern in the establishment of this body are that it be effective and have the resources to be effective, and the way it will be regarded at international level.  As many Members are aware, the Irish Human Rights Commission was regarded by the UN as an independent national human rights institution.  The new body will not have that special status.  It will not yet comply with the Paris Principles&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;but it needs to prove in its first year that it is able to be independent and comply.  As Members will recall, the budgets of the Irish Human Rights Commission and the Equality Authority were cut significantly in 2008, totalling about &euro;3.4 million.  The working group&rsquo;s report noted that the current bodies do not have enough resources to meet their existing obligations.  On &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; earlier this week the Minister for Justice and Equality indicated that with the merger there would be immediate savings of &euro;500,000, which is welcome because it could go towards the work, but will the Leader ask the Minister from where those savings will come and how we will recover the &euro;4 million that has been lost by the two bodies to allow the body be effective in its first year?  It must be effective in its first year to be declared independent in terms of the Paris Principles.  Given that we are still seeking a seat on the Human Rights Council the Minister should be able to answer these questions sooner rather than later.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CatherineNoone"><NameTxt>Senator Catherine Noone</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I was alarmed to read this morning figures on the sale of the morning-after pill.  Some pharmacies have increased their sales of the morning after pill from 30 to 90 per week, which is astonishing.  This is something that should be a last resort but this indicates that perhaps it is being used as a contraceptive.  Young women in many instances are putting themselves at risk of sexually transmitted diseases.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">3 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P Just="Left">It also has many side-effects for reproductive health and causes other problems down the line for young women.  Will the Leader ask the Minister for Health to liaise with the pharmaceutical bodies to obtain more precise figures on this?  Perhaps raising the price should be considered.  The price was reduced from &euro;50 to &euro;15 last year.  We should also have an awareness campaign about the potential dangers of partaking in this type of contraception.  The bigger problem is the social one that throughout the country intercourse has become much more casual, and we probably need to debate this and the Minister for Health should bring his attention to it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>Last week the European Court of Justice ruled on MasterCard&rsquo;s multilateral interchange fee.  This is quite an important decision but has not received much attention.  It applies only to cross-border transactions but its effect startled me.  It will mean a reduction in costs to European consumers &mdash; solely for cross-border transactions &mdash; of &euro;25 billion per year.  The court ruled the multilateral interchange fee is unfair to consumers and retailers and consumers receive no benefit for the charge.  The court ruled it should also be reduced and removed internally in each of the European countries.  Will the Leader draw the attention of the Minister for Finance and the Competition Authority to undertake this?  It has huge implications.  The multilateral interchange fee is also charged by Visa but the case heard last week was against MasterCard.  The UK and other countries have stated the ruling should also apply domestically in each member state.  I urge that we do this.</P>
        <P>The constitutional convention will be convened and we should have time to debate it in the House rather than wait for it to be debated outside the House.  It is exactly the type of topic we should discuss.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>I also call for a debate on the referendum and its fallout and on who was telling the truth and telling lies during the campaign.  This would become very clear if we had a frank debate in any forum.</P>
        <P>I agree with Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien with regard to the &euro;200,000 Sinn F&eacute;in is seeking from the taxpayer to pay for its grandstanding on the eve of the referendum.  To put it in football parlance seeing as the European championships are beginning on Sunday, when Sinn F&eacute;in saw it was losing the match it decided to attack the referee.  It was sad.  The &euro;200,000 in legal fees which Sinn F&eacute;in will attempt to have paid by the taxpayer could employ eight teachers in Donegal for a year who otherwise might be let go.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>I accept that any individual is entitled to claim fees if a legitimate constitutional question is raised.  However, Sinn F&eacute;in is not an ordinary person on the street.  It is the only party in the jurisdiction which has deposits in sterling and dollars.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>I call for a debate on the referendum.  Sinn F&eacute;in benefits from a fall in the euro but this is not the case for the Labour Party, Fine Gael or Fianna F&aacute;il.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>These are points the Senator can make during the debate.  We are not having the debate now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>Tell the people at a child care meeting in Donegal next week that the &euro;200,000 in fees will be taken from their budget.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We are not having the debate now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish the Irish soccer team the best of luck&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P>What about all the money you spend on special advisers?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not spend any.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P>The Government has and far more than &euro;200,000.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does Senator Harte have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>My question is whether we will have a debate on the referendum.</P>
        <P>I was not allowed finish my sentence about the Irish soccer team.  I wish them, Giovanni Trapattoni and the Irish fans the best of luck.  I was amused by Sinn F&eacute;in&rsquo;s sudden interest in the Irish soccer team.  It was just like its sudden interest in the Donegal GAA team last year when it reached the all-Ireland semi-final.  If Donegal does not get past the first round Sinn F&eacute;in does not appear at the game.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The all-Ireland is a 32-county competition.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>If I were a bookmaker I would offer very short odds on Senator Harte speaking about Sinn F&eacute;in because every contribution he has made since I have been a member has been an attack on Sinn F&eacute;in.  He is trying to take over from Senator D&rsquo;Arcy as the Government spokesperson on Sinn F&eacute;in.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryBrennan"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Brennan</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not fair as he is absent.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>If that is how he wants to waste his time in this House it is a matter for him.</P>
        <P>I agree it is important to have a debate in the aftermath of the referendum.  I commend all of those who voted and all parties, Independent Deputies and Senators, trade unions and civic leaders for the role they played in both sides of the campaign.  The campaign, which took place in recent weeks and months, was very constructive.  The Government and those advocating a &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote now have a responsibility to deliver on the rhetoric of the campaign and deliver the stability, certainty, investments, jobs and all that was promised.  It will be interesting to see in the months and years ahead what exactly will happen in Europe and here.</P>
        <P>A number of people have raised the issue of the court case and I should be given an opportunity to respond.  I will quote Mr. Justice Kevin Feeney who stated the case raised complex, important and powerful issues concerning European international and Irish constitutional law which might be considered by the European Court of Justice and the Irish Supreme Court.  Any citizen of the State who feels constitutional issues need to be examined, and as the judge stated&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>Mr. Justice Gerard&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;complex and important issues, they should be raised&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes, but Mr. Justice Hogan wondered why Sinn F&eacute;in waited until two days before the referendum.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>The Cathaoirleach allowed plenty of latitude for him to be questioned, now let him reply.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>When Fianna F&aacute;il Senators speak about recovering costs for court cases perhaps their party should stump up the costs of the Moriarty and Mahon tribunals&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;which cost hundreds of millions of euro because of the corruption in their party.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>This is not relevant to today&rsquo;s Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>It would be far better for the country if they paid for these tribunals rather than attacking an individual for taking what was a good court case to examine the constitutional issues at play.  The country would be better served if this happened.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMullins"><NameTxt>Senator Michael Mullins</NameTxt>
	<P>I join Senator Leyden in welcoming the recent launch of the air ambulance service based in Athlone.  It is a commitment by the Government to provide a top-class health care service.  I know the new service has been welcomed by everybody along the western seaboard.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I also welcome the decision of the Irish people in the recent referendum.  People voted for certainty, stability, recovery and the availability of future funding.  I am pleased people rejected the negative campaign waged by the &ldquo;No&rdquo; side based on many untruths and irrelevancies.  However, there is one outstanding matter with regard to the referendum and I ask people to address it.  A large amount of very unsightly posters remain throughout the country, particularly in the city of Dublin.  I am very disappointed that these posters were not removed in time for the Olympic torch coming through the city.  Many visitors will come to Dublin for the Eucharistic Congress at the weekend and I appeal to all organisations to ensure the posters are removed.  They are unsightly, and many cable ties, which look particularly awful, also remain.</P>
        <P>Now that the referendum is over I hope we will begin to discuss positive initiatives on how we will get out of our economic difficulties and create more employment.  Following a commitment made some time ago by the Minister for Jobs, Innovation and Enterprise, Deputy Richard Bruton, I call on the Leader to schedule during this session an update on the jobs initiative which will give us all an opportunity to further feed into the programme.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Senator Marc MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>I would also welcome an opportunity to debate the jobs initiative and, from my perspective, its failure.  An ESRI conference yesterday learned how 80% of the jobs created in recent times have been located in Dublin, Galway and Cork even though job losses in those locations would only have been 60% of those elsewhere.  It is important to focus on the original visions of the national spatial strategy and why it has clearly failed.  Why has Government policy to date not adequately tackled those areas that have suffered the highest redundancies and unemployment <i>per capita</i>, when one considers Donegal and the counties in the north west?  As Senator Leyden has said, it is consistent with the plan to phase out services throughout the area north of a line from Dublin to Galway.</P>
        <P Just="Left">It is very insulting to celebrate the provision of an air ambulance when people are entitled to a health service comparable to that of the rest of the country.  If the people of Roscommon now find themselves in need of an emergency department and cannot get to Galway quickly enough, provided the weather is favourable and the air ambulance works, they might survive, but if not they are second-class citizens compared with the people based on the east coast or close to a so-called centre of excellence.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I would welcome the opportunity to debate some of these issues, in particular the employment issue other Senators have raised.  It is unacceptable that the lion&rsquo;s share of activity as measured by grants and other resources provided through IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland is in certain areas.  The Government's focus should be at least a basic acknowledgement that those people who happen to live outside the pale or outside the catchment area of our larger cities are just as entitled to a policy that at least aspires to provide the same level of employment and resources to them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>I echo what Senator Mullins said about posters.  I have an aversion to election posters being left up&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>If the Senator does not get elected.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;for any longer than is absolutely necessary.  I hope Senator Leyden has taken down the posters in County Roscommon.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>They are wonderful when one gets elected.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>I believe the Fine Gael posters in Roscommon looked very good and the result was correct.  I am delighted with the result of the referendum, which was appropriate.  People voted for stability, confidence and rebuilding Ireland.  They realised that our future lies in playing a central part in the European movement.  However, we will have a fundamentally more important referendum later this year &mdash; not the referendum on the abolition of the Seanad, but the referendum on children&rsquo;s rights.  Senator van Turnhout mentioned that the missing children&rsquo;s hotline has been funded from Brussels, which I welcome.  I believe Europe has put up approximately &euro;150,000.  It is waiting for a contribution from the Government to move to the next phase.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should not forget what happened at the previous budget.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>As it is moving to the next phase, it is very important that the 116000 number be launched as a matter of urgency.  I call on the Leader to ask the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Fitzgerald, to ensure this happens.</P>
        <P>While speaking of children&rsquo;s hotlines, I repeat what I said here previously.  It is appalling that Childline is funded completely from voluntary contributions.  It costs &euro;6 million to run Childline.  If it were not for the good nature of the people who fundraise for Childline, we would not have this facility.  Each day hundreds of calls remain unanswered because Childline does not have the resources, which is an indictment of the country.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P>Of the Government.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>That is a clear example of why we need a referendum to ensure that children&rsquo;s and young people&rsquo;s rights are enshrined in the Constitution.  Successive governments have failed the children of this country.  I commend the Minister, Deputy Fitzgerald, in her quest to ensure that the constitutional amendment will receive broad support and that the referendum will happen in 2012 to enshrine the rights of children in the Constitution once and for all.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator voted for a budget to put more children into poverty.  That is a clear contradiction.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnCrown"><NameTxt>Senator John Crown</NameTxt>
	<P>As we are now more than a year into the term of the Government, I ask the Leader to consider scheduling in the near future a formal broadly based debate on the fundamentals of health policy reform.  This should not be another of the very worthy but piecemeal debates we have had on individual pieces of legislation, which could be broadly construed as part of an overall agenda for reform, but I believe they are not.  The fundamentals of reform of our health system were contained in the programme for Government synthesised by the two parties.  It was based on two quite informed individual party strategies, which together formed a nice synthetic programme which if implemented would address the core problems in our health service, which are poor quality, inefficiency and inequity.</P>
        <P>My good friend and colleague, Dr. Gerry Burke, a consultant in Limerick, has been quoted in the press commenting on what he regards as rampant managerialism which is impeding the development of the health service.  I fear somewhat that some of the first tentative steps, which we are being told are part of the reform process, are in fact steps in the direction of further managerialism and not dealing with the fundamental problems.  I will give one quick example which I would like the Leader to convey to the Minister for Health regarding the National Rehabilitation Hospital in D&uacute;n Laoghaire.  Any Senators who have had the privilege of visiting it will know it is an extraordinary institution which works in very difficult circumstances with some of the most challenging problems of often young people facing incurable spinal injuries as a result of trauma, cancer or sports injuries.  They go through very rigorous rehabilitation with variable outcomes and get the very best care they can in an institution that is grotesquely under-provided for in two key areas.</P>
        <P>The number of consultants is approximately 60% to 70% what it would be by UK standards and less than 10% of what it would be in France.  The number of beds is approximately one fifth of what is recommended by the professional body.  As a result, for some of its specialist neuro-services there is a six-month waiting list to get started with rehabilitation.  This means that someone whose spine has been fractured or head badly injured may be either sitting at home or in a hospital bed losing rehabilitation time because he or she cannot move on.  This causes the downstream effect of failure to admit people for other procedures that have varying degrees of urgency.  This is merely one example of a system that is deeply dysfunctional and we need to have this debate in the near future.</P>
        <P>I wish to comment on Senator Noone&rsquo;s &mdash; if I understand her correctly &mdash; somewhat extraordinary suggestion that the right way to deal with the widespread use of the morning-after pill is to increase its price.  It would be somewhat like trying to reduce abortion by increasing the waiting list to ten months.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CaitKeane"><NameTxt>Senator C&aacute;it Keane</NameTxt>
	<P>D&rsquo;fhoilsigh an Comhchoiste um Chomhshaol, Iompar, Cult&uacute;r agus Gaeltacht tuarasc&aacute;il an-t&aacute;bhachtach mar gheall ar an teanga Gaeilge agus r&oacute;l Foras na Gaeilge inniu.  Ba cheart go mbeadh d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht sa Teach seo ar an tuarasc&aacute;il sin.  As this morning we published a very important report on the role of Foras na Gaeilge and the future funding mechanism for the Irish language organisations, it would be opportune for this House to discuss that report&rsquo;s recommendations with the Minister of State so that we can further enunciate the report&rsquo;s recommendations to ensure it goes to the North-South ministerial council, from which the initial recommendations came through Foras na Gaeilge.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister of State, Deputy McGinley, to come to the House to discuss that report.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P>Taca&iacute;m leis an moladh at&aacute; d&eacute;anta ag an Seanad&oacute;ir Keane.  Tr&eacute;asla&iacute;m leis an gcomhchoiste as foilsi&uacute; na tuarasc&aacute;la c&eacute;anna.  Ach an oiread leis an Seanad&oacute;ir Moran, ba mhaith liom gach dea-ghu&iacute; a sheoladh chuig na mic l&eacute;inn ar fad at&aacute; ag d&eacute;anamh scr&uacute;daithe faoi l&aacute;thair.  Ba cheart go mbeadh d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireacht againn maidir le c&uacute;rsa&iacute; oideachais tr&iacute; mhe&aacute;n na Gaeilge.</P>
        <P>I have asked for a number of debates on the fishing industry, the Celtic Sea quota division that will be done and our marine resources policy.  The Leader indicated previously that the Minister would be willing to attend and I would be very grateful on any update on that.</P>
        <P>I agree with Senator MacSharry that the national spatial strategy has been an abject failure under the previous Government.  As I have previously suggested, perhaps the Seanad could be used in an innovative way to have a series of debates on the regions.  We should consider the needs of each of the regions individually, which have specific needs.</P>
        <P>My main question for the Leader will be of particular interest to the Cathaoirleach.  It relates to the earthquake off the coast of Mayo, which is of concern.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I am not responsible.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh is safe.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P>We are safe thankfully.  It is a very serious issue.  Could the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources be invited to the House to give a statement on it?  It was apparently a 4.0 magnitude earthquake and it has serious implications for the oil and gas industry off the coast of Mayo, in particular.  There have been a number of calls this morning for clarification, particularly from Councillor Rose Conway-Walsh, regarding the infrastructure of the oil and gas pipelines off the coast and whether any damage has been done.  In addition, when the development of the Corrib gas field and other fields off the west coast of Ireland was taking place, did the environmental impact statements take into consideration that there might be seismic activity of this type?  Was that factored in and was seismic testing carried out?  It is potentially a serious issue.  If any damage was done to that infrastructure, it could have catastrophic repercussions.</P>
        <P>Bheadh f&aacute;ilte roimh an tAire, an Teachta Rabbitte, teacht isteach agus c&uacute;lra an sc&eacute;il a thabhairt agus a mh&iacute;ni&uacute; d&uacute;inn c&eacute;ard go d&iacute;reach a tharla agus an bhfuil an t&iacute;r seo ag coinne&aacute;il s&uacute;ile ar na gn&oacute;tha&iacute; seo agus an bhfuil muid ag t&oacute;g&aacute;il na c&uacute;ins&iacute; is s&aacute;bhailte agus is sl&aacute;inti&uacute;la san &aacute;ireamh gur c&oacute;ir a dh&eacute;anamh.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien raised the review of the community employment, CE, scheme and the pyrite report.  I will find out when the CE review report will be available and will revert to the Senator.  I have been constantly asking about the pyrite report.  I am told it is imminent but we were told that a few weeks ago.  I assure the Senator that I will pursue the matter and report back to him, but I understand that it might be available in the next week or so.</P>
        <P>On the High Court challenge by Sinn F&eacute;in, I do not propose to intervene in an argument between Fianna F&aacute;il and Sinn F&eacute;in.  However, it is great to see that Sinn F&eacute;in now recognises the courts.  It is not long ago that it failed to recognise them so it is great the party is taking cases to court.  Senator O&rsquo;Brien also sought a debate on the referendum, as did other Members.  I am agreeable to that proposal and will schedule it for Thursday afternoon next week.  There will possibly be no Minister present but I will schedule it for that afternoon.</P>
        <P>Senators Bacik, Moran, van Turnhout and others wished our students well at the start of their examinations.  We all agree with those wishes.  They also welcomed the Olympic torch to Dublin.  It was great that it came to this country.  It again highlights the links between Great Britain and ourselves that the torch came to Ireland, and it was great to see so many people on the streets of Dublin and elsewhere to welcome it.</P>
        <P>I will try to arrange a debate on the establishment of a constitutional convention.</P>
        <P>Senator van Turnhout raised the issue of the missing children hotline.  The Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, has welcomed the allocation of &euro;150,000 by the EU Daphne programme to the ISPCC for setting up the initial operation of the 116000 missing children hotline in Ireland.  Last year, the Minister established a project team to oversee the establishment of the hotline, something she announced in the course of a debate in the Seanad, which was very welcome.  I understand that the ISPCC has advised that it will make an application to the Government for funding for the balance of the set-up costs.  The Minister, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, will consider any funding application in conjunction with the Department&rsquo;s agencies involved in the project team and she hopes that any additional funding requirements can be met.  That is to be welcomed.  It is a matter that has been highlighted by Senators van Turnhout, Conway and others on numerous occasions.</P>
        <P>Senator van Turnhout also welcomed the activities of the Garda and the PSNI on Operation Quest.  We all welcome that activity.  The Senator also asked about the report on child deaths and when it would be published.  I will revert to the Senator on that matter.</P>
        <P>Senator Norris called for a debate on homophobia and suicide.  The joint committee on justice discussed this and I understand that the Deputy Leader, in my absence a week or so ago, referred to this in the House.  I assure the Senator that we can and will arrange such a debate at an early date.</P>
        <P>Senator Clune raised the Pfizer job losses and the future of the pharmaceutical industry.  We all regret that 177 jobs have been lost in Pfizer and our thoughts are with the workers and their families.  All the supports of the State will be made available to the workers.  As the Senator correctly pointed out, products coming off patent is a reality of the pharmaceutical industry and one that all companies throughout the world must face.  However, I will try to arrange a debate with the Minister on that matter.</P>
        <P>Senator Leyden sought a debate on health.  I am working with the office of the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly, to arrange a debate and question and answer session&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Excellent.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;similar to the one we held in October.  I hope we will have a date for that soon.  We all welcome the emergency ambulance scheme and, as Senator Leyden mentioned, we can already see the effectiveness of the introduction of the air ambulance.</P>
        <P>Senator Moran spoke on the significance of the handing over of the Olympic torch in Dundalk.  We all realise its significance.</P>
        <P>Senator Zappone referred to the merger of the Equality Authority and the Human Rights Commission.  She put forward a number of questions for the Minister.  Perhaps Senator Zappone would raise that matter on the Adjournment.  As there were so many questions involved, she would get proper and necessary answers in an Adjournment debate.  The questions she asks are very relevant.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Noone and Senator Crown referred to the morning-after pill.  Last week, for the first time, we held a sexual health awareness week, which was very welcome.  When we arrange the debate with the Minister for Health I am sure the Senators can raise the points they raised today on that matter.</P>
        <P>Senator Quinn asked that the Competition Authority investigate the charge in respect of MasterCard.  I agree with the Senator and I will raise the matter with the Minister.  Like other Senators, he also called for a debate on the constitutional convention.  I will arrange such a debate soon.</P>
        <P>In response to Senator Harte&rsquo;s request for a debate on the referendum, as I said earlier I will schedule a debate for next Thursday afternoon.  Of course, we all wish our soccer team and all our supporters travelling to Poland and Ukraine well and a safe journey, and we wish the team every success.</P>
        <P>I agree with Senator Cullinane in commending all the people who voted in the referendum.  That will be debated next week.  Senator Mullins and others referred to the posters that are still on display.  There is a law relating to such posters and I hope the local authorities will enforce it.  The Senator also sought an update on the jobs initiative.  In the next number of weeks the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, will be in the House to deal with three, if not four, Bills.  I am sure there will be an opportunity during the debates on those Bills to raise the question of the jobs initiative.  If not, I certainly will try to arrange to have the Minister come in to deal with that matter specifically.  However, it would be unfair to deal specifically with the matter, given the Minister will be in the House at least four or five times in the next number of weeks to deal with several Bills under his remit.</P>
        <P>Senator MacSharry raised the national spatial strategy and how it appears that jobs are going to Galway, Dublin and Cork and that little is going further north than a line from Dublin to Galway.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Senator Marc MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>Absolutely.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I assure the Senator that those of us who are from the south east are also greatly concerned by the lack of jobs and this is a matter on which I should and will arrange a debate with the Minister.</P>
        <P>Senator Conway raised the children&rsquo;s referendum, which will proceed in September or October.  It is another day&rsquo;s work and I commend the Senator on raising the question of the Childline helpline.</P>
        <P>Senator Crown called for a debate on health policy reform after a year in Government.  I will try to arrange a debate with the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly and as I stated, I am trying to arrange with the Minister&rsquo;s office to have a question and answer session.  However the Senator seeks to have a specific debate on health policy reform and I can perceive the reason for this.  I will raise this proposal with the Minister.</P>
        <P>Senator Keane raised the role of Foras na Gaeilge.  As a Bille na Gaeltachta is scheduled to come into the House in the coming weeks, perhaps the debate on that Bill could include a debate on the role of Foras na Gaeilge.</P>
        <P>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh referred to the fishing industry.  While I had thought the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Coveney, attended the House to discuss the fishing industry only a matter of weeks ago, I will ask him for an update in that regard.  The Senator also called for a debate on the regions and I will ascertain whether this can be arranged.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P>Including the south east.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I note the Senator&rsquo;s points on the earthquake in Mayo and his question in respect of the infrastructure of the oil and gas fields.  I am sure Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh will consider raising this issue as an Adjournment matter to ensure he has the proper information from the relevant Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="European Union" RHead="Treaty: Motion."> 
    <Title>European Union Treaty: Motion</Title>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:</P>
        <P LI="2">Proposal for a Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on the freezing and confiscation of proceeds of crime in the European Union, a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 3rd April, 2012.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P FLI="0">Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Referral to Joint" RHead="Committee: Motion"> 
    <Title>Referral to Joint Committee: Motion</Title>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That, in relation to the Joint Committee on Finance and the Public Service draft Ninth Report: <i>Report on the Principle of Acceptance by Public Bodies of Recommendations of the Ombudsman</i>, the papers connected therewith of the Joint Committee on Finance and the Public Service established by orders of D&aacute;il and Seanad &Eacute;ireann of 16 October 2002 and 17 October 2002, respectively, be referred to the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform established by orders of D&aacute;il and Seanad &Eacute;ireann.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Government (Miscellaneous" RHead="Provisions) Bill 2012: Second Stage"> 
    <Title>Local Government (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2012: Second Stage</Title>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMullins"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Michael Mullins</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Jan O&rsquo;Sullivan, to the House and invite her to address Members.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Jan O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>I am pleased to bring the Local Government (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2012 before the Seanad today.  The Bill is required to facilitate the Department&rsquo;s agency rationalisation programme, to underpin legislatively any new body established under the Local Government Services (Corporate Bodies) Act 1971 and to provide that one person may be the manager of Limerick city and county councils and north and south Tipperary county councils.</P>
        <P>The Local Government Services (Corporate Bodies) Act 1971 provides that the Minister may, by order, establish corporate bodies to provide services to local authorities or to the Minister.  It remains the case that the Minister should have the capability to establish bodies, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, to provide services to local authorities or the Minister where it is more practical, efficient and economical to so do.  Thirteen bodies have been established under the 1971 Act and of those, seven still exist in law, namely, the Limerick Northside Regeneration Agency, the Limerick Southside Regeneration Agency, the Local Government Management Services Board, the Local Government Computer Services Board, the Affordable Homes Partnership, Irish Water Safety and the Fire Services Council.  Generally, the bodies were established to provide specified services for local authorities with the benefit of having a single expert provider, rather than each local authority acquiring or providing the service.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Members may recall that in 2008, the Local Government Services (Corporate Bodies) (Confirmation of Orders) Act was enacted.  That legislation was required to address the possible unconstitutionality of section 3 of the 1971 Act.  This followed advice of the Attorney General in respect of the Health (Corporate Bodies) Act 1961, which contains similar provisions to the 1971 Act.  Article 15.2 of Bunreacht na h&Eacute;ireann explicitly confers on the Oireachtas the &ldquo;sole and exclusive power of making laws for the State&rdquo;.  In various constitutional challenges over the years concerning whether secondary legislation infringed Article 15.2 of the Constitution, the need for the Government to have a mechanism to establish corporate bodies has been recognised in judgments of the High Court and Supreme Court.  In his judgment on the Pigs Marketing Board <i>v</i>. Donnelly case, Mr. Justice Hanna acknowledged that &ldquo;the functions of every Government are now so numerous and complex that of necessity a wider sphere has been recognised for subordinate agencies, such as boards and commissions&rdquo;.  The then Chief Justice, in his judgment in the Cityview Press <i>v</i>. AnCO case, outlined that the test of the constitutionality of the legal instrument establishing corporate bodies is that it gives &ldquo;effect to principles and policies which are contained in the statute itself&rdquo;.  Basically, when a corporate body is being established, it must be underpinned with principles and policies contained in the primary legislation.</P>
        <P>This 2012 Bill is required, <i>inter alia</i>, to address any legal uncertainty surrounding bodies established under the 1971 Act.  The intention behind the amendments contained in this Bill in respect of section 3 of the 1971 Act is to set out the principles and policies, in primary legislation to which the Minister shall have regard in his consideration of the requirement to establish any bodies by way of statutory instrument.  It is very important to note the Bill is not being pursued for the Minister to increase the number of State bodies under the Department&rsquo;s aegis.  On the contrary, the Bill is required to give full effect to the Department&rsquo;s State agency rationalisation programme.  This is in keeping with the Government&rsquo;s public sector reform plan announced on 17 November 2011.  The plan announced an expanded programme of State agency rationalisation within the Department, which will rationalise 21 such bodies to 11.  In this regard, the Bill will allow the Minister to abolish existing bodies and, where appropriate, to establish new bodies to carry out the functions.  As for the bodies established under the 1971 Act that still exist, they will be dissolved and merged or subsumed into other public bodies as part of the rationalisation programme.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I will outline the proposals in respect of each of the bodies.  The Local Government Management Services Board, LGMSB, and the Local Government Computer Services Board, LGCSB, already are merged in an operational sense and now operate on a joint administrative basis pending the establishment of the merged body, namely, the local government management agency, on a statutory basis.  The Local Government Computer Services Board and the Local Government Management Services Board provide services to local authorities including shared ICT services and collection of public-facing charges on a shared basis for local authorities, as well as industrial relations and human resources shared services.  The local government management agency will take on the LGMSB and LGCSB functions and will also take on residual functions from An Chomhairle Leabharlanna.  I will discuss An Chomhairle Leabharlanna later in greater detail.  Section 12 of this Bill contains a provision that will allow the local government management agency, when established, to continue to carry out LGCSB and LGMSB functions in respect of the administration of the household charge.</P>
        <P>The Affordable Homes Partnership will be dissolved and its functions, as well as those of the Centre for Housing Research and the National Building Agency, have been merged into the interim Housing and Sustainable Communities Agency, IHSCA.  This agency is currently operating on an administrative basis and will be given statutory footing through this Bill.  Senators will recall that the Affordable Homes Partnership was established in 2005, a very different time in terms of the housing market in Ireland, to co-ordinate and promote the delivery of affordable housing in the greater Dublin area.  The Housing and Sustainable Communities Agency works with the Department, local authorities and approved housing bodies in the delivery of housing and housing services.  The agency brings together, under one body, a broad range of support and advisory services in respect of housing and other construction-related matters.  Although this Bill allows for the establishment of the agency, further and more complex legislation will be required to define its roles and functions.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Fire Services Council was established in June 1983 and provided a central training programme for local authority fire service officers which provided courses and seminars that complemented training organised locally by individual fire authorities.  The Fire Services Council&rsquo;s term of office expired on 30 June, 2009 and no new appointments were made to the council after that date.  The Minister announced that the work of the council would be absorbed into the National Directorate for Fire and Emergency Management.  The national directorate was established on 22 June, 2009 and operates under the aegis of the local government division of the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government.  The establishment of the national directorate was in keeping with the desire to reduce the number of agencies while providing appropriate political accountability.</P>
        <P>The Limerick regeneration agencies were established in June 2007, with a term of operation for five years to 14 June 2012.  The agencies were established to secure the social and economic regeneration of four areas of Limerick city.  This Bill will provide for the dissolution of the two regeneration agencies.  Their functions will be taken over by the new office for regeneration which has been established in Limerick city.  The regeneration office was set up initially with administrative support from Limerick City Council but will report directly to the manager designate of the new Limerick unitary authority once appointed.  This post was recently advertised.  The Bill, at sections 8 and 9, provides for a modest extension of the existence of the Limerick regeneration agencies from 14 June 2012 to the 31 July 2012.  The orders under which the Limerick regeneration agencies were established contain so-called &ldquo;sunset clauses&rdquo; which will see them cease to exist from 15 July 2012.  The short extension provided for in this Bill is to ensure an orderly transfer of their functions, assets and liabilities to Limerick City Council.</P>
        <P>Irish Water Safety is relatively small, with six staff members, but it facilitates a huge amount of volunteerism in the area of water safety in Ireland.  Its role is to educate people in water safety best practices.  The agency also represents Ireland on the international stage.  Under the provisions of the Bill, IWS can be dissolved and it is proposed that it be re-established under the amended 1971 Act.</P>
        <P Just="Left">An Chomhairle Leabharlanna, the Library Council, was established  by the Public Libraries Act 1947.  An Chomhairle Leabharlanna has served the country well in terms of the promotion of libraries and library services, the co-ordination of training and dissemination of best practice and interaction with national bodies such as F&Aacute;S, SOLAS, and EU and international organisations.  However, it is necessary to amalgamate State agencies to ensure the most efficient delivery of all services.  In this regard, the local government management agency will not only amalgamate the Local Government Management Services Board and the Local Government Computer Services Board but will also amalgamate the residual functions of An Chomhairle Leabharlanna.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Part 4 of the Bill contains three sections which will amend chapter 2 of Part 14 of the Local Government Act 2001, dealing with the position of city-county manager.  I introduced these provisions on Committee Stage during the Bill&rsquo;s passage through the D&aacute;il.  They are relevant to the Government&rsquo;s local government reform programme and in particular to the reorganisation of structures in counties Limerick and Tipperary.  As Senators are aware, the Government approved proposals to establish single local authorities to replace Limerick County Council and Limerick City Council and north and south Tipperary county councils by mid-2014.  In both cases, the establishment of interim management arrangements, whereby a single person would oversee both authorities in the run-up to full merger, was also approved.  Existing local government law does not allow for such a position and this Bill amends the Local Government Act 2001 to provide that in the case of Limerick County Council and Limerick City Council the same person shall be the manager of the authorities and the same provision will be made in regard to north and south Tipperary county councils.  These provisions form an important early element of an evolving programme of local government reform related in this instance to reorganisation in Limerick and Tipperary.  More substantive legislation will be enacted at a later date to provide for the establishment of a new unitary authority in these areas and the transfer of the functions and relevant finance, assets, liabilities and staff from the existing councils to the successor authorities.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I now turn to the main sections of the Bill.  Section 1 contains the usual provisions of a general nature dealing with such matters as Short Title, collective citation and commencement.  Sections 2 and 3 are standard technical provisions.  Although no direct expenditure in implementing the Act is anticipated, it is prudent to include a standard provision.  Section 4, or the amendment of section 2 of the Act of 1971, deletes the reference to &ldquo;health board&rdquo; as an authority to which this Act applies.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Section 5 inserts an important amendment to section 3 of the 1971 Act to deal with the link between the policies and principles of primary legislation with bodies established by statutory instrument under the 1971 Act.  When the Minister is considering the establishment of bodies the amendment will require that he have regard to such key issues as: the promotion of efficiency, effectiveness and economy; the resources available to the Minister or local authorities; and the desirability of reducing the number of bodies providing the services.  Furthermore, the Bill would also amend section 3 by the addition of subsection 9 to clearly establish the types of services that are envisaged to be provided.  Services included at subsection 9, paragraphs <i>(a)</i> to<i> (k)</i>, include shared services, ICT, training and research and procurement.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Section 6, which amends section 5 of Act of 1971, provides that in the case of a revocation order the Minister may transfer or distribute the property, rights and liabilities of a body subject to a revocation order to a Department of State, with the relevant Minister&rsquo;s consent.  The 1971 Act already allowed for transfer to this Department, the agencies under this Department&rsquo;s remit or local authorities.  Section 7 provides that the Minister may transfer the assets and liabilities of any of the bodies listed in section 10, namely, bodies to be dissolved.  The Minister may make provision for the transfer of a body and its functions, property, rights and liabilities to the Minister, to another body, to a local authority or to another Department.  If the Minister is transferring a body to another Department it has to be done with the consent of the receiving Minister.  The Minister may also make provision in the transfer order to preserve existing contracts, the continuance of legal proceedings, the transfer of staff, arrangements for pensions, the preparation of final accounts or reports.</P>
        <P>Sections 8 and 9 provide for amendments to the respective establishment orders of the Limerick northside and southside regeneration agencies.  These amendments provide for a short extension to the existence of the Limerick regeneration agencies, from 14 June 2012 to 31 July 2012.  This extension is necessary to ensure an orderly transfer of their functions, assets and liabilities to Limerick city.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Section 10, on the dissolution of bodies, provides that the list of bodies in section 8 be dissolved.  The bodies to be dissolved are as follows: the Local Government Computer Services Board; the Fire Services Council; the Local Government Management Services Board; the Affordable Homes Partnership; Irish Water Safety; Limerick Northside Regeneration Agency and Limerick Southside Regeneration Agency.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Section 11, which deals with the revocation of certain orders is self explanatory.  Section 12 contains a provision that will allow the local government management agency, when established, to continue to carry out LGCSB and LGMSB functions in respect of the administration of the household charge.  Section 13 provides that An Chomhairle Leabharlanna, the Library Council, dissolved.  Section 14, a transfer order, provides specifically for the transfer of the assets and liabilities of An Chomhairle Leabharlanna.  The transfer will require the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  In addition, any transfer orders made will be laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas and can be annulled by resolution within 21 days.  Section 15, repeal and revocationis self-explanatory.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Section 16 amends section 144 of the Local Government Act 2001 so that a single person may be appointed as dual manager in the cases of Limerick county and city councils and north and south Tipperary county councils.  Sections 17 and 18 deal with a number of related aspects of the position of manager to ensure that the new dual manager position is incorporated into pre-existing arrangements.  Section 17 amends section 145(3) of the 2001 Act to provide that the provision relating to the automatic appointment of a manager, where a recommendation by the Public Appointments Service has not been approved by resolution of a council, would apply to a county or city council in a group of authorities, as in the case of Limerick and Tipperary.  A new subsection (3A) is also inserted in section 145 which, in relation to the first appointment after the commencement of these provisions, allows the Minister to appoint, by order, a person who already holds the office of manager in a city or county that is part of the group of authorities to the office of manager of a group of authorities.</P>
        <P>Section 18 makes a number of amendments to integrate the interim dual manager arrangements with the provisions dealing with the appointment of a deputy manager contained in section 148 of the 2001 Act.  Section 18(<i>a</i>) provides that in the case of a group of authorities, the manager must consult with the cathaoirligh of both authorities concerned before he or she appoints an employee to be deputy manager.  The amendment at section 18(<i>b</i>) seeks to cover circumstances in which the manager has become unable to act and no deputy has been appointed, or there is no current appointment, or the deputy manager is unable to act.  Given the possibility for delay and disagreement in respect of an appointment in such circumstances, it is proposed to give the Minister the power to direct which one of the two cathaoirligh will make the appointment.</P>
        <P>I look forward to discussing these provisions.  I expect that we will consider constructive and helpful Government and Opposition amendments on Committee Stage.  I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMullins"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Michael Mullins</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State for her comprehensive outline of the Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State.  Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it go dt&iacute; an Seanad.  I suppose I should be reluctant to speak about activities in the Minister of State&rsquo;s back yard.  The primary provision of this Bill is the abolition of the regeneration quango.  I understand that is the term now being used.  I am sure the Minister of State will have a robust response to the criticisms of the decision that has been taken.  The bad news that comes out of Limerick is not merited.  All of us are appalled that two thuggish families have besmirched the name of a very old and respected city.  I commend the various forces of the State that have been doing everything they can to ensure the people of Limerick can sleep soundly in their beds.  I refer particularly to the Garda, the local authorities and local representatives in general.  I include the Minister of State in that.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I am not sure whether the abolition of the Limerick Northside Regeneration Agency and the Limerick Southside Regeneration Agency will address the challenges that are being faced by the people of Limerick and by the statutory agencies in that city.  The outgoing chief executive of the agencies, Mr. Brendan Kenny, highlighted the depth of the challenge that remains in tackling the problems in Limerick when he said that despite over &euro;100 million having been spent on the project, some families are worse off compared to when the regeneration process began.  His comments have received widespread media attention in recent weeks.  I am sure the Minister of State will reiterate that Mr. Kenny has had many achievements since the board first came into being, including the demolition of 900 houses and the rehousing of 300 families in other parts of Limerick city.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Minister of State has announced that some 100 new homes will be built this year.  It is clear that major work remains to be done to achieve the objectives set out in the Fitzgerald report, which led to the establishment of the Limerick regeneration areas.  As I recall it, we all welcomed this initiative as an integrated, cohesive and co-ordinated approach to the many social problems that have developed in Limerick over recent decades.  I am sure the Minister of State will take this opportunity to set out exactly what the Government plans to do when all the powers of the outgoing authorities are given to the revamped Limerick City Council.  I suggest there continues to be a need for a coherent approach to advancing the regeneration of the blighted areas of the city.  That might be put on the back burner when the agencies that were established to tackle social problems in these areas are abolished as a cost-cutting measure.  I would be interested to hear the Minister of State speak about the priorities she would like the new Limerick City Council to adopt when it takes on board what the original agencies were tasked with doing.  Given that all local authorities have widespread problems, is she satisfied and confident that this new authority will address the priorities that were outlined in the Fitzgerald report and implemented to date by the Limerick Northside Regeneration Agency and the Limerick Southside Regeneration Agency?</P>
        <P>I will bemoan the loss of An Chomhairle Leabharlanna, which was established in 1947.  It survived successive Administrations because it did valuable work.  Having represented the Library Association of Ireland in this House for many years, I am aware that An Chomhairle Leabharlanna is the Cinderella of our semi-State agencies.  When the annual estimates were considered at local authority level in previous years, the book fund was often the first thing to be cut.  Over recent years, a more mature approach to the importance of our public libraries has been taken at local authority level.  Great credit is due to all of those who work in such libraries.  They have managed to get away from the stereotype of the old Carnegie approach, which was solely about lending books.  They have adapted to the new technological age by providing essential services, such as free Internet access, particularly to the unemployed and those seeking employment who need to access technology.  A wide range of services is being provided in our library system.  I ask the Minister of State to reiterate the Government&rsquo;s commitment to ensuring our libraries will continue to comprise a central and essential building block in the recovery of this country.  Some of us might have taken them for granted over the years.  As a result of the sad increase in unemployment, an increasing number of people are having to reskill and upskill.  The libraries in our towns and villages have proven to be an enormously important resource.  I hope the abolition of An Chomhairle Leabharlanna will not diminish that role in any way.</P>
        <P Just="Left">It is interesting that this legislation will change a system of local government that has been in place since 1899, when the first Local Government Act established Tipperary North Riding and Tipperary South Riding.  Those Anglified names are not particularly used now.  They give an indication of the background to this Bill.  I often wondered why Tipperary was split in two.  In England, Yorkshire was similarly split into north and south ridings.  The same thing happened in some other parts of the English local government scene.  We need to consider what will happen next.  I know the Minister of State is not responsible for answering that question at this time.  It is a matter for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Hogan, who has already indicated in this House that he plans to establish a local authority review commission as soon as the revised D&aacute;il constituencies have been agreed.  Perhaps the Minister of State can tell the Seanad the date that has been set for the publication of the recommendations of the Constituency Commission on the redrawing of D&aacute;il constituencies.  The timing of that announcement will have an impact on the date of establishment of the new commission, which will consider the redrawing of local authority boundaries.  The Minister has already committed himself to publishing the results of the commission&rsquo;s findings by January of next year, which would be 18 months in advance of the next local government elections.</P>
        <P>This Bill proposes to reconfigure Limerick City Council and to merge North Tipperary County Council and South Tipperary County Council.  I am curious to know why it was decided to do this in a piecemeal fashion.  What is the purpose of including this proposal in this legislation at this time?  Why is it so urgent?  The Minister, Deputy Hogan, has promised that the Government will develop a much wider reform initiative.  Many councillors around the country are not sure of their futures, but it has nothing to do with the electorate.  They are more focused on the Minister&rsquo;s plans.  I would like clarification on the proposed or rumoured reduction in the number of councillors in each local authority, the proposed or rumoured abolition of town councils and the rumoured abolition of borough councils such as those in Kilkenny and Sligo.  There are no sub-authorities in my own county.  It is a single local authority area.  It has been suggested that it will suffer as well as a consequence of its low population.  I know the Minister of State will not be in a position to answer all of these questions.  I am sure it is like the budget in the sense that even if she could provide these details, she would not do so.  I am raising it because I suggest it is germane to the proposal to reconfigure two local authorities.</P>
        <P>I welcome the overall thrust of this legislation, which is to reduce the number of quangos.  I have been informed that &ldquo;quango&rdquo; is an acronym for &ldquo;quasi-autonomous non-governmental organisation&rdquo;.  As many of these agencies are State-registered and State-funded, it might not be exactly correct to refer to them as quangos.</P>
        <P>However, the suggestion that by doing so it will have a major impact on the economy raises that question.  I would remind the Minister of State that the programme for Government stated: &ldquo;The Government will make substantial cuts to the number of State bodies and companies.&rdquo;  I suppose we must concede that at least a start has been made in this regard.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">4 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>I note that Irish Water Safety is to be abolished under the proposed scheme.  In her speech, the Minister of State said it would be re-established but perhaps she will clarify exactly what she means.  If it is being re-established, why is it being abolished in the first instance?  I commend the officers of Irish Water Safety for their outstanding work at local swimming pools around the country, including in my own town of Drumshanbo.  Since the pool opened in the mid-1970s, at least a generation has learned about water safety under the expert guidance of representatives of Irish Water Safety.  I hope the body&rsquo;s future will be strengthened rather than diminished in any way.  Once again I wish to thank the Minister of State.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CaitKeane"><NameTxt>Senator C&aacute;it Keane</NameTxt>
	<P>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire go dt&iacute; an Teach.  I welcome the Bill before the House, which addresses the reform of local government.  Senators will be aware that reform of the public sector has been on the political and administrative agendas for some time.  When I was elected back in 1991 the terminology &ldquo;reform of local government&rdquo; was around then, but we have seen very little reform in the interim.  We must obviously start somewhere, so I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
        <P>In 2008, a Government efficiency review required Departments to examine overall administrative spending, including that of State bodies and agencies under their remit.  The final report of the local government efficiency review group contained 106 recommendations, some of which are being implemented under the provisions of the Bill before us.</P>
        <P>A number of other reports have also been published outlining the best way to reform the public service, including the OECD review of the public service and the Green Paper on local government reform.  The previous speaker referred to local government reform so I will not say too much about it.  However, I hope that when the forthcoming reforms are announced the Minister will attend this House to consult with Senators, as our electorate comprises local government councillors.  That may change with the review of the Seanad, however, if it is not abolished.</P>
        <P>The programme for Government draws on many of the recommendations made in many of the reports to which I have referred.  The programme also contains a commitment to transfer back to local government many of the functions currently being performed by these agencies.  I ask the Minister of State to ensure that, where possible, functions of agencies should be transferred to the responsible local government body.</P>
        <P>Section 4 refers to the abolition of the reference to health boards but a lot of good work is being done in the health area through local councils&rsquo; community departments, particularly for youth mental health.  For example, the Headstrong agency works with local councils and, given current suicide rates, local government could be utilised in this area.  Headstrong has six or seven groups around the country, so it should be possible to utilise this facility as part of the current reforms.  Many people who are on the brink of committing suicide require somebody to talk to, so a lot could be done by local government community departments in conjunction with voluntary agencies.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I realise that the health function of local government has been gone for some time, but it is time to consider bringing back something similar to the community, rather than abolishing agencies.  Local government is closest to people who are in trouble, and such services are easier to access than those that are centralised.</P>
        <P>Last November, the Government&rsquo;s statement on public service reform set out a rationale for reducing the total number of State bodies.  The Minister of State has already referred to the number being reduced.  The objective of the measures will deliver enhanced services and efficiencies, together with ensuring a more focused and democratically accountable public service.  The measures are therefore to be welcomed.  The Bill will facilitate the agency rationalisation programme currently being undertaken by the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, thus reducing the number of agencies.</P>
        <P Just="Left">While discussing the reduction or abolition of such agencies, it is nonetheless important to pay tribute to their good work.  They can, however, continue the same work with fewer bodies following amalgamation.  The Minister of State referred to the Limerick regeneration agencies whose term of office expired this year, and the fact that everything is up for review to see how it can be done better.</P>
        <P>The Local Government Computer Services Board did fantastic work at a time when local authorities were not as<i> au fait</i> with computerisation as they are now.  In the computer age, it is now possible to do so much more with fewer people and less office space.  One can now put into a computer information that long ago required a storeroom to hold.  The objective of the Bill is to deliver enhanced services through this streamlining process.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Section 5(2) provides for the provision of services, training and equipment relating to ICT.  I am curious to know if this will apply to councillors as well as administrative staff who run the councils.  I have spent long enough on councils to know that training is an important element for councillors as well as for staff.  I look forward to the Minister of State&rsquo;s positive response on that point.  It is a prerequisite in every area for people to be IT proficient, so such training should be facilitated.  Most people are IT literate, but there may be some who are not.</P>
        <P>Section 5 further provides for the streamlining of administrative services, which is also to be welcomed, along with cost-effectiveness and centralisation where necessary.  The section also provides for the promotion of public safety awareness and the organisation of training measures on public safety.  This is an important provision and there is a lot of ambiguity among councils on how safety guidelines are being implemented or interpreted.</P>
        <P>It has been brought to my attention that safety regulations can vary between councils.  In some instances, it may take a man and his mother to put out cones on a road or to cut a bit of grass.  Another council, however, may not need to close a road for 24 hours to cut grass.  Guidelines on the interpretation of safety regulations in this area would be useful.</P>
        <P>The same section refers to the provision of research and advisory information services.  Consultancy is also mentioned, but that should be greatly reduced as many people can undertake their own consultation through Google and Wikipedia.  There are many such research aids, so the use of consultants should be cut back.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In the last D&aacute;il debate on local government legislation, the Minister of State spoke about the Limerick regeneration agencies, which are being amalgamated into a new organisation under the auspices of Limerick City Council.  I hope that will carry out the relevant work for the entire Limerick area, thus ensuring that the job is done.</P>
        <P>I welcome the disbandment of An Chomhairle Leabharlanna, the Library Council, although in its day it did good work.  I worked in the UCG library but local and county librarians have now taken over the role of An Chomhairle Leabharlanna.  One librarian &mdash; who is not from Dublin in case anybody may think I am identifying a librarian from the capital &mdash; told me that the Library Council turned out to be a total and utter talking shop in the end.  I do not know if that is true but it was said to me.  Nonetheless, An Chomhairle Leabharlanna did valuable work, but that body has now been subsumed by the county librarians&rsquo; body and all the staff have been transferred.</P>
        <P>The overall pooling of resources is good, but how much are we saving?   The Minister of State mentioned quite a small amount of savings that will be achieved in this initial tranche.  Another Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, recently reformed the framework for managed print services for all the organisations and it is expected it will result in savings of &euro;22 million.  We are not talking about peanuts in terms of the savings that will be achieved from amalgamating bodies; we are talking about achieving efficiencies and increasing effectiveness and work productivity.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The Minister of State is welcome.  It was a joy to listen to her speak and also a joy to listen to Senator Keane who has a great deal of experience in this area.  I have met her in Rathfarnham where she is actively involved in a committee.</P>
        <P>I have had an interesting morning.  I attended the business improvement district conference that took place in the Westbury Hotel.  A great deal of work is under way outside local government to attempt to improve the district.  The real threat is to the high streets, the main streets, and how we manage to keep them alive and retain shops and retailers there when many planning decisions are being made throughout the country that are damaging the infrastructure of towns.</P>
        <P>I welcome the Minister of State&rsquo;s reforms.  They will hopefully make local government that little bit more efficient and finalise arrangements for the rationalisation of State agencies under the control of the Department.  However, I am concerned there are no cost savings figures available or, if there are, I do not see them.  There is much more we can do in terms of local government.  We need to empower our local government structures in order that Deputies have the ability to think of the country in terms of our national interests instead of the current structures that we have.  The Seanad is notable for Senators thinking that way on the much broader national level.  The debates in this House are different as a result of the way we are elected to this House.  However, on a much more basic level, local government needs to be run much more efficiently.  We must find more efficient ways of doing it.  We simply have too many structures for such a small country.  Do we need 29 county councils, 75 town councils, five city councils and five borough district councils for a population of 4.5 million in the Republic?  Does Dublin need four local authorities?  Marc Coleman made the point on  Newstalk that the inefficiency of local government in the South compared to the North is massive.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>He is a main source.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">He is very good.  Dublin City Corporation alone has 6,000 employees, half of whom are administrative, that is, they do not work in the fire services or the libraries and nor are they street cleaners.  Red tape under this bureaucracy can also be bad for business.  With local government reform I would like to see, like many others, the planning process streamlined.  The process of making an application for planning permission where a business may have to deal with any number of the 88 local planning authorities is inefficient, as is the system of appeals.  We simply do not need this layer of bureaucracy for such a small population in such a small area.  In addition, the original report by the local government efficiency review group recommended that social housing rents due to local authorities should be deducted from social welfare payments in order to reduce the overheads required to collect rent and to reduce arrears.  The report also proposed that the online motor tax system &mdash; a topic I have raised previously &mdash; should be expanded to allow owners of commercial vehicles to pay online and a handling fee of, say, &euro;10 could be introduced to encourage online motor tax applications among other easy to implement measures.  Why are these not being pursued as these inefficiencies could be removed with the stroke of a pen?  Will the Minister of State explain what she is doing in this area?</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Revenue Commissioners collect income tax, the universal service charge, capital gains tax and corporation tax.  Local authorities meanwhile collect commercial rates, business improvement tax, district taxes, levies and the non-principal residential tax.  An Post, of which I have some experience, collects the television licence fee and the dog licence fee.  The latter used to be seven shillings and sixpence; I do not know what it is now but I am surprised it is still in place.  The Private Residential Tenancies Board collects the residential landlord tax, not to mention new taxes such as the water charge or the septic tank charge.  The various tax collection systems seem to be highly inefficient.</P>
        <P>For example, in France rates are collected with the electricity bills.  In addition, people who do not have television sets must opt out of rather than opt into the licensing system, and I know we are changing the system here.  The French system seems to be much more efficient.  We should have a look at how they handle it there.  I have a daughter living in France and she impresses me with their systems that seem to work so well.</P>
        <P Just="Left">This matter needs much more discussion.  As I also mentioned, we need to tackle the hundreds of millions in revenue lost to this country through fuel smuggling.  We could stop that by forcing commercial users to get refunds, perhaps applying online.  There is great potential there.  A reform of local government would hopefully get people to engage more with politics.  We should also examine the citizens&rsquo; initiative mechanism that is in place in Switzerland.  It is a very interesting one.  It allows voters to change the Constitution directly or to veto legislation.  Thus, there is much greater involvement and engagement with voters.  In analysing local government and the overall lack of engagement with politics, such a structure would at least foster much more interest in the political system and that would be very useful and healthy.  Last year, almost 1,000 Belgian citizens were brought together to discuss the future of their country.  Why can we not do something similar here as a starting point?  The constitutional convention might be a way to do that.</P>
        <P Just="Left">We can make structures more efficient quite easily.  There are many concentre examples for the reform of local government that merit discussion.  For instance, in England, Suffolk County Council is in the process of cutting its workforce from 27,000 to just a few hundred staff.  It is attempting not to cut services, but rather it plans to get the private sector and social enterprises to take over the vast majority of those services.  The council said that it &ldquo;had a [sterling] &pound;100 million overspend by the end of the ten year contract period with BT [British Telecom]&rdquo;.  Similar inefficiencies are reported here every day and we must try to take similar steps here.  It was reported earlier this year that Sligo Borough Council was continuing to pay a bullying expert almost &euro;1,000 a meeting to monitor the behaviour of councillors.  It is paying that expert &euro;1,000 a meeting despite finding no evidence of bullying in the past two years.  A human resource consultant is to be paid &euro;19,000 this year for sitting in and taking notes on the conduct of those attending the council meetings.  I note the Ceann Comhairle is indicating that I have spoken long enough.  This will bring to &euro;54,000 the amount the council will have spent on having a private human resources consultant observe and report on all its meetings.  This is absurd.  Other councils in the UK are also transforming the service delivery side of the councils, from housing to benefits, into an arm&rsquo;s length commercial style business with at least just 14 staff.  There is an awful lot we can do.  The steps the Minister of State is taking are in the right direction.  I congratulate her on that and support them but we can do an awful lot more.  The challenge is there for us to do it and that challenge is open to be taken now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DenisLandy"><NameTxt>Senator Denis Landy</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it go dt&iacute; an Teach.  I cannot let the opportunity pass without responding to my learned colleague, Senator Quinn who, on the one hand, criticised the number of local authority elected members in the country and, on the other, referred to England as a good example of the way local government operates there.  He also referred to the system in France.  For his information, for every 130 citizens in France, there is an elected representative.  Also, in Great Britain the Conservative Government last year re-introduced parish councils with statutory powers because of the failure of local people to engage in local democracy.  Figures of below 30% and, in some cases, just over 20% were recorded in local elections.  Therefore, they decided to re-engage with people.  Ireland has one of the lowest <i>per capita</i> rates for elected representatives in Europe and to say that we have too many and that this is a cause of inefficiency is a simplistic assessment of the situation.  Reference was made to bids and to the best of my knowledge this happens only in Dublin, Cork and perhaps Galway.  I wished to clarify these matters prior to making my contribution.</P>
        <P>I welcome the legislation in so far as it attempts to deal with the abolition and merger of bodies in the remit of the Minister of State.  It proposes a reduction of more than 50% of those listed.  I recognise that savings can be made and it is important we make these savings.  I support the comments of Senator Keane with regards to An Chomhairle Leabharlanna.  My knowledge of the organisation comes from almost a quarter of a century in local government.  It never fed back to local government despite the fact many of its members were elected representatives.  As outlined by Senator Keane it eventually became a talking shop.  This must not be confused with the fact that the function of libraries throughout the country will remain and they will get stronger under the Government.  In my opinion we can do without An Chomhairle Leabharlanna.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I wish to mention the regeneration companies in Limerick.  The media suggest regeneration will stop in Limerick because these bodies, which were established in 2007 for five years, will come to an end.  Nothing could be further from the truth.  I know because of the Minister of State's drive to ensure the work continues that it will do so.</P>
        <P>The main thrust of the section on local government gives power to the Minister to allow a manager to operate for two local authorities, namely, south and north Tipperary and Limerick city and council.  My colleague, Senator Heffernan, will speak about Limerick but in the case of Tipperary, which is where I am from and I know a great deal of detail about it, an implementation body was established last year which consulted very widely with staff and their representatives.  However, consultation with elected members has been in stark contrast, with only one joint meeting of the two local authorities to discuss the matter.  The whips of each political group in the county have met on a number of occasions but not at minuted meetings.  Rather they have had casual discussions and conversations.  Much more information needs to be provided to members in the areas.</P>
        <P>I concur with Senator Mooney&rsquo;s comments on the urgency to deal with the local authorities in north and south Tipperary and Limerick city and county prior to the Constituency Commission&rsquo;s report on D&aacute;il constituency boundaries and electoral areas.  Local councillors in Tipperary and Limerick have been kept in the dark and they do not know what will happen in their areas.  They do not know whether the area they represent now will remain in the same electoral area.  It is quite unfair they were picked out ahead of the changes to be made.  The cart has been put before the horse.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Minister of State knows my views and will not be surprised to hear me say local government should be strengthened.  The role of local government at town level should be enhanced and strengthened.  I have made it quite clear I do not concur with the views of Senator Quinn and others who stated we have too many councillors.  We have a great system of local democracy, albeit many powers have been stripped down.  The role of local government should be enhanced and I do not subscribe to the view that if we had fewer councillors we would have more efficiency.  The cost of elected members in any local authority per annum is approximately 0.01% of the cost of running the local authority.  Those who say fewer councillors would mean more efficiency are not speaking about economic efficiency.  Most have their own agendas with regard to rezoning and as far as they are concerned the fewer councillors they have to deal with the better.</P>
        <P>The implementation group established in County Tipperary was supposed to present its report to the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government on 31 May but I understand this has not yet been done.  When this is done and a decision is being made on local government, particularly with regard to boundary changes, we should be given an opportunity to debate it in the House with either the Minister of State or the Minister, Deputy Hogan.  We deserve this because it involves our electorate and we should be able to discuss it first hand with people throughout the country.  During the referendum campaign I met many councillors from all parties.  Many of them asked about local government reform and what it would mean for them.  Everybody is concerned about his or her own area.  Every Deputy and Senator is concerned about the boundary commission report.  It is a topic of discussion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>Fine Gael seems to know what is in it already.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DenisLandy"><NameTxt>Senator Denis Landy</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Deputy Byrne is very friendly with Fine Gael.  He may be able to tell me then.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>I am not accusing the Labour Party.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DenisLandy"><NameTxt>Senator Denis Landy</NameTxt>
	<P>Councillors are also interested in the changes which will affect them.  It is important that this information is brought out as soon as possible.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Local government should be enhanced by the provision of extra powers and local government at town level should be retained, albeit if it must be outstretched to rural areas.  I am in favour of the retention of local government at town level.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  While my party supports the Bill and is supportive of a rationalisation in the local government sector, the Minister of State would probably admit the Bill is limited enough in its scope.  We are speaking about the Limerick regeneration agencies being merged in tandem with the merger of the local authorities in Limerick.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Local Government Management Services Board and the Local Government Computer Services Board already operate together.  Unfortunately the Affordable Homes Partnership served its time and I am not sure whether it did a very good job.  Certainly the affordable homes schemes put in place during the boom were not effective and have left people in considerable hardship.  Irish Water Safety does fantastic work.</P>
        <P>The existence of the Fire Services Council shows in some ways the rationale for having more centralised services in local government in Ireland.  Many services could be done nationally and not on an individual county basis.  The issue with regard to the Fire Services Council dates back to 2009 when the term of office of the board expired.  Nobody has been appointed to it since and its functions have been taken over by the National Directorate for Fire and Emergency Management established by the previous Government in 2009.  Much has already happened and the Bill is merely putting this in place.  It is a pity it does not go substantially further.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I have not had any dealings with the Library Council.  I presume it has done a good job over the period of its existence and the Minister of State has said it has.  However, I will speak about a local issue.  The Laytown town library in east County Meath, which has an expanding population, was closed by Meath County Council in late 2005 or 2006.  Ever since, Meath County Council has been waiting for funding from the Department, and I believe consent from the Library Council, to open a new library in the area, which is the second largest urban conurbation in the county.  Nothing has happened in the meantime.  I do not blame the Department, which has a role to play, as have the Library Council and Meath County Council.  Between the three bodies something has got stuck and there is no proper library provision in east County Meath in the Laytown, Bettystown and Mornington areas.  It is a shame and a disgrace that has been allowed to happen as a result of the dispersal of responsibility with no one directly responsible.  When I raised it with Meath County Council I was told it had to wait for the Library Council or for funding from the Department.  If I raised it with the Department I am certain I would be told of something somebody else would have to do.  I am not trying to blame the Department in this.  I had understood that some funding had been applied but nothing has happened.  With this plethora of bodies no one is in charge and things do not happen.</P>
        <P Just="Left">We must go further down the road of merging bodies and getting the best practice.  Councils need to work together and share best practice in order to be more efficient and get better value for the taxpayer.  If every household is now expected to pay &euro;100, people will expect the best possible services from their local authorities.  People will not accept a lack of services in a particular area when they are paying the same household charge &mdash; or property tax as it will be next year &mdash; as everybody else.  People will need to get value for money and fairness, and they have not got that under the existing system where we have had too many bodies.</P>
        <P Just="Left">While the Bill is welcome it merely tidies up things that happened under the previous and current Governments.  The Minister needs to go much further in local government reform.  I understand there is a master plan for that and it is a pity that these types of tidying up arrangements were not done as part of that because they would only be an add-on to whatever the Minister is planning in this area.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdreClune"><NameTxt>Senator Deirdre Clune</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank the Minister of State for her contribution.  While the Bill is limited in many ways, it forms part of the reorganisation of local government to which we all look forward.  Members of this House who were elected by local authority members would have a keen interest in this area.  The previously established bodies, to which the Bill refers, including the Limerick regeneration agencies, have served their terms at this stage.  The Affordable Homes Partnership had its day.  The area I represented on Cork City Council had a considerable amount of affordable housing.  People now find themselves with unaffordable mortgages.  However, at the time it was a very real solution and gave young people the opportunity to live in an area of the city in which they had grown up.  It was good for the cities and provided new blood and potential for the schools and for the local services.  While it is easy to look back now, at that time it provided a solution for young people in areas where housing had become unaffordable for them.</P>
        <P>Much has been said about local government reform and much can be done.  I read the recommendations of the local government efficiency review group, one of which was reforming the payroll and the cost of local government.  It recommended a reduction in the numbers of the county and city managers by 30%; directors of services by at least 20%; senior and middle managers by 15%; and staff working in corporate services planning, roads and engineers by 15%.  This is what people want to see in terms of efficiencies and reducing payroll in local authorities.  That is where they want to see the cuts because salaries as we know have become excessive in many cases.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The payroll budget of local authorities has expanded over the years.  The number of whole-time equivalents in local authorities has reduced by 18% from 951 in 2008 to 783 today.  In my experience many of those reductions have come in frontline services and have directly affected the services to the local community.  Most obvious is the landscaping and cutting of grass.  I do not know why any manager or engineer responsible for a budget would not prioritise such an item because in many cases it is the first impression one gets when one arrives, particularly into the city of Cork.  The verges coming into the city and at the airport have been affected by the cutbacks and there is insufficient funding to cut grass.  Do people responsible for these budgets really think about what their function is?  It should be to provide a good impression of the city for visitors.  I am picking on a small thing, but I see many instances where the decisions made to cut corners, which have necessarily been forced on local authority managers, have been in the wrong areas.  We need to see reductions in staff numbers across the directorates and across senior staff members.  That can be done very easily.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Within Cork city and county there is great scope to share services, particularly in the housing area.  There is a boundary that does not really exist as far as the public is concerned and yet it does in terms of local authority management areas.  I welcome the direction the Minister is taking in establishing a national water authority, which makes sense in bringing efficiencies to the area.  We have had the establishment of the local employment offices, LEOs, the one-stop shops.  That is an ideal area in which we could have cross-administrative area shared services.  Procurement, including the purchasing of computers, library books etc., could be done on a cross-county basis.  There is considerable scope and we need to use our imagination and be innovative in how we reduce costs across local authority areas.  The efficiency review group pointed to many areas.  We might have another discussion on another day when I am not limited to five minutes in which to speak.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SeanDBarrett"><NameTxt>Senator Sean D. Barrett</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  What we have embarked upon today is very important.  We know we need to be able to live within our means, which will occupy us all in coming years.  I assure the Minister of State that she will have support from these benches because it is vital that we be able to return to the markets and run our finances in an economical way.</P>
        <P>The problem with which we are trying to grapple is put very succinctly on page 12 of the report of an bord snip, which pointed out that from 1997 to 2009 the number of senior Civil Service managers rose by 82% as opposed to a 27% increase in the Civil Service as a whole.  That is reflected in local government in the McLoughlin report, which found that there were ten surplus county managers; 50 surplus directors of service; 112 surplus corporate services staff; 171 surplus planning staff; and 250 surplus roads staff.  It recommended the reduction of Dublin City Council and Cork City Council by 1,185 giving total reductions at the management level of 1,778.  A comprehensive survey on this issue was carried out by Jennifer Hough in the <i>Irish Examiner</i> on 9 April last.  She found that Carlow, with a population of 54,500, had five directors of services while Westmeath, with a population of 89,000, got by with just two.  These managerial layers must be discussed.  Sometimes one wonders at the ostentation of the titles of directors of services, such as community and enterprise; economic development; corporate services; finance information technology; transportation, safety and emergency services; housing; recreation, amenity and special projects.  These are small counties with grandiose titles.  One cannot have a separate economic policy for Carlow and for Westmeath.  The rationalisation by the Department, which the Minister is embarking on today, is commendable.  We must run public services within the capability of the public purse to finance them.</P>
        <P>I commend the Minister of State and wish her good luck in her endeavours.  The McLoughlin report shows that a great deal of work is required in this area and, as I know from talking to them, most people in the local authorities know that.  They tend to hanker after the time when a road engineer was the person with a shovel who cleared up drains, and there was a county engineer and a county manager.  The citizens or customers of local authorities also wonder how all these layers were introduced between them and the people with whom they deal.  I wish the Minister of State every success in tackling this problem.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesHeffernan"><NameTxt>Senator James Heffernan</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State.  It is nice to have another Limerick person in the Chamber, for a change.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DenisLandy"><NameTxt>Senator Denis Landy</NameTxt>
	<P>Someone to commiserate with on the hurling.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JamesHeffernan"><NameTxt>Senator James Heffernan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I understand Senator Landy spoke about the amalgamation of north Tipperary and south Tipperary county councils.  I wish to raise some points about the amalgamation of Limerick City Council and Limerick County Council.  There was division for a long time between city and county perspectives, with one side wanting a boundary extension and the other side favouring amalgamation.  I praise the Department for driving the process of amalgamation.  It is now in full swing in the county.</P>
        <P Just="Left">However, one of the queries I have received, and the Minister of State will have received it too, is from elected representatives, councillors, who have an eye on the next election and want to know where they will be standing for election.  There is talk of super-electoral areas, taking in great swathes of County Limerick.  Limerick is an unusual county.  County towns such as Kilmallock, Rathkeale, Newcastle West and Abbeyfeale are big towns but they are not big enough to support town councils, such as exist in other counties.  In County Cork, for example, the towns of Fermoy, Mitchelstown and Charleville, which border the Limerick area, support town councils.  As a result, Limerick has 45 elected representatives covering the entire county and city.  I appeal to the Department to keep that number of representatives in so far as possible as it is quite disproportionate to the number other counties have.  Counties like Tipperary, Wexford and Donegal, for example, have up to 60 and 70 elected representatives between town councils and county councils.  What changes does the Minister of State envisage in that regard and when can we expect those changes to be announced so the electorate can get used to their representatives if they have to move into new areas and so councillors and prospective candidates can know where they stand and what areas they must cover?</P>
        <P>There was another query arising from the amalgamation of the city and town councils.  It is the concern about cash flow and the money that can be raised.  The county&rsquo;s rates are currently much lower than those collected in the city.  I presume rates would have to be equalised with the amalgamation.  That would leave a deficit of approximately &euro;6 million per year, assuming the city rates were to decrease to the county rates.  A number of businesses have made representations to me about rates and the burdens they impose.  The shop owners in Kilmallock, the publicans in Croom and the small business owners in Bruff, for example, are put to the pin of their collars at present, so any increase in rates would hit them very hard.  I presume, therefore, that if there is to be equalisation, the city&rsquo;s rates might come down to the county levels rather than the county rates having to increase to the city&rsquo;s levels.  That would leave us with a deficit of approximately &euro;6 million.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Last year there was a cut of &euro;2 million in the local government grant to the county.  Given the unique situation with the amalgamation, special treatment will be required and I appeal to the Minister of State to provide that, perhaps through the local government grant, for at least the next few years leading up to the amalgamation.  Can the Minister of State give me any indication in that regard?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State.  The first thing we should ask ourselves when we examine or discuss reform of local government or government generally is what principles should underpin the reform.  For me, it is about adding value, achieving benefits and improving services.  All I have seen so far from this Government, including what is contained in the Bill, is reduction and subtraction, with no addition.</P>
        <P>An earlier speaker spoke about property taxes potentially being introduced next year or the year after.  However, a range of services have been removed from local authorities, such as waste services.  Water services are due to be removed and the privatisation of the maintenance of local authority housing is now on the agenda as well.  Increasingly, fewer services are being provided through local authorities, yet we are talking about reform.  The reform is all about reduction, cutting numbers, cutting councils and amalgamations and mergers.  I do not see where the improved services will arise.  I agree with Senator Barrett about the directors of services.  Waterford is a good example.  There are five directors of services in the city and there are five or six in the county, which makes no sense.  However, that is the reality and it is an area we must examine.</P>
        <P>Other Senators have mentioned Tipperary and Limerick so I will discuss the situation in Waterford and what might happen there.  There is also a proposal to merge Waterford City and County Councils.  It appears to be a good idea, on the face of it.  Amalgamating the two authorities should save money and provide better services, but I am not sure that will be the case.  Take the example of Waterford city.  It is Ireland&rsquo;s oldest city and has an individual history and heritage.  It would be mad to have a situation where some towns will continue to have councils, whatever format those councils will take, yet cities such as Waterford and Limerick might not have their own local authorities.  It makes no sense.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The national spatial strategy identified Waterford city as the gateway of the region.  It must be the economic hub and driver of the region.  However, there has already been a loss of services.  Waterford is fighting for a university and is the location of the regional hospital, but it is having a hard time getting the resources it needs to create the jobs that will sustain not just Waterford but the entire south-east region.  Removing the city council and its status will be a retrograde step and could undermine the city&rsquo;s gateway status.  However, if one has a unified council &mdash; to put this in crude terms &mdash; the balance of power will be with the county in terms of numbers and this must be considered.  Consequently, there is real concern one could see a drift away from building and expanding the city, which is what is needed, towards something different.  Moreover, the county in Waterford has its own outlook, which often is rural when compared with the urban outlook of the city.  Consequently, forcing an amalgamation with the potential diminution of the city&rsquo;s status &mdash; and certainly removing city council status from Waterford &mdash; is perceived by many people from across all parties and by many parties as a retrograde step that must be re-examined.  I make the case that Waterford must be supported culturally, socially and economically to be that economic hub and driver which will ensure it can then function as the economic engine of the south east.  However, removing its city council status will not help in this regard.  I agree the Minister should examine shared services as an area in which potential savings could be made.  It could be a compromise between amalgamations and wishing to achieve savings and improved services and would be a far better approach for the Government to take.  However, I wish to put on record Sinn F&eacute;in&rsquo;s opposition to any merger of the city and county councils for the reasons I have outlined.  The concerns of the people of Waterford, from both the county and the city, are genuine in respect of a merger.</P>
        <P>I do not wish to limit my comments to Waterford city because Limerick also is important.  Limerick city and county have their own unique outlooks and like Waterford, Limerick county has a rural outlook.  I will comment on the regeneration projects and the disbandment of their boards.  I note that when those projects were first launched, many promises were made by the previous Government in respect of doing huge work to regenerate Limerick.  However, since that major announcement was made five years ago, 1,000 homes have been demolished but only 34 homes have been built.  This constitutes a failure of the political system and one must be highly cognisant of this point when considering the abolition of such boards.  What will replace them and will the necessary funding be made available to ensure the people of Limerick get what they deserve, especially in those communities that have been so greatly disadvantaged by Government policies over the years?  One must ensure they are not forgotten about simply because money is tight and we are in straitened economic circumstances.  This should not mean such communities, which are suffering the most at present, are not looked after as I argue they should be shielded as much as possible.</P>
        <P>While I welcome the abolition of some of the boards as proposed in this Bill, I have real concerns about giving the Minister powers in this regard and there is an issue regarding consultation.  If the Government decides to opt for amalgamations, why not put such proposals to the people in those areas?  Why not hold a plebiscite in Limerick and Waterford and let people there decide?  This was done in the most recent elections in the United Kingdom concerning directly elected mayors, in which some areas went for the proposals and others against.  It would be wrong for the Minister simply to hold the power himself and to make a decision that will have far-reaching consequences for the people of Waterford, Limerick and elsewhere.  Democracy must prevail and the people who live in those communities should have their say.  The best way to do this would be through a plebiscite.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMullins"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Michael Mullins</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator.  The Minister of State might be afraid the Senator would campaign against it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister of State to the House and have listened with interest to the contributions of my colleagues and in particular to those of the previous speaker, Senator Cullinane.  As the Minister of State is aware, this is an interesting and expansive topic that certainly requires more than a limited five-minute slot in which to make a decent contribution.  While this is a matter for Members themselves rather than for the Minister of State, they should attempt to hold a thorough debate on local government and its reform in the near future.  During this week in two years time, the public will vote on local election day.  Thousands of people nationwide will offer themselves as candidates to become councillors in their parishes, counties, towns, cities or whatever and between 50% and 60% of the Irish electorate will cast a ballot on that day.  While it is important to get the structures right, with a short window of two years remaining I am worried there is as yet no clear picture as to what will be the structures and what will be the size or scale of the council areas.  Consequently, it is important that the Minister of State, Deputy Jan O&rsquo;Sullivan, and her colleague, the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Hogan, will make progress on these matters in the near future.  I note the constitutional provision for local elections every five years that necessitates the holding of such an election in 2014.  However, as a person who is disinterested from an electoral perspective but is highly interested in local government, I am a little worried that at present, sufficient time is lacking to put in place proper structures.</P>
        <P>As the Minister of State and the Minister work towards their target, it will be important to try to see the bigger picture of local government because at its best, it can be a huge driving force of economic activity and regeneration across the country.  It is not simply a question of bigger or smaller councils or of less or more local government but is a question of better local government, which is the title of a document published some years ago.  Over the past 30 years, virtually each Administration has attempted to put in place better local government and new structures and new plans.  However, as they have not worked tremendously well, some detailed thinking is required over the next few weeks.  I was advised yesterday that the Minister has now asked each local authority to liaise with each individual councillor, who will be asked his or her views on the question of local government reform over the next week or two.  While this is important, the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, the Minister of State and the Minister, Deputy Hogan, must now lead the charge.  One must be brave and radical in respect of local government reform.  One must focus on strong, better local government and avoid getting hung up on questions of whether there should be fewer or more councils.  The Bill&rsquo;s proposals are quite modest and it certainly makes sense.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">5 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P Just="Left">I note with a degree of sympathy the points made by Senator Cullinane on the level of representation for Waterford and Limerick cities, which is highly important.  However, one must move as quickly as possible to a phase in which the structures, electoral areas, powers and functions are known.  There is some scope for imagination and flexibility in this regard and unlike D&aacute;il constituencies, about which there are constitutional limits regarding maximum and minimum populations that require change of such constituencies after each census, one can have somewhat more certainty in respect of local government.  A plan must be put in place that will not simply last but will work well for the next 25 or 30 years.  This constitutes a major challenge for the Minister of State, her ministerial colleagues and the Department because what they set in stone now will not be changed in five or ten years&rsquo; time but will last for perhaps a quarter of a century and, consequently, one must get it right.  However, Members are talking in something of a vacuum at present.  Moreover, while they debate particular components of this Bill, I note that in recent months and years, significant local authority powers have been taken away in respect of roads, housing, the environment and taxation.  There is even talk of removing some of the decisions with regard to zoning and planning.  Consequently, it is no wonder that some councils are asking what is their role at all, when all those serious roles from the 1940s, 1950s and 1960s have been reduced.  One must aspire to local government being more than a form of training school for national politics or a retirement home for former Deputies and Senators.  Local government must be a dynamic place of politics in which politicians at local level interact with their local community, local business and local development and make a real difference.  If one reflects on the local government structures that obtained in the Ireland of the 1920s, 1930s, 1940s and 1950s, they appear to be much more dynamic.  For instance, there was a much more significant role for local government in education and in the delivery of health services and we have gone considerably backwards in this respect.</P>
        <P>I had better mention the Bill before concluding, as it is what Members are meant to be debating.  I welcome the Bill but look forward to early progress, as clear signals are needed before the summer recess as to what are the Government&rsquo;s intentions in respect of local government.  I have been expecting such a development since January but the summer is almost upon us.  While I acknowledge consultation is important and I welcome how the aforementioned broad consultation appears to be under way, action is now needed.  It is unfair to ask people to contest elections in two years time unless it is known fairly soon what are the structures and electoral areas and what are the powers, roles and responsibilities.</P>
        <P>There are very many good people who are not involved in politics at present who might be willing to get involved.  There are many hundreds of very effective councillors who wish to remain involved.  We need to clear up the picture as soon as possible and must aspire to have local government, not as a mini-D&aacute;il or mini-Seanad, but as a place of serious importance where major decisions are made and there is a fulcrum of local economic development and regeneration.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I have high aspirations for local government and I hope they are matched by national government.  What the Minister of State and her colleagues put in place will last for a quarter of a century.  It will be their local government legacy and I hope it will be worthy of the name "reform".  I have seen too much reform with a small &ldquo;r&rdquo; during the past 30 years that was reform in name only.  We need to see real progress on this occasion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMullins"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Michael Mullins</NameTxt>
	<P>As there are no further speakers, I call the Minister of State to respond.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Jan O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank all Senators for their participation in the debate.  As usual in this House, there is very wide knowledge and interest in local government and that entire area and it is very useful to hear all the contributions.  I will convey to the Minister, Deputy Hogan, those points that are specifically relevant to the decisions he and the Government will make in the near future.  I note in particular the request for having information provided as soon as possible while acknowledging that widespread consultation is important, particularly with those who will be directly affected in local government.  It is important to provide information and to do so as soon as possible with regard to the reform of local government.  I note, especially in Limerick and Tipperary, the concern to know what will happen with the councils in those areas and, indeed, with councils in all areas for 2014 because there will be changes for everybody.  The Minister, Deputy Hogan, is quite close to providing that level of certainty.  He will come to talk to this House about these issues which are very important.  I agree with all Senators that local government is hugely important in Irish life.  I acknowledge this is a relatively modest Bill but what we are trying to achieve with it, and also in subsequent legislation, is to ensure we save money where we can and then, in turn, we will have the money for the kind of front line services to which many Senators referred.  We do not wish to spend a lot of money on having many bodies and large numbers of back office staff; we want to have it for the front line services.  That point was made by a number of Senators.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I will give some indications in regard to what is happening in this area.  Local authority staff numbers, for example, have been reduced from the figure of 2008 by about 23%.  Specifically, the number of directors of service has been reduced by more than 20% since 2008.   There is, therefore, some progress in that regard.  On the merging of the various agencies, again there have already been savings.  One example is the Housing and Sustainable Communities Agency which will operate with half the number of staff from the three agencies being amalgamated.  The National Building Agency has already sold its building for &euro;2.8 million.  Other buildings will become available for sale or for other use as a result of the various amalgamations taking place.  There are real savings.  Senator Quinn in particular asked about quantifying some of these savings.  Some of that has been done in regard to the amalgamation of Limerick city and county.  Whether they will all be realised remains to be seen but the anticipation is that there will be savings.  I certainly support Senators who want to see that this money goes to services for the public.  That has been very clearly articulated in this House.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Some other specific issues were raised.  Regeneration was raised by a number of Senators, starting with Senators Mooney, Keane, Landy and others.  I have quite an amount of experience of the Limerick regeneration process and I absolutely assure the House it is intended not only to continue with regeneration, but to accelerate its progress under the new arrangement.  A director of service for regeneration has been appointed, provisionally at this stage.  When the new manager comes into play and that appointment is made as we expect it to be made during the summer, the director of service will report directly to the new manager of the combined council which will be finally established in 2014.  Offices will be retained in the regeneration agencies.  The representation of local voices will be maintained with the local forum, etc.  What will be speeded up is the construction of houses, compared with the current situation where, as Senator Cullinane outlined, much of the focus has been on moving people rather than on construction.  That will be accelerated.  However, we want to maintain the good elements of regeneration which were referred to, in particular social regeneration, which has been very positive as I know from my experience.  Some &euro;27.5 million has been allocated for Limerick regeneration this year and we intend to spend the money wisely.  What I want to achieve is greater benefit for the people in the regeneration areas and for Limerick as a whole, as a result of the amalgamation and the change in the structure.  It will all be under one umbrella from now where there had been parallel processes which sometimes caused delays.  That has been acknowledged and we want to ensure it works efficiently and effectively in the interests of the people concerned.</P>
        <P>A number of issues were raised with regard to Limerick, Tipperary and Waterford.  The intention is to clarify exactly what will happen with the finances in respect of the councillors and their numbers, as raised by Senator Hefferman.  Waterford is not yet at the stage that Limerick and Tipperary are and there is ongoing consultation.  Everybody has acknowledged we need reform and that, in a relatively small country, we need to ensure we do not duplicate.  Shared services were referred to and there is much scope for that, perhaps among other local authorities that are not proposed for amalgamation at this point.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Some other specific issues were raised.  In regard to An Comhairle Leabharlanna, differing views were expressed.  The intention is that the functions will be maintained and there will be no loss of service but we will not have this extra body.  Some Senators suggested this is a good thing.  Senator Mooney raised the issue of the re-establishment of Irish Water Safety.  I reiterate its work will continue.  It is a very lean organisation with only six members of staff but has a great deal of volunteerism and much good work being done.  The Bill will allow it to be re-established by statutory instrument, as per the original intention envisaged.  I assure the House the work of IWS will continue and the body will also continue but under the new legislation.</P>
        <P>There were some other issues.  Senator Keane was concerned about IT training and I will pass on her views that councillors should be included in that.  Senators Clune and Barrett raised the efficiency review group&rsquo;s recommendations.  That is what this Bill is doing, in effect, implementing the recommendations in these particular areas to ensure we save money.  Obviously, much work remains to be done in regard to those recommendations.</P>
        <P>I believe I have covered the points raised.  Most speakers made general points about savings, the importance of reform and regeneration and spoke about having an opportunity to continue with the debate.  There will be further legislation to deal with the full amalgamation of Limerick city and county councils and Tipperary north and south county councils.  With regard to the amalgamation of the two local authorities in Limerick and Tipperary, the present element is intended to facilitate this work.  For example, in Limerick the new manager will be able to do the amalgamation work in advance of the actual amalgamation.  That is the limitation as proposed in this Bill with regard to those amalgamations.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I again thank Senators for their contributions.  I look forward to Committee Stage which I understand will be held in the very near future.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMullins"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Michael Mullins</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMullins"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Michael Mullins</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CaitKeane"><NameTxt>Senator C&aacute;it Keane</NameTxt>
	<P>Tomorrow.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMullins"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Michael Mullins</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
        <P>As business is ordered for 5.45 p.m., I propose the suspension of the House until that time.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>Sitting suspended at 5.10 p.m. and resumed at  5.45 p.m.</i></P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad."> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad</Title>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Before coming to Private Members&rsquo; business, I call the Leader.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business to discharge the Order of the House in regard to No. 1, which is the substantive motion re proposal for a directive on the freezing and the confiscation of proceeds of crime in the European Union.  The motion that ought to have been moved is No. 24, which is the motion to refer the item to the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, which is to be taken without debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move that the motion in regard to No. 1 be now discharged.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="EU Directives: Referral" RHead="to Joint Committee."> 
    <Title>EU Directives: Referral to Joint Committee</Title>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:</P>
        <P LI="2">Proposal for a Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on the freezing and confiscation of proceeds of crime in the European Union,</P>
        <P FLI="0">a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 3 April 2012, be referred to the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3), which, not later than 14 June 2012, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 73, and Standing Order 75(2) shall accordingly apply.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="NAMA and Irish Bank Resolution Corporation" RHead="Transparency Bill 2011: Second Stage."> 
    <Title>NAMA and Irish Bank Resolution Corporation Transparency Bill 2011: Order for Second Stage</Title>
        <P LI="1" el="5">Bill entitled an Act to provide that, in the interests of transparency, all relevant details of loans, properties, or other assets offered for sale by or with the approval of NAMA or the Irish Bank Resolution Corporation be available to the public by means of publication on a website.</P>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I move: &ldquo;That Second Stage be taken now.&rdquo;</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="NAMA and Irish Bank Resolution Corporation" RHead="Transparency Bill 2011: Second Stage"> 
    <Title>NAMA and Irish Bank Resolution Corporation Transparency Bill 2011: Second Stage</Title>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I move: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
        <P>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Michael Noonan, to the House.  This is important legislation and I ask the Minister to consider it thoroughly.  The people of Ireland must have confidence in institutions of the State.</P>
        <P>On 20 February 2012, the <i>Financial Times</i> described NAMA as one of the largest property companies in the world.  On 26 January 2011, I raised this matter first in this House with the then Minister for Finance, Deputy Brian Lenihan, when I described situations where property developers were purchasing back land on which they had previously taken out loans for well under the current market value, and these properties were not being put on the open market.  There is a growing concern throughout the country about the way NAMA and the IBRC are selling assets and loans.  I was joined on 14 June in raising concerns in regard to developers buying back property from NAMA and from NAMA-controlled banks by the Taoiseach when he said: &ldquo;I have had some indications of attempts to acquire property that was taken from... developers through a variety of methods.&rdquo;  That featured in the <i>Irish Examiner</i> when the Taoiseach was attending the British-Irish Interparliamentary Body meeting.  The following day, the Taoiseach had to climb back from what he had said and he then said he had been reassured by NAMA this was not happening.</P>
        <P>I can confirm it is happening.  Ms Emily O&rsquo;Reilly, the Ombudsman, is so concerned that on 10 March she again reiterated she would like to see NAMA brought under freedom of information legislation so all information in regard to property transactions with NAMA would be open and transparent.  The difficulty and the consequence of freedom of information is that it is applicable only after the event.  What we would then have is a post mortem examination of sales when what we should be looking for is transparency at every step of the process.</P>
        <P>The NAMA Act set out clearly what should happen.  Section 35 of the NAMA Act stated that a code of practice should be set up by NAMA on how it would dispose of assets.  This code of practice was adopted three months later, when it said all credit facilities or securities on credit facilities would be sold in accordance with the code of practice for the governance of State bodies.  What the guidelines outlined was as follows: &ldquo;The disposal of assets of State bodies or the granting of access to properties should be by auction or competitive tendering process . . . The method used should be both transparent and likely to achieve a fair and market-related price.&rdquo;  That is simply not happening.</P>
        <P>NAMA and I have been in constant contact and communication.  It disputes whether the properties it has control of through banks come under this Act.  We must ask ourselves, and any judge would ask himself or herself, what was the intention of this House when it passed the NAMA Act.  The intention of this House was that all properties would be sold in an open and transparent manner.</P>
        <P>I have a legal opinion from barrister Mr. Donal O&rsquo;Laoire, which I can provide to the Minister, that all assets, whether they be properties or loans which NAMA has control of, should be sold under the code of conduct for the sale of State assets.  Whether they are controlled by Bank of Ireland or AIB, ultimately, NAMA has given Irish taxpayers&rsquo; money to those institutions in order to keep those institutions afloat.  What we have is a situation where, as we all know, NAMA is simply not following the laws set out by this House.  That is why we are introducing the Bill, namely, to make clear that it should sell all properties and assets it has control of under the code of conduct &mdash; when I say assets, I mean loans as well as properties.  To facilitate this, it should list them on a website.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">6 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>I  am not alone in this.  I proposed this in January last year and, six months later, NAMA decided it would have a website and it would show properties it had control of only.  After all the money it has given out, it only takes control of roughly 5% of the properties itself whereas it never takes control of 95%.  What we are now looking at is examples which are coming to the fore.  My colleague, Senator Paul Coghlan, and I have previously discussed a situation in Cork where land that was sold for &euro;10 million was recently sold for &euro;7 million to the person who had originally put together the entire deal, yet nobody in Cork, including the adjoining landowners and farmers, were aware this property was for sale.  Irony of ironies, NAMA justified this by saying it had got a higher price than the valuation, which basically means the valuer got it wrong on the first day.  It lauded the valuer and claimed it had got more money, when, in fact, if it had sold for less, what would it have done?  Very little.</P>
        <P>We included the former Anglo Irish Bank in this legislation arising from a situation where in regard to the Four Seasons Hotel, which had borrowed &euro;50 million from Anglo Irish Bank, a director of that bank had co-ordinated the purchase of that hotel from NAMA, and, again, nobody knew this property was for sale.  How is it possible that this is in the best interests of the taxpayer?  Does this sound like insider trading?  How could the Irish people have confidence in an institution that sells property back to directors of Anglo Irish Bank when Anglo Irish Bank had originally given out a loan on that property?</P>
        <P>With regard to the reason behind this, a more disturbing case, the details of which I will give to the Minister, is the situation of Nos. 2 to 14 Baker Street, which is an extraordinary loss to the taxpayer.  I see my colleague, Senator Paul Coghlan, shaking his head when he has not even heard the evidence, which I think means his mind is closed on this issue.  For his benefit, let me outline what happened.  In September 2005, Nos. 2 to 14 Baker Street was purchased from British Land for &euro;47.5 million.  When the bust came, they sold it after receiving planning for 50% more square footage on the site in 2009.</P>
        <P>On 16 April they sold it back to British Land for &euro;29 million, representing a loss of &euro;28.2 million to the Irish taxpayer.  This property was&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>That was dealt with by Bank of Ireland before NAMA was involved and the Senator knows it&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>This property was not placed on the open market.  How was that in the best interests of the Irish taxpayer?  Could my colleague, Senator Coghlan, outline how on 16 April, a trust was set up in Jersey?  A legal agreement signed in Westminster City Council shows that McAleer and Rushe had a beneficial interest in this trust.  Was this to deceive the Irish taxpayer?  On 21 September 2011, in a report and a press release to the market, British Land said:</P>
        <P LI="1">We repurchased approximately 50% of the value it previously sold for in 2004.  We structured a three-way deal to purchase the site from McAleer and Rushe, Bank of Ireland, with the consent of NAMA&rdquo;, [ I ask Senator Coghlan to note].  This acquisition has already performed very well.  Since purchased the valuers have increased the site value by 52%.</P>
        <P FLI="0" Just="Left">This is in one year.  Does this tell us it was undersold?  Does this tell us that the market value was achieved?  It most certainly tells us that.  I could get no answer from either Bank of Ireland or NAMA as to why McAleer and Rushe when they went into that agreement with the consent of Bank of Ireland and with the consent of NAMA, were profit sharing, which means that the money achieved first day was not the entire market value.  Was Bank of Ireland aware of this profit-sharing agreement?  Was NAMA aware?  I do not know the answer.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator received a letter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">For the information of Senator Paul Coghlan, I received a letter which told me they could tell me nothing.  If a situation like Baker Street arose in the future, this Bill would ensure that everybody would know the property was for sale, that anyone could bid for it and there would be confidence in NAMA and the IBRC as a result.  At present there are back room deals going on which have nothing to do with the Department of Finance.  I have confidence in the people in NAMA but the way this is being structured at the moment, they are not selling it in accordance with the rules laid down by this House and by the laws passed in this House.  There needs to be a website where everyone can see what is for sale otherwise the Irish taxpayer is continuing to lose money on a daily basis and not millions or tens of millions but hundreds of millions of euro.</P>
        <P>I ask the Minister to consider doing what we have requested in this very straightforward Bill, to have a website showing every property for sale on behalf of NAMA or under its control and that such property would be on the website for four weeks before being sold.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the motion.  I thank my colleague, Senator Daly, for doggedly pursuing this issue which is of great concern to him.  I remind the Minister and his officials that the last time Senator Daly used parliamentary privilege &mdash; which I presume he is using in some of his statements &mdash; it was a very effective use of Seanad privilege and has resulted in a Garda investigation of child sexual abuse in the Munster region.  Therefore, when Senator Daly uses privilege he is to be listened to and what he says must be taken very seriously.  I do not think he uses it just for the fun of it.</P>
        <P>He raised a very serious issue of considerable public concern.  I am aware of a situation and I am happy to provide the details to the Minister after this debate as I am not prepared to put those details on the record of the House.  An auctioneer was called by a legal adviser in IBRC and asked if it would be appropriate for a person whose property had been repossessed to bid at an auction.  The auctioneer was absolutely shocked that a solicitor would ask such a question and he replied it would be completely inappropriate.  In fact, the same auctioneer announced at the auction that this person or his representatives were prohibited from bidding on the property.  When I brought this case to the attention of Senator Daly, he amended the Bill to include IBRC because the same principles apply to both NAMA and the IBRC.</P>
        <P>My party was criticised when the NAMA scheme was first introduced with accusations that we were trying to do some deal.  Deputy Bruton at the time accused us of looking after developers in a secret deal to benefit our friends.  The Labour Party made great fun of the notion of properties abroad being subject to NAMA but thank God for them because they are the only properties bringing in any money.  The arguments against the establishment of NAMA were quite simplistic in many ways.  I do not mean to say NAMA was the perfect solution but the arguments against it were very simplistic.  NAMA is working, although it is not working that well.  The public need to have confidence in NAMA because of the size of the problem and the size of the black hole which the two entities which comprise IBRC have presented.  The Irish public are entitled to the information which Senator Daly proposes in section 3 of the Bill.  NAMA&rsquo;s action on the properties under its control is nowhere near enough and this is an important point because banks are selling properties.  Apartments in my area are going at a very cheap price and they are all being sold privately.  I do not see any advertisements for their sale.  Apartments taking in rents of up to &euro;10,000 a year are being sold at about &euro;85,000 to &euro;90,000 in private sales by banks.  This results in a significant return to investors who are able to find out which properties are for sale.  A local auctioneer or a willing seller will be looking for substantially more than what the banks are willing to take for the properties.  These properties are being sold by the banks with a return of 12.5% to 13% but many people do not know about this and this information must be made available to all.  Such information would provide the confidence that everything is above board.  As Senator Daly said, such information gives people the opportunity to take advantage of such sales and it would also result in higher prices and better returns for the taxpayer.</P>
        <P>NAMA will forever be branded as a Fianna F&aacute;il proposal and it is very important that those of us in the Fianna F&aacute;il Party keep an eye on the organisation to ensure it is working in the best interests of the taxpayer which in my view it intends to do.  Senator Daly has shown there is a dire need for this legislation as proposed by him.  We are not alleging any fraudulent activity by NAMA nor any wrongdoing but we maintain there is not sufficient transparency and the public have a right to know what is happening.  If that process is brought to its logical conclusion, which would be to support this Bill, the public could benefit because properties would be sold at higher prices and more people would bid on them.</P>
        <P>I reiterate that when Senator Daly reveals facts in this House he should be listened to very closely.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I wish to welcome the Minister for Finance to the House and I am very pleased he is in attendance.  I will call on the Minister after Senator Paul Coghlan who has ten minutes speaking time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I warmly welcome the Minister to the House.  This Bill is fatally flawed, both legislatively and commercially.  I am glad the Minister is here to add his authoritative voice on the subject.</P>
        <P>The Bill proposes the contravening of the legislation which established NAMA and which governs how it conducts its business.  It envisages the public revelation of commercially sensitive information and the placing of NAMA at a significant competitive disadvantage in the market place.  It does so under the pretext of protecting the interests of Irish taxpayers when in practice the opposite would be the effect of this proposed legislation&rsquo;s enactment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Will the Senator please explain how the Bill&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Senator Paul Coghlan without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Sections 3 and 4 of the Bill propose the publication of debtor-specific information, including details of debtor properties.  This is expressly prohibited under the legislation which established NAMA and which was introduced by Senator Daly&rsquo;s party.  It was expressly prohibited for reasons I will raise presently.  Information about debtors is also protected against disclosure by the Data Protection Act and the normal rules of banking confidentiality.  This Bill would, in the face of these protections, expose the State to constitutional challenge by a NAMA debtor.  From a commercial perspective the Bill is extremely poor.  Its implementation would have the effect of placing NAMA in a straitjacket in the conduct of its business on behalf of Irish taxpayers and would actively discourage potential purchase interest in NAMA-controlled properties.  Sections 3(f) and 4 would require that all offers and successful bids be published.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>As an auctioneer, I have no idea how Senator Paul Coghlan could say that property being sold on the open market is not in the best interests of the taxpayer.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly, please desist.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>This would, with immediate effect, scare off institutional investors for whom confidentiality is a must.  To whom, therefore, would large NAMA-controlled commercial buildings be sold were this Bill enacted?</P>
        <P>The effect would be to give non-NAMA institutions, who are actively deleveraging in the marketplace, competitive advantage over NAMA.  It is incomprehensible to me that this House would support legislation which seeks to weaken the hand of the taxpayer in dealing with the impaired loans and assets that are a legacy of the policies pursued by the Senator&rsquo;s party and whose resolution is essential&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>Was the sale of the property in Cork in the interests of the taxpayer?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;for Ireland&rsquo;s recovery and sustainable economic growth.</P>
        <P>The Bill also raises the possibility of collusive behaviour between potential buyers, particularly in the case of larger properties.  I can only presume that this is an unintended consequence of the Senator&rsquo;s Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>How would the Bill, which proposes transparency, do that?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>If the Senator does not like it, he had better stand back because he will hear more.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>The case in Cork shows exactly the opposite.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Bill also raises the possibility of collusive behaviour.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly can discuss this matter with Senator Coghlan in private when they are in County Kerry, if he so wishes.  Let Senator Coghlan continue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The scale of the obligation placed on NAMA would be huge and represent an unnecessary use of scare resources.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>Is Senator Coghlan aware of the NAMA website?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly had ten minutes to make his contribution.  Will he please allow Senator Coghlan to continue?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>This Government intends introducing a new mechanism soon to be established by the Property Services Regulatory Authority.  NAMA supports the new mechanism, which will see the publication of all residential sales prices in the country and has suggested that the extension of this to commercial property would be equally welcome.</P>
        <P>NAMA recently announced its intention to provide &euro;2 billion in project investment in Ireland up to 2016.  Some of this work will be carried out through public private partnerships, PPPs, and other joint venture type arrangements.  Willing partners will be low on the ground if this type of legislation, proposed by Senator Daly, is imposed on NAMA.  This investment will be in both residential and commercial projects in the Republic of Ireland, which represents a significant boost for Ireland&rsquo;s construction sector and a substantial jobs dividend in the wider economy.  Certain projects are in the public domain, including funding for the completion of the Charlestown shopping centre in Finglas, the next phase of a residential development on the grounds of the former D&uacute;n Laoghaire golf course, the proposed completion of Beacon South Quarter in Sandyford and the completion of a substantial shopping centre complex in Portlaoise, County Laois.  All such projects are subject to full cost-benefit appraisal and NAMA only invests where there is a demonstrable return on that investment which outweighs the additional exposure being undertaken.</P>
        <P>NAMA will not be repeating the bad practices sponsored by the Senator&rsquo;s party which resulted in the disastrous overheating and ultimate destruction of our property markets.  In addition, NAMA has also indicated that it will make up to &euro;2 billion in vendor financing, loans of up to 75% loan to value, available to prospective purchasers of commercial property in Ireland.  Already, the availability of vendor financing, at a time when traditional lenders to the sector globally are retrenching, has brought both renewed interest and significant price tension to commercial property sales under NAMA in Ireland.  A good example is the recent sale of No. 1 Warrington Place, Dublin 2, to a private US investor, Northwood, which was making only its second ever investment in Europe, its first being in Paris.  In a press release to announce the purchase, Northwood indicated its intention to work again in future with NAMA.</P>
        <P>The National Asset Management Agency recently launched its 80:20 deferred payment initiative on a pilot basis in counties Meath, Dublin and Cork.  Within the first month of this scheme, a large proportion of the available 115 houses have sale agreed.  The initiative, which provides buyers with significant protection against future falls in the price of their new homes, will be rolled out more generally across the NAMA portfolio.  NAMA has, to date, approved more than &euro;8 billion worth of asset disposals and it has done so without fire selling or hoarding.  It is firmly on track to meet the target of paying down 25% of its debt by end-2013 and it is funding debt repayment, development capital, vendor financing and its own operations out of its own cash reserves.  It will not be turning to the taxpayer for additional moneys.</P>
        <P FLI="0">NAMA and the Department of Health recently confirmed that they are in serious discussions on relocating the National Maternity Hospital at Holles Street to buildings controlled by NAMA at Elm Park.  NAMA has similarly engaged in strategic alliances with other Departments and other public bodies around marrying its commercial remit with the State&rsquo;s need for land and buildings to achieve key public policy objectives.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>I remind the Senator that he has one minute remaining.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly refers to transparency when what he really means is revelations of commercially sensitive and confidential debtor information.  I make this point while noting that NAMA is already subject to a high level of public accountability compared to other commercial semi-State bodies, reflecting the fact that it is managing a significant financial exposure on behalf of the taxpayer.  Too many Members are willing to buy the line on transparency peddled by some, such as Senator Daly, without looking at the facts.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>The Chairman of the Committee of Public Accounts would disagree with Senator Coghlan&rsquo;s view.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I am dealing with the facts.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator would need to read the minutes of the last PAC meeting.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The NAMA Act makes the agency accountable in a number of ways.  Its annual report and financial statements are laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  I am advised by NAMA that its annual report and financial statements will be published within the next two months and will be a full and detailed account of its 2011 operations and results.  The chairman and chief executive are also accountable to the Committee of Public Accounts, PAC, and other Oireachtas committees and give evidence to those committees whenever required to do so.</P>
        <P>Furthermore, there have been numerous parliamentary questions addressed to the Minister on NAMA and the associated replies are on the Oireachtas record.  In addition to its annual accounts, however, NAMA is also required to submit to the Minister for Finance an annual statement by 30 September each year setting out its proposed objectives for the following financial year, the scope of activities to be undertaken, its strategies and policies and its proposed use of resources.</P>
        <P>NAMA is also required to report to the Minister on a quarterly basis, giving detailed information about its loans, its financing arrangements and its income and expenditure.  These reports, which also include other information specified under section 55 of the NAMA Act, track progress on a quarterly basis.  NAMA&rsquo;s accounts are comprehensively audited by the Comptroller and Auditor General, who has a permanent team of officers based in the agency with unrestricted access to all its records and files.  If there is concern about a specific aspect of NAMA&rsquo;s work, it is within the power of the Comptroller and Auditor General to scrutinise any aspect of it.  The Comptroller and Auditor General has already produced two special reports on NAMA&rsquo;s activities and they have been broadly positive in their assessment of how NAMA is managing its complex business.  The process of loan valuation and acquisition is also audited by the European Commission.</P>
        <P>I am very supportive of NAMA&rsquo;s efforts and I think it has at all times acted in the public interest and within the law.  The Government will not impose restrictions on NAMA that would place it at a competitive disadvantage in the market place by preventing it from acting, in every instance, in the most commercial manner and hindering its ability to get every last cent back for the taxpayer.</P>
        <P>As I have said to Senator Daly on several times, he would neither put up nor shut up.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>With all due respect to my colleague, his Taoiseach and Leader has questioned me on that.  Senator Coghlan has not&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Will Senator Daly please resume his seat?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>No, Senator Daly has not.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>On Wednesday, 15 June last year, he questioned NAMA&rsquo;s activities.  I have outlined in this House, if the Senator was listening, that NAMA has sold property in Baker Street and in Cork, of which Senator Coghlan is aware, and that it gave them away.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly, respect the Chair.  Before I call the Minister, I remind all Senators that they have six minutes after the Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><TitleTxt>Minister for Finance</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator Daly for introducing this Bill.  It gives Seanad &Eacute;ireann an opportunity to debate the issues and it gives the public another insight into the workings of NAMA.  The proposals in this Bill have been considered and it has been concluded that the Bill as initiated would place these bodies at a competitive disadvantage to other institutions disposing of assets.  Were these proposals to be implemented they would undermine the commercial mandate of NAMA and IBRC.  Implementation of the policies in this Bill would also be likely to leave these bodies open to constitutional and other legal challenges.</P>
        <P>The two substantive provisions in this Private Members&rsquo; Bill would require NAMA and the IBRC to display various details relating to their assets on proprietary websites.  The level of detail seems to be primarily intended to generate awareness of assets that are to be sold and reveal the likely sales prices for those assets.</P>
        <P>The Bill also proposes that NAMA and the IBRC would publish the achieved sales prices for all relevant disposals on those same websites.</P>
        <P>The obligations proposed in the Bill would lead to negative financial impacts for the taxpayer.  It would reduce the expediency of asset disposal and the value that could be realised, and obstruct the efforts of the institutions to secure the optimum return for the taxpayer.  The Bill would most likely give an advantage to property market funds and developers at the expense of the taxpayer.  Clearly this would not be desirable.  The Bill is clearly at variance with the NAMA and IBRC legislation which established the entities and which governs the conduct of their respective businesses.</P>
        <P>Sections 3 and 4 of the Bill specifically propose the publication of debtor-specific information, including details of debtor properties.  This would work contrary to the intent of the NAMA Act 2009, which provides for NAMA to make a return for the taxpayer on the loans it has purchased, and is also contrary the normal rules of banking confidentiality which apply to NAMA&rsquo;s debtors and continue to apply to IBRC customers.  In relation to the work of both the IBRC and NAMA, the Government&rsquo;s primary concern is ensuring a commercial return for the taxpayer.  While the need for transparency is recognised, there is a commensurate need to ensure that these bodies can operate in a commercial manner.  It is, therefore, in the public interest to ensure that neither NAMA&rsquo;s nor IBRC&rsquo;s commercial mandate is undermined.</P>
        <P>The proposed Bill also has the potential to reduce the number of bidders for property and could be particularly damaging in the cases of sale of larger assets where bidders could be relatively few and therefore more easily identified.  I am particularly concerned about the latter aspect and the risk that publication of the price achieved on a property would give rise to collusive behaviour on the part of purchasers of similar assets.  As a direct result, the Bill would likely have the consequence of leading to gains for international property funds at the expense of the taxpayer.</P>
        <P>There is a contractual duty on both IBRC and on NAMA to respect the right to confidentiality which debtors of financial institutions enjoy.  Such contractual obligations also apply to NAMA by virtue of the contractual arrangements entered into by participating institutions with their customers and which remain in force by virtue of section 99 of the NAMA Act as it provides that, on acquisition of a loan, NAMA takes over the obligations of the participating institution under the loan.  Furthermore, in the case of property under the control of NAMA&rsquo;s debtors, the agency is precluded, under section 202 of the NAMA Act 2009, from disclosing confidential information, which is specifically defined to include information relating to debtors.  Information about individual debtors or guarantors is also protected against disclosure by the Data Protection Acts which apply to both NAMA and to IBRC.</P>
        <P>In drafting the NAMA legislation, it was decided that safeguards protecting the existing contractual arrangements would be required in the NAMA legislation.  The general position taken was that the debtors&rsquo; rights and obligations would not be changed and that NAMA would assume the position of the participating institution, thus ensuring that the rights and obligations of debtors remain unchanged by the NAMA legislation.</P>
        <P>Given the wide array of legislative and case law protection currently available to debtors of both NAMA and IBRC, I consider that there would be a substantial risk of constitutional challenge by any enactment which requires the disclosure of a debtor&rsquo;s identity&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order, every time a Fianna F&aacute;il Private Members&rsquo; Bill is put before this House, the Constitution is invoked against it.  It is an abuse of the Constitution.  Every time we write a Bill and get senior counsel to advise us on it, it is a disgrace and a shame to come up with constitutional reasons against it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>I call on the Minister to continue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;particularly in circumstances where there were no similar disclosure requirements in relation to debtors of all other financial institutions.</P>
        <P>I would like to remind the Senator who intervened, that the last two Private Members&rsquo; motions &mdash; one of which was a Bill introduced in the D&aacute;il by his colleague, Deputy Michael McGrath &mdash; were accepted by me.</P>
        
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
<P>Not in here.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>We are not opposing them.  This is the exception because it is invalid and I cannot accept it on legal grounds.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>This is a different Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>The relationship framework between the IBRC and the Government ensures that the bank remains a separate economic unit with independent powers of decision and that its board and management retain responsibility and authority for determining the bank&rsquo;s strategy and commercial policies and for conducting its day-to-day operations.  This relationship framework was put in place as a condition of the Government&rsquo;s programme of assistance.  The proposal would be contrary to the bank&rsquo;s obligation to its clients and contrary to the IBRC&rsquo;s ability to operate commercially and in the public interest.</P>
        <P>The existing commercial rules, which apply to both NAMA and IBRC provide for considerable transparency, consistent with bank confidentiality and maximising the commercial return from the assets.  The Government is not opposed to maximising transparency where this is consistent with the commercial mandates of these bodies.  In the case of NAMA, the existing legislation provides for extensive public reporting on its activities and for review of these reports by an Oireachtas committee.  NAMA is already subject to a high level of public accountability compared to other commercial semi-State bodies, reflecting the fact that it is managing a significant financial exposure on behalf of the Irish taxpayer.  I met with the NAMA board very soon after taking office and explained that I expected the agency to comply with the high standards of transparency provided for in the NAMA Act to the maximum extent possible.  The board of the agency and I liaise closely on this issue.</P>
        <P>The NAMA Act 2009 makes the agency accountable in a number of ways, including laying its annual report and audited financial statements before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  The agency is also required to report to me on a quarterly basis and those reports are, in accordance with the Act, also laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas.  The chairman and chief executive are also accountable to the Committee of Public Accounts and other Oireachtas committees.  They give evidence to committees whenever required to do so.  NAMA&rsquo;s accounts are comprehensively audited by the Comptroller and Auditor General, and it is also open to the Comptroller and Auditor General to conduct other <i>ad hoc</i> examinations.</P>
        <P>Under the Anglo Irish Corporation Act 2009, a relationship framework agreement was specified by the Minister in relation to the bank and this agreement defines my relationship with the bank.  The agreement, approved by our external partners, assigns responsibility and authority for all operations and business of the bank in accordance with the board&rsquo;s legal and fiduciary duties.  The board also has responsibility and authority for ensuring compliance with the regulatory and legal obligations of the bank.  The shareholding management unit in my Department oversees the operation of the agreement.  Furthermore, as a licensed credit institution, the bank is regulated by the Central Bank of Ireland and also produces and publishes detailed audited accounts on an annual basis.  Interim accounts are also published six months into the bank&rsquo;s financial year.  In addition to that, the bank operates in accordance with the terms of a restructuring plan approved by the European Commission.  The Commission has appointed a monitoring trustee to oversee the bank&rsquo;s compliance with the terms of the restructuring plan, which reports to the Commission on the bank&rsquo;s compliance on a regular basis.  The level of oversight and published information is extensive, appropriate and in keeping with the commercial mandate of the bank.  This is wholly consistent with other regulated financial institutions and the commercial and contractual sensitivity associated with the business of the bank.  Nonetheless, the matter of transparency is kept under constant review.</P>
        <P>Since 2011, NAMA has included on its website a database of properties which are under the control of receivers appointed to enforce against its debtors.  This provides a single source of information on NAMA assets which are for sale and is updated on a very regular basis.  In each instance, information to facilitate potential purchasers, such as contact details for the seller, is provided.  The NAMA board issued policy guidelines in mid-2011 which require that all sales must be appropriately marketed and that an independent valuation of all assets is carried out.</P>
        <P>The Government made a commitment in the programme for Government to improve the quality of information available on the Irish housing market by requiring that the selling price of all dwellings be recorded in a publicly available national housing price database, including prices achieved in sales by both IBRC and NAMA debtors and receivers.  The register will comprise a database searchable by a number of criteria, including address or value of property by county, city or town.  The information, which will be contained in the database, will be the full address of the property, its sale price and date of sale.  The register will cover all sales from 1 January 2010.  While September 2012 is the outer limit for publication of the register, it is intended to bring it on stream at the earliest possible date.  A similar initiative is being undertaken with respect to commercial letting agreements and rent reviews.  Commercial property is, more often than not, arranged by lease and therefore emphasis has been placed on leases rather than sales in those cases.</P>
        <P>I would like to remind Senators of the potential positive contribution that NAMA can make to the recovery of our economy.   The Government has been working with NAMA on plans for getting people back to work.  This has recently culminated in NAMA&rsquo;s plan to invest at least &euro;2 billion in Ireland over the coming four years.  This investment by NAMA will be an important contribution to the Government&rsquo;s plans for getting people back to work.  Some &euro;2 billion of investment will generate up to 25,000 direct and indirect construction jobs and up to 10,000 additional jobs in the wider economy.  NAMA has advised that this investment will include the completion of properties and, importantly, it will allow the development of land in anticipation of future supply shortages.  Already, there have been discussions between NAMA and IDA Ireland about the development of additional office space to facilitate future foreign direct investment decisions as based on the number of announcements there is a likelihood of shortages emerging in the medium term.</P>
        <P>I reiterate my point that the proposals in this Private Members&rsquo; Bill have the potential to undermine the commercial mandate of NAMA and IBRC and place these institutions at a competitive disadvantage, thus allowing other banks and companies who are the direct competitors of NAMA and IBRC to make higher returns than is currently possible, at the expense of the Irish taxpayer.  Clearly, this would not be a desirable outcome.  The proposals also leave both NAMA and IBRC open to potential constitutional and other legal challenges.  The existing transparency regimes at these institutions provide as much transparency as is consistent with bank confidentiality and ensuring a commercial return from their assets.  The Government is committed to maximum transparency and accountability of these bodies.</P>
        <P>Given all the above, I feel the operations of NAMA and IBRC are currently sufficiently transparent and this Private Members&rsquo; Bill is opposed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SeanDBarrett"><NameTxt>Senator Sean D. Barrett</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  None of us wants to be here for this debate.  This is a situation we inherited and it has been a disaster for the Irish economy.  The conduct of bankers and their friends in the property business has brought this country to its knees, destroyed its international credit and raised unemployment from 4.5% to 14.5%.  I am sure the Minister would much prefer to be presenting his plans for the development of the economy rather than having to tidy up the mess that was left as a result of the conduct of the banks and the property sector.  I believe he will have the support of the House for all his efforts to do that.  It is part of the difficulties we have had over the weekend in trying to persuade the Germans to take an attitude that some of the bank debt should be their responsibility.  Having seen what has gone on, they would not touch it with the proverbial barge pole.</P>
        <P>The population of the country is furious that the people who did this to the country are still walking around.  The number of special needs assistants, the carer&rsquo;s allowance and so on have been cut and it will be four years in September since the rescue of these people and nothing has happened to them.  It is a fault of the entire system of governance, perhaps including the Houses of Parliament, that these are still immune from the consequences of the damage they did to this country.  There is huge anger among the people about that.  I imagine that a sizeable proportion of 40% who voted against the treaty in the referendum last Thursday were annoyed that we have not yet called these institutions, banks and builders to account for what they did.</P>
        <P>The Minister mentioned the Comptroller and Auditor General&rsquo;s report and I note a reference on page 11 which links in with Senator Daly&rsquo;s proposal.  The report states:</P>
        <P LI="1">In practice, NAMA has not, to date, disposed of property directly.  Property has been disposed of, has been sold either by debtors or by insolvency practitioners.  This means that most disposals are not governed by the NAMA Code of Practice for the disposal of bank assets or the Code of Practice for the Governance of State Bodies, both of which require competitive processes when disposals above a certain value are being made.</P>
        <P FLI="0">He said that this embodies commercial confidentiality and so on but commercial confidentiality went out the window with those banks.  In saying they are regulated by the Central Bank, for those crucial years, the Central Bank did not regulate the people concerned.</P>
        <P>There is a good deal to be said in terms of the McCarthy report on the disposal of State assets in that we conduct these without beauty contests.  Going through NAMA is a kind of a beauty context.  Colm McCarthy did not quite say, in his inimitable way, that they should be put on them eBay, but the disposal of all the State assets should be as open and as transparent as possible.  I would add that we should do this as quickly as possible.  The long-term economic value argument in this respect is largely bogus.  Some people hope that property prices will pick up while others do not.  When one goes to the auction, the two balance each other out and that is the price, as it were.  In terms of hoping that things will turn out better and that NAMA will become a development agency, I do not see that happening.  We should do this now and get on with the development of this country.</P>
        <P>Interestingly, the Comptroller and Auditor General found that we had lost another &euro;5 billion.  We acquired assets that had a &euro;74 billion face value, we paid &euro;32 billion for them, which represents a loss in their value of 57% and they have now lost another fifth of their value.  The &euro;63 billion bank bailout in the period reviewed by the Comptroller and Auditor General has now become a &euro;68 billion bank bailout for 776 people, 800 borrowers, 12,000 loans and 35,000 properties.  Those 776 people have done an enormous amount of damage to this country and they should not be protected in any way.  The sooner we dispose of these properties, realise the assets and get on with developing the country, the better, and their disposal should be transparent.</P>
        <P>If we sell the ghost estates now, local authorities, sports clubs and people who intend to do good things can buy them.  It is an asset to this country to allow property prices to fall.  It is only at the behest of the banks that we assumed it was a goal to try to keep property prices up.  The sooner they fall, the better and that will precipitate the revival of the Irish economy.</P>
        <P>I favour Senator Daly&rsquo;s proposal and the Minister also spoke in favour of transparency.  Commercial confidentiality in respect of bankrupt organisations does not seem to me to be a high value we should espouse.  We should take these assets away from the people who made such disastrous investment decisions and passed the bill on to the taxpayer and sell them on to somebody else who can help us to develop this country.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister.  While we would prefer not to have to do so in the first instance, the acquisition of &euro;75 billion worth of loans for an outlay of &euro;32 billion illustrates the scale of the collapse of the property sector and the enormous challenge the country faces.  It represents a 57% reduction in their par value, as Senator Barrett said.  We welcome the recent announcement of NAMA&rsquo;s &euro;2 billion investment and the number of jobs that will generate. I note that NAMA&rsquo;s quarterly report as of December 2011 was published.  While it contains much that is of a descriptive manner, it does not go very far in explaining the activities of NAMA, a point to which I return.  Other reports, including Special Report 79 of the Comptroller and Auditor General on the activities of NAMA, add something to the debate but the complexities of NAMA require more than an ordinary level of scrutiny.</P>
        <P>Senator Daly&rsquo;s Bill attempts to bring some clarity to this area but, unfortunately there are some problems with it, particularly in regard to confidentiality as well as some obstacles of a contractual nature.  In addition, we can see the Bill as placing a barrier to much of NAMA&rsquo;s commercial ability, particularly the prescriptive insistence on the publication of details which might place the working of NAMA&rsquo;s commercial activity in a disadvantageous position in regard to other actors in the property market.  There is a serious flaw in the Bill.  However, I can understand some of Senator Daly&rsquo;s concerns and I have heard some of them raised in other areas.  In this regard, I thank the Senator for using his party&rsquo;s Private Members&rsquo; time to bring this Bill before the House for debate.   Unfortunately, Senator Daly previously made comments in the House about the operation of NAMA but has failed to provide any further information despite being invited to do so on numerous occasions.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>Hold on until I get you the paper.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly&rsquo;s previous assertions&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>There is one in Cork and Nos. 2 to 14, Baker Street and I can give all of the information to Senator Gilroy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly will have four minutes at the end of the debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>You are wrong on both.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I did give evidence and Senator Coghlan is aware that if anybody gets a 52% uplift in one year the taxpayer does not get a benefit from it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Gilroy to continue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly&rsquo;s previous assertions of wrongdoing at NAMA have not been substantiated and I seem to remember an exchange between Senators Daly and Coghlan in the House in which much unsubstantiated comment was made.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>One person who backed me up in June last year was the Taoiseach so I am in good company.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>That debate fizzled out because Senator Daly failed to provide the required information.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">If the debate had fizzled out we would not be here this evening.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>I also remember the previous Minister for Finance, Mr. Lenihan, inviting Senator Daly to provide information which he failed to do.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I provided it to NAMA.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Byrne&rsquo;s comments on Senator Daly&rsquo;s previous use of privilege were very good and welcome, but he omitted to refer to the very rapid climbdown Senator Daly had to make in the House this year when he was challenged about unsubstantiated allegations of wrongdoing.  We need to be very careful in how we express ourselves in the Chamber and have no ambiguity, or allow room for any ambiguity to arise, as to our motives.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>For the record Senator Gilroy, I have never retracted anything I have said here because everything I say is researched.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>NAMA&rsquo;s financial objectives are clearly set out in the latest report and include an immediate target to reduce its debt by 24% by 2013 and ultimately to achieve a surplus on its activities by 2020.  This looks reasonable.  It will be a great relief when this is achieved but it might not be all plain sailing and we might face some headwinds.  How likely does the Minister think it is that the economic conditions predicted for NAMA to achieve its aims will materialise?  Concerns are also raised about NAMA being unable to collect the expected cash from debtors and failing to achieve the maximum obtainable price when assets are disposed of.  This latter point is Senator Daly&rsquo;s main concern and he expressed his concerns in the House with regard to a land transaction in Cork which he feels may not have maximised the proceeds of the sale.  I invite him to provide the information we are all very anxious to see in this regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>Deputy Buttimer is in agreement with me on this.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Minister concerned that some of the property disposed of by NAMA has not come onto the open market?  If this is the case will the Minister offer an explanation for it?  NAMA disposes of or approves of the disposal of a large amount of property each month estimated to be in the region of approximately &euro;750 million.  While we have every confidence in NAMA&rsquo;s abilities and oversight powers there is some concern about the level of external oversight not being what it might be despite the number of agencies charged with examining the affairs of NAMA.</P>
        <P>It has been pointed out that NAMA&rsquo;s accounts are opaque and distorted by accounting adjustments which make them very difficult to interpret.  It also makes reading them very ponderous.  It is very difficult to ascertain whether the price obtained by NAMA is accurate due to the low level of similar sales which may act as comparators.  This is a fair point.  However, in London, where comparators do exist,  there are indications the prices obtained by NAMA might well be at the low end of the expected price index.  This is a fact.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I have the evidence.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>It is very frustrating to be constantly interrupted when trying to make a point.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatONeill"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Pat O&rsquo;Neill</NameTxt>
	<P>I will give the Senator 20 seconds more.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>It has been suggested that one way to amend NAMA legislation, which Senator Daly&rsquo;s Bill has not considered and which removes the possibility of placing NAMA at a commercial disadvantage, would be a requirement for NAMA to publish details after a fixed time, perhaps 12 or 18 months following the completion of a disposal.  Perhaps the strengthening of the oversight role of the Office of the Comptroller and Auditor General with an increase in specialised support staff could go some way towards removing any residual doubt that remains in certain quarters about the transparency and accountability of NAMA&rsquo;s activities.</P>
        <P>Senator Daly&rsquo;s Bill is welcome in so far as it has facilitated this debate on NAMA.  It might do no harm if we could devote further time to a comprehensive debate on NAMA in its entirety.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AverilPower"><NameTxt>Senator Averil Power</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I join my colleagues in highlighting the need for greater transparency in the way NAMA does its work.  It is a crucial factor in having public confidence in the institution.  Other issues also need to be prioritised to ensure people and the taxpayer have confidence in the institution and feel it will deliver value for money and its social objectives, as NAMA was also supposed to deliver social dividends in the housing sector during its term of office.</P>
        <P>Several months ago I raised the issue of the extent to which NAMA is proactive in chasing developers filing bankruptcy proceedings outside the State with the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, who gave me a general reply but not much more.  The Minister is very aware of the situation in Priory Hall and the despicable conditions in which residents found themselves when they were left living in a death trap and had to be evacuated from their homes overnight.  To add insult to the injury of this trauma and despite bankruptcy proceedings having been lodged here, they had to watch the developer concerned, Thomas McFeely, go to London to avail of bankruptcy tourism, which will ultimately mean he will be free to go about his personal and professional business sooner than if he had taken the appropriate course through the Irish courts.  The fact that NAMA has not pursued him has caused incredible anger among residents.  A private individual, a lady who was a victim of one of his other developments, is taking a case.  My colleague, Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien, wrote to the Minister to highlight the issue.  While I appreciate the Minister cannot respond to me on an individual development on the floor of the House I impress on him the need to raise the general issue with NAMA.</P>
        <P>To have confidence in the institution people need to feel that NAMA is taking the same steps as a private institution would and precedent was set by the Sean Quinn case.  He was declared bankrupt in Belfast but this was challenged by the IBRC which was successful in proving his centre of interest was in the Republic and had the decision overturned.  NAMA should take the same steps and pursue people with exactly the same vigour on behalf of the taxpayer as any other institution would.</P>
        <P>Many unfinished estates throughout the country are related to NAMA loans.  People live in developments which are building sites, including in the north fringe in my area.  People were promised a particular lifestyle and community facilities in these developments but instead they live in filthy dusty building sites without any of the promised community facilities.  Some developments still have hoardings up stating they will open in 2006 or 2007.  This is a very serious issue as people live in the most dreadful and unacceptable conditions.  They bought at the height of the boom and paid a huge amount of money for their apartments and houses and now live in dreadful conditions.  Is it the agency&rsquo;s intention to facilitate a process by which all of the affected estates would be brought up to a suitable standard as soon as possible?  There is a social imperative for families living in these states to ensure they are provided with pleasant and safe places to live.  The Minister is aware of the child who drowned in a development in Galway in February.  This child had wandered out and across from his house to a pool of water in an unfinished development building site and was found dead.  This is the harsh reality of what it is like and parents are concerned because they live across the road from building sites.  There is also an economic imperative from the point of view of NAMA delivering value for money on the loans over time with regard to future site value of undeveloped land and empty units.  To realise the best possible economic value, it would be worth considerably more if the development were finished properly.  I appreciate they will not be finished to the full scale of what was initially promised, but new realistic plans should be drawn up for each.  In the current context it might not cost that much and might help to stimulate economic activity while ensuring that families have somewhere decent to live.</P>
        <P>Transparency is a big issue as mentioned by my colleagues.  However, the unfinished estates are important.  NAMA needs to be rigorous in chasing developers and being seen to do so in order that people do not take advantage of the easier bankruptcy situation across the Border or across the water in Britain.  I urge the Minister to address those issues which are important for public confidence.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelWDArcy"><NameTxt>Senator Michael D&rsquo;Arcy</NameTxt>
	<P>At the outset I take the opportunity to withdraw some of my perhaps excessively harsh criticism of Senator Marie-Louise O&rsquo;Donnell on the last occasion we had a debate.  I was disappointed with her contribution and considered it to be all style over substance.  I was harsh because I consider Senator O&rsquo;Donnell to be somebody of substance.</P>
        <P>I reviewed the speech I gave in the other Chamber during the debate on the National Asset Management Agency Bill.  All of the issues raised then are on the record.  I had a real concern about the price for property on the basis of the sharp practice that took place in the development, auctioneering and construction sectors.  This should not be dealt with through a Bill of this type for just one or two institutions.  It is crucial that the property services regulatory authority is established as quickly as possible so that we have no more sharp practice.  The method by which sharp practice is concluded is that every price on every sale goes up within a period of time as the Minister mentioned in his speech.  Those prices will be going up, backdated to 1 January 2010.  That will be of real benefit to every future purchaser of a property from now on.</P>
        <P>I welcome the &euro;2 billion that NAMA will invest in the construction sector.  Effectively it is an injection of cash following its sale of property abroad.  I am not sure if that will be replaced by other funds.  On a number of occasions I have said in this House that the 100,000 construction workers who are unemployed need to be given an opportunity to get back into work.  I am not talking about building unsustainable developments, but building residential units, sustainable energy infrastructure or other crucial structures.  I welcome that wholeheartedly.</P>
        <P>I have a real concern about the NAMA scheme with the effective 20% underwriting of a property that may fall further in value.  The best method of regulating the market is by the market itself.  If NAMA put enough of the appropriate properties on the market, starting off effectively in Dublin city centre, there would be a wave effect from there throughout the country.  It will take some time for that wave to travel throughout the State but it will happen in time.  In the past two months property prices in Dublin city have not only stabilised, but have increased.  While we do not yet know if this is a trend, we will find out in the coming months.</P>
        <P>Based on my experience on the Committee of Public Accounts, I do not believe there is any Government organisation as professional, capable and authoritative in the job it does than the Office of the Comptroller and Auditor General.  Anybody who has had any dealing with those in that office will agree that they are the best at what they do.  The Comptroller and Auditor General has a full-time team in NAMA scrutinising everything that is being done.  I would welcome an expansion of its role, with greater interaction between the Comptroller and Auditor General and us, perhaps through the committees or perhaps via information flow from the Minister.</P>
        <P>The point about commercially sensitive information cannot be ignored.  We cannot have two institutions, one a major property company and the other a bank, having that information in public and none of their competitors making that information public.  That simply would not work because in time it would cost the taxpayers&rsquo; money.  Nobody in this Chamber or the other one wants to see this costing the taxpayers more than it should.  We are all satisfied that it is costing more than enough.</P>
        <P>The anger and downright fury is because citizens do not believe the people who caused the crash have been held to account yet.  I am hopeful that the various agencies, the DPP, the Garda and the Office of Corporate Enforcement will do their jobs well.  Nobody should influence any potential case.  Nobody wants a repeat of what happened when Ms Mary Harney spoke about the former Taoiseach, the late Charles Haughey.  <i>The New York Times</i> once asked, &ldquo;Can one bank bring down a nation?&rdquo;  While we do not know the answer to that question yet, we know it went damn close to it.  It is crucial that the bankers and developers who caused the crash along with those in the Government and the State agencies who did not do their job well enough should be called to account.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  Ba mhaith liom f&aacute;ilte a chur roimh an mBille seo thar ceann Sinn F&eacute;in.  Cuirfidh muid f&aacute;ilte roimh rud ar bith a chinnteoidh go bhfuil an eagra&iacute;ocht ar a dtugtar NAMA n&iacute;os oscailte agus n&iacute;os tr&eacute;dhearca&iacute;.  Taca&iacute;m le cuid mhaith den mh&eacute;id a d&uacute;irt an Seanad&oacute;ir Michael D&rsquo;Arcy maidir leis an imn&iacute; at&aacute; ar dhaoine os rud &eacute; nach bhfuil an dream at&aacute; ciontach as an titim tubaisteach a tharla i margadh tith&iacute;ochta na t&iacute;re agus, d&aacute; bhr&iacute; sin, i gc&oacute;ras bainc&eacute;ireachta na t&iacute;re tagtha os comhair na c&uacute;irte, nach bhfuil siad &aacute; bhfeice&aacute;il ar aghaidh na ngi&uacute;ist&iacute;s agus nach bhfuil ceart agus c&oacute;ir agus cothrom na &eacute;inne &aacute; fh&aacute;il.</P>
        <P>I support the Bill because anything that can make NAMA more open and transparent in its dealings is welcome.  Deputy Pearse Doherty introduced legislation in the D&aacute;il to provide that the Freedom of Information Act should be brought to bear on NAMA.  We need to be able to see what is going on in the organisation.  Every day NAMA is dealing in billions of euro of taxpayers&rsquo; money and is essentially the largest holder of State assets.  It disposes of millions of euro worth of assets on average every month and yet there is very little public knowledge of its activities.  NAMA costs the State more than &euro;500,000 per day in running costs.  On its payroll it has developers earning more than &euro;200,000 and it is mired in potential conflicts of interest.  NAMA does not want a spotlight shone on its activities.  It is currently fighting a case against the Information Commissioner because it does not want to provide information under environmental legislation sought by an Internet blogger.  This case by one arm of the State against another will cost the taxpayer hundreds of thousands of euro.</P>
        <P>We have a number of other reasons for calling for more openness and transparency around NAMA.  Many more applications were made under the previous freedom of information legislation, but with the change in the rules, that has reduced dramatically.  Many people would like to find out more about what is going on.  NAMA will cost the State &euro;531,000 in operating costs every day of 2012.  Since its establishment, NAMA has spent &euro;27.5 million on legal fees and &euro;2.5 million on audit fees.</P>
        <P>NAMA is disposing of an average of &euro;500 million worth of assets per month by reference to the original values of the loans, roughly &euro;200 million by reference to what NAMA paid, and will do so at least until the end of 2013.  Up to December 2011, NAMA had been disposing of assets on average worth &euro;750 million per month, at original value, or &euro;15.8 billion worth of loans.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">7 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>NAMA has advanced millions to developers to finish projects, with &euro;568.2 million being forwarded to developers outside the island of Ireland.  Over two-thirds of NAMA properties are on the island of Ireland, yet only 41% of its cash advances are spent here.  NAMA is funding development projects in Britain and Europe while Ireland is dotted with ghost estates and empty hotels.  Under the original NAMA Act, the body can borrow up to &euro;5 billion in total to loan to developers to finish projects.  NAMA is paying more than 100 developers&rsquo; salaries, with some earning as much as &euro;200,000 a year.  NAMA has considered the introduction of a developer incentive scheme which would allow a developer to keep a portion of an asset sale if the sale met and exceeded NAMA targets.  This kind of incentivising is not in the original legislation.</P>
        <P>A total of 16 firms have been identified by NAMA to advise it on loan sales in Europe and the US.  These firms have been put onto Europe and US &ldquo;panels&rdquo;.  NAMA has admitted that several existing NAMA employees have close links with these firms and were formerly employed by them.  The newly appointed head of asset management in NAMA is a former chairman and managing director of Jones Lang LaSalle, JLLS.  JLLS is on both advisory panels.  Other firms listed on the panels include Ernst &amp; Young, Goldman Sachs, KPMG and UBS.</P>
        <P>NAMA is using an &ldquo;effective interest rate&rdquo; methodology to calculate interest payments in its quarterly accounts.  This method assumes interest repayments rather than allowing for actual interest repayments and can overstate profits, delivering a misleading picture to the general public about NAMA operations; for example, in its third quarter reporting in 2011, NAMA reported &euro;255 million in interest payments, whereas only &euro;175 million was received.  Given the continued decline in property prices and worsening economic conditions, there is no way of knowing how loans will continue to perform, so estimating interest that may come in is hardly advisable.</P>
        <P>The Minister has appointed an additional advisory group to advise him on the future strategic direction of NAMA.  It is unclear whether this group will just act as a conduit to the Minister on the strategic direction of NAMA or actively direct NAMA on strategy.  NAMA is not effectively managing conflicts of interest.  It appointed PricewaterhouseCoopers, PWC, to advise it on bad loans.  PWC was then appointed as a receiver to Treasury Holdings against which NAMA is currently fighting a court case.  PWC is a tenant of a Treasury Holdings building which is listed as security for loans held by NAMA.  NAMA claims it has protected against conflict of interest by appointing Ernst &amp; Young as a receiver to the Treasury Holdings building in which PWC is resident.</P>
        <P>Ernst &amp; Young were auditors to Anglo Irish Bank.  During their role as auditors they failed to detect and report massive loans to directors as well as the massive window dressing arrangement of &euro;8.2 billion with Irish Permanent TSB which was used to improve Anglo Irish Bank&rsquo;s balance sheet at year end.  They also stood over accounts that showed a profit for the bank.  Consequently, Ernst &amp; Young are being investigated for their role in the Anglo Irish Bank debacle.  As a result of their involvement in Anglo Irish Bank, the Chartered Accountants Regulatory Board, CARB, commenced an investigation into Ernst &amp; Young in 2009.  The investigation was led by the former Comptroller and Auditor General, John Purcell.  Ernst &amp; Young attempted to block this investigation through the courts but were unsuccessful.  In September 2011, the CARB investigation concluded that Ernst &amp; Young do, on the face of it, have a case to answer in respect of their involvement in the Anglo Irish Bank debacle.  However, criminal investigations into Anglo Irish Bank have meant that the Director of Public Prosecutions has asked that the investigations be held off until his work is complete.</P>
        <P>In a separate matter, NAMA has appointed a senior legal figure to fight a case against the State&rsquo;s Information Commissioner, on the basis of an Internet blogger seeking information from NAMA under environmental legislation.  The senior legal figure is currently representing Treasury Holdings against NAMA.  NAMA is actively fighting another arm of the State, with taxpayers&rsquo; money being spent on both sides, to stop information about it being available under freedom of information legislation.</P>
        <P>Cuireann Sinn F&eacute;in f&aacute;ilte roimh rud ar bith a thaca&iacute;onn le tr&eacute;dhearcacht NAMA.  F&aacute;ilt&iacute;mid roimh an mBille at&aacute; curtha ar aghaidh ag an tSeanad&oacute;ir Daly agus beimid ag tac&uacute; leis.  T&aacute; s&uacute;il agam go dtiocfaidh s&eacute; chun cinn chomh tapaidh agus is f&eacute;idir.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimmyHarte"><NameTxt>Senator Jimmy Harte</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome Senator Daly&rsquo;s Bill because it gives us an idea of how people are thinking about NAMA.  It is very confusing for many members of the public, including myself, to grasp how NAMA operates and how we ended up in this position.  It was the result of the previous administration.  I am not referring to the political Administration but to the developer-led economy in this country.  If one studies what happened with the Irish Glass Bottle plant site in Ringsend, it is an example how the entire system ran into itself eventually.  It ended up with one State body buying the property from another State body for approximately &euro;412 million.  It is worth approximately &euro;40 million now.  AIB is owed approximately &euro;300 million and Anglo Irish Bank is also owed money but the bottom line is that the taxpayer will pay for it.</P>
        <P>The usual suspects were involved with that site purchase and no consideration was given to the end game.  The game in Ireland at that time was that one bought a site, got planning permission changed for it and sold it off to somebody else.  The pyramid scheme kept growing until eventually the taxpayer ended up footing the bill.  Many developers were genuine property developers who got caught in the flow.  Other developers were laundering money, using development for criminal purposes.  Those guys are in the same boat as the rest, but we are paying off their debts as well.  These people, and we all know who they are, were using it as a money laundering procedure because they could hide under the cloak of a developer.  We also know people who became developers.  One day they were sitting drinking in a pub and the next day they were driving a mercedes.  Many people who have worked in this country for 40 years are lucky to buy a new car.  These people are now back on the street, doing what they used to do before that.  Other guys who are still driving the mercedes also caused the problem.</P>
        <P>Ultimately, we must consider what is in this for the ordinary person on the street.  I believe that in ten or 20 years NAMA will be a textbook example in schools and universities of how things went wrong and how we tried to solve them.  I met a young couple yesterday who are anxious to change their house.  They have had a mortgage for 16 years &mdash; I know them longer than that &mdash; and they owe perhaps &euro;3,000 on that.  They wish to move to another cottage up the road that they like.  The wife is working full time and the husband is working part time but because he is working part time they have been told there is no way they will get a mortgage.  They are only seeking &euro;70,000, never missed a mortgage payment in 16 years and they have substantial savings of &euro;10,000.  They told me the bank told them that unless the husband is working full time for at least a year, it will not even consider them.</P>
        <P>As the young gentleman said, they want to buy the cottage and will spend their own money doing it up.  When somebody else bought their property, they had to install a new kitchen.  However, the entire system has ground to a halt.  That is the practical impact of the situation caused by the multimillionaires in this country.  Many of them are still millionaires.  Until that young couple, and other couples like them, can move to the property they desire, the property market will not move.  We have been reading reports recently that property prices are actually too low at present.  That is basically because people cannot borrow money.</P>
        <P>In Donegal and probably in other parts of the country, houses that are worth &euro;80,000 or &euro;90,000 can be bought &euro;60,000 or &euro;70,000, but people cannot buy them.  They are interested in buying the properties but they cannot access the credit which they could have accessed ten years ago.  These people are good clients.  They are rearing families and maintaining properties, but they do not wish to rent houses all their lives.  They want to be in a position to buy the property.  They are capable of paying the money back and their track record proves that, but these are the people who are being victimised.  It is not the Derek Quinlans, Bernard McNamaras and the like, who were buying property from each other and bumping up the prices.  They did not care about the end game.</P>
        <P>NAMA has an important role but, for me, it is still a little confusing to assess where it will end up.  However, I agree with the Minister that if information is commercially sensitive, we should not give it away.  The sooner NAMA can shut its doors, say it has done its job and helped in some small way to bring the country and the property market back to normality, the better.  There is a glut of people who wish to buy property but who cannot afford to so do, not through their own fault but through the fault of others.</P>
        <P>Finally, I agree with Senator Power&rsquo;s point regarding unfinished estates.  Much of the &euro;2 billion that the National Asset Management Agency wishes to spend should be spent on flattening down and cleaning up some estates.  While much work is involved in cleaning up an estate, it helps many families who live in areas in which six or eight properties are run-down or in which the block work was left half-complete.  Consideration should be given to using the money to finish estates, to clean and flatten down estates and to grow lawns on which kids can play, rather than having parents concerned about torn-down fences and holes full of water.  I ask the Minister to use his good offices to push that agenda as well, in respect of how the aforementioned &euro;2 billion will be spent.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House and it is good to see him here today.  Most Members across both sides of the House are in agreement that there is work to be done on how NAMA goes about its business.  As Vice Chairman of the Committee of Public Accounts in the previous D&aacute;il, I have some experience in this regard and many Members are correct on how NAMA reports and is answerable to the Office of the Comptroller and Auditor General and to the Committee of Public Accounts.  However, the proposals in this Bill get down to detail and I commend my colleague, Senator Daly, on introducing it.  He has been highly consistent on this issue over&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>Consistently wrong.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>That is the Senator&rsquo;s view but&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I note the Taoiseach is with me on this one.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien, without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Daly has been consistent on this issue and this goes back to the previous Government.  Were I obliged to vote again on the creation of NAMA as I did back in 2009, I would and the same vote would apply as when I was a Member of the other House.  NAMA is extremely important to the future prosperity of this State.  It was an important part of the attempt to cleanse the balance sheets of our banks to allow them to do what they are not doing at present, that is, to lend into the real economy.</P>
        <P>I have a couple of questions to which the Minister might respond now or later.  In his opening statement, the Minister mentioned the Government&rsquo;s primary concern is ensuring a commercial return for the taxpayer.  While I fully agree with him, I consider NAMA&rsquo;s disposal of properties in the context of an average discount, or haircut as it was called back then, on loans taken over to NAMA of approximately 50%.  Moreover, the taxpayer ponied up 100% if one includes the cost of the recapitalisation of the banks in addition to NAMA&rsquo;s purchase of the loans at a discounted price.  I have an issue with how NAMA now tends to track what are its so-called profits on the basis of what it has made above and beyond the price for which it purchased the loan.  However, the taxpayer is on the hook for a lot more than the aforementioned average 50% discount.  While colleagues today have mentioned that NAMA has not engaged in a fire sale, I believe it has moved too quickly in selling European and British property in particular for which there have been good rent rolls and good tenants.  Vultures from across the world have been looking at prime property, particularly in London, where there have been such cases, and NAMA has sold such properties on the cheap.  I refer to the basis of the agency&rsquo;s staff performance guides by which its staff will receive bonuses for hitting certain targets.  Is it true the targets they are hitting in this regard are above and beyond the price for which NAMA actually purchased the loans?  In other words, in the case of a loan with the average discount of 50%, were NAMA to sell it for 50% plus 1%, this 1% would be deemed by the agency to be a profit.  However, that is not a profit to the taxpayer and is not, in the Minister&rsquo;s own words, a commercial return for the taxpayer.  This is not what it said on the tin two or three years ago and this is an issue to which all Members must give genuine consideration.</P>
        <P>In addition, I fully agree with Senator Michael D&rsquo;Arcy in that I have a concern regarding the NAMA scheme for guaranteeing properties against future falls in market value.  Moreover, I am concerned about some properties NAMA has put forward as part of its pilot scheme.  In particular, in respect of one development in north Dublin listed on the NAMA website, I ask the Department of Finance to ascertain whether it can confirm the estate in question has pyrite.  I believe it does and while I do not wish to put this on the record of the House, I will give details to the Minister&rsquo;s officials after this debate has concluded.  Issues have arisen in this regard in which the Minister is involved and on today&rsquo;s Order of Business, I asked when the pyrite report will be issued.  This issue also is tied in to NAMA because unfortunately, many of those who live in unfinished estates, particularly on the east coast but throughout Ireland, have been hit with a double whammy of having pyrite issues within their unfinished estate.  I greatly hope the &euro;2 billion announced by NAMA first and foremost will be directed towards making them safe.  I acknowledge the former Minister of State, Deputy Penrose, did some good work at the outset to ensure estates were, at the very least, safe.</P>
        <P>However, to revert to the Bill itself, I do not agree with the premise that this information is commercially sensitive.  Incidentally, I am glad the Government included in its programme for Government a national property database, which I had sought during the lifetime of the previous Government.  My colleague, Senator Daly, has given a few examples demonstrating how an issue certainly exists with regard to how some commercial properties are being purchased and sold.  I do not suggest all of them but there is an issue in respect of some of them.  The Bill itself sets out clearly how this can be done, which would mean bringing in commercial property to this register if, at the very least, NAMA has an interest.  As my colleague has stated, NAMA does not control the properties for most of the loans it has and in more than 90% of cases, it has control of the loans themselves.  Consequently, it is possible to suggest that as the agency does not hold the property, it cannot release that information.  However, the bottom line is that for people to have greater confidence in NAMA, one must realise when the current system is not working as it should.  I might add I have confidence in those who work in the agency, which has some excellent people who are doing a tough job.  This Bill offers a way to ensure people know how and when decisions are made regarding the selling of properties or loans or properties involving loans held by NAMA and to ensure they go through a proper public process.  In the instances mentioned by Senator Daly in the Chamber today, it is clear no such proper auction or sale on those properties took place.</P>
        <P>I will conclude by noting the National Asset Management Agency Act 2009 is clear on what the agency should be doing.  Given his opening comments, I do not expect the Minister to accept this Bill.  However, should this Bill fail to proceed beyond this Stage after a division, the Fianna F&aacute;il grouping will continue to put forward suggestions as to how it believes it can make NAMA work better.  In this context, I ask the Minister to indicate what, in NAMA&rsquo;s view and his own view, constitutes a commercial return for the taxpayer.  Is it 50% plus 1% or is it 100% plus 1%, because I believe the taxpayer is being sold short in many instances?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdreClune"><NameTxt>Senator Deirdre Clune</NameTxt>
	<P>The recently-published report of the Comptroller and Auditor General is timely and makes for some stark reading.  It gives a summary of NAMA, which has been in operation for more than two years, during which time it has acquired loans from the five financial institutions at a face value of &euro;74 billion for approximately &euro;32 billion.  As Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien has just noted, it is immediately evident how the taxpayer is paying on both fronts.  I was also interested to read that completed properties account for 71% of its portfolio, properties in the course of development make up 9% and the remaining 20% consists of land.  I had thought the percentage of properties in the course of development would have been higher but that element constitutes just 9% of the loans or the properties that are in contention or discussion with NAMA.  In common with other Members, I have served on the Committee of Public Accounts and the Comptroller and Auditor General&rsquo;s report is beyond reproach.  The reports produced by the former Comptroller and Auditor General, Mr. John Buckley, always have been above reproach, as they have been thorough and have been carried out with expertise.  Mr. Buckley, like all Comptrollers and Auditors General, always has been straight and has been willing to say it as it is.  It is an important report and I note more such reports will be produced to facilitate tracking of what NAMA is doing and its present position for these Houses and the taxpayer.  There is also the summary of properties in receivership on the NAMA website, which is very useful.  I scanned it today and do so on a regular basis to see the extent of properties listed.  One can looks through one&rsquo;s own area or another one knows and see each property.  That is a very important step from which we can all benefit, in terms of properties in receivership and those ones on which receivers are working.</P>
        <P>In respect of the Bill before the House, NAMA was set up with the primary function of maximising a return for the taxpayers.  It is very important to keep that basic function to the forefront all the time, in that maximising value and any possible return from these properties for the taxpayer must be borne in mind.  As the Minister and others have noted, we must respect commercial sensitivities.  We all live in the real world and we understand that if properties or loans of properties are for sale there is information available and if one wishes to maximise the return one will not show one&rsquo;s hand.  I completely understand the desire to have as much transparency as possible and that all possible information be available but nonetheless, in order to protect the taxpayer&rsquo;s interest, there are certain issues concerning which it would be counterproductive to provide sensitive information.  I can see Senator Daly&rsquo;s position with regard to the Bill but at the same time, if an action blows a deal for the taxpayer we should not go down that route.</P>
        <P>As he stated in his speech, it is important to note &mdash; and welcome &mdash; that the Minister has regular meetings with the board of NAMA.  On coming into Government, he stressed to that organisation the importance of ensuring there is transparency and that it be increased and maximised wherever possible.  The database is part of that process and so are the regular meetings the Ministers has with NAMA in order to ensure that whatever information can be provided is provided.</P>
        <P>The recent announcement of the &euro;2 billion investment over the coming four years is very welcome.  We have heard a great deal in recent years, particularly from IDA Ireland in regard to would-be investors in this country, about the need to have third-generation office space, particularly in the Dublin region.  I am sure that much of this &euro;2 billion will go towards refurbishing such office space, which is needed if we are to sell this country abroad.  We need to able to say this is the building, it is there for the investor who wants to come and set up whatever operation we are trying to attract.  That type of office space is very important.  A shortage of it has been identified and this is expected to continue.  That &euro;2 billion is a very welcome development in addition to the funding of &euro;600 million that already came about for developing facilities to a point where they are marketable.</P>
        <P>I refer to the original figure of &euro;5 billion from NAMA.  We questioned the organisation on this when Mr. Daly attended Oireachtas committees during the past 12 months.  He always stated NAMA believed there was never a need to go to that &euro;5 billion.  Is the &euro;2 billion, recently announced, part of that package?</P>
        <P>We are in a difficult situation.  There is a lot of anger from people who borrowed excessively.  Money was made available to them but they seem to be writing down their loans in many cases in negotiation with NAMA.  We do not know the details of everything but we hear anecdotally there are people in this situation and it is adding to the public anger.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I am sorry if I forced the Senator to finish abruptly.   I call Senator Wilson.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Senator Diarmuid Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>I will take the one minute Senator Clune did not use.  I welcome the Minister to the House and compliment him on staying here for the duration of the debate.  I know he is a busy man.  I congratulate my colleague, Senator Daly, for bringing forward this legislation.  There seems to be some confusion among the Opposition&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGilroy"><NameTxt>Senator John Gilroy</NameTxt>
	<P>You are the Opposition.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Senator Diarmuid Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;as to what it is about.  I listened with particular interest to Senator Coghlan&rsquo;s contribution and could not disagree with any part of it because it concurred exactly with what Senator Daly is trying to enact in this short Bill.  For the benefit of Senator Coghlan, the Bill is: &ldquo;An Act to provide that, in the interests of transparency, all relevant details of loans, properties or other assets offered for sale by or with the approval of NAMA or the Irish Bank Resolution Corporation be available to the public by means of publication on a website&rdquo;.  That is all it attempts to do and I hope the Government may change its mind in this regard.</P>
        <P>As an auctioneer, Senator Coghlan will appreciate, along with other colleagues, that transparency is very important, both for the auctioneer and the person selling the property and also for the person buying it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>One is an agent for the vendor.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Senator Diarmuid Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>There should be no perceived conflict of interest and everything should be above board and seen to be so.  This legislation is about transparency and affording the Irish taxpayer who owns NAMA the opportunity to see exactly what NAMA has for sale and, ultimately, while not getting involved in the negotiation, to discover who bought the property.  That is what this small piece of legislation is about and I do not see how anybody could disagree with it.</P>
        <P>That is all I have to say on this matter.  Perhaps the Government would consider accepting the legislation.  My colleague, Senator Byrne, a learned lawyer, does not see any conflict between this Bill and the Constitution and, as a layperson, I tend to agree with him.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I call on Senator Daly to conclude.  He has four minutes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank all my colleagues for their input and the Minister for his reply.  I am not happy that the Government has come up with a number of reasons that, in themselves, are at variance with some of the facts.  As I and colleagues have outlined, NAMA proposed a website six months after I proposed it but it is limiting its one only to properties of which it has taken title control.  That represents a very small fraction of all the loans it has given out.  My proposal is that NAMA would put all properties it is allowing to be sold onto the website.</P>
        <P>What we must understand here is that section 35 of the NAMA Act asked the organisation to set up a system whereby all its assets would be sold, whether they were property or loans.  That was the legislation; it was our intent.  Within that, NAMA had to come up with its process within three months.  That process is the same as that for selling a State asset, which must be done by tender or public auction.  The reason I asked the Attorney General to come to the House is that I cannot understand why NAMA is not selling the property and the loans under its control as laid down by the NAMA Act and as signed off by the Minister, Deputy Noonan&rsquo;s colleague.  Why is NAMA not doing that?  We have legal opinion on both my side and NAMA.s side.  It claims it does not have to do this while my legal opinion states it should do so but is simply not doing so.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The result is a lack of transparency.  I do not accept the point about commercial sensitivity.  Senator Clune would be aware of this from her own constituency.  How is it in the best interest of the taxpayer that 450 acres of land in Cork was sold without anybody knowing about it?  How is that in the interests of anybody?  It is only in the interest of the people who bought it quietly from the bank, with the agreement of NAMA.  Colleagues have pointed out that I have not produced the evidence.  I have produced evidence, namely, the property on Baker Street.  The company which bought it said that in one year the value had gone up 54% from 2010 to 2011.  That can only suggest that it was undersold in the first place.  Commercial property in Baker Street, London, did not increase by 54% in one calendar year.  What also happened was that the people who had taken out a loan of &euro;49 million were part of the profit share on the sale.  It is stated by British Land which is now in control of that property that NAMA and Bank of Ireland agreed to all this.  The Irish taxpayer has suffered a loss of &euro;28.2 million on one sale.</P>
        <P>I am talking about simple transparency.  Like Senator Coghlan, I am an auctioneer.  If every property for sale by banks which had been given a loan by NAMA was put on a website there could be no doubt.  Would the taxpayer lose if there was a website?  The taxpayer is losing already to the tune of &euro;28 million on one sale.  I will give the evidence to anyone.  Let no one come into the House and say &ldquo;Mark Daly did not produce evidence&rdquo;.  I am presenting the evidence.  Senator Coghlan is welcome to talk to the individual or to anyone.  When I asked about this at Bank of Ireland it referred to commercial sensitivity.  However, the NAMA Act says that every property&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Has the Senator his own correspondence with NAMA about this property?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I not only have correspondence, I have had meetings with it.  It said it had nothing to do with it.  British Land states that NAMA had given agreement for the sale to go ahead.  McAleer and Rushe which owes the Irish taxpayer money will make a profit from this land even though it still owes us &euro;28 million.  I ask Senator Coghlan to outline how that is in the best interests of taxpayers.  This was not done in an open and transparent manner.  If it had been we would have go the upside.  When Senator Coghlan reads this and he gives me a comprehensive reply I will write an apology.  However, my apology will not be coming his way.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put.</P>
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 17; N&iacute;l, 24.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading>
        <YesVote pid="SeanDBarrett">Barrett, Sean D.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="ThomasByrne">Byrne, Thomas.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnCrown">Crown, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DavidCullinane">Cullinane, David.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarkDaly">Daly, Mark.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="TerryLeyden">Leyden, Terry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarcMacSharry">MacSharry, Marc.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaschalMooney">Mooney, Paschal.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="RonanMullen">Mullen, R&oacute;n&aacute;n.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DarraghOBrien">O&rsquo;Brien, Darragh.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="NedOSullivan">O&rsquo;Sullivan, Ned.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="TrevorOClochartaigh">&Oacute; Clochartaigh, Trevor.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianODomhnaill">&Oacute; Domhnaill, Brian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AverilPower">Power, Averil.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</YesVote>
        <NHeading>N&iacute;l</NHeading>
        <NoVote pid="IvanaBacik">Bacik, Ivana.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulBradford">Bradford, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TerryBrennan">Brennan, Terry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DeirdreClune">Clune, Deirdre.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulCoghlan">Coghlan, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelComiskey">Comiskey, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MartinConway">Conway, Martin.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MauriceCummins">Cummins, Maurice.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JimDarcy">D&rsquo;Arcy, Jim.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelWDArcy">D&rsquo;Arcy, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnGilroy">Gilroy, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JimmyHarte">Harte, Jimmy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JamesHeffernan">Heffernan, James.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="LorraineHiggins">Higgins, Lorraine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CaitKeane">Keane, C&aacute;it.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnKelly">Kelly, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DenisLandy">Landy, Denis.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MarieMoloney">Moloney, Marie.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TonyMulcahy">Mulcahy, Tony.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelMullins">Mullins, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CatherineNoone">Noone, Catherine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PatONeill">O&rsquo;Neill, Pat.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TomSheahan">Sheahan, Tom.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnWhelan">Whelan, John.</NoVote>
        <Tellers>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Mark Daly and Diarmuid Wilson; N&iacute;l, Senators Ivana Bacik and Paul Coghlan.</Tellers>
        <Decision>Question declared lost.</Decision>
      </Vote>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters</Title>
    <Sect LHead="Social Welfare" RHead="Benefits"> 
      <sTitle>Social Welfare Benefits</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Ar aghaidh leis an Seanad&oacute;ir, t&aacute; ceithre n&oacute;im&eacute;ad aige.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P>Cuirim c&eacute;ad f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute;im bu&iacute;och go bhfuil s&eacute; anseo, ach t&aacute; d&iacute;om&aacute; orm nach f&eacute;idir leis an Aire sinsearach teacht isteach don cheist seo, mar is ceist &iacute; seo at&aacute; ag d&eacute;anamh tinnis do go leor daoine faoi l&aacute;thair.  T&aacute; an-chuid cainte ar na t&aacute;irsigh freisin maidir leis na hathruith a bhaineann le li&uacute;ntais c&iacute;osa.  Tuigeann muide go gcaithfidh an Rialtas iarrracht a dh&eacute;anamh an ch&iacute;os at&aacute; &aacute; &iacute;oc le tiarna&iacute; tal&uacute;n agus mar sin de a &iacute;sli&uacute; agus tuigeann muid go bhfuil c&iacute;osanna an-ard &aacute; &iacute;oc i gc&aacute;sanna &aacute;irithe agus nach c&oacute;ir go mbeadh siadsan le n-&iacute;oc ag an St&aacute;t.  Ach, t&aacute; fadhb againn leis an meicn&iacute;ocht at&aacute; t&oacute;gtha ag an St&aacute;t le sin a chur i bhfeidhm, is &eacute; sin na tion&oacute;nta&iacute; at&aacute; sna tithe a chur ag marg&aacute;nta&iacute;ocht.</P>
        <P>I raise the issue of the change to the rates for the rent allowance supplement.  Although we agree in principle with the idea that landlords certainly need to be tackled on the issue of the rents under this scheme, there are serious issues with the way the scheme is administered currently.  The tenants are being forced to renegotiate their leases with landlords.  This is a disastrous situation for many people.  Sinn F&eacute;in has been contacted by many people in Galway and we held a meeting on Friday evening.  The tenants are finding it impossible to renegotiate and the landlords are playing hard ball and they are not willing to move on the rates.  The Government should have used another mechanism.</P>
        <P>This is current Government policy and Sinn F&eacute;in disagrees with the method of its implementation.  I know of one family in Knocknacarra in Galway city which was informed two weeks ago by letter from a representative of the Department of Social Protection that the new level of rental support was being introduced.  As a result of this new rate, the family&rsquo;s supplement was being lowered from &euro;800 a month to &euro;700.  This will not cover the rent for their house and there is no accommodation available in the area at a suitable rent.  The Department has stated the review of this case was based on figures from <i>daft.ie</i>, and the CSO.  However, neither of those websites show properties in that area for that level of rent.  The children attend a local school and both parents are unemployed.  Before the end of last month, 31 May, they were forced to write to their landlord to say they would have to break the lease agreement and leave the house.  They do not have any alternative accommodation and they will be homeless for all practical reasons.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I ask if an appeals system is available for such cases where the rent is more than the relevant limit.  The Department&rsquo;s website states that in some cases rent supplement can be paid at the discretion of the Department&rsquo;s representative, formerly known as the community welfare officer, CWO, where the rent is over the relevant limit.  There are three circumstances.  For example, if a member of the household has special housing needs, for example, a disabled person in specially adapted accommodation; if a tenant can pay the rent by taking up employment the rent supplement at a higher rate can be paid for a short period of six to eight weeks; and if there are other exceptional circumstances.  I ask for clarification as regards circumstances.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The decrease in the rate for rent supplement will cause some tenants to default on the lease agreement and they will be in a very precarious legal situation.  It will also mean they will have to leave their home and force them back on the local authority homeless list to be accommodated in some other manner at a cost to the State.  The system needs to be reviewed because tenants are being forced into a very awkward and unfair position.  I ask for clarification about the appeals process because these people need a remedy for an immediate problem. Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an fheagra.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPerry"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy John Perry</NameTxt>
	<P>I will do my best, Senator.</P>
        <P>I am taking this Adjournment matter on behalf of the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, who sends her apologies for not being in a position to reply to the Senator.  The purpose of the rent supplement scheme is to provide short-term income support to assist with reasonable accommodation costs of eligible people living in private rented accommodation who are unable to provide for their accommodation costs from their own resources and who do not have accommodation available to them from another source.  The overall aim is to provide short term assistance and not to act as an alternative to the other social housing schemes operated by the Exchequer.</P>
        <P>New maximum rent limits came into force on 1 January 2012 and are in place until June 2013.  These new limits are in line with the most up to date market data available.  The emphasis of the rent limit review was to ensure that maximum value for money for tenants and the taxpayer was achieved while at the same time ensuring that people on rent supplement are not priced out of the market for private rented accommodation.</P>
        <P>Rent supplement is subject to a limit on the amount of rent that an applicant may incur.  The general practice is that rent supplement is not paid where the rent is above the relevant limit.  However, regulations provide that a supplement may be paid in cases where the circumstances so warrant.  Guidelines are issued to determining officers to provide guidance as to the circumstances in which a rent supplement may be paid where the relevant limits are exceeded.  The guidelines are as follows.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">8 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P Just="Left">Where there are special housing needs related to exceptional circumstances, in particular, for example, a person with a disability in specially-adapted accommodation or homeless persons whose housing needs cannot be met within the standard terms of the rent supplement scheme etc; and where the person concerned is entitled to an income disregard and has sufficient income to meet his or her basic needs after paying rent, taking into account the appropriate rate of rent supplement that is otherwise payable in the case.  Sufficient income in this context means the relevant basic supplementary welfare allowance rate less the prescribed minimum contribution to rent; where the tenant will be in a position to re-assume responsibility for his or her rent within a short period.  For this purpose, a guideline period of no longer than six to eight weeks is suggested but where there are exceptional circumstances, an extension up to a total of 12 weeks may be allowed; where an existing claim is under review, the rent paid to the landlord is in excess of the prescribed limit and the lease agreement is not for immediate renewal, staff may use their discretionary powers and pay rent supplement based on the rate quoted within the lease agreement for up to 13 weeks.  They may further use their discretion, and extend the 13 week period  in circumstances where the lease agreement will expire within a reasonable timeframe, or; the termination of the lease agreement may give rise to onerous penalties payable by the applicant, or; the minimum notice within the lease agreement, that a tenant must provide a landlord to vacate the property, is in excess of the 13 week period.  Appeals officers examine each case to determine the most appropriate response having regard to the particular circumstances of the case.</P>
        <P>I suggest the Senator advise the family to go to the local appeals officer who has discretion and their very clear circumstances may be facilitated.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TrevorOClochartaigh"><NameTxt>Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the clarification provided by the Minister of State.  It is important to note that this is a scheme which provides a short-term response but it will not be suitable because the local authority housing is not available for people who are in the scheme.  Directors of services in the local authorities I deal with are saying they are being forced by the Government policy towards private rental accommodation because houses will not be built to deal with the demand.  This gives a short-term reprieve and I welcome the clarification but it will not be a solution to the issue and I call on the Minister of State to talk to the Minister for Social Protection to ask her to review this policy as it is a very flawed policy which is putting undue pressure on tenants and it will not solve the problem.  It will force people out of their homes and children out of their schools.  It will create ghettos in areas where only people of a certain class or those on social welfare are corralled into certain areas of cities.  I call on the Minister for Social Protection to completely review this policy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPerry"><NameTxt>Deputy John Perry</NameTxt>
	<P>I assure the Senator that I will speak to the Minister for Social Protection and I will bring the file to her attention.</P>
        <P>The point was made clearly.  The rent supplement scheme is reviewed constantly and I have no doubt the Minister will take on board the Senator&rsquo;s recommendations.</P>
        <P>The Senator questioned the availability of local authority housing.  Galway may be the exception, but in many counties private landlords are happy to facilitate persons in receipt of the rent supplement as they would prefer to have a tenant in their vacant property.  However, I hear the point the Senator is making and will bring it to the Minister&rsquo;s attention.</P>
        <P>I hope the short-term measures will accommodate the Senator&rsquo;s concerns.</P>
      </Speaker>
    </Sect>
  <Sect LHead="Redundancy" RHead="Payments"> 
    <sTitle>Redundancy Payments</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I have a very short question.  I ask the Minister to outline the details of an evaluation carried out by the Government prior to the introduction of the new redundancy arrangements, as they place a major onus on small businesses dealing with redundancies.  It certainly does not help job creation.  It acts as a deterrent to anybody considering employing a person.</P>
        <P>Will the Minister outline the scheme and its effects on job creation?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPerry"><NameTxt>Deputy John Perry</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank Senator Daly for raising this very important issue.  I am taking this Adjournment matter on behalf of the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, who sends her apologies for not being present to respond in person to the Senator.  The purpose of the redundancy payments scheme is to compensate workers, under the Redundancy Payments Acts, for the loss of their jobs by reason of redundancy.  An eligible employee is entitled to two weeks statutory redundancy payment for every year of service, plus a bonus week.  Compensation is based on the worker&rsquo;s length of reckonable service and reckonable weekly remuneration, subject to a ceiling of &euro;600 per week.  Employees must have at least two years&rsquo; service to be eligible for a redundancy payment.</P>
        <P>It is the responsibility of the employer to pay statutory redundancy to all their eligible employees.  An employer who pays statutory redundancy payments to its employees is then entitled to a rebate from the State.  I am sure the Senator is aware of these provisions.  Where an employer can prove to the satisfaction of the Department that it is unable to pay the statutory redundancy to its employees the Department will make lump sum payments directly to the employees and will seek to recover the debt from the employer.</P>
        <P>Both the redundancy and insolvency payments scheme transferred to the Department of Social Protection in January 2011.  Payments under both schemes are made from the Social Insurance Fund, SIF, which is currently in deficit.</P>
        <P>While the SIF is constituted primarily from employer&rsquo;s contributions, the taxpayer&rsquo;s contribution is also significant.  Significant amounts have been paid out in redundancy rebates to employers from the SIF in recent years.  The total amount paid out in redundancy rebates to employers was &euro;152.2 million in 2006; &euro;167.4 million in 2007; &euro;161.8 million in 2008; &euro;247.9 million in 2009; &euro;373.2 million in 2010; and &euro;185.3 million in 2011.</P>
        <P>The deficit in the Social Insurance Fund is of significant concern at present and it is not considered that the country should continue to borrow money to plug the hole in the SIF in order to fund the cost of making people redundant &mdash; often from very profitable companies.</P>
        <P>In the context of the 2012 budget, the Government decided that the 60% level of rebate was not sustainable in the current economic climate.  As a result, the rebate was reduced to 15% for cases where the date of dismissal for the purposes of redundancy occurs after 1 January 2012.  It is expected that this measure will save &euro;81 million in 2012.</P>
        <P>It has been acknowledged that this may cause difficulties for employers, and I appreciate the Senator is making this point, but it should be noted that redundancy rebate payments to employers are not common in many EU states or other jurisdictions.  For example, in the UK the redundancy payment is funded by the employer and there is no recovery from the state.  In Sweden there is no statutory system of redundancy payments from employers while in Spain the employer cannot claim back any amount from the state.  This new arrangement brings Ireland more closely into line with practice elsewhere.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>An bhfuil an Seanad&oacute;ir s&aacute;sta?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>As the Minister of State will be aware, it was stated in the reply that people were made redundant &ldquo;often from very profitable companies&rdquo;, but at times they are seeking their redundancy payments from companies that are not profitable.  This is militating against the creation of jobs.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State is responding on behalf of the Minister for Social Protection and has been given the reply.  However, I asked if a detailed evaluation was carried out prior to the introduction of the change in the scheme.  I think the departmental officials did not read the question I asked, because I was looking for a cost benefit analysis and the impact on job creation, which should be done prior to the introduction of new measures.</P>
        <P>I sincerely thank the Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Perry, for coming into the House to respond to the Adjournment, but unfortunately the reply he was given was not appropriate to the question I raised.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPerry"><NameTxt>Deputy John Perry</NameTxt>
	<P>I can answer that question.  It is evident that an evaluation was conducted &mdash; the scheme cost &euro;373.2 million in 2010, and if one considers that 1.8 million people are currently working in Ireland, of which 700,000 work in small companies, 137,000 work directly in IDA and an equivalent number in Enterprise Ireland companies, it is a question of affordability.  Unfortunately, the evaluation of the Social Insurance Fund found that the tills are empty.</P>
        <P>I fully accept that reducing the rebate to employers from 60% to 15% puts great pressure on small companies.  The sad reality is that because we are borrowing from the IMF, it leaves the Government with few choices.  An evaluation was carried out by the Department of the Finance which found that the scheme was no longer sustainable.  The bottom line is that the scheme cost &euro;247.9 million in 2009 and &euro;373.2 million in 2010, which is a significant amount.</P>
        <P>The backbone of our economy is the 200,000 companies employing fewer than ten people and giving employment to 700,000 people.  The action plan for jobs is focused on increasing the number of jobs in SMEs by creating 100,000 new jobs by 2016.  While the reduction of the redundancy rebate will have an impact, the Government has alternative schemes to encourage people to create jobs.  The job of government is to make people employable and to encourage enterprise.  The Government is incentivising companies to create jobs through the action plan for jobs, the lowering of the VAT rate, the reduction of the PRSI in the expectation, as the Taoiseach stated, that 50,000 small companies would each created one job at little or no cost to the State.</P>
        <P>In 2010 it was costing the taxpayer &euro;7 million each week to fund the rebate of the redundancy payment from the Social Insurance Fund.  That is not sustainable.  My job as Minister of State with responsibility for small business is to encourage employers and give them ten reasons to create a job and not ten reasons to make people redundant.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">When I asked for an evaluation, I did not simply mean an evaluation in terms of pounds, shillings and pence but an evaluation of the measures to create jobs.  If an employer is thinking of employing an additional person and then looks at the changes to the redundancy scheme, it is aware it will cost it a fortune to let the person go.  This is another barrier to creating jobs.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister has given a comprehensive reply.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for his response and I appreciate that he came into the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister, who is always welcome in this House.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 8.10 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 7 June 2012.</adjournment>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" /></Sect>
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
