<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="25" Month="Oct" Year="1928" Vol="10" No="32" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 25 Deireadh Fómhair 1928" DateEnglish="Thursday, 25 October 1928" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1349">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1349" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT" RHead="No. 7) BILL, 1928&mdash;REPORT">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT No. 7) BILL, 1928&mdash;REPORT.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be considered on Report&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT" RHead="No. 8) BILL, 1928&mdash;REPORT">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT No. 8) BILL, 1928&mdash;REPORT.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be considered on Report&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SUSPENSION" RHead="OF STANDING ORDERS">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SUSPENSION OF STANDING ORDERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. GUINNESS Mr. GUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That the Standing Orders be suspended for the purpose of taking the remaining stage of the Constitution (Amendment No. 8) Bill, 1928, to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT" RHead="No. 8) BILL, 1928&mdash;FINAL STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT No. 8) BILL, 1928&mdash;FINAL STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That this Bill be received for final consideration and do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT" RHead="No. 9) BILL, 1928&mdash;REPORT">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT No. 9) BILL, 1928&mdash;REPORT.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be considered on Report&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SUSPENSION" RHead="OF STANDING ORDERS">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SUSPENSION OF STANDING ORDERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. GUINNESS Mr. GUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;That the Standing Orders be suspended for the purpose of taking <Col N="1350" /> the remaining stage of the Constitution (Amendment No. 9) Bill, 1928, to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT" RHead="No. 9) BILL, 1928&mdash;FINAL STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT No. 9) BILL, 1928&mdash;FINAL STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That this Bill be received for final consideration and do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SEANAD" RHead="ELECTORAL BILL, 1928&mdash;REPORT">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SEANAD ELECTORAL BILL, 1928&mdash;REPORT.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be considered on Report&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SUSPENSION" RHead="OF STANDING ORDERS">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SUSPENSION OF STANDING ORDERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. GUINNESS Mr. GUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That the Standing Orders be suspended for the purpose of taking the remaining stage of the Seanad Electoral Bill, 1928, to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SEANAD ELECTORAL" RHead="BILL, 1928&mdash;FINAL STAGE">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - SEANAD ELECTORAL BILL, 1928&mdash;FINAL STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That this Bill be received for final consideration and do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PUBLIC BUSINESS. - FORESTRY BILL," RHead="1928&mdash;REPORT (RESUMED)">
    <Title>PUBLIC BUSINESS. - FORESTRY BILL, 1928&mdash;REPORT (RESUMED).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The Report Stage of this Bill was allowed to stand over so as to obtain the Government's views with regard to amendment No. 14 in the name of Senator Colonel Moore and amendment No. 18 in the name of Senator Bagwell.  The following were the amendments moved:&mdash;</P>
      <P>14.&mdash;Section 8.  To add at the end of the section a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(4) In every case in which a licence granted under this section <Col N="1351" /> contains a condition of the kind specified in sub-section (2) of this section, the Minister shall, on demand, cause to be supplied and delivered to the licensee young trees of the kind specified and to the number required, free of cost.&rdquo;&mdash; (Senator Colonel Moore.)</P>
    <P>18.&mdash;New section.  Before Section 9 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;9.&mdash;(1) When a prohibition order has been made or a licence withheld the Minister shall state in writing his reasons for the making of such order or the withholding of such licence.</P>
    <P>(2) When a prohibition order has been made or a licence withheld an appeal shall lie to the Judicial Commissioner who shall determine whether under all the circumstances of the case the reasons given by the Minister justify the making of such order or the withholding of such licence.</P>
    <P>(3) Should the Minister make a prohibition order or withhold a licence with a view to the preservation of scenic beauty compensation shall be awarded to the owner and the amount of such compensation if not fixed by agreement shall be determined by the Judicial Commissioner.&rdquo;&mdash;(Senator Bagwell.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. BENNETT Mr. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Colonel Moore is not very strong, and is not able to attend the meeting of the House to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator gave his reasons already in moving the amendment and the Minister will reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan) MINISTER for AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for AGRICULTURE (Mr. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose dealing in my reply with the two amendments, and I would ask the Seanad not to insist on their insertion in the Bill. With regard to Senator Colonel Moore's amendment, there are a number of detailed departmental objections to it.  One is that we find, as a matter of practice, that whenever the Department of Agriculture supplies anything, unless it turns out to be 100 <Col N="1352" /> per cent., there is a demand afterwards for compensation.  For instance, the Department might supply quite good trees, but if they were not properly planted and attended to the person who got them would afterwards come to the Department and say that they were no good.  That may not appeal very much to Senators, but we find that that always occurs where a State Department supplies anything.  It always leads to endless correspondence.  Apparently, persons who get anything from a State Department for nothing, always seem to think that they can treat it as they like and afterwards get compensation if the results are not to their satisfaction.  That reason, as I have stated, is not likely to appeal very strongly to the Seanad.  I suggest that if this amendment, or any amendment like it, were passed it would inevitably give rise to a most unsatisfactory position, because it means that where a replanting condition is imposed that the person who gets the licence, with that condition imposed, gets the trees free of cost.  I do not want to be misunderstood, but I think it is inevitable in the course of administration over a large number of years, that such an amendment as that would give rise to all sorts of abuses.  The temptation, for instance, to refuse a licence rather than supply trees which may not be readily available to the Department at the time, is bound to be great, and if Senators will consider it, even if this particular section were inserted in the Bill, there are at least a hundred and one ways of getting round it. The head of the Forestry Branch or a Minister could easily get round it if they wished to do so, and for that reason, if for no other, I think the section should not be inserted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Exactly the same considerations apply, but with even stronger force, to Senator Bagwell's amendment, because the Senator's amendment comes to this: that where a licence is withheld, and where it is stated that it is withheld so as to prevent the person from cutting trees possessing some scenic value,  compensation should be given to the applicant for the licence.  That also could be <Col N="1353" /> evaded in a hundred and one ways if it were wished to do so.  In addition to the abuses that there might be on the side of the Department administering the Act, there could be very grave abuses from the point of view of people, say, in Kerry or Wicklow. Supposing that section were inserted, is it not inevitable that many people would come along with an application to cut trees which they never intended to cut?  Of course, there is a way out of that&mdash;to refuse the licence, not to put in a replanting condition, and not to give the scenic consideration as the reason.  I suggest that, if the section is inserted, it is bound to lead to abuses.  People who never intend to cut trees around the Lakes of Killarney or in Wicklow and other places will come along applying for leave to do so.  They will not get the leave, and if it is stated that the trees are for a scenic purpose they must get compensation and they are bound to take advantage of that.  It might be said it is not dishonest on their part, but it is not a particularly moral transaction.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>It offends against public morality.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, to some extent. It is also an invitation to the Department to meet it in that way.  If these two provisions are inserted they are bound to lead to abuses.  I suggest that what Senators have really in mind is met by a section in the Forestry Act of 1919, which enables the Forestry Branch to give grants or loans for afforestation purposes.  Sub-section (3) of Section 3 of that Act is very wide.  It states that, subject to any direction which may be given by the Treasury, the Commissioners&mdash;in our case it would be the Forestry Branch&mdash;shall have power to do the following things:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(d) Make advances by way of grant or by way of loan, or partly in one way and partly in the other, and upon such terms and subject to such conditions as they think fit, to persons (including local authorities) in respect of the afforestation (including the replanting) of land belonging to those persons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1354" /> The proviso to that section limited that power, and reads as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Provided that any advance by way of a grant under this section shall be subject to the condition that any profits resulting from the operations in respect of which the grant was made shall, after allowing for a return to the owner, of four per cent. compound interest on the cost incurred by him (exclusive of the amount of the grant), be charged with the repayment to the forestry fund of the amount of the grant together with compound interest at four per cent.</P>
    <P>Under the Bill before us in the Schedules a number of sections are repealed and that particular proviso is repealed.  The Treasury have power to make advances to anybody for afforestation purposes.  They may make them without any condition as to repayment.  That, I submit, is evidence of our bona fides, evidence that when there is sufficient money available for afforestation it is the intention of the Government to put a forestry policy into operation.  I suggest to Senators that that is very much the better way of dealing with the particular problem which they have in mind in connection with those two amendments, and a more satisfactory way than it could be dealt with if these two amendments were passed.  I would ask the Seanad not to pass them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="MARQUESS of LANSDOWNE MARQUESS of LANSDOWNE">
      <NameTxt>MARQUESS of LANSDOWNE</NameTxt>
      <P>What would be the position of anyone who wanted to cut a tree and to whom a replanting condition was attached? The Minister's Department will wash their hands of it altogether.  Will such a person have to make an independent application to the Treasury for a grant?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>No, the Forestry Branch would have to have the prior consent of the Treasury.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there a fund at present at the disposal of the Forestry Branch?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a Forestry Fund which has to be voted annually.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1355" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="MARQUESS of LANSDOWNE MARQUESS of LANSDOWNE">
      <NameTxt>MARQUESS of LANSDOWNE</NameTxt>
      <P>Would he be dealing with the same Department or another Department?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>He would be dealing with the Forestry Branch exclusively in the same way as landowners deal with the Land Commission.  In the Land Acts there are certain limitations as to what the Land Commission may do without the consent of the Treasury. The way that is managed in practice is that an Act is passed, certain general principles are agreed upon between the Land Commission and the Department of Finance, and within the limitations agreed upon the Land Commission proceed to deal with the money they have, and which is voted to them every year. In the same way in the Forestry Branch if it is decided to put the forestry policy into operation at the beginning of the year there will be discussions between the Department of Finance and the Forestry Branch with a view to seeing how far the Forestry Branch may go with the money available, but once the initial consent is obtained it would be the Forestry Branch that would exercise its discretion as to how the money would be distributed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. BENNETT Mr. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to amendment 14, the explanation given by the Minister makes it clear to my mind that the condition sought can be reasonably met.  I do not think the amendment should be pressed.</P>
      <P>Amendment 14, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. BAGWELL Mr. BAGWELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAGWELL</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is under some misapprehension as to what I had in mind.  What I had in view would not be met by the operations of the Forestry Act.  What I had in mind was a wood in a celebrated beauty spot, and I was contemplating the refusal of a licence to cut the wood, not on the grounds that the owner refused to replant, but on the grounds that it would be destroying a national asset&mdash;a place of scenic beauty.  If the Minister prohibits the owner from cutting the trees because it would be to the national detriment, how is the owner to be compensated? It is not a question of a condition of replanting, but the possibility of his being refused leave to cut his wood <Col N="1356" /> altogether, because that wood was a national asset from the scenic point of view.  Perhaps the Minister would explain whether he has examined that aspect of the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister dealt with that.  He said that if you have a provision of that kind you at once give enormous temptation to people to apply to cut trees who do not intend to cut them down, and who know their application would be rejected on the grounds of scenic beauty and who, therefore, would get compensation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. BAGWELL Mr. BAGWELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAGWELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I recognise that, but I think if the Bill is passed without dealing with the point I have raised it is a very unsatisfactory position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister were satisfied that there was a bona fide intention to cut a wood I think there ought to be compensation.  It is difficult to follow the purposes for which a free grant can be obtained under the Forestry Act.  Would a case such as is contemplated by Senator Bagwell's amendment come within the purpose of the grant?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. GUINNESS Mr. GUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Forestry Branch when considering the allocation of its funds at the beginning of the year never takes into consideration compensation to individuals.  It would be based on the reafforestation requirements of the Department which have recently been extensive, and no provision is made for cases in which compensation is asked because a licence is withheld for reasons of scenic beauty, or for furnishing money for the replanting of woods that have been cut down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. BAGWELL Mr. BAGWELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAGWELL</NameTxt>
      <P>What I fear is that a licence might be withheld for reasons of scenic beauty and a man might be absolutely prohibited from cutting his trees.  If there were a limitation in the power to withhold a licence, and if a licence could not be withheld if the owner was prepared to replant, then I would be satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there is a distinction between the two amendments. <Col N="1357" /> and there is no doubt about it that the objection I have stated against this amendment is there.  Senator Brown made a suggestion with regard to the Minister giving compensation where the application is bona fide.  If you put in those words how can you test the bona fides of the applicant?  That is the difficulty I am in.  There is no doubt that if you pass the amendment in its present form it will invite applications from people who are not bona fide.  Of course, there may be a way to meet it.  I admit that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Would you be satisfied, Senator Bagwell, if your amendment ran in this way:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Should the Minister make a prohibition order, or withhold a licence with a view to the preservation of <Col N="1358" /> scenic beauty, compensation may be awarded by the Minister if satisfied with the bona fides of the applicant, and the amount of such compensation if not fixed by agreement shall be determined by an official arbitrator appointed under the Acquisition of Land (Assessment of Compensation) Act, 1919&rdquo;?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. BAGWELL Mr. BAGWELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAGWELL</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I consider that a reasonable compromise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that.</P>
      <P>Amendment, as suggested, put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That concludes the Report Stage.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 3.30 p.m. until 12 o'clock on Friday, October 26th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>