<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="1" Month="Feb" Year="1989" Vol="121" No="17" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 1 Feabhra 1989" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 1 February 1989" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1885">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1885" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Gerry Reynolds that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Agriculture and Food to give a direction in writing to An Teagasc under section 19 of the Agriculture (Research, Training and Advice) Act, 1988 in relation to carrying on the specified service of the Agricultural Research Station in Ballinamore, County Leitrim, which is due to be closed.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Nuala Fennell of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for Health to acknowledge that there is an obligation on the Government to give special financial assistance to haemophiliacs who have developed AIDS or are HIV positive, through blood transfusion given prior to 1986.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator John A. Murphy of the following matter:</P>
      <P>The recent large increase in the number of experiments on animals.</P>
      <P>I also received notice from Senator Brendan Ryan of the following matter:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1886" /> The need for the Minister for Health to investigate the reasons for the increase in the rate of infant mortality.</P>
    <P>I regard the matters raised by Senators Reynolds, Fennell, Murphy and Brendan Ryan as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matter raised by Senator Reynolds and it will be taken from 8 p.m. to 8.30 p.m. Senators Fennell, Murphy and Ryan may give notice for another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is intended to take Items Nos. 1, 2 and 3 today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I clarify that we are just taking Second Stage of Item No. 2 today?  Secondly, will the Leader of the House inform us when it is proposed to introduce legislation dealing with the proposed university status of NIHE, Limerick and NIHE, Dublin and whether this will involve consequent changes in the university representation in the Seanad?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a bit wide for the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>Very pertinent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>May I also ask the Leader of the House if he has any information on the establishment of the Anglo-Irish parliamentary tier?  What progress has been made on that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>When will it be possible to take Item No. 20 on the Order Paper.  That motion has been there for almost a year.  Many people, especially in the rural areas, are quite alarmed and do not know what to expect from the unseasonal weather.  The European Community have recently taken note of this problem&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not taking it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that but could I have an indication of when it will <Col N="1887" /> be possible to take time for this very important item?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan" hpid="Mr. B. Ryan Mr. B. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Leader of the House about Item No. 12 on the Order Paper, a Bill in the name of myself and other Independent Members entitled Register of Members of the Oireachtas Interests Bill, 1989.  I would like the Leader of the House, to accommodate me and the other Members by allowing that Bill to be printed which entails a simple motion to that effect.  If at some stage, either tomorrow or next week, he would agree to that I would be most grateful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Leader of the House what progress, if any, has been made on a proposal made many times in this House about the establishment of a joint Oireachtas committee on foreign affairs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Leader of the House if he would give Government time for Item No. 9 on the Order Paper which is the Bill dealing with abolition of the death penalty.  It is a very simple, straightforward Bill which should be non-partisan and non-contentious in political terms.  I know that Amnesty International this year are going to launch a special campaign to abolish the death penalty and I would be interested in the Government's response to this Bill which is in my name and the other Independent Senators.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>In response to Senator Manning, yes, it is intended that today we take only Second Stage of Item No. 2.  There will have to be changes because of the status that was conferred upon the two new universities recently.  I am sure the consequent changes in regard to representation in this House will be taken into account when the actual universities have been formally set up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the question of the Anglo-Irish parliamentary tier, I will query the relevant Minister on that item.  On Item No. 20, I <Col N="1888" /> would suggest that if the Leas-Chathaoirleach feels very strongly about that, he can put it down as the next Fine Gael motion to come before the House.</P>
    <P>The question of the establishment of a joint Oireachtas committee on foreign affairs has come up on many occasions in the House.  I do not think there is any indication that this committee will be set up but I will speak to the Tánaiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs on that matter.</P>
    <P>It is not intended to give Government time to Item No. 9.  As regards Item No. 12, I can discuss with Senator Ryan the relevant time to introduce that item.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Criminal Law (Rape) (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1988: Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Criminal Law (Rape) (Amendment) Bill, 1988: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say at the outset that we in Fine Gael welcome this Bill in principle.  We see it as an expression by the Government of their concern in regard to the very serious problem of rape.  We do have reservations about a number of aspects of the Bill and we have some proposals for change which we will be putting forward in the course of the debate.</P>
      <P>There are few more serious or more horrible crimes than that of rape.  The act of rape is a savage violation of one human being by another which, unfortunately, appears to be increasing in both the number and in the variety of permutations. It is primarily an act of violence using sex as a weapon and is without doubt one of the most heinous and repugnant of crimes.  We as legislators must do everything possible to ensure that this most primitive and personal violation is not just curbed but as far as possible is eradicated from our society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Rape is not, as is often misunderstood, a crime of passion.  In most cases &mdash; in fact in the majority of cases according to the figures &mdash; it is a meticulously and carefully planned crime.  In cases of rape <Col N="1889" /> involving one man, research shows that over half of such cases have been carefully planned and could not, therefore, be regarded as crimes of passion.  Where a group of men are involved in the rape, as many as 95 per cent of the cases are carefully planned.  Rape, therefore, is a cold, callous crime and one which needs a very strong reaction.</P>
    <P>The Bill before us, and indeed any attempt to deal with this crime, must bear in mind that it is not just a question of the size of the penalty, the swiftness of the trial, the admissibility of evidence and so on.  Rape or any form of sexual assault is a crime which needs attention at its roots and origin.  Legislation concerned with rape and sexual assault should not assume that rape or sexual assault is inevitable. Such legislation must take a compassionate view of the real trauma and the real tragedy which the crime inflicts. We should make a much more determined effort to ensure that such offences do not occur by analysing the reasons for these crimes and concentrating our efforts on trying to prevent them occurring rather than spending our time legislating for what will happen after the assault has taken place.</P>
    <P>The number of incidents of rape is clearly on the increase.  Yet, we are told that rape is probably the most under-reported of all crimes, especially in a society like ours where there is very often a reluctance even to consider matters such as rape.  Indeed, we have moved a very long way in a short time to a situation where a problem like this can be discussed in an open and sensitive way.  We have moved away from the prudery which characterised discussion of this topic not so very long ago.</P>
    <P>The rate of under-reporting of rape cases appears to be quite significant.  For example, between 1 January and 31 October 1987 the Rape Crisis Centre received 1,236 calls relating to sexual abuse of adults and children.  Yet, throughout 1987 only 75 cases were reported or known to the Garda and in only 36 of these cases were criminal proceedings commenced.  These figures, even though certainly on the conservative <Col N="1890" /> side, are significant in themselves.  They indicate that rape and sexual assault crimes occur all too regularly in Ireland today and that in many cases the victims are afraid to bring their assailants to court.</P>
    <P>It is our job as legislators to try to make court proceedings less intimidating and off-putting to victims of rape and sexual assault.  This House must now make a clear declaration to the women of this country.  We must assure them that as far as the laws can help, every effort will be made to ensure that the corner is turned and that proper and adequate defence in law will be given to women in these very distressing circumstances.</P>
    <P>The Bill here today is a good piece of legislation which has many advantages over the Criminal Law (Rape) Act, 1981, and I wish to commend the Minister for the speed with which he introduced this Bill and for the obviously open attitude which he has taken to the discussion so far in this House.  Comparing this Bill with the Criminal Law (Rape) Act, 1981 this new legislation replaces the offences of indecent assault on a male or female with the offence of aggravated sexual assault with a maximum penalty of life imprisonment and sexual assault with a maximum penalty of five years in jail.</P>
    <P>Secondly, this new legislation criminalises rape within marriage, that a husband can now be found guilty of raping his wife.  This reform is particularly welcome as the Rape Crisis Centre reports that the majority of rapes probably occur within marriage and the fact that the woman is married to her attacker certainly does not make the crime any less abhorrent to her.</P>
    <P>Thirdly, the Bill abolishes the rule of law which stated that a male under the age of 14 was physically incapable of committing a sexual offence, so that all males may now be found guilty of rape regardless of their age.  This is a welcome reform as in the past few years many cases have received media attention in which one or all of the rapists or sexual abusers were under 14 years of age.  Research shows that many of these youths who commit <Col N="1891" /> crimes in their early teens have themselves been abused and, therefore, need urgent treatment and help.  If sentenced for committing a rape or some other form of sexual assault they, and indeed rapists of all ages, must be given treatment and counselling during their sentence so that when they are released they will be less of a risk and a danger to women.</P>
    <P>Fine Gael welcome the fact that the public will now be excluded from hearings of rape and sexual assault cases.  In any rape trial all concerned, especially the complainant, desire to be shielded from the public.  All other family law cases have been allowed to be held <i>in camera</i> for some time now and I am very pleased that at last rape and sexual assault cases will be treated similarly.  We are also pleased that this Bill allows rape and sexual assault cases to be held in the Central Criminal Court as opposed to the Circuit Court where they are held at present.</P>
    <P>The Bill before us, however, omits some much needed reforms which I hope can be included in the Bill on Committee Stage.  As I see it, the Bill has two main weaknesses.  If fails to provide for independent legal representation for the complainant and it fails to broaden the definition of rape.  Those involved in treating victims of rape and sexual assault have constantly lobbied for separate free legal representation for the complainant. They believe it is necessary because in many cases the counsel for the prosecution is not sufficiently concerned to protect from cross-examination the woman who has been raped.</P>
    <P>Many complainants in rape cases find the proceedings very stressful indeed. They complain that they feel totally alone and unrepresented in the witness box and are subjected to a humiliating and highly personal cross-examination about their sexual behaviour, their history and general character.  Separate legal representation for the complainant during rape and sexual assault cases would help to protect the victims and keep them from feeling that it is they who are on trial throughout the proceedings.  The Bill, <Col N="1892" /> however, fails to provide for such independent legal representation for the complainant. This is a flaw which I hope will be rectified.  Certainly, we in this party will attempt to amend the Bill in this regard during Committee Stage.  We feel very strongly that in the interests of justice and equality for both the victim and the accused everything possible should be done to help the complainant and to put her as much at her ease as possible during the trial.</P>
    <P>I regret also that in this legislation the definition of rape has not been extended to cover the kind of offence now called aggravated sexual assault.  A woman knows when she is raped, not because of the technical way in which her body has been attacked but because she feels abused, degraded and humiliated.  She herself regards the crime as rape whether it is technically described as such or not. This broadening of the definition of rape was recommended both by the Law Reform Commission and the Joint Committee on Women's Rights and has been argued for for very many years also by the Rape Crisis Centre who are widely regarded as experts in this area.</P>
    <P>I take this opportunity to pay tribute to these centres throughout the country who have worked for many years with the victims of rape and their families, giving them much needed treatment and counselling.  As well as helping rape victims themselves, these centres have raised public awareness of the need to reform the law in relation to rape and such pressure has, in part, resulted in the Bill before us today.  It is indicative of the change in public attitudes that a group like the Rape Crisis Centre who in the early stages had to face a great deal of opprobrium, a great deal of questioning of their motives, and ill-founded criticism and abuse, are now regarded as a very important part of the whole social fabric of the city.  They are rightly commended for the work they have done, both in helping the victims and in pioneering new approaches to the problem.</P>
    <P>It is a great shame that the existence of such a hardworking organisation should, for so long, have been threatened by lack <Col N="1893" /> of funding, especially in the light of the amounts of moneys that were disbursed to far less worthy organisations from the proceeds of the national lottery.  Surely the rape crisis centres, who provide such a vital and necessary service to victims of rape and sexual assault, are obvious targets for funding from the national lottery? Why did the Government take so long to come to their rescue on this occasion?  The Government should have been quicker to respond to the obvious problems which the centres face, to help them to sort out their financial problems and put them on a sound footing.  I hope we will not see a recurrence of this problem arising from lack of funding.</P>
    <P>The Government have not gone far enough in helping the Rape Crisis Centre.  They have allocated some money to the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre which should help to relieve its present financial crisis and allow it to continue its invaluable work with victims of rape and sexual assault but the other rape crisis centres have been completely ignored.  They have not received a single penny from the Government.  Their work in Cork, Clonmel and Galway is every bit as necessary and vital as is the work of the centre in Dublin.  I ask the Minister to look carefully and sympathetically at the whole question of the rape crisis centres and see if, in consultation, some better arrangement could be arrived at so that they are able to carry out their work unworried by the constant financial crisis which seems to hang over them.  They give very good value for money and they provide an important service and would be the view of all parties in this House that they should be encouraged and helped to continue to do this work.</P>
    <P>I am delighted at one level that the Government have shown their appreciation of the work done by the Rape Crisis Centre in Dublin.  They have, I hope, solved the problem there for the moment but I urge the Minister to see if funds can be made available and new structures agreed upon to enable the work of the rape crisis centres in other parts of the country to go ahead.</P>
    <P>We in Fine Gael warmly welcome this <Col N="1894" /> Bill.  We see it as an expression by the Government of their concern for tackling the very serious problem of rape.  In commending the Bill to the House &mdash; and I am sure it will be agreed to by all parties &mdash; I would ask the Minister to look again at the funding of the rape crisis centres.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to have the opportunity to make a short contribution to this debate.  I welcome the introduction of the Criminal Law (Rape) (Amendment) Bill, 1988.  I also welcome the fact that the Minister decided to introduce this Bill in the Seanad.  It is a wide-ranging measure which proposes to substantially amend the law on rape in order to give greater protection to those who experience sexual attacks.</P>
      <P>It also implements a commitment to reform the law on rape which was given in the 1987 Fianna Fáil <i>Programme for National Recovery</i>.  The law on rape was the subject of a report in January 1987 by the Joint Committee on Women's Rights.  I had the honour to be a member of that committee at the time and this is one of the factors which prompted me to speak in this debate.  I know how carefully that committee, which was chaired by the Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach, Deputy Máire Geoghegan-Quinn, examined every aspect of this issue and the very many submissions which we considered in great detail before the final report and recommendations of the committees were issued.</P>
      <P>During the course of those deliberations even those of us who previously might not have given any in-depth consideration to this issue became convinced of the urgent need to significantly amend and strengthen the 1981 legislation.  I am very pleased that the Minister for Justice has given such a high priority to the preparation of this legislation and that he has succeeded in bringing a Bill for that purpose before the Oireachtas with so little delay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Shortly after the issue of the report of the Joint Committee on Women's Rights &mdash; a report which was widely welcomed <Col N="1895" /> and endorsed &mdash; the then Attorney General requested the Law Reform Commission to formulate proposals for the reform of the law relating to rape.  In December 1987 the commission published a consultation paper on the law on rape in which they invited comments from mebers of the public and in connection with which an all-day seminar was held in January 1988.  Having given consideration to the submissions which were received and the views which were expressed at the seminar, the commission presented its final proposals for reform to the present Attorney General in mid-1988. I want to join with all the other speakers who have complimented the Law Reform Commission on their excellent report.  They are also deserving of our gratitude and appreciation for having brought their report forward so expeditiously in view of the widespread public concern which exists in relation to this matter.</P>
    <P>The Bill before the House deals with all the main areas which were identified by the Joint Committee on Women's Rights and the Law Reform Commission as being in need of reform.  However, instead of broadening the definition of rape as suggested by the Joint Committee and supported by the majority recommendation in the commission's report, the Government have instead decided that the definition of rape should remain unchanged, that the Bill should create a new offence to be known as aggravated sexual assault which will cover all the various assaults which it was suggested should be covered by an extended legal definition of rape.</P>
    <P>Until I read the minority report of the commission in relation to this matter, I have to admit that I was firmly convinced that the definition of rape should be widened. The case for so doing was made very strongly to the Joint Committee both in oral and written submissions by the Rape Crisis Centre.  However, having read the minority report and having considered the arguments advanced therein, particularly in relation to the difficulties which could arise from a broadening of <Col N="1896" /> the existing definition of rape, I am now reasonably satisfied that the Government's approach is the correct one.</P>
    <P>I welcome the fact that the Bill provides for the replacement of the offence of indecent assault with the offences of sexual assault and aggravated sexual assault and that the offence of aggravated sexual assault will carry a maximum penalty of life imprisonment.  Certainly the term &ldquo;indecent assault&rdquo; was far too mild a term to adequately describe many of the serious and brutal sexual assaults which appear to have become so common in recent years.</P>
    <P>The Bill also proposes to abolish the marital rape exemption.  Under the present law a woman may not accuse her husband of rape.  The Joint Committee on Women's Rights having considered a number of submissions in this regard, and again particularly the submission from the Rape Crisis Centre, were satisfied that many battered wives suffered the additional humiliation and degradation of being raped by their husbands.  In such cases the fact that the criminal is married to the victim does not and should not mitigate the behaviour involved and I am delighted that this will be the situation when this Bill becomes law.  In order to prevent the institution of spiteful or mischievious proceedings by a spouse or by some other party as a result of the criminalisation of rape within marriage, the Bill contains the safeguard that a prosecution for marital rape can only be brought with the consent of the Director of Public Prosecutions and I welcome this provision.</P>
    <P>Under the present law there is also a presumption that a boy under 14 years of age is incapable of sexual intercourse and, therefore, cannot be convicted of rape.  This presumption is being abolished in the Bill.  I welcome this decision because we are all aware over the past few years of cases reported in the media in which some or all of the rapists or sexual abusers were under 14 years of age.  I would like to think that young boys who are found guilty of sexual offences will receive appropriate treatment during <Col N="1897" /> their imprisonment or detention.  Otherwise it is almost certain that as they grow older they will become involved in further sexual crimes.</P>
    <P>Under existing law it is mandatory for a judge in trials for sexual offences to warn the jury of the danger of convicting on the uncorroborated evidence of the complainant.  In accordance with the recommendation of the Law Reform Commission, this Bill proposes that such a warning should no longer be mandatory and that the decision as to whether a warning should be given and the terms of the warning should be left to the discretion of the trial judge.</P>
    <P>I want to give a special welcome to section 7 of the Bill which provides for alternative verdicts as between rape, aggravated sexual assault and sexual assault.  This section enables the accused to be convicted of the appropriate alternative offence as warranted by the evidence. I believe that this section will make it more difficult for accused persons to evade conviction as a result of technicalities for crimes in which they were involved.</P>
    <P>Another important provision in the Bill is that the anonymity of the complainant is being retained and extended to all sexual offences.  That is a good decision. However, I feel that the anonymity provisions relating to an accused should also be extended to cover aggravated sexual assault and sexual assault and that the identity of an accused should only be made public on conviction.</P>
    <P>Cases involving sexual assault attract a greater degree of publicity than most other offences and persons accused of such offences attract a greater degree of public odium than most other accused. Consequently, the damage done to the reputation of an innocent person, even though he is acquitted, is much greater than would be the case if he were charged with some other offence.  It can also happen that when an accused is acquitted in a sexual assault case, such a decision of the court does not always receive the same prominence in the media as the actual trial itself.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1898" /> I now come to what is probably the most controversial question as far as this Bill is concerned and that is the question of whether the complainant in a rape or sexual assault case should have separate legal representation.  The Rape Crisis Centre, in their submission to the Joint Committee on Women's Rights argued very strongly for separate legal representation for the complainant in rape cases on the basis that most complainants of rape found the experience of a criminal hearing to be horrific, degrading and humiliating and that in no other case would a witness be subject to the type of cross-examination and humiliation prevalent in rape cases.  I was quite surprised at first to learn that the Law Reform Commission did not make a recommendation for such separate legal representation but having read their report and having noted their fear that to do so might result in some unjustified acquittals, I am now satisfied that, on balance, such representation should not be provided.</P>
    <P>Section 10 of the Bill provides for the exclusion of the public from hearings of rape and aggravated assault cases and it also provides that the jury and the press will be excluded whenever an application is made during a trial to cross-examine a plaintiff about his or her previous sexual history.  On reading this section I notice that section 10 (3) provides that, notwithstanding anything else in the section, a parent, relative or friend of the complainant &mdash; whatever the complainant's age &mdash; or of the accused, if he is not of full age, may remain in court during the hearing.  It struck me from the way that subsection is worded that in either case only one parent would be entitled to remain in the court even though the complainant or accused might wish to have both parents present.  If my interpretation of the subsection is correct, I ask the Minister to consider amending it so that in all such situations both parents could be present as of right.  I know that is a point which, I suppose, could be more properly made on Committee Stage but I am raising it now to give the Minister an opportunity to look into it.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1899" /> In conclusion, I wish to join in the welcome that has been given to this Bill by all sides of the House and to wish it a speedy passage through the Oireachtas. I cannot let this occasion pass without welcoming the very generous provision in the budget for the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre and I want to compliment the Government on having responded so positively to the financial needs of this very worthwhile organisation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the legislation of this Criminal Law (Rape) (Amendment) Bill, 1988.  It represents a timely updating of Irish law and is progressive when we think of the struggles that took place on this very same legislation way back in 1981.  I suppose in terms of how quickly change can occur in the area of legislation, this change is fairly rapid.  For a party who do not have a surprising or illuminating track record in progressive social legislation, nevertheless, I commend the Government party in relation to this legislation before us today.</P>
      <P>Rape is horrific.  It is an appalling and an intimate violation of bodily integrity. The victim suffers not only physically but also has to endure emotional and psychological aftershock which can take a very long time to eradicate or ameliorate if, in many instances, it is ever possible to do away with the lasting effects of such a brutal attack or assault.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am glad that the Government made the decision to introduce this legislation into Seanad Éireann.  Contributions in this House, particularly in areas of sensitive legislation, are generally thoughtful and reflective.  Indeed, they reflect a certain expertise that some Senators in the House are fortunate enough to possess and their specialist concerns as individuals are very often brought to bear on legislation such as this.  Certainly the debate to date has shown that kind of input which I think shows this House at its very best.  It is also interesting to note that there are five women Members in this House.  I know you, a Chathaoirligh, are precluded because of your position <Col N="1900" /> from participating in debate but all of the other women Members have made a particular point of speaking on this legislation which is a good thing.  I am also heartened by the number of male Senators from all parties who have to date made very fine contributions and who have extended the debate and discussion on this legislation.</P>
    <P>The framing of this legislation has taken place against a background of much research and consultation on the subject. The first Oireachtas Joint Committee on Women's Rights brought out a comprehensive report &mdash; their fourth &mdash; on the subject of sexual violence and of course the Law Reform Commission submitted its report to the Attorney General on 3 May 1988.  This report had been requested by the former Attorney General, John Rogers.  It is good that the Government have acted so swiftly in bringing forward this legislation.  Would that other Law Reform Commission reports could receive the same speedy response because there is a criticism, and a legitimate criticism, that so many of the Law Reform Commission reports &mdash; good valuable, important and significant documents &mdash; are gathering dust and there has been legislative, and consequently governmental, inactivity on implementing their suggested reforms.</P>
    <P>Turning to the specific provisions of the Bill before us, I must voice my disappointment at the failure of Government to accept the need to amend the definition of rape itself.  This is a criticism which has been made by my party and we have entered amendments for Committee Stage to that effect.  Both the Law Reform Commission report and the Joint Committee on Women's Rights were of the view that there was a clear need to broaden the definition and the Law Reform Commission in particular approached their task of reviewing the matter in an all-embracing, consultative manner.  In fact, I think they blazed a trail in this regard and I hope it will be a pattern of the way in which they will approach major pieces of law reform in future.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1901" /> It is interesting to note what they actually did; they produced a discussion document in the first instance.  That was well received and widely debated by interested groups and received excellent press coverage at the time.  Then they invited written and oral submissions and then they held a special conference on the subject.  At the end of this exhaustive examination, the Law Reform Commission recommended, and I quote:</P>
    <P>that the crime of rape should be defined by statute so as to include non-consensual sexual penetration of the vagina, anus and mouth of a person by the penis of another person or of the vagina or anus of a person by an inanimate object held or manipulated by another person and that in this form the crime should be capable of being committed against men and women.</P>
    <P>I find it impossible to understand why the Government have chosen to ignore this advice which quite clearly followed upon detailed consultation and consideration, much of it as I have outlined, conducted in public.</P>
    <P>In his introductory speech on the Bill here in this House the Minister failed to adequately explain the decision to limit the definition other than to make vague references to the fact that in his view the community regarded rape as distinguishable from other crimes of a sexual nature.  As an explanation the Minister's remarks are not adequate and they have been described by my Seanad colleague, Senator Mary Robinson, as unverifiable, unjustifiable and unwarranted.  I hope when the Minister is responding to the Second Stage debate he will expand and give justification, verification and reason as to why the Government and he decided to limit the definition and not to go along with the majority Law Reform Commission recommendation in this regard. We feel this a major weakness in an otherwise excellent piece of legislation.</P>
    <P>We must remember here that Ireland has an opportunity to come to the forefront in the area of progressive, reforming legislation in this particular context. Like other opportunities which have been <Col N="1902" /> missed by this Government, I feel that unless our amendments are accepted this will be another opportunity which will be missed and sadly so.  It certainly will not be for the want of telling, reminding, indicating, cajoling, persuading and arguing on this side of the House.  In my view this is a most disappointing feature of an otherwise excellent and welcome piece of legislation.  We will be putting down amendments in an attempt to improve it and to more accurately reflect the views of the public at large as ascertained by the Law Reform Commission.</P>
    <P>Persons who have been violated by instruments, bottles and other objects or who are forced to engage in degrading sexual activities share the same violation, humiliation and trauma as those who have been the victims of enforced penile penetration.  Calling such actions as this legislation does &ldquo;aggravated sexual assault&rdquo; solves little as, in practice, they will be regarded as less serious than rape itself.  In my view, they are every bit as serious as rape itself and certainly in the view of the victims against whom crimes have been perpetrated, they are rape itself.  Ms. Anne O'Donnell of the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre has gone on record as stating that in her view victims of such assaults could not distinguish between the various penetrations.  In her view such a woman has been raped &mdash; full stop, end of story &mdash; not the victim of aggravated sexual assault.  I have no doubt this will be the subject of more detailed discussion on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>Mention of Anne O'Donnell of the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre give me an opportunity here to pay tribute to this very fine Irishwoman who, against the tide, took a stand and became involved in this whole area of crisis, intervention and counselling.  She has announced in recent days that she is resigning from her post as director of the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre and I would like to place on record my appreciation of all of her involvement in this area over the years.  She has always been lucid, reasoned, calm and very purposeful in her attitude towards approaching education and information-giving and in her follow through when approaching <Col N="1903" /> Government and Government Departments and indeed Opposition, she has kept up the pressure for change, as have people around her in that particular body.  I admire that singleminded pursuit of an objective which has been exhibited and I wish her well in the future.</P>
    <P>Indeed, all rape crisis centres throughout the country deserve much commendation, in particular the one in Waterford which is undergoing particular difficulties, Clonmel, Galway, Cork and the one in the Minister's own constituency of Limerick.  All of these people are coping with human misery and with crises in peoples lives.  Not only do they deal with the immediate victims of rape but it is interesting to note that some 70 per cent of clients in the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre in the first half of 1988 were past victims of child sexual abuse.  That is disturbing and worrying but at least there was an organisation there to meet their need and to provide them with consultation because such people now know and must know that society cares about what has happened to them and is willing to give an input into seeing if their sad and residual difficulties can be coped with and ameliorated to some degree.</P>
    <P>Much mention has been made of funding for rape crisis centres.  I recognise the fact that the Minister of State, Deputy Geoghegan-Quinn, has spoken about some £20,000 and that in recent days further funding has been mentioned by way of a special budgetary allocation.  As late as yesterday there had been no official confirmation of it nor had any money actually been received by this body which is currently involved in litigation in the High Court.  I would like the Minister to clarify where is the blockage in ensuring that this funding gets speedily to those people for whom it is designated.  I hope there is no official stalling in this regard and that the funds are made available because they are quite clearly and quite explicitly needed and needed urgently by this body.</P>
    <P>Returning to the Bill, I would like to place on record my support for many of the reforms it contains.  I support the abolition of the concept of indecent <Col N="1904" /> assault.  I support the restriction on the cross-examination of a complainant concerning her previous sexual history and the exclusion of the press from that part of the proceedings.  I welcome the inclusion of the concept of marital rape. It is interesting to note that in 1981 such a concept was not even countenanced. Again, I refer to the welcome change in thinking and in action which has occurred in that regard.</P>
    <P>I welcome the fact that rape and aggravated sexual assault cases will be heard in the Central Criminal Court and that the general public will be excluded from such hearings.  I would like to make a comment in passing on the nature of press reporting of rape cases.  Certainly, I have noted very lurid and, to my mind, quite unnecessary detailed reporting of such cases particularly in the provincial press. Some of these accounts of what has taken place have been a voyeur's delight.  To my mind they are reprehensible in the extreme and quite unnecessary.  They certainly raise the whole issue of the necessity for a press council, which I recognise as a separate issue and a separate discussion.  I have in the past publicly remonstrated against such reporting and will continue to do so again, although I hope the need does not arise.  Certainly, in a provincial context it is always generally known who is the victim is in this regard and that kind of reporting represents yet a further trial of that victim by the public at large.  I think it is extremely damaging and in some way is a reflection of the descent in terms of standards which afflict so much of life today.  I invite the Minister to comment specifically on what I say and to ask him if he has noted the nature of such reporting if he finds it acceptable to see such detailed, quite literally blow-for-blow accounts, of such sexual assaults against people detailed in the press.</P>
    <P>I welcome the giving of discretion to judges as opposed to a mandatory requirement in the matter of warning the jury about accepting uncorroborated evidence. This is significant and it is to be welcomed.  The abolition of the strict rule of law under which a boy of 14 years <Col N="1905" /> was regarded as being incapable of sexual intercourse is to be welcomed.  That never, ever tallied with reality and certainly today's young people, both in terms of their physical maturation &mdash; which I suppose is a consequence of improved diet and a greater awareness of health &mdash; and their precocity, have shown speedier development.  As well as that, I think there has been a certain sexual precocity abroad which has made that earlier legal provision a nonsense.  I am glad to see that that has been addressed in this legislation.</P>
    <P>I must express my disappointment that the legislation does not admit the need for separate legal representation of rape victims.  This was a recommendation of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Women's Rights and the Rape Crisis Centre.  It is something that I am sure will be dealt with in detail on Committee Stage.  Certainly, we on this side of the House will return to it with some vigour.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, and in view of the fact that Second Stage is merely considering the general principles of the Bill, I would like to express a personal view &mdash; would that we did not have to consider such legislation.  The increasing incidence of rape and violent sexual assault is profoundly disturbing and particularly worrying is the apparent growth in sexual attacks on elderly women.  It must be asked why this is happening.  Is it because such women are alone, defenceless, passive and unlikely to put up any resistance? Is robbery and theft the over-riding consideration? In any event, such attacks evoke profound revulsion in the community at large.</P>
    <P>Obviously, victims of rape deserve speedy professional support but we must make reference to rapists also.  I was interested to hear what Senator Mullooly had to say about this, particularly in relation to young people who become involved in this kind of activity.  It is true to say that rapists do not evoke any public sympathy, and indeed very little understanding apart from professionals involved in the field of counselling but they, too, must be cared for by society and proper rehabilitation programmes <Col N="1906" /> must be put in place for them.  Such men are generally hostile to the whole female sex and research and follow-through is urgently needed in this area, and indeed a greater understanding as to why rape occurs.  There are many theories floated in relation to this and I am sure little bits and pieces of all of them make up the whole as to why such attacks are perpetrated.</P>
    <P>I hope this legislation will act as a deterrent. Certainly, it gives an enlightened and up-dated official response to what is a growing and horrendous menance in our society.</P>
    <Speaker pid="VivianOCallaghan" hpid="Mr. O'Callaghan Mr. O'Callaghan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Callaghan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall be very brief. The primary purpose of my contribution is to avail of the opportunity to congratulate the Minister on introducing this legislation in such an expeditious manner.  The mechanics of the Bill have already been dealt with in fair detail and I do not propose to go into them again at this early stage.  It is important that we record the public's perception of and reaction to the Bill in the light of what has been printed and published in the media already.  There is great welcome for the introduction of this additional legislation.  It is significant and we should comment on the fact that after seven short years we see a necessity to change in a fairly substantial way the previous Bill.  This, of course, is a response to what is a public crisis, not just in Ireland but in the civilised world.  The Minister has acted in an extremely expeditious manner in the framing of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It should also be noted &mdash; Senator Bulbulia touched briefly on this &mdash; that there continues to be such an upsurge in the incidence of rape in all its shapes and forms.  In the past 16 or 18 months the Minister has sought to close off a number of loopholes that existed in various other areas that in themselves contribute to the crime of rape.  I refer in particular to the legislation relating to pornographic videos because there is definite evidence abroad now that quite often the act of rape is a direct consequence of a person, or indeed persons, having viewed some of these video nasties that until quite <Col N="1907" /> recently at least were freely available in this country and elsewhere.  The direct result of such viewing was that the people in question were involved in the crime of rape soon afterwards and there are a number of examples to prove that.</P>
    <P>Another cause which crops up with monotonous regularity in court proceedings, particularly among younger people, is the phenomenon of excessive drinking.  Again, the Minister has endeavoured to address this difficult subject by closing off many of the loopholes which existed in the law whereby young people had a greater degree of access to alcoholic drink than they should have had or were intended to have under previous legislation.  Slowly but surely, the Minister is closing off various avenues which either contributed to encourage people to become involved in this crime or which when they had been involved provided escape routes when they got to the courts.</P>
    <P>I would also like to refer briefly to the fact that the actual mechanics of going to the courts now and getting a conviction are a good deal easier.  This is the kind of response the public expect and want.  The citizens of this city, and indeed of many of the cities and towns throughout the country, are seriously concerned about the safety of young girls particularly going out at night.  In one of the national newspapers yesterday it was alleged that there was a serious crisis on some of our university and third level campuses around the country which has required a response by college authorities by way of providing additional security guards, lights and so on.  The need for this is an extraordinary development in what is supposed to be an enlightened society. The problem is getting progressively worse and I am certain that this legislation in a substantial way, if not totally, grasps that nettle.</P>
    <P>People were looking for this type of protection and now they have got it.  It is extremely comprehensive.  It ensures that the public can have confidence in the rule of law and that if such a crime is <Col N="1908" /> perpetuated against any citizen the perpetrators will be dealt with in a proper manner.  That is to be welcomed.</P>
    <P>As I said at the outset, my primary purpose in speaking today was to be associated with the tributes to the Minister in introducing this Bill in such an expeditious manner.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall be brief.  I would simply like to welcome the Bill and to congratulate the Minister and the Government on bringing forward this very important legislation.  I see it as an expression of concern on their part and they should be congratulated for that.</P>
      <P>I do not normally get involved in what might be described as women's rights issues but I consider rape is a most horrible form of crime.  Mention has been made of the various newspaper reports. Unfortunately, one now reads regularly in our daily newspapers of crimes of rape and sexual assault cases.  These crimes are on the increase.  While the daily papers will give a factual report in most cases, there is an element of hypocrisy in the reports in some newspapers which go overboard on the matter.  They try to be do-gooders and condemn rape and, at the same time, sell their papers because they have pictures of suitable &ldquo;Page three&rdquo; people.  I find that a little disgusting in many ways and certainly there is an element of hypocrisy in it.</P>
      <P>I would like to refer also to what Senator Bulbulia said about the detailed reporting of some of the sex assault cases that I have read.  In particular, in rural Ireland they seem to go a little overboard. In rural Ireland it is a delicate, sensitive issue.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Request under" RHead="Standing Order 29">
    <Title>Request under Standing Order 29.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I interrupt the Senator for a moment?  I have to take an item under Standing Order 29 and I will then call on him to resume.  I have notice from Senator John A. Murphy regarding a motion which he wishes to move under <Col N="1909" /> Standing Order 29.  I now call on Senator Murphy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I request leave to move the Adjournment of the Seanad under Standing Order 29 so that Seanad Éireann can discuss the indefensibly drastic reduction in the opening hours of the National Library beginning today, reflecting the general crisis in our greatest cultural resource centre and the consequent damage both to scholarship and to Ireland's image abroad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given careful consideration to the matter raised by Senator Murphy and I do not consider it to be a matter contemplated under Standing Order 29.  I regret, therefore, that I have to rule it out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMurphy2" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank you, a Chathaoirligh.  Let me observe, briefly, that despite the Taoiseach's reputation as a patron of learning, the mishandling by his Department of the National Library is a national disgrace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Criminal Law (Rape) (Amendment)" RHead="Bill, 1988: Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Criminal Law (Rape) (Amendment) Bill, 1988: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is obvious that the aim of the Bill is to endeavour to reduce the type of rape crimes we are talking about. However, its aim should be not just to reduce them but to eliminate them totally. Gang rapes which we have all read about &mdash; one as recently as yesterday &mdash; are extremely henious.  While this legislation is an objective of the women's rights movement, 99 per cent of the men of Ireland support the aspirations contained in it.  Perhaps it does not go far enough but I agree with the basic thrust of it.  The vast majority of Irish men support the view that rape is an extremely henious, horrible crime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1910" />
    <Speaker pid="KatherineBulbulia" hpid="Mrs. Bulbulia Mrs. Bulbulia">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Bulbulia</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no doubt that that is so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="Mr. Fallon Mr. Fallon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fallon</NameTxt>
      <P>Much of the cause of the problem has been levelled at drink and certainly one has to agree with this.  Many rape attacks are committed by men who have taken a lot of drink.  Most cases of violence against the wife are as a result of drink and rape within marriage is, for the most part, caused by excessive drinking. It is true to say that many married women live in fear of violence, including rape, from husbands who have too much drink taken but just because a rapist had drink taken he should not be treated with any greater sympathy by the courts.</P>
      <P>My criticism of the Bill is that the penalties are not severe enough.  If the Minister decided to stiffen them severely I would support him, but is is a good start and I congratulate the Minister for introducing the Bill.  I do not intend to go into the detail of it.  I have read it but I am sure other Members are far more competent in understanding it than I am. However, it goes a long way towards helping in the matter and I welcome the Bill.  I congratulate the Minister for bringing it forward so speedily and I wish it success.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardCollins" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Collins) Gerard Collins">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Collins)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator for their contributions to the debate on this very important legislation and for their general welcome for the Bill.  The welcome given by Senators Manning and Fennell to the Bill on behalf of their party is particularly appreciated. I know that the law in regard to rape was a matter of particular interest to Senator Fennell when she was a Minister of State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill represents a concerned and progressive approach to the law on sexual assaults.  As a result of the changes which the law will bring about, our law on rape and other sexual offences will be considerably more advanced than in many other jurisdictions and will show a real concern for women.  When considering what changes in the law should be included in this Bill, the Government fully examined all proposals for change that had been made whether by the Law <Col N="1911" /> Reform Commission, the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Women's Rights or any other group.  Where a proposal for change was not accepted by the Government it was because following careful examination of the matter, it was considered not to be in the public interest, including the interests of women, to accept it.</P>
    <P>One proposal which the Government did not accept &mdash; and a number of Senators including Senators Fennell, Manning, Bulbulia, Robinson and Fitzsimons have commented on it &mdash; is the proposal made by the Oireachtas Joint Committee and a majority of three to two of the Law Reform Commission that the definition of rape be broadened to include certain types of sexual assault which do not at present amount to rape. In deference to the Senators who spoke on this question on the previous occasion I will deal at some length with the issues involved.</P>
    <P>The question of extending the definition of rape was considered fully by the Government before they came to their decision not to do so.  Careful consideration was given not only to the report, including the minority report, of the Law Reform Commission but also to the views of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Women's Rights which reported on the crime of rape in January 1987.  The Government's decision was arrived at with one view only in mind: what the Government considered would be in the best interests of the victims of rape and other serious sexual assaults and of the public generally.  This is in no way a political issue and I want to make that quite clear.  It is a legal and social issue which must be considered in the context of what is the best provision we can make for the purpose of fulfilling our obligations to the public generally and in particular to the victims and would-be victims of these offences.</P>
    <P>On the question itself, the Government were faced with an issue on which clearly there were opposing views.  On the one hand, the joint committee and <Col N="1912" /> three members of the Law Reform Commission were in favour of the extension of the definition of rape.  However, two members of the commission &mdash; its President, a distinguished High Court judge and its full-time commissioner, with considerable experience in the Office of the Director of Public Prosecutions &mdash; were against an extended definition.  Senators will also be aware that submissions received by the joint committee from the Garda Síochána and the Law Society also argued against broadening the definition or rape.  Clearly, objections can be made to certain aspects of the existing law on serious sexual assaults which do not amount to rape yet, equally clearly, many of those who have experience in administering the criminal law are not in favour of including these assaults in an extended definition of rape.  In view of the obvious disagreement about the proposal to extend the definition of rape, if for no other reason, it was necessary for the Government to examine the issue fully. Even if the Law Reform Commission had been unanimous in recommending this change, this fact would not have relieved the Government of the obligation to form their own view on the question.  I will deal with the report of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Women's Rights first.</P>
    <P>It was the view of the committee that &ldquo;the existing Criminal Law (Rape) Act, 1981 ignores the seriousness of other forms of sexual assault such as forced anal and oral sex, apart from penile penetration, and in so doing it implies that one form of sexual attack is more serious than another&rdquo;.  The Government accept that such sexual assaults can be as distressing as rape and it is for that very reason that the Bill creates the new offence of aggravated sexual assault with the same penalty as for rape and which along with rape, will be tried in the Central Criminal Court.  The committee's report goes on to say:</P>
    <P>It is important that the gravity of forced sexual penetration through the use of objects is fully recognised and that the protection at present afforded <Col N="1913" /> to victims of rape should be extended to the victims of such sexual acts.</P>
    <P>Again, the Government agree with this proposition and the Bill provides for the extension to all sexual assault victims the protection both as to cross-examination on previous sexual history and anonymity at present afforded to rape victims.  Finally the report says:</P>
    <P>Members agree that there is no logic in keeping as separate the treatment by law of offences that reflect a correspondingly degrading level of sexual violence.</P>
    <P>The Government agree generally with this proposition also and henceforth, following the enactment of this legislation, victims of the various sexual offences in question and the offences themselves will be treated in the same way as rape and the perpetrators will be subject to the same penalty.  But equal treatment by the law of these offences does not necessarily mean that the name &ldquo;rape&rdquo; should be applied to those offences which do not come within the definition of rape as at present.  On the contrary, there are good reasons why the concept of rape should not be applied to the offences in question.</P>
    <P>I now turn to the Law Reform Commission's report.  Those members of the Law Reform Commission who favoured change argued, for instance, that the existing law does not reflect the community's concept of rape.  The Government are not convinced that this is the case.  Neither, indeed, were all the members of the commission.  There is, of course, no research which can prove or disprove this argument.  However, it would surely be regarded as strange and misleading to read that a man had a number of convictions for rape where the offences were, in fact, buggery of men or boys.  It would seem, however, that in the view of the majority of the commission the main objection to the present definition of rape is that rape is &ldquo;a form of sexual assault which is no more distinctive than any other similarly serious forms of sexual assault which are grouped together <Col N="1914" /> within a single offence&rdquo;.  The Government did not accept this argument.</P>
    <P>The crime of rape clearly has certain features which distinguish it from other crimes of a sexual nature.  Indeed, in a recent important judgment the Supreme Court laid emphasis on the distinctive features of rape, including the possibility of pregnancy, when emphasising that the crime of rape must always be viewed as one of the most serious offences contained in our criminal law.  This is so even when rape is committed without violence beyond that constituting the act of rape itself.</P>
    <P>Apart from the risk of pregnancy, the essential feature of the crime of rape is that it consists of an act which is not in itself criminal but becomes criminal where there is an absence of consent by the woman.  Although in many cases the act of rape is also an act of savage violence, it is the absence of consent to intercourse rather than the use of force that is the essential feature of rape.  To extend the definition of rape to cover the grosser acts of serious sexual assault, such as forcing a bottle into the vagina of a woman, by providing as the Law Reform Commission proposed that the offence should embrace non-consensual acts of this nature seems to the Government to be wrong in principle.  There is the implication that such acts, if consensual, would be acceptable.  It is also an inescapable fact that no matter how the issue is dealt with, the presence or absence of consent would always be the issue in a trial for rape but would not normally be a real issue in relation to other serious assaults.</P>
    <P>Another concern of the Government relates to the following.  The view has been expressed that by applying the term &ldquo;rape&rdquo; to those serious sexual assaults that at present do not amount to rape, all such assaults would thereby attract the odium and stigma associated in the public's mind with the crime of rape.  This argument seems to be based on the view that the seriousness of the grosser forms of sexual assault apart from rape is not fully appreciated and that a change in the law is needed to stigmatise more <Col N="1915" /> adequately these acts.  In the Government's view, these assaults are viewed with total abhorrence by people.  If there is any need to reinforce that perception by changes in the law the provisions of the Bill, particularly the penalty of life imprisonment and trial in the Central Criminal Court, fully meet that need.</P>
    <P>However, a broadening of the definition of rape could work against the interests of women.  The effect of bringing a number of offences within the definition of rape might well be to change the public perception of rape.  The public would no longer know when a rape as at present defined had been committed and, as a result, the stigma and odium which the public attach to rape could be reduced, thus bringing about the opposite result to that desired.</P>
    <P>A benefit which the majority of the commission claim for extending the definition of rape is that such a change could offer to victims of serious sexual assaults other than rape some degree of psychological reassurance by describing the experience to which they had been subjected to as rape.  In the Government's view this claim, even if it has any substance, is not an adequate reason for changing the long-established concept of rape.  Again, it can be replied that any psychological reassurance that may be thought to be needed will be supplied by the obvious seriousness with which the Bill treats serious sexual assaults other than rape; in effect, the Bill equates these assaults to rape in seriousness.</P>
    <P>In summary, therefore, in the Government's view the substantive arguments advanced for extending the definition of rape are met by the creation of the new offence of aggravated sexual assault, by providing that these offences will be triable in the Central Criminal Court and by the extension to victims of all sexual assaults of the protection at present afforded to rape victims.  I hope that on reconsideration of the matter and taking into account the considerations which decided the Government not to propose extending the definition of rape, Senators who spoke on this question will agree <Col N="1916" /> that in a difficult area in which there are conflicting views the proposals in the Bill are a proper response to the concerns expressed.</P>
    <P>Senator Fennell, Senator Ryan and others raised the question of the penetration of the anus by an object not being specifically included in the definition of aggravated sexual assault.  There are difficulties in this regard but I assure Senators at the outset that if there was a grave sexual assault involving penetration of the anus by an object it would come within the general definition in the Bill of aggravated sexual assault.  There is no doubt about that.  The difficulty relates to making specific mention in section 3 (1) of the penetration of the anus by an object.  There are circumstances where penetration of the anus by an object might not, in fact, amount to an aggravated sexual assault. For example, you could have horseplay between schoolboys which results in penetration of the anus by an object such as a pencil and it would not normally be appropriate in such circumstances to charge aggravated sexual assault.  I am sure Senators could think of other examples.  If in such cases the violation amounted to a sexual assault, then it would have to be charged as aggravated sexual assault and tried in the Central Criminal Court if the Bill, in section 3 (1) (b), included penetration of the anus by an object.</P>
    <P>Senators Fennell, Manning, Bulbulia, Robinson and others referred to a proposal that has been made that there be separate legal representation for rape victims. This proposal was examined by the Law Reform Commission and was strongly rejected.  They raised the question of the constitutional propriety of the proposal and went on to point out that in some cases separate legal representation might actually lead to unjustified acquittals of the accused.  My understanding of the situation is that the reason this proposal was put forward in the first place was a perception that complainants were not being sufficiently protected by prosecuting counsel and they felt alienated from the legal process.  The commission <Col N="1917" /> were of the view that these problems could be resolved within the confines of the existing legal system.  I agree with them on this point.</P>
    <P>For the information of the House, I might say, that I raised this matter with the Director of Public Prosecutions and he agrees with the general approach of the Law Reform Commission.  There are certain administrative steps that he has taken or intends taking in the near future which, when fully implemented, will be of particular benefit to complainants in sexual cases.  The Director of Public Prosecutions considers it important that the complainant in a sexual case be furnished without delay with a copy of her statement and be afforded access to the solicitor and counsel acting for the prosecution before the hearing of the case in court.  Such consultation already happens in the great majority of cases as a result of arrangements made by his office some years ago, although there is still some residual opposition from individual barristers.</P>
    <P>The Director of Public Prosecutions now proposes that when it has been decided that a case is being prosecuted on indictment and the book of evidence is being prepared, all proposed witnesses, except gardaí and certain professional witnesses, will be sent a copy of their statement on which will be endorsed a request to study it carefully and to notify any alterations or additions which the witness may wish to make to a named prosecuting lawyer, usually a State solicitor. This will be in addition to the complainant receiving a copy of his or her statement at an earlier stage.  It is further proposed by the Director of Public Prosecutions that a pre-trial consultation will be held with all witnesses at which they would collectively be asked if their evidence will correspond with their statements and, if not, to specify the variations.</P>
    <P>Of the proposed arrangements only the supplying of the statements to the witnesses has so far been implemented to any extent.  However, it is hoped to implement the arrangements in full very shortly.  This will ensure that in sexual <Col N="1918" /> cases there will always be contact between the complainant and the prosecuting team.  In addition, what could be described as a familiarisation course will be made available to the complainant on request in which the layout and procedure of the court will be explained to the complainant and in which she will be advised, in very general terms, of the type of question which she might be asked.</P>
    <P>Senators Fennell, Fitzsimons, Cassidy and others referred to the funding of the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre.  The Senators will no doubt be aware that the Government, as the Minister for Finance announced in his budget speech, have decided to provide £100,000 for the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre.  I am glad to know that Senators on all sides of the House welcome this announcement and other comments made in this regard today will be brought by me to the attention of the Minister for Health who has overall responsibility in this area.</P>
    <P>I agree entirely with what was said by Senators McKenna, Fallon and others when they referred to the abuse of wives by drunken husbands.  The law makes no excuse for a man who, in a drunken state, rapes a woman.  I also agree with the Senators when they say that serious sexual abuse merits substantial penalties and the Bill reflects that view very strongly.  Senator Ryan referred to the recommendation of the Law Reform Commission that the words &ldquo;imbecile&rdquo;, &ldquo;idiot&rdquo; and &ldquo;feeble-minded&rdquo; in the 1935 Criminal Law (Amendment) Act, be replaced by the words &ldquo;mentally handicapped&rdquo;. As I have said, the matter is not free from difficulty.  The reason is that it is not simply a matter of replacing existing words with new words.  It would probably be necessary to define any new phraseology that might be used and establishing such new definitions raises complex, legal, psychiatric and social issues.  A balance has to be struck between protecting persons with severe mental handicap or infirmity from sexual abuse and avoiding what might be regarded as an unwarranted intrusion into the personal life of persons only <Col N="1919" /> slightly handicapped who feel they have a right to lead a full life.</P>
    <P>To come up with a definition that is accepted in legal, psychiatric and social terms would require detailed consideration and consultation.  The Law Reform Commission will be looking at the general law, including the 1935 Act relating to sexual offences on the mentally handicapped in connection with their examination of the law on child sexual abuse.  It would be far preferable to deal with the particular definitions in the 1935 Act in the context of the overall review which has been promised by the Law Reform Commission.  However, I agree entirely that words such as &ldquo;imbecile&rdquo;, &ldquo;idiot&rdquo; and &ldquo;feeble-minded&rdquo; are no longer acceptable.</P>
    <P>Another point raised by Senator Ryan was the question of having a definition of consent in the Bill on the lines suggested by the Law Reform Commission.  The Bill, of course, already provides that any failure or omission by a person to offer resistance to an act does not of itself constitute consent to the act.  Senator Ryan thinks we should go further than that but I must disagree with him on that point.  As far as I am aware, and indeed as far as the Law Reform Commission were aware when producing their consultation paper and report, the fact that consent is not statutorily defined has not given rise to any problems in rape trials. On this basis alone I see no justification for including a definition of consent in the Bill.</P>
    <P>More importantly, however, there are strong reasons for not attempting to provide a statutory definition of consent and any attempt to do so could give rise to considerable difficulties.  The draft suggested by the commission, which is based on a definition in the law of Western Australia but subsequently rejected by the Law Reform Commission of the State of Victoria, is flawed and could effect significant changes in the existing law, changes which the commission do not advocate.</P>
    <P>The difficulties arise particularly in cases where consent is vitiated by the fact <Col N="1920" /> that it was obtained by fraud or threats. In the case of fraud, for example, there is no consent where a man induces a woman to have sexual intercourse by impersonating her husband.  In such a case the man can be found guilty of rape. Nor is there any consent where the fraud relates to the nature of the act.  However, misrepresentations by a man as to his wealth or willingness to marry would not vitiate consent to intercourse and rape would not be committed in such circumstances.</P>
    <P>In the case of sexual intercourse obtained by threats, it would be impossible in a statutory definition to draw the line between those threats under which the act would constitute rape and those which would not constitute a basis for a charge of rape.  Sexual intercourse obtained by a threat to kill or seriously injure a woman clearly constitutes rape but a threat to break off an engagement if the woman does not consent to sexual intercourse would surely not be sufficient to ground a charge for rape.  In between these two points is a grey area which can only be resolved case by case.  Therefore, I would be opposed to having consent statutorily defined as it would inevitably cause considerable difficulty and confusion without, on the other hand, effecting any improvement in the existing situation.</P>
    <P>Senator Norris quite legitimately asked for an explanation of section 13 of the Bill.  Section 8 of the 1981 Act provides for the anonymity of the accused after he has been charged with a rape offence. Restrictions on the publication or broadcasting of matter likely to identify the accused as having been charged with a rape offence may at present only be lifted on the application of the accused himself or another person charged with a rape offence at the trial or after he has been convicted.</P>
    <P>Section 13, by inserting a new subsection (8) in section 8 of the 1981 Act, provides for another circumstance where the restrictions on publication or broadcasting may be lifted, that is, on the application of the Director of Public Prosecutions on the grounds of public <Col N="1921" /> interest.  This is to cover a situation where, for example, a person charged with a rape offence escapes before the conclusion of his trial and the publication of his identity is necessary to assist in his apprehension.  It would seem that under existing law, even in these circumstances no matter could be published which would be likely to identify the accused. No situation has yet arisen where the restrictions on publication or broadcasting has led to difficulties but that is not to say that such a difficulty might not arise in the future.  This section should resolve any potential problems.</P>
    <P>Senator Norris dealt with the question of previous sexual history.  The 1981 Act introduced a very specific test to deal with this question.  A judge will only allow questions about a complainant's previous sexual history if allowing or not allowing that questioning would make the difference between conviction and acquittal. The matter, therefore, is not open-ended. This test was introduced in 1981 so that the judge trying the case in coming to his decision would have to direct his attention specifically to whether such questioning would have an effect on the verdict of the jury.  Senator Norris also raised the recent judgment of the European Court of Human Rights in his case. The matter dealt with in that judgment is a separate matter requiring detailed consideration and will be dealt with separately.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson referred to the Law Reform Commission's recommendation on the matter of compensation. She felt that each crime should be dealt with separately in so far as it relates to compensation. I am afraid I cannot agree. In my view, it is generally preferable to consider the question as a general issue in the context of all crimes and that I intend to do.</P>
    <P>I thank Members for their warm welcome for this Bill.  I would like them to consider the replies I made to matters of importance and concern which they raised during the course of their participation in the debate.  I thank them for the way in which they approached the Bill <Col N="1922" /> and I look forward to much discussion during Committee Stage whenever the debate takes place.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NualaFennell" hpid="Mrs. Fennell Mrs. Fennell">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Fennell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to thank the Minister for his very detailed reply. Indeed, I am very happy that we did not get the premature reply which we nearly got in his absence at the start of the debate.  It was well worth while and this is why I wanted the Minister to be there. I have to say that his adherence to the traditional view as to why the concept of rape should not be extended or defined is regrettable, I suggest that, again, it is because of the pregnancy element.  May I suggest that the Minister listens a bit more to women in this particular area because the people surrounding him are men and a lot of the people he spoke about are men.  This is terribly important because I believe the Minister will go off and deliberate.  He should ask the Minister of State, Deputy Geoghegan-Quinn, about this because I know she feels very strongly about it.  I would like to thank the Minister very sincerely.  We will be seeing him another day on all this.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Cregan) Acting Chairman (Mr. Cregan)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Cregan)</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardCollins" hpid="Mr. Collins Mr. Collins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Collins</NameTxt>
      <P>The House would need at least two weeks to consider amendments and we will let the Whips agree on a time between themselves.  It is important legislation but it is important that we do not rush it.  I would like to explain to the House that through no fault of mine I was missing when the debate went on because of serious family business.  I apologise for that.  The views of all persons are always taken into account and I never differentiate between female views and male views.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NualaFennell" hpid="Mrs. Fennell Mrs. Fennell">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Fennell</NameTxt>
      <P>This is why I think it is important.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardCollins" hpid="Mr. Collins Mr. Collins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Collins</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Seanad will agree it is very important that I listen to all sides, as I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1923" /> Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 15 February 1989.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Firearms and Offensive Weapons" RHead="Bill, 1989: Order for Second Stage">
    <Title>Firearms and Offensive Weapons Bill, 1989: Order for Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Bill entitled an Act to amend and extend the Firearms Acts, 1925 to 1971, to control the availability and possession of offensive weapons and other articles and to provide for certain other matters connected with the matters aforesaid.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Second Stage be ordered for Wednesday, 8 February 1989.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 4.5 p.m. and resumed at 6.30 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we commence the item before us this evening, I have just heard that Senator Mary Robinson, our distinguished colleague with long service in this House, has been declared Mayo Person of the Year and I want to express mu heartiest congratulations to her.  I am absolutely delighted for her.  It is a well-deserved honour and I am delighted that it has come from Mayo.  I wish her great happiness in the year ahead.  These awards may seem small but they are terribly important.  I am delighted for Senator Robinson.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to join with the Cathaoirleach in congratulating Senator Mary Robinson on this distinguished honour she has received.  The Minister is from Mayo and he knows it is a very important county.  It is a wonderful honour for the Senator and I hope that she enjoys every day as Mayo Person of the Year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulBradford" hpid="Mr. Bradford Mr. Bradford">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bradford</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of the Fine <Col N="1924" /> Gael Party I should like to add our sincere congratulations to Senator Robinson on this well earned award.  I am sure she will fill the position with distinction.  She follows a very fine line of previous recipients of this award.  It will certainly highlight the granting of the award and I sincerely congratulate her personally and on behalf of the Fine Gael Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to join with the Cathaoirleach in extending to our colleague, Senator Mary Robinson, our very best wishes and congratulations on receiving this great honour.  Senator Robinson has achieved many honours in her time.  She has achieved honour at European level and at national level in the past and it is only fitting that her native county would so honour her at this stage in her career, which has been a tremendous career for a lady with a lot of courage.  She has never been afraid to express her views on all sorts of subjects, on which she is an expert.  Other high office-holders in this country have already been conferred with this honour and there is no better person than Senator Robinson to receive it on this occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanHaughey" hpid="Mr. S. Haughey Mr. S. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, as a fellow Trinity graduate, offer sincere congratulations to Senator Mary Robinson. Given the previous recipients of the award, she is in very good company.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>As co-ordinator of the Independent group we consider ourselves to be asking in the reflected glory.  To be honoured in one's own place is the highest honour of all because that is always the most difficult one to achieve. I am sure Senator Mary Robinson knows that better than most having fought the county through two referenda down through the years.  I congratulate the Senator.  I see the Minister of State looking askance at me.  I can supply chapter and verse if he wishes to hear more on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCalleary" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. Calleary) Sean Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. Calleary)</NameTxt>
      <P>With the permission of the Cathaoirleach, may I also offer my congratulations to Senator <Col N="1925" /> Robinson on the very well deserved distinction. As Senator Haughey has said, she is in very good company.  She has had a very distinguished and long career, both politically and legally.  As a fellow Mayo person I offer her my sincere congratulations. I have known Senator Robinson for probably longer than anybody here &mdash; I do not think either of us would like to go back to the length of time we know each other.  Because of that it is very gratifying to see somebody who has had such a distinguished career from Mayo still being honoured by the Mayo Association.  I offer my sincere congratulations to her.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I call Senator Robinson, I am sure the Clerk and the Assistant Clerk of the Seanad would like to be associated with the remarks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Cathaoirleach, the Minister, my colleagues and friends.  I am very touched indeed at the acknowledgement of the honour that has been given me.  I was very surprised when I was contacted and told that I had been chosen as Mayo Person of the Year and I felt particularly pleased because as Senator O'Toole said it was from my own people, my own county.  That is probably more precious than any other type of acknowledgement or any other type of honour that might come.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Indeed, as the Minister will appreciate, I felt very much that I should respond as Mary Bourke.  It was Mary Bourke who grew up in and has stayed very close to Ballina and to Mayo generally.  It is a very favoured place with my children.  My roots there are extremely strong and very well nurtured and will continue to be very strong and very well nurtured.  There is a value in having a place that I have known all my life, that I visit very frequently, where I know all the people and where I have kept very closely in touch.  It is an enormous resource and tremendous way of reflecting on the country in general and on what I am about.  It is a very strong connection.  I am delighted to share the <Col N="1926" /> honour with the Bonniconlon Community Council who got the group medal award for 1989.  That also gave me particular pleasure.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Human Rights in Tibet:" RHead="Motion (Resumed)">
    <Title>Human Rights in Tibet: Motion (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann&mdash;</P>
    <P>(1)  Noting the 40th Anniversary of the United Nations Declaration of Human Rights, and noting that Chinese police on 10th December, 1988 in Lhasa fired pointblank at a non-violent parade of Tibetans marking the said anniversary resulting in the death of several Tibetan monks and the injury of nearly thirty other people, including a Dutch tourist, and</P>
    <P>(2)  Noting the Irish Government's support for the fundamental rights and very existence of the Tibetan nation at the United Nations, with particular reference to Resolutions 1353 (XIV) of 21st October, 1959, 1723 (XVI) of 20th December, 1961 and 2079 (XX) of 18th December, 1965, and</P>
    <P>(3)  Noting that an estimated 1.20 million Tibetans have been killed since the Chinese invasion of Tibet in 1949,</P>
    <P>(4)  Concerned that an estimated 2,200 monks, nuns and lay Tibetans were imprisoned without trial, interrogated and tortured following demonstrations in Lhasa in October, 1987 and March, 1988&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  strongly condemns the Chinese regime for its grave violation of human rights in Tibet and calls on other international bodies to protest these actions,</P>
    <P>(b)  urges the Irish Government to support all international measures for establishing peace and the respect for human rights in Tibet,</P>
    <P>(c)  calls on the Irish Government to instigate a motion in support of <Col N="1927" /> the Tibetan people at the United Nations.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Senator Robinson)</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I am trying to dispel the nice sentiments out of the Chamber for the moment and to bring the Minister back to close attention on this.  We have had no indication on how the Minister will respond but we are hopeful that the Government will show an enlightened and progressive approach to this matter. I know the Minister would feel very close to the comments that were made by his fellow county person, Senator Robinson, last week and would wish to support those views and the positive proposals from her.  I look forward to hearing from him.</P>
      <P>The difficulty we have, which the Minister will not refer to, is the fact that nowadays everybody needs China and everybody wants to be friends with China, and if you are not friends with China it can be a costly thing in commercial and trade terms throughout the world.  That is the underlying issue which will not be adverted to in the response of nations to the problems in Tibet.  It is the underlying cause for the lack of response in the western and developed world to the problems of Tibet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Tibet, Nepal and that area over the centuries was considered to be almost a closed part of the world and it is now suffering from that reputation.  It is a country that over the years has been a peaceful one, where the head of State, the Dalai Lama was also the head of the religion in the area, the Tibetan Buddhism, an area where they have had stable government from 1391 or roughly that period, 100 years before the discovery of the United States of America. Since that time there has been stability and succession until 1959.  In 1959, because of the abolition of the republic through the invasion and the influence of China the Dalai Lama had to leave and has since been in exile.  He lives away from Tibet.  From 1912 until 1959 Tibet operated as a republic.  This was abolished by the Chinese.  That is the sort of <Col N="1928" /> background which has been well teased out by previous speakers.</P>
    <P>It is important to recognise that the issues we are talking about are the issues of self-determination, the right to self-rule, the right to participation in democracy which is of particular importance, and the right to human, civil and political rights.  That is why this matter is being discussed here tonight.  We are discussing the position of the people in Tibet.  The proposals in the motion are a response to the position of the Tibetan people at the moment.</P>
    <P>In many other ways it is an issue of decolonisation.  We have all had experience of that and in Ireland it strikes a chord.  I ask Senators to respond in their own way to it.  The fact is that the Tibetan people at the moment are under the uncaring hand of China and have been controlled by suppression and violence. It is not without much consideration that I would criticise a nation which aspires to socialism as China purports to do but it is not socialist practice to rule with the system of suppression and violence which is now the day-to-day reality of life in Tibet.</P>
    <P>The Tibetan people can best at the moment be described as fifth-class people in their own country, with little or no access to civil or political rights.  As a country they have suffered massively and are still suffering the results of the Cultural Revolution which extended into Tibet.  During that time a very sensitive, well developed education service was erased.  Starting from scratch, with the idea of the revolution starting at nought, they are still at nought.  There is no access to proper education facilities in Tibet at the moment because of the refusal of the Chinese rulers to invest in a developed education service.</P>
    <P>A similar case can be made about the health service.  It is not being developed. There is not access to a decent health service for the Tibetan people.  Hand-in-hand with the oppression, poverty and suppression there is a rich country, a country of natural richness, beauty, minerals and many other assets which at the moment are being exploited, and many <Col N="1929" /> of the assets exported by the Chinese rulers in Tibet.  The people of Tibet do not profit from the wealth of their own country.  Apart from the loss of civil rights and the material loss, the Chinese have now made Tibet a nuclear dump with the positioning and basing of nuclear arms and nuclear warheads in Tibet, and also we are told, with the use of areas of Tibet for experiments in chemical warfare.</P>
    <P>I hope the Minister will respond to those two points because there is a clear policy of the Government on the question of nuclear proliferation and the extension of nuclear activities in other countries.  I hope the nettle will be grasped and a decent response given to it, to say to us, &ldquo;We are not prepared to comment on another Government&rdquo; but not to ignore the fact that this is happening in Tibet. The world deserves to know about what is happening and developed First World countries need to respond to it.</P>
    <P>We also hear about the terror and intimidation that is being brought to bear on the people of Tibet who are seen or known to speak with or in any way have any interaction with non-Tibetans. Amnesty International published a report in February 1988 on Tibet and what is going on there.  They referred at some length to the question of detention without trial, to the widespread ill-treatment of detainees, of detainees being held incommunicado without access to lawyers, to family or friends, and allegations of brutality and ill-treatment of detainees while being arrested or while being held in detention.  That is the position there at the moment.  We do not get too many reports because there is almost an international news black-out.  There is need to expose what is happening in Tibet so that the world will know about it.  We get reports of police shooting civilians on a number of occasions.  We have had descriptions of Buddhist monks demonstrating for the independence of Tibet on a number of occasions over the past couple of years and, in particular, last March on the 29th anniversary of the loss of the republic.</P>
    <P>The question of harassment, arrests, intimidation of peaceful demonstrators <Col N="1930" /> and scenes of violence has been the story from Tibet over the past number of years and it is growing.  Next month will be the 30th anniversary of the abolition of the republic.  Undoubtedly there will be demonstrations, violence, killings.  Our request here is that the world takes note and that the world responds.  Our control and influence extends through this State. Tonight we are requesting that this State takes note and responds, takes a lead and shows responsibility in responding to the problems of the people of Tibet.  It is not a time to bow to the sensitivities of the Chinese.  It is not a time for us to say: &ldquo;Let us not put our trade, commercial prospects and material gain at risk for the sake of a suppressed and oppressed people&rdquo;.  Our history should not allow us to do that.</P>
    <P>I appeal to the Minister first to address the issue, to respond to the rights and wrongs of the issue, to indicate how the Government read the scene and then to indicate to us the action the Government propose to take.  In the area of action it is the responsibility of people like myself, if I am to stand and demand things of Government and perhaps try and influence the direction taken by Government, to have some proposals to make and I would like to make very definite proposals to the Minister.  I ask that the Irish Ambassador to India or to China lead a fact-finding mission to Tibet on behalf of the Government, to meet the people, to meet the different interest groups on all sides and to put together a report on what they have found.  The report of the mission led by an Irish Ambassador should be brought to the Government. Following consideration of that report by the Government they should seek formal discussion with the Chinese authorities to assess the situation internationally and participate internationally.</P>
    <P>I hope I will not get a sort of &ldquo;I am all right Jack&rdquo; response or &ldquo;It is none of our business&rdquo;.  If we participate in the international community we have responsibilities and duties as well as privileges and rights.  What might be right in terms of trade might be all wrong morally. The objective of the discussions the <Col N="1931" /> Irish Government might have with the Chinese authorities would be to persuade the Chinese to move towards granting civil and political rights to the people of Tibet and that they would respect and recognise the dignity and culture of the Tibetan people, that the Irish Government would demand that the Chinese discuss with the Dalai Lama, the religious and political head of the Tibetan people, a programme which would lead to self-rule for the Tibetan people.</P>
    <P>I have briefly referred to the history of Tibet, to international opinion and in some sense have summarised what has been said about Tibet.  I have put forward proposals.  Those proposals should start off with the prerequisite that we would not be dependent on the propaganda of other Foreign Offices, that we would take the lead ourselves, that we would send on behalf of the State an Irish Ambassador on a fact-finding mission to Tibet, who would report back and set the ball rolling for an intervention by this State in resolving the problems of the Tibetan people.  I commend the motion and support it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>In supporting this motion totally in the wording used, a motion signed by my colleague, Senator Jack Harte on behalf of the Labour Party, we went over in detail the actual requirements of the resolution on Government. We did so in the knowledge that, first of all, there is a contravention of the human rights of the Tibetan people and, secondly, there is the principle of how the Irish Government, as a neutral nation, a long-serving member of the United Nations, have a proud history of defending minorities and defending oppressed people throughout the world.  The Department of Foreign Affairs originally proposed that China be admitted to the United Nations.  That courageous act carried out by the late Frank Aiken in his day as an Irish Minister for Foreign Affairs showed a marked departure from the attitude of people of that era to the whole concept of allowing a different ideology and culture to take part in the magnificent <Col N="1932" /> organisation of the United Nations.  That is something we can be proud of.  In doing that we were of the belief that any country we would support and sponsor for membership of the United Nations would live up to the charters of that organisation for oppressed people throughout the world.  That is why they have declarations from time to time on important subjects. Forty years ago they issued a declaration on the rights of individuals, namely, United Nations Declarations of Human Rights.  We are all proud of it.  We are coming up to the anniversary of that declaration.</P>
      <P>It staggered all of us to hear that when a non-violent people, the Tibetans, had a small demonstration of that recognition of independence some of them were mowed down in cold blood for just a passive demonstration to remind the oppressors, the Chinese, that they had broken that convention.  Those of us who have read books on Tibet have looked in amazement at their magnificent culture which has been influenced by their religious beliefs on reincarnation.  A nation which is so steeped in religious culture, that was never among the warring factions in the world, to be annexed by such a powerful nation as China, a nuclear nation, is against all the principles we have ever espoused in this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is for that reason that we are asking the Government to do something through our membership of the United Nations which has issued these charters.  They have three declarations with refer specifically to Tibet which we supported. I hope we will reaffirm our support for them.  We should also do so as part of the European Community.  As part of the 12 countries we carry some weight and, hopefully, we can in the Council of Ministers there stimulate an interest by the European Community in the misfortunes of Tibet which has a proud religious belief in pacifism.  If a Catholic nation had been occupied by another country, particularly a communist country like China, then we would not be sitting here tonight discussing it; we would be participating in every activity to ensure the freedom of <Col N="1933" /> that country because we would believe that from the religious point of view alone, they had a right to self-determination.</P>
    <P>We have been slow in being associated with other areas of discrimination of human rights.  The Israelis have done some extraordinary things to the Palestinians, coinciding with the 40th anniversary of the UN Declaration of Human Rights.  There have been advancements in that regard, and we welcome them, but our Government have to do more than just be involved in associations like the United Nations and the European Community.  As a nation which is respected throughout the world for its impartiality, its acceptance of the rights of minorities and oppressed people, its nuclear stance, its support of most of the principles of CND and its recognition that the Chinese are now using Tibet as a dumping ground, not alone for nuclear waste but also as a base for nuclear weapons, the distribution of nuclear chemicals and other deadly weapons which are condemned and outlawed by international law, how can we stand by and allow what is happening in Tibet to continue?</P>
    <P>I hope that in his response the Minister of State, Deputy Calleary, will be receptive to the motion as it is worded at present.  If there are some areas the Minister is worried about he should communicate them to us.  I do not think this is a subject the House should divide on by voting because it could be a misrepresentation of the support we have for the Tibetan people.  One of the ways we can overcome the necessity of having this type of debate here is to establish a foreign affairs committee of both Houses of the Oireachtas&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;who would have an input into deciding how we should deal with problems such as this in a structured way.  This committee could advise the Minister and the officials in the Department of Foreign Affairs who, unfortunately, are not permitted to go outside recognised parameters which have been <Col N="1934" /> set for them by precedent and otherwise. Most other democratic states already have this type of committee and they make a major contribution in assisting governments in the formulation of their foreign policies and I believe such a committee should be set up here to assist our Government.</P>
      <P>The Minister should take on board the suggestion, which has been passed by resolution in this House, to establish an all-party foreign affairs committee.  I am confident that there are people in this House who could make a major contribution to that committee.  I believe their work would be recognised by the Department of Foreign Affairs for what it would be, namely, assistance in the formulation of policy.  I do not know whether an ambassador has the right to carry out an independent investigation &mdash; perhaps that is outside his brief &mdash; but maybe the Minister will say how people in Ireland can get first-hand information about what is happening in Tibet.  If we have the information then we can act on it and if the information is obtained at ambassadorial level, parliamentary level or by the officials in the Department of Foreign Affairs or by the Minister, we should pursue it to make sure we have the correct facts and figures before us about the loss of life.  To all intents and purposes the Tibetan people are living in a concentration camp or a work camp; they have no right to self-determination, the expression of civil liberty or any of the rights, which they as a small nation aspire to having.  I do not think this motion is asking our Government to do too much in this case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaulBradford" hpid="Mr. Bradford Mr. Bradford">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bradford</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support the motion and to congratulate the movers on bringing it before the House. While my comments might be slightly repetitive, it was about time we got the opportunity to speak about the problem which faces the Tibetan people today and, in that respect, I think the more attention given to the matter the better. Unfortunately, up to now we have perhaps regarded this problem as one that is out of sight and therefore out of mind, <Col N="1935" /> but we must now face the sad reality that under the present regime the future for the people of Tibet is not very bright.  In fact, one wonders if there is any future at all for them.  Their problems have to be brought to the centre of the world political stage and while this motion which, hopefully, will be passed by Seanad Éireann tonight, may not produce an immediate response, it will be a move in the right direction.  We must at least make whatever move we can at that level.</P>
      <P>The history of the people of Tibet is a very sad example of the violation of the human rights of a minority people.  The fact that this problem has not been on our political agenda at the level it should have been reflects in a sense what was said by Senator O'Toole earlier tonight &mdash; perhaps we do not want to criticise a régime who we feel are moving slightly in our direction and we do not want to rock the boat.  If we are to note the positive changes that have taken place in China, and one day to recognise China as a totally mature, free, democratic country, then the Chinese themselves must act in the sort of manner that would befit such a country.  However, while that country is stamping down &mdash; and I think one could use that phrase &mdash; the people of Tibet, we must be quite reserved in our position towards China.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I hope that the political difficulties which face the Irish Government in criticising a country of the size of China will not stop us from making the points that have to be made and will not stop the Government from raising this issue at the highest possible level.  We do not have the military might, the financial might or economic wealth of larger nations but as a small, independent, neutral country I think our voice will be heard and we must use that voice in whatever forum is available to us.  While the issue of Tibet may be far away from us in a sense it should not be regarded by the Irish people as being remote.  Our history has shown us what can happen to a country that is forgotten by its neighbours.  We must do what we can for small countries <Col N="1936" /> the world over and if enough countries try to bring the problems of Tibet to the world stage then hopefully, action will be taken on their problems.</P>
    <P>The history of Tibet has been well documented during the debate on this motion but I would like to briefly refer again to the major difficulties which have arisen in that country since it was invaded by the Chinese in 1949.  Since those days the people of Tibet have been persecuted, their religious and democratic rights have been removed totally from them and by taking their minerals and other sources of wealth, etc., their economic wealth has been removed from them also.  Much of this has been done by the use of forced labour, as operated by the Chinese authorities.  We are talking about a people whose political freedom, democratic rights and religious liberties have been removed from them and whose economic wealth is being removed from them on a daily basis.</P>
    <P>The facts of the matter speak for themselves. The Tibetan people will become a minority race: in Tibet at present there are only 1.8 million Tibetans as opposed to 2.5 million Chinese.  That shows the extent of the problem which has been created as a direct result of modern-day colonialisation.  The Tibetan people have always regarded themselves as an independent race and just not an autonomous area within China.  Unfortunately, their voice has not been heard on the world stage and their problems have not been presented as they should have been.  As a result, their difficulties and sufferings have been more or less ignored or kept from us for the past 40 years, and, in particular, since the 1959 rising.  The Cultural Revolution operated by Mao Tsetung between 1966 and 1976 had, of course, a dramatic effect on a country such as Tibet which had serious enough problems in 1966.  As a result of the Cultural Revolution the monasteries in Tibet &mdash; I believe almost 6,500 of them &mdash; were destroyed, the Tibetan language, religion and the culture were repressed and removed almost totally from the people of the country.</P>
    <P>As Senator Ferris said, we would speak <Col N="1937" /> in very lofty tones if there was a problem such as this in Europe, particularly in eastern Europe, but because this is happening many miles away from us we think we are removed from it.  Unfortunately we have to face the fact that while there is a problem, regardless of where it is, we have some responsibility for highlighting it and for attempting to take action to seek a solution.  The continual threat to Tibet and its population from Chinese emigrants must not be understated. Developments in the country over the next few years will finally determine whether Tibet will lapse further into a state of apartheid or whether it will return to the sort of country the people of Tibet wish it to be.  We speak very loudly about apartheid in countries on whom the media may be focused but there is also a very serious problem of apartheid in Tibet and we do not even give it a mention. The form of apartheid being experienced by the Tibetan people is very serious and must be addressed.</P>
    <P>I think Senator O'Toole spoke on this issue and spoke of the total lack of education and health care facilities available to those people.  We have to recognise that people who live under conditions such as those do not have any future and we must insist on action being taken to counteract this.  The failings in regard to human rights in that country at present, and indeed over the past 30 to 40 years, must be noted and we must seek to redress them.  They are as severe as those in any country in eastern Europe or in South America but, again, they do not get the media attention those other countries get.  I suppose it illustrates the power of the press that even primary school children in our country can talk about South Africa, Poland and East Berlin while at the same time very few people in this country know anything at all about the problem being faced by the people of Tibet.  On that basis I believe the more media attention given to this problem the better chance we will have of getting a response from the Chinese authorities.</P>
    <P>With regard to the specific question of what we as a nation can do to redress the situation, we may not have the wealth, <Col N="1938" /> the armaments or the economic voice to make a huge difference but we must try to ensure that the forum of the United Nations is used by us to the maximum extent possible to raise the plight of these unfortunate people.  I hope that the kernel of the motion, paragraph 4 (c), which calls on the Irish Government to instigate a motion at the United Nations in support of the Tibetan people, will be seriously considered by the Government. Not only do we have a right to do this but we have a duty to do so because when we can see a small country like Tibet being almost removed from existence by a new superpower, nineties-style colonisation, we cannot stand idly by.</P>
    <P>I hope for a positive response from the Minister when he replies to this motion. As Senator Ferris said, I hope we do not have a division on this motion because it would be in the interests of the House and of democracy for a forum such as Seanad Éireann to throw its full weight behind the people of Tibet and initiate a public debate on the issue.  The more mention we make of this problem, the more speedy will be the response of the people who will decide the future of Tibet, namely, the Chinese authorities.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCalleary" hpid="Minister for State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. Calleary) Minister for State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. Calleary)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for State at the Department of Foreign Affairs (Mr. Calleary)</NameTxt>
      <P>First, I want to thank Senator Robinson in particular for putting down the motion because it gives us the opportunity to discuss human rights in Tibet.  However, the Government could not endorse a motion phrased in the terms of the one that is before this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Ireland has taken a position on human rights in Tibet and elsewhere in the world.  Together with our partners in the European Community we have a deep commitment to the respect, protection and further promotion of human rights which we consider a cornerstone of European co-operation and security and an essential element in our relations with third countries.  With the adoption of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and the subsequent human rights treaties, the protection of human rights has become an essential duty of the international <Col N="1939" /> community as well as of each of its members.  Neither the need to respect national boundaries nor the principle of non-interference in domestic affairs lessen this obligation of the members of the international community.</P>
    <P>Ireland has sought also to be helpful in integrating the People's Republic of China into the UN and for that reason, as was mentioned by Senator Ferris, voted in the UN in favour of discussion of Chinese membership.  We did not establish diplomatic relations with the People's Republic of China until 1979. At that time we recognised the Government of the People's Republic of China as the sole legal Government of China. At the time we established diplomatic relations, Tibet was part of the territory of the People's Republic of China and is part of that territory today.</P>
    <P>The question of Tibet is a long-standing and complex one.  Its status has historically been the subject of some debate. As Senator Robinson outlined very explicitly in her contribution the extent of the geographical area of Tibet is a matter of some dispute between different parties based on the historical interpretation of each.  I can see no point in focusing on the historical origins of Tibet or what may constitute its boundaries because this motion addresses the issue of human rights.  Ireland has been encouraged by positive developments in Chinese policy towards Tibet in recent years.  The shift in that policy has been recognised in the Council of Europe and I would also refer Senators and, in particular, Senator O'Toole, to the publication <i>Asia Watch</i> report of February 1988 which outlines the progress that has been made in recent times.</P>
    <P>In the last decade there has been a conscious and demonstrable effort by the Chinese Government to ease tensions and to implement economic and other reforms in Tibet.  In 1987 the Chinese authorities stressed a continued commitment to liberalisation and autonomy in Tibet which has been an autonomous region of the People's Republic of China since 1965.  This policy has benefited the <Col N="1940" /> Tibetan people especially in the economic field.  Developments in other fields include the reopening of monasteries and the increasing percentage of Tibetans in local government.  This conciliatory approach was reflected in the amnesty announced by the Chinese authorities for most of those arrested for taking part in the disturbances in autumn 1987.  It is suggested from reports and documentation submitted by the Tibetan support group that of the numbers who were arrested in 1987 approximately 100 are still in prison.</P>
    <P>Senators have referred to resolutions on the question of Tibet adopted by the United Nations in the past.  Ireland supported these because of a concern for the necessity to protect human rights which is not confined to Tibet.  These resolutions essentially dealt with the need for respect for the human rights of the people of Tibet.  As mentioned by Senator O'Toole it is clear that the Tibetans, like other nationalities within the territory of the People's Republic of China, have their own language, religious beliefs, customs and habits.  We continue to attach great importance to respect for human rights, not only in Tibet but elsewhere in the world also.  The Chinese authorities are well aware of the importance which Ireland and its partners in the European Community attach to human rights being scrupulously observed.</P>
    <P>In many of the debates I have taken part in there seemed to be almost a condemnation that quite often we as a Government talk about what we do in relation to human rights by referring to &ldquo;our concern, with that of our European partners&rdquo; but so long as our principles and philosophies are accepted by our European partners we will continue to use them.  We have adopted clear and unequivocal moral stances on many issues and we will continue to maintain them regardless of what our European partners accept.  In this respect I want to refer in particular to Senator Bulbulia's contribution.  On one occasion in the not too distant past when the Government <Col N="1941" /> deviated from what our European partners did, her party were not very happy about that.</P>
    <P>I have no direct reports of what happened in Tibet during incidents reported to have taken place on 10 December 1988.  However, reports we have seen indicate that further efforts are necessary to ensure that the human rights of Tibetans are fully respected.  Ireland considers that a dialogue between Tibetans and the central authorities in the People's Republic of China can promote the necessary respect for Tibetan human rights.  Irish policy is directed towards encouraging such a dialogue.  As mentioned by Senator O'Toole, both the Dalai Lama and the Chinese authorities have expressed a willingness to hold talks.  China has stated that it respects the religious beliefs, customs and habits of the Tibetan people.</P>
    <P>The Dalai Lama is the respected religious leader of Tibetans and it is understood that his staff are in contact with the Chinese authorities about arranging such a meeting.  Ireland believes that such a dialogue deserves the full support of the international community with a view to resolving the grievances of Tibetans.  As was mentioned by some Senators, the past year has seen a remarkable blossoming in dialogue worldwide to resolve disputes peacefully and we hope that the difficulties and problems in Tibet can be addressed in a similar manner.  Senator O'Toole spoke about the forthcoming 30th anniversary. Our Ambassador in Beijing will clearly monitor developments in Tibet and other parts of the territory of the People's Republic of China and report fully to us on them.</P>
    <P>We are also convinced that it is by promoting such a dialogue that an acceptable solution can be found to the problems which Tibet faces.  Ireland is determined to do everything it can to promote this dialogue with a view to ensuring full respect for the human rights of the people of Tibet in circumstances which are acceptable to all.  However, as I said at the beginning, the Government <Col N="1942" /> could not endorse a motion phrased in the terms of the one before this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I had intended to speak on this motion until I heard what the Minister had to say.  It is the most disappointing reply in a series of disappointing and disastrous replies on foreign policy from the Minister given in this House over the past few months.  It is the worst cop-out that he has produced here after producing a number of copouts on foreign policy.  I would fault him on several things but in particular I would fault him on what I have faulted him on before, that is, his speech continually referred to &ldquo;our attitudes, together with our European partners&rdquo;.  This is simply not good enough from a country which trumpets its neutrality so loudly and which make such a fuss about its neutrality in the internal affairs of the EC. When it comes to having some moral courage on an issue of human rights which should be non-negotiable the Government fail abysmally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>Obviously the Senator was not listening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I read the Minister's speech.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>On page 1 of his speech the Minister said: &ldquo;Together with our partners in the European Community ... &rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>You should also have listened to what I said but which was not in my script.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I listened to what you said about the one occasion you referred to when you deviated from the European Community in the recent past&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisDinoCregan" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Cregan) Acting Chairman (Mr. Cregan)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Cregan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Through the Chair, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very disappointing to hear the Minister admit &mdash; something which I did not know &mdash; that there was <Col N="1943" /> one occasion only in the recent past when we deviated from the European Community.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>I said in the recent past and the Senator did not agree with that deviation either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not on the record as agreeing or disagreeing with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanHaughey" hpid="Mr. S. Haughey Mr. S. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>We can check that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is it only Independent and non-Government Members who are asked to intervene through the Chair?  I note that in the past five minutes one person has been asked to speak through the Chair but there have been three or four interruptions. I ask the Chair to note that fact.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>My apologies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that is a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It is fine so long as it is on the record.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>May I continue without interruption?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you.  I find it very difficult, having listened to the Minister speaking on foreign policy here coincidentally on quite a number of occasions in the past few months, to take this type of standard foreign affairs reply to sensitive, prickly questions.  It seems to me that our neutrality means this: we are frightened of offending the United States on Nicaragua; we are frightened of offending Russia on persecution of the Jews; we are frightened of offending Libya and Iran because of trade; and now we are frightened of saying anything about the Chinese suppression of human rights in Tibet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Our foreign policy and our moral standing in the world are, I put to the <Col N="1944" /> House, a complete shambles if we have to put up with a speech like this which is full of platitudes, which says nothing about condemning the Chinese.  I do not understand why the Minister is frightened of condemning Chinese violations of human rights in Tibet.  Perhaps the Minister is right and it is very difficult to obtain information on what happens in Tibet.  I do not know very much about Tibet and I am quite happy to admit it, but I do not see very much admission in the Minister's speech that he does not know very much about Tibet, or he chooses not to know very much about Tibet.  To a Government like this, human rights should not be negotiable.  It seems to me that to say that the Chinese authorities are doing X, Y, and Z which are direct quotes from Chinese Government statements is not good enough.  It ought to be&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not quote Chinese Government statements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I will find it in a moment.  I will come back to it.  Basically what the Minister said was what the Chinese Government were maintaining and he was respecting that right.  It should be the business of the Government to find out and verify whether these atrocities which are referred to in the motion are true and, if they are, not to hedge their bets on them but simply to condemn them.  I congratulate the Tibetan Action Group who are here this evening on raising public awareness on an issue like this.  It is a great shame that we as a country who fought for self-determination over many years and achieved it are not prepared to stand behind the people of Tibet when they are trying to do this and are not prepared to condemn those who are oppressing them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I will come back to where the Minister quoted Chinese Government policy.  In the middle of page 2 he says: &ldquo;Ireland has been encouraged by positive developments in Chinese policy towards Tibet in recent years&rdquo;.  He goes on to say: &ldquo;In 1987 the Chinese authorities stressed a continued commitment to liberalisation and autonomy in Tibet&rdquo;.  That is an <Col N="1945" /> unquestioning acceptance of what the Chinese have said.  It is an acceptance which I do not go along with.</P>
    <P>Finally, as Senator Ferris and other Senators said, it is a great disappointment to those of us in this House who have tried to get involved in a foreign affairs committee that we cannot have a foreign affairs committee which could discuss matters of this sort and make recommendations to the Minister for Foreign Affairs.  It is a great disappointment that the Government not only will not agree or support this but that the contribution of the Government side to this debate has come exclusively from the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Robinson.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Mrs. Robinson rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry, Senator. I understand another Senator has requested time to speak.  Will Senator Robinson give him some of her time?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnConnor" hpid="Mr. Connor Mr. Connor">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connor</NameTxt>
      <P>Like Senator Ross, I am very disappointed with the Minister's response.  I find it quite inadequate.  We are taking propaganda statements issued by the Chinese Government about events in Tibet, putting them on the record of the House and expressing them as part of the foreign policy of this country.  I do not think that is good enough.  We have all read and seen objective media reports of serious acts of violence committed against the Tibetan people in the very recent past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There used to be a view in the West until pretty recent times that China was to be seen as a delinquent nation who preyed somewhat on her neighbours. That, of course, is not part of Chinese history but, strangely, in terms of its relations towards Tibet it has been.  The irony of it all is that the Chinese-Tibetan claims and the <i>vice versa</i> Tibetan-Chinese claims started hundreds or perhaps 1,000 years ago when a Tibetan leader laid claim to a part of China but there is no recorded historical claim right through the various dynasties in China of a <Col N="1946" /> Chinese Emperor laying a particular historical claim upon Tibet.  That was a phenomenon which appeared after the Chinese Communists took control in China in 1949 when China moved, as large powers are inclined to do, to secure its borders and set up buffer states along its border.  It looked towards Tibet because Tibet was caught there.  It is called the roof of the world.  She moved very quickly.  The Tibetan people were the most peace-loving people in the world.  Their culture was totally anti-violence and they were easy prey for the Chinese.  They might, indeed, have looked north to Mongolia where there is a traditional Chinese claim upon what nowadays we call Outer Mongolia but at that stage Outer Mongolia had become a client State of the Soviet Union and the Chinese did not move in that direction where they would have a far greater historical territorial claim than they ever had in Tibet.</P>
    <P>This motion calls upon the Government here to stand up for the principles that this country has always espoused and abided by down through our history.  We should not forget that this country above all in this part of the world has had a nightmare colonial past of oppression. We should be easily able to find common cause with the people of Tibet who have a religious, cultural, ethnic identity of their own oppressed and suppressed by a much larger neighbour.</P>
    <P>I remember not so many years ago when the Dalai Lama, the religious and civil leader in Tibet, was accepted in this country. He was received by the then President of this country, the late Erskine Childers.  He was given to all intents and purposes the reception and the welcome of a head of State.  There has been a noticeable movement in foreign policy and in the attitude of the Department of Foreign Affairs towards Tibet in recent years.  If a matter of this kind was raised in this House or in the other House a decade ago, the response coming from the Minister would be quite different.  It would, indeed, I suppose, have a lot of the rhetoric of the cold war in it but nevertheless it would be quite different, <Col N="1947" /> a lot more friendly and would give a lot more recognition to the self-determination rights of the Tibetan people.</P>
    <P>I know Senator Robinson is waiting to wind up.  I am grateful that I was given a few moments to express these views.  I support the motion and commend it to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to begin my reply to this debate by referring to a letter which I received just as I was coming into the Chamber for the debate this evening.  It is a letter from the Dalia Lama on his official notepaper dated: 17 January 1989.  The letter is in the following terms:</P>
      <P>Dear Senator Robinson,</P>
      <P>I am glad to learn that with your support a motion condemning the Chinese abuse of human rights in Tibet is to be debated in the Irish Senate on 18 January 1989.</P>
      <P>On behalf of the Tibetan people and on my own behalf, I write to express my deep sense of appreciation for your support to the motion.  I am sure the people of Ireland will be more aware of the true situation in Tibet through such debates in the Irish Senate.</P>
      <P>World-wide interest and support for the state of affairs in Tibet is not only a source of inspiration to us but also one of the most effective ways of drawing the attention of the Chinese authorities to the Tibetan situation which they have been ignoring for so long.</P>
      <P>Thanking you and with good wishes,</P>
      <P>Yours sincerely,</P>
      <P>The letter is signed by the Dalai Lama.</P>
      <P>I wanted to begin by putting that letter on the record because it is important that we recognise, and indeed recognise I hope with a sense that we are doing something useful, that this debate is creating some ripples, that it is having an effect, indeed was having an effect before it began last week and has continued today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to begin by thanking the nine Senators, apart from myself, who spoke.  Ten of us spoke from the floor of <Col N="1948" /> the House and the Minister also contributed as the 11th speaker.  On a motion of this kind that is a very good and broad-based contribution.  However, I was disappointed that the contributions, although representative of Fine Gael, the Labour Party, the Independent Group and indeed Senator Robb, an Independent from the other side of the House, did not contain individual contributions from members of the Fianna Fáil Party. That is disappointing because this is an issue of human rights.  It is an issue in which I am sure individual members of Fianna Fáil have a considerable interest and concern and it is regrettable that we do not have that voice expressly on the record.  Nonetheless I am very grateful to those Senators who have contributed and who have added their voices very strongly to the thrust of the motion.</P>
    <P>Understandably when I am replying I am principally responding to the contribution by the Minister who speaks on behalf of the Government on this occasion.  Although I do not have the same approach on a number of fundnamental issues as the Minister &mdash; I will come to that &mdash; I was heartened by the emphasis which the Minister placed on the importance of both reinforcing the protection of human rights in Tibet and also the necessity for constructive dialogue between the Dalai Lama and his representative and the Chinese authorities. Furthermore, I was encouraged by his response to the practical suggestion which Senator O'Toole put forward. Senator O'Toole canvassed the idea of the Irish Ambassador either in China or India leading a fact-finding mission to Tibet and being in a position to report at first-hand on the situation so that there could be a more structured Irish concern expressed.</P>
    <P>The Minister in his speech referred to the role of the Irish Ambassador in Beijing in monitoring and reporting on the situation in Tibet.  That is important particularly in the coming months for the reason that has been given, during the month of March 1989 and perhaps for several months after that.  It would be something that this House would greatly <Col N="1949" /> appreciate if the Minister could undertake to have any reports from the Ambassador conveyed to this House, and indeed placed in the Library of this House so that they can be available to Senators. In having a debate on issues it is extremely important that we also try to advance the cause somewhat, that we try to be practical and constructive in seeking to advance it.</P>
    <P>I appreciate the extent to which the Minister emphasised the concern which Ireland has had and continues to have for the protection of human rights in Tibet and the active concern to ensure the furtherance of reconciliation between the Tibetan people through their representatives, and particularly through the Dalai Lama and his staff, and the Chinese Government.</P>
    <P>I would now like to tease out some of the areas.  Like the two Senators who spoke after the Minister I was disappointed at the thrust and emphasis which he placed on the issues raised in this motion.  The Minister said that it was not possible to endorse the precise wording of the motion while appreciating the thrust of it.</P>
    <P>The first thing to which the motion refers is the incident arising from the 40th anniversary of the United Nations Declaration of Human Rights.  The Minister indicated that it was not quite clear to him or to the Government what had transpired.  It is clear now to the world from independent reports, from the manner in which the events have been described, what took place and indeed it is an issue on which Governments have been prepared to come out quite strongly and to condemn what happened.  For example, the United States State Department, not always known for being a State Department which will condemn violation of human rights in various parts of the world, have strongly deplored the shooting of unarmed demonstrators and bystanders in Lhasa on 10 December 1988.  Therefore, there is no need for any reserve on the part of the Irish Government in relation to the recognition which is very widely shared at the moment that that was a particularly notorious occasion <Col N="1950" /> and incident in violation of the individual human rights.</P>
    <P>The second point in the motion was to note the Irish Government's support for the fundamental rights and the very existence of the Tibetan nation and it refers to the particular resolutions which Ireland had supported under the leadership given in that regard by our representative at the time, Frank Aiken.</P>
    <P>In my contribution to this debate last Wednesday I referred to a specific question which had been put by the Tibet Support Group to the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Lenihan, in a letter written in early January as to whether Ireland supports the language used by Frank Aiken.  I had hoped that the Minister in his contribution would address that question in the manner in which it was posed and reaffirm Ireland's commitment to the resolutions which we have supported down the years at the United Nations, that he would do it unequivocally and that he would use the opportunity to place that on the record.  The Minister has not precisely referred to the reasons for reserve with the wording of the motion but the purpose of having a debate of this kind is to have an opportunity to tease out these issues and to clarify the position.</P>
    <P>When I was opening this debate I referred to something which has been a popular theme in a number of the contributions made by other Senators.  That was my regret that we did not have a committee on foreign affairs where we could deal in a much more structured and developed way with these issues, not just a once-off debate where there is a very little opportunity for dialogue, where the Minister makes a contribution and the mover of the motion can reply to it but there is no further opportunity for dialogue and for exploring further these issues.</P>
    <P>I think it is becoming increasingly important that we should have a committee on foreign affairs.  It is becoming increasingly important for another reason that has surfaced during this debate.  We have in Ireland, for better or worse &mdash; I personally believe for better &mdash; stated <Col N="1951" /> that we have a particular position within the European Community.  We are not part of a military alliance, we have negotiated a particular wording of the Single European Act, of Title III to the Single European Act, to accommodate a difference which we say is important and which the Irish people quite clearly believe is important.  It is, therefore, absolutely vital that we have a parliamentary committee which can examine in depth, which can monitor how we reflect this in our international affairs, and indeed in our relationships with our partners in the European Community. That is an important broader theme that has come out in this debate but it should not take from the real thrust of the wording of this debate.</P>
    <P>The third issue that is raised is to note the very significant estimates of the number of Tibetans who have been killed since the Chinese invasion of Tibet in 1949.  Again, this is a matter which has been the subject of very considerable international analysis and is likely to be adverted to again next month when the 30th anniversary of the uprising against that Chinese invasion will be celebrated.</P>
    <P>I was pleased and encouraged to receive a letter from Mary Lawlor, Director of the Irish section of Amnesty International, welcoming this debate in the Seanad.  She said that Amnesty International was very interested in the recent Seanad initiative concerning Tibet, reinforcing a point which has been made by some Senators that Amnesty has been monitoring very carefully what is happening in Tibet and is very concerned about it.  The motion addresses an issue which has been the subject of independent reports, including indeed the type of report which the Minister himself quoted from the official report of February 1988 of <i>Asia Watch</i>.  At the moment these types of reports are the best evidence we can get out of Tibet of the very difficult situation for the people there. The motion in adverting to an existing situation has done so in a responsible <Col N="1952" /> way, in a way that is in line with independent, well-informed world opinion on this issue.</P>
    <P>The positive end of the motion &mdash; what we ask to be done &mdash; is a condemnation of the Chinese regime for its grave violation of human rights in Tibet.  Every Senator who spoke addressed this question of violation of human rights.  The only question I suppose we can pose is whether it is more constructive when you are seeking dialogue and reconciliation to condemn or to use more conciliatory language.  That is a question worth addressing.  Certainly when it comes to a concern about human rights it is necessary at times to call a spade a spade.  It is necessary to face up to difficult issues.  It is probably particularly necessary when you are dealing with people such as the Chinese people who respect those who, in fact, take positions of integrity and stand by them and are not swayed by other considerations.</P>
    <P>I come then to the last two paragraphs of the motion in the brief time left to me. We urge the Government to support all international measures for establishing peace and respect for human rights in Tibet.  I have no doubt from his contribution to this debate that the Minister would unequivocally support that part of the motion.</P>
    <P>Finally, we call on the Government to instigate a motion at the United Nations in support of the Tibetan people.  The Minister has come a considerable way in a practical sense by referring to the fact that the Irish Ambassador in Beijing will be and is monitoring closely the situation in Tibet.  I would certainly hope that should there be occasion to do so, Ireland will either initiate or support any action which may be taken at the level of the United Nations to draw attention to the situation and in particular to focus on the need for constructive dialogue between the Dalai Lama and other representatives of the Tibetan people and the Chinese Government.</P>
    <P>The debate has raised an issue of very real importance and obviously one of very real concern to a large number of Members of this House.  It is noted <Col N="1953" /> already in the country that we are concerned about this.  For that reason I am very grateful indeed to those who participated and I hope that the ripples will continue in a constructive way.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, before you actually put the motion or not in view of the Minister's coming part of the way with us on the sentiments expressed, in view of his comments that he could not endorse this motion as it is worded, I would suggest, if the Government side would agree, that we would allow a sos so that we could have an acceptable compromise wording.  If this motion is voted down, it will be misrepresented that this Government are in favour of what the Chinese are doing.  I know they are not and I know that the Standing Orders might not allow this kind of procedure&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>You have made your point, Senator, and I can&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFerris" hpid="Mr. Ferris Mr. Ferris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ferris</NameTxt>
      <P>I am surprised that the Minister did not amend the motion in a structured way.  Is it possible for us to arrive at a situation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a good point. May I ask if it is agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I felt that there was a very important area of common ground in the approach&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry.  I have to put the question on the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is it possible under the changes in the Standing Orders which I have not got in front of me to be registered as being in support of the motion without pushing it to a vote?  Can you indicate to me the new position under the Standing Orders?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is agreed on the ministerial side and if it is agreed on all sides of the House, that can be done. You can record your dissent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1954" />
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. J. O'Toole Mr. J. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Can one record one's assent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>No, only dissent. The question is: &ldquo;That the motion be agreed to&rdquo;.  Those in favour say Tá and those against say Níl.  The question is defeated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>Vótáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a certain decision in relation to the taking of a vote in this matter and the confusion may, in fact, reflect the reality of the situation which is that there is a lot of common ground and there is a reluctance to have the matter, which is a very sensitive international issue, voted upon in this manner, In the particular circumstances, if the House would allow me, I would like, as the mover of this motion, to seek the leave of the House to withdraw it at this stage.  That would be a conclusion on the motion which would best reflect the real issues which have been debated.</P>
      <P>Let the debate speak for itself.  Since there was confusion, and still is confusion, in the minds of most of us as to what exactly happened at the end perhaps the House would allow me to withdraw the motion at this stage and not have the matter voted upon.  Had I fully understood the situation that is what I would have put to the House at an earlier stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I will put the question again, Senator Robinson, namely &ldquo;That the motion be withdrawn.&rdquo;  Is that it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am now putting the question: &ldquo;That the motion be withdrawn.&rdquo; Is it agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      <P>Motion, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>Tomorrow at 10.30 a.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1955" />
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We will now take the matter on the Adjournment of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. - Ballinamore" RHead="(Leitrim) Research Centre">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Ballinamore (Leitrim) Research Centre.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. G. Reynolds Mr. G. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>My subject matter on the Adjournment relates to the Ballinamore Research Station.  I should like to give the background to the actual research station.  Ballinamore Research Centre was opened by An Foras Talúntais in October 1959 very soon after AFT were set up.  Sixty acres of land were purchased from a gentleman about two miles from Ballinamore and six workmen, together with the first director, Basil Regan, set about putting them into order.  Over the next quarter of a century activities increased and very important work was done to enable the large number of farm holders on dauby drumlin soils to improve their position. Roughly 15 acres in the vicinity were obtained and an additional about 220 acres at Creevy and about 20 acres at Gorvagh were leased for appropriate use.</P>
      <P>The number employed increased under subsequent officers in charge.  The number of employees was increased to 15 and more recently it settled at ten. One of the directors, Mr. Mulqueen, developed an all-weather playing pitch, the prototype of which was established nearby at St. Felim's College in Ballinamore. The use of sand and drainage enabled playing surfaces to be laid on wet dauby land which could be used for sports activities in mid-winter.  Many pitches with this type of surface have been laid in places as far away as Kerry.  This was one of the major breakthroughs from the research station in Ballinamore.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When the last director was moved to Grange about two and a half years ago no graduate was put in charge.  Since then one of the technicians has been the officer in charge of the station.  I saw this as the first phase of a process towards closure of the station.  The present proposal to cease research at Ballinamore is the second phase.  The undefined role of the <Col N="1956" />&ldquo;transmission farm&rdquo; is but the half-way house towards complete closure.  The facility may remain as a depot for the remnant of the old ACOT service at least for some time but an important aspect of the Teagasc remit, namely research, will be no more.  It would not be a good step just to have the station there as a place to put some ACOT employees.  Teagasc have stated that they will keep one technician and about one or two farm workers.  Nobody needs to explain that research with that amount of staff would be almost impossible.  It would only be a function of keeping the station alive which in the short term would be uneconomic and in the long term would mean closure.  That would be a farcical gesture on the part of any board.</P>
    <P>Research is now to be effectively terminated in the wetlands and in the province of Connacht.  Connacht has already lost AFT research stations.  Now two more are to be closed and a third, Ballinamore, is to be reduced to a mere ghost of its former self.  This, in spite of the fact that EC drainage experts who visited this county early in 1986 reported that the provision of effective drainage systems on west of Ireland farms is a matter of survival for the farmers and not a means of boosting production, that field drainage is necessary in these regions to improve the socio-economic environment and to preserve the rural fabric of the region and that the provision of water management information is necessary for the proper development of these regions.  It would appear from this that the proposed cessation of research at Ballinamore is not in conformity with EC policy regarding the preservation of the family farm.</P>
    <P>Arising from this it must be clear that there is an acute pollution problem in areas such as this.  In the vicinity of Ballinamore we have something like 65 lakes in a ten mile radius where coarse angling is a major tourist attraction.  It is one of the Government's priorities that tourism should be boosted.  Many farmers have run into problems with pollution of these lakes and they have been asked to provide very elaborate buildings on small <Col N="1957" /> holdings of 35 to 40 acres of land.  Even with the minimal grant of 35 per cent from the western package of the EC they find this very hard to do.  Surely continued and appropriate research at Ballinamore is preferable to pollution prosecutions and the bad feelings between farming and tourist interests which are consequent on this.</P>
    <P>Dairying is a very important aspect of life on the family farm in Leitrim.  The dairy enterprise at Ballinamore centre should be expanded rather than contracted. It could be tailored to boost the quality and quantity of winter feed.  This area suffered very badly in the winters of 1985 and 1986 and I would like to put on the record of this House that the staff in the research station in Ballinamore provided a lot of help and assistance to farmers in that area so that fodder could be provided.  They must be congratulated because they kept many a farmer in fodder for the winter when they decided to help.  Otherwise we would not have been able to get that help and the farmers would not have been able to get fodder. It could also be used to investigate cheap methods of solving slurry holding and spreading problems, so peculiar to wetlands.</P>
    <P>Other research which should be undertaken or continued includes: (a) economic assessment of drainage, (b) a suckler cow trial, (c) mixed stocking trial with sheep and cattle, i.e. dry stock and cows, (d) alternative farm enterprises. There is much talk about diversity in the western package at the moment and a research station would be able to help farmers with mushrooms, goats, rabbits, pigs and poultry.  Also agro-forestry could be researched here.</P>
    <P>There should be no reduction in staff in Ballinamore or transfer of Ballinamore staff further south.  Graduate staff should be catered for adequately to enable the farming community to be given the quality of information they deserve.  Ballinamore station should be the location where problems related to marginal land are tackled and resolved.</P>
    <P>I would like to state why I think Ballinamore should not be downgraded. <Col N="1958" /> There is continued and, indeed, increased need for research to improve the lot of those living in the wetlands area because the survival of the family farm is at risk with the various social and economic consequences.  Ballinamore is the ideal place to do this research.  It is quite cheap costwise.  In Ballinamore we are of the opinion that station costs are very reasonable.  Ballinamore is by far the most northerly station in the Teagasc network. Should all research activity now be brought down to south of the Galway-Dublin borderline?  Should not the research be done where the problems are?  Is there to be no further research in the northern part of the country?  Should the problems to Connacht bear such a huge part of Teagasc cutbacks while Munster bears very little, if any?  Should the stronger and wealthier areas prosper more as a result of policies which send the weaker closer to the wall?  That outlines the situation at the moment.  One of the reasons Teagasc was formed was to help research but apparently the whole Connacht region wetlands have been forgotten. It is almost a case of going back to the old Cromwellian statement, &ldquo;To Hell or to Connacht&rdquo;.  The Government have a social obligation to look after each section of the community.</P>
    <P>Ballinamore is situated in a Border county.  There is scope for North-South co-operation in this area.  There should also be increasing scope for external funding.  We do not know what the future may bring for this entire area of activity. The all-weather pitch project was an example of North-South co-operation.  It was also adopted by an institute in Ennis-killen and this worked very well for the people involved north and south of the Border.  If the Government are looking for funding to keep the research station open on a temporary basis, the present international fund could be looked at because of the close proximity to Northern Ireland.</P>
    <P>Ballinamore needs those jobs more than any place to which they might be transferred.  Leitrim is the only county losing its population since 1966.  No public service job should be taken out <Col N="1959" /> of Leitrim until this trend is reversed. Leitrim is the only county in the vicinity which does not benefit from current or proposed redevelopment of civil servants or location of military barracks.  This is the only area of optional State job location which we have and it should not be removed.  That is a very valid point; as well as the research and agricultural aspect there is a social aspect.  I am thinking of the Thurles sugar factory where 175 jobs are going but the loss of ten jobs in Leitrim is as big a blow to a small economic area.  I have no doubt that the Minister will have long and hard consultations about the 175 jobs in Thurles. Ten jobs in Ballinamore are very important to the structural and economic development of the area.  Ten jobs in a national context seem very little but are a major consideration in the light of our needs in Leitrim.</P>
    <P>I call on the Minister to extract the Ballinamore proposals from the remainder of the Teagasc plan and base his action on social principles.  The board should be asked to make the necessary minor adjustments to accommodate this.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture and Food (Mr. Kirk) Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture and Food (Mr. Kirk)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture and Food (Mr. Kirk)</NameTxt>
      <P>As the House is aware, the reason the Government decided to amalgamate the agricultural research, training and advisory services was to establish a strong unified structure for the effective delivery of those services which are vital for the successful development of the agriculture and food industries.  The Government were also conscious of the need to have an authority of the highest calibre to enable the new body to discharge their responsibilities in an effective and business-like manner.  After full and careful consideration the Minister for Agriculture and Food appointed a group of people eminently qualified to fulfil that role.  The Authority are representative of all the farming organisations, the Irish Co-Operative Organisation Society Limited, the trade unions and staff associations, universities and education institutions, and they are presided over <Col N="1960" /> by Mr. Joe Rea, former President of the IFA.</P>
      <P>I am pleased to say that in a very short period since their establishment the Authority have set about the task of welding the former services into a cohesive organisation capable of providing services relevant to the present and future needs of agriculture.  Under the legislation the Authority have the responsibility to decide their priorities and organise their services within the limits of the resources available to them.  Teagasc inherited very considerable resources from An Foras Talúntais and ACOT.  On their establishment the Authority examined very thoroughly all the ongoing activities with a view to determining those which are most relevant in the rapidly changing environment we have in agriculture today.  The Authority then submitted to the Minister for Agriculture and Food their programme of activities for 1989, including rationalisation of their services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Teagasc prepared this programme with the following key objectives in mind: the necessity to achieve maximum integration of research, advisory and training services and the long-term viability of the organisation; the need to ensure that all services are delivered in the most cost-effective manner; the need to allocate resources and manpower in a manner which reflects programme priorities.  The main features of the Teagasc programme for 1989 are: the reorganisation and the refocusing of the agricultural advisory, training and research services; special emphasis on education and training for young farmers and on field research as required under the legislation; a special advisory programme for all small producers; the establishment of six regional centres with enhanced capacity to promote special programmes of regional and national importance; concentration of administration in a single headquarters and a review of local advisory and training centres; the funding of capital works such as the new recruit centre through the sale of assets; the transfer of the research work at Creagh and Belclare stations to Athenry and the setting up <Col N="1961" /> of a reserve fund from the economies achieved for designated western projects.</P>
    <P>While Creagh is to close, the research will be transferred to Athenry and the surplus on the sale of the land will be used to undertake studies of western farming. The resources will be put to use for the benefit of the research that is necessary in the unique situation that pertains in the west of Ireland.</P>
    <P>The other objectives include: the retention of Lullymore and Ballinamore stations for use as transmission farms and advisory centres; more commercial orientation of research at Johnstown Castle; rationalisation of the Rural Economics Centre and recruitment of some additional staff in key areas and a reduction of staff in other areas, to be achieved by voluntary retirement.  The programme represents the first phase of the Authority's plan for rationalisation of existing services over a three year period so as to achieve maximum integration and delivery of the most relevant services in the most cost-effective manner.</P>
    <P>The Minister has indicated to the Authority his acceptance of the broad thrust of the programme for 1989.  The proposals for Ballinamore are just one element of the overall national programme. Over the years the research activities there included the study of drainage systems, studies to determine more suitable grass species, optimum levels of grass fertiliser on drumlin soils, dairying on such lands and mixed stock enterprises of cattle and sheep.  The Authority take the view that research is no longer critical in the light of developments within the EC regarding surplus production and the state of agricultural markets generally.  Part of the land at Ballinamore will be retained for studying farm forestry.</P>
    <P>The Authority consider that the overall needs of farmers in the north west will best be served by applying the results of relevant research undertaken at Ballinamore and elsewhere through transmission farms.  While research may not continue in Ballinamore, the fruits of such research will continue to be available in a practical way.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1962" /> On the question of the staff at Ballinamore, discussions are ongoing between management and unions.  The voluntary early retirement scheme also continues to be available to the staff of Teagasc in 1989.  I am a little surprised that Members of this House should urge the Minister to reverse the proposal of Teagasc given that during the course of the passage of the Teagasc legislation there were objections to the controls held by the Minister regarding Teagasc activities. At that time the House sought an undertaking that the Minister would not interfere unduly in Teagasc activities.  An undertaking was given that, subject to priorities set by the Government for the agricultural research, training and advisory services and the resources available to them, the Authority would be allowed to get on with the job they were appointed to do.  It is intended to maintain that position.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I have to say that the current economic reality involves looking at all public services critically on the basis of their cost-effectiveness.  This applies as much to the agricultural sector as elsewhere. We have made it clear from the outset that the Government expect Teagasc to be even more commercially oriented than their predecessors and Teagasc proposals fully reflect this.  The Authority's objective is, in fact, to reduce dependence on Exchequer income from 73 per cent at present to 55 per cent in 1993.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GerryReynolds" hpid="Mr. G. Reynolds Mr. G. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Minister one question?  I would like an explanation of what &ldquo;transmission farm&rdquo; means.  I would also like to make one statement about the involvement of the Minister.  That is a most hypocritical statement to make.  I am not blaming the Minister but obviously the Minister for Agriculture and Food is involved up to his neck in the Thurles sugar factory.  A board was set up supposedly to function without any political involvement.  I cannot see why he is making one rule for one community and another for another community.  It is farcical for a statement like that to emanate from this House in <Col N="1963" /> the circumstances.  The West of Ireland is being shunned at the moment.  The Minister has the power to look at the Teagasc overall plan and research in Ballinamore cannot be continued with a staff of one or two.  It is just a political device to keep people at bay for the moment.  I would like to know what &ldquo;transmission farm&rdquo; means because this seems to be causing some problems in my area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusKirk" hpid="Mr. Kirk Mr. Kirk">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kirk</NameTxt>
      <P>It is really intended that the farms will be used for demonstration purposes, for farms to reflect the results of the research which comes to hand from <Col N="1964" /> the programmes that will be in operation in other centres.  Obviously, the advisory services will use it as a demonstration for the farmers within a particular catchment area.  Beyond that, one cannot anticipate what the personnel in Teagasc will see first.  Essentially it will be used for the demonstration of new techniques which will be developed over the years through the research programmes at the other centres.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 8.35 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 2 February 1989.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>