<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="8" Month="Dec" Year="1994" Vol="447" No="7" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 8 Nollaig 1994" DateEnglish="Thursday, 8 December 1994" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="841" /> Chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Announcement" RHead="of Business">
    <Title>Announcement of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="NoelDempsey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. Dempsey) Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. Dempsey)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. Dempsey)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 8 and 13 and a statement from the Taoiseach on the status of the Privilege and Compellability Bill.  It is also proposed, notwithstanding anything in Standing Orders, that: Nos. 8 and 13 shall be decided without debate; and the Taoiseach will be called upon to make a statement on the status of the Privilege and Compellability Bill which shall not exceed ten minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>May I take it that the proposals for dealing with Nos. 8 and 13 are satisfactory and agreed? Agreed.  Is the proposal that the Taoiseach shall be called on to make a statement not exceeding ten minutes satisfactory and agreed?  Agreed.  We now proceed to deal with item No. 8, the motion rescinding order to select committees on reporting of Bills.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Expression of Sympathy" RHead="to Senator Wilson">
    <Title>Expression of Sympathy to Senator Wilson.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlanShatter" hpid="Mr. Shatter Mr. Shatter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Shatter</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we proceed with the business of the House, I propose that the condolences of the House be conveyed to Senator Gordon Wilson <Col N="842" /> and his family on the appalling tragedy that has befallen them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the House will agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I concur with the view expressed by Deputy Shatter.  I have already conveyed my sympathy to Senator Wilson and his wife on yet another horrible tragedy to strike that family.  Words fail all of us in expressing our deepest sadness at such a double shock for Senator Gordon Wilson and his wife.  I wish to endorse the expression of sympathy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to join the Taoiseach in saying how inexpressibly shocked all of us in this House were when the news spread of this awful tragedy that has befallen the Wilson family.  It must be as near to an unbearable burden as anything possibly can be in any person's life that a double tragedy of this nature should occur.</P>
      <P>What has struck me most about Senator Wilson, particularly listening to his contributions at the meetings of the Forum for Peace and Reconciliation, is the sense in which everything he does in his political life is informed by his faith in God.  His religious beliefs seem to shine through in all his work in political life.  That is probably his most notable characteristic.  I have no doubt that that faith will help him immeasurably and his family, whom I have no doubt share that faith with him, in coping with this tragedy which it is almost impossible to cope with.</P>
      <P>It is my hope that at tomorrow's meeting of the Forum for Peace and Reconciliation &mdash; Senator Wilson has been probably the most eloquent and interesting contributor to all our discussions &mdash; where there will be a wider representation of parties than in this House, we will be afforded an opportunity to underline the sense of sympathy felt by every person on this and the neighbouring island with Senator Wilson and his family on this terrible loss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="843" />
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>On my own behalf, and that of my parliamentary colleagues, I would like to convey deepest sympathy to Senator Wilson who has experienced tremendous tragedy in the past.  He will need all of the strength he has shown since then to cope with this latest tragedy.  I conveyed my sympathy to him this morning.  As the Taoiseach said in his statement last night, Senator Wilson has the sympathy of everybody on this double tragedy which has befallen him, his family and the family of his late son.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to join the Taoiseach and other party leaders in extending my sympathy, and that of the Progressive Democrats, to Senator Wilson and his family.  Senator Wilson has shown what forgiveness is all about in the way he bore the awful grief when his daughter, Marie, died.</P>
      <P>After he was nominated to Seanad Éireann all Members of the Oireachtas got to know him personally.  It is fair to say that on all sides of both Houses he is seen as a really decent man, one who is loved by everybody, a very generous and open-minded person.  I extend my sympathy to him on this dreadful tragedy.  As Deputy Spring said, I have no doubt that the strength he showed before will be required at this time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>On hearing the news this morning I was deeply shocked at the tragedy Senator Wilson has to endure yet again.  When his daughter was murdered some years ago he showed an extraordinary capacity for forgiveness, tolerance, compassion and demonstrated to all of us the strength of character needed in circumstances in which people find themselves from time to time.</P>
      <P>On my behalf, and that of Democratic Left, I should like to convey to Senator Wilson, and his family, our deeply felt sorrow at their sad loss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrevorSargent" hpid="Mr. Sargent Mr. Sargent">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sargent</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very sad for us today to think about the loss the Wilson family have had to bear on the death of yet <Col N="844" /> another family member, Peter.  It is a tragedy occurring on top of another of which all of us became aware after the Enniskillen bombing.</P>
      <P>It is important to state that somebody like Senator Wilson is an extremely respected figure and, as such, the sympathy of this House and of the people of both parts of Ireland will be very much with him and his family.  Although it may be of small comfort to them, anything and everything we can do will be done to help.  It has to be said that Senator Wilson has brought a level of humanity to these Houses with his ability to forgive, to reach out, understand and accept that others have points of view with which we may not altogether agree but which nonetheless are deserving of respect.  Therefore, his loss, and that of his family, is all the more poignant since it tests what we would all hope would be almost beyond our greatest endurance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us rise in prayerful silence.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Members rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Rescission of Order of Dáil:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Rescission of Order of Dáil: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="NoelDempsey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. Dempsey) Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. Dempsey)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. Dempsey)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the Order of the Dáil of 3rd November, 1994, providing that the Select Committees on Enterprise and Economic Strategy and Legislation and Security report back to Dáil Éireann by 7 December, 1994, is hereby rescinded in respect of the four Bills comprehended. </P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotAhern" hpid="Mr. D. Ahern Mr. D. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of information, a matter came to my notice last evening in relation to the meeting of the British-Irish Inter-Parliamentary Body proposed for 12-14 December 1994.  As co-Chairman I endeavoured to find out <Col N="845" /> the position since we are to have a plenary session in Cardiff on those days.  As the House will be aware, 25 Members of the Oireachtas are due to travel to Cardiff to meet our British counterparts from Monday to Wednesday of next week.  I contacted our Whip's office and I received a message late last night indicating that the Whips unanimously are of the view that the meeting should not take place.</P>
      <P>I have been in contact with my British counterpart, co-Chairman, Mr. Peter Temple Morris, MP about the position. I want some indication, particularly from the Leaders of the political parties in this House, on what is the exact position. This is a very important meeting, one of two we have in the course of the year and, if cancelled, would send all the wrong signals with regard to whatever peace process is in place.  It is important that this Parliament give Members some direction on whether this meeting should take place in the next or coming weeks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair has had no notice of the matter referred to by Deputy Ahern.  However, I would express the hope that the important matter to which he has adverted can be resolved in consultation with the Leaders and the Whips of this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Tánaiste and Minister for Finance (Mr. B. Ahern) Tánaiste and Minister for Finance (Mr. B. Ahern)">
      <NameTxt>Tánaiste and Minister for Finance (Mr. B. Ahern)</NameTxt>
      <P>I know it would be out of order &mdash; if order is still a matter of importance in this House although I know that when you, a Cheann Comhairle, are in the Chair you do your utmost to maintain it &mdash; but in our view it is important that this meeting which has been arranged for some time should not be cancelled.  It is crucial that the peace process continue.  This House always facilitated such meetings and I think that meeting should go ahead. There is no difficulty on our side of the House about that meeting.  Perhaps the Whips could meet later today to discuss the matter and I would be quite happy about such a discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="846" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that, rather than this matter being discussed across the floor of the House where statements might be made which might appear superficially plausible but may have other elements requiring elaboration&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotAhern" hpid="Mr. D. Ahern Mr. D. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>I totally object to that implication.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Ahern, this delicate matter should not give rise to argument or disorder of any kind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotAhern" hpid="Mr. D. Ahern Mr. D. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>I totally object to that remark.  How dare Deputy John Bruton.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. N. Treacy) Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. N. Treacy)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach (Mr. N. Treacy)</NameTxt>
      <P>That was a disgraceful statement by Deputy John Bruton.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Members should restrain themselves in respect of this delicate matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>The peace process is a particularly sensitive issue and it should be discussed in a careful way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cowen</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should cop himself on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should not act in a bullish manner.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>People who wish to raise matters affecting the peace process would be well advised to give notice to those concerned beforehand so that the response can be measured and careful. It is unreasonable to raise matters without notice in this fashion.  I suggest, therefore, we agree that the matter be discussed between all the party leaders or by the Whips during the recess we will probably have later today.  In that way we will be able to reach an agreed solution.  It may well be that it is possible to find an agreed solution to satisfy everybody, but it is unlikely that we will <Col N="847" /> find it in a form of cross talk in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>It is well known I have always said that the British-Irish Inter-parliamentary Body has an extremely important function regarding relations between this House and Westminster. We should have a meeting of the party leaders shortly after the House is adjourned and consider the possibilities of how that meeting may go ahead.  It may be possible for the meeting to sit for one day instead of the normal sitting of two-and-a-half days.  The party leaders will consider if a resolution can be found.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Deputies Bruton and Spring.  We should meet after the House is adjourned and discuss how we can facilitate the meeting going ahead.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the proposed postponement of this interparliamentary body was agreed by the Whips, including the Government Whip, last night.  I am surprised that it has been raised across the floor this morning.  I agree it should be discussed by the Whips and the party leaders and not across the floor in an antagonistic fashion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am ruling, therefore, the consensus of this House is that this matter be referred to the Leaders of the various parties and the Whips for consideration and decision.  I will hear no more on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotAhern" hpid="Mr. D. Ahern Mr. D. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>A Ceann Comhairle, may I make a point?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order, Deputy Ahern please resume your seat forthwith.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DermotAhern" hpid="Mr. D. Ahern Mr. D. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>I am entitled to make a point.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="848" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Ahern, you may not disobey the Chair in this unruly fashion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Deputy A Deputy">
      <NameTxt>A Deputy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has put his foot in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy still a member of Fianna Fáil?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>There is faction fighting in that party.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of Select Committee:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Report of Select Committee: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DanWallace" hpid="Mr. D. Wallace Mr. D. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>I move, &ldquo;that the Dáil takes note of the following report of the committee on Legislation and Security&rdquo;: (1) the committee met at 10.30 a.m. in the Dáil Chamber on 7 December 1994; (2) the committee deemed it appropriate to question the following persons: the Attorney General, Mr. Eoghan Fitzsimons S.C.; Mr. Harold Whelehan; Mr. Matthew Russell, Senior Legal Assistant, Office of the Attorney General; Mr. James Hamilton, Legal Assistant, Office of the Attorney General; the Research Officer in the Office of the Attorney General who located the Duggan case; the Secretary of the Department of Justice; the Commissioner of the Garda Síochána; the members of the Government in the order in which they made statements in the Dáil on Tuesday, 6 December 1994; the Government Chief Whip; members of the Labour Party who recently resigned from the Government; and Dr. Martin Mansergh, Adviser, Department of the Taoiseach; the committee also agreed that it might call other witnesses if necessary; (3) the Attorney General appeared before the committee subsequently and informed the committee that he would not be in a position to answer questions to the committee in the absence of certain undertakings by the Government and absolute privilege; (4) the committee subsequently requested the attendance of the Taoiseach to inform the committee of the <Col N="849" /> Government's response to the Attorney General's requests; the Taoiseach appeared before the committee at 2.15 p.m. he confirmed the Government's agreement to meet the undertakings requested by the Attorney General and (5) following discussion, the committee concluded that it is unable to proceed further with examination of witnesses who had not been Members of the Oireachtas prior to the enactment of legislation to provide for absolute privilege for witnesses appearing before the committee.</P>
      <P>I would like to refer to comments by the Deputy Leader of Fine Gael, Deputy Owen, on &ldquo;Prime Time&rdquo; last night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit to the chairman of the committee that he ought not go beyond the report he submitted to the House, which is without debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanWallace" hpid="Mr. D. Wallace Mr. D. Wallace">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Wallace</NameTxt>
      <P>A Cheann Comhairle, the Deputy said&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I must ask the Deputy to resume his seat.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been decided that this matter will be dealt with without debate.  Deputy Wallace, resume your seat forthwith.  It is most unfair of the Deputy to intervene in this controversial fashion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Mrs. Doyle Mrs. Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Doyle</NameTxt>
      <P>We will see the Deputy outside.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Wallace is watching too much television.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Privilege and Compellability" RHead="of Witnesses Bill: Statements">
    <Title>Privilege and Compellability of Witnesses Bill: Statements.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>At the meeting of the Select Committee on Legislation and <Col N="850" /> Security yesterday, I said that the Government had been advised by the Attorney General that legislation was needed to grant absolute privilege to those appearing before it.  I undertook to report to the House on the present status of the Houses of the Oireachtas (Privilege and Compellability of Witnesses) Bill.  I am now in a position to state that I am arranging for the text of the Bill as it stands to be circulated, with an indication of points which are currently being addressed in the Attorney General's Office.  It will be clear to Deputies that this draft Bill would require further consideration before being finalised.  However, the Government wish it to be available to the House at this stage.</P>
      <P>In addition, yesterday evening the Attorney General's office drafted a more limited Bill, which we are also circulating. It confers absolute privilege and immunity on the witnesses who come before this committee in the course of the inquiry which it has undertaken. This immunity is already enjoyed by all Members of the Oireachtas.  The Bill will provide a level playing field for other witnesses who are not Members of the Oireachtas by giving them the same level of privilege and immunity as Members enjoy for the purposes of this inquiry only.</P>
      <P>I hope Deputies will accept that, in putting forward these proposals, the Government is anxious to co-operate fully with the select committee in discharging its task.  We are asking the Dáil to consider both measures and to decide, in plenary session or in committee, how it wishes to proceed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The reality is of course that the Government is at present functioning in a caretaker capacity.  As is obvious from the Privilege and Compellability Bill and the attendant documentation which we are circulating, there are major issues to be considered and decided in relation to this measure. Thus, it would not be appropriate for a caretaker Administration to push forward such fundamental policy changes. That is why we have brought forward <Col N="851" /> the more limited specific measure for consideration.  It is up to the Members of this House to decide on what course to take.  Needless to say, we are willing to listen to other suggestions.</P>
    <P>I would also like to refer again to the advice of the Attorney General on whether the procedures of the Select Committee on Legislation and Security were adequate in regard to the rules of natural justice and Article 40.3 of the Constitution.  The Attorney General advised in relation to the latter point that any person called as a witness whose good name and reputation is at issue is entitled to legal representation with a right to cross-examine witnesses who make statements which would reflect unfavourably upon such persons. Such legal representation would also serve to protect persons called as witnesses from oppressive questioning.</P>
    <P>In relation to the rules of natural justice the Attorney General has advised that persons called as witnesses whose good name and reputation are at issue, are entitled &mdash; in advance of giving evidence &mdash; to the statements of witnesses who will be giving evidence which would reflect unfavourably upon them.</P>
    <P>I hope it will be possible to deal with these matters in a reasonable way.  It is important and essential for the dignity of the House that it be seen to act in a manner appropriate to a national parliament. We cannot be a party to the setting up of a &ldquo;star&rdquo; chamber.  The House must conduct its affairs in an orderly and civilised manner and we should proceed on that basis.  The people we all serve deserve no less.  We must pursue the truth with justice.  The truth will come out in the end and justice must be done and be seen to be done.</P>
    <P>I understand the Whips agreed that the House should be suspended now to allow the Whips and the party leaders discuss the options before the House, and let us proceed from there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I will call the spokespersons for the main parties.  I <Col N="852" /> hope their contributions will be very brief so that we can adjourn and deal with this matter in a manner in which the dignity of the House can be seen to be upheld.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing here with a matter that has been a problem for this House for some time.  The beef tribunal proved to be a very costly way of getting information and there was a general view that we should find a less costly way.  It is clear from what the Taoiseach said that there are profound problems in regard to legal representation arising from claims as to the entitlements under the Constitution of people appearing before a committee. Members of this House, particularly on the Opposition benches, who favour Dáil reform and the committee system have been for a very long time seeking legislation to cover privilege and compellability of witnesses.  A crisis has accelerated the process for the production of this legislation and while the crisis is not welcome we now have an embarrassment of riches in the sense that there are alternative Bills before us rather than just one.  At least we are getting to grips with the problem, which is very important in the interests of everybody in the House and I welcome that.</P>
      <P>I agree with the Taoiseach that we should proceed in an orderly and careful way because the House, if it is to take more of these matters into its own hands and away from expensive tribunals, must be capable of being fair to everybody.  I propose that when initial statements have been made by the various parties there be an adjournment of an agreed duration so that the parties may consider the various options.  We may not be able to solve all the longer term problems but I am fairly confident that we will be able to at least come to an agreement on how to deal with the immediate problems in respect of the Select Committee on Legislation and Security.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="853" />
    <Speaker pid="DickSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>If I understand the Taoiseach's suggestion correctly, the proposal is to adjourn the House for some time to allow party leaders meet to consider what are extremely complex issues and reflect on the advice given by the Attorney General to the Government.  I would like to think we could find a solution to the immediate problem as quickly as possible and allow the House to conduct its business in a dignified manner.  I do not believe we will be in a position, either today or in the near future, to deal with the proposed legislation being prepared on the wider issues, but I would agree to have an early meeting to see if we can provide a solution to the immediate problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryHarney" hpid="Miss Harney Miss Harney">
      <NameTxt>Miss Harney</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the Taoiseach's suggestion that we adjourn to consider this matter.  On a first reading, the proposed Government Bill looks attractive.  It is confined to the current inquiry which is welcome in the circumstances. It is important that we facilitate the investigation by the Select Committee on Legislation and Security into recent events and that we do so as quickly as possible.  I would be happy to meet with the other party leaders and the party Whips to discuss the way we might progress a Bill to allow that committee begin its investigation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach's statement that we need to reach the truth is very welcome.  The reason we are in the current difficulty is that the truth has come dripping slowly and we could not have anticipated that the Attorney General would seek immunity from the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cowen</NameTxt>
      <P>From us as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important we have a system whereby the committees of the House can, in a simple, straightforward way, reach the truth in any given situation.  Nobody sought a star Chamber.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="854" />
    <Speaker pid="BrianCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cowen</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy must be joking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>It is in nobody's interest to take that approach to the business of this House, and certainly yesterday's events in the House were not dignified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>We should not seek to have a rehash of yesterday's proceedings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not rehashing anything; I understood I was being given&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us not indulge in personalities either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood I was being given an opportunity to comment on the proposal before us and that is what I am doing.  I agree with the proposal that the House be adjourned for a period to consider the options.  I understand the proposal is that we adjourn for an hour, but I honestly think it would take a little more than an hour to discuss the complicated and complex issues.  Perhaps we should have a two hour break.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The question relates to how long the House requires to deliberate on this important matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="The Tánaiste Bertie Ahern">
      <NameTxt>The Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>To comply with Standing Orders, the Government Bill will have to go through the Bills Office, the other Bill is for the information of the House &mdash; I do not wish to be in breach of Standing Orders.  I agree with Deputy Bruton that these complex issues have existed in one form or other since 1976. If we cannot deal with the matter in the complex Bill circulated to Members of the House, we are at least required to consider the shorter version of the Bill. I welcome Deputy Harney's support for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not wish to create further animosity in the House as a result of yesterday's committee.  I congratulate my <Col N="855" /> colleague, Deputy Dan Wallace, who had a difficult day yesterday and did a good job.  In the opinion of the public the carry-on yesterday at the Select Committee on Legislation and Security was a disgrace and is something we can neither comprehend nor condone.</P>
    <P>I agree there should be a meeting of the party leaders.  On Tuesday evening my colleague, the Minister for State and Chief Whip, made the point that it would not be possible to simply have a committee meeting, to call and question people and report back to the House on Thursday morning.  That was proposed on Tuesday evening.  It was the flavour of the week that anything said by a Fianna Fáil person was put down as nonsense and unhelpful.  A motion was railroaded through the House.  While I do not want to condemn it for doing so it is always better that matters be considered. The Dáil did not give any guidance to the select committee; there was no meeting between the Whips or discussion about the procedures.  After the wrangle, when the chairman, on the instructions of the select committee, called the first witness that person made it clear he did not have absolute privilege and could not proceed.  What we are endeavouring to do now is put a procedure in place to enable us conduct our business.  That is the correct thing to do.</P>
    <P>Yesterday at the select committee my good colleague in the House, Deputy Gay Mitchell, and I exchanged some angry words.  As the Deputy well knows, I would not want any rancour but the point he was making was why someone should have raised with the Ceann Comhairle the question of natural justice. In the crossfire yesterday I was the one who raised the question.  I am aware that Members on all sides of the House have received telephone calls from the Law Library and various other concerned people to point out that there could not be an investigation or a debate of the kind envisaged without first putting procedures in place.</P>
    <Col N="856" />
    <Speaker pid="GayMitchell" hpid="Mr. G. Mitchell Mr. G. Mitchell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Mitchell</NameTxt>
      <P>Without the fellow at the other end of the telephone line.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Mr. B. Ahern Mr. B. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>I was glad that the Fine Gael Whip, Deputy Enda Kenny, came into the House at that stage to make it clear that he accepted my point, and this has been acknowledged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GayMitchell" hpid="Mr. G. Mitchell Mr. G. Mitchell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. Mitchell</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept your apology.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Mr. B. Ahern Mr. B. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach and I &mdash; to ensure I will not be accused later by the party Leaders &mdash; are due to leave later today to attend the summit at Essen.  I ask the Opposition Leaders to take this into consideration.  I am aware that they are trying to form a Government. As I stated the other day, we will not be unhelpful in that regard.  On another occasion some of the parties in Opposition allowed me and others to negotiate to form a Government. Neither the Taoiseach nor the Tánaiste will be available from this afternoon. When matters of fundamental importance to the Taoiseach and my party are being discussed I would like to be present.  I ask party Leaders to take this into account in their deliberations, perhaps before they meet me later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now that we are putting proper procedures in place I am happy that the advice we gave the other day is being followed and that we have learned from the mistakes made yesterday.  We can now deal not only with this urgent matter but also the matters we considered with the Labour Party last week, including the question of this House having an investigative committee.  In this regard I would like to quote from page 31 of the draft document which states under the heading, &ldquo;to ensure that Dáil Éireann has real powers to investigate matters of serious public concern&rdquo;&mdash; I agreed to this with Deputy Spring on Sunday night &mdash;&ldquo;a. immediate publication and urgent implementation of the Privilege and Compellability of Witnesses Bill&rdquo;&mdash; the Taoiseach has laid this Bill before the House today &mdash;&ldquo;b. mindful of the public concern of the high costs of the <Col N="857" /> beef tribunal, a Committee of Investigation may be formed to investigate a matter of serious public concern from time to time&rdquo;.  This can be done if legislative changes are made.  It could not be done the other way; a bad mistake was made on Tuesday and we are now about to correct it.  Fianna Fáil will do all it can to be constructive.</P>
    <P>Members of the House have to remember that it has been proved in the past that railroading legislation onto the Statute Book is not the correct thing to do.  One has to balance the legislation passed by the House against what is right not only to protect Members of the House but also officials who may be called before it.  If there are matters which may in some way work against them or the positions they hold they are entitled to natural justice as outlined in the Haughey case of 1971.  I raised this question yesterday as did the Minister of State, Deputy Dempsey, the other day to ensure that this would be the case.  This has been accepted.  It was not the intention of the Fianna Fáil Party to delay the process in any way but to ensure that this House conducts its business properly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us agree to suspend the sitting for a designated period in order to afford Members an opportunity of deliberating on which is the best Bill to bring forward in the circumstances. How much time is required?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoraOwen" hpid="Mrs. Owen Mrs. Owen">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Owen</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest two hours.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 11.15 a.m. and resumed at 1.15 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="The Tánaiste Bertie Ahern">
      <NameTxt>The Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>The party leaders and Whips have had the opportunity to meet and we have an all-party agreement to ask that the Dáil shall sit later than 4.45 p.m. this evening and that the sitting be suspended until 6 p.m.  For the information of Members, we are reflecting on the documents put before the House <Col N="858" /> by the Taoiseach this morning and on the proper procedure to follow from here.  We are examining the legislation prepared by the Attorney General and the more comprehensive Bill which has been in preparation for several months, if not years.  After consultation with the Attorney General and advisers to the party leaders, we will reflect on this and meet again during the afternoon.</P>
      <P>I ask that the sitting be suspended until 6 p.m. and we will report on an all-party basis at that stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The House has heard the proposition that the Dáil sit later than 4.45 p.m. today and that the sitting be suspended until 6 p.m.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 1.20 p.m. and resumed at 6 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Dáil">
    <Title>Business of Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="The Tánaiste Bertie Ahern">
      <NameTxt>The Tánaiste</NameTxt>
      <P>The party Leaders had a further meeting some time ago and, as I stated earlier, we are anxious to accommodate the passage of the legislation in the shortest possible period. Following discussion with the party leaders, it is proposed that the second Bill &mdash; the short version giving privilege to Members appearing before the committee &mdash; will be taken tomorrow.  It is hoped the Bill will be finalised by the Government at a meeting shortly after the House adjourns.  The Attorney General continues to work on submissions I have given him from the Fianna Fáil Party, and from Deputies Bruton, Harney and Spring, as well as further considering matters from the earlier Bill, the compellability of witnesses legislation, which we also had before us in draft form today.  He was to have provided me with a note for the commencement of this session but, unfortunately, he was unable to get it to me on time.  I presume we will have that note in time for the Cabinet meeting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is the intention that the Bill will be <Col N="859" /> published later tonight.  The Bills Office stated it will take approximately two and a half hours from the time of the Cabinet meeting for the Bill to be published. Because of the legal and constitutional difficulties and other matters, and from previous experience in this House, the party leaders are in agreement that to put all Stages of this Bill through both Houses of the Oireachtas tomorrow would be improper.  It is proposed, therefore, that Second Stage of the Bill be taken from 10.30 a.m. to 4 p.m. tomorrow.  There is also a temporary proposal that the House will meet at midday on Tuesday next to take Committee and remaining Stages and the Seanad will meet later on Tuesday night.  The Bill will then be referred to the President on Wednesday.  That proposal is subject to change because some people, within the House or outside it, may wish to consider the Bill or some of the constitutional or other matters that might arise from it, although we believe our Bill, as mentioned by the Taoiseach this morning, stands the best chance of holding its position against any challenge. That is a matter for the President in the final instance but others may wish to offer their points of view and they will have an opportunity to do that over the weekend.  I believe I speak for all party leaders when I say we hope people will examine the Bill over the weekend so that we will at least have a clear position and ensure that the legislation we will endeavour to pass on Tuesday night will stand any test. However, that is a matter for others.</P>
    <P>Without making any strong political point, I think we realise that the matters I and the Minister of State stated here on Tuesday did not amount to window-dressing or filibustering.  They were valid parliamentary points and I believe the House is now proceeding in the way we should have done on Tuesday. However, that is history.  Because of the way we are now proceeding, the legislation will be passed but, we should consider the second issue over the weekend <Col N="860" /> and refer it to the Whips to determine the best way of structuring an investigative committee.  The view is held that the large committee which sat yesterday is perhaps not the best way to proceed but it is a matter for the Whips to reflect on tomorrow and we will stand over their report.</P>
    <P>In summary, the Bill will be published later tonight, subject to the clearance of the Attorney General and the Cabinet meeting.  There will be no delay by my party in that regard.  The House will sit tomorrow from 10.30 a.m. to 4 p.m. to take Second Stage of the Bill and, all going well, both Houses will sit next Tuesday to take Committee and remaining Stages.  The Bill will then be referred to the President on Wednesday and if everything is in order &mdash; a matter totally for the President, not for me or the House &mdash; we will then deal with the matter on Thursday in whatever committee is decided.</P>
    <P>I have now received the note, which is fairly long, from the Attorney General.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlanMDukes" hpid="Mr. Dukes Mr. Dukes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dukes</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy read it this time?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>Smart alec.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlanMDukes" hpid="Mr. Dukes Mr. Dukes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dukes</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Deputy Treacy awake?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelTracey" hpid="Mr. N. Treacy Mr. N. Treacy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. Treacy</NameTxt>
      <P>Always.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cowen</NameTxt>
      <P>They were right to get rid of Deputy Dukes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Deputy A Deputy">
      <NameTxt>A Deputy</NameTxt>
      <P>You were John the Baptist for a short period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="Bertie" hpid="Mr. B. Ahern Mr. B. Ahern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. B. Ahern</NameTxt>
      <P>In his note the Attorney General sets out amendments he is making to the Bill on issues such as natural justice, the right to furnish statements, cross-examination, the right to give rebutting evidence, the right to address by senior counsel or solicitor and other matters he is building into the legislation.  Members will see the Bill later tonight when the Government clears it.  I propose that the Dáil adjourn until 10.30 a.m. on Friday, 9 December.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="861" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. J. Bruton Mr. J. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>What the Tánaiste said is an accurate and fair reflection of our discussions.  For over 20 years we have sought legislation to provide for privilege and compellability of witnesses.  It is undoubtedly true that there are difficult constitutional and practical problems to overcome but frequently administrators use the existence of such problems as a basis for not taking decisions.</P>
      <P>I do not doubt the sincerity of those involved in that from time to time they have attempted to solve the problem but there has not been a sustained effort to do so.  It is only because of the crisis which has arisen that we are at last making a sustained effort, perhaps under pressure of time, to solve these problems. They must be solved if we are not to be in the position where, the next time we want to hold an inquiry, we must rely on a beef tribunal type model which is vastly expensive, cumbersome and inconclusive.  We must fashion an instrument in the House that will work and we are making a serious effort to do so.</P>
      <P>It is said that it is not good to make decisions under pressure of time but the reality is most people do so because the natural tendency, in all walks of life, is to postpone things until we must deal with them.  Now that we must deal with the issue we will do so.  I agree with the Tánaiste that it is necessary to have a time lag between Second Stage and Committee Stage.  This point has been made by Oppositions of all complexions for years but it is necessary that we do so when a possible constitutional rights issue is being dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Tánaiste is correct in saying there is general agreement that we deal with the matter on Tuesday and he gave the outline of a possible timetable.  That is subject to revision.  The precise times are not necessarily agreed and may not be appropriate from other points of view.  Broadly speaking, we are proceeding to deal with the matter correctly.  I hope the precedents we establish will be durable and useful for the broader legislation which must be introduced <Col N="862" /> urgently.  We cannot afford to be in the position again where the natural demand to have a matter investigated is frustrated because of a 20-year delay in dealing with the long advertised difficulty of privilege and compellability of witnesses.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanTreacy" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Seán Treacy">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the question is that the House adjourn until 10.30 a.m. tomorrow, I would dissuade Members from attempting to debate the matter now.  I respectfully submit that we await the circulation of the Bill and that the debate proper take place tomorrow morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that.  I compliment the party leaders for the way in which they dealt with the matter.  We agree to the proposal and welcome the provision of time over the weekend to enable people reflect on the contents of what will be a short Bill so as to remove any scintilla of legal doubt that might surround it.  The exercise in which we will engage is a serious one and we must ensure it is done within the law and the confines of the Constitution.  Natural justice must not only be seen to be done but must be fully observed by all who participate in it both inside and outside the House.</P>
      <P>The normal arrangements for the management of business no longer apply in the House in that we do not have the traditional structure of Government with a clear majority and Opposition.  Therefore, in the narrow timeframe we have set for Committee and Report Stages from noon until 7 p.m. on Tuesday, we must be self-disciplined in regard to contributions and observations, otherwise we will not meet the rigorous timetable set by the Tánaiste.</P>
      <P>The Labour Party accept the proposed order for dealing with this business and will enter into the debate in the spirit I have outlined on the understanding that other parties do likewise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Progressive Democrats agree to what is proposed. <Col N="863" /> The timetable is longer than one would wish.  However, in the circumstances, there is no option but to adhere to it. Notwithstanding the fact that this Bill will take a few days to enact I hope the other and even more important work being carried on in parallel will not be delayed further and the formation of a Government is completed as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PrionsiasDeRossa" hpid="Proinsias De Rossa Proinsias De Rossa">
      <NameTxt>Proinsias De Rossa</NameTxt>
      <P>I agreed, in tandem with the other party leaders, that Second Stage of this Bill should be taken tomorrow and the Committee and Report Stages next Tuesday.  It is important to allow that time lapse between the Second Stage and Committee Stage in order to reflect over the <Col N="864" /> weekend on the implications and nuances in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlbertReynolds" hpid="The Taoiseach Albert Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Now that the House has reached agreement on the type of Bill it wants the Government will meet after this session to progress the wishes of the House.  It is our wish that the ongoing work to form a Government should proceed at an accelerated pace. I have said this on a number of occasions and I hope by the time we return from the summit in Essen Deputies will have made up their minds as to the parties which will be in Government and get on with governing the country.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 6.20 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Friday, 9 December 1994.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>