<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="30" Month="Nov" Year="1927" Vol="10" No="4" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 30 Samhain 1927" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 30 November 1927" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="83">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="83" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DUN LAOGHAIRE," RHead="BLACKROCK, DALKEY CORPORATION BILL, 1924">
    <Title>PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DUN LAOGHAIRE, BLACKROCK, DALKEY CORPORATION BILL, 1924.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH (Mr. Bennett) LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH (Mr. Bennett)">
      <NameTxt>LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH (Mr. Bennett)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Dun Laoghaire Blackrock Dalkey Corporation Bill, 1924, be read a first time.&rdquo;  This is in accordance with a Resolution that was adopted by the Seanad on 16th November, 1927.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Sir T. GRATTAN ESMONDE Sir T. GRATTAN ESMONDE">
      <NameTxt>Sir T. GRATTAN ESMONDE</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DUBLIN PORT" RHead="AND DOCKS (BRIDGE) BILL, 1927">
    <Title>PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DUBLIN PORT AND DOCKS (BRIDGE) BILL, 1927.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move: &ldquo;That the Dublin Port and Docks (Bridge) Bill, 1927, be read a first time.&rdquo;  This is in accordance with the Resolution adopted by the Seanad on the 16th November, 1927.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Sir T. ESMONDE Sir T. ESMONDE">
      <NameTxt>Sir T. ESMONDE</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Dublin Port and Docks (Bridge) Bill, 1927, be read a second time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Sir T. ESMONDE Sir T. ESMONDE">
      <NameTxt>Sir T. ESMONDE</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Go bhfuil sé oiriúnach Có-Choiste den dá Thigh do cheapa chun Bille Port agus Duganna Bhaile Atha Cliath (Droichead), 1927 do bhreithniú, eadhon, Bille dá ngairmtear Acht chun a chur ar chumas Bórd Port agus Duganna Bhaile Atha Cliath Droichead Bhutt d'ath-thógáil, d'atharú agus d'fhairsingiú; <Col N="84" /> chun cistí do sholáthar chun na hoibreacha so do dhéanamh; chun ráta breise nó ráta in ionad seanarátaí áirithe d'údarú agus chun crícheanna eile.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That it is expedient that a Joint Committee of both Houses be appointed to consider the Dublin Port and Docks (Bridge) Bill, 1927, being a Bill entitled an Act to enable the Dublin Port and Docks Board to rebuild, alter and enlarge Butt Bridge; to provide funds for the execution of these works; to authorise an additional or substituted rate in the place of certain existing rates and for other purposes, and that a message be sent to the Dáil accordingly.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>You will have to add to the motion &ldquo;and that a message be sent to the Dáil asking its concurrence.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Sir T. ESMONDE Sir T. ESMONDE">
      <NameTxt>Sir T. ESMONDE</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question as amended put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE BUSINESS. - CORK" RHead="HARBOUR BILL, 1927">
    <Title>PRIVATE BUSINESS. - CORK HARBOUR BILL, 1927.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That the Cork Harbour Bill, 1927, be read a first time.&rdquo;  This is in accordance with the Resolution that was adopted by the Seanad on the 16th November, 1927.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BenjaminHaughton" hpid="Mr. HAUGHTON Mr. HAUGHTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HAUGHTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE BUSINESS. - PILOTAGE ORDER CONFIRMATION" RHead="(No 2 BILL), 1927&mdash;THIRD STAGE">
    <Title>PRIVATE BUSINESS. - PILOTAGE ORDER CONFIRMATION (No 2 BILL), 1927&mdash;THIRD STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move that this Bill be taken in Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this a private Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>It was introduced as a private Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is so, how is it going to be taken in Committee of the whole House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>LEAS-CHATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>This is only to exercise the powers conferred on the Minister for Industry and Commerce by the Act of 1913.  These are only provisional Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="85" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>You are satisfied that the procedure is right?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>LEAS - CHATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill passed through Committee without amendment.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered to be reported.</P>
      <P>The Seanad went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE BUSINESS. - LOCAL ELECTIONS" RHead="BILL, 1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>PRIVATE BUSINESS. - LOCAL ELECTIONS BILL, 1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Local Elections Bill, 1927, be read a second time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to take advantage of this opportunity to protest against the continued disfranchisement of the citizens of Dublin.  It will, no doubt, be said that this Bill does not affect the position of the municipality of Dublin, but it postpones the elections that are due to take place.  Facilities were offered for criticising this Bill in the other House, and I hope the same facilities will be offered here, so far as the Bill concerns local administration in Dublin.  I read the speeches that were made in the Dáil, and I saw that the President made a statement with which I am in entire agreement. Speaking on the Second Reading, the President said:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I have had as much experience of elections as most members of the House and I have definitely come to the conclusion that there is scarcely any country in the world which can present such an intelligent electorate as ours.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>These were the President's words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we all agree with them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with them, but, at the same time, having made that statement, the President has been responsible for the disfranchisement of the people of the capital of Ireland for the past six years, so far as local administration is concerned.  It seems an extraordinary state of affairs that we have in the country&mdash;and I presume the capital represents the intelligence of the country&mdash;the most intelligent electorate&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="86" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A SENATOR A SENATOR">
      <NameTxt>A SENATOR</NameTxt>
      <P>Query.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>I will come to that later.  We have the President's statement, with which I am in entire agreement. But, notwithstanding the intelligence of the electorate of the country, the citizens of the capital are denied the right of electing people to represent them and to carry on local administration. I think that is a perfect scandal.  The Minister will, no doubt, say it is only being postponed, but I have been listening to that for the last six years.  That has been going on for six years, with the result that the people of the city have been denied their fundamental right to elect representatives to carry on local administration. I suppose we will be told, as Deputies in the other House were told, that the old much-abused and much-maligned Dublin Corporation were dissolved as a result of an inquiry.  I know something about the inquiry, and I know something about the manner in which inquiries have been held into the conduct of local bodies.  I say that the inquiry held with regard to the Dublin municipal authority was held by order of the Ministry, without any charge being made.  It was a roving Commission. As to one man who went before that inquiry to make a statement with regard to corruption in one department of the Corporation, when the charge was put up to him he ran away from it.  It was on evidence such as that that the Corporation of Dublin was dissolved, and the people denied the right of electing their representatives, for the past six years.  As a matter of fact, the citizens have been denied their rights and privileges since 1920.  As a Dublin-born man I say that is an absolute scandal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think it is good enough for any man to come along, whether he is from Tipperary, Limerick, Clare, or anywhere else, and to disfranchise the citizens of Dublin by saying that they are not fit to carry on the affairs of the city.  That is what the citizens have been listening to for the last six years, and I take this opportunity of registering my protest against it.  The Local Elections Bill does not deal with Dublin, as it has been stated that the question of Dublin's management will be <Col N="87" /> settled when the Report of the Greater Dublin Commission has been considered, and legislation introduced to give effect to the recommendations contained in the report.  I often heard it stated that the Dublin Corporation was a disgrace, because it wasted its time dealing with political affairs or discussing political matters.  I believe it was for political reasons that the Dublin Corporation was dissolved, and not because of corruption.  I have never been opposed to a change of conditions with regard to local administration, because I believe, from my experience as a member of the Corporation, that a drastic change was necessary.  What I object to is that the citizens have been denied their rights.  If they are the intelligent electorate that the President tells us, then I think, if proper schemes are put before them, they will elect men and women who will carry out their wishes. It is not a change that I object to, but the manner in which it is brought about.  If the citizens of Dublin are competent to elect representatives to the Dáil they are equally capable of electing representatives to carry out local administration.</P>
    <P>The present Minister for Local Government is a representative of the city of Dublin, and I am sure he would be the last man to say that the citizens were not wise in their choice of administrators. They elected him to do the national work, and, if they were competent and intelligent enough to elect the present Minister for that purpose, I claim that they are equally competent to elect people to carry on the work of local administration.  The time has arrived now when steps should be taken to put an end to the present disgraceful state of affairs.  I have referred to the Report of the Greater Dublin Commission and I read an account of the proceedings at one of the sittings.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Has this Commission made its report yet?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, sir.  I read a report of one of the meetings of this Commission, and I am sure it must have spent a good deal of time in a political harangue between the Chairman of the Commission and a well-known gasbag from one of the urban councils near <Col N="88" /> the city.  The &ldquo;Evening Herald&rdquo; was full of the political discussion between the Chairman and this well-known local gas-bag.  If the Dublin Corporation was responsible for wasting as much time on a political discussion as the Greater Dublin Commission wasted on that day they would have had headlines in all the Dublin papers condemning them. There is not a great deal in this Bill that one can find fault with, but it gives me again an opportunity to make the protest that I have been continually making against this system.  As a born citizen of Dublin I protest against it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BenjaminHaughton" hpid="Mr. HAUGHTON Mr. HAUGHTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HAUGHTON</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I come to the crux of the Bill, I should like to say that I am sure we all heartily approve of the changing of the date of the elections to the month of June.  But I would suggest, in view of obvious reasons, in connection with the Report of the Greater Dublin Commission, that the date be further deferred, and I suggest that they should be held in September. I noticed from the discussions in the Dáil that the month of June does not suit some of the Western districts, such as the Counties of Mayo and Tirconaill, on account of the migration of harvesters across the Channel, and it occurred to me that if they were deferred to a later period in the year it might also suit holiday-makers, who would then have returned home.  Another reason that occurs to me is one that perhaps the Minister for Local Government, whom we are all happy to see filling that position, might convey to the President.  I think September is a lucky month.  It was in September that the recent elections took place; it was in September that we were honoured with the presence of the President in the city of Cork, and it was in September that he obtained an unprecedented majority there.  Therefore, I think we should bear that well in mind when considering the date of these elections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think it is generally approved that the double elections, whenever they are held, should be held that month, for they would always be a saving in expense and in inconvenience, because schools in which polling takes place would then be available, and we might <Col N="89" /> also to some extent, clear away that terrible apathy that has so largely prevailed, here and elsewhere.  But many people think that instead of triennial elections, annual elections would be more suitable.  Such a system as that would keep the electors more in touch with those who represent them, would put those who were elected more on their mettle to look after their duties and prevent them from absenting themselves too much.  I suggest that the Minister might reconsider the position and arrange that after the first triennial period had elapsed the elections might be held annually, and the people thus brought constantly in touch with the matter.</P>
    <P>Senator Farren has alluded to Dublin; I notice that he was careful to leave Cork out of the discussion.  I think we have a special grievance in the city by the Lee, because we are simply tied up with Dublin as regards going back to the old institutions that we had.  I do not see why Cork should be asked to await on this belated Report from the Greater Dublin Commission. I want to put myself right with regard to the Commissioner whom we have had living amongst us for some short time.  I have nothing whatever to say against his administration. He has done his work admirably, and the state of Cork, its streets, etc., is admirable.  But notwithstanding that, it is wrong in principle that important cities like Dublin and Cork should be, so to speak, led in tutoring strings&mdash; led by the nose&mdash;and should quietly submit to what officials&mdash;able no doubt &mdash;have been carrying out for some years.  I put it to the Seanad that whereas places like the Urban District of Cobh, the County Council of Offaly, the District Council of Tipperary and the councils of Trim, Ennis, and others, are to be permitted to function almost immediately, Cork must wait until 1929 before reverting to the electoral system.  Why is all this done?  I do not know as much about Dublin as I do about my own city of Cork, but we have in this House and in the other House, some of the representatives of the late Dublin Corporation, and I think everyone in this room will admit that they are men above average intelligence, <Col N="90" /> men of ability and men of integrity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A SENATOR A SENATOR">
      <NameTxt>A SENATOR</NameTxt>
      <P>Nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BenjaminHaughton" hpid="Mr. HAUGHTON Mr. HAUGHTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HAUGHTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I say so, sir, and although I was never a member of the Cork Corporation I have had the privilege of the acquaintance of most of the members, and the same applies to that body.  As well as I remember the old members of these bodies over-stayed in office the specified time.  In Cork there was not an election for some years over the prescribed three years.  The members in some cases got lax in their attendance&mdash;some never attended&mdash;and became dissatisfied and disgruntled. In Dublin they used what influence they had, and Dublin was dissolved. Then I suppose it was not thought right that the metropolis should be the only place where the Corporation should be dissolved, and the Corporation of the important city of Cork had also to be dissolved.  Senator Farren has said that there was no charge whatever made publicly against the Dublin Corporation. The same applies to Cork. There was no charge of corruption, extravagance, neglect of duty or disobedience of the Local Government Department's orders, ever put forward. When the Commissioner took over the different Departments of the Corporation, all appeared to be in good order, and he expressly specified the Public Health Department and the Waterworks Department as being most creditable.  On November 23rd, Mr. Bourke used these words in the Dáil: &ldquo;There is an idea that because you have a body in existence for a great number of years you ought never to change it, that the old order should never be changed and that you should never have anything new, but that is a wholly wrong conception.  I hope the Commissioner system will be retained, whether with some kind of advisory body or not.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Everybody is entitled to his opinion, but, as one conservative in my views, I submit that there are old historical records of our corporations and other institutions that are of great value. We, in Cork, have many charters, but the first was granted in the 12th century, in the reign of that king from whom subsequently Magna Charta was <Col N="91" /> won, and ever since that date down to the present, except for a few years during the usurpation of the Commonwealth, we have had a long succession, from the reign of King Edward I. to the present day, of mayors and lord mayors.  Do you think that we, who can look at this matter from a standpoint such as that, are prepared readily to scrap old charters and old institutions, have Commissioners in charge and abandon the principle of election?  I for one will protest against it.</P>
    <P>In Dublin you have the advantage of having a Mansion House, which we in Cork have not.  We have not even a town hall since the destruction of the Town Hall in those unhappy times from which we have so satisfactorily emerged.  Our present Lord Mayor, who is now, I am glad to say, a Deputy in the other House, under great difficulty is endeavouring to show, at any rate, some hospitality, and whatever Cork's faults have been, she has never been charged with lack of hospitality. We are only too glad to entertain political leaders or any prominent men who come amongst us, but we have now no place in which to do so; we have to hunt the city for rooms in hotels, and that sort of thing, to entertain our guests.  Immediately before the Commissioner was appointed advertisements appeared in the Press inviting tenders for the erection of a new town hall.  Tenders were received, and the lowest, a little over £60,000, was virtually accepted.  Subsequently, for some reason or other, the thing was dropped and the money was relegated to the building of houses, which there was certainly a great demand for at the time and for which there is still, fortunately, a demand.  But I submit that this should be seriously taken into consideration, and that the money that was earmarked for the Town Hall should be given to us so that we could erect a building in which we could entertain our guests satisfactorily.  I hope the Minister will seriously consider the points I have raised, and at any rate bracket Cork with the other councils that have been suppressed and that are going to function again.  I hope they will be functioning satisfactorily within the next year.</P>
    <Col N="92" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. DOWDALL Mr. DOWDALL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOWDALL</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite recognise that it is an extremely easy thing to put up a case against Commissioners.  In fact, theoretically, I think it would be practically impossible to defend them. But, speaking with a rather intimate knowledge of Cork, I am compelled to say that the Commissioner system there has been productive of very much more good, within a short time, than the Corporation has ever been.  Nevertheless, I am not out for a permanent continuation of the Commissioner system.  I know, and perhaps the Local Government Department may not be quite innocent of the fact, that a Bill prepared by some local people is in existence. In the past few weeks I have consulted all the Cork members on that Bill, with the exception of the President, who is now the senior member for Cork.  Possibly we will have a discussion on it, and we hope to have the advantage of Senator Haughton's presence. When we come to practical agreement, we will probably consult the President also.  I fancy the terms of that Bill will be such as will commend themselves to the Local Government Department.  I may say, however, that that Bill does provide for the continuation of a City Manager, and a very much smaller Corporation than formerly existed.  In fact, I believe that if you have a large Corporation, even with extremely able and industrious men, you are bound to have inefficiency, because for executive purposes the smaller the body you have the more effective and efficient it is likely to be.  That is my view with regard to it.  Until that agreed measure takes final shape I do not propose to have any criticism of the existing administration. I can only speak of it in the very highest terms and I give every credit to the Commissioner, because he certainly has put a great many things that were previously unsatisfactory into a satisfactory condition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should just like to touch on another point that Senator Haughton has raised, and that is in reference to the Town Hall.  The money that was awarded as compensation for the reconstruction of the Town Hall was spent on providing additional housing.  I am not clear of guilt in regard to that <Col N="93" /> transaction. because I suggested it.  I am very pleased to see that the housing conditions are very much better than they were.  I think it is far better to provide houses for poor people than to provide places of entertainment for visitors who may come along.  When they do come along, we are able to cater for them in hotels, and I have never heard any serious complaint as to the quality of the entertainment given.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. BARRINGTON Mr. BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>Coming as I do from a more ancient city than either of the two Senators who have spoken, I should like to quote a very old and homely proverb, which I think will throw a lot of light on this question. and that is, that the proof of the pudding is in the eating.  These local bodies existed for the purpose of administration rather than glorification. Whoever administers the city best deserves the best thanks of the community. In Dublin the Commissioners found that the citizens were paying most exorbitant taxes.  They have cut down these taxes by I forget how many shillings in the pound.  No doubt the Minister will be able to enlighten us on the subject.  I do not think anybody who has had any experience of affairs in Dublin can say that the public services are worse than they were in the days of the Corporation.  I believe the universal opinion will be that they are far and away better.  The same thing, I believe, applies to Cork.  As long as you get better results by the administration of Commissioners, I see no reason for the re-establishment of those public bodies who, however well-intentioned, did not do their work efficiently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. GOGARTY Dr. GOGARTY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. GOGARTY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in agreement with Senator Barrington.  We heard from Senator Farren many complaints about the principle of elections.  But when did a municipal election change the personnel of the Council?  He spoke as a dissolved Councillor.  There was no question of corruption, but it was said to be inefficient.  One has only got to see the immense change in the city and the newly-built houses.  I do not know whether the old problem of 52,000 people living in single rooms still holds.  With all the new houses built it may have decreased.  That was under the old Corporation system.  The <Col N="94" /> idea that there should be an election held on every public question is an absurd one.  The very best administered towns on the continent are run by a professional City Manager.  There is nobody to elect a crowd of councillors who have time at their disposal.  The corrupt things in life are caused by people who give gratuitous time to things, from Select Vestries down to Corporations.  A paid City Manager is far more sensitive and responsive to his employers than is a corporation. In spite of invoking the wrath of Senator Farren, I must confess that I signed a minority report&mdash;I think I was in a minority of one&mdash;hoping to goodness that we would never have the Dublin Corporation back again.  I did not like to extend it to say that the whole county should be run by Commissioners. It is not very much bigger than the city of Dublin and it is more easily managed.  In America the centralisation of government is going on apace with great results, because there are things that are not within the purview of citizens.  An ordinary mass of 100,000 citizens is inchoate and not necessarily intelligent acting in a massed way.  I find that the more intelligent the electors are the less intelligent are the results, because very many of them have no choice in the matter.  As I say, for twenty years the personnel of the Dublin Corporation has hardly changed at any election.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. GOGARTY Dr. GOGARTY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. GOGARTY</NameTxt>
      <P>There was the one Lord Mayor for many years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>There were eighty members.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. GOGARTY Dr. GOGARTY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. GOGARTY</NameTxt>
      <P>There was only the one Lord Mayor, and it was becoming chronic&mdash;it was very nearly becoming a hereditary position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>He rendered good service anyhow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. GOGARTY Dr. GOGARTY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. GOGARTY</NameTxt>
      <P>We will not enter into that.  I am sorry they abolished the position of Lord Mayor, if for nothing else than to have someone to carry the mace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>You are as much concerned as anyone else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="95" />
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. GOGARTY Dr. GOGARTY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. GOGARTY</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Haughton's remarks can be understood from the fact that he comes from the county of the persuasive stone.  He also appealed to sentiment, and thought there should be an election about every single thing touching a city.  I hold that there are very many important things in life that are not subject to an election.  One does not consult the populace about what one will have for dinner.  The city is amazingly improved, as one can see from the surface of the streets and the promenade of houses arising in Fairview. Take a period of twenty years before and five years after, and see which is the more desirable condition of things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is responsible for the housing in Fairview?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. GOGARTY Dr. GOGARTY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. GOGARTY</NameTxt>
      <P>The Commissioners, of course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>You are wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>We had better pass from that; it is a disputed point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. GOGARTY Dr. GOGARTY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. GOGARTY</NameTxt>
      <P>They must have been a sort of ante-dated construction thrown forward from the imagination of the councillors, including Senator Farren.  Some of them are only about eighteen months up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>Who made the scheme?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. GOGARTY Dr. GOGARTY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. GOGARTY</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not go into the question of schemes.  It was the Government laid the schemes when they laid the schemers and put in the Commissioners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>They sent us a few schemers all right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. GOGARTY Dr. GOGARTY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. GOGARTY</NameTxt>
      <P>I need not enlarge further on that.  I only express the hope that the Commissioners will be continued and the elections deferred as long as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir J. KEANE Sir J. KEANE">
      <NameTxt>Sir J. KEANE</NameTxt>
      <P>I sympathised with the last speaker when he said he was in a minority of one.  That is the way I have sometimes been myself.  I am very much disposed to agree with him on this occasion, but I am afraid I cannot wholly agree.  I do not say that either the elective or the nominated method is <Col N="96" /> necessarily right.  We have hitched ourselves as a matter of governing principle, to the elective method, and I think that at this stage it is very hard to get away from it.  If the Government think it should be abandoned, in my opinion it should be abandoned in a more logical manner, and we should definitely break with the elective method in regard to municipal government. Probably if we examine the matter we will find there is a half-way house.  To a certain extent that is met by the report of the Poor Law Commission. I should like the Minister to say whether he has yet considered that report&mdash;not necessarily the majority report only, but the minority report also&mdash;and whether he is prepared to say that the recommendation with regard to a nominated health commissioner&mdash;a nominated officer to be the executive of the county council in all matters of health&mdash;will be adopted.  To my mind that effects the best compromise.  The county councils will be elected and will deal with general policy and pass estimates. Beyond that they will leave all the detailed administration to an appointed commissioner.  I think the Local Government Department themselves cannot escape a certain responsibility for any inefficiency on the part of local bodies.  They are so tied up and hampered by petty restrictions that they do not get an opportunity of feeling their sense of responsibility.  In certain cases when things get too bad they must undoubtedly be abolished, but I think it would be a far better principle to give them a little more rope so that they may hang themselves, and not tie them up by regulations, restrictions and interference from the central body.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid most of the matters that have been discussed here are things that have come in as a kind of side-wind to this particular piece of legislation.  The real matter that is dealt with in this Bill is the postponement of the elections for urban districts from a time in January to a time in June and the bringing of the date of elections for urban districts into definite relation with the date of elections for the county councils and the re-starting of a triennial <Col N="97" /> series that was broken as a result of the conditions&mdash;I might say&mdash; following 1914 down.  I am glad to get the kind of general approval that the Seanad has given to the general scheme of the Bill.  It was necessary in dealing with the main matter in the Bill to make clear what was the position with regard to certain bodies that had been dissolved.  The effect of Section 3 is to give the Minister the discretion that he still has arising out of previous legislation to keep the Commissioner system going in Dublin City, in the Dublin Union, in Cork City, and in the three urban districts of Trim, Ennis, and Westport. Senator Haughton misunderstood the position with regard to Trim, Ennis and Westport.  They will be continued, as far as I can see at present, under Commissioners but if the situation changes to such an extent between this and next June that we think the election can be held, we would be prepared to allow urban elections to be held there.  Section 3 gives us that particular power and in the third part of the Bill, we propose to postpone the elections in County Dublin, as distinct from the County Borough of Dublin, so that we will not have elections in the very many bodies that already exist in County Dublin under the circumstances.  You might have an election next year costing anything from £5,000 to £10,000 according to the area covered and as a result of decisions taken under the Greater Dublin Commission, you might have a re-election of those bodies or a replacing of them within twelve months. The Bill retains, to the Minister, his discretion in regard to certain dissolved bodies and proposes to postpone elections in the County of Dublin that would otherwise take place there.</P>
      <P>Senator Haughton suggested that September would be a better month than June.  Perhaps in the way he put it, it would be introducing politics into Local Government if we postpone the elections to September.  It would not however cover his point with regard to migratory labourers.  The point it would raise with regard to this is that they leave at a date in June and are away for a considerable period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A date in June has been selected <Col N="98" /> after exhaustive considerations, and seems the date most generally agreed on.  The county councils seem satisfied. June is a good date for them.  We had to postpone them to the end of June to get rid of the difficulty created by the new register not being the statutory register until the 1st June.  We had to get away from the 1st June by a period of about twenty days.  I do not think it is possible to get away from the June date of the election, and I think even if the matter were properly reasoned out on an amendment, we would find a better date could not be suggested. With regard to Cork and Dublin, part of the discussion would seem to suggest that the Government had departed from the principle of elected bodies. That is not a fact.  The Local Government Act of 1925 makes it perfectly clear that in any case in which a body has been dissolved, for any reason stated in the Act, not later than three years after the date of dissolution of the body the Minister will cause an elected body to be re-elected, and will hand to that body all the powers and properties that originally existed; so the principle is not departed from at all.  A partial discussion of that principle cannot take place on a Bill like this.  If the discussion is to take place, let it be applied to the definite matter concerned.  If, in discussing a Bill dealing with one main matter, we attempt to discuss anything that is only partially related to it, we can get no satisfactory discussion of the matter beyond having a few opinions expressed. These opinions even do not get a fair opportunity of carrying weight, because they are not related to a proposal to take a definite decision. I would not like it to be understood that the legislation at present existing implies in a way a departure in the matter of Government policy from elected bodies.  If we take what has been said with regard to Cork and Dublin, I think that the Senate perhaps has had some slight evidence in the discussion that has taken place of how questionable it is to discuss the merits, good, bad or indifferent of the dissolution of these two bodies.  I suggest that it really does not arise on the Bill that is at present before us.  If the merits of the case with regard to Cork <Col N="99" /> and Dublin were to be discussed, I suggest they ought to have arisen on the Local Elections (Dissolved Authorities) Act, 1926, when it was before the Senate here.  I think that the discussion might have taken place then, and might rest until that particular Act had run its course.  The matter was discussed here in 1926, and under the Act of 1926, the Minister for Local Government was given authority to retain Commissioners in Dublin and Cork to a date not later than the 31st March, 1929.  Nothing has arisen since, so far as I am concerned as Minister for Local Government, either with regard to Cork or Dublin.  The suggestion to replace the Commissioners there by elected bodies has arisen on this particular Bill, and not in any kind of formulated way. Senator Dowdall's case in 1926 was that there was not a tittle of opposition in Cork.  The matter was next brought to my attention by a Deputy who has had considerable experience of city government in Cork suggesting that the Corporation ought to be restored there, but at the same time that, instead of a Corporation of 56, there should be a Corporation of 12 or 20.  That suggestion contained a very radical change, and I think it ought not to arise as a side-wind to this particular legislation here.  On Cork, I have simply to say what I said in the Dáil on this matter, and that is: If there is going to come from any class of the community in Cork ideas which we consider cannot be better, we are not going to stand in the way of their being put into operation at the earliest possible moment.</P>
    <P>Senator Dowdall said there has been a Bill, but so far as I know that Bill has been left to hang fire, practically to see what is going to be the result in Dublin City.  The interests of a city like Cork are great and important, and if allowing the election of a new elected body in Cork to wait over for nine months, that is from June to a date not later than the 31st March, 1929, is going to give perhaps one or two additional important ideas towards the solution of city government there, the delay would be well worth while.  However the position is that if Cork City <Col N="100" /> people are moving in the way Senator Dowdall says they are no one will be happier to see what they are going to do than the present Minister for Local Government, and everything they have to say will be very carefully and sympathetically examined.</P>
    <P>On the question of Dublin, as I say, a discussion of the past brings us into a discussion that has not its roots in anything. We cannot have a discussion with its roots in anything except we are discussing something practical.  The practical proposition that faces us here to-day is the Report of the Commission on Greater Dublin, which draws our attention to the fact, on Page 3 of the Report, that in the area to be comprised within Greater Dublin, and to enjoy unitary control and administration in that area, there now function some 19 thinking and spending authorities. This report has been published since November, 1926.  The time that has passed since has not been normal. The co-ordination of the different bodies that exist in Dublin, the standing back and looking at the affairs in the City and County of Dublin, with a valuation of upwards of £2,000,000, will require very careful examination and thinking out.  I do not think that, in our present circumstances, a complete examination of this report and a complete setting up of our proposal in connection with the matters and their embodiment in legislation could be expected sooner than the spring of 1929, and we are not asking anything unreasonable when we ask that the present system of government in Dublin City should be continued until such time as we are able to bring forward these proposals.  The present County Council in Dublin should continue to deal with the government of County Dublin until such time as we have settled the whole question as to what is to be done with the Greater Dublin Commission's report.  To do anything other than that would be either to skimp and to rush a consideration of this very important matter or, alternatively, to have elections for the City and County of Dublin spending on them something like £10,000 and dissolving these bodies say, in less than twelve months, in order to replace them by other types of bodies.</P>
    <Col N="101" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>You dissolved Parliament after two months, and it cost a good deal more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the dissolution of the Dublin Corporation, these are historical facts.  We have to face the problem that lies before us, that is, how we are best to organise the government of the capital and the county.  I suggest we are not asking too much when we are asking for the nine additional months that the legislation of 1926 allows.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. WYSE POWER Mrs. WYSE POWER">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. WYSE POWER</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister is here, perhaps he would give us an idea as to when we may hope to have legislation on the matter of the Greater Dublin Commission.  I think the whole argument of to-day really centres around that legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know whether you will be able to draw him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. WYSE POWER Mrs. WYSE POWER">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. WYSE POWER</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope I may.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Anything I have to be drawn can be drawn.  I have already done very vigorous work in relation to this.  There is a Committee examining the whole finance and one examining the whole engineering side of it.</P>
      <P>As I have said in the Dáil in connection with this matter, I am stretching my hope, simply because I am stretching my own efforts and those who are working with me when I say that I hope legislation dealing with that matter will be finished in such time as to allow the different bodies that are to be set up to be established not later than the 31st of March, 1929.  That is my hope and, at present, all that I can be drawn about is my hope.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. WYSE POWER Mrs. WYSE POWER">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. WYSE POWER</NameTxt>
      <P>Legislation next year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>It would mean legislation towards the end of next year.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DEFENCE FORCES (TEMPORARY" RHead="PROVISIONS) (NO. 2) BILL, 1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>PRIVATE BUSINESS. - DEFENCE FORCES (TEMPORARY PROVISIONS) (NO. 2) BILL, 1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That this Bill be read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE BUSINESS. - FINANCE (NO." RHead="2) BILL, 1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>PRIVATE BUSINESS. - FINANCE (NO. 2) BILL, 1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <Col N="102" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill has been certified by the Ceann Comhairle of the Dáil as a Money Bill.  The question is &ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir JOHN KEANE Sir JOHN KEANE">
      <NameTxt>Sir JOHN KEANE</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know the correct form which an amendment should take requiring this Bill to be reconsidered by the Dáil.  That is what I would like to have done but I have hardly any hope that the Seanad would support me in that way.  I should hope to spare the Dáil the outpouring of economic talk, or rather economic heresy, which this Bill and the matters connected therewith received when under discussion there.  Feeling strongly as I do and associated with so few people who share my views, I regard it as necessary to lose no opportunity of becoming bold and placing before the House and the country, so far as one can, one's view of the whole doctrine of our fiscal policy.  I know that there are some people who regard opposition of my kind, of what might be called a doctrinaire free trader, as completely out of date and futile&mdash; nothing but a sort of Rip van Winkle waking up to find that times and circumstances have changed.  All I can say is that we are in good company. Only recently a manifesto was signed largely by leading business men of repute in all countries, calling attention to the increasing danger of these tariff barriers.  Only recently an Economic Council at Geneva, where it is very hard to get agreement, also sounded a note of warning and, although the report is obviously a compromise, it deals with the danger involved in economic isolation by piling up tariff walls, limiting markets and by the inefficiency of small-scale production which such a policy involves.  A business man, no less eminent than Sir Hugh Bell in a recent speech, pointing to a map prepared by Mr. Morrison Bell showing the effect of tariff walls, said: &ldquo;There are people starving and dying on account of these.&rdquo;  That is true.  The economic policy of isolation and selfishness is responsible more than anything else for the inability of Europe to recover to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In this country, in approaching the <Col N="103" /> problem, we played in a cautious manner. We adopted what is called the selective method.  I do not think that that method is any better; in fact, I think it is rather more dangerous than some scientific and co-ordinated method.  The selective method reminds me of a man who drinks himself to death by a slow process.  He has a whiskey and soda to-day and it does no harm.  He has two to-morrow and the next day, and the process apparently does no harm, but the process is certain and the end is sure.  He has created a demand and craving for a drug which ultimately ruins his whole constitution. That is not an unfair analogy to the psychology and mentality involved in this doctrine of so-called protection. You make one schedule to-day in connection with tariffs, and you make another to-morrow, and before you know where you are you have the whole thing ringed around and you are in the meshes of this vicious system.  I only refer incidentally to what I believe to be the official policy of the Opposition, which is neither restrained nor scientific. It is madness, in my opinion.  It is a doctrine which has as its undisguised object to build up through economic methods a spirit of nationality, and the nationalism is to be forced on the country through its economic system, and, by prohibition and licence, to compel articles to be made within our shores, however unsuitable people may be for making them, however scant we may be in raw material, or untutored in industrial tradition of manufacture.  Surely the first intentions of the Government were right, and why they departed from them has not been satisfactorily explained. They said: &ldquo;You must first settle principles before we discuss details.&rdquo; They appointed the right class of people to examine them.  Obviously, business people are not suitable in that respect.  You get all kinds of logrolling, wire-pulling, and you discover qualities of cupidity and avarice when you refer such matters to business men. It is a case of &ldquo;You support me and I will support you.&rdquo;  Everyone tries to get behind the barrier as immediate profit lies there and the question of national interests is rather liable to be <Col N="104" /> overlooked.  As I say, the right people were appointed, people who had no axe to grind, and they turned the whole thing down.  They admitted in principle that if you had to settle this matter by a body free from all political influence, and if you were to remove it all from party politics, you might conceivably fix on certain duties which would do no harm.</P>
    <P>What did the Government do?  In the face of that report they immediately proceeded to rope in fifty per cent. of non-agricultural imports.  They roped them in behind a tariff wall and they proceeded to appoint a Commission to deal with the remainder.  They then called in civil servants.  I admit that civil servants are a better tribunal than business interests but they are far inferior to trained economists who are the only people with knowledge and with the power of seeing the unseen, because it is the unseen that is so important in matters of this kind.  A distinguished French economist, Professor Bastiat, recently dealt with great skill and in a popular manner with this seeing of the unseen and all the repercussions involved in these fiscal heresies. We are now dealing with the first born of this Tariff Commission.  Doctors say that first born are generally weak but it does not mean that the next offspring will not be stronger.  It is often said that the youngest child is strongest of all.  If that analogy comes true you see what we are in for later on.  We have quite enough in the comparatively minor recommendations contained in this Bill to enable us to examine all the implications of it.  We can see in connection with the margarine tariff the manoeuvring that evidently must have gone on behind the scenes.  We reached a stage where the three parties involved disagreed, but am I wrong in suggesting that before that disagreement came an attempt was made to arrive at a division in percentages of the pool?  I may be wrong, and, if I am, I shall be glad to be corrected. That is what generally happens. Interests get together and they say: &ldquo;We are now going to be all right. Our market is to be restricted.  We will pool our produce and share the great percentage of the receipts.&rdquo;  That did not happen in this case.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="105" /> We see disagreement and we also see a curious thing.  One firm&mdash;it is common knowledge that it is controlled by a foreign combine&mdash;gave a guarantee as regards price and quality and we see another firm withdrawing altogether from the application.  Then we see a curious development in the other case, where an attack is made on that firm controlled by a continental combine and they say: &ldquo;This is no use to us because it is going to be behind the tariff wall controlled by this large continental group and they will have such great resources and be so efficient that we, independent people, will be beaten.&rdquo;  If that did not happen and if the guarantee had not been given I can see a state of affairs that would have occurred.  The percentages of division would be agreed, the prices would be arranged, but they would not be in the interest of the consumers. There would be substantial profits and concerns would have no inducement to become efficient in their methods of production.  Prices would be fixed as they were during the war.  During the war the price of turning a sack of flour into bread had to be fixed so as to allow for the variations in efficiency of between 10s. and 35s.&mdash;10s. in the case of the efficient and 35s. in the case of the inefficient firm.  That is, more or less, the method that would be involved in fixing the prices if the agreement as to percentages had been made.  This tariff on margarine shows the danger involved in the question of tariff barriers.  You might conceivably get a better managed foreign firm driving out of business its competitors in this country and then raising prices against the consumer.  Where it is claimed that the consumer is protected in the present case is that the guarantee is given that prices will not be higher and that the quality will not be inferior to the same article produced under the same conditions in England.  I ask you, as sensible men, what is that guarantee worth.  The prices of margarine can be compared, but what about the quality?  There is no article in which quality varies more than margarine. It is common knowledge that there must be a great difference in quality as there is in price.  How does this State <Col N="106" /> claim that it is going to safeguard the taxpayers?  Will all this margarine in retail establishments be periodically submitted to chemical analysis and will there be maintained an array of State chemists going round the country and pronouncing on these various qualities? I do not believe that can be done and it would be wholly unnecessary if we had a rational doctrine of free imports. We have also curious arguments brought forward in connection with this special article.</P>
    <P>I notice that in the Dáil one Deputy asked, &ldquo;Why do you not also protect the oil, which is an ingredient?&rdquo; The reply was, &ldquo;Our policy is not to protect raw material,&rdquo; suggesting that oil is a raw material.  It is the raw material of one trade, but it is the finished article of another trade&mdash;seed-crushing. Why not protect seed-crushing, and have our oil produced at home? Professor Whelehan, one of the Tariff Commissioners, has discovered that it is very hard to say where one trade begins and another ends.  I am surprised that it should be necessary to receive evidence so that the Commission may arrive at a knowledge of an elementary economic truth.  You have prohibition of machinery in this margarine tariff.  Where margarine is produced with the greatest efficiency it is alongside the seed-crushing business, and the oil is conveyed from the seed-crushing plant to the margarine works. Here you are bringing oil over in barrels, and the extra cost has to be borne by the consumers.  Margarine is the poor man's butter and a large amount of it must be consumed.  You have in this subsidised inefficiency for which the consumer somehow, in spite of all guarantees, will have to pay.  This whole question of protection is difficult, and is the blemish of small nationalities; they are good, they are cultural, and they are individual, but they have this blemish, that they all try to make themselves, fiscally and in a manufacturing sense, self-contained.  Their markets are small, their capital limited and their sources restricted, and they cannot produce articles with the same efficiency as if there were a system of free imports where industrial tradition could be used to the best advantage for employing the raw material, and the <Col N="107" /> natural resources of each developed in its proper medium, so that the world would get the advantage of combined efficiency.  We hear of the analogy of America and how it has prospered under the doctrine of protection.  There is no analogy.  If you had the whole of Europe one economic entity, and all these twenty-eight tariff barriers that are destroying the economic light of Europe swept away, and if you had free interchange such as there is between the States in America, then the position would be somewhat analogous; or if you had that free interchange within the British Empire you would have something analogous to America, which is a huge continent, self-contained, and with a population of eighty millions. I hope the Government will study the question of Australia.  To-day Australia is being very sorely pressed by her policy of heavy tariffs.  Prices are rising and land is going out of cultivation. It is generally believed that her very heavy borrowing policy, which has become mainly the policy of the world, is largely accounted for by that.  Her policy of protection can only mean subsidising inefficiency to build up industries. I hardly dare to ask the Seanad to send back the Bill for reconsideration, but I hope the House will seriously consider the dangers of this policy I have referred to&mdash;of when you get into trouble taking another pull at the bottle.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'FARRELL Mr. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>To come to the Bill before the House, if the main object of the two new tariffs proposed in the Bill is to give employment, as is claimed by the Government, then certainly the maximum achievement to be hoped for is negligible, and would, in my opinion, hardly justify the introduction of a special Finance Bill.  To listen to or read the speeches of Deputies in the other House as to the utility of protection in solving unemployment, made when this little Bill was under discussion, one would imagine that the unemployment problem was to be solved by the imposition of these tariffs.  One of the results of the tariffs will be that they will make it more difficult for the poor to live, unless there is going to be some guarantee that there is to be no <Col N="108" /> increase in the price of margarine. Only 85 people were employed in the manufacture of rosary beads in 1926. Many of these are low-paid women, and the majority of them were only part-time employees.  The maximum it is hoped to employ when this tariff is in force, and the sale of Irish rosary beads has increased, is 160.  Seeing that the majority of these are low-paid workers, and taking into consideration the amount of time that has been wasted before the Tariff Commission, by the draftsman, and in the debates in both Houses, and the amount of publicity given to the whole thing, surely one has to admit that there has been a mountain of noisy labour to bring forth a very delicate and ricketty mouse. Incidents small in themselves have sometimes far-reaching consequences.  I can foresee quite a difficult problem for the customs authorities when they come to collect the tariff on imported rosary beads.  One can carry several dozen rosary beads in his pockets without very appreciably increasing his bulk.  Fancy a person laden down with religious emblems being asked if he has any rosary beads with him, and his commercial instincts overcoming his religious convictions, and his giving an untruthful reply.  One can easily see that the moral qualities of the Irish trader are quite equal to salving his conscience for the breaking of manmade law by the knowledge that he would thereby make it easier for the poor to follow their religious practices by his importation of the rosary beads in defiance of the customs law.  Could the Minister say what is the maximum number of rosary beads a traveller can import free of duty?  Every year large pilgrimages go to Lourdes and Rome. Ministers, including the President have gone on these pilgrimages.  It is quite a common occurrence for many of these pilgrims to bring back rosary beads&mdash; perhaps hundreds of them&mdash;for distribution among their friends, and for use generally in the district in which they live.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Are these rosary beads to be admitted free of duty?  If they are to be admitted, what protection is there against an unscrupulous trader using a friend in a pilgrimage to import hundreds of beads from England or elsewhere on <Col N="109" /> the plea that they were brought from Lourdes?  Another problem is that the beads brought in in that way are all blessed, and as such cannot be sold. They cease to have any value in a commercial sense&mdash;that is, if anyone can value them in a commerical sense.  Suppose a tax is imposed, how can the officer say what is their commercial value, and what is their religious value?  I see here a conflict of opinion between the Church and the State.  The problem has to be solved by the inland revenue and customs authorities.  I do not like the idea of laying hands on a passenger and rudely searching him for beads, as if he were being searched on suspicion of being a bootlegger.  This tariff on beads is going to make it very difficult for the poor to carry out their religious practices.  The same people will, perhaps, later on have to pay more for their margarine.  Coming to margarine, according to the figures given by the Minister, the number of people employed in that industry last year was under 150&mdash;104 in one factory and 37 in another.  A number of these were out of employment at the end of the year.  The amount of extra employment to be given as a result of the imposition of this tariff is, and must be, exceedingly small.  I find that the value of the margarine produced in Ireland in 1926 was £271,800.  Of that £153,000 worth was exported.  The value of the margarine imported was £168,000, so that our imports and exports in that particular commodity almost balance. The total consumption in the Saorstát was £286,000, so that there is a danger of our losing the foreign market.  Even if we capture the whole of the home market we will not be able to employ many more people than were employed in 1926, probably the worst year in the margarine trade.</P>
    <P>As Senator Sir John Keane said, margarine is the butter of a large section of the poor.  Unless there is some effective control in regard to price, it will mean the imposition of an unwarrantable burden on the poorest section of the population.  We are assured by all those who look for tariffs that prices are not going to go up as a result of tariffs; that, in fact, they may go down, because as there will be a bigger turnover they will be able to sell cheaper. <Col N="110" /> We find that in practice it is quite the reverse.  A couple of years ago a tariff of, I think, 33? per cent., was put on furniture.  I have had a specific example of the manner in which that tariff has been used by an Irish manufacturer. There is a particular type of cheap armchair, for kitchens and dining-rooms, brought out by an Irish firm, which is being considerably assisted under the Trade Loans Act.  Before the tax was put on the wholesale price of that armchair was 24s. 6d., and it included a very substantial cushion which would cost 4s. or 5s.  The price of that article now, with the tariff, is 28s. 6d., minus the cushion.  It is the same article in every respect, but the wholesale price has gone up, allowing 4s. for the cushion.  That is only one example of the manner in which these tariffs are exploited.  People furnishing their houses find it much more difficult to get furniture than before the tariff was put on.  These are difficulties the poor, and even people of the middle class, are experiencing as a result of tariffs.  We know that the importation of boots has scarcely diminished since the imposition of a tariff.  The Minister gave some figures in regard to that. He said the value of the boots imported in 1924 amounted to £1,900,000, and in 1926 to £1,790,000.  The general belief is that a cheaper type of boot is being imported.  It carries a tariff which is paid for by the purchaser, so that less value is being received by those who buy.</P>
    <P>I went into a shop belonging to one of the principal Irish boot manufacturers recently for a pair of boots. Six pairs were shown to me and out of the six only one was an Irish-made pair.  Here was an Irish firm that had applied for a tariff and got a tariff and, instead of trying to sell the Irish article, they were endeavouring to pawn off imported goods.  It is simply because they are able to make a bigger profit as a result of the manipulation of the trade in connection with tariffs. The plea before the Tariff Commissioners is that they are going to give more employment and will help to solve the unemployment problem if a tariff is put into-operation.  As far as one can see, almost the net result of the imposition of the tariff is to increase the <Col N="111" /> cost of the article that has the tariff imposed upon it.</P>
    <P>The two articles before us are, of course, of comparatively little consequence. No one would die of hunger because he could buy a rosary beads. In the case of margarine suffering may be caused amongst the very poor people who have to use margarine instead of butter.  To my mind, the Government will have to consider the question of controlling prices in the cases of protected articles.  I find that those who are most loud in objecting to any form of State interference in connection with private industry are the people most clamant for State interference when it is a case of protecting what is very often their own inefficiency in industry. State interference otherwise seems to be anathema; it would tend to clog industry.  But the people who are antagonistic in those circumstances are the very people who rush along and demand it for everything connected with their own business.  That policy is inconsistent and it has largely been used by ignorant politicians as a popular party cry.  It has been used throughout the country without any real consideration of all that is involved, and it looks like the wholesale development of a protectionist policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. BENNETT Mr. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>One is almost coerced by what has been said here to venture a few remarks upon this question. Tariffs, from the point of view of Senator Sir John Keane, who is a doctrinaire free trader, are anathema.  The Senator gives us two or three basic facts in connection with the imposition of tariffs.  He refers to the scantiness of raw materials and mentions that they could not be used economically in industry where they are not locally available.  He refers to the question of small nationalities and trying to use tariffs as a means of bolstering up small nationalities.  The Senator also refers to the cost of imposing tariffs which will not be of any real value, as he suggests is the case in the present issue.  I am neither a doctrinaire free trader nor the reverse, but I would like to point out that this country is in a position in which it is incumbent on Ministers to investigate the question of tariffs.  We certainly are a small <Col N="112" /> nationality and I think we might hold that under the treatment we received for many years we were a backward nationality, and backward nationalities the world over have been exploited by the financiers of the world for their system of exchange, to get for themselves something for nothing, so to speak.  Backward nationalities produce food and other things of that sort and they have been exploited by the commercial enterprises of the world that have given exchange values of a very high character to everything which is manufactured and exchange values of very low character to everything which is produced from the fertility of the soil and which is the gift of God.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Here in this country the main things produced and the main things exported are agricultural products, which on exchange have a very small value.  All that is put into them through God and through the soil is supposed to be a gift for the world at large, and rightly so, and all the arguments of economists are based on suggestions of this nature, that it is only the values that you put into these matters by hand that are of any consideration.  We, unfortunately, have no products in connection with which that great value is put in by industrialists and by hand.  We have great fertility of soil, and the products of the farm, as the result of the work of farmers, may have a small exchange value, but they have a large utility value.  The Government have set up the process of selective tariffs, and we must consider by what means the product we have to sell can be made so effective that we will keep for ourselves as much as we can of the gifts of nature, and utilise as far as we can the resources of nature to the advantage of our own country.  When we consider exchange values, we should consider also utility values and the views of trained economists. All our efforts for industrial economy should be aimed at creating a market in this country for a great portion of our products.  The only product we have, the great factor which pays for all these wonderful exchange values, is agriculture.  I think this is the commodity which pays almost entirely for what we buy.  We sell little else.  The object of our tariffs should <Col N="113" /> be to try to secure for our commodities &mdash;if possible, by local consumption, which is the best means by which we can arrive at it&mdash;that we only select for tariffs such subjects as will utilise our raw materials.  We have vast supplies of raw materials.</P>
    <P>I believe the Government are giving careful consideration to all these matters. Trained economists, to my mind, are not of great advantage in this country of ours at the moment.  I will not profess to be a trained economist, but since I was twelve years I have studied economics and have taken many prizes in economic subjects.  I think the system that applies to England and other countries is not a system that would be inherently useful in this country.</P>
    <P>The two tariffs imposed in this Bill are tariffs on rosary beads and margarine. I will not deal with the subject in a light manner.  I agree with Senator O'Farrell that they are of small value and little worth.  I would like to point to the difficulty of collection of the tariffs.  A number of people may possibly be involved in the collection of the duty, and I wonder will the cost of the collection of this small tariff be justified.  I fear a number of small tariffs will involve a larger number of customs officers than the collection of the tariffs will pay for.  I am quite satisfied that this matter has been thought out, but I would like an assurance from the Minister that in this case the cost of collection is justified by the amount of the income derived.</P>
    <P>The Government's course of selective tariffs is the only course that the State could adopt.  I am quite sure that good results will come.  We must be patient.  I think in all these matters the idea is to secure that in imposing tariffs we should, in the first case, select industries for which the raw material is procurable in this country, and there are many.  It is not economic to start an industry on a small scale where you have to import the raw material.  That is an economic truth.  I do not think we lack in this country raw material and I hope consideration will be given to that matter.  I would like to feel in connection with the the tariffs that have been imposed, that consideration <Col N="114" /> has been given to the effect on local raw material.</P>
    <P>As regards the question of boots, I would be glad to know how far the tariff has furthered the purchase of Irish hides.  I have been told, but I may be wrong, that the number of Irish hides used in the production of Irish industries is very small indeed.  Irish hides are of great value and I am told that they are too good to be put into the manufacture of Irish boots.  I hope I am wrong and that I will be contradicted. I hope, in the imposition of tariffs, first consideration will be given to industries the raw material for which is available.  Being available, a larger amount of labour will be given and the resultant effects will be greater.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. BARRINGTON Mr. BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the Minister whether any arrangements are in contemplation for the protection of the consumer against the imposition of these tariffs.  In the discussion in the Dáil it was stated that arrangements had been made for the protection of the wholesaler, and the Irish producers of margarine had agreed to supply the wholesaler without increasing the price.  Are there any arrangements in contemplation for the protection of the consumer?  I had an instance the other day&mdash;I do not know if the tariff is actually in force&mdash; when an old lady who lives in my neighbourhood and is given occasional employment at my place poured out the vials of her wrath upon me because she had been charged 3d. extra for margarine.  If unscrupulous retailers are not in some way prevented from charging to the poor the imposition that is authorised by this Oireachtas, I am very much afraid the consumer will be the real sufferer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephOConnor" hpid="Mr. O'CONNOR Mr. O'CONNOR">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNOR</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to this question of tariffs I must say that it is one in which I, and indeed the whole country, are much interested.  I notice that the Cathaoirleach has allowed the debate to digress from the issue now before the House in regard to rosary beads and margarine into other channels. As far as rosary beads are concerned, I rather deprecate that an emblem of our Catholic religion should be so much thrashed out here in the <Col N="115" /> matter of import duties.  It is rather a small matter to have brought into this prominence in the discussion in connection with tariffs.  The question of margarine has been already more or less ably dealt with, and I observed that one Senator has made mention of the length of time that has elapsed since he formed an opinion on that matter. My own opinion on tariffs was formed over forty years ago.  Over forty years ago I formed my opinion as between tariffs and free trade&mdash;which was the best for the country, and which would be the best to follow.  I formed that opinion in favour of protection, and I am still a determined protectionist, and one of the reasons was looking at the five, six or seven mills in my native district of Roscrea which are now idle but which I know were hives of industry seventy years ago. At that time all the flour needed in the district, for many miles around, was produced in these mills, and as a result we had the by-products for feeding cattle and sheep sold there at reasonable prices.  The first blow to the working of these mills came when the roller system was adopted in the American flour mills.  As a result, five of these mills in Roscrea are now idle.  There is not one man employed in the five.  Of the remainder, one is run by the Monastery at Mount Saint Joseph's, because they have free labour.  As a result of what I saw in these mills in Roscrea I became a protectionist, and I am still a protectionist.  I hold that protection is required for more than flour&mdash;in fact, I do not wish to discriminate in any particular article that could be manufactured in Ireland.  The view I hold, and the view I have always held, is that if I had the making of the laws I would put tariffs on all manufactured articles coming into Ireland.  I would have no such thing as imported articles coming into the country, and I would have every manufactured article coming into the country taxed.  There should be no such thing as making fish of one and flesh of another.  I am an out-and-out protectionist in regard to everything coming into the country. Tanned hides and all things like that coming into the country should be <Col N="116" /> taxed.  I would allow none of those in free.</P>
      <P>Ireland is an agricultural country. The protection that is now being given in the matter of selected tariffs does not go as far as I would wish it to go. Perhaps there are experts that know more about these matters than I do. I do not claim any distinctive knowledge on this question, but I tell you candidly I would run the risk of making no mistake about them and so I would protect them all.  I would allow nothing to pass into this country at the expense of the people of the country who want work.  There are many in this country who know that this question of tariffs and free trade was always in England's mind in the far-off days when she discriminated against Ireland's products and industries. England has herself been a manufacturing country and was always in a different position from Ireland. Speaking from the farmers' point of view, I say that, in my opinion, it would benefit the farmers if tariffs were put on every imported article, for by helping our industries here we would be giving the farmer a market at his own door.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NugentEverardBart" hpid="Sir NUGENT EVERARD Sir NUGENT EVERARD">
      <NameTxt>Sir NUGENT EVERARD</NameTxt>
      <P>Although not such an out-and-out protectionist as the Senator who has just spoken, I must say that I was amazed Senator Sir John Keane should have at this time tried to convert the members of the Seanad to his views.  I suppose that was the object of his speech&mdash;to convert the Senate to his point of view. That view is that any form of protection or any tariffs are injurious to the country.  I suppose Senator Sir John Keane does read the history of mankind in other countries, and I think that before he holds us up as a horrible example to the world for having adopted such a mild form of selected tariffs as we have adopted, he should be able to show us some examples of a country which we ought to follow in the matter of free trade.  He should have shown us the experiment of some country carrying out free trade and, as the result of that experiment, prosperous above all other countries.  He did mention Australia as yearning for free trade.  If you take the different Colonies <Col N="117" /> comprising that Federation you will learn the position with regard to protection there.  I have a distinct recollection of reading a debate in the other House where the States of Victoria and New South Wales were mentioned as examples respectively of free trade and protection.  I remember reading there how free trade failed and how protection succeeded, and how the free trade country eventually adopted protection.  In the protected country not only was food cheaper but everything else was cheaper.  Labour was abundant and emigrants flowed in: whereas in the country that adopted free trade the emigrants were flowing out, food was dear, and it was the same with other things.  As a result it was practically unanimously decided that the free trade country would adopt the same form of protection as was followed by the sister State.</P>
      <P>Everybody knows, and it is not necessary to tell us, that the United States of America has a diversified climate and fertile soil, and that great country has facilities in the way of raw material that are unequalled on God's earth.  But why was it necessary then for that great country as a whole to put up a tariff wall that even a little country like ours cannot jump over? It seems small-minded on her part, but I presume that Sir John Keane, who is nothing that is not really sound in economics from the academic point of view, had some reason for not mentioning England as the greatest traitor to the cause of free trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now we are talking here of such matters as rosary beads.  It is a little matter, but the fact that a tariff has been placed on rosary beads is an indication of the want of a patriotic spirit on the part of the people who would rather buy German rosary beads than beads made in their own country and made of materials produced in their own country.  One may think that this matter of rosary beads is so small that it is ridiculous, but it is well to remember that in England there is an industry that is somewhat similar to rosary beads, but it is a very big industry.  I refer to the manufacture of buttons. Here you will find a great apostasy on the part of England from the doctrine of Cobden and the other free traders. <Col N="118" /> At the present moment the Board of Trade are actually considering the imposition of a tariff on buttons.  I wish in this matter of tariffs that Senator Sir John Keane had given us an example of a country that we all could follow.  Of course some Irish people think that this is the best of all possible worlds, but we will have to go outside this world to find any place such as Senator Sir John Keane thinks has adopted an ideal policy.</P>
    <P>There is one point that I notice is notoriously absent from the speeches and arguments of free trade economists, and that is the question of employment. Now, may I ask if the arguments and theories of free traders were carried out to the Nth power or the Nth extreme, what sort of possible occupation could there be found for the labour that is found superabundant in this country? We know very well that in that event there would be only one outlet for labour and that is through the Irish ports in emigrant ships.  Why should that be?  If we had industries in the country we should still be able to retain the population within the four shores of Ireland at any rate and not have to send them out to these protectionist countries.  I suppose as they are protectionist I should not mention them.  To help by tariffs to build up industries is a more patriotic idea than the adoption of a principle of economic policy&mdash;the teachings of free trade professors who have been all their lives teaching these theories and doctrines without being able to persuade any of the countries of the world to adopt them.  I do not know whether I would call them doctrines or policies, but I do say this that their rules have been, in every country in the world, more honoured in the breach than in the observance.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>There seems to be some confusion in the minds of Senators Sir John Keane and Sir Nugent Everard with regard to the reason America put up a tariff wall.  I think it would be just as well it should be understood now that America put up a tariff wall because the people of that country believed in giving a decent standard of livelihood to their <Col N="119" /> workers.  The tariff wall was put up in order to prevent the employers from exploiting cheap labour.  That is the reason.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'HANLON Mr. O'HANLON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HANLON</NameTxt>
      <P>Apparently there is room for a full dress debate on this subject under another item on the agenda to-day and when that debate comes along many of us will have much to say.  I hope really that we will not be treated to the line of reasoning which Senator O'Connor put forward this evening.  That is a line of reasoning of a number of protectionists who go on the assumption that all we have got to do in order to re-start our mills, to find work for the unemployed, and convert this country into a land flowing with milk and honey is to put up a tariff wall.  That is a strange assumption. We would have to have a much closer line of reasoning before many of us would be converted to the view-point of the protectionists and converted to the view-point that protection is going to afford a panacea for all our ills, and that when we have protection we are going to have the millennium.  Senator Farren has just mentioned why a tariff wall was raised up in America&mdash;in order to secure for the workers in America better labour conditions.  Does the tariff do that?  Senator Sir Nugent Everard mentioned Australia as an example of protection.  What is the position there in one of the most highly protected countries in the world?  The position is that the land is going out of cultivation in a country with illimitable resources, possibly the greatest resources of any land on God's earth. The people are crowding into the cities and the country is being run largely on borrowed money.  The National and State debts are increasing.  The National and State debts are at the present time in this highly protected country £955,000,000.  What do we find there in relation to what Senator Farren says? We found there the other day one thousand unemployed in the capital city storming the Treasury in a country where a tariff is the real thing and which is most highly protected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Sir Nugent Everard should study the conditions in Australia.  A <Col N="120" /> lot could be said about America.  A great deal could be said on this subject, and I hope we will have an opportunity later of going into a more detailed discussion of it.  With regard to margarine, there was one thing that struck me as rather extraordinary about the whole case.  It was this: that the people who made a case for a tariff on margarine admitted that they send margarine into foreign countries and have secured a portion of the trade in them.  That means that they are able to produce margarine here at a certain price, that they are able, after paying the transport charges on the margarine to these countries, to enter into competition with the foreigner on his own ground and secure a portion of his market, How is it that these people who are able to do all that, who are able to meet the foreigner in his own market, are not able, by a little reduction in the costs of production here, and by the introduction of more efficient methods, to capture the home market?  I cannot understand why the Government or the Dáil should ever have agreed to the principle that a tariff should be given to people who put forward such a case. It seems to me to be a wholly illogical case.  The putting on of a tariff on such an article inevitably leads to an increase in the cost of living for the very poorest of our people, who can least afford it.  That is the position as I see it, and I hope the Seanad will be given another day to go fully into this matter.  Some Senator said that Senator Sir John Keane was trying to convert this House to his views about free trade.  I am quite sure the Senator knows well that he was not trying to convert some of us who hold equally strong views with him on this matter.  When the opportunity is given on another day we hope to put forward our views.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBagwell" hpid="Mr. BAGWELL Mr. BAGWELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BAGWELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot help making a short contribution to this debate. I do not propose to speak at any great length, nor do I hope to say anything on this question that I have not said already.  We have heard a great deal as to what the economic characteristic of this country might be if we followed <Col N="121" /> the example of this, that or the other country.  That is all a matter of hypothesis. The fact is, that the industry in this country which gives employment and a livelihood to an enormously greater number of people than all the other industries put together is agriculture. The mutton, beef, eggs, chickens, butter and all the other things that we produce are, for the most part, sent to England and sold there.  You cannot protect an industry where your market is away from you.  For that reason it seems to me that Ireland, of all countries, should be a free trade country for the reason that you cannot protect your principal industry.  Such industries as you can protect in the home market will only have the effect of raising the cost of living and putting a mill-stone around the necks of our agriculturists.  Why should we do that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDillon" hpid="Mr. DILLON Mr. DILLON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DILLON</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of what my friend, Senator O'Connor, has stated, that he is a full-blooded protectionist, I must, sitting on the same side of the House as he, rise to say that I hold very much the opposite point of view.  I think it is well I should refer to some practical matters that affect us agriculturists.  One fact brought home to us is this: that agriculturists in all highly protected States constitute the poorest class in those States.  Take any of the highly protected countries that have been referred to, such as America and Australia.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The agriculturists in them constitute the poorest class.  So much is that a fact that agriculturists in these countries are flying to the cities.  When it is said that protection may result in more employment being given at home, I can cite facts to show that such is not the case.  The number of unemployed in America, a highly protected country, average from one and three-quarter millions to five millions.  If protection, as its supporters contend, meant more employment at home, we would not have that fact staring us in the face. In an agricultural country like ours we have to depend largely upon our exports. Practically every citizen in this country, directly or indirectly, has to depend on agriculture for a living.  If we have to sell practically all that we produce in another market, what is our <Col N="122" /> position going to be if we become a protected country?  It may be an academic thing to say, but I believe if we reduce our imports that our exports will be correspondingly reduced in value.  In the last couple of years there has been a reduction in our export trade, both as regards its volume and value.  It is a matter for our economists to consider whether the items on which tariffs have been placed during the past few years have not had some influence on this admitted reduction in our export trade.  I just got up to say these few words because of the fact that my friend, Senator O'Connor, had made the statement that he was a full-blooded protectionist.  I am opposed to that policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>The two tariffs that are dealt with in this Bill are comparatively unimportant. They are proposed because the Tariff Commission presented reports. In the case of one of the articles dealt with, rosary beads, if immediate action had not been taken it would not have been any use to impose a tariff at all because such a degree of forestalling would have taken place that there would have been no possible increase of employment.  It was necessary to act on the reports at once if we were going to act at all.  The collection of such taxes as will have to be collected on these articles will impose practically no increase in the cost of the customs service.  They are minor matters, and we have customs' officers at all the ports and at points on the road where goods are imported.  They will be able to deal with this matter with very little difficulty.  It is not anticipated that any actual increase in staff will be required.  I do not think that the difficulties Senator O'Farrell referred to are incapable of being overcome. I do not think the people who bring home rosary beads may be expected to tell lies, or that they will go to the same trouble to smuggle as people bringing home other classes of contraband. In any case, if the difficulty arises I think it can be met.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the question of the quality and price of margarine, it is quite easy to deal with price.  It is more difficult to deal with quality.  The only thing that is possible there is, in <Col N="123" /> case there are any complaints, to investigate those complaints thoroughly and occasionally to have tests as regards quality carried out.  Then if it is found that the undertakings that are given are not being kept the Government will have every justification for going to the Dáil and proposing that the tariff be abandoned.  It would be much more difficult to do that if the promises were not there, and it would be impossible to convict the firm or firms concerned of any misbehaviour, so to speak.  I do not think I need discuss the general question at great length, but it is a fact, and all Senators, I am sure, will acknowledge that in certain cases, by means of tariffs, you can have increased employment at no additional cost to the consumer.</P>
    <P>The tariff on cigarettes which we took over, as it were, automatically, when we took over the British system of taxes in the beginning of 1923, has caused the erection of a number of factories and has given a considerable amount of employment without involving any increased cost to the consumer. So far as the confectionery tariff is concerned, the position has been almost the same.  There are, perhaps, one or two grades of sweets in which exactly as good quality as the imported sweets cannot be obtained, but in general you have, without any cost to the consumer, and without any increase in the cost of living, a great deal of employment provided.  I admit that the general effect of tariffs, taken all round must be to increase the cost of living.  I have said that in certain cases there would be no increase in cost, but in certain cases there might also be an actual cheapening of the real price of the article.  These are exceptional cases than otherwise, but in general it may be accepted that some increase in cost to the consumer may result.</P>
    <P>We cannot be content to go on as we are going on and not look ahead.  I think it is not desirable to have a country depending entirely on agriculture if that can be avoided.  I think it is desirable that we should not have all our eggs in the one basket, as it is said, and if there is a very bad period in agriculture the country should have me chance of making that up in other <Col N="124" /> directions.  Then there is the whole question of the sparsity of population. The great sparsity of population here involves a heavy burden on the country.  It is this sparsity of population that makes our Post Office a losing proposition, although the postage here is twopence while the postage in England is only three-halfpence.  If you had an increased population our railways would find it easier to carry on than they do at present, and would be able to give a better and a cheaper service to the country.  In many respects government is dearer on the individual when the population is sparse.  It is more difficult to provide good schools and give educational facilities.  Every advantage of that sort is more difficult and costly to provide when you have a sparse population.  The view that we hold, without taking any sort of what might be called an exaggerated view of the national future, is, that it is worth while to make some small sacrifices in the present for the sake of getting a more diversified economic life and of being able to retain greater numbers of our people at home with a view of being able to have an increased population. We feel, however, that we must go carefully about it, because it is a fact that so far as tariffs throw a burden on the consumer, they throw a burden on agriculture, which is our main producer, and is in an ill condition to bear an increased burden.  It is for that reason that we are trying to have as good an investigation of every proposal for a tariff as we can have before any steps are taken to put it into effect.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. JAMESON Mr. JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to know from the Minister if he is able to give us any figures as to the increase in the employment of labour that is likely as a result of these tariffs here. There is no doubt whatever that as regards margarine it is one of the foods of the poor, and it is one of the last things that I would have expected anybody to try to protect.  The Government, I imagine, must think that extra employment will be given as a result of these tariffs.  Otherwise I am sure they would not feel justified, in the eyes of any ordinary economist, in proposing to impose such taxes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>There are some estimates <Col N="125" /> given in the report of the Tariff Commission with regard to both industries. I cannot at the moment put my hand on the paragraph in the report dealing with this, but I think the figures are 80 or 90 in each case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. JAMESON Mr. JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is to say employment to about 170 more people?</P>
      <P>Question: &ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MESSAGES FROM THE DAIL. -" RHead="THE OIREACHTAS LIBRARY">
    <Title>MESSAGES FROM THE DAIL. - THE OIREACHTAS LIBRARY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it the Seanad will agree with the following Message which has been received from the Dáil:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Go mbunuítear Có-Choiste a bheidh có-dhéanta de thriúr ball den Dáil agus de thriúr ball den tSeanad chun congnamh agus comhairle do thabhairt don Cheann Comhairle agus don Chathaoirleach i dtreora agus i stiúra Leabharlann an Oireachtais.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That a Joint Committee consisting of three members of the Dáil and three members of the Seanad be set up to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Library.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MESSAGES FROM THE DAIL. -" RHead="THE OIREACHTAS RESTAURANT">
    <Title>MESSAGES FROM THE DAIL. - THE OIREACHTAS RESTAURANT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it the House will also agree with the following Message received from the Dáil:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Go mbunuítear Có-Choiste a bheidh có-dhéanta de chúigear ball den Dáil agus de chúigear ball den tSeanad chun congnamh agus comhairle do thabhairt don Cheann Comhairle agus don Chathaoirleach i dtreora agus i stiúra Seomra Bidh an Oireachtais.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That a Joint Committee consisting of five members of the Dáil and five members of the Seanad be set up to assist and advise the Ceann Comhairle and the Cathaoirleach in the direction and control of the Oireachtas Restaurant.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MESSAGES FROM THE DAIL. - INLAND TRANSPORT&mdash;QUESTION" RHead="OF REGULATION AND CO-ORDINATION">
    <Title>MESSAGES FROM THE DAIL. - INLAND TRANSPORT&mdash;QUESTION OF REGULATION AND CO-ORDINATION.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="126" />
    </P>
    <P>Debate resumed on Motion by Senator O'Farrell.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That the Seanad is of opinion that the question of the regulation and co-ordination of all branches of inland transport is urgent and demands the earliest consideration by the Executive Council.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>As the President is here I should like to let him know what exactly the position is with regard to this motion.  The motion, as originally moved by Senator O'Farrell, contained the suggestion that the remedy for the situation would be the setting up of an independent Ministry or separate department for the purpose of dealing with this matter of transport.  In the course of the discussion, while there seemed to be very general consensus of opinion that the rest of the motion was desirable there was some question and controversy as to the remedy proposed.  Another Senator proposed that the matter should be entrusted to a commission, another Senator suggested legislation, and I see that yet another Senator has given notice of an amendment that the subject should be referred to a Committee of both Houses.  I am only mentioning these matters so that the President may know that the motion was subsequently amended so as to leave out of it any suggested remedy, the idea being that it might be of advantage to hear what the policy of the Government was in regard to the matter, and that such policy as outlined by them might be such as to commend itself to this House.  Consequently if it suits the President the most convenient thing would be that he, having heard the views of the House, might now be heard in return, and then it would be open to any Senator afterwards to continue the discussion and move any amendment he thinks fit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that what I would be expected to deal with would be the motion, and not the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The principle of the motion was generally accepted <Col N="127" /> by the House, that is to say, that the matter required urgent consideration. What was not decided was the particular remedy or the method of bringing about the reform required.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not concern myself at all with the amendment, which appears to me to be slightly in conflict with the motion.  The amendment suggests a Committee, on which both Houses of the Oireachtas should be represented with powers to take evidence, whereas the motion says that the question is urgent and demands the earliest consideration by the Executive Council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment on the paper was not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I much regret that the Minister for Industry and Commerce is not able to be present this evening, nor will he be able to be present for a little while to come.  With a matter of this kind he is much more closely in touch than I am, and the Senate must, therefore, have some little patience with me while I endeavour to deal with it.  I observed that Senator O'Farrell referred to the importation, or possible importation, of quite a number of buses.  He mentioned the possibility of forty being introduced in a short time, and, I inferred from his remarks, although it is not quite clear, that in respect of that he had some misgivings as to whether or not the Government had done all that was possible with a view to having the application of the coach builders for a tariff dealt with.</P>
      <P>The application came to the Ministry on 31st January, and it was then referred to the Tariff Commission.  The Secretary to the Tariff Commission informed the applicants that a fee of £100 would be required.  That fee, I think, was paid four months later. Somewhere about October the applicants were requested to provide a concise statement setting out the scope of the application.  As far as a tariff is concerned, or anything in regard to the importation of buses, I assume that the Senator is satisfied&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'FARRELL Mr. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of fact I was not thinking of the tariff at <Col N="128" /> all.  I gave that as an instance of the feverish haste&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Of the accumulation of vested interests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'FARRELL Mr. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>And the feverish haste in which the orders were given. I was not thinking of a tariff at the time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as the motion is concerned it deals with practically two questions, viz., the regulation and co-ordination of inland transport. As far as regulation is concerned the railways and canals are regulated by the Railways and Canals Act.  Road regulation is now being considered by the Inter-Departmental Traffic Committee and I presume that it will be admitted that investigation by such a Committee is essential in order to get the information required.  Now the Railways (Road Motor Service) Act provides a substantial measure of co-ordination between railways and roads. I understand that working agreements have provided a substantial measure of co-ordination between the canals and the railways, so that the two chief matters mentioned in the resolution have been attended to in one case and in the other case are in the course of receiving attention.</P>
      <P>There is also very close contact between the Ministries of the various Departments having control of the different activities of traffic, namely, the Ministry of Industry and Commerce, the Ministry of Local Government, the Ministry of Finance and, then, there is the Executive Council, for considering any difference or settling any points which might arise and call for settlement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So far as the resolution is concerned, the Government would have no objection whatever to its being passed, having regard to what I have said.  But, in the first place, the question of regulation and co-ordination, in the one case has been attended to, and in the second case is in the course of receiving attention. It may be that there are some misapprehensions regarding what is called co-ordination.  I do not know whether it was intended by Senator O'Farrell that there should be an allocation of traffic in this matter of co-ordination. <Col N="129" /> This term has been largely used in the newspapers.  I do not know that anybody has ever examined it for the purpose of presenting to the public what is actually meant.  But I presume there is some dissatisfaction in the minds of people that the bus traffic, as it is called, is not regulated in as strict a manner as the railway routes.  But it must be remembered that when regulating anything you must have something to regulate, and the bus traffic has not, even at the moment, assumed very gigantic proportions.  There are cases in which there are abuses, such as the speeding of those huge omnibuses.  I gathered, from the statement made by Senator O'Farrell, that that was one of the matters with which he was concerned. It is a matter which does not exactly fall within the purview of the Ministry for Industry and Commerce: it is a matter largely dealt with by the Ministry for Justice, and it is just one of those items in connection with the whole economy of omnibus traffic that is, at present, being examined.  As I have said, quite a number of items of information in connection with this matter require elucidation, and the purpose of the Inter-Departmental Committee will, I believe, provide data upon which the various Ministries concerned will ultimately base any recommendations they may make to the Executive Council.</P>
    <P>Legislation to deal with the allocation of traffic is not a matter on which I think I could promise any early introduction of a Bill.  I do not think, at the moment, it is likely that any such Bill will be introduced.  Meanwhile, as I have said, the Railways Act, the Road (Motor Services) Act and the Departmental Committee have provided and are providing for the ascertainment of the necessary information that will enable the various Ministries concerned to make whatever recommendations they consider advisable, and if necessary to introduce legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there was general agreement that there was necessity for consideration being given to this problem which has arisen.  It is quite true, as the President said, that the introduction of the bus service and the motor service is of recent growth, and that we have hardly reached the <Col N="130" /> fullness of the problem, if I might say so.  But undoubtedly there is a problem that needs attending to.  It is the opinion of people familiar with these things that it should be attended to immediately, and that there should not be four or five Ministries dealing with this matter.  For instance, it appears to me, it is a ridiculous thing that the Ministry for Justice should be responsible for the inspection of motor buses. Trade unions have been agitating for close on 30 years that there should be proper inspection of every vehicle licensed to carry passengers.  There is not proper inspection given of a large number of vehicles plying for hire in the streets of the cities and towns of the country to-day.  There is not enough of inspection now.  If there is a serious accident the cry will go up when it is too late: &ldquo;Why was there not proper regulations for inspection?&rdquo; I put it to Senators is any ordinary member of the Civic Guards a fit and proper person to inspect buses plying for hire, as to their suitability and as to their being in a proper condition for the purpose of carrying the large number of passengers that they do to-day. As a matter of fact, a large number of these buses have only one entrance, and that is by the front.  Everyone knows when a fire takes place in one of those buses it is generally in front that it breaks out, and if such a fire occurred I should be sorry for the people inside.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I say that the Civic Guards are not the proper people to inspect these buses and that the buses are not receiving proper inspection; that a proper emergency door is not provided, that the windows are not tested and that these buses are not in a proper condition for travelling long journeys from Dublin to Cork or Belfast or Limerick.  I say there should be a proper system of inspection such as that provided by the Board of Trade officers, which could be properly carried out.  As I understand it the railways are subject to Board of Trade inspection and certain regulations are laid down and must be complied with before passenger trains are allowed to leave the platform.  It is quite a common thing to see every day from any railway platform men coming along with hammers tapping the wheels of the train.  Is there any such examination <Col N="131" /> in the case of buses plying for hire in Dublin and district?  I say that there ought to be, and I go further: I say that these vehicles should be inspected by competent mechanics who understand their business, and not by the Civic Guard.  When this motion was before the House last week it was agreed that the question of the setting up of a separate Ministry should not be proceeded with.  In re-forming the Government offices after the last general election the Department of Posts and Telegraphs was put in charge of a Parliamentary Secretary.  I would be perfectly satisfied if all these traffic problems were grouped together and put into that Department, under the responsibility of one man, because I think it is not right that five or six different Departments should deal with different aspects of the problem.</P>
    <P>The question of national waste was mentioned last week, by Senator Bagwell, I think.  I agree that it is national waste to have numbers of people competing for the same traffic on the same routes.  I was astonished when I read in the newspapers a few weeks ago that a railway company was proposing to run a bus service on a road parallel to their own system, from Bray to Wexford. If that is not national waste I do not know what is.  No doubt the Railways Company would answer by saying that the competition is forcing them to do that, but I think that is the whole problem that ought to be considered. The question of national waste also arises in the case of that railway with a splendid works at Inchicore, with men capable and competent to make any class of vehicle, whether it be an engine, a railway carriage, or an omnibus, and yet this same company, with its employees working four days a week, are sending to England for forty buses.  It appears to me to be national waste&mdash;forty buses being ordered by a railway company which owns a magnificent works, with skilled artisans who are only working four days a week, and with machinery and everything necessary, at least for the building of bodies; I will not refer to the chassis, as I am not competent to deal with that, but I do say that there are plenty of men in the employment of <Col N="132" /> that company in Dublin quite as competent as anybody else to build bodies, and I think it is pure national waste to send away an order for forty bodies.</P>
    <P>Another matter to which I would like to refer is the question of somebody with the duty of seeing that people who are plying for hire with all these different types of vehicles should be responsible for third-party insurance. I think it is an absolute scandal that people should be plying for hire with buses all over the country and risking the lives of their passengers every day in the week&mdash;when there is no proper supervision on these buses&mdash; and that if anything happens to a breadwinner that he should become maimed for life when coming home from his work, his wife and children will have to suffer because of the neglect of somebody in some department.  I think it is the duty of the State to see that everyone plying for hire, more particularly the owners of these high-powered vehicles, should be compelled by law, before licences are issued to them, to take out third-party insurance.  I think it is the duty of some department to see to that, and that is why I say it is wrong for five different departments to be responsible for little bits of this problem; it is a job that ought to be handled by one department.  I do not care what Minister gets it, but I say, it is of sufficient importance, and the problem is growing to sufficient dimensions to warrant some Minister being made responsible for every aspect of it.</P>
    <P>The President has said that the matter was considered as far as railways and canals were concerned, but I think that the motion was not intended to deal so much with railways and canals as with the growing problem of road traffic.  It is growing and will grow.  I am not opposed to bus traffic; I rather welcome it, because I believe it has been a great boon to people in rural areas.  It is a great boon to people who had to walk five or six miles to a railway station to get into Dublin, even when they live only ten miles from Dublin.</P>
    <P>People in Swords had to walk three or four miles to Malahide station, wait for a train, and spend the whole day in order to do half an hour's business in Dublin.  It is a great thing for these <Col N="133" /> people, and for people in the rural areas, whose doors are now passed by buses, who had many miles to go to railway stations.  In some cases people had no railway stations near them at all.  Take Graiguenamanagh, a fine thriving business town, with a good population but no railway service.  The nearest railway is, I suppose, five or six miles from it.  So that the bus has been a great blessing and boon to people in rural areas.  I am not opposed to it.  I want to see it developed, and if it is being developed I want proper protection for the public, and I want one Minister to deal with and look after the interests of the public.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. BARRINGTON Mr. BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the amendment of which I have given notice:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;To add at the end of the motion the words &lsquo;with a view to the appointment of a Committee upon which both Houses of the Oireachtas shall be represented, with power to take evidence: the Committee to submit proposals as to the best means of dealing with the question.&rsquo;&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be better to speak upon the motion and suggest this in the course of your speech?  I think the general view of the House was that they ought to content themselves as far as possible in getting an affirmance of the principle that this matter was urgent and called for immediate consideration.  They were against suggesting how it was to be met, because opinion would certainly differ upon that, as you have seen already.  Would it not be sufficient for your purpose to discuss the merits of the motion and then suggest, as Senator Farren has done, that the best way of dealing with it would be to set up a Committee?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. BARRINGTON Mr. BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is exactly what I would like to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That would avoid having a vote on it.  If I put your amendment the House would have to vote on it, whereas if you simply discussed the matter and bring this up as your own recommendation you will gain all that you want to get.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. BARRINGTON Mr. BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think in all <Col N="134" /> probability that when the House has heard what I have to say on the matter it will agree that it is a very desirable thing, because I feel that there is a vast amount of information that it is necessary and desirable to obtain.  I entirely object to the principle, which I think the resolution would contain if it were to pass, as it now stands on the Order Paper, the principle that we are all objecting to, of putting everything on to the Government.  In the past there has been far too much readiness in this country to put everything on to the Government, and I think the resolution as it stands rather bears out that idea.  All Governments have their limitations, and the chief limitation of our Government is time.  The Government consists of a number of more or less overworked Ministers, and I feel we cannot shelve the responsibilities we as well as they have to the country by putting over on their shoulders the solution of this very complicated question. I feel that a great deal more information is needed for its proper solution, and for the protection of the country ratepayers whose condition, bad enough as things are, is likely to be made much worse if the present system, or want of system, is allowed to continue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There has been a very great departure from the principle which was always acted upon in the past when it was sought to get out of the public rates a subvention to any line of traffic. It will be, probably, news to most Senators that some of our main lines were built by subventions from the rates.  Take the Midland Great Western Railway.  It was extended into Galway by a subvention from the rates.  Many of our other lines were built up in the same way, but, under the system, or, rather, want of system which has grown up in connection with the buses the rates are called upon to pay a subvention to these services, many of which are wholly unnecessary, without any notice whatsoever being given to the ratepayers. In the past, if the rates were to contribute to any service of the kind notices had to be given in the first place to the public at large; notices had to be published; appearances had to be made at what were known as road sessions, <Col N="135" /> and afterwards at the Board of Guardians interested.  Then the question went to the Grand Juries which, in those days, were very practical bodies. Now some English manufacturer very often has an agent over here, is desirous of finding employment for buses, and between them they hatch out a scheme to run buses from some town, we will say, in the west of Ireland to Dublin.  They pay a licence for a bus and by negotiation with the various officials or Departments they get the right to run that bus.  The first notice very frequently that the ratepayers have of the service is when they see the vehicle on the roads.</P>
    <P>There can be no doubt as to the damage buses do to the roads.  If any Senator has any doubt as to the mischief they do, I would ask him to take his stand on one of those beautifully-finished roads with a tarred surface.  It is fairly slippery after a shower of rain and, on a steep hill, I have seen these vehicles attempting to get up and they literally flay the surface off the road. The roads were originally made at the expense of the ratepayers.  They have been re-surfaced by the Road Fund out of the taxes paid by the motor vehicles.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir JOHN KEANE Sir JOHN KEANE">
      <NameTxt>Sir JOHN KEANE</NameTxt>
      <P>Including the buses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. BARRINGTON Mr. BARRINGTON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BARRINGTON</NameTxt>
      <P>Including the buses.  As soon as the roads have been finished and have a fine surface, they are handed over to the ratepayers to maintain.  These roads have to be maintained out of the already overburdened rates.  The ratepayers will not get a loan for the purpose.  They will not get any further grant, so that it is out of taxation these roads must be kept in order.  That means a very heavy contribution. It is difficult to know what the upkeep will amount to.  These are questions that deserve a lot of consideration and inquiry before a proper solution can be arrived at, and the President has stated this information is being collected at the present time by an Inter-Departmental Committee. To come back to the question of the contributions to the railways, many of them were beneficial, many of them were paid back in full with interest. It does not seem to me to be a <Col N="136" /> reasonable thing that the ratepayers should be now asked to supply a permanent way for buses, and then maintain it and get no contribution from the profits of these buses.  It is obvious that there must be profits.  If not there would not be so many people competing. That is another question that requires very careful consideration.  I do not think it is outside the bounds of possibility that some of the officials&mdash; and the Government have many very capable officials&mdash;would be able to make a reasonable calculation as to the damage that these vehicles do to the roads, and find out what would be a reasonable contribution that they should make out of their profits towards the repairs which enable them to earn these profits.</P>
      <P>On these grounds I ask Senator O'Farrell to accept the amendment. I think it will take some little time to ascertain the information, but it is necessary to obtain it in the interests of the ratepayers, who are very hard pressed, and who find it almost impossible to fulfil their obligations.  I say that there are many facts to be ascertained, and that useful suggestions could be made as to the conditions under which persons should be permitted to use the roads on such a large scale for private profit, without contributing any portion of the profits to the ratepayers supplying the means of earning them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDuffy" hpid="Mr. DUFFY Mr. DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise to support the motion, not because I am opposed to the bus services, but because I believe the proper development of the bus traffic is essential for the development of the rural areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Are you supporting Senator Barrington's suggestion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDuffy" hpid="Mr. DUFFY Mr. DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>No, the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>If Senator Barrington wants to move his amendment it must be seconded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OsmondGrattanEsmonde" hpid="Sir THOMAS ESMONDE Sir THOMAS ESMONDE">
      <NameTxt>Sir THOMAS ESMONDE</NameTxt>
      <P>I second amendment.  I have certain views on this question generally that I feel inclined to express.  As far as I could follow the discussion, the Seanad generally was of opinion that this question should be inquired into without delay. <Col N="137" /> With that view I cordially agree, and I am very glad to hear from the President that an Inter-Departmental Committee is examining into it.  No doubt, eventually it may be found advisable to amend the law or to bring in new regulations. That will be a matter for the Executive, and we can discuss that question fully when it arises.  This is really a very much bigger question than has become apparent during the course of the debate.  Many sections of the public in this country are vitally concerned with a solution of the present difficulty, and they may be vitally concerned in its future development. It appears to me that one section of the community has not yet been sufficiently represented.  I read the discussion that took place in the Seanad and the various contributions that appeared in the newspapers, and it does not seem to me that the section that is really most concerned in a proper solution of the difficulty, namely, the taxpayer&mdash;either the national or the local taxpayer&mdash;has been properly represented or has so far made itself vocal.  The taxpayer, national or local, it appears to me must bear the greater part of the weight of whatever solution is arrived at eventually, and I hope that as he is so vitally concerned, he will not be forgotten in whatever inquiries that take place.  Then you have the railway shareholders, who are vitally concerned in the preservation of what capital is left to them.  They are in the main the greatest developers of this country, and that fact should be borne in mind in whatever solution is eventually arrived at.  Then there is an important section of the community &mdash;the railwaymen&mdash;who are concerned with the preservation of their means of livelihood.  That is what they are up against, and we cannot blame them. Then you have the motorists, who contribute a very large amount of taxation towards the upkeep of the roads.  They have claims that ought to be considered. Finally you have the motor industry.  We live in the 20th century, and we know perfectly well that the development of this country to a very considerable extent will depend upon the development of that industry.  The motor industry as such has an undoubted claim for proper and full consideration. <Col N="138" /> All these categories of people, to my mind, have legitimate and proper claims for consideration in connection with the solution of this important question.</P>
      <P>There is, however, one matter upon which I am perfectly satisfied, and that is, that we cannot, in whatever solution we arrive at, put either the national or the local taxpayer to any further expenditure. One thing that I can never agree to is the establishment of a new Government Department, Commission, Board, or whatever you may like to call it, for the purpose of dealing with this matter.  We have ample machinery of government.  We have experts directing our Executive.  It is up to them to enforce whatever law is passed by the Oireachtas.  Senator Farren thought that the Minister for Justice, as the representative of the police, should not be entrusted with the application of the law.  The Minister for Justice, or the police, in other words, are responsible for the administration of motoring and traffic laws in every country.  Why should they not be fit and proper persons to administer the law here?  I think that that would be the cheapest and most practical way in the taxpayers' interests of putting into force whatever solution is arrived at.  After all, these are minor matters.  We have to bear in mind the taxpayer and the various people interested in transport. Their legitimate and proper claims ought to be met as far as possible.  I repeat that I will never consent to the establishment, at the ratepayers' expense, of a new Government Department to deal with our transport problem.  We are perfectly competent with our existing executive machinery to deal with the matter.  One thing really necessary is to have an inquiry made into the matter.  I hope the President will consider the various aspects from which the question may be viewed, and the interests of the various people concerned in a proper and fair solution of this difficulty.  If he does that, and if his inquiries result in legislation being proposed, I can assure him, so long as these points are borne in mind, that he will have my support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDuffy" hpid="Mr. DUFFY Mr. DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support the motion, not because I am <Col N="139" /> opposed to bus traffic, but because I believe that the proper development of bus traffic is essential to the welfare of the agricultural community.  The railways undoubtedly are beneficial in so far as they deal with large quantities of heavy traffic and even with large numbers of passengers going from one populous centre to another.  But there are large areas where there was no adequate transport service in the past.  I think everyone will agree that these areas are being opened up by the bus services.  A good deal has been said about the injustice of asking the ratepayers to make roads for the buses to come along and destroy them.  We ought to be perfectly clear on these matters before we come to any conclusion. I know something about roads, and in my opinion the ratepayers are not spending on the roads anything like the amount of money that they would be spending if there were no motors.  In 1913/14 the sum spent out of the rates on the roads was something like £670,000. For 1926-7 the expenditure only went up to £1,073,000, or, roughly, a little over 50 per cent. increase. This year the expenditure will be even lower than that.  I do not think any concern in this country can get work done to-day at 50 per cent. over pre-war rates.  Not alone have the ratepayers as good ordinary roads as they had in 1913-14, but they have the advantage of up-to-date and first-class roads which have been made out of the funds derived from motor taxation. Indeed the roads are much better than they were in 1913-14, and when the £2,000,000 which has been borrowed for the development and improvement of the main roads is spent, the roads will be improved out of all comparison with what they were in pre-war times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What sort of roads had we when motorists first began to use them?  I remember well that if, at that time, a timber merchant bought a few hundred tons of timber in a certain locality and started to convey it to the railway station, by the time he he had completed the cartage of the timber the roads would be in such a state that the county council had to prosecute him <Col N="140" /> for excessive damage to them.  If 20 or 30 hay carts with loads from 15 cwts. to a ton went along after each other, the roads would be cut in two.  You do not hear of anything like that now, and I hold that the duties coming from motorists and lorries are paying for the improvement and that the ratepayers and taxpayers are not paying.  This state has not spent £1 on the roads over and above what is paid from motor taxation with the exception of what they spent in the repairs of roads and bridges out of the 6d. rate.  There is a lot of exaggeration on this question about the enormous facilities motor bus owners have provided for them.  In justice to the ratepayers I hold there is no injustice whatsoever.  It may be found after investigation that bus owners could pay perhaps higher taxation than at the moment.  If, on investigation, that is so, then I say increase the taxation.  If it is found that they are able to run their buses and make enormous profits at low rates, if there is room for increased taxation, that can be remedied without doing great injustice to anyone else.</P>
    <P>I heard a good deal, from time to time, about the great injustice done to the railways by charging them rates. One would imagine that the railway concern was not interested in the upkeep of roads.  I ask any commonsense man what would the railways of this country do if there were no roads to finish the delivery of the stuff to its destination.  Are not the railway people as much concerned with the upkeep as any other people, and why would they not pay rates like any other commercial concern?  If they are not concerned with the upkeep of roads, I do not know who ought to be.  Every ton of stuff and every passenger have to proceed by road first to get to the railway, and surely no good case could be put up as to why the railway company should escape paying rates any more than any other concern.  I believe that regulation of this inland transport is essential, and I believe if it were properly regulated it would be found that the best interests of this country would be served by linking up the road service and the railway service by providing small lorries and small passenger <Col N="141" /> buses at the principal railway stations throughout the country which should deliver the goods and bring the passengers expeditiously to their homes.  Until that is done we will not have efficient and quick transport, and in an agricultural community such as ours, where the majority of the stuff we produce is more or less of a perishable nature, it is essential that we should have quick and efficient transport to get to the markets as quickly as possible.  Anyone charged with the regulating of this traffic would have to take into account how far the railways and the bus services of this country could be utilised to give that efficient service.</P>
    <P>One other reason for advocating the regulating of inland transport is this, and I think it is about the best reason anyone could give as to why the particular section of inland transport under the heading of bus service should be regulated.  A number of bus services at present throughout this country, because of the very keen competition for traffic, are working their drivers and conductors as much as twelve and fourteen hours per day for very low wages. I hold any man, driving a public vehicle with perhaps 30 or 40 passengers, whose lives are in his charge, and who has to work 12 to 14 hours a day continuously, will ultimately bring about some terrific accident.  I believe the reason the hours were regulated on railways was because some very great catastrophies occurred on some of the main lines in England. It was only after the loss of a great number of lives that the people realised it was not right or proper to have a man in charge of a vehicle or train with a number of lives depending on him to be conveyed safely to their destination who worked an unreasonable number of hours.  Nature would assert itself in the long run, and eventually perhaps he would fall asleep at his post, with consequences which would immediately bring everyone's attention to bear on the matter.  I think the bus services of this country are running the danger of having some very serious accidents of this character because of the long and unreasonable hours which the drivers and conductors are called upon to work.  I am not referring <Col N="142" /> to every bus company at present, because I believe some of them only employ men for eight-hour shifts, but certainly others employ men from 12 to 14 at a time.</P>
    <P>There is also this question of third party risk.  That should be insisted upon, not alone with the bus services but for every other motor used on our roads.  It is not so very many years ago since any mechanically propelled vehicle, travelling on a public road, had to have a man with a red flag walking in front.  That necessitated that it could not go at more than a walking pace of three or four miles an hour.  I think plenty of people in this Assembly can remember that, and when motors are allowed to come out on the road and proceed at 12 miles an hour, as buses, and 20 miles an hour, as ordinary motor are, some safeguard is due to the general public.  I hold the least safeguard you can ask of any man driving such a vehicle at such a speed, is that before getting his licence to use that road he should have an insurance against third party risks, so that if any member of the ordinary public suffers an accident he will have something to fall back upon to compensate him.</P>
    <P>There has been a good deal of talk about traffic competition and national waste, and it is usually mentioned that these take place in the country, but it seems to me that in the city of Dublin you have worse waste than anywhere else.  I do not know if it is right for us to come to a very sudden conclusion in regard to this matter, because in Dublin you have the Tramway Company, with well equipped tramway services, finding it profitable to run buses side by side with their trams.  I cannot understand the talk about unreasonable competition among the bus companies when you find a company like the Tramway Company running buses in competition with their trams.  What is the use of talking about national waste and about other companies competing with one another for traffic when you have one company crowding the streets of Dublin with two different sorts of vehicles?  This question requires very serious consideration.  I think no conclusion can be reached until due consideration has been given to the whole question, and to the interests of <Col N="143" /> the entire community.  I agree with the mover of the motion that our internal transport needs very careful regulating in the interests of the whole community.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir JOHN KEANE Sir JOHN KEANE">
      <NameTxt>Sir JOHN KEANE</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the Seanad until 3 o'clock to-morrow, when I will have the right to continue the discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'FARRELL Mr. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make a <Col N="144" /> personal explanation.  There are circumstances over which I have no control which render it necessary for me to be absent from Dublin to-morrow and Friday.  Consequently I hope there will be no misunderstanding if I am not here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>We will not accuse you of running away.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 6.15 p.m. until 3 p.m. Thursday, 1st December.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>