<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="23" Month="Mar" Year="1927" Vol="8" No="13" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 23 Márta 1927" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 23 March 1927" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="627">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="627" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar a 3 a chlog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ELECTION OF" RHead="SENATOR">
    <Title>ELECTION OF SENATOR.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The first business is the election of a Senator to fill the vacancy caused by the death of our late colleague, Senator Martin Fitzgerald.  The following candidates are being proposed.  I will read out their names in alphabetical order:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Robert Andrew Anderson, whose qualifications are: &ldquo;By his association with Sir Horace Plunkett in the Irish Agricultural Organisation Society he has done honour to the nation by his useful public service.  By his special qualifications and attainments he represents one of the most important aspects of the nation's life.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Peter de Loughry, who was a former Senator.</P>
      <P>Patrick Joseph Hooper, Journalist and Barrister, who had eighteen years' experience as a Parliamentary Journalist, who was editor of the &ldquo;Freeman's Journal,&rdquo; 1916-24, and who was called to the Bar at Gray's Inn in 1915.</P>
      <P>Seán Milroy, who was a member of Dáil Eireann, 1921, to October, 1924, who is a writer on national, political and economic subjects, and has been an active worker in the national movement for thirty years.</P>
      <P>We will now take the first ballot; each Senator may vote for one or two out of the four names.  He need not vote for two, but he cannot vote for more than two.  The first ballot will be taken on those four names.  You will please put a cross opposite the candidate or candidates for whom you wish to vote.</P>
      <P>This having been done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The result of the first ballot is as follows:&mdash;Anderson, 21; de Loughry, 13; Hooper, 35; <Col N="628" /> Milroy, 21.  Mr. Hooper is, therefore, one of the two candidates in the final vote.  There is a tie for the second place between Messrs. Anderson and Milroy. I think, in view of the provisions of the Constitution, it is essential that I should give a casting vote as to which of those two should go into the final ballot.  At the same time I feel it an inconvenient thing that I should be called upon to decide a matter of this kind where there has not been a straight issue between the two candidates, and, therefore, it would be an assistance to me, and I hope the Seanad will not think it too hard on them, if I ask them, for my information and assistance, to take a direct vote now as to whether Anderson or Milroy is to be the second candidate in the final ballot. I want to make it quite clear that I reserve and am not surrendering my constitutional right &mdash; I do not call it a privilege &mdash; or constitutional duty to give a casting vote, but, at the same time, I might, by my casting vote, be excluding the candidate who would ultimately win the seat.  I do not want that to be put upon me without first getting some indication of the wishes of the Seanad as between those two candidates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasForan" hpid="Mr. FORAN Mr. FORAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FORAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest it would be far better if the three names went to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not agree to that at all.  I might be depriving Mr. Hooper of the position he has attained; he is entitled to it.  The other two are in a different position; there is only one place, and the two have tied.  I would, without hesitation, give my casting vote had there been a straight issue between the two, but as there has not been a straight issue I would like to have the Seanad's vote as between these two candidates.  I therefore ask you to assist me in giving a vote between them.  I want each Senator to say whether he votes for Anderson or Milroy.  That is the only question on this ballot.</P>
      <P>The following result was announced:&mdash;Mr. Anderson, 30; Mr. Milroy, 30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I give my casting <Col N="629" /> vote in favour of Mr. Milroy.  I will now take a vote as between Mr. Hooper and Mr. Milroy.</P>
      <P>The following result was announced:&mdash;Mr. Hooper, 34; Mr. Milroy, 16.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Accordingly I have to declare Mr. Patrick Joseph Hooper duly elected to fill the vacancy.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ORDER OF" RHead="BUSINESS">
    <Title>ORDER OF BUSINESS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I might mention that I anticipate for next Wednesday we will have received the Army Pensions Bill and the Jurors Bill from the other House.  Very likely the two will pass their final stages to-day or to-morrow. What I would suggest is that Senators should study these Bills with a view to seeing whether they would desire to put down amendments in Committee.  I should like to take the Committee Stages on Thursday.  I do not like to call the House together for Wednesday and have only one day's work.  If we get these Bills and they are circulated to Senators to-morrow or next day we should then be in a position to take the Committee Stage on Thursday.  I suggest that any Senator who wishes to hand in amendments should do so before Thursday, and that would enable us to take the Committee Stage on that day.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="CENTRAL FUND BILL," RHead="1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>CENTRAL FUND BILL, 1927&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That this Bill be now read a second time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'FARRELL Mr. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with the Vote on Account for the League of Nations, I want to draw attention to an incident that occurred at the last meeting of the League Council.  Sir Austen Chamberlain made a statement there arising out of a decision of the Imperial Conference respecting the form of treaties to be negotiated in future under the auspices of the League of Nations.  In regard to the general statement there was very little of importance attaching to it, and very little that could be taken exception <Col N="630" /> to, but a Press report, claiming to be accurate, credited Sir Austen Chamberlain with a statement towards the end that is of some considerable importance to the Saorstát as an independent member of the League and of the British Commonwealth of Nations.</P>
      <P>He is reported as having said: &ldquo;I sit here as a representative of Great Britain and the Dominions.&rdquo;  If that be the case, if Sir Austen Chamberlain is correct in his claim that he represented at the League Council not only Great Britain but also the Dominions, including the Saorstát, then it must follow that we are bound by whatever decisions may be arrived at by the Council of the League of Nations.</P>
      <P>At the last meeting of the general assembly of the League Sir George Foster, on behalf of Canada, claimed the right of Canada to be elected to the membership of the League Council.  A candidature of the Saorstát was actually presented and was voted for by a good number of the various representatives present.  If, notwithstanding that, Sir Austen Chamberlain feels he is entitled to make that claim, then it would look as if both Canada and the Free State have surrendered the claim they so determinedly maintained in the League in December last.  It is desirable and necessary that a very definite statement should be made on behalf of the Government as to what our position is in this respect.  It is not, I think, enough to say we must first of all ascertain whether that statement was made. I think we want to have our position made clear; that Sir Austen Chamberlain is not in a position to make any such statement, and that we are an independent member of the League; that we are only bound by decisions of that body to which we ourselves are parties by our own direct representatives, and that Sir Austen Chamberlain has no right at meetings of the League Council to bind this State to any decision that may be arrived at by that body.  I invite, therefore, the Minister for External Affairs to make the position of the Government plain in regard to the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. JAMESON Mr. JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>Can a Senator raise any question in regard to duties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="631" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no limit to the questions, as long as the subject matter relates to services for which votes are taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. JAMESON Mr. JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>The only point I wish to raise is whether one citizen of the Saorstát should be charged a certain duty on a motor car, and another citizen of the Saorstát charged a different duty on a car of the same value. I thought that in regard to the payment of duties to the State that all citizens were alike, but as a matter of practice I find out now that the law is so interpreted by the Commissioners that, according to the price that you pay for the car you are charged duty. An ordinary citizen is charged for a car a different duty to that which one who is in the trade is charged for the same kind of car, and a car of the same value.  My neighbour, who happens to be in the motor trade, can get a car in on which he will pay a duty on the price which the British manufacturer charges him&mdash;that is, he pays a great deal less duty on the car than I pay when buying a car from an agent.  The matter came out rather peculiarly in my case.  Holding the view that the maker's price to one Irish citizen should govern the whole case, I sent in, when I imported a car about nine months ago, the maker's invoice price &mdash; that is, the price at which the company sold the car to me.  It was perfectly clear in the invoice, and it was accepted at the time.  I was told at the time how much duty I should pay and I paid it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>But nine months afterwards somebody in the Department discovered that I had paid a different price to that which the manufacturer received for the car.  Now, I am sent in a bill for £43 extra.  Had I imported the car and had I been an ordinary dealer in cars, I would have got the car at £43 cheaper in the way of taxes, but because I just bought it from an agent here I am asked to pay £43 more.  I do not know that the Commissioners have the right to increase the duty on the very same car according to the amount the citizen pays for the car.  My neighbour got his car in and paid £43 less duty for it than I have now to pay, simply because he happens to be in the <Col N="632" /> trade.  Now, here is the letter which the Assistant Collector writes me:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;With reference to your letter of the 8th instant, relative to the dutiable value of your car imported by you on the 26th May last, I have to inform you that the duty is payable on the statutory value, which is defined by law as</P>
    <P>&ldquo;&lsquo;the price which an importer would give for the article if the article were delivered freight and insurance paid in bond at the port of importation, and duty shall be paid on that value as fixed by the Revenue Commissioners!'...</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The price shown on the invoice to the consignee is usually accepted in support of the value declared on the Customs entry, provided the Officers are satisfied that the value is not incorrect and that the invoice produced represents the full amount actually paid to the consignor by the first bona fide purchaser in Saorstát Éireann.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I do not know that there can be a bona fide purchaser at one price who can get off for less than the duty that a bona fide purchaser at another price must pay for the same article.  That is not the principle that is laid down here.  The trade importer would pay the manufacturer's price and I do not get it at that price, and so I have to pay £43 more than my neighbour who is in the trade.  Not only that, but I also incur, apparently, various penalties, because I am told I am only let off and that ordinarily very serious notice would be taken of this irregularity, &ldquo;but in view of the fact that your under-declaration of value was obviously inadvertent,&rdquo;&mdash;it was not inadvertent at all, it was because I believed it was what I should be charged&mdash;&ldquo;the matter will in this instance be adjusted on payment of duty on the basis of the price actually paid by you for the motor car, plus freight.&rdquo; Therefore I am to be allowed off for the offence of having robbed the revenue.  I do not see why one individual citizen in the Saorstát should pay one duty and another citizen pay an entirely different duty &mdash;</P>
    <Col N="633" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>You have not been let off the £43?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. JAMESON Mr. JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I have to pay it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>But you have not paid?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. JAMESON Mr. JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not as yet. I am now raising it.  I would like to hear from the Minister his views on the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be more convenient if each Senator raises any particular question he wants to raise and then there could be a general reply from the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel MOORE Colonel MOORE">
      <NameTxt>Colonel MOORE</NameTxt>
      <P>I dare say that most people will be rather surprised at what Senator Jameson said.  I am not surprised at anything the Minister for Finance or his officials may do.  I am past being astonished.  Some months ago, it will be remembered, the Minister presented what he called an Ultimate Financial Settlement between Great Britain and the Free State.  In my belief that ultimate settlement will be rejected by the ultimate authority on finance&mdash;the people of the Free State. I feel very confident about that.  Senators will remember that I was very anxious to go into details on this question, to find out what the settlement meant, so that we should be well acquainted with the contents.  The Minister for Finance very strongly objected to his statement being criticised.  The less the public know about the details the better pleased he is.  When it was proposed to appoint a Committee, the Minister said he would give them no information and would not attend, nor allow any of his officials to attend. That seems to me to be a most extraordinary attitude for a Minister to take towards the Seanad, the members of which are bound in duty to their constituents and to the whole country to find out as much as they possibly can about Ireland's finances.  The attitude that the Minister adopted has been continuous and, as far as I can see, he has made every effort to prevent people knowing what is happening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When the question was debated, I estimated that the Free State was paying <Col N="634" /> Great Britain an annual sum of 4½ millions.  Some Senators were very anxious about that state of affairs. They were surprised at the statement that 4½ millions was sent over to Great Britain annually.  It would seem as if our people did not own this country at all, if they are to pay a constant tribute of that sort.  I have ceased to be surprised. The British Government issued a White Paper, and in it I find there are a number of things quite different to those in the White Paper that was issued by the Minister.  There were a number of things in the White Paper issued by the British Government indicating the amount of money that had been received from the Free State &mdash; actual sums paid and sums paid in return. As far as I can understand it, the Free State paid 6½ millions of money to the British Government last year. The Free State received back under various headings about half a million. There was a clear balance against the Free State of 6 millions.  That represents about one-fifth of the total revenue of this country including Land Purchase Annuities.  Senators will be astonished when I read some of the items.  I am not at all astonished that the Minister should wish to conceal these facts and prevent the appointment of a Committee which would investigate them.</P>
    <P>At the time it astonished me to find that half the members of the Seanad, who ought to be, at least, as favourably disposed towards Ireland as any other country, deliberately voted against any investigation.  I wish those Senators would be as Irish as those on this side of the House and look after the interests of Ireland without necessarily opposing the interests of any other country.  Apparently, such is not the case, if I am to judge by the vote that was taken.  We were always told that these people wished to look after the finances of Ireland.  Apparently that is the last thing they want to do.</P>
    <P>Amongst the items on the White Paper are some that reached enormous sums in 1925-26.  I find that the R.I.C. represents £1,304,000, which was sent over to the British Government.  I dare say that was on account of the <Col N="635" /> Treaty.  It is an enormous sum of money, but I do not criticise it because, possibly, they were entitled to it. The Land Commission contributions towards Bonus and Excess Stock came to £183,000.  On the Local Loans Fund the payment on account came to £735,000.  Land Purchase Annuities came to £3,995,000 or nearly 4 millions, which were sent to the British Government. Then there is an extraordinary note: Public Office Sites (Dublin) Act, 1903.  I looked up the Act of 1903 and, to my astonishment, found that £13,222 was being paid to the British Government on account of the very office in which the Minister for Finance is doing his work.  Apparently the offices do not belong to the Free State at all, unless the Minister can give some explanation to the contrary.  Maybe he would be able to clear the matter up.</P>
    <P>The next item concerns the Irish Railways Act of 1896, and the Marine Works Act of 1902.  As far as I could interpret them, these deal with narrow gauge railways and piers that Mr. Balfour built when he was Chief Secretary. The piers are not very good, but the money was spent on them.  We have been paying £28,878 in annuities to clear off that debt.  The next item is in connection with a Telegraph Act.  I was not able to find the date of the Act, as it was not given.  I presume this refers to the railways.  Last year we paid on that account to the British Government £43,237.  Another item concerns the Military Works Act.  I cannot say what these works were, as the date is not given.  I presume they were works or buildings put up by the military in the past.  We have to pay for them.  There are a number of other very interesting items, one being minor claims in respect of miscellaneous services, £15,000.  I was under the impression that this country belonged to the Irish people.  Apparently it is heavily mortgaged to the British Government for all sorts of services.  I see that paragraph of the Minister's ultimate statement says:</P>
    <P>Subject to the provisions of this Agreement the British Government undertake to make no further claim in respect of any portion of the value <Col N="636" /> of property taken over by the Irish Free State belonging to British Government Departments whose administration and powers were under Article 9 of the Provisional Government (Transfer of Functions) Order in Council of 1st April, 1922, excluded from transfer to the Irish Free State Government.</P>
    <P>I cannot say whether any of the sums I have mentioned are being wiped out by the settlement, as these things are never explained by the Minister.  A sort of cloud is thrown over them. Whether they are wiped out or not it seems extraordinary that we should be asked to pay for them at all.  The Transfer of Functions Order of April, 1922, was provisional for handing over the services to the Provisional Government, and was to last for only twelve months.  I do not know why we should continue paying for five years afterwards. The Minister may possibly be able to explain that.  If so I hope that on this occasion he will be illuminating.</P>
    <P>A question also arose concerning Haulbowline.  As far as my information goes, the British Government claimed 4 millions for it and our Government was prepared to pay it.  Fortunately they sent down an intelligent person who, very much to the astonishment of the British officer, declined to pay anything.  When an intelligent person is sent to look after these things they are generally cleared off.  I hope the Minister for Finance will be able to clear up in the same way the matters I have mentioned.  I would also like to ask the Minister for a definite statement about the Hibernian School.  It was mentioned in the ultimate settlement, but in such a way that really I do not know to whom it belongs.  A statement made in the Dáil was equally cloudy.  Perhaps the Minister will say now if the school belongs to the Free State Government.  I also wish to ask to whom Kilmainham and the National Stud Farm belong.  These questions are being asked through the country. The Minister refused to give any explanation when I asked him before.  I can assure him that attitude is not doing him any good in the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnKeaneBart" hpid="Sir JOHN KEANE Sir JOHN KEANE">
      <NameTxt>Sir JOHN KEANE</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to draw the Minister's attention to circular <Col N="637" /> 30a, that has been issued by the Revenue Commissioners, dealing with the drawback on home-manufactured sugar.  It appears to me that duty is not paid on home-manufactured sugar. I thought the price, £23 a ton, was fixed on the understanding that extra duty was paid by covenants.  The fact that the duty is not paid necessitates that the drawback is not permitted, and then follows a most extraordinary complication which I am sure the Minister must realise, if he saw the circular. Separate accounts have to be kept by manufacturers for goods, of which sugar is an ingredient, differentiating between home-made sugar and imported sugar.  Separate stores have also to be kept for home-made and imported sugar.  The Customs authorities are insistent upon that requirement.  I suggest to the Minister that that is a very irksome and embarrassing regulation on manufacturers, and not in the interests of production.  It is what must be expected, I am afraid, when we embark on the slippery slope &mdash; protection of industries.  I suggest to the Minister that that duty might be avoided in this case by fixing the subsidy on home-grown sugar so that the excise duty would be paid.  I submit that if manufacturers, especially those in the export trade &mdash; which is of such importance &mdash; are hampered by restrictions of this kind, it is very damaging to production in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>In reference to the question raised by Senator Jameson, the position, I am afraid, is as the Revenue Commissioners have stated to him, that is the ad valorem duties are charged on the value to the importer &mdash; on the price he paid, the costs of transit, insurance commission, and so forth.  The duties are charged in that way, and I am afraid Senator Jameson has no option but to pay the £43.  One can make the argument for some other arrangement in the case of motor cars, but the Senator, I think, will see, on the whole, considering the other articles that are obliged to pay ad valorem duties, like boots or wearing apparel, it would be impossible to do anything else than to take the value to the importer. It is necessary to include everything, <Col N="638" /> because you would have all sorts of devices resorted to for the purpose of evading duty by having special invoices prepared.  I think the system we have is the system that is in operation in Great Britain.  I believe there are slightly different systems in operation in other countries, but the system we have is certainly the system which, on the whole, is simple and fairly satisfactory to work.  I would not undertake to the Senator that any other system would be adopted.  I have not heard a great number of complaints, because, as a rule, most purchasers are practically in the same position.  As a rule the car is imported by an agent here, and if there is anything added to the manufacturer's price it is added by the agent here after importation, but, in fact, the duty that is charged in the ordinary way is on the manufacturer's price to the agent plus the cost of transit here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. JAMESON Mr. JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Minister to keep us out of jail by allowing the Commissioners to publish the conditions necessary to be complied with, because apparently I was running very serious danger by doing what I believed was the legal thing, whereas if there were clearer regulations laid down by the Commissioners to guide anybody buying a car, there would be no such trouble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the majority of the people are aware of the position but I would certainly be agreeable to having words inserted in any fresh issue of the regulations that would make perfectly clear what the position is.  Senator Keane raised a point in connection with the non-payment of the excise duty on sugar.  The position is that the excise duty is not paid but the customs duty on imported sugar is taken into account in deciding how much of the £23 10s. or £24, that is provided for by the Sugar Beet Subsidy Act shall be actually paid to the manufacturer. The manufacturer is not paid the total of the subsidy in cash.  He is paid the total of the subsidy minus the duty on imported sugar.  He has the advantage over imported sugar laid down in the Act, but he is not actually paid the full subsidy in cash.  If we were <Col N="639" /> manufacturing all or nearly all the sugar required for home consumption, the point raised by Senator Sir John Keane would undoubtedly be an urgent point.  We only manufacture a fifth or a sixth of the requirements of the country. It does not seem to me that it is in any way urgently necessary at the moment to adjust the matter.  The manufacturer using sugar who is exporting his goods and for whom the question of the drawback arises, ought really to use imported sugar, and the matter will be entirely simple for him. The home producer can find a market. There is no question of supporting the home manufacturer.  The home manufacturer can only supply a small portion of the market.</P>
      <P>With regard to Senator Colonel Moore's tale of woe, the only thing I need say about it is that in the case of the sites, for instance, the Public Offices sites, the position is that here is an asset handed over to us at the change of Government which was not fully paid for when handed over.  The site of Government Buildings was purchased by means of money raised by terminable annuities, and these annuities have not been completely paid.  The position is, therefore, that we are completing the payment for this asset.  I do not think it is necessary, and I do not propose to go into it at any length, but one can say there is no reason why the British Government should pay for this asset of which we are in possession, seeing that we assumed no share of the British National Debt.  If Article 5 of the Treaty had been acted upon, and if some share of the British National Debt had been apportioned to us, then a new position might have arisen in regard to this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The same thing applies to the annuities under the Telegraph Act.  They are in repayment of money expended on telephone extensions, and in fact the repayment of portion of the money paid to the National Telephone Company. We have got the assets and the debt was referrable to a specific asset. The debt was raised for the purpose of acquiring a specific asset which we have got and consequently we are paying for it.  I do not propose to go any <Col N="640" /> further into the matters raised by Senator Colonel Moore.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel MOORE Colonel MOORE">
      <NameTxt>Colonel MOORE</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask is it not a fact that these sums were raised out of the United Kingdom Funds, and if the British Government is entitled to recover from us for buildings, telephones, and other things in this country, are we not entitled to a share of those things that were acquired by the United Kingdom Government in England?  Ireland was a part of the United Kingdom, voluntarily or involuntarily, and, I presume, is entitled to a share of the assets as well as the debts.  I think if there are debts for these things in Ireland there must be dividends from these things in England, and why should Ireland have to pay and England not pay us for our share of the assets over there?  I have no doubt that it would be extremely difficult to come to any such arrangement. The only way would be to wipe out the two items and put one against the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I despair of getting any facts home to Senator Moore, but the position is that we are not paying for any asset in England, and we are not asking the British to pay for any asset here which remains to be paid for and which we have in our possession.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="MINISTER for EXTERNAL AFFAIRS (Mr. Fitzgerald) Desmond FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for EXTERNAL AFFAIRS (Mr. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>With reference to the point raised by Senator O'Farrell, the Senator spoke on the strength of a Press report.  I am exactly in the same position.  I have not any sure knowledge of what statement was made at the meeting of the Council by the British representative, but as we have it in the Press and in a semi-official minute, the statement does appear to have been made: &ldquo;I sit here as representative of Great Britain and the Dominions.&rdquo;  The British representative does not sit on the Council as a representative of the Dominions.  In the same statement prior to that, Sir Austen Chamberlain had taken care to say that he made this statement at the express desire of the Governments represented at the Imperial Conference, which, I think, is almost a recognition of the fact that he only can speak in <Col N="641" /> the Council in our name when he is directly requested by us to do so.</P>
      <P>The right of the Dominions to a separate representation in the Council has been made abundantly clear.  If we possess that right, obviously the British representative who sits there and has a permanent seat, is not elected by us and we have no control over him as a member of the Council. Therefore he cannot ipso facto claim to represent us.  At the last meeting of the assembly, the Canadian representative &mdash; I think the Senator referred to his statement &mdash; in the course of his speech said &ldquo;I think it is right at this stage to say to this assembly and to the League that we consider we have equal rights of representation on the Council and otherwise, with every one of the 56 members of the League and we do not propose to waive this right.&rdquo;  The only way we can be represented on the Council of the League of Nations is directly by ourselves or in the case of an election by mandating power to an individual member of the Council directly.  As the British representative is there permanently and is not elected by us, obviously he would not represent us. He can only represent us to the extent that we expressly request him to make a statement on our behalf.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'FARRELL Mr. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I to take it that when Sir Austen Chamberlain made the statement &ldquo;I am here representing Great Britain and the Dominions,&rdquo; he was for the time being representing them at the request of the Minister himself or was it a slip or a mere mis-statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>The statement &ldquo;I sit here as representative of the British Dominions&rdquo; was not a justifiable statement and is not in accordance with facts.  The previous statement &ldquo;I make this statement at the express desire of all the Governments&rdquo; was a correct representation of the facts. The British representative is a representative of Great Britain and does not sit in the Council as the representative of the Dominions.  As far as I can understand the statement in the form I have got it, it is incorrect.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PILOTAGE ORDER CONFIRMATION BILL, 1927 (PROVISIONAL" RHead="ORDER CONFIRMATION BILL)&mdash;COMMITTEE STAGE">
    <Title>PILOTAGE ORDER CONFIRMATION BILL, 1927 (PROVISIONAL ORDER CONFIRMATION BILL)&mdash;COMMITTEE STAGE.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="642" /> The Bill was passed through Committee, without amendment, and ordered to be reported.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="INDUSTRIAL AND COMMERCIAL PROPERTY" RHead="(PROTECTION) BILL, 1926&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>INDUSTRIAL AND COMMERCIAL PROPERTY (PROTECTION) BILL, 1926&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <P>The following Government amendments were agreed to:</P>
    <P>1.  &mdash; Section 19, sub-section (3).</P>
    <P>After the word &ldquo;London&rdquo; in line 59 to insert the words &ldquo;or in the register of clerks kept under this Act.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>2.  &mdash;Section 62.  Before sub-section (2) to insert a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(2) If and when the Minister so directs there shall be kept at the office a book called the register of clerks in which shall be entered the names of approved clerks of registered patent agents.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>3.  &mdash;Section 63.  Before sub-section (4) to insert a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(4) If a register of clerks is established under this Act the Minister may by order make rules for the management of such register and may by such rules prescribe the qualifications and conditions for eligibility for and the fees to be paid on registration in such register.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>4.  &mdash;Section 63, sub-section (4). To delete in line 47 the words &ldquo;the rules aforesaid&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the words &ldquo;rules made under this section.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>5.  &mdash;Section 89, sub-section (1). After the word &ldquo;Act&rdquo; in line 49 to insert in brackets the words &ldquo;(including a mark registered under Section 62 of the Trade Marks Act, 1905).&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments 5 and 7 should be read together; they are carrying out the premise made here the last day that I would put down such amendments as would allow the Irish Trade Mark to be registered here. They have the further effect of allowing <Col N="643" /> the Association to assign to the Minister and the Minister to take the assignment if desirable.  No. 6 is an amendment which insists that I should take over the Trade Mark; amendment 7 allows it to be taken over.</P>
      <P>Amendments agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NugentEverardBart" hpid="Sir NUGENT EVERARD Sir NUGENT EVERARD">
      <NameTxt>Sir NUGENT EVERARD</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the following amendment:&mdash;</P>
      <P>New Section.  Before Section 122 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>122.  &mdash;(1)  The control of the Irish Trade Mark registered under the provisions of Section 62 of the Trade Marks Act, 1905, as a mark of origin and advertised in No. 1492 of the &ldquo;Trade Mark Journal&rdquo; by the Irish Industrial Development Association (Incorporated) and all the rights of the said Association under all existing agreements with their licensees shall be transferred to and vested in the Minister, and the said Irish Industrial Development Association (Incorporated) shall as soon as convient may be after the passing of this Act assign the said Trade Mark to the Minister, but no compensation whatsoever shall be payable to the said Association in respect of such transfer.</P>
      <P>(2) The Minister may procure the registration in Part A of the Register of the said Irish Trade Mark and shall be and be registered as the proprietor thereof and may procure the registration of the said Irish Trade Mark in any register maintained in any place outside Saorstát Eireann if and so far as and subject to such conditions as such registration is permitted by the law regulating such register and in any such case may procure himself to be entered as the proprietor of the said Irish Trade Mark.</P>
      <P>(3) The Minister shall in relation to the said Irish Trade Mark have all the powers conferred on Ministers in relation to marks of which they are the registered proprietors by Section 121 of this Act (which relates to the registration of marks by Ministers).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(4) Nothing herein contained shall <Col N="644" /> prejudice or affect licences already granted by the said Association to any persons to use or apply to any goods the said Irish Trade Mark during the respective period or periods for which such licences may have been granted by the said Association.</P>
    <P>(5) Every licence to use the said Irish Trade Mark granted by the Minister shall contain such provisions, conditions and restrictions as the Minister may think proper for ensuring that the said Irish Trade Mark shall only be applied by the licensee to goods of Irish origin and of specified quality or description.</P>
    <P>(6) The whole time staff of the said Association unless taken over with their consent by the Minister for the administration of the said Irish Trade Mark upon similar terms of employment as they at present enjoy shall be entitled to be compensated for the loss of their employment upon the like terms as those to which they would be entitled if they were members of the Civil Service.</P>
    <P>I would like the Minister to explain to the House how he has endeavoured to meet the views of the Association in regard to the defence of the Irish Trade Mark.  I am aware that a great part of our work is protecting the trade of this country and helping the interests of consumers from the use of misleading titles and trade marks which would represent goods manufactured outside the Saorstát as having been manufactured here.  Under other provisions of the Bill that is provided against.  As regards the power of the Ministry to take over the Irish Trade Mark without the amendment proposed by the Government that would be impossible, and therefore I am gratified that the Minister has given administrative power to acquire it if, at any future time, our funds are depleted to such an extent that we are not able to give adequate protection to the Irish Trade Mark in any part of the world.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the amendment more or less explains itself. It simply leaves it that the Government can take over the mark.  If it be taken over the Government will have <Col N="645" /> full power with regard to protection. One difficulty in this matter is that it is the Irish Trade Mark, and is used by certain North of Ireland firms.  I am not sure how far the Government here could take on the defence of an Irish Trade Mark as used, say by Six-County firms, or take action on behalf of Six-County firms if the mark were being used in other parts of the world.  There are other inherent difficulties and the question of its value would come up for consideration.  The point I wanted to meet was that the actual design, this collar design, was such that the Minister for Agriculture might be able to use it if he thought fit on his national mark. But again we are going to be involved in difficulties with the Six-County holders and users of the Irish Trade Mark.  However, we are leaving it here.  It may, at any time, be taken over if it seems a right and proper thing to do.  There is no decision made on that at the moment.  It is a matter which will require long and detailed consideration, and all I could bind myself to do was to have consideration given to it and to permit the Government at some future date to avail of this mark.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NugentEverardBart" hpid="Sir NUGENT EVERARD Sir NUGENT EVERARD">
      <NameTxt>Sir NUGENT EVERARD</NameTxt>
      <P>Another power given to the Trade Mark Association is the privilege of registry in this country, so that in case of depletion of our funds the ownership of that Trade Mark could not pass to anyone else for fourteen years.  That is the period, I understand, which can be registered for in this country.  That is a concession which will be extremely useful for those users of the mark who at present export to foreign countries.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>The following Government amendment was agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 123.  To add at the end of the section a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(2) The proprietor of a mark registered under this section or of a mark originally registered in the Patent Office in London under Section 62 of the Trade Marks Act, 1905, and subsequently registered under Section 89 (which relates to the registration <Col N="646" /> of trade marks registered in the Patent Office in London) of this Act in the register of trade marks in the Office, may assign such mark to the Minister and the Minister may take an assignment thereof, and on such assignment being made Section 121 (which relates to the registration of trade marks by Ministers) of this Act shall apply to such mark as fully as if the Minister had procured the registration thereof under the said Section 121.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. BENNETT Mr. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Dowdall asked me to move the following amendment:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 154, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;and&rdquo; in line 38 to insert the words, &ldquo;in case the author is a citizen of Saorstát Eireann, and desires to secure copyright in Saorstát Eireann, the work for which copyright is sought to be secured shall be printed in Saorstát Eireann, anything in this Act to the contrary notwithstanding; and&rdquo;</P>
      <P>It was fully debated before, so I shall withdraw it.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>The following Government amendments were agreed to:&mdash;</P>
      <P>9.  &mdash;Section 154, sub-section (1). In the fourth line of amendment No. 18 inserted in Committee to delete the word &ldquo;are&rdquo; and to substitute therefor the words &ldquo;were at the date of the making of the work.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>10.  &mdash;Section 154, sub-section (1). In the fourth line of amendment No. 18 inserted in Committee, after the words &ldquo;citizens of&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;and resident in.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 169, sub-section (2).  After the word &ldquo;within&rdquo; in line 5 to insert the words &ldquo;or import into.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It means that within this section a person will be entitled to make or import into the country genuine or authorised reproductions of works and the same fees will be paid.  There is no piracy about it at all.  It means that in the case of authorised productions of musical works such as gramophone <Col N="647" /> records, etc., leave would be given to import these on the payment of stamp duties.  This does not concern pirated works but authorised reproductions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'FARRELL Mr. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator is under a misapprehension with regard to the whole matter of importation. There is another section which deals with it.  The point about copyright in musical works is best explained in this way.  The author has copyright in the actual musical air.  There is also further copyright in gramophone reproductions. The original composer can control the reproduction in the first instance.  He can refuse to have records made of the air, but if the law is that a right is given to any one person, on particular terms to reproduce, the same right must be given to all comers on the same terms.  This deals with the particular limitation upon the acquiring of copyright by the owner of the air.</P>
      <P>Sub-section 2 of Section 169 says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;It shall not be deemed to be an infringement of copyright in any musical work for any person to make within Saorstát Eireann records, perforated rolls, or other contrivances by means of which the work may be mechanically performed if such person proves&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) that such contrivances have previously been made by, or with the consent or acquiescence of, the owner of the copyright in the work, and has given certain notice.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>All that is intended to be established is that any person within the Free State, on proving that he is merely taking to himself rights which have previously been granted by the owner of the copyright to somebody else, is kept outside infringement of copyright. A similar point about notice applies, but this section means merely that at the point where the first owner of the copyright has allowed records to be made he cannot prevent all and sundry records from being made on payment and acceding to the conditions, <Col N="648" /> but the conditions are not to be given to one or two or three but must be assigned to all.</P>
    <P>The point of importation is different. The Senator looks to it as if this prevented importation.  It does not.  Importation is always allowed, but at the importer's risk.  If the Senator buys a copy of a book from a publisher in England and brings it in here, or buys several copies and sells them here, he does not protect himself against a penalty for infringement if there be infringement merely because he has paid someone from whom he believed he got copyright of the work.  He imports at his own risk.  The same thing applies to gramophone records.  The fact that he is the importer does not bar an action in the court if there were infringement. The Senator thinks to prevent what there was no necessity to prevent.  He thinks that because the words &ldquo;to make within Saorstát Eireann&rdquo; are there that it debars importation. Importation is possible under certain conditions, but is subject to that one fact that it is at the importer's risk.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I had in mind was that the original person who had the copyright might authorise persons to make reproductions on which the ordinary fees had been paid, and that persons in this country dealing in those things would be entitled to import into this country various reproductions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>There is, at present, nothing to prevent them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. FARREN Mr. FARREN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FARREN</NameTxt>
      <P>If that is so there is no necessity for this amendment and I withdraw it.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. BENNETT Mr. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Dowdall I move amendment Number 12:&mdash;</P>
      <P>New Section.  Before section 173 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>173.&mdash;(1) Any person may apply to the Minister for a licence to print and publish in Saorstát Eireann any book wherein copyright subsists and of which the author is a citizen of Saorstát Eireann or of a country <Col N="649" /> with which no convention relating to copyright and binding on Saorstát Eireann exists, if at any time after publication and within the duration of the copyright the owner of the copyright fails&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  to print the said book or cause the same to be printed in Saorstát Eireann; or</P>
    <P>(b)  to supply by means of copies so printed the reasonable demands of the Saorstát Eireann market for such book,</P>
    <P>and the Minister may grant such licence on such terms and subject to such conditions as he may think fit.</P>
    <P>(2) Every licence granted under the provisions of this section shall be deemed to be a contract, on the terms and conditions embodied in such licence, between the owner of the copyright and the licensee and the licensee shall be entitled to the like remedies as in the case of a contract, and shall have the same power and right to take any action or any legal proceedings to prevent or restrain any infringement of copyright which affects the rights of such licensee or to recover compensation or damages for such infringement that the owner of the copyright would have for an infringement of his copyright, and the provisions of section 165 (relating to importation of copies) of this Act shall apply to the importation of copies of the book in respect of which the licence has been granted as if the licensee were owner of the copyright in the book.</P>
    <P>(3)  For the purposes of this section the word &ldquo;book&rdquo; shall include every volume, part or division of a volume, pamphlet, sheet of letterpress, sheet of music, map, chart, or plan separately published.</P>
    <P>It was admitted on the last day by the Minister that this amendment was not on all fours with the one which had been withdrawn that day.  The Minister said it conformed more nearly to the Canadian model than was the case of the other amendment.  My own peculiar line of action in the debate was largely guided by the words of Senator Brown that Canada was distinctly outside <Col N="650" /> the Berne Convention as regards copyright and printing in Canada. Since then one has an opportunity of looking into this matter and consulting the authorities.  Copinger, on the question of copyright, definitely states that &ldquo;Canada adhered to the Berne Convention and to the Protocol of 1914 on January the 1st, 1924.&rdquo;  Copinger's book is the highest authority on copyright law.  Furthermore, the Canadian Almanac for 1926, which is more or less the Whittaker of Canada, states that on the 1st of January, 1924, Canada's adherence to the revised Berne Convention became effective.  That is the opinion of the Canadian Almanac, an authorised authority on this matter, and it gives an actual contradiction to the opinion on which we based our withdrawal of the particular clause on the last day.  Whether or not it was a wise thing to have withdrawn our amendment on the last day, this particular amendment put in now simply asks to give people the licence to publish in the Saorstát any book wherein copyright exists.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Would not the effect upon the Convention be precisely the same?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. BENNETT Mr. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>I dare say it would, but considering the authorities which I have quoted, I urge that it will not place us outside the Convention.  I am not giving my own opinion at all.  I should not have the audacity to put my own opinion against that of learned lawyers, but it is the opinion of Copinger, and it is also the opinion of the &ldquo;Canadian Almanac,&rdquo; that Canada is within the Berne Convention.  That being so, I think this amendment might be accepted.  It simply asks if the existing owner of the copyright does not wish to comply with the terms and have his work printed here that the Government should have power to give a licence to have such work printed here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I know nothing about the law on the Convention, but it occurs to me that possibly what you have read is consistent.  They brought themselves into the Convention, but they also have got themselves out of it by what they have done.  Is <Col N="651" /> not that the question?  And I do not think those opinions you have quoted touch that at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. BENNETT Mr. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>They brought themselves in by acts similar to what we want to have done here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Bennett presses that this amendment is more nearly in accordance with the Canadian model, but the argument here was: Even if you got perfectly close to the Canadian model, we are definitely making a breach in regard to the Convention, and that eventually we would be put to a choice between the Convention and this amendment.  The Senator quoted Copinger, but what Copinger said is that Canada joined the Berne Convention.  So Canada did, and until the point is raised by someone who is hurt by this amendment, Canada will remain inside, but that does not mean that if the point was raised Canada would not be put to her election between remaining in or adopting a different position.  Meantime, I have had an opportunity of fortifying myself with another opinion.</P>
      <P>It was hinted on the last day that I had consulted and had taken the Attorney-General's opinion.  I had not done that then, but I have done so since, and he is clear that any amendment of this kind of our copyright would have the effect of our having to choose between remaining in or being put outside.  This amendment is rather nearer to the Canadian conditions. The principle is very much the same and, as the Chairman pointed out, the effect of being inside and being outside the Berne Convention is precisely the same.  It is a matter of opinion but, fortified by the legal opinion that I have got, I say we would ultimately have to make our choice between the Convention and the printing requirements.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. KENNY Mr. KENNY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KENNY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am advised that as to the position in Canada the law as it now stands is this: That to secure copyright in Canada, citizens of Canada must print in Canada.  And this is only a compromise, for up to the 1st of January, 1924, the Canadian law was the same as that of the United States <Col N="652" /> of America; that is to say, that in order to secure copyright in Canada, citizens, not only of Canada, but of all countries, had to print in Canada.  The effect of this was that Canada, like the United States of America, was not in line with the Berne Convention.  By an amendment which came into force on the 1st of January, 1924, the Canadian Government restricted this printing condition to citizens of Canada, and this restriction brought them into harmony with the Berne Convention, which was the actual and only object of the amendment. This being the present state of the law of Canada in this matter and as it does not prevent Canada from remaining in the Berne Convention, a similar law could not possibly put the Saorstát out of the Convention.  The amendment does not affect the rights of any member of the Convention outside the Saorstát.  They will still have their full rights under the Convention; but citizens of the Saorstát to secure copyright in Saorstát must print in Saorstát, though they may publish wherever they like.  When it comes to printing and publishing we find they are entirely different things, but we have dealt with all that before.</P>
      <P>Under this amendment a citizen of Saorstát may send his manuscript to a publisher in London and have his work published there, but, as a rule, the great publishers in London are not printers.  The publishers would simply send out the manuscript to a printer in Great Britain.  All the amendment asks is that the work of printing should come to the Saorstát.  That involves no hardship on Irish authors, as they can get their work printed as cheaply and as well in Ireland as elsewhere.  And as they get their inspiration and material in Ireland it is most unfair that all the profit of producing their books should go to the foreigner while scores of Irish printers are walking our streets idle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>It should be made clear to the Seanad, before they come to any conclusion, that they will have to choose between this amendment and the Berne Convention.  Now, beyond all doubt, this is in the form of the Canadian legislation at present, but <Col N="653" /> equally, beyond all doubt, it is just as much a breach of the Convention as would be the direct printing amendment the other day, as in the conditions it would have the same effect. Now, that being so, it is simply a question of lawyers' opinion as to whether this does put Canada outside the Berne Convention and would put us outside the Convention.  I express my own very settled opinion on the matter, and I am happy to say now that I am backed up by the opinion of the Attorney-General. The Seanad will have to choose between the opinion of the Attorney-General on this matter of importance and this amendment, and, therefore, I ask them to pause before they alter the decision they came to last week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasBennett" hpid="Mr. BENNETT Mr. BENNETT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BENNETT</NameTxt>
      <P>In the circumstances I ask leave to withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Government Amendment.&mdash;Section 179, sub-section (1).  After the word &ldquo;Dublin&rdquo; in line 5 to insert the words &ldquo;or of any of the respective authorities having control of the three constituent Colleges of the National University of Ireland.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGILLIGAN Mr. McGILLIGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGILLIGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to call the attention of the Seanad to an amendment passed on the last day on the motion of Senator Brown.  Certain information has been since received with regard to the effect of that amendment.  It was amendment No. 19 on the Order Paper, to Section 154, and read:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Provided that such rights shall as regards translations into the Irish language cease to exist unless the author of the work or his legal representative shall have within a period of 10 years from the date of the first publication of the work published or caused to be published in Saorstát Eireann a translation of the work into the Irish language.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The effect of that was this, that if, say, within 10 years from the first publication no translation has been made, then without infringement of the copyright a translation could be made here into the Irish language. <Col N="654" /> That seemed to be allowable for the reason that there were two revisions of the Berne Convention&mdash;one at Paris and one at Berlin.  In the original Berne Convention there was a certain amount of talk as to whether there was to be any limitation of the author's right to copyright in translation.  In other words, was the right of copyright subsisting for the lifetime of the author and 50 years thereafter also to apply to a translation of that work, or to the language of the work in which it was first produced, and the idea seemed that it should be all-round copyright in the most extensive way. It was discussed at Berne, and afterwards at Paris, and later on at Berlin, and the effect was that there was a limitation allowed.  It had been found that four countries had, by domestic legislation, taken the right to themselves that if a work was not translated into their own language within 10 years, then translation might be made and there was no infringement of copyright. In the two sessions held there was some talk about it; eventually it was decided to adhere to the Berne Convention with reservations, and one of the allowed reservations was on this point of copyright.  Consequently, various people concerned, including the Department of Education, stressed the importance of having the right to translate modern authors into Irish if the translation was not made in 10 years by the authors themselves.  An amendment was considered and passed here.  In addition to the Berne Convention and Union there is also the Commonwealth Union, of which we are members, or are likely to be members.</P>
    <P>Our legislation up to that point on the translation, although straining something of the terms of the Commonwealth Union, was not regarded as putting us outside that Union.  The translation point, we are now advised, will put us outside the Commonwealth Union.  The advantages or disadvantages likely to accrue on our being outside the Union are not very clear to me.  I see this advantage, that by being in the Commonwealth Union the moment our legislation is passed we can assure Irish authors that automatically they get certain rights in the countries forming <Col N="655" /> the Commonwealth Union.  If we leave that Union, instead of getting these rights automatically, we must make mutual agreements with each of the particular countries.  But we are bound to get the terms of the Berne Convention.  Inasmuch as they are members of the wider Union&mdash;the Berne Union&mdash;we must get the Berne terms from them.</P>
    <P>The objection and the only disadvantage that I can see likely to follow in being outside the Commonwealth is, that instead of having a block of countries with which we have reciprocal arrangements immediately, we would otherwise have to get these by a separate understanding with each.  That, however, does not seem to matter very much, but there will be a Conference held at Rome this year to consider the whole Berne Convention over again. Italy has given notice that she intends to move that States will no longer have a right to adhere to the reservations of the Berne Convention.  Italy is one of the countries which is adhering to the reservations with regard to translation, and that fact, with other facts, would seem to indicate that this point with regard to translation will disappear.  If Italy is making that move, Senators may have themselves in this position that we may pass an Act here now embodying this particular clause with regard to the ten years translation period, and after some time we may have to move to take that very clause from the Act.</P>
    <P>I would like to suggest to the Senate that in view of the fact that this Conference is to be held in Rome this year, and that that clause with regard to translations could not be availed of by the Department of Education or anybody else for a period of four-and-a-half years to come, it cannot operate until 10 years after December, 1921, and in view of the fact that no benefit can accrue until December 1931, I think it would be better that we should omit the provision.  I think we will find it is likely that the Rome Conference will decide that States will no longer have a right to adhere to the reservations of the Berne Convention. Of course we could snap our fingers at <Col N="656" /> the Convention and put ourselves in the position of the United States.  I do not know whether under your Standing Orders it would be possible to move now to delete the amendment passed last week, or whether notice would be given to move at the next sitting the deletion of the particular section put in last week?</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be wiser that notice be given for the next meeting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. BROWN Mr. BROWN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BROWN</NameTxt>
      <P>I give notice to delete the amendment put in with regard to translation last week.</P>
      <P>Ordered: That the Fourth Stage be resumed on Wednesday, 30th March.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE" RHead="ADJOURNMENT">
    <Title>THE ADJOURNMENT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we adjourn, I wish again to remind the Seanad that the Constitution (Amendment) Bill No. 5 is at present in a state of suspense, and that we cannot proceed any further with it unless a motion with reference to it is put down by a member of the Seanad.  The motion would be either to send it back to the Select Committee or to recommit it to the whole House.  Possibly in view of what happened, recommittal to the whole House would be the wiser course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. KENNY Mr. KENNY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KENNY</NameTxt>
      <P>If no Senator sees his way to table such a motion, will the Bill remain permanently suspended?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it would become operative after the period fixed by the Constitution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. KENNY Mr. KENNY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KENNY</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that would be only after consideration by this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>We did consider it.  We passed the Second Stage, and so we have considered that Bill. You may recollect that the question of consideration occurred in reference to the Intoxicating Liquor Bill of 1924. But there, instead of giving the Bill a Second Reading, as I recollect, we postponed the consideration of the Second Stage.  Notwithstanding that, the Government were advised&mdash;I am not going to say that I agree with the view or not&mdash;that the period operated, and at the end of the stipulated number of days provided by the Constitution that <Col N="657" /> the Intoxicating Liquor Bill automatically became law and they proceeded to enforce it.  I do not think anybody was more surprised than the Government themselves when they discovered it had become law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. KENNY Mr. KENNY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KENNY</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to say that the two cases are not the same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, have we not actually passed the Second Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I have said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickKenny" hpid="Mr. KENNY Mr. KENNY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KENNY</NameTxt>
      <P>That is only part consideration. A Bill cannot be deemed to have been considered until it is finally and completely considered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>There is another point, and it is this&mdash;if we do nothing with this Bill until June, and there is a dissolution in June, I am rather inclined to suggest that the effect of that dissolution will be to get rid of the Bill altogether.  I do not pronounce a definite opinion on that because the position has not yet arisen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'FARRELL Mr. O'FARRELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'FARRELL</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes; it did on the Intoxicating Liquor Bill of 1924.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I was strongly of the opinion that the Liquor Bill of 1924 was dead, but the Government thought otherwise and nobody raised the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>The Constitution does not deal with that point, wisely or unwisely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="658" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Then we would have to go back to Constitutional usage and practice.  I had no doubt at that time that under the Constitutional practice of Great Britain, that the Bill was as dead as Julius Caesar, but it was brought to life and has been kept going for a couple of years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. JAMESON Mr. JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you not think the Seanad should have an opportunity of deciding whether they intend to hang up the Bill or not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Any Senator can get an opportunity of discussing that by putting down a motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. JAMESON Mr. JAMESON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JAMESON</NameTxt>
      <P>We could not get the Senate to dispose of the whole matter of leaving it in suspense without having the Senate decide whether they wished to hang it up or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is in order I will put down a motion that the Constitution (Amendment) No. 5 Bill be considered by a Committee of the whole House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest to the House that that is the wiser course. Instead of re-committing it to the Select Committee, I think it would be better for the House to keep control of the Bill itself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>If we move that it be considered in Committee of the whole House that would make the matter right.  I will put down a motion to that effect.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 5.15 till 3 o'clock on Wednesday, 30th March.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>