<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Fri" Date="5" Month="Jul" Year="1996" Vol="148" No="10" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 5 Iúil 1996" DateEnglish="Friday, 5 July 1996" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="993" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have notice from Senator Finneran that on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The need for the Minister for the Environment to sanction the Ballagh-Ballybeg water scheme in County Roscommon and that he provide the necessary funding in 1996 to have the scheme constructed.</P>
      <P>I regard the matter raised by Senator Finneran as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and it will be taken on the conclusion of business.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Today's business is items 1 and 2.  Item 1, Second Stage, will be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business until 1 p.m.  There will be a sos from 1 p.m. to 2 p.m. after which Committee and Final Stages of the Metrology Bill, 1996, will be taken.  If item 1 has not been concluded it will be resumed after completion of item 2, although I suspect item 1 will be completed by 1 p.m.  I suggest 20 minutes per spokesperson on item 1 and 15 minutes for other speakers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="994" />
    <Speaker pid="GVWright" hpid="Mr. Wright Mr. Wright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wright</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to next week's business, what is the position with the Courts and Court Officers Bill? Can the Leader give us some idea about what is in that Bill?</P>
      <P>The Leader of the House will be aware that a tour operator, Classic Choice, went into liquidation overnight. Radio stations and offices have been inundated with telephone calls from consumers, and probably from other companies, as this is the height of the holiday season.  Will the Leader recommend to the Minister for Transport, Energy and Communications that a public statement be made about the protection of the consumer under the 1982 Act?  That Act offers complete protection to the consumer with regard to the cost of the holiday and the Department will ensure that every holiday maker is returned to their country of origin.  It would be useful if a public statement or advertisement was run in the newspapers and other media over the weekend to allay the fears of consumers. I understand that there is no holiday available on this weekend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>This morning's edition of <i>The Examiner</i> has a worrying front page story about the lack of resources for the Chief State Pathologist and his office.  This issue creates much concern and a number of people I spoke to this morning have raised it.  They were unaware of such a problem as they simply assumed that the office was fully resourced.  I would like to hear a response to the story from the Leader of the House.  Perhaps he could organise a discussion on it.  I am not qualified to make statements on the matter as I do not know enough about it.  In the vast majority of serious cases the technical evidence from the Chief State Pathologist's office is quite crucial to the production of evidence for the conviction of criminals.  The House should be informed about this matter either through a statement from the Minister or through a brief debate.  We need reassurance.  I am trying to anticipate the problems or criticisms that might <Col N="995" /> arise in the future if it turns out that the lack of resources in that office led to flawed evidence.</P>
      <P>With regard to today's business, I doubt that item 1 will continue until 1 p.m.  I do not object to the Order of Business but I would be happier if the sos were taken on the conclusion of item 1 if it concludes before 1 p.m.  That would mean we could proceed to the next item.  If item 1 finishes in an hour and the sos is taken from 1p.m. to 2 p.m. there will be a sizeable gap in the day's schedule.  I ask the Leader to consider accepting my suggestion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Wright's remarks about Classic Choice and I ask the Leader to ensure that people who are stranded abroad are looked after.  The Department is doing what it can but it is important to reassure people that since their holidays are bonded, they will not be out of pocket, although they will be seriously discommoded.  If they have to book new holidays there will be a financial aspect involved.</P>
      <P>My other point is to do with Bord na Móna.  This matter was raised by Senator Finneran and others yesterday. The extended nature of the dispute between the board and the chief executive must come to a conclusion.  I appeal to the Leader to ask the Minister for Transport, Energy and Communications to do everything possible to resolve this matter speedily because it is affecting morale within the company and its capacity to compete effectively.  This matter needs to be brought to a conclusion as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator O'Toole's comments on the State Pathologist's office.  It is a serious matter and the comments made by <i>The Examiner</i> need to be addressed at the earliest possible date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I strongly protest at the comments made by two District Court Judges, Judge Martin and Judge Pattwell, at recent sittings of the District Court.  In <Col N="996" /> making these comments, they have clearly moved from the judicial to the political field.  One judge went so far as to advocate that people &mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot raise this matter.  The Judiciary is separate from the political arena.  I must rule you out of order, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>That is why I am raising the matter.  There is a clear separation between the Judiciary and the political arenas.  These two judges have moved into the political arena.  That is unwise and dangerous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator cannot raise that on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>What they stated was not part of their judicial function; they have moved into the political arena. When will this House be afforded an opportunity to discuss these comments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>The behaviour of judges.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomEnright" hpid="Mr. Enright Mr. Enright">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Enright</NameTxt>
      <P>I regard it as a very serious matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>The public will be shocked and horrified at the disclosures by the Chief State Pathologist on the current chronic state of forensic pathology in the Department.  Today's disclosure has raised serious questions about the ability of the State to function properly in this area, which is central to some of our present problems in the justice area. Can we have an opportunity discuss this matter and get an indication from the Minister for Justice as to what is being proposed to deal with that situation, which has also been described as chronic in the areas of personnel and staff.  The State Pathologist, Dr. Harbison, drew attention to the fact that his assistant, Dr. Bolster, is only employed on a temporary basis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not discussing the technicalities of that report now, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="997" />
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>It may be the most serious issue raised in recent times on the administration of justice.  We need to get an indication from the Minister for Justice if she proposes to deal with that and, if so, how and when?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator O'Toole's and Senator Daly's requests for a debate on the comments made by the Chief State Pathologist.  The situation is at such a level that on occasions the Chief State Pathologist must pay his own way to go to international conferences. That is not a healthy situation, given the present state of crime.  Not alone should the office function well but it should also be seen to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I also support discussing the situation highlighted by Dr. Harbison. He is a respected public servant and we should all pay attention to his views.  Maybe we could have an opportunity to discuss it next week.</P>
      <P>Would it be possible for this House to take some time to discuss the affairs of Bord na Móna?  The issue was ducked by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Commercial State-Sponsored Bodies yesterday in an outrageous way.  If either House of the Oireachtas is to have any function in this matter, we should set aside time for it now.</P>
      <P>I also concur with Senator Enright's views on the Judiciary.  We will have the opportunity to discuss the matter in the Courts and Court Officers Bill next week.  Judges are now beginning to meander into the political field.  While I welcome them expressing their views&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already ruled on that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DickRoche" hpid="Mr. Roche Mr. Roche">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Roche</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not talking about any one judge, but it is about time we unfettered the Houses of the Oireachtas to express our views about judges, some of whom are duffers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Wright raised two issues.  The Courts and Court <Col N="998" /> Officers Bill will be taken next week.  It is scheduled for Thursday but the Whips may agree to take it on Wednesday; that is open for discussion.  This Bill will establish three new judges to help clear the current backlog of cases waiting to be heard.  It will also give Members an opportunity to discuss the points raised by Senator Enright and Senator Roche, the overall structure and performance of the judicial system.  Like the two Senators, I was also astonished to read some of the self-indulgent outbursts from the two judges mentioned in recent times, which in one case virtually amounted to incitement.  The less said on that, the better.  There will be an opportunity next week for Members to discuss that matter.</P>
      <P>Senator Wright mentioned the tour operator case.  I am sure the Minister and his Department are doing everything possible, but I will pass onto him the urgency of the matter and the need to make a statement at the earliest possible moment.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Toole and others raised <i>The Examiner</i> story concerning Dr. John Harbison.  He is one of the most respected public officials in this State and is a person of great integrity and dedication to duty.  Anything he says must be taken seriously.  The way to follow this up might be to put a motion on the Adjournment next Tuesday to provide basic information and, if need be, we could then have a debate on the matter next Wednesday or Thursday.  Putting down a motion on the Adjournment might be the best initial way to get the facts.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Toole also raised the question of the ordering of today's business. The reason I had a fixed time for discussing the Metrology Bill is because there is a need for a degree of certainty in how we run our business so that people know exactly when it is being taken and not be caught on the hop.  The Whips can discuss this afterwards, but it is better to have a fixed time for this matter so Members can arrange their day with some degree of certainly as to what will happen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="999" /> Senator Dardis and Senator Daly raised the question of Bord na Móna. On the morning when the board, hopefully one way or the other, is coming to the final act &mdash; for all our sakes I hope it is &mdash; it would not be appropriate to have a debate today.  However, I have no problem with having one next week if this would help.  Today would not be the day to do this, when the matter is still being resolved and we do not have the full facts.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Borrowing Powers of Certain" RHead="Bodies Bill, 1996: Second Stage">
    <Title>Borrowing Powers of Certain Bodies Bill, 1996: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Coveney) Avril Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Coveney)</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senators will note from the explanatory memorandum circulated with it, the Borrowing Powers of Certain Bodies Bill, 1996, is essentially a technical one.  It is designed primarily to remedy what appears to be a deficiency in existing laws governing the borrowing powers of State bodies whose borrowing is subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance.  This apparent deficiency came to light fairly recently when the legal advisers to a State body queried that body's authority to engage in a finance lease and the legal validity of any State guarantee associated with it.  As a result and until the legal situation is clarified, financial institutions are reluctant to contract any further finance leases with those State bodies which do not have express statutory power to transact such leases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In general terms, a finance lease is a contract under which an asset is purchased by a party other than the lessee, usually a financial institution, which, by availing of capital allowances, etc., can reduce the cost of financing to the lessee.  The lessee in such an arrangement assumes all the risks and rewards of ownership other than legal title to the asset.  Because of their cost effectiveness, <Col N="1000" /> such leases are widely used as a means other than direct borrowing to acquire assets.  A number of State bodies have in recent years funded some of their capital investment by way of finance leases.  The total value of outstanding finance leases for commercial State bodies at the end of 1995 was £575 million; of this, £72 million carried a State guarantee.</P>
    <P>On receipt of the inquiry concerning the doubt about the legality of the contracting by a particular State body of a finance lease, my Department consulted the Office of the Attorney General.  Following detailed consideration of the issue, that Office advised that express statutory power is required for State bodies to enter into finance leases and that a similar power is required if the Minister wishes to guarantee the resultant obligations of State bodies.</P>
    <P>Against that background, Senators will appreciate the need for the present Bill, if only to confirm the validity of those existing finance leases whose legality is in doubt.  Up to the time the legality of the involvement of some of these bodies in finance leases was queried, everyone involved in such transactions, including financial institutions, had accepted that the legislative authority was there.  My view is that it would be regrettable if I were now to pass over the opportunity the present Bill affords to put beyond doubt what precisely the borrowing powers of State bodies are.</P>
    <P>There has been a rapid evolution of financing techniques.  That has been accompanied by an ever-increasing complexity in the financial instruments which have been developed in response to the requirements of market participants to reduce the costs of borrowing and to minimise the risks caused by fluctuating interest and exchange rates.  This process of refining existing instruments and inventing new ones is likely to continue and it behoves us to take account of it in this Bill.  It is for this reason that I make provision for the Minister for Finance, after consultation with the Central Bank and the Revenue Commissioners, to be able to prescribe other <Col N="1001" /> capital financing mechanisms which the State bodies may avail of.  Otherwise, we could be faced in the future with a situation of either having to deny a State body access to new financial instruments or else bringing in fresh primary legislation for every new kind of transaction or class of transactions that a State body may wish to avail of.</P>
    <P>In this context I would like to assure Senators that what is being proposed in this Bill is not of major significance.  In the first place, all it is doing is effecting through legislation that which a private sector company established under the Companies Acts could do through amending its memorandum and articles of association.</P>
    <P>There are other assurances I would like to offer in relation to the Bill.  The Bill does not in any way give any more powers to State bodies than are at present conferred by or under statute, it simply removes a doubt.  The powers being clarified in this Bill can only be exercised in accordance with specifications laid down by the Minister for Finance, after consultation with the relevant Minister, where appropriate.  The Bill lays down strict procedures for the calculation of a State body's financial exposure to a transaction for the purposes of the statutory limits on its borrowing and any related State guarantee. In preparing the Bill, my Department had detailed discussions with organisations likely to be affected by it, including the State bodies mainly concerned, the Irish Bankers' Federation and the Irish Finance Houses Association.  All of them found the Bill acceptable. Finally, I would like to reassure Members of the House that the published figures for the debt of State bodies and any associated guarantees include the liabilities arising from finance leases.</P>
    <P>This Bill also provides for an increase in the limit on the borrowings of ACC Bank.  At present the limit is £1,400 million and the Bill proposes to raise it to £2,400 million.  The agricultural sector was hard hit by the economic difficulties of the early 1980s and this had severe <Col N="1002" /> knock-on effects on the finances of ACC.  In fact, the corporation sustained heavy losses in 1987 under the weight of accumulated bad debts and increases in arrears.  The Agricultural Credit Act, 1988, was introduced to address these problems, in particular through broadening ACC's remit with a view reducing its dependence on a single economic sector.</P>
    <P>The finances of ACC improved over the following years.  The ACC Bank Act, 1992, removed all remaining restrictions on its lending.  That Act also changed the name of the corporation to ACC Bank plc to signify the more diversified nature of the its activities.  It also raised the authorised share capital from £35 million to £50 million and increased the limit on borrowing from £800 million to £1,000 million.  Another important feature of the Act was that it made the bank subject to the prudential supervision of the Central Bank.  This means that ACC Bank must obey the same rules and regulations as other credit institutions supervised by the Central Bank.</P>
    <P>Over the past five years ACC Bank has grown rapidly, with deposits more than doubling to reach almost £1,000 million at the end of 1995.  The bank's total borrowings, including deposits amounting to nearly £1,230 million, are quite close to the present borrowing ceiling of £1,400 million.  This rapid growth in the bank's activities was due to its success in attracting new business, particularly in the home and commercial mortgage sector.  Unlike more established mortgage providers, however, the bank does not have a portfolio of maturing mortgages to offset against new mortgage growth.  Thus, because all mortgages undertaken by the bank are mostly new business, this business generates a higher rate of asset growth.  If the existing ceiling of £1,400 million on borrowing is not raised, the bank's growth will effectively be halted. It is for this reason that I am now proposing to raise the ceiling, and the amount I have in mind is £1,000 million. At the average rate of growth which has <Col N="1003" /> been realised in recent years, this should cover the bank's requirements for the next four to five years.  The financial performance and growth of ACC Bank over the past few years, in an increasingly competitive market, is due mainly to the effort and commitment of the board, the management and the staff of the bank.  I would like to thank them all for their contribution to this success.</P>
    <P>As I said in my introductory remarks, this Bill is essentially a technical one designed to fill a gap in existing law governing the borrowing powers of State companies.  Section 1 specifies the definitions to be included in the legislation and is a standard provision.  As the definition of &ldquo;capital value&rdquo; relates to section 7, I propose, if Senators agree, to deal with it when treating of that section.</P>
    <P>Section 2 defines the bodies to which the Bill applies.  Section 3 contains the main provisions of the Bill.  Section 3 (1) confirms the powers of the bodies concerned to engage in the specified list of capital financing transactions and enables the Minister, after consulting the Central Bank and the Revenue Commissioners, to prescribe by order other capital financing transactions which these bodies may conduct.  The latter provision is designed to take account of the continuing development of financial mechanisms and the possibility that State bodies may in future wish to avail of an instrument not yet developed.  Section 3 (2) enables the Minister, again after consultation with the Central Bank and the Revenue Commissioners, by order, to amend or revoke any previous order made under this or the preceding subsection.  Section 3 (3) relates exclusively to the class of transaction known as finance leases and is designed to give the Minister the authority to take account of any changes in definition which may be made to it as accountancy practice evolves.  Section 3 (4) defines the terms &ldquo;finance lease&rdquo; and &ldquo;body&rdquo; for the purposes of the section.</P>
    <P>Section 4 gives the bodies concerned <Col N="1004" /> the power to provide indemnities and to charge their assets in respect of any of the specified transactions.  Section 5 provides that all existing provisions in respect of borrowings and guarantees, including requirements in relation to ministerial consent, will apply to all the transactions authorised by the Bill.  It also enables the Minister, after consultation with a relevant Minister where necessary, to determine the terms and conditions under which a State body may engage in any of the specified transactions.  Section 6 extends all existing guarantee powers, rights and obligations of Ministers and State bodies respectively to the transactions specified in the Bill.</P>
    <P>Section 7 specifies the manner in which the borrowings of State bodies and any related State guarantees are to be calculated for the purposes of the statutory limits imposed by the Oireachtas.  These limits set ceilings on the financial exposure of State bodies in the case of borrowings and of the State in the case of guarantees.  To this end it is necessary to ensure that any financial exposure or potential liability arising from a transaction authorised by this Bill is recorded by the State body concerned as borrowing for the purposes of the statutory limits in question.  The section relies on a specific definition of &ldquo;capital value&rdquo; in this regard, namely, the total value of the transaction less any inherent interest amounts and any amounts which do not constitute a legal liability on the body concerned.</P>
    <P>Finance leases do not comprise separate principal and interest payments as in the case of a normal term-loan. However, in pricing a leasing contract, there is effectively an imputed or inherent interest element included in the repayments.  For the purposes of determining the level of borrowing under the Bill, it is proposed that the amount borrowed will be calculated by reference to the nominal value of the repayments less the inherent interest amounts.</P>
    <P>In the case of certain structured finance leases, a State body may secure the <Col N="1005" /> lease payments by making a deposit with a third party who takes over the payment obligations of the lessee.  Generally, these structures do not allow the lessee assign to the third party its legal liability for the lease payments.  Thus, if for any reason the third party were to default on its payment obligations, the liability to make the payments would fall back on the lessee.  The Bill requires that any such potential liability or exposure be recognised for the purposes of both the borrowing limit and, where appropriate, the guarantee limit.</P>
    <P>Section 8 confirms that State bodies may contract leases other than finance leases.  The leases in question are operating leases and relate mainly to normal rentals such as office space and equipment.  As such, the section provides that they are exempt from the requirements specified in the Bill in relation to finance leases and other capital financing instruments.</P>
    <P>Section 9 provides for an increase in the borrowing limit of ACC Bank to £2,400 million from its present level of £1,400 million.  Section 10 is a standard provision in Bills which alter the powers of State bodies, and sections 11 and 12 are standard to all legislation.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I warmly thank Senators for agreeing to process this Bill as a matter of urgency.  I commend the Bill to them and am anxious to hear their comments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>As has been outlined by the Minister of State, this technical measure before the House has two main provisions &mdash; first, to confirm the legal powers of State bodies to engage in capital financing transactions and, second, to increase the borrowing limits of the ACC Bank plc.  The measure is necessary to clear up any doubts or questions which may have arisen or may arise about finance leases with State bodies, as financial institutions were reluctant to conclude such leases until the legal position was clarified.  The Bill enables that to be done.  The existing borrowing limit of the ACC will be reached later this year and the provision in the Bill is <Col N="1006" /> necessary to allow the bank to continue to expand its operations and secure its future limits for the next four years. Fianna Fáil will not oppose this legislation and will not propose amendments to it.  We also support the comments of the Minister of State.</P>
      <P>Nevertheless, while we support the progressive expansion and development of State bodies and the necessity to enable them to engage in capital financing and leasing arrangements, there is growing concern about Government financing and borrowing generally.  The Minister of State is aware of the evidence of deterioration in State finances and perhaps in his Second Stage reply he will avail of the opportunity to give the House a brief account of current Government borrowing, including that of State companies.  We have heard much concern in the past about State borrowing, and any indications of a deterioration in that regard would be serious for the long-term prospects of the Irish economy and would cause public worry.</P>
      <P>In the run up to the next election, which is about a year away, there is no question but that the Government will endeavour to make itself popular by engaging in a public spending spree. The Minister knows the long-term consequences of allowing public spending to get out of control.  Too many sacrifices have been made in the past in an attempt to manage public borrowing, and it has been successfully achieved at great inconvenience to many people and much personal discomfiture to many politicians.  If the Government believes it can embark on a spending bonanza which would have to be paid for later, it is gravely mistaken because the public will not be fooled a second time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In supporting the measures in the Bill, I advise the Government to exercise caution.  It should not allow borrowing by semi-State bodies or the Government to lead to a deterioration in Government finances and cause repercussions for economic progress and development.  Strict financial management must be maintained.  The Minister <Col N="1007" /> for Finance and the Government may believe that because of an impending election they can embark on excess expenditure.  If they do, it will be a serious matter for our long-term economic prospects, so it must be avoided.</P>
    <P>There are indications that Government borrowing is beginning to rise again.  The Minister for Finance has recently drawn attention to that and we support his efforts to tackle it.  However, there is a risk that he will be overruled, as he is in a three-party arrangement in which pressures are building up from different areas.  We could find ourselves back to the bad days of borrowing to gain popularity or favour, when at the end of the day the bills must be paid and the costs met.</P>
    <P>I note the success of the ACC Bank. In 1995 its total assets were £1.3 billion, which is a healthy financial position; its customer deposits increased by 33 per cent and loans to customers increased by about 20 per cent.  The ACC Bank, which is a relatively small institution, makes a valuable contribution to the overall development of the economy and provides a stable means of financial support, especially to the agriculture sector.  It employs about 550 people at present.  It also provides valuable employment in the regions.  I am glad to see from the ACC's annual report for last year that it has opened new outlets in Cork and Dublin.  The extension of the branch network is important and should continue as the bank grows in the future.  Since the legislative change in 1989 which gave the bank the freedom to engage in various financial transactions, it has made a valuable contribution in some of the niche market areas, such as the provision of film finance and home and commercial loans.</P>
    <P>My colleague, Senator Rory Kiely, will deal with the importance of the ACC to the agricultural sector.  The ACC should be reminded that the backbone of its business &mdash; about 30 per cent of its business &mdash; is in the agricultural sector.  The agricultural industry faces a serious situation at present.  Reference <Col N="1008" /> was made in the House recently to the critical situation facing many of the small farmers hit by penalties for the overproduction of milk.  The ACC, in conjunction with the Department of Agriculture, Food and Forestry, should put a package in place to assist small producers, of whom there are about 500 in my constituency, who have been hit with a bill of £1 million in penalties for the oversupply of milk last year.  That bill has to be met by small farmers who are already financially stretched.</P>
    <P>We should send a message to the ACC that it should continue its interest in the agricultural industry, which has been the backbone of its business. Although successful and expanding, it should keep in mind that many of its initial customers were from the agricultural sector.  There remains a large demand for capital finance in that sector. In the efforts to create employment there is a need and an opportunity to use banks like the ACC to establish small agriculture related businesses.  Cooperation between the development agencies, such as the LEADER groups and the county enterprise boards, the farming agencies and the ACC, could help to halt the decline in agriculture and provide jobs in the farming areas which are most in need of employment.</P>
    <P>Agriculture is faced with a grave challenge at present.  Apart from the crises in the beef and milk sectors, there are long-term structural problems which cause a decline in the small farming sector, a fall off in the number of small family farms and a continuing drift from agriculture.  There is a need for co-operatives, banks and politicians to find a mechanism whereby the decline can be slowed or stopped.  Over many years the ACC has played a valuable role in the small farming sector, and with its new powers I look forward to it continuing to look to the future with confidence.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister of State give an indication of the present levels of borrowing in the ESB and Bord na Móna, especially in the ESB for additional generating capacity?  The new challenges facing the ESB in electricity generation <Col N="1009" /> have been referred to on a number of occasions in the House.  With competition from Europe there is the possibility of foreign operators entering the generating business in Ireland.  How does the Minister of State see the ESB's future borrowing requirements to face the challenge of competition being met? Will its borrowing powers be strengthened to allow it to provide the additional generating capacity essential for the ongoing development of the economy?</P>
    <P>We are deeply concerned at events in Bord an Móna.  I do not know if the Minister of State can offer any clarification in the debate on this Bill, but the future of Bord na Móna is threatened unless the squabbling at board level can be resolved quickly.  I am aware the Minister for Transport, Energy and Communications has demanded information from the board on the events concerning the chief executive.  Bord na Móna is an important semi-State body with a mandate to undertake certain responsibilities.  The company should endeavour to meet the challenges it faces for the future and there is no time for the public squabbling we have seen over the past few weeks.</P>
    <P>The matter needs to be finalised.  We should send a clear message to the board to resolve its differences with its chief executive officer, to get back to the responsibilities given to it by the Government and to stop the disgraceful public squabbling of late which has brought the board and its personnel into disrepute.  This House expects Bord na Móna to carry out the functions assigned to it, including those being provided for in this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the Senator should continue on that road.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am off the road.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Be careful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be the last to stray down a bog road.  I keep away from bog roads because they cause trouble for <Col N="1010" /> politicians.  However, in the case of this bog road it is time the pot holes were filled.  We support the Bill and do not propose to amend it.  I look forward to the Minister of State's replies to the issues I raised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a technical Bill which has the main objective of confirming the powers of State bodies to engage in capital financing transactions, including, in particular, finance leases. Over the last decade or so there has been a phenomenal growth in financial services in Ireland and abroad.  This has resulted from many factors, including the worldwide liberalisation of financial markets, international payments and capital movements.  Helped by constantly improving technology, it has been accompanied by an ever-increasing sophistication in the financial instruments developed in response to the requirements of market participants to reduce the costs of borrowing and to minimise the risks caused by fluctuating interest and exchange rates.</P>
      <P>Ireland has benefited from these developments as witnessed by the growth of our own financial sector and the success of the International Financial Services Centre.  In regard to the latter, the direct incremental employment created by the IFSC now stands at over 3,000, most of it highly-paid, and many more jobs have been created in ancillary areas such as accountancy and law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The private commercial sector has been very quick to exploit the potential benefits of new financial instruments for their capital financing needs.  However, our big commercial State bodies have been equally adept in this area.  Indeed, given their need to finance sizeable capital programmes, these bodies have developed a particular expertise and sophistication in the use of capital financing instruments.  One of the mechanisms they use to this end is the finance lease, a contract under which an asset is purchased by a party other than the user, usually a financial institution, which, by availing of capital allowances, etc., can reduce the cost of financing to <Col N="1011" /> the user, the lessee, who, in such an arrangement, assumes all the risks and rewards of ownership, other than legal title to the asset.  Such leases are commonplace and widely used as an alternative to direct borrowing to acquire assets because it is more cost-effective.</P>
    <P>A number of State bodies have acquired assets in recent years by way of finance leases.  The total value of outstanding finance leases for commercial State bodies was £575 million at the end of 1995.  This is largely a technical Bill which confirms the power of State bodies to employ modern capital financing instruments.  Effectively it is to make explicit what we have assumed was implicit and to add for future requirements. That is something any private company can do simply by changing its memorandum and articles of association. In the case of most State bodies, however, their powers are established in statute and as such require a change in statute.</P>
    <P>The reason for this Bill is not that the specified transactions are <i>ultra vires</i>&mdash; the State cannot tolerate State bodies being a little bit <i>ultra vires</i> but rather that there is a question of legal doubt specifically over the issue of finance leases.  The existence of this doubt has resulted in a situation whereby financial institutions are reluctant to conclude any finance lease contracts with State bodies who do not have explicit statutory power to engage in finance leases in their own legislation.  The purpose of the Bill, therefore, is essentially to reassure the market and to put the question of the scope of the borrowing powers of State bodies beyond question.</P>
    <P>The ACC borrowing limit has been increased five times since the bank was founded in 1927.  This current increase, the sixth, represents the largest single increase in both monetary and percentage terms and arises from the success of ACC Bank in the provision of mortgage finance.  Because all mortgage business currently represents new lending, this mortgage finance has a major impact on the borrowing and asset base of the <Col N="1012" /> bank, in that the bank does not have a mature position whereby new mortgages would be offset by maturing mortgage debt.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the ACC Bank as over that last number of years it has expanded out of all recognition.  It has done great work in local communities and for farmers &mdash; on which it should be congratulated &mdash; but I concur with Senator Daly that it has moved slightly from what it was set up to do, largely to look after farmers.  However it is now moving into the mortgage and financial end of it and the house market in particular. It should concentrate more on the agricultural sector which was what it was set up to do.  It still provides a great service for farmers and local communities but should concentrate more on farming needs.</P>
    <P>I draw the attention of the Minister of State to bank charges, in particular for small businesses which have been fleeced by the major banks here over the last number of years from both interest and bank charges.  There is a huge difference between the A rate, at which the big business people borrow and the AAA rate.  The majority of small businesses borrow at the high rate and there is a significant difference.  It puts them at a huge disadvantage to the big business people who can borrow competitively.  I ask the Minister of State to address this because there is great scope here.  We have seen our exports grow in leaps and bounds over the last number of years in particular.</P>
    <P>This country is geared to small businesses which are the life and soul of this country.  If we are to expand further, more consideration from a financial point of view should be given to small business in terms of bank and interest charges.  It behoves the Government to take this on board and to put it up to the banks to do something about it.  Various schemes have been introduced over the last few years by the Government and the banks where special &mdash; and welcome &mdash; interest rates were set up for new small businesses.  The small business pays a huge price for all those <Col N="1013" /> schemes because it is paying the high interest charges and charges that the banks have imposed.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister of State and the Government on the way the economy has grown over the last number of years.  Senator Daly has no need to worry about the way the country is being run.  The economy is going well, it is in good capable hands.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this a commercial?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no doubt we will see another attractive budget next year from the Government which is performing well.  There has been an escalation in the property market over the last number of years which also benefits the financial institutions because when the property market is buoyant, the banks do extra business which helps the economy.</P>
      <P>I will have a few questions on Committee Stage but, again, I congratulate the Minister of State and the Government on the economy.  Will he take the few issues I raised on board in relation to the bank charges for small businesses?</P>
      <P>I have a press release here from the Small Firms' Association stating that there is a 33 per cent difference in basic charges between the six major banks and there is a 57 per cent differential in interest rates charged between small and large business.  The SFA quarterly survey of bank charges has established extreme variations in the cost of banking in the area of bank charges and interest rates.  The survey conducted in association with Chapman, Flood Chartered Accountants established that for the same services the typical small firm will incur a quarterly charge of between £90 and £120 depending on which of the six banks the enterprise deals with.  On borrowings the survey establishes that small firms may pay up to 57 per cent more in interest charges than large corporate businesses.  This bears out what I have said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the Bill.  We have no option but to grant the Minister what he <Col N="1014" /> wants as it is in the interest of progress. I compliment ACC Bank on its work in recent years.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not rise to the bait which Senator Burke threw out and talk about whether there are a safe pair of hands at the helm.  We will leave that debate for another day.</P>
      <P>I recognise and accept the need for the Bill.  Perhaps the ACC Bank will acquire some of the financial leases to be used by the State sector, so maybe there is a connection between the ACC Bank and the State companies who will use these instruments.</P>
      <P>I am worried at the extent to which it is possible to expose the State to a liability by the use of some of these instruments. I accept the State sector should be allowed operate on a competitive and commercial basis but if banking or leasing facilities are available to companies within the commercial sector, the State sector should have the same capacity to use those instruments but in a controlled system.</P>
      <P>To highlight control or the lack of it, one could cite the controversy in Bord na Móna.  Without getting into the rights of the individual case, a degree of close monitoring, accountability and control must permeate the State sector.  I sometimes wonder how significant that control has been in the past.  If these instruments are not used prudently, where we are talking about large sums of money &mdash; the Minister has mentioned that £570 million had been taken on by way of lease and only part of that is guaranteed by the State &mdash; there is a capability to run a company into fairly serious difficulties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In a certain sense we are regularising something which, on the face of it, is illegal.  Certainly, there is a significant doubt about its legality.  The Minister referred to that in his speech.  How did we get to a point where the commercial State bodies had outstanding finance leases of £575 million at the end of 1995 without its potential illegality being spotted.  The Minister said the deficiency came to light fairly recently <Col N="1015" /> when the legal advisers of a State body queried its authority to take up a finance lease.  Which State body was involved or who were the legal advisers to the State body?  If I am correct in my assumption about the £575 million in outstanding finance leases, it seems this matter had escaped the attention of the legal advisers to quite a few State bodies. I accept what we are doing is correct, but it strikes me the matter had gone on longer than it should have before it came to light.</P>
    <P>The other matter is to do with the ACC.  I would echo some to the points made by the two previous speakers.  The ACC did a huge service to Ireland, the people and the economy by what it did for farming in the 1960's and 1970's, because there was a need to expand agriculture.  Certainly, the ACC made huge investment to bring agriculture into a competitive and modern era.  The quality of farming is testimony to the fact that funds were made available at reasonable rates and periods of repayment which allowed people who did not have large cashflows to avail of credit, invest in their businesses and expand. We owe a tremendous debt to the people who created the ACC and worked in it in the early days.</P>
    <P>That agricultural ethos is still apparent in ACC Bank, but the bank must operate in a competitive and commercial environment.  I welcome its diversification into other areas, that it is lending to commercial business, providing mortgages and conducting private banking because that has helped the bank to survive within a competitive environment. The Minister has outlined the growth in the bank's business and that is to be welcomed.</P>
    <P>Fortunately, the fifth banking force has not loomed as an issue in this debate.  I would not like to embarrass the Government parties by raising the matter here because it might lead to dissension. The way forward for the ACC Bank is not through amalgamation with TSB or other Irish financial institutions to create the fifth banking force but <Col N="1016" /> through linking with like-minded European businesses such as <i>Credit Agricole.</i> That is where alliances should be sought rather than in the creation of a fifth banking force.</P>
    <P>Having welcomed the diversity of the ACC Bank's activity and its growth, its core business should remain that of financing good commercial propositions from the agriculture sector.  It still has a significant contribution to make in that area and can do much to develop farming, forestry and other alternative farming enterprises which can lead to growth.  ACC Bank understands the farming business probably better than any other financial institution.  From that point of view alone, ACC Bank is in a good position to judge the merits of cases and their funding.</P>
    <P>The Minister mentioned the Central Bank's controls and its role in liquidity. I am a little confused about section 9(1) which states:</P>
    <P>The Corporation may (subject to such conditions and limitations on amounts as the Minister, after consultation with the Central Bank, may determine) raise or borrow money ...</P>
    <P>I am interested to hear the Minister's clarification on the matter.  To my mind, it almost permits the Minister to allow the bank to do things which the Central Bank would not allow in terms of liquidity. In other words, if the Minister consults the Central Bank, he might then be in a position to set aside certain rules of the Central Bank which would apply to the banking sector in general.  I do not think that is the intention of the Bill, but it is a matter which needs clarification. I am interested in an explanation of the role of the Central Bank within the control which would be exercised on ACC Bank and how that control might differ from other commercial banks.</P>
    <P>Returning to the State sector aspect of the Bill, I do not understand why one would not include &ldquo;interest amounts&rdquo; and &ldquo;amounts which do not constitute a legal liability on the body concerned&rdquo; in the definition of &ldquo;capital value&rdquo; in <Col N="1017" /> section 1.  In looking at the viability of the business and its annual accounts, it would be important to have those matters integrated into the &ldquo;capital value&rdquo;. Perhaps they are treated under separate headings in the accounts of the company. I do not understand why they are not taken into account.  We have concentrated on the finance leases but there is a range of other instruments under section 3.  I say that by way of comment rather than asking the Minister of State for an explanation.</P>
    <P>I am fascinated by the term &ldquo;finance lease&rdquo;.  Having read the section, I still do not know what a finance lease is.  The section purports to explain and clarify what a finance lease it, but it does not. There seems to be tautology in the definition in section 4(a).  My suspicious mind has come to the conclusion that this is a device created by lawyers because if they make the language impenetrable enough they will be able to dine off it for years to come and have these matters redefined in the courts.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State gave us a very clear explanation of a finance lease in his speech.  There is also a very clear explanation in the explanatory memorandum accompanying the Bill.  The average, well informed citizen who reads the legislation should be able to understand what it says.  This section is extremely difficult to understand, although I am sure the financial experts and lawyers understand it.</P>
    <P>The Minister of State defined it quite clearly when he said:</P>
    <P>A finance lease is a contract under which an asset is purchased by a party other than the lessee, usually a financial institution, which, by availing of capital allowances etc, can reduce the cost of financing to the lessee.  The lessee in such an arrangement assumes all the risks and rewards of ownership other than legal title to the asset.</P>
    <P>That is clear, simple and easy to understand. However, I do not understand the definition in the Bill.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1018" /> Senator Burke referred to the charges imposed by the banks.  I agree with him in terms of the very high level of charges which small businesses must pay. However, I find certain encouragement in the survey to which he referred, in that there appears to be some difference between the rates charged by different banks.  There is now a degree of competition in the banking sector in respect of their charges and interest rates.</P>
    <P>In my bitter experience of dealing with banks, 15 years ago one could go down any street in Ireland and get exactly the same deal from every bank on that street.  That was wrong and I am pleased that there appears to be some level of competition.  At that time I banked in England and it was very evident that the cartel which operated in Ireland was absent there and that one could get different deals by shopping around.  That is how commercial life should be.  I accept the level of charges is very penal on small businesses. However, I welcome the development of a difference in the rates charged by banks, which I hope will continue so that there will be meaningful competition in the banking sector.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Coveney, to the House and congratulate him and the Minister for Finance, Deputy Quinn, on their stewardship of the economy.  The latest economic figures published this week confirm this country recorded the highest rate of growth in the European Union last year and that we are well on course for achieving the same feat this year.  We are a long way from the days when certain politicians and financial commentators used to claim that the Labour Party could not be trusted to handle the economy.</P>
      <P>This is a technical Bill which has two main purposes, as stated in the explanatory memorandum:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(i)  to confirm the legal powers of State bodies to engage in capital financing transactions, including finance leases, and to make certain other <Col N="1019" /> provisions in relation to such transactions by these bodies, and</P>
    <P>(ii)  to increase the borrowing the limit of ACC Bank plc from £1,400 million to £2,400 million.</P>
    <P>Certain difficulties have arisen for State bodies in transactions concerning financial leases.  These difficulties have led to a reluctance on the part of some financial institutions to entertain leases with State bodies.  The Minister of State explained clearly what is involved in the Bill when he stated:</P>
    <P>It is designed primarily to remedy what appears to be a deficiency in existing laws governing the borrowing powers of State bodies whose borrowing is subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance.  This apparent deficiency came to light fairly recently when the legal advisers to a State body queried that body's authority to engage in a finance lease and the legal validity of any State guarantee associated with it.  As a result, and until the legal situation is clarified, financial institutions are reluctant to contract any further finance leases with those State bodies which do not have express statutory power to transact such leases.</P>
    <P>Losses are often incurred by State bodies in such situations.  We do not want to see State bodies losing money because the proper legislation is not in place.  As the Minister of State stated, the opinion of the Attorney General has been sought as to whether specific statutory provisions need to be made to resolve these difficulties.  The Attorney General's view is that some statutory intervention is necessary.</P>
    <P>I commend the Minister on moving so quickly towards resolving this difficulty. He and I believe in doing everything to improve State bodies.  They should be able to compete on a par with private companies.  Only then can we be expected to judge how well they are serving the State.  This means that any doubts about finance leases already <Col N="1020" /> entered into by State companies should now be removed.  Whatever legislation is necessary to allow State companies access to a wide range of capital support should be introduced.</P>
    <P>As the Minister of State pointed out, what is involved here is very limited.  In effect, we are doing no more than a private company does when it alters its memorandum and articles of association. Nonetheless, it is important that it is done.  The Minister is committed to resolving all outstanding matters with this legislation, so that future Ministers for Finance will not have to draw up similar legislation.  I cannot see how any Member of this House could not support this aspect of the Bill.  The Bill only applies to State bodies whose borrowing powers are subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance.  As the Minister of State informed us, there are only about 50 such bodies.</P>
    <P>The Bill also seeks to increase the limit on borrowings allowed by ACC Bank.  The threshold increase appears to be in the region of £1 billion.  As a Member from a rural area, I know well the role played by the ACC over the years. I am particularly pleased that in recent years it has turned around its fortunes and is now heading for is ninth successive year of profitability.  The passing of the ACC Bank Act, 1992, in effect made ACC a commercial bank subject to the supervision of the Central Bank.  At that time, the limit on the bank's borrowing was £1,000 million.  However, so strong has the bank's performance been in the meantime that borrowing is now close to its upper limit.</P>
    <P>This performance has been generated by the bank broadening its range of activities outside its traditional agricultural base.  As the Minister pointed out, the mere fact that he is coming before this House today seeking to extend the ACC borrowing limit is a testament to the bank's success in the last decade.  I compliment the work of the management and staff of ACC in turning around its fortunes.  It would be churlish of any Senator to oppose that section.</P>
    <P>I now wish to refer to the exchange <Col N="1021" /> rate rip-off.  Exchange bureaux have different rates for buying and selling currencies and they charge commission. These rates are too high.  Tourists to this country and our young emigrants returning home are being ripped off. They are feeling the pinch now because the punt is stronger than sterling.  This means that in exchanging every £100 sterling they may end up with only £93 or £94.  Variation in buying and selling rates is one thing, but it is unacceptable to include commission charges.  We should be providing an exchange rate service within the EU rather than making it difficult for people to travel.</P>
    <P>The difficulty with Bills of this kind, which involve little or no substantive political or philosophical disagreement, is that it is not easy to elaborate on them at length unless one is opposed to State participation in commercial activities.  I compliment the Minister of State and the Minister for Finance, Deputy Ruairí Quinn, on their handling of the economy and the good job they are doing with the ship of State.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome this necessary Bill.  The explanatory memorandum to the Bill states:</P>
      <P>The purposes of this Bill are</P>
      <P>(i)  to confirm the legal powers of State bodies to engage in capital financing transactions, including finance leases, and to make certain provisions in relation to such transactions by these bodies, and</P>
      <P>(ii)  to increase the borrowing limit of ACC Bank plc from £1,400 million to £2,400 million.</P>
      <P>In his speech the Minister stated that the Bill:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>... is designed primarily to remedy what appears to be a deficiency in existing laws governing the borrowing powers of State bodies whose borrowing is subject to the consent of the Minister for Finance.  This apparent deficiency came to light fairly recently when the legal advisers to a State <Col N="1022" /> body queried that body's authority to engage in a finance lease and the legal validity of any State guarantee associated with it.  As a result and until such legal situation is clarified, financial institutions are reluctant to contract any further finance leases with those State bodies which do not have express statutory power to transact such leases.</P>
    <P>It is strange that such leases as were conducted did not appear to be legal. However, if there is any doubt the situation should be remedied and I congratulate the Minister of State for introducing this Bill.</P>
    <P>Regarding finance leases, the explanatory memorandum to the Bill states:</P>
    <P>A finance lease is a common form of asset financing in the private commercial sector.  In a finance lease, the asset is purchased by a party, other than the lessee, which, by availing of capital allowances etc., can reduce the cost of financing to the lessee.  The lessee in such an arrangement assumes all the risks and rewards of ownership other than legal title to the asset.  Such leases are commonplace and are widely used as an alternative to direct borrowing to purchase assets because it is more cost-effective.  A number of State bodies have raised finance in recent years by way of finance leases.</P>
    <P>Was the doubt about the legality in respect of the State bodies raising finance by way of finance leases, or was it about, for example, a farmer purchasing a tractor from ACC Bank plc or another bank by way of lease?  In such transactions the farmer will accept the responsibility of ownership but the bank will own the tractor until the terms of the lease are met, when the farmer will have the option to purchase.  Is legislation necessary for these types of transactions?</P>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>No, the Senator is referring to a hire purchase transaction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1023" />
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>Was the doubt about legality solely related to the finance raised in recent years by State bodies by way of lease?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>That is correct.  The legislation has no effect on the other matter the Senator referred to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RoryKiely" hpid="Mr. R. Kiely Mr. R. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the provisions in the Bill which will rectify this anomaly.  I also welcome the provision to raise the borrowing limit of ACC Bank plc from £1,400 million to £2,400 million.  The bank was founded in 1927 to help the agriculture sector and proved to be most valuable.  Under the ACC Bank Act, 1992, the bank widened its scope to deal with other sectors in addition to the agriculture sector.  This was necessary to make the bank more competitive and structure it in such a way as to ensure its continued successful existence.</P>
      <P>When speaking on the ACC Bank (Amendment) Bill, 1994, I referred to the great work done by the bank and commended the management and staff. The staff are very co-operative in giving loans, especially to the farming community. In his speech the Minister stated:</P>
      <P>However, the sector was hard hit by the economic difficulties of the early 1980s and this had severe knock-on effects on the finances of the ACC.  In fact, the corporation sustained heavy losses in 1987 under the weight of accumulated bad debts and increases in arrears.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One of my constituents found himself in difficulties in meeting his repayments to the bank.  I had occasion to discuss his problems with the manager of the local branch and found the bank most helpful and understanding.  It was prepared to meet the person, discuss the situation and come to an arrangement.  When money is lent to a person the capacity to repay the loan must be taken into account.  Similarly, it is good for people to obtain loans and they should <Col N="1024" /> acknowledge this by repaying them promptly.</P>
    <P>In 1992 the bank widened its scope to cover the commercial sector.  The Minister of State should ensure that the bank will always look after the agricultural community.  Senators Burke and Calnan referred to the great economic growth that is taking place.  However, this is not reflected in agriculture.  Farmers have experienced the worst period of their careers during the past six months because of depressed prices in the beef and meal sectors.  The bank has the facility to provide subsidised loans which should be provided to farmers in trouble.  Senator Daly referred to penalties farmers face.  In the Golden Vale area they must pay big fines because of milk over production.  Some of them may not be in a position to pay these fines and the bank should help them.</P>
    <P>With regard to the issue of bank charges, farmers may exceed their overdraft limits and be subject to crippling referral fees. These fees are most unfair and can only be reduced if the overdraft limit is extended, which makes it more difficult to repay.  I support Senator Calnan's plea regarding the exchange rate. People going abroad are penalised and it is most unfair.  I welcome the Bill and I ask the Minister to ensure the agricultural sector is a priority of ACC Bank.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Coveney) Avril Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Coveney)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senators on all sides for their support for the Bill.  It is short, technical legislation designed to confirm what most people believe to be the case anyway.</P>
      <P>The Bill does not confer any additional powers on Ministers, the State or the bodies in question in relation to their capital financing.  While a private company can confirm that it has such powers by changing its memorandum and articles of association, the powers of most State bodies are established in statute.  As such, the act of confirmation of powers requires a statute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I indicated earlier, the main bodies involved are the large commercial <Col N="1025" /> State operations.  Given the demands imposed on these bodies to become more efficient, to improve performance and customer services and to deliver services more cost effectively, it would be unacceptable that they could not take advantage of the full range of capital financing instruments which are available in the market.  Senator Dardis referred to that aspect.</P>
    <P>The types of financial instrument covered by the Bill are particularly important in accessing international capital markets.  The removal of restrictions on capital movements between EU member states and between members states and third countries has significantly improved the availability of capital in Ireland.  The development of the financial services centre has also had knock-on effects in that it brought Ireland to the attention of financial institutions worldwide in a manner which makes it easier for Irish companies seeking funds to tap into a much bigger pool of resources than heretofore.</P>
    <P>The Bill will enable these bodies to continue securing cost effective capital to meet their capital financing requirements. I assure Senators that the inclusion of a guarantee provision in the Bill in no way commits the Minister to any increase in State guarantees, nor is it intended to provide any increase in the current level of guaranteed debt. The current policy is that State guarantees are given only where the body in question would otherwise be unable to secure access to credit or where the cost of such credit would be prohibitive. Since 1991, the percentage of commercial semi-State debt guaranteed by the State has fallen from 90 per cent to 60 per cent, or from £4.7 billion to £3.5 billion.  It is expected that this trend will continue, it will be the policy of this Government and, I expect, its successors.</P>
    <P>Senator Daly urged caution in relation to Government borrowing. However, at this point in the year the borrowing requirement, mainly for capital purposes, is expected to be approximately <Col N="1026" /> £150 million less than the forecasted figure of £729 million on budget day.  It appears the figure will be £579 million.  The Government is conscious of the need to contain borrowing levels at or below its stated objectives at the start of the year.  I am anxious to ensure public spending is kept under rigid control. Senator Daly also raised this point. However, some unforeseen problems emerged during the year, primarily in relation to the BSE crisis and the knock-on effects in the beef industry. There are also requirements regarding the measures to deal with crime and in the health area in terms of hepatitis C and these will cost additional money.</P>
    <P>While I give a commitment regarding the Government's determination to maintain strict control on public spending, it would be dishonest not to refer to some of the difficulties which confronts it in that area.  However, there is the overriding consideration of the Maastricht criteria.  It would be irresponsible for a Government to fail to continue to meet or exceed the targets set under those criteria.  The Government is determined to do that and it will.  Although it is a matter of reasonable political debate, it is fair to point out that the Government operates in a prudent financial management mode and will continue to do so.</P>
    <P>Senator Daly also mentioned the temptations facing Governments heading into general elections in relation to spending.  However, we must resist those temptations if going down that road would damage our ability to meet and exceed the Maastricht criteria. Irrespective of an election, there is an imperative on whatever Government is in power to examine the issue of personal taxation in relation to a new national agreement, which is one of many major considerations.  This point must be highlighted in responses to debates about the management of the economy.  It will impact on the overall financial situation but such an examination must be carried out.</P>
    <P>Senator Daly spoke at length about the ACC Bank and its focus on the agricultural <Col N="1027" /> sector.  Senator Burke went further in that regard, but all the contributors mentioned the bank.  It is the case that 35 per cent of ACC Bank's business is focused directly on the agricultural sector; that is the biggest element of its operations.  As Senator Dardis said, the diversification into which the ACC entered has made it a much stronger bank and enhanced its ability to respond to the difficulties in the agricultural sector at present.  I hope it will do so.</P>
    <P>Undoubtedly there is a threat to small family farms and the response of the ACC Bank is a small but significant element in slowing that down and making a contribution in that regard.  Given its tradition and continuing focus on agriculture, the bank will do what it can in that area.</P>
    <P>The less I say about Bord na Móna the better.  It is not relevant to this debate, but the sooner this unseemly public squabble is brought to an end the better for Bord na Móna, its employees and the State.  In so far as a signal can be sent from the House, I agree fully with the comments from all sides about the need to bring the unseemly squabble to an end, today if possible.</P>
    <P>Senator Daly mentioned the ESB's borrowing.  The borrowing of the ESB has fallen.  It was £1,050 million in 1994, dropped to £929 million in 1995 and is scheduled to fall by a further £13 million in 1996.  I will have to write to Senator Daly on the other matter he raised relating to the ESB's ability to borrow for increased generating capacity, which is important.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke also spoke about ACC Bank and I have covered that point.  It is not reasonable that ACC Bank should stick only to agriculture because the problems it had are now solved and it is a much stronger bank as a result of broadening its base.  It is important that the broadening of the base be recognised as being worthwhile.</P>
    <P>On the question of bank charges, one of the most significant aspects is the anger among small businesses on this <Col N="1028" /> issue.  I share that anger.  Two matters will hopefully improve this situation. First, I concur with Senator Dardis's point on competition in banking.  There are undoubtedly beneficial results from this.  I well remember, like the Senator, when the idea of going from one of the two larger banks to the other &mdash; there was not much more available 20 or 30 years ago &mdash; was not an option.  A person would not get a better deal from one than the other.  A duopoly is nearly as bad as a monopoly and that is what was operating.  That has certainly changed and I am happy to see that the banks are willing to cut each others' throats in the interests of the consumer. It is good that there are other players.</P>
    <P>I commend Senator Dardis for resisting the temptation to get deeply involved in third, fourth or fifth banking force arguments.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I apologise for that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>It goes without saying that there are differences in approach between the partners in Government but they are being worked through.  I ask the Senator to believe that none of the parties wants a compromise for the sake of philosophical differences which would not produce a new banking arrangement that increases competition for the consumer's benefit.  I hope that will be the primary result when the proposals are seen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Apart from the beneficial effects of competition on bank charges, the other big event in this area has not had time to show results.  That is the Consumer Credit Act, 1995, which gives the Director of Consumer Affairs very wide and extensive powers to look into every aspect of bank charges.  That came into effect only in May 1996, literally a month and a half ago.  I have very high expectations of it and it should be a mouthwatering subject for the Director of Consumer Affairs and the public.  I encourage the Director, who is independent of me, to involve himself quickly in this area.  To put it mildly, this is a source of irritation not just amongst <Col N="1029" /> businesspeople but all small borrowers. It is probably not reasonable in a competitive market to expect financial institutions to equate very large businesses with small ones because of the economies of scale.  Nonethless, it is widely felt that small businesses and small personal borrowers are bearing a disproportionate amount of bank charges. That is unreasonable and should change.</P>
    <P>I believe that the Director of Consumer Affairs, whose powers in this area are very wide, should also be able to look at currency exchange by banks. This also comes down to what are seen as charges above or below the table.  I agree that one can enter different financial institutions with English or Irish currency and, irrespective of the parity between the two, one seems to finish with the same result.  The story of the man with £100 starting in Dublin and touring the capitals of Europe doing nothing but changing his money is very sobering and the best possible argument for European Monetary Union, to which we are steadfastly committed.  In that area I hope to see advances through competition, by the Director of Consumer Affairs and ultimately by our membership of European Monetary Union.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>How much did the man lose?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot recall the exact figure but it was startling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>He had nothing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We will ask the Minister to give us the answer in ECUs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Dardis speculated on how the requirement for the Bill has come to light.  I do not want to name any particular semi-State body but many of them have access to the best legal advice and those legal advisers are constantly questioning everything.  It is not unusual that this has come up.  It has not been confirmed as <Col N="1030" /> being corrected.  It has just been confirmed that there is a doubt about business between institutions and semi-State bodies.  This Bill ensures that the doubt is removed.</P>
      <P>On the question of how loans are reflected in balance sheets, in company accounts generally the loan principal is counted on the balance sheet.  The interest amount is not.  The treatment of these leases involves a separation of the capital value and a notional interest figure to comply with good accountancy practice.  The definition of finance leases intrigues me.  The simple definition in my opening remarks was much clearer but then that is sometimes the case.  The definition of the finance lease in the Bill is that which is contained in standard accounting practice SSAP 21 and the Minister is satisfied to accept the current standard definition.  However, the Minister reserves the right in subsection (3) to allow the definition of finance lease to evolve in line with accountancy practice.  It would be inappropriate to allow the definition to evolve without some control being exercised nor would it be appropriate to fix the definition and not provide for the continuing evolution of these types of transactions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>We have included the accountants as well as the lawyers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but the current definition SSAP 21 is widely recognised across the whole financial services sector. The other question concerns the Minister consulting with the Central Bank and the possibility that the Minister might ignore or modify the Central Bank's advice.  There was never a question of the Minister taking a decision on the ACC which would be contrary to the advice of the Central Bank, though there is a theoretical possibility that he could, imprudently, do so.  We could discuss this on Committee Stage but I do not think there is a serious problem with it.  It is replicated in the Agricultural Credit Act, 1978, and in the ACC Bank Act, 1994, so it is consistent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1031" /> Senator Calnan also raised the question of exchange rate abuses and I answered that.  What Senator Kiely was describing as possibly a finance lease is in fact a hire purchase agreement and I have mentioned that to him.  He also raised issues about ACC and bank fees and charges which I have already dealt with.  I hope I have covered everything. I thank Members for their contributions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>This side of the House is agreeable to concluding all Stages now if it would facilitate matters.  If Members need a 15 minute recess to consider it.  I am quite agreeable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be very helpful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a matter for the House to decide if it is agreed to take the remaining Stages now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State had given the Leader a commitment to come back into the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State can be absolved of that commitment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>I gave no commitment; nobody asked me to.  It may have been given on my behalf.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take Remaining Stages now.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Borrowing Powers of Certain Bodies" RHead="Bill, 1996: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Borrowing Powers of Certain Bodies Bill, 1996: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="1032" />
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>Does section 3 include local authorities who would borrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Coveney) Avril Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Coveney)</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it does not.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 5 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>The legislation clearly says that the authorisation of a Minister is required for borrowing.  I presume that in some cases where public bodies wish to borrow, depending on the amounts, ministerial authorisation may not be required.  Is there any proposal to rationalise that so that we have a clear indication of who needs authority from a Minister to borrow?  As the Minister is aware, different bodies may be responsible to different Ministers under different Acts of the Oireachas.  Is there any proposal to rationalise this so we could have a clear indication that the same procedure applies to, for instance, the Department of Defence and the Marine and the Department of Enterprise and Employment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>The legislation does not change any of the existing arrangements but there is no proposal in this Bill to rationalise them.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 6 to 8, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 9 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has satisfied me in his reply to my query regarding Central Bank regulations and how they would relate to the Minister's area of <Col N="1033" /> responsibility.  I had a concern about liquidity ratios which are established by the Central Bank and it struck me that it would be possible.  The Minister conceded its theory is such &mdash; I accept that it is more a theoretical possibility than a practical possibility &mdash; that it would be open to the Minister under the legislation to allow the ACC Bank to operate outside the liquidity ratios operating for banks in general.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>I am reminded that the EU laid down mandatory liquidity ratios which bind all financial institutions and it would not, therefore, be open to the Minister to do so.  I can give Senators a categorical assurance that the Minister for Finance would be the last person to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the Minister of State is aware of the comments in the media today in relation to bank charges, indicating that ACC Bank and the TSB have the lowest charges.  While that is very welcome, there is general apprehension at the rates of bank charges.  If people wish to withdraw some of their own cash from their accounts now they have to pay to do so, which is reaching the limit of decency.  I wish to avail of this opportunity to encourage the major banks to take example from Trustee Savings Bank and ACC Bank.  If the smaller banks can reduce charges, bigger banks have a responsibility to act likewise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome Senator Daly's comments in relation to bank charges. State banks should set the standard.  If smaller institutions can do this, the larger banks should be able to do it.  The larger banks are definitely ripping off the smaller individuals and the smaller businesses in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a widely held view both in this House and outside it.  I hope the Director of Consumer Affairs, who only recently became entitled to get involved in this, will do so effectively. Anything that can be done by way of setting a headline from the State <Col N="1034" /> banks is welcome.  However, it is a double edged sword.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I wanted to make an apology to the Minister in the House for introducing a fifth banking force, as if a third banking force was not one too many.  I apologise for getting my terminology mixed up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughCoveney" hpid="Mr. Coveney Mr. Coveney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coveney</NameTxt>
      <P>I was intrigued by that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 10 to 12, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeSherlock" hpid="Mr. Sherlock Mr. Sherlock">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sherlock</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not expert in financial matters but I wish to make a comment from my own experience.  Is as an taithí a bhfaightear an t-eolas, mar a dearfá.  I do not know whether provision has been made for this, but I would like the Minister to address at some stage the various anomalies which arise in the matter of borrowing from the banks and other lending institutions, particularly the local loans fund of the local authority under the Small Dwellings Acquisitions Act, 1957.  It is easy for people to provide protection for their mortgage under a mortgage protection policy, but some of the lending agencies insist on endowment policies which cause hardship for those making the repayments. An endowment mortgage adds a colossal amount to the borrowing repayments as I know from experience. People are showing greater interest in credit union borrowing and the five year restriction on such borrowing should be changed as a matter of urgency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive reply to questions raised on Second Stage and compliment him, his officials and advisers for the expeditious way in which they dealt with the legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1035" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I also thank the Minister of State.  We have expedited the passage of the Bill through the House by virtue of the fact that he dealt comprehensively with our questions.  I hope the legislation will be successful and the money he is providing will be available when I approach the ACC bank for a loan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State and his staff for dealing with the Bill in an expeditious manner.  I also thank him for answering our questions on Second Stage as this meant there was no need to enter a detailed debate on Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelCalnan" hpid="Mr. Calnan Mr. Calnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calnan</NameTxt>
      <P>I compliment the Minister of State on his handling of the Bill and thank him for dealing with it in such a speedy fashion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AvrilDoyle" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Coveney) Avril Doyle">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. Coveney)</NameTxt>
      <P>I first saw this Bill early this morning and equipped myself as best I could to deal with it.  Members were very reasonable regarding the questions they raised.  I am delighted the House agreed to take all stages of the Bill.  I wish our business could always be completed so efficiently.  There is a clear need for this legislation and Members immediately grasped the fact that it is not controversial and facilitated its passage.  I am grateful for that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 12.35 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Metrology Bill, 1996:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Metrology Bill, 1996: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 to 6, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 1 and 5 are related and both may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1036" />
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 8, subsection (3), line 42, after &ldquo;include&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;a person suitably qualified to the satisfaction of the Minister and approved by him or her to be&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise and Employment (Mr. Rabbitte) Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise and Employment (Mr. Rabbitte)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise and Employment (Mr. Rabbitte)</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Haughey's amendment seems to have been tabled for clarification purposes and, having studied it, I believe the purpose he seeks to achieve is provided for in the section. The suitability of the person appointed to be the director of legal metrology shall, in accordance with section 7(4), be a matter for the board of Forbairt in the first instance.  However, when the appointment made by the board goes to the Minister for approval, the appointee shall hold office on such terms and conditions as the board with the concurrence of the Minister and the Minister for Finance may approve.  The proposed procedures are those which currently apply to similar type appointments, thus in effect the requirement proposed by Senator Haughey is already comprehended in the proposed appointment arrangements.  In the circumstances, therefore, the amendment is unnecessary since the purpose behind it is met.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I disagree with the Minister's comments because this section does not provide for the qualifications of the person to be appointed.  If we accept this section, anybody will be able to apply for the job and be appointed, not on merit but perhaps on political favour.  The Minister then makes the appointment.  My amendment is fair and makes the situation foolproof.  It will also improve the quality of those in the public service.  It would mandate them to reach a standard acceptable to the Minister, the political representative, who is responsible to the House for decisions he makes.  I am sure he will make a decision in the best interest of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1037" />
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>The point Senator Haughey has raised concerns suitability in terms of the qualifications of the director of the service.  The Senator will appreciate that since the decision to refer a name to the Minister for approval is one for the board of Forbairt, it would be difficult to see a situation where it would appoint to the position of director of the legal metrology service somebody who was not equipped to do the job.  The interview and appointment process will have taken place at that stage.  A name is submitted to the Minister, who may disapprove it and require another to be forwarded to him.  Whatever about the question of political complexion, which is not an unknown phenomenon in the culture of Irish politics, I cannot conceive of a situation where somebody would be appointed director of this service without the requisite qualification. That is comprehended in the section as it stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>As someone who is politically anaemic in terms of complexion, although not in real life, I would like clarification on this issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is never anaemic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be helpful if the Minister outlined the qualifications and experience which would be sought. Senator Haughey has raised a point of merit which needs to be teased out.  The Senator's point is valid in that an appointment could be made by the Minister without any checks or balances being built into the process.  We need reassurances as regards how a person will be sought and appointed, the qualifications and experience required and the person's background.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>The provision whereby the decision is taken away from the Minister is good.  It is proper that the board of Forbairt should make the decision.  Without wandering into current <Col N="1038" /> controversy, a board appointed to do a job on behalf of the State ought to have the power to do that job as it sees fit.  I am not sure if Senator O'Toole or Senator Haughey are going back to first principles and querying the appointment and competence of boards, but if one wants to appoint a secretary-manager of a hospital one does not seek candidates in the local abattoir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not rule it out either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>The normal procedures within the public service, with which we are familiar, apply.  Terms of reference are drawn up for the job.  They set out what qualifications are required and what will be expected of the person who will head the metrology service.  The post will be advertised and appointment will be made presumably by the interview board on recommendation to the board of Forbairt.  At that stage it will be referred to the Minister and he or she may approve or disapprove.  The Minister does not make the selection.</P>
      <P>Theoretically the Minister could keep referring the appointment back but that is somewhat unlikely.  It will be the normal process &mdash; preparation of the job specification, stipulation of the qualifications required, selection of candidates for the post, appointment by interview board by recommendation to the board of Forbairt, approval of the name by the board and the name being forwarded to the Minister.  The process is at arm's length from the Minister and that is desirable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanDaly" hpid="Mr. Daly Mr. Daly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Daly</NameTxt>
      <P>Will this be a new appointment or will somebody be seconded to the position from the existing service?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know and it is right that I do not know.  The terms of reference will be set out in the job specification in terms of the qualifications required.  Without knowing anything about it, I expect it will be somebody already in the service.  However, that is <Col N="1039" /> a matter for the interview board and the board of Forbairt.  We are seeking to create a unitary service to replace the present run-down and fragmented service. That is not a comment on the efficacy with which the job has been done by people in the service, but the service has become run-down and there is an investment programme planned. Indeed, much of the investment has already been made.</P>
      <P>It is likely that somebody from the service will be appointed but I do not know if that will be the case and it is right that I do not know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the amendment is <i>ex abundanti cautela</i>, for supreme caution.  As time progresses the quality of and qualifications for the job will change.  Technology will also change.  The Minister's approval is not mandatory in the Bill; he or she is only given discretion.  Civil servants and the board need direction from the Minister of the day.  Giving this right to the Minister and enshrining it in legislation makes sense and does not put cumbersome problems in the way of the board. It means the Minister can say he wants somebody with a PhD in a certain subject if he so wishes.  The amendment facilitates the Minister giving the board direction in this matter and that is a sensible step.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Surely it is sensible, given the present difficulties in public bodies, that the Minister of the day has the final say as to whether somebody is appointed or measures up to the specifications.  It <Col N="1040" /> would save a great deal of embarrassment if, in advance of the process, the board asks the Minister what standard he or she wishes to achieve in the appointment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree it is sensible that before the appointment is confirmed the board and the Minister ought to be satisfied the person is appropriately qualified to discharge the duties of the post.  However, the parliamentary draftsman confirmed to me this morning that the sections as drafted provide for that.  There is an automatic inference to be drawn from the relevant section that the person appointed will be suitable.</P>
      <P>The job specification can be put to the Minister in advance of an appointment. The details of the qualifications required will be set out in the job specification. The post will be advertised and the assessment will be made by people who are competent to judge.  I would not be competent to judge whether somebody would be a suitable director of the Legal Metrology Service.  I might have an idea of who would manifestly not be qualified but I doubt that I am competent to say if somebody is qualified. If a PhD in the science of measurement is required it should be specified in the job specification.</P>
      <P>Senator Haughey has asserted his argument that the person must be suitably qualified.  The intention of the legislation is that the director will be somebody with the necessary qualifications to perform the director's functions.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 15; Níl, 20.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Byrne, Seán.<br />Daly, Brendan.<br />Dardis, John.<br />Finneran, Michael.<br />Fitzgerald Tom.<br />Haughey Edward.<br />Honan, Cathy.<br />Kelleher, Billy.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kiely, Rory.<br />Lanigan, Mick.<br />McGennis, Marian.<br />Mullooly, Brian.<br />O'Brien, Francis.<br />O'Kennedy, Michael.<br />Wright, G.V.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="1041" />Belton, Louis J.<br />Burke, Paddy.<br />Calnan, Michael.<br />Cosgrave, Liam.<br />Cotter, Bill.<br />D'Arcy, Michael.<br />Doyle, Joe.<br />Enright, Thomas W.<br />Farrelly, John V.<br />Howard, Michael.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="1042" />Kelly, Mary.<br />McDonagh, Jarlath.<br />Magner, Pat.<br />Maloney, Sean.<br />Manning, Maurice.<br />Norris, David.<br />O'Sullivan, Jan.<br />Quinn, Feargal.<br />Townsend, Jim.<br />Wall, Jack.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Fitzgerald and Haughey; Níl, Senators Senators Cosgrave and Magner.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <P>Section 7 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 8.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 2 has been substituted by amendment 2a. Amendment No. 3 is related and amendment No. 4 is an alternative and all may be discussed together.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 2 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2a:</P>
      <P>In page 9, between lines 15 and 16, to insert the following subsection:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(2) A person who, being a member of the Garda Síochána, accepts employment in Forfás under subsection (1) may, with the consent of the Minister for Justice, be appointed and enrolled as a member of the Garda Síochána within a period of 18 months from the date of enactment of this Act and thereupon such employment shall cease.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>In proposing this amendment, I inadvertently omitted Senator Norris's name as seconder.  This amendment is about people.  This is the issue of concern to Members on both sides of the House. We are talking about the careers and expectations of people who have given time&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I thought I was being facetious on the Order of Business yesterday and the day before when I talked about metrology and mentioned that people in the country&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator have a point of order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>The point of order is that on the monitors it states the &ldquo;Meteorology&rdquo; Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MickLanigan" hpid="Mr. Lanigan Mr. Lanigan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lanigan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are discussing the Metrology Bill and the monitors say the &ldquo;Meteorology&rdquo; Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Lanigan for that illumination.  It will change the complexion of the debate.  I will ask the Minister to bear it in mind and the next time he should do a four page explanation instead of two pages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a load of <i>Aurora Borealis.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>It will not make any difference to some whether it is two or four.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>The reaction to this legislation has been positive.  It is a necessary consolidation and development which reflects changing times when people want the Garda to be more focused on their core work.  There is no <Col N="1043" /> objection to the main changes proposed. In this situation however, people joined the Force, distinguished themselves to the point of achieving promotion and then moved into this specialised area. This is far from being the most popular job in the Garda.  It is a job where somebody has to tell a Dublin taxi driver that the meter is not working properly and needs to be corrected, a publican that his glasses are not legal measure or a butcher that his scales are not giving the correct weight, etc.  It is a tense job where there is abuse.  The other equivalent public service would be a vet telling a farmer he had a reactor cow in the herd.  They do not bring the most welcome news.  They have handled themselves with distinction, courage and commitment over the years, so there is an understanding that people can have trust in the system and weights and measures.  They have done this through various changes, including metrication since joining the EU.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I use this lead-in because I want the Minister to consider my amendment not just in the cold terms of the officials in the Department of Justice.  This is not about lines of legislation and theory. This is about people, the management of change and recognising how best to implement it.  One of the best ways of encouraging change and giving people the courage to move towards it is to give them guarantees regarding their current situation, which they deserve.  For that reason I raised a certain number of proposals on Second Stage in relation to garda sergeants being seconded to Forfás for a period of three years, at the end of which their secondment would finish and they would go back to the Garda or decide to stay on.  That was reasonable.  I raised this matter with the Minister and officials from the Department of Justice.  I have difficulty accepting the objections of that Department, that secondment means a person is working in a different job and not under the control of the commissioner, but because they are still a garda they are still under the control of the commissioner. <Col N="1044" /> The officials in the Department of Justice are looking at the management of change as it affects people on the ground not as it affects people at all levels, including themselves.  The management of change also means change at departmental and legislative level.  There has to be fluidity and flexibility in this matter.</P>
    <P>I think the Minister pointed out on Second Stage that secondments do not take place.  I cannot quote chapter and verse on this but there may have been exceptions over the years.  I checked the UN connection, on which I was incorrect. I accept that groups working with the UN have transferred as a portion of the force that still has a clear chain of command.  I am not so sure about individual members of the force who have occasionally been seconded to work with the UN.  It has been drawn to my attention that in the 1950s sergeants of weights and measures worked with the Garda as part of Dublin Corporation.  I do not know the details.  It may be that officials in the Department of Justice will find some nuance of difference between that and what I propose.  I have also listened to the different kinds of approach.  I did propose deferring the establishment date for certain people.  It was pointed out to me that this legislation could create a conflict between it and the legislation in the 1920s for the establishment for An Garda Síochána.  I do not accept this fully.  I believe legislators legislate.  If legislation today is different from that of 60 years ago, that is the way it must be.  We do that all the time and it is a matter not of conflict but of change, which must be accommodated in legislation.</P>
    <P>I have given a long-winded justification of amendment No. 2a, which I propose with something less than enthusiasm.  I move it because I wish to meet the Department of Justice's objections to the secondment provision in my original amendment No. 2.  Although I do not accept most of the objections, I recognise the integrity of the people making the case and cannot discount their views.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1045" /> In recognition of this I have taken three steps backwards to accommodate the Minister.  First, I have changed this from a provision on secondment to an opportunity to revert to the Garda Síochána &mdash; that is not a major change. Second, I halved the period from three years to 18 months.  None of these people will revert to the Garda, because once they become established in a new place they will get the feel of it, make it their own and develop it until it becomes part of them.  It is not important whether the period is 18 months or three years because the people concerned will have made up their minds in that time as to whether they want to stay or go.  The other reason I chose 18 months was that a short period would be tempting to the Minister.  It is like the difference between a half-pint and a &ldquo;meejum&rdquo; which we discussed on Second Stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>Half-full or half-empty?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is neither half-pint nor pint but &ldquo;meejum&rdquo; legislation. The various Ministers of Government have been described as &ldquo;half cars&rdquo; and &ldquo;full cars&rdquo; or half-Ministers and full Ministers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Paris seems an appropriate image in the circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>That begs the question as to what one would call the Minister, Deputy Rabbitte, who sits at the Cabinet table but is neither a full Minister nor a half-Minister.  Perhaps he is a &ldquo;meejum&rdquo; Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we should return to the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an appropriate image for a man who supports that measurement.  I am trying to find a middle line to allow the Minister respond to the issues I have put forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have much more difficulty on the third point.  I recognise, although I was <Col N="1046" /> not prepared to say so until now, that the Minister for Justice is ultimately responsible and she must indicate whether the person may revert to the Garda.  I put the amendment forward on the understanding that this would operate in an open and honest fashion if it were accepted.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to accept the amendment and I have given good reasons for doing so.  I also ask him to indicate that it could be implemented in a fair way.  It does not meet every aspect of the arguments against my original amendment by the Department of Justice but it meets all of them to some extent.  Most importantly, it meets the needs of people doing a decent job. During a tetchy afternoon yesterday, we spoke at length about recognising the value and contribution of public servants. This amendment is a small step to ask the Minister to take.  It requires a change and would mean that the Department of Justice would have to swallow hard.  Even so, is it not worthwhile that we arrive at change through a consensual approach?  It would be good if we could do so after yesterday's debate.</P>
    <P>I urge the Minister to show magnanimity in this respect, to recognise the movement I have made in the substitute amendment and to acknowledge the worth of those who have done this work, which is not highly valued by society but underpins much of the retail activity of the State.  I appeal to the Minister to accept this, as someone who, like myself, has come through the business of negotiation and knows that where people differ they must eventually find a middle line.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister confirmed to the House on Tuesday that agreement has not been reached with employees of Dublin Corporation and the quality control officers, which is why I put down amendment No. 4.  It would be a travesty of justice if the legislation remained as it was, because it would force these people to accept what has happened.  As it stands, the provisions <Col N="1047" /> of section 8 (2) apply &ldquo;save in accordance with a collective agreement negotiated with any recognised trade union or staff association concerned&rdquo;.  As no agreement has been reached, this will give rise to enormous problems.  That phrase serves no useful purpose other than to coerce people and put them at a disadvantage.</P>
      <P>Both my amendment and Senator O'Toole's original amendment provide for secondment.  That is reversible &mdash; a person can be seconded for a period, which is not specified in the Bill, and in law the person can go back at any time. It is unfair that some men worked up to 30 years in a certain section, remained at the level of sergeant and were prevented for gaining promotion because of the legislation.</P>
      <P>These people have worked in one section but they are members of the Garda Síochána so they have terms and conditions, pay and pension rights which are different from those of the people they work alongside.  They should not be deprived of the rights which apply to their colleagues.  For instance, others in the section may be able to work until they are 60 but these gentlemen must retire at 57.</P>
      <P>I will agree to Senator O'Toole's amendment if the Minister agrees to my amendment to accommodate the people from Dublin Corporation and the quality control department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnDardis" hpid="Mr. Dardis Mr. Dardis">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dardis</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator O'Toole's amendment.  If someone joins the Garda at a young age, he does so as a career choice.  His expectation is that he will be in that career until he retires. In many senses it is a vocation.  The issue may seem unimportant but it is important in that context.  The people involved regard themselves as members of the Garda and a means of accommodating them should be found.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a precedent the Minister of State might examine which happened with the Milk (Regulation of Supply) Bill, 1994.  When that Bill was first introduced in 1992 people who were working <Col N="1048" /> for the Dublin District Milk Board had serious concerns about their status. Their concerns were taken into account, the Bill was withdrawn and reintroduced about 18 months later on the basis of negotiations which led to the employees' concerns being addressed. The Minister of State could take that precedent on board in this instance because it seems to be a closely allied case.</P>
    <P>It is a question of not just human rights but of generosity.  There are not many people involved and in the circumstances the Government should adopt a generous approach.  Senator O'Toole talked about the medium way; perhaps, in the context of metrology, we should say the median way.  The Minister of State should accept amendment No. 2a.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator O'Toole gave a well reasoned explanation for amendment No. 2a.  He described himself as being politically anaemic which was an error on his part.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Not enough carrots.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>In this amendment he diluted his original proposal to meet the problems related to this issue.  From a human point of view, we would like to accommodate the individuals affected.  I do not know if such a provision in this Bill would be compatible with the Garda Acts.</P>
      <P>I am unclear as to what exactly Senator O'Toole proposes.  Will the members involved leave the Garda Síochána, work for Forfás for up to 18 months and then rejoin the Garda?  The Senator's amendment states &ldquo;... with the consent of the Minister for Justice, be appointed and enrolled as a member of the Garda Síochána ...&rdquo;.  Presumably, they would have to know they would get that consent before they left to join Forfás, rather than 18 months later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1049" />
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator O'Toole's amendment.  I imagine he has a receptive audience in the Minister of State who, like Senator O'Toole, has a distinguished record as a trade unionist. I have no doubt he will feel sympathy for this small number of officials affected by this.  This is not a large problem and it would not cost a huge amount of money to resolve.  It is also a finite problem because we are dealing with a transitional stage.</P>
      <P>The amendment allows for somebody who is a member of the Garda to accept employment with Forfás and he may, with the consent of the Minister for Justice, be appointed and enrolled as a member of the Garda Síochána within a period of 18 months of the date of enactment of this Bill and, thereupon, such employment shall cease.  This allows a way out.</P>
      <P>I have a good deal of fellow feeling with the people in this situation because I have been granted a form of early retirement, a kind of permanent disability benefit, which means I get a pension of sorts.  However, always lurking at the back of my mind is the awful threat of a return to full health and being stuck back in the college for the sake of an undivided Trinity marking exams, to which I would not look forward. Having been out for nearly three years, it would be an appalling psychological shock to be forced to attend departmental meetings and ghastly academic huddles.  I shall do everything I can to be as sick as the Act under which I receive my pittance requires.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Thus, I have a great deal of sympathy with the men involved.  It is difficult to readjust.  If they feel a strong loyalty and association with the Garda Síochána, allowing a possibility of a return in a transitional phase is a good measure. Senator O'Toole has made the point that their task is somewhat thankless. They have to investigate matters of standards, taximeters, etc., and may have to give people unwelcome news.  I know and get on very well with some taxi drivers because they go the same inner city gym that I use.  I assure the <Col N="1050" /> House I would not relish being invited to put them in their place because they are very ready of tongue.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Toole was deprived of his rhetorical flourish.  However, I invite the Minister of State to be a man, bite the carrot and bugger the Department of Justice.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanFallon" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure what that has to do with the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>How can one follow Senator Norris's impassioned plea? Senator O'Sullivan mentioned that we have to have sympathy in terms of the human issue involved.  I agree.  We have sympathy for these 20 people who have devoted their lives to this task and are highly regarded.  I have heard not a word of criticism of them, only praise. We must be careful to act sympathetically.</P>
      <P>That said, the question foremost in my mind is crime.  As I understand it, the Garda authorities are unhappy with the arrangements proposed in terms of their fight against crime if they lose 20 places they had thought they would fill with crime fighters.  If, the sympathetic approach we seek, would shackle the Garda authorities in their efforts to fight crime we should stop and think carefully before we act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister of State must be sympathetic in this instance.  Senator O'Toole referred to consensus. I am concerned that in the past when seeking consensus we sometimes made errors that placed us in the position where we now have the current crime problem.  I hope the Minister of State will put my mind at rest by saying that if these are going to be on secondment &mdash; and it is an ideal solution and I support the concept &mdash; the jobs will be filled by people capable of fighting crime and that any steps taken to accept this amendment will not hamper, hinder or shackle the Garda authorities in their efforts to fight crime.  Let us make sure that we continue the fight against crime. <Col N="1051" /> Action is being taken and the Government is committed.  I would like to ensure that it is not weakened by any action we take in full sympathy for the human issue involved.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnVFarrelly" hpid="Mr. Farrelly Mr. Farrelly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farrelly</NameTxt>
      <P>We would all like to ensure we will not do something that we will regret, considering that there are only a few people involved.  It was mentioned on Second Stage that nobody ever had any complaints through the years about the work these gardaí did, which they performed professionally.  I hope the Minister of State may be in a position to accept the amendment because there are two issues here. Senator Quinn said the Department of Justice might say that they have 20 more gardaí involved in fight againse crime. That may be the case but surely we must look at the period of time they have been doing their current job.  If there are changes to be made, they can be made over the period of time between these individuals reaching retirement and the new people carrying out this work being employed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Dardis mentioned negotiations and the withdrawal of the Milk Board Bill.  I was involved in that.  Lengthy negotiations took place after it was withdrawn but there were 18 months of negotiations involved before this legislation arrived here.  It would not be true to say that there were not lengthy negotiations. I hope the Minister of State can ensure, on the basis of amendment No. 2a being accepted as a reasonable compromise for the people involved, that we are not seen not to look after 20 people.  These people have for most of their careers been carrying out a specific job and, as Senator O'Toole said, it is hard to adapt to change.  Those Senators who have been in the teaching profession for years and have had the opportunity to enter these Houses would find it hard to readapt if they have been here for a number of years; all of us would be in a similar position. On that basis, I look forward to the <Col N="1052" /> Minister of State's contribution.  Perhaps we can come to a reasonable compromise on the issue.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Members who have contributed on these amendments. Senator Haughey and I are fundamentally at cross purposes on his amendment No. 3.  There is a misunderstanding of the import of the words which Senator Haughey is seeking to excise.</P>
      <P>The purpose of the words that Senator Haughey seeks to excise is to achieve the opposite of what he said in his contribution.  The effect of a decision to excise &ldquo;save in accordance with a collective agreement negotiated with any recognised trade union or staff association concerned&rdquo; would be to undermine the trade unions, not just the Garda sergeants representative organisation but IMPACT and trade unions representing other staffs.  If there is a voluntary collective agreement, either between that Garda sergeants association or between IMPACT and the management, it should be enforced.  It is only in circumstances where that does not apply that the provisions of that section apply.  If people voluntarily decide that on consideration it is better for them, voluntarily and by negotiation, to agree to conceding something here for something better there, we should leave them that right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The clause which the Senator seeks to delete is fundamental to the conduct of normal industrial relations.  It provides the structure for the orderly conduct of negotiations between employer and employee.  If the amendment were accepted it would permit the exclusion of recognised trade unions or staff associations from any further role in representing the interests of their members in this reorganisation.  I am sure that the Senator intended the opposite.  This has not been the case up until now and it would be unacceptable to me, the trade union movement, Forbairt, who will operate the new service, and to most Members of this House, including Senator Haughey.  Garda seratio <Col N="1053" /> geants are currently represented by the Association of Garda Sergeants and Inspectors and IMPACT represents the local authority and departmental staff involved.  For that reason, I cannot accept that amendment and I ask the Senator to reflect on it.  It is peculiar drafting language that gives the opposite meaning to its intent.  It is an important safeguard in terms of acknowledging&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>What happens if agreement is not reached and the legislation comes into play?  That is my concern. Would that not force the representative bodies to enter into an agreement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so.  I have met IMPACT representatives and the issues they are prosecuting are the normal trade union issues which they would be prosecuting in any event.  I accept that in the case of the Garda sergeants it is a distinct and different issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there agreement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>There is.  I can reassure the Senator on that.  On amendment No. 2a, Senators will be aware that the issue of secondment of Garda sergeant <i>ex-officio</i> inspectors of weights and measures has been tossed about several times over the past couple of months.  I have explored a number of avenues to see if some resolution can be found which would accommodate the concerns of the gardaí involved and I have met several of them.  I have on a number of occasions alluded to the fact that an agreement was reached with the Association of Garda Sergeants and Inspectors last January.  The agreement, copper-fastened by the guarantees in this Bill, provides that the Garda sergeants will retain their existing pay and conditions on a personal basis.  They will also maintain a link with pay developments for the Garda sergeant grade as well as retaining other conditions including <Col N="1054" /> annual leave, bank holiday work and security of employment.</P>
      <P>I am aware of the nervousness these people are experiencing about joining a new organisation.  However, the transfer of staff to the new service has been the subject of thorough and well considered discussions with their representative association through the established procedures of the conciliation and arbitration scheme of the Department of Justice.  This is the recognised channel through which the vast majority of issues affecting members of the Garda Síochána are negotiated, and it would be unwise for this House to get into the business of second guessing the normal industrial relations machinery.</P>
      <P>In the interests of keeping the temperature down, perhaps I should not read out the rest of my note.  The situation is very difficult and it has nothing to do with not recognising the job done by these people over the last 25 or 30 years.</P>
      <P>The milk supply board is not a helpful precedent, if it was I would easily accede to Senator O'Toole's request, not to mention his lucid argument, because it would be normal that, where restructuring like this takes place, the substance of Senator O'Toole's remarks should be accepted.  The case of the milk supply board involved civilians but we are not dealing with civilian staff here, that was the impediment from day one, if it had not been we would have resolved the matter long ago.</P>
      <P>Kind things were said about me and my background and some not so kind things about me being a &ldquo;meejum&rdquo; Minister.  I would never accept being a &ldquo;meejum&rdquo; Minister but I must accept the term &ldquo;medium&rdquo;, unfortunately.  I would have been quite amenable to accepting it but it is fundamentally a matter for the Minister for Justice, for precedent under the Garda regulations and Garda Acts, and of the chain of command to the Garda Commissioner. I have not yet found a precedent where that has been departed from and that really is the nub of the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Quinn raised a question <Col N="1055" /> which was in my mind for some time in trying to establish the real objections to all this.  It seemed at one stage that by the transfer of these 21 Garda sergeants the Garda Commissioner is free to increase his crime fighting team by 21 without increasing the quota.  I am not sure that it is actually the case.  The essence of the matter is that the sergeants concerned have not been concerned with crime-fighting during the course of discharging their functions. The posts have probably been filled as they have been gradually eroded over the years in any event.</P>
    <P>The Department understands that Garda sergeant posts which have become vacant since the commencement of the reorganisation of the service in 1991 have been reallocated to normal Garda duties.  The number entailed is about 25.  Thus, there has already been a switch from civilian duties to more conventional Garda activities.  Therefore, I can probably reassure Senator Quinn that it would be slightly disingenuous of me to shelter behind that in trying to defend myself against Senator O'Toole's onslaught.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a reasonable request.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DavidNorris" hpid="Mr. Norris Mr. Norris">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norris</NameTxt>
      <P>Carrot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I withdraw that.</P>
      <P>The three steps backward to which Senator O'Toole referred from his original amendment, secondment narrowing the window from three years to 18 months and the fact that it would be irresistible to me are, I admit, compelling arguments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, I am concerned, and humbly submit that Senator O'Toole ought to be concerned too, about effectively undermining a decision of the conciliation and arbitration scheme within the Garda service.  An important point which must be underlined is that this has been through the mill and has been in negotiation for a very long time.  The people representing the Garda sergeants <Col N="1056" /> concerned agreed on their behalf to what is now given expression in the Bill. That is not challenged by anybody.  It is a voluntary agreement to which I am not a party and I do not want to get into speculating about how the Association of Garda Sergeants and Inspectors does its business, how it communicates with its members, etc.  Officially, agreement was reached in the negotiations.  We seem to have been engaging in a rethink and if I accept Senator O'Toole's amendment, I am, in effect, second guessing that agreement and undermining a registered agreement.  I have some concerns about that.</P>
    <P>I repeat that this is not because of a lack of recognition on my part or that of the Government of the work of the people concerned, nor, I assure Senator Norris, was it my intention to discomfit his life in the inner city gym as I would not wish to do that.  Certainly, the appalling vista of a full recovery to health is something I do not wish on Senator Norris either.</P>
    <P>The fact of the matter is that we are dealing with the creation of a precedent. Senator O'Toole invited the House to act as legislators &mdash; we make the law and let the relevant organs of the State implement it.  I suppose it is hard to resist that argument.  I find it even more difficult to resist Senator Norris's invitation to be a man, bite the carrot and bugger the Department of Justice. Whatever about the third element of that invitation, I certainly find the first two almost irresistible.  I am probably left with no alternative, given the arguments which have been advanced and notwithstanding the disquiet which I expressed earlier, but to accept the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeOToole" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I am shocked almost into silence.  I had a grand speech prepared about the fact that we were not undermining but rather improving the conditions of the conciliation and arbitration decision.  We had dealt with the secondment argument by getting rid of secondment.  The Garda and civilian reference was also addressed.  It is a good <Col N="1057" /> thing to establish precedent.  Every day we establish a precedent we know we are implementing change.</P>
      <P>I express my gratitude to the Minister as this matter has been difficult.  It is an important step forward.  It is important for these people in that it is a vote of confidence in them and an encouragement. I am delighted the amendment has been accepted.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 3 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
      <P>In page 9, subsection (2), line 22, after &ldquo;day.&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;Any member of the Garda Síochána transferring to Forfás for the purpose of this Act shall be deemed to be seconded only.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Section 8, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 5 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 9 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 6:</P>
      <P>In page 12, subsection (7)(b), line 18, after &ldquo;information&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;or item relevant to this legislation which he or she has within his or her possession, knowledge or under his or her control&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>The powers of inspectors provided for in the earlier subsections of this section are extensive.  In regard to this amendment, section 10(1)(g) and section 10(4) are relevant. An inspector may require the owner, person in charge or any employee of the <Col N="1058" /> place entered, to provide all reasonable assistance, including personal assistance, books, records or other documents to enable the inspector to carry out functions under this Act.  An inspector may seize or retain any article, instrument, stamp, goods or documents which he reasonably believes to be in contravention of the Acts.</P>
      <P>Subsection (7)(b) strengthens the power contained in section 10(1)(g) in relation to providing co-operation and assistance by those being inspected.  For example, in testing a large weighing instrument at a factory premises, an inspector may require manual assistance to operate the instrument under test or to help lift standard weights or equipment used to carry out the test.  There is a duty on the owner or manager of the business to provide this assistance.</P>
      <P>The items in which an inspector would have a primary interest are measuring instruments of goods and associated books, records and documents relating to instruments or goods.  The Bill already provides adequate powers for gaining access to, inspecting and seizing such items.  In addition, any article may, under section 10(4), be seized and retained.  Therefore, this amendment is unnecessary and I regret I cannot accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of State and I are at one on the purposes of the amendment.  Perhaps, in subsection (7)(b) the wording &ldquo;assistance or information&rdquo; is an error and should read &ldquo;assistance and information&rdquo;.  According to the present wording, it could be construed that if he gives his assistance he does not have to give the information. Now that the Minister of State has clarified that this is strengthened in other sections, I am quite happy about that.  However, an electric meter can be slowed down by a magnet which is not on the premises but some distance away from it.  Use of such instruments were the reason I tabled this amendment.  I am not sure that is accommodated in the section the Minister of State mentioned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1059" />
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Haughey.  We are <i>ad idem</i> in terms of this item.  It is our view, and our advice from the draftsman's office, that the earlier section includes any such definition. However, the Senator may be right in respect of subsection (7)(b) which states &ldquo;fails, without reasonable cause to give an inspector any such assistance or information&rdquo;.  He may be right that it should read &ldquo;and information&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We appear to be dealing with the section rather than the amendment.  I would prefer to dispose of the amendment and then deal with the section.  That issue appears to arise from the section rather than from the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>My disposition is that Senator Haughey may be right in regard to the second matter he raised.  In regard to the amendment, it is our advice that the import of what he wishes to give expression to is already in the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to suggest that because we are going directly from Committee to Report Stage and I do not have time to take advice on this&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister of State, wishes we could adjourn for a short interval between Committee and Report Stages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to suggest to Senator Haughey that we use the wording &ldquo;assistance and/or information&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>That is acceptable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister of State formally moving that amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>If the House is agreeable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1060" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 7:</P>
      <P>In page 12, between lines 24 and 25, to insert a new subsection as follows;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(8) For the purposes of <i>subsection (7),</i> 'a person' shall be deemed to mean one or more persons.&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>It was not quite clear whether &ldquo;a person&rdquo; was defined.  My concern was whether there was accommodation for a number of people being involved.  I could not see that in the Bill, which is why I tabled this amendment.  I would like to hear the Minister of State's views on this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Mr. Rabbitte Mr. Rabbitte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Rabbitte</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept what Senator Haughey said.  The problem is a technical one.  As I understand it from the parliamentary draftsman's office, the way in which it is framed in the Bill is the normal way for such matters to be given expression in legislation.</P>
      <P>The reference to &ldquo;person&rdquo; in subsection (7) already embraces the thrust of Senator Haughey's amendment.  In legal terms &ldquo;persons&rdquo; are of two kinds, natural and artificial.  A natural person is a human being and an artificial person is a collection or succession of natural persons forming a corporation.  Section 11(A) of the Interpretation Act, 1937, provides that every word importing the singular shall, unless the contrary intention appears, be construed as if it also imported the plural, and every word importing the plural shall, unless the contrary intention appears, be construed as if it also imported the singular. The clarification and statutory basis is already there.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 10, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 11 to 34, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>First Schedule agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1061" /> Second Schedule agreed to.</P>
    <P>Third Schedule agreed to.</P>
    <P>Title agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported with amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardHaughey" hpid="Mr. Haughey Mr. Haughey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Haughey</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State for his courtesy and co-operation, both in respect of one small item and on the major issue of the Garda Síochána. We are all agreed on producing better legislation and getting more people to co-operate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanOSullivan" hpid="Ms O'Sullivan Ms O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Ms O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister of State, especially for the way in which he accommodated the amendment this afternoon.  A form of words was eventually found to deal with the specific aspects of the Bill which caused problems.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I compliment the Minister of State.  It is always a pleasure to have him attend the House because he brings a certain flair and style, even to a Bill such as this.  It was a good and useful debate.  I am pleased he accepted the amendment for which Senator O'Toole and others argued so strongly. It is good that he can have an open mind on such matters and that he will return to the House next week.  I also compliment Senator Haughey on the fair minded and meticulous way in which he steered this, his first major legislation, through the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatRabbitte" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise and Employment (Mr. Rabbitte) Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise and Employment (Mr. Rabbitte)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise and Employment (Mr. Rabbitte)</NameTxt>
      <P>I express my appreciation to all Members of the House, especially to the Opposition spokespersons, including Senator Haughey, for the manner in which they dealt with this legislation. The Bill is improved as a result of the scrutiny it has undergone in this House. The amendment constructed by some <Col N="1062" /> Senators on the Opposition benches has provided a solution that eluded us in the other House.  If I have a residual regret it is that I must return to the Dáil to copperfasten what has been agreed here today.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Message" RHead="from Dáil">
    <Title>Message from Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has agreed to the amendments by Seanad Éireann to the Transport (Dublin Light Rail) (No. 2) Bill, 1996.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Tuesday at 2.30 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Matter. -" RHead="Roscommon Water Supply Scheme">
    <Title>Adjournment Matter. - Roscommon Water Supply Scheme.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose to share my time with Senator Mullooly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomFitzgerald" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald) Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelFinneranFF" hpid="Mr. Finneran Mr. Finneran">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finneran</NameTxt>
      <P>An application for the Ballagh-Ballybeg group water scheme has been with the Department of the Environment since 1993 to construct approximately 14 miles of a mains that would service the main line that would replace these two originally proposed water schemes.  The mains would provide for approximately 200 connections between houses and farms and would also service four schools.  Many smaller group schemes need to be constructed off this mains but they cannot proceed without the sanction and construction of the mains pipe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The two schemes, now combined, will service a mostly rural area south-east of Strokestown, covering the rural Ballybeg and Ballagh areas.  However, the <Col N="1063" /> Ballagh portion of the scheme cannot proceed without the Ballybeg scheme being in place.  It was logical to put a new proposal to the Department for a mains to enable the smaller group schemes to proceed.  Roscommon County Council adopted this proposal in 1993 and the people of the area accepted that it was a good one.  The scheme will link to the north eastern regional water scheme at Ballyfeeney and will service both schemes.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, to date, these schemes have not been cleared by the Department of the Environment.  I hope the Minister of State will be in a position to give a positive response to those who have been awaiting a water supply for many years.  The original proposals were put on hold because of other developments regarding water in the county. If matters had been left to the people ten years ago they would have installed their own water supplies.  However, following consultation between the local authority and the Department it was decided not to proceed on this basis as the area was to be included in an overall plan.  The people have suffered in consequence, although they appreciate that the plan is in their best interests, provided it is not left on the long finger.</P>
    <P>People in the area now want the necessary funds &mdash; £1.25 million &mdash; to be provided to allow Roscommon County Council to go to tender on this scheme and have it constructed in 1996.  A delegation comprising of local council members and Oireachtas Members met the Minister for the Environment some months ago.  He was very positive but unfortunately an announcement has not been made.  The people are sceptical and worried that the scheme will not be funded in 1996.</P>
    <P>Will the Minister of State indicate to my colleague, Senator Mulloolly, who is a councillor for most of the area in question, and me that the scheme is sanctioned to proceed this year?  Even if it is sanctioned now construction will take many months.  The Roscommon County Council county engineer has informed <Col N="1064" /> me that within a matter of weeks he will be in a position to start pipe laying if he gets the sanction to proceed from the Department and the Minister.  He is well briefed on the scheme and he has already forwarded the information to the Department.</P>
    <P>I hope the Minister will be in a position to indicate to the people of Ballagh and Ballybeg, a sprawling rural area between Roscommon town and Strokestown, that the scheme will go ahead. While it is in progress, they can start to organise small group schemes.  I thank the Minister for coming to the House to respond to this matter and I hope I and my colleague, Senator Mullooly, will be able to bring back good news to the people of the area.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank Senator Finneran for sharing his time and the Minister for coming to the House to respond to this matter, which is important to the people of the area.  This large rural area in County Roscommon has no public water supply.  Eventually, approximately 200 houses, over 80 farms and three schools in the area will be served by a water supply.  It is referred to as the Ballagh/Ballybeg scheme because the original proposal was to service the area by means of two separate group water schemes.  The Ballybeg scheme dates back to 1980 and the Ballagh scheme to 1990.</P>
      <P>Following the construction of the north-east Roscommon regional supply scheme, it was agreed by Roscommon County Council and the Department of the Environment that the source for the Ballagh/Ballybeg areas would be the reservoir at Ballyfeeney.  As Senator Finneran pointed out, the Ballagh scheme is, in effect, an extension of the Ballybeg scheme.  Given the high cost involved in increasing the pipe size, etc., Roscommon County Council in 1993 decided to construct the main pipeline through both schemes as a public scheme.  Proposals for this work were prepared, costed and submitted to the Department of the Environment in late 1993.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1065" /> Some months later a request was received from the Department of the Environment for additional data.  This was supplied but since then all inquiries have elicited the same response, that the matter is under examination in the Department.  As Senator Finneran said, a delegation from the area met the Minister for the Environment some months ago.  The meeting was positive and the Minister gave the delegation reason to believe there would be a positive response in the near future.  We hope the Minister of State has that response today.  Having paid their money many years ago, the people feel they are entitled to know the precise situation and when the water supply scheme will come to fruition in the area. I urge the Minister to indicate that approval will be forthcoming to Roscommon County Council to proceed with the construction of the main pipeline so the area can be serviced with a public water supply.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen) Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen)">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment (Mr. Allen)</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators for raising this matter.  The Department is aware of the difficulties in relation to this scheme and of the deep concern locally that a satisfactory water supply should be provided at the earliest opportunity.</P>
      <P>County Roscommon is benefiting fully from the large programme of investment in water and sewerage schemes which is supported by the EU Cohesion and Structural Funds.  The Senators will be aware that a number of major water and sewerage projects in the county have been prioritised for investment under the Cohesion Fund. Two major lake catchment schemes in Lough Derg and Lough Ree are aimed at eliminating organic pollution of the lakes and the principal inflowing rivers through the provision of new and upgraded sewage collection and treatment systems at the main population centres and the development of a comprehensive monitoring programme for the management of both catchments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Within these catchments, cohesion <Col N="1066" /> funding has been sought for new and improved services at Monksland, Boyle, Ballaghadereen, Tarmonbarry and Roscommon town at a total cost of over £10 million.  The Minister recently announced the approval of the Monksland scheme and further positive announcements on a number of the other projects may be expected soon.</P>
    <P>Regarding water supply projects, the construction of stage one of the Boyle/Ardcarne water supply scheme, costing approximately £3 million, was approved earlier this year.  Work is well underway and the scheme will be substantially completed later this year.  A proposal for the provision of new water treatment facilities at Ballyleague, at a cost of over £100,000, was also approved under the small schemes programme.</P>
    <P>Roscommon County Council has submitted proposals for an expansion of the public water supply network to serve the north and east of the county.  A preliminary report has been received for a project to serve the Ballagh and Ballybeg areas in addition to other villages in the region.  Up to 100 households in this area depend on private individual supplies, many of which are subject to quality and quantity variation.  These householders proposed to extend the public supply by way of a group scheme. However, given that the design for the council scheme required the laying of a ten inch trunk main, Roscommon County Council and the Department concluded that the task of constructing this main would be beyond the resources of the group scheme and could only be carried out by the council. The cost of laying that part of the trunk main as far as Ballagh/Ballybeg is of the order of £1.2 million.  This main would directly serve the majority of households in the area of the proposed group scheme.  The remaining households would then be served by way of group scheme connections.</P>
    <P>Senators are aware that the Minister has approved some 50 projects to commence construction under the water and sewerage capital works programme for 1996.  The full cost of these projects is <Col N="1067" /> estimated at over £200 million.  Having regard to the existing high level of commitments with regard to these projects, unfortunately it is not possible at this time to approve the Ballagh/Ballybeg scheme.  The council's proposal will be given due consideration in the context of the capital works programme for 1997.</P>
    <Col N="1068" />
    <Speaker pid="BrianMullooly" hpid="Mr. Mullooly Mr. Mullooly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mullooly</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said &ldquo;due consideration&rdquo; but I hoped he would say &ldquo;favourable consideration&rdquo; in the context of the capital works programme for 1997.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>I give every man his due.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 3.50 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 9 July 1996.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>