<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="3" Month="Nov" Year="1972" Vol="263" No="4" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 3 Samhain 1972" DateEnglish="Friday, 3 November 1972" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="693" /> Chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="The Taoiseach Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take No. 1 and No. 22 and, in No. 22, Votes 47 and 42.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it proposed to provide time for Private Members' Business next week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="The Taoiseach Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to talk to Deputy Cosgrave about that, perhaps on Monday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Coiste Roghnóireachta:" RHead="An Naoú Tuarascáil">
    <Title>An Coiste Roghnóireachta: An Naoú Tuarascáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DavidAndrews" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach (Mr. Andrews) David Andrews">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach (Mr. Andrews)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tuairiscionn an Coiste Roghnóireachta go bhfuil sé tar éis an Teachta Deasún Mac Goibheannaigh a ainmniú chun fónamh ar an gCoiste um Chuntais Poiblí ar na Cuntais Leithreasa don bhliain dar chríoch an 31 Márta, 1970 chun an folúntas a líonadh a tharla de dheasca an Teachta Pádraig Ó hÓgáin d'fháil bháis.</P>
      <P>Tairgim:</P>
      <P>Go leagfar an Tuarascáil faoi bhráid na Dála.</P>
      <P>Cuireadh agus aontaíodh an cheist.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Estimates," RHead="1972-73">
    <Title>Estimates, 1972-73.</Title>
    <P>The Dail, according to order, went into Committee on Finance and resumed consideration of Estimates for Public Services for the year ending 31st March, 1973.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Committee on Finance. - Vote 47:" RHead="Social Welfare (Resumed)">
    <Title>Committee on Finance. - Vote 47: Social Welfare (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="694" /> Debate resumed on the following motion:</P>
    <P>That the vote be referred back for reconsideration.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&mdash;(Deputy Creed).</P>
    <Speaker pid="BarryDesmond" hpid="Mr. Desmond Mr. Desmond">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Desmond</NameTxt>
      <P>When I reported progress last week I had dealt with a number of aspects of social security in the EEC context.  This morning I wish to complete these observations and to deal with the other matters in the Estimate.  I pointed out on the last occasion that the national social security systems in the EEC have, to a very large extent, grown up quite independently of one another, I want to stress this point again this morning. I do not think we appreciate the extent to which the different social security systems in the EEC have emerged quite separately and independently in each of the member States.  I do not think we appreciate that these systems have evolved in response to quite differing social, economic and political pressures in each of the member states. We must take into account the fact that the schemes in the EEC countries very so much in respect of their objectives. They very very considerably in the methods of financing.  They vary enormously in the way in which the social security systems are organised. We must bear this in mind in any effort towards harmonisation.</P>
      <P>In the Government's White Paper, &ldquo;The Accession of Ireland to the European Communities&rdquo; it is stated quite bluntly at paragraph 3.54:</P>
      <P>The EEC Treaty does not specifically provide for the harmonisation of social security systems and, accordingly, membership of the Community will not impose any direct obligation on us to modify our system.  However, as the Treaty envisages, the operation of the Common Market will itself tend to bring about harmonisation of the social security systems of the Member States.</P>
      <P>The other paragraph dealing with the broad question of social security is paragraph 3.55 which provides:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="695" /> The resources of the European Social Fund will be available to us to assist in the expansion of our retraining and resettlement schemes. As stated above, the special Protocol concerning Ireland calls on the Community institutions to use all the financial means at their disposal to assist us in achieving the aims of our policies of economic development.</P>
    <P>The Department of Social Welfare, the Minister, the Cabinet and the Dáil must recognise the European implications and perspectives of social security within which we will be working from next January.  I do not detect in the country or in the attitude of the Government very much appreciation of these perspectives and of the approaches towards harmonisation. I do not detect any urgency on our part to try to develop such approaches as a social fund, or a social budget, and so on.</P>
    <P>The European Commission have pointed out that economic and monetary union would be largely deprived of meaning if the Community did not implement, in addition to a co-ordination of general economic policies, effective policies to correct structural, sectional, social and regional imbalances.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry to interrupt Deputy Desmond but a discussion on social welfare services in the EEC which would require legislation would not be in order on the Estimate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BarryDesmond" hpid="Mr. Desmond Mr. Desmond">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Desmond</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think the matter I have referred to would require legislation.  The Minister dealt with the question of the EEC in his statement. I want to conclude the comments I was making on the last occasion.  From the point of view of administration we must put the entire expenditure on social welfare &mdash; the figure is £154 million this year and it will be £175 million next year &mdash; into an administrative structure which will be known as the &ldquo;Social Budget&rdquo;.  That will be entirely in accord with the recommendations of the EEC Commission.  The Commission, at the request of the Council of Ministers, adopted as one <Col N="696" /> of its priorities the creation of a European social welfare and social security structure.  Germany, France and the Netherlands are Community countries which have social budgets and other countries in the Community are considering the adoption of the concept of social budgets for the administration of their social welfare and social security system.  I suggest there is need here for a complete recasting of Government budgetary strategy in the field of social services.  This can be done by adopting the Community practice of social budgets and I would strongly urge the implementation of the recommendation in the report on the development of the social situation in the Community in 1971.  At pages 189 and 190 the recommendation is very clearly set out.</P>
      <P>In my experience the Fianna Fáil Party is the most sluggish, lethargic and &mdash; I have to use the word &mdash; incompetent political party with regard to this point of restructuring of expenditure. I have no great admiration for Fianna Fáil literature but I did find lately the 1969 clár of the 39th Ard-Fheis and the social welfare section of that clár contained a specific recommendation tabled by no fewer than nine different Fianna Fáil Cumainn. The resolution was adopted and then ignored.  The resolution said there was urgent need to bring our social welfare structure into line with modern European standards and asked for a progress report.  This resolution was proposed by the Father Augustine Cumann of Cork city and it was endorsed by some ten or 12 other cumainn. The resolution was accepted but nothing has ever been done about it. We should have had a report setting out our approach to social welfare and social security within the EEC. We shall become members next January.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a responsibility on the Government to ensure that we fully avail of the resources of the European Social Fund.  This morning the unemployment statistics were published and recently we had the statistics relating to redundancy.  While I do not think these are cause for any great alarm they highlight the distance this country will have to travel towards full employment.  There is <Col N="697" /> need to avail of every possible facility offered by the European Social Fund. I have not noticed any urgency on the part of the Government in this regard.  The full utilisation of the nation's resources depends to a considerable extent on the enterprise and initiative of our Government.  Half of the resources allocated to the European Social Fund will be available for the part-financing of schemes proposed by member Governments and projects proposed to deal with unemployment resulting from Common Market policies will have to meet with the ready co-operation of member Governments.</P>
    <P>We must face up to the implication of availing of the finances of the Social Fund.  The Government should give a very high priority to the formulation of schemes to deal with deep-seated, structural unemployment problems.  The Minister has a joint responsibility for Labour and Social Welfare and he has, therefore, a major responsibility in this field.  Many of the policies in relation to the European Social Fund are not as yet fully formulated.  It will not be a simple matter in years ahead for the Irish Government periodically to look for a few &ldquo;bob&rdquo; from the European Social Fund.  Projects and schemes of training and retraining will have to be devised and we will then have to look for the finance to ensure that the schemes we put forward to the Commission are fully backed.</P>
    <P>I was struck by the Taoiseach's contribution on regional policy at the recent meeting of heads of State.  It was widely criticised by responsible members of the Oireachtas.  Senator Mary Robinson was very critical of the Taoiseach's nebulous and vague contribution.  The correspondent to the <i>Cork Examiner</i> was provoked into describing it as a timid contribution. If we have a similar approach on the part of Ministers, particularly the Minister for Social Welfare, I am afraid the benefits available from the European Social Fund will be minimal. That will certainly be the case if Ireland's voice in Brussels is one of the weakest.  I have that fear.  It is a legitimate fear and one which we must express here in public.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="698" /> I want to deal with the question of the EEC and our relations with other European countries, particularly Northern Ireland and Great Britain. There should be a special examination undertaken by the Department with a view to extending the various reciprocal insurance agreements with member states of the EEC.  At present, to the best of my knowledge, the only reciprocal arrangements we have are those with Great Britain, Northern Ireland the Isle of Man.  These generally cover insurance eligibility and insurance benefit, but now is the opportunity to extend, particularly with some of the more progressive European countries, our reciprocal arrangements.  We should not just hope that in the year 1980 when the EEC brings in some particular insurance regulation or directive we would then fall in line.</P>
    <P>I want to refer briefly to Northern Ireland.  The Minister had several questions down to him in relation to our social welfare system and its relationship with that of Northern Ireland. I would strongly urge that the Department of Social Welfare should undertake a great deal more public comparative study of the cost of bringing the social services in the Republic into line with those of Northern Ireland.  I am aware that within the Department of Social Welfare a good deal of work has been done. Many projections have been undertaken, but it is disgraceful that the Minister has refused to make this information public.  I think he has just sat on it out of sheer embarrassment, and as a result Members of this House are obliged to talk in very broad estimates of the cost of bringing our benefits in line with those of Northern Ireland.  Figures varying from £100 million to £150 million and £250 million have been mentioned.  The truth does lie within these global figures, and, therefore, if we are serious about national unity the Government should commission, I would suggest, the Economic and Social Research Institue to undertake these comparative expenditure studies in regard to health, education, social security, housing, community welfare services, in both areas.  All the Fianna Fáil <Col N="699" /> Deputies I meet shy away like frightened horses from any discussion in depth on this topic.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Health, Deputy Childrens, has been much more forthcoming in this connection.  On 2nd November, 1971, in Dáil Éireann, he admitted that if eligibility for all the services here were extended to the entire population the additional expenditure of public funds would probably be of the order of £30 million. In response to a question last week the Minister for Health reiterated that figure. Ever since November, 1971, in Dáil Éireann, the Minister for Social Welfare has been extremely coy.  On that occasion he said that about £51 million additional expenditure would be required to bring our social welfare services up to the level of those in the North.  On that occasion his estimate of £51 million was very strongly challenged by Deputy Garret FitzGerald, myself and other Deputies.  We suggested, at column 674 of the Dáil Official Report of 2nd November, 1971, that the figure of £50 million was an extremely conservative one and that £80 to £100 million was nearer the mark. In the analysis in the appendix to the recent publication by Deputy Garret FitzGerald <i>Towards a New Ireland</i> he arrives at a fair minimum conclusion, which I strongly support, that the expenditure on levelling up would be in the region of £150 million.  We should have some confirmation of that from the Minister for Social Welfare, and I would ask him to be more explicit on that area in his reply to the debate.</P>
    <P>In order to illustrate the gap which exists in the social welfare services North and South I wish to quote some statistics.  In Northern Ireland a man with a wife and two children with earnings of £24 a week would get unemployment and sickness benefit amounting to £19.20 a week, that is, a flat rate benefit of £14.20 for himself, his wife and two children and a supplementary earnings-related benefit of £5.  With earnings of £24 he would have a total social security payment of £19.20.  In the Republic the same man with a wife and two children would get £11.65.  Any working person in the North who may be clamouring <Col N="700" /> for national unity would want very seriously to ponder that wide gap.</P>
    <P>In regard to children's allowances, in the Republic a family with three children gets 98p per week, and in Northern Ireland the same family gets £1.90 &mdash; twice as much in Northern Ireland.  In the Republic a family with five children gets £2.2; in Northern Ireland, £3.90.  These are the hard facts that people have to bear in mind.</P>
    <P>I gave the example last week of the young man I met in Long Kesh who is now living in the Republic.  He certainly got a shock when he realised the difference in that area.  We have a long way to go before we appreciate the magnitude of the task before us. To take one area of cost, I should like to bring to the attention of the House the fact that the Minister for Social Welfare has admitted that the annual cost of increasing children's allowances in the Republic to the rates currently being held in Northern Ireland would be £15.2 million extra. That is a pretty startling figure.  In that regard we must certainly question very seriously the Taoiseach's assertion that there would not be any serious problem in the alignment of the Republic's social services with those of Northern Ireland.  It is not just a problem; it is a massive problem, if we ever attempt to face it.</P>
    <P>In particular, I draw the attention of the House to and question the extent to which the Estimate for the Department and the whole Government approach get to grips with the problem of poverty in our community, the extent to which the expenditure of £154 million contributes to the elimination of poverty here.  Many of the Members of the House may not have been born very far from very low levels of income.  That is a fact of Irish life but there is an appalling complacency in Dáil Éireann in regard to appreciating and understanding what constitutes poverty today.  The House has fallen into the classical political trap of saying: &ldquo;Next year we shall give another 50p to the old age pensioners.  We will&rdquo;&mdash; as I believe the Government will next April &mdash;&ldquo;abolish the means test in relation <Col N="701" /> to widows' pensions and do other little bits and pieces here and there and as a result, poverty will be abolished.&rdquo; This approach certainly does not &ldquo;get to grips&rdquo; with the real areas of poverty.  Simply handing out another 50p a week does not resolve the problem of the rural, aged poor.  Many social welfare recipients live in isolation in rural areas in very small holdings and frequently in great poverty despite contributions from the State.</P>
    <P>We politicians owe a debt of gratitude to and should at least thank the Council for Social Welfare of the Catholic Bishops who in November, 1970, brought together in Kilkenny a widely representative group to discuss the evils of poverty.  It is ironical that the bringing together of national experts in this field was undertaken by the council of one of the churches and that not one political party in the history of the State ever held such a conference. That is an indictment of our society.  It happened only because of the pioneering work and outspoken views of such social pioneers as Dr. Birch, Bishop of Ossory and founder of Kilkenny Social Services Council. The headline he has set for politicians should stimulate us to get to grips as politicians with the question of poverty.</P>
    <P>Another major work in this field was that done by Patrick Lyons, lecturer in Economics at Trinity College, who outlined at length the areas of poverty in our community and areas of wealth distribution.  In the past fortnight there was the publication by the Economic and Social Research Institute of the report of their conference on poverty and the work done by Dr. Brendan Walsh.  These have thrown up a great deal of information in regard to poverty in this country and it is high time that the politicians sat down in Dáil Éireann and asked themselves: How do we abolish the situation in which tonight two out of every ten of our population &mdash; men, women and children &mdash; are living well below the minimum subsistence standard?  This is the purpose of politics, the very reason for the existence of this House &mdash; to try not just to alleviate the most obvious forms of poverty but to remove and abolish in society by whatever means <Col N="702" /> are open to us real and measurable poverty.</P>
    <P>The kind of social welfare charity we have here and the reliance on private charity and on a few shillings being given each year in the annual Budget does not by any stretch of imagination get to grips with the problem. The past 15 years are an indictment of Fíanna Fáil in that regard.  We can examine exactly what the Government have done in that period.  They were returned to office in 1957 following an economic crisis and since then all we have seen are what one might describe as incidental structural improvements of the existing system.</P>
    <P>The Fianna Fáil Government brought in an old age contributory pension in 1961.  So what?  We had a social insurance system which was no great shakes.  An old age contributory pension in 1961 was long overdue. Occupational injuries insurance was brought in by the Government in 1967.  Free television licences were hind, at a time when almost every enlightened European country had already introduced such a scheme on a State basis and it was no longer the private preserve of the insurance companies.</P>
    <P>The Government with a great deal of hoo-ha introduced the subsidy for electricity for pensioners in 1967.  Free travel for pensioners was provided in 1967.  Free television licenses were provided for pensioners in 1968.  These budgetary concessions did not prove costly to the Exchequer because there was no fundamental reform involved in them.  The deserted wife's allowance was introduced in 1970.  This again was an elementary normal development of social welfare in a civilised country.  By no stretch of the imagination could it be regarded as a major innovation.  There were the increases for the old age care allowances in 1970.  Roughly speaking, these were the improvements that were introduced. They were not very great. They may have been good enough to win a couple of by-elections but certainly it cannot be suggested that the Fianna Fáil Party have raised the basic levels of social welfare.  They have simply kept them in line with <Col N="703" /> increases in the cost of living on a rough and ready basis.</P>
    <P>I do not think it is fully appreciated by the electorate or, in particular, by politicians that a person who retires at the age of 65 on a State retirement pension, who has no other occupation or pension available to him gets £1.48 per day for himself and his wife.  That represents a personal rate of 89p per day.  For a Member of this Dáil who would have a few drinks on an evening before he would go home, 89p or £1.48 would not go very far.  How many people spend £1.48 on an evening's entertainment?</P>
    <P>In the constituency that I represent there are many old age pensioners who have full insurance for contributory pensions, who live on a subsistence level, in what could be described as poverty.  They get 89p per day, or £6.20 per week.  For a husband, wife and a dependant the rate is £1.48 per day.  I do not feel any great pride as an Irishman when I meet such constituents.  I certainly feel very little pride as a politician when I meet them.  Take the case of a widow with three young children who has an income as from 1st October of this year of £10.10 per week, a daily rate of £1.44.  How many Members of this House could feed, clothe, house and educate three children and maintain himself on £1.44 per day?</P>
    <P>These are the harsh realities of Irish society in the year 1972.  It is all very well for someone to shrug his shoulders and to say that in 1967 the inter-Party Government gave them half a dollar, or whatever it was.  That type of justification means nothing to the unfortunate widow and her three children living in 1972 on £1.44 per day, representing a contributory pension on the basis of her husband's insurance record, a factor which is sometimes forgotten.</P>
    <P>If the outline of the daily rates which I have given does not stir the conscience of our community, I shall be very reluctant to call it a Christian community.  This year we are spending £54 million.  There is a basic priority which this House must recognise. A far greater proportion of the national resources must be allocated <Col N="704" /> to social security.  Social welfare must not be on a quasi-charity basis.</P>
    <P>There is one important statistic which is an indictment of Irish politicians and Irish society.  Many Members of the House do not welcome statistics.  They are difficult to record, assimilate and report.  In the 1960s there was very considerable economic growth and the standard of living improved very considerably.  The people may take justifiable pride in that fact.  Things are somewhat more difficult in the early 1970s but I am quite convinced that we can overcome our difficulties, particularly if there is a change of Government.  In the 1960s, the opportunity presented itself to devote a higher percentage of national expenditure to social welfare but, in fact, the reverse happened. On 26th October I asked the Minister for Social Welfare to state the expenditure on social security and welfare as a percentage of the total expenditure by authorities both central and local.  The Minister gave two statistics: in 1963-64 the figure was 17.67 per cent; in 1971-72 the provisional figure is 17.36 per cent.  In other words, there has been a slight decline in the percentage.</P>
    <P>There has been no change in the past ten years in the proportion of expenditure spent on social security. In 1962-63, the figure was 17.05 per cent; in 1963-64, 17.67 per cent; 1964-65, 17.89 &mdash; an increase; in 1965-66, 16.51 &mdash; a decrease.  In 1966-67, after the general election the figure went up to 17.66.  In 1967-68 it went down again, to 16.89; in 1968-69 it was 16.32, in 1969-70, 16.81, in 1970-71, 17.33 and in 1971-72 it was 17.36. There has been no change of any consequence whatever in the Irish Republic in the past ten years and I think that alone is an indictment of the allocation of national resources for social security.  This illustrates for me the public hypocrisy of a political party who state that they have every intention of realigning completely the system of social security in a more equitable and egalitarian manner.</P>
    <P>I hark back, and legitimately hark back, to say that we need a new approach in this country, the approach which came about in 1940, for <Col N="705" /> example.  Whatever political views may be held in this House about the contribution of the late William Norton, it was he who caught expenditure on social security and its administration in this country in 1949, by the scruff of the neck, shook it and produced a White Paper on social security.  In 1952 major proposals were made and implemented by the Fianna Fáil Government in the Social Welfare Act of that year, but since 1949 we have never had a Government White Paper on social security.  We have had nothing.  We have had changes and minor innovations here and there, with incidental benefits and so-called concessions introduced here and there, but really there has been nothing of a widespread insurance nature undertaken in the community since 1949-52.  When we look back on Irish social welfare, the only people to whom I can allocate credit is William Norton, in terms of his real contribution, and Dr. Duignan, Bishop of Clonfert, for his tremendous contribution in the war period around 1944 when he proposed a comprehensive national social security system. We have, therefore, to ask the Government to consider major changes in the social insurance system.</P>
    <P>I do not think that it is good enough simply to extend social insurance to all wage and salary earners in the State, much as I would wish to see it extended.  I do not want to impinge on an area requiring legislation but I strongly suggest to the Government that it is high time they devised a comprehensive national social security system which would take into account the interests of all wage and salary earners and also the very large numbers of self-employed persons in the State, as well as the farming community.  Until such time as the whole of the working population are brought into comprehensive national social security, I do not see our system being worthy of approval by any of the political parties.</P>
    <P>I make that strong recommendation to the Government and point out that there is at the moment in the State what one might call the middle income poverty trap, the poverty trap of the family who are over the £1,600 <Col N="706" /> limit and who have not got the full benefits of social welfare because they are outside the insurability limit and are, therefore, very frequently caught in a trap in terms of health services and the social insurances services of the State.  There are many thousands of such white collar and industrial workers, blue collar workers, in the State who are caught up in that middle income trap of a lack of full coverage.  Therefore, in respect of social security, I put forward three basic demands: the level of cash benefits must be substantially increased, the basic levels I have referred to; secondly, the system must be a comprehensive national system; and thirdly, contributions and benefits must be wage-related right up the line and self-employed persons and farmers brought within the context of compulsory social insurance in this State.  This will require a complete restructuring of our social security system and I do not think the provisions in the proposed new legislation, the 1972 Bill &mdash; I do not intend to refer at any length to this &mdash; go far enough or are broad enough.  They bring in far fewer people than we would wish.  We need a universal system rather than a general system which is very limited in scope.</P>
    <P>I want to raise, in relation to the Minister's Department, the matter of a question I put down and which I intend to repeat.  It was on 26th October that I asked the Minister for the total number of wage and salary earners in the income ranges between £1,600 and £2,000, between £2,000 and £2,500, between £2,500 and £3,000 and over £3,000.  I must confess that I was rather surprised to get back from the Minister by way of written answer on 26 October, to Question 468, a reply which said that the compilation and supply of statistics of this nature is not the function of his Department. The Minister has on occasion waxed eloquent about the number of extra people who will be covered by an extension of the social insurance limit.  When it was brought up from £1,200 to £1,600, the Minister had no difficulty whatever in indicating the number of people in these income categories who were covered by way <Col N="707" /> of extended social insurance and my simple reply to the Minister is that this answer is not good enough.  The information is available in the Department and if it is not, it is the function of the Department to obtain the information and to supply Deputies with it.  I intend to repeat that question with a view to obtaining the information from the Minister.</P>
    <P>Regarding the organisation of the Department, I want to repeat a recommendation I made in public recently in a draft policy document. On that occasion I suggested that the Department of Social Welfare and the Department of Health should be amalgamated and that we should have a new Department.  I am not quite certain what we would call it, whether it would be the Department of Social Services or the Department of Social Development, as it might well be called in years ahead.  I see a great logic in the amalgamation of those two Departments.  They are inextricably bound up in terms of social policy. It is essential that they should be amalgamated with responsibility for the co-ordination of our social services.</P>
    <P>The excuse of the Fianna Fáil Party that there is now some experimentation and restructuring and re-organisation going on in the Department of Health is a very lame one for not going ahead with the rationalisation of the functions of the two Departments. It would be wise to do it also because I see the Department of Labour growing up as a major Department. As we enter the EEC the Department of Labour will assume major new responsibilities in respect of the social fund and training and re-training in that area of the social fund.  It will have major responsibility in representing this country in the industrial and social policies affecting workers in the EEC.</P>
    <P>When we think of worker participation in the EEC, which will come in time, and when we think of the growth of the social legislation affecting industrial relations, it is very unwise to continue to have the Department of Labour and the Department of Social Welfare the exclusive responsibility <Col N="708" /> of one Government Minister. I strongly urge that we should have a separate Minister for Labour. That is a legitimate claim on our part. Therefore, we should amalgamate the two Departments I mentioned and reorganise them as a single Government Department, as was recommended in the Report of the Public Services Organisation Review Group.</P>
    <P>The Government do not seem to have taken into account the recommendations of August, 1969, by the Devlin review group.  They recommended that comprehensive care, involving medical and social welfare effort, was now the accepted basis for most modern health and welfare activity.  The Devlin review group saw a logic in the two Departments coming together.  They pointed out that planning for health and welfare services was directly inter-related and directly dependent on the same kind of social skills, the same kind of social administrators, and the same kind of general budgetary expenditure.  Therefore, they recommended that the two Departments should come together.</P>
    <P>I would be very interested to hear whether the Minister accepts the need for a rationalisation of the two Departments. I do not think there would be any insurmountable administrative problems, although in both the Department of Health and the Department of Social Welfare it might well be that some of the more cherished empires would have to fall.  In the nature of things, if a recommendation is worthy of implementation, it should be implemented without further ado.</P>
    <P>I would also recommend that there should be set up within this House a joint all-party committee of the Dáil and Seanad on social affairs.  I should like to make the point, as a newly elected spokesman for the Labour Party, that it is quite impossible for a spokesman on social welfare to speak for several hours and deal effectively, and in a comprehensive manner, and in any reasonable depth, with the whole range of expenditure on social welfare totalling £154 million in a single contribution once a year, and then sit down and hope that the Department and the Government <Col N="709" /> and the House will take note of his recommendations.</P>
    <P>It is a typical piece of feudal parliamentary democracy that this should be the way in which our legislators should run their affairs.  It is entirely logical that if the Social Welfare Bill arising out of the budget each year, and the Social Welfare Estimate presented annually to the House, and the various other legislative matters which arise inevitably during the year, are to be discussed in any reasonable depth, such a committee should be set up. Any recommendations made to the professional staffs of the Department of Social Welfare could be made at the committee and discussed.  It is entirely proper that an Oireachtas committee on social welfare should be established.</P>
    <P>How does a politician on the Opposition benches open up any kind of contact with the professional staffs of the Department?  Public servants do not exist simply to service the political party in power.  They are responsible to the State.  They are responsible to the Oireachtas and responsible to the nation as a whole.  It would be a very healthy development in democratic discussions if Deputies had an opportunity to sit down on an Oireachtas committee on social affairs and discuss with the professional staffs of the Department of Social Welfare and the Department of Health the various implications of the legislative matters coming before the House.</P>
    <P>This House is creaking to a standstill as we approach the EEC.  In 1973-75 we will be faced with the prospect of hundreds of regulations, hundreds of directives and massive volumes of reports being presented to the House for public discussion and public review. We will be involved in the ramifications of the European Social Fund. Employers and workers will participate in the EEC economic and social committee. Members of this House will discuss social security in the European Parliament.  Therefore, it is imperative, if we are entering into this kind of national and international dialogue in relation to our social affairs, that the crude, inefficient and ineffective parliamentary structure which we have in <Col N="710" /> this Dáil should be transformed into some sane sensible structure in which it would be open to the politicians to play a more constructive role.</P>
    <P>I make that recommendation to the House fully confident that the Fianna Fáil Party will pay not the slightest attention to it, because the Fianna Fáil Party have a contempt for what happens in this House.  Their only concern is with ministerial prerogative, with dishing out favours to individuals and, above all, with power.  They are not concerned with a vibrant, dynamic democracy which would enable all public representatives to air fully their views and their attitudes in a more open, almost non-party, manner.</P>
    <P>With regard to pensions, the numbers of workers retiring annually are increasing. There are some workers who retire earlier than 65.  Unless we get to grips with the current level of pensions, both social insurance and occupational, we will find ourselves with a new stratum of poverty-stricken people between the ages of 60 and 70.  The prospects of obtaining suitable alternative employment from 60 onwards are very remote indeed.  As well as normal retirement there is also the problem of redundancy.</P>
    <P>The implementation of a national comprehensive pension scheme related to income is a matter of grave urgency.  Workers and employers alike would contribute to such a scheme.  There is grave need for such a scheme.  There are many CIE pensioners living on appallingly low incomes, many of them as low as £1.50 per week.  They have given a lifetime of service to our national transport system and this is their reward for that service.  There are workers who, after 30 or 40 years' service, find themselves compelled to exist on £2, £3 or £4 a week.  This will be supplemented by their social insurance but, even so, it gives them a bare subsistence level.  We should follow the example of Britain and Northern Ireland and introduce a graduated pension scheme.  Such a scheme would give a worker retiring at 65 between his occupational pension scheme and his State pension scheme two-thirds of his earnings.  That should not be an insurmountable objective.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="711" /> This is something which should be done expeditiously because of the growing numbers retiring and because of the growing appreciation of the vital importance of being covered effectively. I can give a personal example. I am not covered by any pension scheme.  I was in two different pension schemes in two different trade union organisations.  When I transferred from the first I was given £100 refund of pension contributions.  When I left the second on becoming a Member of the Dáil I was given a refund of a couple of hundred pounds.  Now, at 37 years of age, having started my working life at 20, I find myself not covered for any pension whatsoever.  It is in this kind of situation that one becomes firmly convinced that this kind of thing should not happen.</P>
    <P>The Minister and the Government will have to get to grips with the major deficiencies that exist.  The levels of pensions, particularly in the case of manual workers, so-called, are abnormally low.  Added to that is the fact that many workers lose pension entitlement on redundancy.  If a firm folds up, pensions also fold up.  Workers who change their jobs lose their pension entitlements.  Pressure should be brought to bear on those who administer occupational pension schemes to ensure that this disability is substantially mitigated.  Every worker has a right to build up pension rights and, as he changes from one job to another, those rights should go with him.  Social insurance rights pass from job to job and surely pension rights should also pass thereby enabling those in private occupational pension schemes to accumulate their rights.</P>
    <P>The Government have an obligation to produce a White Paper on this matter because it is becoming a matter of grave concern not only to the trade union movement but to the workers themselves.  Again, women are treated as second class citizens where pensions are concerned; they may have to pay the same flat rate contribution but they will get lower benefits when they retire.  There is the golden handshake for the director, the silver handshake for the senior executives and the copper minimum payment to the wage <Col N="712" /> earner.  The Minister should take a sharp look at occupational pension schemes and he should introduce a comprehensive national scheme designed to bring about major improvements.</P>
    <P>Such occupational pension schemes should, if possible, also provide for benefits to devolve on dependants. Many of these benefits die with the holder thereof.  We should ensure that on the death of an employee the support of his dependants should not be left to either the State contributions or to private charities and that dependants should have a right to a pension which would give them a decent living.  The classic example of that is the CIE pension scheme, and the Department of Social Welfare should examine that.</P>
    <P>I wish to refer to certain aspects of child care for which the Department of Social Welfare is responsible.  We find ourselves making the public plea that the Minister should bring his influence to bear on the Government to ensure that national child care services are placed under the auspices of a single Government Department.  I would have no great objection if a Parliamentary Secretary were given responsibility for this.  It is ironic that a Parliamentary Secretary were can be given responsibility for school transport services or can be given responsibility for the Office of Public Works but cannot be given responsibility for national child care services.</P>
    <P>At the moment there are 3,500 children maintained by health boards in approved children's homes and residential schools.  These children have relationship with the Department in the context of Social Welfare entitlements. The co-ordination of the functions of the Department of Health, of Education, of Justice and of Social Welfare is urgently needed in this area.  The fact that no single Government Department seems to have responsibility in this area has caused confusion, mismanagement and a waste of resources.  Therefore, I would ask the Minister to give serious consideration to this recommendation for reform.</P>
    <P>The negative attitude of the Minister and his Department in respect of the children's allowances scheme is <Col N="713" /> still a matter of public concern.  I cannot understand why a claim for children's allowances may be submitted only by the father of a family.  The classic answer of the Minister is that it is not a major issue.  It is a question of social entitlement and of social rights, and it is manifestly unfair and unjust that the mother of a family is, by implication, precluded from applying for children's allowances.  It requires the most careful examination of the Department and the most profuse returning of forms to the claimants before the Department is prepared to sanction a claim submitted by the mother of children.  The father of the family is regarded as the head of the household and only he may apply for children's allowances.  As recently as the 26th October the Minister, in reply to a question, said he was not prepared to consider the amendment of this regulation.  There have been several recommendations to the Minister to examine the whole question of application forms for children's allowances.</P>
    <P>Recently I had the case of an unmarried mother who applied for children's allowances and, even though I sent in a covering letter to the Department stating that this was an application by an unmarried mother, in thick red pencil back came the form saying it must be signed by the head of the household.  Eventually the Department was prepared to accept her father as head of the household.  She was the mother of the child.  This reveals a lack of sensitivity, of which I rarely accuse the Department.  I think it gets a great deal of abuse which it does not deserve. However, there is need for change in the certification of application forms.</P>
    <P>I would ask the Department to have a full-scale review of the whole question of family allowances.  I do not think it is enough just to say that if we want the level of Northern Ireland family allowances it will cost us an extra £50 million a year.  The stage has been reached when it should examine the real effectiveness and the benefit to society of the present system of family allowances in the Republic. I know this is a thorny political problem. <Col N="714" /> At the moment there are roughly 60,000 families with five children or more who get family allowances.  To what extent are the allowances which are given to those five-child families of immeasurably greater benefit than the money which is allocated to the 92,000 one-child families?  There are 67,000 families with three children. Have we examined the relative levels of income tax paid by them and the value of the benefit given to them by way of family allowances?  Have we examined the relative importance of this very substantial allocation of public funds?  Have we examined the fact that to some wealthy families children's allowances are merely bingo money?  How do we apply the principle of selectivity to the allocation of family allowances?  Have we examined, for example, in the Department the &ldquo;claw-back&rdquo; principle of giving family allowances and taking them back from wealthier families by means of income tax?  These are areas of social policy on which, with all due respect to the House, we do not find information publicly and readily available for discussion or serious political debate.  Family allowances are supposed to be under examination by the Minister for Finance for the past three or four years but nothing has really been done yet in this area.</P>
    <P>The Minister should bring in, as a matter of urgency, his reforms in respect of home assistance.  I hope these reforms will be very extensive in scope.  It is now universally accepted that our current home assistance system is a national scandal.  The 31,000 people receiving home assistance would probably be first to agree with that description.  When I read the public-spirited and well-documented case put forward by the association of home assistance officers, the various documents and recommendations they produce, I see the system indicted in a big way.  One need only read the paper presented by Mr. Dick Doyle, superintendent assistance officer in Waterford, which he read at the Kilkenny conference.  That paper showed that the home assistance system is utterly inadequate to deal <Col N="715" /> with areas of poverty in our community.</P>
    <P>The effect of home assistance on poverty is marginal.  Many Deputies know families in their own constituencies who are receiving home assistance and quite frequently one can say the odds are that the next generation of the same families will also be in receipt of home assistance.  The extent to which the system has any real effect in relieving poverty is very much open to question.  There is a veil of bad administration over the home assistance system.  I do not mean bad in the context of staff; they are obliged to administer the system. Home assistance officers are generally untrained and have not much training in social work.  The criteria, the regulations and guidelines under which they operate are so much open to subjective assessment that one often wonders how they manage to administer the system.  The system we have should certainly be reformed.  I should like to see a system of minimum family income benefits of a comprehensive nature replacing it and, before the Minister introduces his reforms, I should like some consultative discussions between Deputies and the Department.  I see nothing wrong with the Minister bringing together Deputies from various political parties and saying: &ldquo;These are the changes I am thinking about. Have you any suggestions about a system of supplementary benefits which would improve the overall situation?&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I do not propose to speak on the role of social workers apart from welcoming the establishment of the association catering for social workers. I trust the Department will co-operate fully with this association because as a unified body for the past 12 months I think that association deserves full public recognition; I have no doubt it will make a major contribution to the reform and extension of our social services.</P>
    <P>I welcome the setting-up of that body just as I welcome the establishment by the Department of Health of the National Social Services Council. <Col N="716" /> I baulk at trying to interpret the reaction of the Department of Social Welfare to this council.  One is aware that the Minister for Health is likely to go off at half-cock in a half-dozen different directions simultaneously and to discover the implications of what he has done two years later.  He does magnificent work in many respects in his Department but there is need for the Department of Social Welfare to be kept fully informed as to what the Minister for Health is doing particularly in the social services field. At present we are liable to develop into a sort of hallowe'en party where crackers will be going off all over the place with social services councils, community welfare councils, social workers employed by this body and by that body and a whole range of duplicated social community services with very little co-ordination.  There is a real danger of this developing with the Department of Health making their contribution, the various regional health boards doing their bit and then the Department of Social Welfare capping the lot.  There is need for much greater co-ordination of these services and I should like the Department of Social Welfare, in conjunction with the Department of Health, to set up community welfare centres throughout the country.  I have advocated in the newspapers and in the House the setting-up of citizens' advice bureaux and I do not propose to delay the House unduly on this matter.</P>
    <P>I conclude with a number of pleas in regard to individual groupings under our social welfare system.  I plead particularly for an urgent revision of the disgraceful anomaly under our social welfare system whereby the Department virtually refuse to recognise the right to social welfare entitlement of deserted wives divorced in Britain by husbands domiciled there.  A similar scandalous situation arises in regard to widows' pensions where divorced husbands have died and wives divorced in England apply for widows' pensions here and are refused on the grounds that they were not married before applying for the benefit.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="717" /> The Minister has said that the Department's legal adviser has advised that such applications, where the deserted wife is involved in divorce proceedings, should be rejected.  The Minister is trying to have it both ways.  He has said:</P>
    <P>To qualify for a deserted wife's allowance a woman must naturally be a wife and arising out of a decision in the case of women who have been divorced in England the deciding officer took into account legal advice to the effect that under our law the divorce in England of a person domiciled in England is effective to dissolve the marriage and the dissolution is recognised as being effective in this country.</P>
    <P>One must draw public attention to the fact that a dissolution by divorce of a marriage in England is recognised in the Republic of Ireland in respect of social welfare entitlement and that this is the legal advice given by the Attorney General and by the legal adviser to the Department of Social Welfare.  I want to state baldly that the State recognises divorce in England when it suits administrative and statutory convenience.  This is a very paradoxical situation.  The Taoiseach has said publicly and privately within his own party that one could never have a referendum in Ireland on divorce because it would be defeated. The other political parties, ironically, have come to the same conclusion &mdash; we all know what I am talking about &mdash; in relation to constitutional referenda.</P>
    <P>The State, the Government and the Minister for Social Welfare recognise divorce in relation to social welfare entitlement.  I shall give the example of a constituent of mine who is affected by this rather perverse interpretation of the law.  This constituent of mine has four children.  Her husband went to Britain, in effect deserting her.  He divorced her.  He died in Britain.  The woman applied to the Department of Social Welfare quite recently for a widow's pension.  A reply which I got from the Department on 25th September, 1972, is as follows:</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="718" /> I am directed by the Minister for Social Welfare to refer to your letter of&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>the date is irrelevant</P>
    <P>&mdash;&mdash;concerning the case of&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <P>I do not propose to name the person</P>
    <P>&mdash;&mdash;and to inform you that a claim for a widow's pension has been received from her.  In order for Mrs. X to qualify for a pension it will be necessary for her to establish that she is a widow.  In deciding this question in regard to women who have been divorced in England the deciding officer takes into account legal advice to the effect that under our law the divorce in England of a person domiciled in England is effective to dissolve the marriage and the dissolution is effective in this country.</P>
    <P>Enquiries are proceeding in regard to the divorce in this case and if the result of these enquiries confirms the position as set out in your letter, the claim, on the advice quoted above, will be rejected.  The grounds of the rejection will be that Mrs. X will have failed to establish that she is a widow.</P>
    <P>I sympathise with the staff of the Department of Social Welfare.  I do not hold them responsible for this.  Their job is to administer the statutes in accordance with the legal advice given but I do seriously suggest to the Minister that the reply which he gave to me last week, that she can go away and apply for home assistance, is not fair and just in the context of 1972 and of our society, which professes serious concern for the Christian family.  Where the breadwinner has gone to England and divorced his wife, she should not be penalised.</P>
    <P>There seems to be an impression abroad that all members of the Garda Síochána are covered by social welfare insurance.  This is very far from being the case.  The Garda Síochána have been excluded from Social Welfare Acts since the inception of the force and that position obtained until 2nd October, 1972, when those members of the force whose income is under £1,600 were included as compulsorily insured persons.  I want to draw particular <Col N="719" /> attention to the fact that the Conroy Commission recommended, in paragraph 1108 (b) that steps should be taken to ensure that a member of the Garda Síochána might become insurable under and share in the benefits of the Social Welfare Acts and the Health Acts.  Since 2nd October about 1,000 members of the total of 7,229 gardaí have been brought under the Social Welfare Acts.  The proportion of members covered will decrease as Garda pay increases.  I do not think the spirit of the Conroy Commission recommendation has been implemented by the Government, notwithstanding the great brouhaha that went on in regard to the recent Social Welfare Act, when the guards got a pat on the back and were told that they were great fellows and that they were being brought under compulsory social insurance.  Of course, members of the force are contributing just as other insured workers are. Gardaí were deprived by law of the right to stamp a card at a time when their salaries would otherwise have entitled them to be compulsorily insured. Recommendations have been made, in particular, by the representative body for inspectors, station sergeants and sergeants.  The Minister should re-examine the matter.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Social Welfare should consider the question of having contributions deemed to have been paid in respect of the employment of each member of the Garda Síochána in respect of each week immediately prior to 2nd October, 1972, up to a maximum of 156 weeks.  This would mean that the three-eighths of pay paid by each member for the past 156 weeks prior to 2nd October would be accepted as a contribution to social welfare.  If necessary, the Department of Justice should credit the Department of Social Welfare with the amounts paid.  On that basis the members of the force would be in a position to become voluntary contributors, if they so wish. They would, of course, have coverage under the Health Acts.  This is a recommendation which I would urge the Minister to consider because it is not enough to say to the members of the Garda Síochána: &ldquo;You are being brought in under social insurance&rdquo;. <Col N="720" /> They should be brought in on fair and equitable terms.</P>
    <P>The only other grouping I want particularly to refer to are the blind. The Department should undertake a very special review of the social welfare provisions for blind persons. There are many serious problems facing blind persons which are ignored in our society and in terms of the provision of employment for blind persons, the provision of tax-free and special disability allowances for blind persons and additional home help for blind persons, our State has been very miserly, rather mean, and rather sparse in its contribution.  The recent report of the National League for the Blind of Ireland highlighted the failure of our community to make reasonable and fair provision for the social rights of blind persons in our community.</P>
    <P>In regard to the cost of all I have been talking about, I made the suggestion earlier that as a community we have to devote an increasing proportion of our national resources towards social welfare.  Where do we get these resources from?  One should bring to the attention of the House the kind of money which is now knocking around the State, as one might say, and I will make one or two comments in this regard.  Income tax has grown from £52 million in 1965-66 to £148 million in the current year, a phenomenal growth in money which is being contributed by wage and salary earners into the Exchequer, and yet there has been no great relative increase in expenditure in the Department over the years.  Revenue from PAYE has rocketed from £21 million to £87 million in the current year&mdash;here again wage and salary earners are making massive contributions to State revenue.  Surtax has doubled, from £2.6 million to £4.3 million.  Value-added tax revenue will be growing very considerably.  There is a buoyancy of revenue in the straightforward areas of taxation.  The amount we still spend on drink is 10 per cent of all personal expenditure so that there seems to be a fairly substantial buoyancy of revenue in the area of drink consumption.  I suggest that it would be possible to <Col N="721" /> have a capital gains tax brought in. In the past year on the Dublin Stock Exchange, £200 million were made in capital gains.  There is an area where, if you want to look for money for social welfare, the money is available. I would also bring to the attention of the Minister that very slight increases in the insurance stamp bring in very substantial amounts of money.  I have not got the exact figure before me but the Minister will agree that roughly speaking one penny on the insurance stamp from an insured worker brings in £300,000, one penny from an employer bringing in about a similar sum.</P>
    <P>We in the Labour Party are under no illusions whatever about the cost of the reforms we are talking about. The cost will be very substantial and this community, if it is really serious about getting to grips with the raising up massively of the levels of social welfare benefit, will have to make up its mind that it is going to pay for it. Those who are going to pay for it are ourselves and the rest of the community through the working population of the State.  If any significant progress is to be made towards achieving the changes I have outlined it will require very substantial monetary contributions from the land speculators, from the tax and bonus share speculators &mdash; who made fortunes in the past two or three years and who, because of their contributions to Fianna Fáil, are allowed to go scot-free because they are valuable at election time&mdash; from employers, and probably more from employers than workers because we have to get away from the idea of identical contributions from employers and workers.  On the Continent now, employers are paying vastly more and in Britain employers are increasingly paying more than workers and wage and salary earners such as myself will have to pay more related to our earnings.  It is quite unfair that I should pay £1 a week as a voluntary contributor as I do to social insurance on a salary of £2,500 while the unfortunate worker with a wife and five children who is earning £24 a week has to pay £1 also.  It is quite unjust.</P>
    <Col N="722" />
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. J. Brennan) Joseph Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. J. Brennan)</NameTxt>
      <P>And you also pay 7s in the £ income tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BarryDesmond" hpid="Mr. Desmond Mr. Desmond">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Desmond</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I pay my income taxation, but in terms of social insurance contributions, it should be based on a fair share of the cost.  I do not think the Minister would dispute the contributions by employers.</P>
      <P>I would urge him also to face up to the fact that if the farming community are to have the benefits of pensions, retirement pensions and widows' and orphans' pensions, and disability benefit, perhaps in the long run, we will have to devise some means whereby that community will make their social contribution.  I do not claim to have any special knowledge of how one would devise a comprehensive national insurance system for farmers, large or small, to contribute to &mdash; under the current system, in relation to health services, there is a £7 per year contribution &mdash; and I do not know whether one would do it through the rating system or through the land annuity system of payments.  If the farming community are to have the full benefits of social security, they cannot have them for nothing and will have to make their contribution.  The self-employed in the community can be brought in without their necessarily having to be involved in an elaborate system of contributions.</P>
      <P>One way or the other, the elimination of poverty in our community and the introduction of a modern social welfare system will require a combination of real political will on the part of the politicians.  I have grave doubts that the Government any longer have the tenacity, or the political will, or the purpose, to undertake this kind of effort.  We need a new Government.  We need an alternative Government.  There is enough political will, effort and experience available on the Opposition Benches to undertake this historic task, to catch the current system of social welfare by the scruff of the neck, give it a good shake in the 1970s, and produce a comprehensive modern system which is long overdue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="723" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnOLeary1965" hpid="Mr. J. O'Leary Mr. J. O'Leary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. O'Leary</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to compliment the Minister on the manner in which this Estimate was introduced.  Whatever Deputy Desmond says about the lack of increases and improvements in social welfare, I believe that the Fianna Fáil Party and Government have made tremendous strides and advances in that field during the past ten years or so.</P>
      <P>This year, for example, the net estimate for social welfare is £87 million, which shows an increase of almost £12 million over the original estimate for the year 1971-72.  As well as that the Exchequer met about £31 million of the expenditure of £45½ million in 1963-64.  This year the expenditure runs to £154 million, of which £96 million will fall on the Exchequer. Total expenditure has grown by about 238 per cent between 1963-64 and 1972-73.  Also between 1963-64 and 1967-68 we should remember that expenditure increased from £45½ million to over £68 million, an increase of 50 per cent, whereas the increase of £85½ million between 1967-68 and the current year represents an increase of 125 per cent.  This surely is a remarkable achievement on the part of the Government.  It is really significant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Total expenditure in social welfare as a percentage of the GNP increased from 5.4 per cent in 1963-64 to 7 per cent in 1971-72.  Deputy Desmond quoted a figure of 16 or 17 per cent as the percentage of the total expenditure from the State and local authorities in respect of social services. That figure is misleading when compared with the figures which I have just quoted.  The improvements in the social services during the past ten years or so have been very significant. Some of the major new changes covered contributory old age pensions, occupational injuries, insurance, invalidity and retirement pensions, allowances for deserted wives, allowances for incapacitated pensioners and others over 70 years of age.  They also covered free travel, free electricity and free television licences.  The duration of unemployment benefit was extended from 156 days to 312 days.  The minimum age limit for entitlement to widows' non-contributory <Col N="724" /> pensions was removed. Payment in respect of dependent children was extended to all such children where it was previously confined to two.  According as the economic position improved, and as the economy was able to afford it over the past ten years or so, our social welfare services were improved also.</P>
    <P>There are a few matters in relation to the administration of the services which I should like to raise.  It appears to me that persons in receipt of unemployment and disability benefit could lose about nine days' payment in certain circumstances.  For example, a person who applies for unemployment benefit could lose about three days' pay at the start. If he becomes ill while he is receiving unemployment benefit he loses three days' payment while he is awaiting disability benefit.  He loses three days' pay at the other end while he is awaiting payment of unemployment benefit.  This position should be rectified.</P>
    <P>I have come across a number of cases where persons applied for contributory old age pensions in the belief that they were entitled to them.  When they found they were not, they applied for the non-contributory pensions which, unfortunately, are paid from the date of application only.  In such cases payment should be made from the date of the original application for the contributory pensions.  Claims for widows' pensions should be considered more quickly by the Department. I am not saying the Department deal with them slowly but they could be dealt with faster.</P>
    <P>I also believe that more signing centres should be established in the rural areas particularly for recipients of unemployment assistance under the small farmers scheme.  According as this scheme is improved yearly, more and more small farmers qualify for assistance.  I see no reason why these centres could not be established in local sub-post offices.  I know there is difficulty in having the Garda available to certify unemployment and to certify that the applicant turns up and signs.  I believe that the local sub-post offices would do the job very well, and willingly, and probably free <Col N="725" /> of charge to the Department.  I would strongly advocate this system.  I believe there should be a higher authority to adjudicate on appeals against decisions of the appeals officer.  I have come across cases in which it was very difficult to understand the decision of the appeals officer, particularly in cases in which a public representative was of the opinion that the applicant was entitled to either benefit or assistance.</P>
    <P>Deputy Desmond said there has been no real change in social welfare over the past decade.  I cannot understand how he could make such a statement.  It is very easy for the Opposition parties to criticise the improvement in social welfare over the past ten years but, so far, they have failed to spell out what they would do if they were in office.  Neither have they told us from whence the money would come.</P>
    <P>I should like to take this opportunity of congratulating the Minister and the Parliamentary Secretary for the way in which they have looked after their Department.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: The Minister stated that since 1963-1964 the amount of money devoted to his Department has increased substantially. He said that between 1963-1964 and 1967-1968 the sum had increased from £45½ million to £68 million, or by 50 per cent, and, from 1967-1968 to date it had gone up by 125 per cent.  The fact is the increases mentioned by the Minister are doing no more than keeping pace with the increase in the cost of living.  Possibly they may be marginally above it. The gap between the social welfare classes and those better off has been widening all the time.  That is something of which we should be ashamed. It is something of which the Minister, in particular, should be ashamed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There are at least three standards of living here.  There is the standard of living of the unfortunate people dependent on social welfare assistance or social welfare benefit.  These are on the bread-and-butter line or, as I said elsewhere on the bread-without-any-butter line.  There is then, the middle income group, tolerably well <Col N="726" /> off but feeling the pinch if exceptional expenditure falls to be met.  Over the last number of years we have had a growing class of people who have incresed their incomes and their standard of living at an alarming rate. They have done this through their contracts with the Government.  They are to be found in every country.  This is one of the most disgraceful aspects of our society at the moment.  You have these people who have blossomed into the semi-millionaire class at the cost of the poorer sections in our community and something will now have to be done to close the everwidening gap between the haves and the have-nots.</P>
    <P>During the referendum campaign we were told that certain saving would be effected following on our entry into Europe.  Figures of £30 million and £40 million were quoted as the savings that would be effected in the case of agriculture.  Whatever saving is effected should be devoted to bringing the standard of living of social welfare recipients up to a reasonable level.</P>
    <P>Comparing our percentage contribution of GNP devoted to social welfare with that of other European countries, we find we are at the bottom of the list.  Expenditure per head of the population in Belgium in 1970 was £143 per head; in France it was £155; in Germany it was £173; in Italy it was £94; in Luxembourg it was £144; in the Netherlands it was £152; in the United Kingdom it was £94 and in the Republic of Ireland it was £43.  This is something of which we should be ashamed.  The Minister said that in 1963-1964 we contributed 5.4 per cent of GNP to social welfare and that that had increased to 7 per cent in 1971-1972.  I do not think an increase from 5.4 per cent in 1963-1964 to 7 per cent in 1971-1972 is something about which the Minister can boast, something he can present to the House as a creditable performance.</P>
    <P>In that time the cost of living has increased alarmingly and the value of money has decreased alarmingly.  He says we are contributing 7 per cent of the gross national product.  In 1970 <Col N="727" /> Belgium was contributing 16.1 per cent; France, 16 per cent; Germany, 17.2 per cent; Italy, 16.6 per cent; Luxembourg, 16.5 per cent; Netherlands, 19.2 per cent and, the UK 15.2 per cent.  My information is that we were contributing 10.5 per cent, which is still low.  The Minister takes credit for only 7 per cent, but anyway we are at the bottom of the league.  As a Christian country, as a country that has professed Christian ideals for 1,500 years, we should have a more Christian approach to this matter.</P>
    <P>Deputy Barry Desmond has compared the position here with that in Northern Ireland. I do not propose to go into this at any length, but it is a fact that they have much more generous payments and schemes in Northern Ireland, supplementary payments, benefits related to wages, which we have not got here.  I understand that in Northern Ireland a man earning £24 a week with a wife and two children would get sickness benefit there amounting to £19.20, whereas a man in the same circumstances here would get only £11.65.  There is a very big gap there and something will have to be done about it.</P>
    <P>I want to urge the Minister and the Government to tackle their duty in regard to the social welfare classes and to tackle it immediately.  The fact that we are entering into Europe and that subsidies will be saved, the fact that we will get more revenue from value-added tax than we have collected in the past, all should be taken into account and all should be devoted substantially to tackling this problem. Take the case with which we are all most familiar, that of the old age pensioner living alone.  That person is now in receipt of something over £5 a week and out of that he or she may very well be called upon to pay £50, £60, or even £75 a year in rates.  That is happening all over the country.</P>
    <P>We know that the Minister for Local Government introduced a scheme to grant relief from rates, but the national Exchequer does not accept responsibility for financing it.  It has to be paid for by the other ratepayers.  The result is that a great many rating authorities <Col N="728" /> never adopted the scheme.  I have come across several cases in my constituency where an old age pensioner is called upon to pay £25 or £30 a year rates out of his or her old age pension.  That is un-Christian, anti-social, and is something of which we should be thoroughly ashamed.  I may be told a county manager may write these off as hardship cases.  Sometimes he does and sometimes he does not, but there should be a relief from rates scheme applicable to those classes financed by the National Exchequer and not operated on a hit or miss basis as it is at present.</P>
    <P>There are a few other matters with which I want to deal.  During the year I came across one case which gave me great concern and it absolutely shocked me.  It is the case of an insured person who was disqualified from sickness benefit because in the year 1970 he had been serving a term of imprisonment arising out of a road traffic accident. This man, a married man with at least one child, had a first-class industrial record.  He was unfortunately involved in a fatal road traffic accident in the course of his employment when driving a truck belonging to his employers.  The judge took a serious view of the case and sentenced him to 18 months. Although he appealed &mdash; I was not the solicitor in the case&mdash;he still had to serve his 18 months imprisonment less remission.  This meant that he spent practically all of 1970 in prison.  He had only three contributions in 1970.  He was released in January, 1971, and in respect of the year 1971 he had 49 contributions.  When he applied for sickness benefit early in 1972 he was told by the Department of Social Welfare that because he had only three contributions in 1970 he would not qualify for benefit again until 5th June, 1972.  I have the letter here.  The insurance number of the case is 1334757.</P>
    <P>I think this is a national disgrace. This man fell foul of the law, and it is not right that in addition to the sentence imposed on him by the court, which he served, that our legislation should also inflict on him a monetary penalty, perhaps, some hundreds of pounds.  It is significant that this man's illness took the form of stomach ulcers.  He had <Col N="729" /> to give up his employment because of this.  Ulcers, I understand, are brought about by certain types of food and particularly by worry, and it is very likely that this man's condition was brought about by his detention in prison for 15 months or whatever it was.  This matter was brought up before but I am now dealing with it at some length.  I ask the Minister to consider this case and take steps to see that this does not happen again.  This man had an excellent industrial record.  He was released from prison early in January, 1971, and notwithstanding that he had 49 contributions in respect of 1971.  I hope the Minister will take note of this case and do something about it.</P>
    <P>There was a row some time ago between the Department and the dentists who operate the dental schemes financed or assisted by the Department. I came across insured persons in my constituency who wanted dental treatment and had to have it during the currency of that dispute.  They had to pay for this dental treatment themselves.  Apparently, the dentists concerned in the scheme, in common with other dentists in County Cavan as far as I know, withdrew from the scheme and insured persons requiring dental treatment procured it from other dentists and then the Department refused to refund the amounts paid.  If normal circumstances prevailed and there was no dispute between the Department and the Dental Association and, if in County Cavan some dentists were operating the scheme and some were not operating it, it would be then reasonable if an insured person sought and availed of the services of the dentist who was not in the scheme that he should have to pay that dentist himself. If my information is correct&mdash; the insurance number is 47083 &mdash; there were no dentists operating the scheme in County Cavan at this time and this man required the treatment and had to pay for it himself.  I say that is not socially just and the Minister should do something about it.</P>
    <P>During the year I had a case where an insured person, who lost one eye when a child and since then has been <Col N="730" /> wearing an artificial eye, applied to the Department for assistance to get a replacement of his artificial eye. I was informed by the Department that the medical and surgical appliances benefits scheme, as administered by the Department provides for a subvention towards the cost of hearing aids and contact lenses only.  In other words, a man could get assistance from the Department to get a hearing aid or contact lenses but could not get an artificial eye and would either have to pay for it himself if he needed it or go about with a gaping socket.</P>
    <P>The same letter went on to say that the applicant might be eligible for assistance under the Health Act and that information in that connection could be obtained from the North Eastern Health Board.  That letter was dated 22nd June, 1972.  I took the precaution of writing to the health board from whom I got a letter dated 23rd June which said:</P>
    <P>It is noted however that Mr. &mdash; is an insured person and I feel that he is entitled to a contribution from the Department of Social Welfare towards the cost of the appliance. He should accordingly obtain the necessary form from his local exchange for the purpose of making the application.</P>
    <P>The health board reasonably thought that being an insured person he would be helped by the Department of Social Welfare but that Department referred him to the health board.  The regulations in this respect should be changed.  That kind of case may not crop up very often but when it does, assistance should be given.</P>
    <P>I know that in the Social Welfare Act of this year the Minister has extended the allowance which is given to a prescribed relative for looking after an old age pensioner to a male relative.  This is a very well-worthwhile scheme and a move in the right direction but it is being operated rigidly and parsimoniously.  It is very difficult to qualify.  I know a case of an old lady aged 78 who, following the death of her husband, went to live with relatives, a married couple.  The woman relative did not qualify because she was married.  In a case like that it <Col N="731" /> would be well to give the relatives who take in such an old person the allowance for looking after her.  This would encourage them and in the long run it would save taxpayers and ratepayers probably £9 or £10 a week which it would cost to keep the old person in a hospital or institution.  If the scheme were operated in a more liberal manner it would be to the advantage of old people who are more at home with relatives, even distant ones, or even with neighbours who might accept them, than when living in institutions and it would save the ratepayers and taxpayers a considerable amount.  I ask the Minister to examine the scheme and try to operate it more liberally.</P>
    <P>I have also come across cases where people have been deprived of unemployment assistance.  In one case a married man was substantially deprived of assistance because he is living with a brother or relative.  A substantial amount is charged against him in respect of free board and lodging.  I find it difficult to understand why this should be.  Why should the brother of the applicant for social assistance be regarded as under an obligation to provide free board and lodging?  He is keeping him from charity until he gets some assistance from the State.  As long as the applicant is living with a relative £6 a week is charged against him with the result that he qualifies for only 85p by way of unemployment assistance.  Maybe it is alleged that he is working for the brother or rendering some service to him.  If that is the argument, it should be stated.  In a few cases that have come to my notice during the past 12 months people have either been deprived of unemployment assistance or have had the payments drastically reduced on the ground that they were in receipt of free board and lodging.  In fact, they were in receipt of charity.  The relatives were not going to pitch them out on the street.  That is no reason why the Department of Social Welfare should not come to their assistance.  The test is, if these people are unemployed, genuinely seeking work and available for work and cannot get it.  If a brother or other relative is giving a person shelter until such time as he can get work the State <Col N="732" /> should not regard that as a source of income and deprive the applicant of unemployment assistance.  I feel very strongly about this matter.  I have come across such cases on a number of occasions.  I would ask the Minister to consider the matter very carefully.</P>
    <P>In regard to old age and widows' and orphans' pensions we run into difficulties where the applicant, or the pensioner, as the case may be, transfers a farm to a son.  The pension will not be paid in that case or the deed will not be accepted in most cases until it is lodged in the Land Registry for registration.  There are many cases where it is extremely difficult and some cases where it is utterly impossible to lodged a deed for registration without going to a great deal of expense.  In some cases, even having gone to expense, it is impossible to lodge it for registration or for it to be registered because there may be relatives at the far ends of the earth who have not been heard of for some time and it is not possible for the person to whom the farm is being transferred to become registered. Once the applicant for the pension has transferred or assigned the deed to a son or daughter or other relative and the deed has been stamped it should be accepted because the applicant for the pension has then done everything he can do to divest himself of the property and to vest it in the son or daughter or other relative whom it is intended to settle on the land.  The fact of the matter is that the applicant for the pension has relinquished all claim to the land and effectively relinquished all claim to the land. There is nothing more he or she can do to relinquish that claim to the land. It may be that the beneficiary may have to take other steps to perfect his or her title but in my respectful submission that has nothing to do with the person who has given away his or her share of the land.</P>
    <P>Let me make this thing clearer by an example.  A man dies intestate.  He leaves a widow and two or three children. Under the intestacy the widow becomes entitled to two-thirds of his estate, whether it consists of a farm or not.  Supposing that one of the children is at home and two of them <Col N="733" /> are in England and one of those in England is awkward and supposing the widow signs a transfer of her two-thirds share in the farm to the son who is at home, is there any reason why that widow should not qualify for an old age pension once the deed is executed and stamped, even if it is not registered &mdash; and it may not be possible to register for a variety of reasons, because the form is registered in the name of the grandfather of the person concerned and the title may not have been dealt with for generations?</P>
    <P>I want to urge on the Minister that once the applicant has effectively divested himself of his two-thirds share in the farm by executing a deed of transfer which is duly stamped, that two-thirds share should not be further assessed as means against the applicant for old age pension.  I hope I have made that clear and I hope the Minister will act on my suggestion.</P>
    <P>There are two other points.  I understand that the Garda Síochána are dissatisfied with section 15 of the Social Welfare Act, 1972.  Deputy Desmond dealt with that and I do not think I will be casting any reflection on him if I say that he probably had the assistance of a brief which I have not available to me at the moment but which I have got.  I will satisfy myself by urging that the spirit of the Conroy Report should be implemented in regard to this matter and that if section 15 of the Social Welfare Act has done something other than was recommended by the Conroy Report, it should be rectified.</P>
    <P>Lastly, I want to ask the Minister to accept a resolution from the Irish Wheelchair Association which was passed at the annual conference of that association.  The resolution reads as follows:</P>
    <P>That the Ballinasloe and District Branch of the Irish Wheelchair Association urge the Minister for Social Welfare that the scheme whereby certain categories of old age and blind pensions are entitled to free electricity and free radio and television licences be extended so as to include deserving persons who, regardless of their age, are <Col N="734" /> suffering prolonged and substantial disability and whose income is derived wholly or mainly from social welfare benefit and assistance schemes and moreover that the regulations governing such a scheme should include the necessary safeguards against abuse of the scheme by undeserving persons.</P>
    <P>That is a reasonable request.  It is merely a request that the schemes for the free electricity and free radio and television licences should be extended to those people who are disabled for life and who are living alone and who have no source of income other than social assistance or social benefit or, I would say, the disabled person's allowance, although I know that scheme is operated by the Department of Health and not by the Department of Social Welfare.</P>
    <P>I again appeal to the Minister to urge the Government not to be satisfied with a 50p increase here or there, but to bring about a substantial increase in social service payments to people who are dependent on them, so that the gap which is increasing instead of closing between the haves and have-nots may be substantially reduced and justice done to this category. I ask him to deal with the other specific cases which I have raised and which have come to my notice during the year because I believe that they must affect a substantial number of people throughout the country.  If I find them up in my constituency, there must be other cases there and many other cases of a similar nature throughout the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. J. Lenehan Mr. J. Lenehan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lenehan</NameTxt>
      <P>As leader of my own party and shadow Minister for Social Welfare in the party, I think it only fair that I should say a few words but I do not intend to keep the House for two hours.  Deputy Desmond was so entertaining in his contribution that a new record was created in the Public Gallery in that children who came in stayed three minutes and went away, the previous record being five minutes. He read out the new social welfare bible at length and I sincerely hope that he will give a copy of it to the leader of his party because when that <Col N="735" /> leader was Minister for Social Welfare for seven years he showed tremendous interest in the social welfare recipients because in that period he increased their allowances by 12½p per week. That was the total increase and now the members of his party who seem to be so actively interested in social welfare have completely disappeared.</P>
      <P>Deputy Desmond tries to ram it down our throats that they have a policy they will implement if they get into office, which of course they will not.  He wants us to believe that if they got in, the social welfare classes would have a Utopia of their own.  I can assure them they will not have such a Utopia if that party happen to get in.  Judging by the interest shown by the party in social welfare at this moment one can well imagine the sincerity of the speech he made here today.  It is grand to attack Fianna Fáil because they were not doing what they should but why did the attackers not do something when they had the opportunity?  The old age pensions regulations were introduced by the British and there was never a Social Welfare Bill or regulation brought in until Fianna Fáil got into power in 1932.  Nobody need try to say there was because there was not.</P>
      <P>I want to thank the Minister, lest I forget to do so, for fixing up my supporters with the dole again and putting them back in his good books.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy Desmond cast all kinds of slurs on Fianna Fáil and very simply forgot that in doing so, he was casting the same slur on the majority of the people who have consistently kept Fianna Fáil in power.  He should remember that.  After his two hours reading of the bible, he conveniently got out.  There is one point on which I do agree with him, that is, that health and social welfare should be amalgamated as in Britain because there is utter confusion in regard to the various allowances.  One section will send you to the other section which will then send you back to the first section.  The £7 payable as health insurance has led to utter confusion and nobody seems able to give a direct ruling on it.  Where people are employed, the £7 is taken by way of <Col N="736" /> extra weekly contribution.  According to the regulations which I have read, if a person is employed, he is covered and if he becomes unemployed he is also covered, but if a person is employed for three months and unemployed for nine months, is he covered without paying the £7 separately?</P>
    <P>In relation to the £1,600 limit, who can know what some people are getting?  What about the cattle buyer who might be making £6,000 and who makes a return for income tax purposes of £1,000?  I presume that he can get away with the £7, while I am in the unfortunate position of having to pay £75 a year for voluntary health insurance, and the longer I keep from making a claim evidently the higher it goes because it started at less than one-third of that.  I never made a claim but up it has gone.  I would like the Minister to clarify this point because there is something peculiar about it.  It has led to utter confusion in my part of the country, and I suppose all over the country.  I have people coming to me who have to go round in circles every day because the answer given by the Department is different from the answer given by the Western Health Board of which I am a member.  The Minister should make it clear where the people stand under this scheme.</P>
    <P>With regard to social welfare allowances, there should be graduated allowances, and contributions.  As things stand, the man with £35 a week who becomes unemployed will get the same allowance as the person earning £15 a week who becomes unemployed.  I do not regard that as just and some change should be made there.</P>
    <P>Deputy Desmond raised a point which has been causing me great concern, too, the question of deserted wives.  A great many of these women, even though they have been divorced in proceedings in England, do not know that they have been divorced. There is also the point that these women evidently have not recognised the difference between desertion and divorce, and if they are foolish enough to mention to the pension officer that they were divorced they get nothing, whereas if they were cute enough to say that they were deserted, they would <Col N="737" /> get something.  Several women used the word &ldquo;divorce&rdquo; unwittingly and they suffered as a result.  I am talking about pension officers.  They are an expensive luxury, and nothing but a public menace, and we could do without them. They spend most of their time going around causing trouble, and that is about all.  A classic example of the nonsense in which they indulge is the shilling a week means which they calculate in the case of old age pensioners who stay with a son, or somebody like that, and who are not paying rent or making some direct payment.  As a result of the assessment of the shilling a week they lose five shillings a week. This is nothing but a piece of rotten gimmickry by these people.</P>
    <P>I want to congratulate the Minister on changing the regulations with regard to the special old age pension allowance of 55s.  I am glad he gave this allowance in the case of a male relative as well as a female relative, but an extraordinary position has cropped up.  If the male relative is in receipt of unemployment assistance, it is maintained now, I understand, that the old person cannot get the 55s.  If that is true, it is grossly unfair, because the young person would probably be in England if there was no work for him here, but he stays on to help the old age pensioner, hoping to get a few days' work here and there, and he then finds that if the old person applies for this allowance it is not payable.  If that is true it is not fair.  I asked two people high up in Government circles about it and one of them told me it was payable and the other one told me it was not. Something should be done about that.</P>
    <P>It often happens that an old person is living alone and were it not for the services of a next door neighbour the old person would have to go into the country home and be kept there. Surely where it can be shown that the neighbour genuinely helps out this old person an allowance should be payable.</P>
    <P>I should like to refer now to children's allowances.  For some extraordinary reason the first child gets a much lower rate than the other children.  I wonder did it ever occur to the Minister that it is far more expensive <Col N="738" /> to deal with the first child than with the second child.  The parents have to buy everything new for the first child but, when the second child arrives, the clothes and other articles of the first child will fit him. This would probably reduce the cost very substantially.  I do not know what Civil Service genius thought of giving a different rate.  The whole system is wrong and should be altered and substantially increased.</P>
    <P>Our social welfare standards are definitely below European standards. The two Deputies who spoke before me obviously read <i>The Irish Press</i> this morning.  I have not got it with me but figures were quoted in it of social welfare payments in the North and in Britain as against those here.  Statements are bandied around this House about the tremendous number of unemployed, but is anybody so simpleminded as to believe those figures? Half of those people are not unemployed at all.  I know contractors in Dublin who spend half their day looking for workers and cannot get them.</P>
    <P>The boys in the city are putting a real gimmick across on the Department. They sign on at the unemployment exchange and then they go out and work for one person for two days, for another person for two days, and for another person for two days.  This is regarded as casual labour and it is not insurable or, at least, no insurance is paid, but these &ldquo;chancers&rdquo; are taking in money hand over fist. Some of them do not work at all by day but go out and work at night.  I have often left a place at night and when I saw it the following morning I did not recognise it because it was completely changed by the midnight masqueraders.  In the hotel where I stay, one morning there was a genius painting.  He painted the outside doors while they were closed and when they were opened each of them had a wedding ring around it.  That was his method of painting.  Indeed, that was done to myself as well.</P>
    <P>There is a rather extraordinary position with regard to free electricity.  I do not know whether the Minister is aware that, if a man is under 70 years of age and holds an Old IRA medal, no matter who is living with him, he gets <Col N="739" /> free electricity.  If he is 70 years of age, unless he has qualified for free electricity under the social welfare regulations, even if he holds an Old IRA medal, he will not get free electricity. There is no justification for that.  In fact, the man who was getting it while he was under 70 years of age loses it as soon as he reaches 70 years of age, even though he holds an Old IRA medal.  I fail to see any justification for that.  I hope a change will be made.</P>
    <P>There is a manifestly unfair method of assessing means for unemployment assistance, that is, basing means on land valuation.  That is all right if a person has a small holding with a valuation of just a few pounds, but there could be a person not one-tenth as well off with a rather high valuation and he will not get anything at all. That is not just.  I know that the National Farmers' Association of the day advocated this daft scheme and it was adopted.  In a good many instances it has been completely overlooked.  It has &ldquo;ricochetted&rdquo; now and unfortunately it has not been helpful except in very few cases.  It is about time it was reviewed.  A man could have a high valuation if his lands were valued years ago.  I know a place where the valuation is £35.  It was valued as game shooting land.  Today there may be a few skylarks on it, there are certainly no other birds on it, but still the valuation is the same.  If you apply to have the valuation reduced, the beautiful excuse given is that unless it is completely water-logged or taken away by the sea, there will be no reduction in the valuation.  This must be quite common throughout the country and it is not fair.  Cases should be taken on their merits, and that is not taking cases on their merits.</P>
    <P>I will not hold up the House much longer.  There must be a tremendous interest in social welfare judging by the fact that since I came in here this morning there were never more than four Deputies in the House.  I do not see why I should blow out my brains or waste my breath talking about it either if that is the interest there is in it.  We should make an effort to bring our social welfare allowances and our <Col N="740" /> social welfare code as near as possible to those of the North.</P>
    <P>I can assure the Members of this House that the social security system here is a much greater deterrent to the people of the North coming in here than is the Catholic religion or Article 44 of the Constitution and if they are to come in, we will have to raise our social security standards to the same level as that which obtains in the North.  I appreciate that that will not be easily done and the figures quoted by Deputy Desmond this morning are utter nonsense.  If they could be substantiated it is a wonder he did not bring in some of his disciples to back him up.  He mentioned a figure of £154 million.  Possibly the figure is much higher than that if one takes into account the various perks that go with such allowances and benefits. There is a concealed figure which must be taken into consideration.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister and the Parliamentary Secretary for the substantial improvements in social welfare benefits over the last few years.  However, there is need for review by a select committee of this House.  Those elected to such a committee should be people who know something about social welfare.  Appointing ten rich men ignorant of the position would pay no dividend.  But that is what usually happens; the people appointed to boards and so forth, are generally people who have no experience at all of that into which they are examining. Think of the organisations set up to deal with itinerants.  Was any itinerant appointed?  Not at all.  As I say, review is urgent and I trust the Minister will take steps to ensure that such a review will be undertaken expeditiously. I also hope the Minister will be long enough in office to make any changes recommended as a result of such a review.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMoore" hpid="Mr. Moore Mr. Moore">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Lenehan said there were very few Deputies in the House this morning.  I do not think that is a bad thing.  It could show the confidence of the Opposition in the Minister.  It could show that they know social welfare is in good hands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is an increase in social welfare this year.  It is heartening to know <Col N="741" /> that each year the Minister has found it possible to increase benefits and to spread benefits over a wider area. The percentage of GNP allocated to social welfare is also increasing and, even allowing for inflation, beneficiaries are now doing better.  This is not something about which to be complacent.  In every society there are always people who need help.  As the Minister pointed out, it is not true that our benefits will have to equal those paid in other EEC countries. Naturally every country will aim to give the best possible services, but every country will remain individual, retaining its own national characteristics, characteristics which must be looked at in providing services.  We will have to have a close examination of those categories needing help most. The Minister told us on an earlier occasion that he is preparing a new social welfare code.  We will not just copy the European pattern; we will have to solve our own problems in our own way.  It would be a great mistake to have a blanket social welfare policy because age groups vary from country to country and the possibility is that we might have more aged people than other countries.  These of course, would have to get special consideration.</P>
    <P>Are we doing enough for the handicapped, either physically or mentally? One might answer that we can never do enough for any person who is handicapped.  The Minister has not got a bottomless purse and we must allocate the moneys available where they will do most good.  Great work is being done by voluntary committees. The State gives help to these committees.  I would like to see more help given to them because local committees are much more <i>au fait</i> with local conditions and problems than are those who may be remote from the centre of operations.  We must always ensure that the dignity of the social welfare recipient is fully safeguarded. We must never look on people merely as statistics.  We must always have a humane approach. No one will object to more money being spent on social welfare but, while we would welcome better benefits, politics being what they are, we <Col N="742" /> have to advert to the fact that better benefits would mean increasing taxation and this is not so easily accepted by people.  However, in their determination to give us a really good social welfare service the Government will never be afraid to impose the necessary increased taxation in order to improve the service.</P>
    <P>A comparison has been made here this morning between the welfare service here and that in the North of Ireland.  If this is examined very closely it will be seen that we are heading towards parity.  I do not begrudge the people in the North the fine welfare service they have, but in the South we must do it on our own. We are not in receipt of any subventions from another government.  It will be seen, therefore, that we are doing far better with the resources at our disposal than are some other people whose social services are vaunted not necessarily by themselves but by other people who wish to make comparisons.</P>
    <P>It may be said that we have not done all that we wanted to do but, apart from the actual cash payments in social welfare, we have introduced, over the past few years such facilities as free travel, free electricity and television licences and some other smaller benefits.  If one assesses all these benefits, our social welfare services will bear comparison with those outside.  If we dare to praise our social welfare services we may be accused of complacency, which, in my view, would not be justified, but we can hardly be accused of hypocrisy, in so far as the Government and the other Members on this side of the House do want to improve the social welfare services and have the courage to go to the people and ask them to accept the heavier taxation necessary.</P>
    <P>One readily accepts increased taxation if one knows of cases in which people will benefit directly, and Members of the House will know of many such cases.  The public at large may not know of individual cases and therefore may question the increased taxation. However, the Minister, in introducing his Estimate each time has given a very clear picture of what the Department and the Government are trying to <Col N="743" /> do.  The result is that the social services here have increased and improved greatly, particularly in the last decade. It is our ambition to go on improving them all the time and when we become a member of the EEC in January we shall see a great change in the thinking of our people on social welfare and allied subjects.</P>
    <P>The old concept of social welfare is going out.  As more and more leisure time becomes available to the people because of progress in science and technology, the Department of Social Welfare will perhaps become one of the most important branches of our Government.  I do not suggest it is not important; it is very important indeed, but with the change in the structure of society we must look forward to the time when the working week will have shortened a great deal, when people will have more time for leisure and when the retiring age from work will be much earlier.</P>
    <P>While we would all welcome more leisure time and higher standards for the people in the social welfare category, we have got to look ahead much more.  Who knows but that in a few years' time the whole structure of Government may be changed.  People will want more money to spend on increased leisure time.  Therefore the burden of financing social welfare will assume greater and greater proportions of the national budget.  This, of course, is a good thing.</P>
    <P>To get down to the more mundane facts which operate now, very often there is criticism of the Department for delays in dealing with claims.  In most cases I am sure this is unavoidable. I will say for the Department that whenever I have to approach them, which is very often, I find there civil servants who are most anxious to help and they will go to great lengths to answer a query.  While this takes time, a Deputy of this House or a civil servant is not waiting in fear, perhaps, of a decision, but the old age or blind pensioner may be waiting for that money to come from the Department. For an old age pensioner a week is a long time to wait.</P>
    <P>It must be said in fairness to the Department that the scope of social <Col N="744" /> welfare has increased tremendously, with many thousands more people registered in the Department's files than were there three or four years ago, and it may be that the staff there has not increased commensurately.  Old people may be impatient at times and it takes all the skill of the civil servant or a Member of this House to assure them that their case is being dealt with. A man who has worked up to the age of 70 and who has his full stamps or, perhaps, the widow of such an insured worker, is naturally annoyed or apprehensive if delays occur.  The officers of the Department, with the co-operation of Deputies who write there, should put as priority number one the removal of delay in dealing with the claims of the aged or the infirm.  They are cut to the minimum but there is a limit on how quickly one can deal with these cases.  One can understand both sides of the story.  In the future, if Europe has anything to offer regarding streamlining social services we should learn from them.  We are a member of the International Social Security Association and we are bound to learn something from which we can benefit and, in return, they may well learn something from us.  It is encouraging that on the international scene there is such an association of which we are a very active member and that it will mean a better service for the people of the EEC countries and particularly for our own people.</P>
    <P>It may be said that since the State was founded 50 years ago we have not made the progress we should have made.  This is not true: this State pioneered the children's allowances scheme and we had widows' pensions before many of the advanced countries, as they are called.  We have already contributed to the betterment of schemes in other countries.  One can never eradicate the human problem created when a wife is deserted or when a father or mother dies.  We have heard much about the problem of the deserted wife.  Present trends do not hold out much hope that the number of erring husbands will be reduced; the problem may well increase and therefore it will have to be examined in great detail.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="745" /> Last year the Minister introduced certain benefits for deserted wives.  Unfortunately the problem will grow and if the laws of this or neighbouring States cannot bring deserting husbands to justice we must ensure that wives and children left behind will not suffer. I should like to see the Minister, in co-operation with some women's societies and charitable societies which deal with this problem, examining the matter in greater detail, not so as to relieve the husband who clears out and shirks his responsibilities but so that we, who cherish the family unit so much, could ensure that even if one of the partners in the family has shed his responsibilities every effort will be made to show that we really care for the wife and children who have been deserted.</P>
    <P>This also applies to widows but their case is more straightforward. While the benefits provided will probably never be sufficient, at least each year they are increased.  It is a proud boast of Members on this side of the House that such schemes as the widows' and orphans' pensions and children's allowances were pioneered by this Government.  It has been suggested that we have changed our social policies but any reading of the Minister's Estimates for years past will show that this is not true and that we are still pursuing the ideal of a society in which the weakest member will have the greatest protection which the State can afford.  The problem of the aged is very great, especially in cities, and I suggest the Minister should consider how to relieve old aged people, especially those living alone and facing rent problems.  If such a person lives in a local authority dwelling no harsh rent will apply, but there are many hundreds, if not thousands, of elderly people in this city living in rooms.  They do not want to leave the room which has been their home.  They may be paying a very high rent.  If the local authorities were to contribute to that rent it might have an inflationary effect on rents as a whole and would also mean that the local authority would have to find the money out of the rates.  This would impose a burden on other old people who must pay <Col N="746" /> rates.  The Minister might consider extending a benefit to local authorities to ease the rent through the health boards, perhaps, since they are empowered to give some assistance in this respect.  Where a reduced rent is given on grounds of age and inability to meet outgoings, the State might well come in with a scheme to ensure that old people especially would have adequate accommodation at the lowest possible cost.</P>
    <P>The humanity of the Department is exemplified in all the new measures brought in to ease the burden of those who must apply for help.  The Minister will have a great opportunity in the new code which was mentioned of really examining any defects left in the social welfare code and of seeing how they can be eliminated.  I speak for the city of which I have most experience and I find that one can come across some tragic cases of old people living alone and very often, if they live in old houses with open fires, they are in great danger. One dreads to think what may happen if an old person goes too near the fire and is burned.  We have a scheme for home help and while this is a good scheme it must be greatly expanded.  At present it may only mean that a neighbour gets some compensation by the health board for looking after an old person for an hour or two daily.  We should remember that if the old person is removed to an institution the cost of keeping him there will greatly exceed anything paid for the home help service.</P>
    <P>In referring to this aspect, I should like to pay tribute to the charitable bodies throughout the country who provide meals-on-wheels and engage in other such activities.  Ecumenism is referred to frequently nowadays. The various welfare societies show the greatest ecumenism.  In my constituency there is an organisation composed of persons of all denominations who are providing a wonderful service for the aged and others. Of course, there is a State subsidy but there is always room for the voluntary organisation.  A Marxist may say that such help is merely bolstering up an imperfect system but those countries that accept the <Col N="747" /> teaching of Marx have not improved on the work of charitable organisations. The world is becoming increasingly materialistic.  In our case we should combine State effort with the effort of individual citizens in order to ensure that no aged, handicapped or infirm person will suffer because of age or infirmity.  The test of a society is its care for the weaker sections.  The combination of State effort and the effort of charitable organisations may provide a solution to the problems of persons who are handicapped through age or physical disability.  We should show to Europe how we operate social services in keeping with our traditions.  I am not trying to minimise the duty that the State has to provide for those citizens who cannot provide for themselves.</P>
    <P>It may be suggested that some of the services are abused.  Of course, they are abused but that abuse is not a condemnation of the system.  The Minister mentioned that prosecutions were taken in some cases.  There is only a tiny fraction of social welfare recipients who abuse the services and in some cases that abuse may be due to ignorance, as I am sure the Department would recognise.  Therefore, it must be accepted that prosecutions occurred only where they were fully justified.  We should not be disheartened by abuse of the system on the part of a small number of persons.</P>
    <P>The total cost of social welfare for the year is about £150 million. That is a substantial proportion of the total expenditure of the State. We must ensure that the provision is increased next year and that the percentage of total expenditure allocated to social welfare does not decline.</P>
    <P>The Minister has shown deep concern for and interest in the Department. When the new code is published we will see improved social welfare services and our services will stand comparison with any in the world.  In some European States there are strange anomalies.  In some State we were told that people had social welfare services from the womb to the tomb. The fact must be faced that in those <Col N="748" /> countries that have no problem in providing the necessary finance, it has not been found possible to solve all the social problems that arise.  Why should this be the case?  I ask that question, not in order to criticise the countries concerned but to ensure that it will not happen here.  One of the reasons is that the citizens become completely dependent on the State for social welfare. This is a grave error.  No State can provide a full scale of social welfare services without the help of voluntary social workers.  We can learn from Europe and we hope that Europe can learn something from us.  Disability affects persons no matter where they may live.  There is an onus on Governments to provide the best social welfare structure. In our case we are going the right way about it.  If at times we are disheartened this is understandable.  It is encouraging if the annual Estimate shows that we are making progress.  It may be suggested that the progress is not at a sufficiently high rate but who is to say what the rate should be?  If it is suggested that the progress should be at the rate of an extra 5 per cent of the GNP, some will say that that is not enough.  When we can say that there is no person in need of care or help who is not getting that care or help, then we can be satisfied.  I know from experience that it is impossible to attain the ideal society but it is our duty to strive to perfect society.</P>
    <P>I am satisfied with the Estimate on this occasion.  This year the Estimate shows an increase of £12 million.  I hope that next year the Minister will find it possible to increase the payments to those who need such increases and will also think up some new ideas, such as the free travel for pensioners scheme. This has transformed the lives of old people in the city because some people never got much chance of travelling outside the city.  One hears nowadays the stories of where they have been. It is not the price of things in life that counts but the quality of life, and it must be the duty of any society dedicated to the principles we hold to strive all the time to improve the quality of life and not just the standard of living.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="749" /> We owe this to our own people who have worked and by their work have created and contributed to the national wealth.  We must ensure that the person who is in any way handicapped, such as by blindness, which I emphasise all the time, will be given the very best the State can afford. In this matter, apart from the payment of a pension to the sightless, we should go in more and more for training these men and women.  I know that quite a lot is being done at the moment but I think we should expand greatly.  With the advances in science and technology many benefits exist now which would help the blind person to ease this handicap.  If we keep abreast of the advances on that scene, sightless people can look forward with hope and encouragement to the day when the handicap of being sightless will be reduced to the very minimum, when the State will invest, as I call it, in these people because the vast majority of sightless persons have the possibility of becoming fully trained in some craft or art.  We want to do this not because they will be able to go to work but because if they can be employed at some trade or craft which they are capable of undertaking, they will become equal citizens with the rest of us who work for a living, will contribute to the national wealth and, above all, will fully realise that the State recognises their importance in our society and that the State is going to invest more and more money on their behalf so that the State can acknowledge its obligations and duties.</P>
    <P>I am sure the people of this part of the country will not complain about increased taxation when they are assured that the money taken in taxation will mean a better social welfare code for the aged and handicapped. Then we will be living up to our profession that we stand for social justice.  As I have said, no country in the world, socialist or capitalist, has perfect social welfare services and when I hear people talking of socialism, I often think they mean social justice but I am somewhat confused about this.  As we enter Europe, in a few weeks' time, we are going to learn more about European social welfare <Col N="750" /> services, and I hope we will do so, as the other eight European countries may well learn from us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to take the opportunity to deal with a couple of matters which I have raised previously when the opportunity presented itself and which I shall continue to raise until such time as the complaints I intend making are either rectified or ameliorated.  The first matter is discrimination by the Department in the case of domestic workers.  I have had occasion to raise this matter before and to point out to the Minister that his Department discriminate in the benefit payable to domestic workers in that they do not qualify for unemployment benefit in the same way as other workers.  This has not been justified in any way whatever by the Department and there seems to be a Victorian hangover which is totally unjust and completely at variance with what should be the standards applied by the Department.  They are charged with looking after the social welfare of our people and if they discriminate against a weak section, they live a lie in regard to their name.  I would ask the Minister to look again seriously and urgently at this question and bring the benefits of domestic workers up to the same level and see to it that they become entitled to exactly the same as any other worker.</P>
      <P>The domestic worker, as she falls out of employment, cannot draw unemployment benefit, unless she has a very long history of stamping.  I do not know what the theoretical justification for this discrimination is.  I presume that there is a Victorian attitude in the Department which assumes that domestic workers can immediately become gainfully employed and consequently should not have to draw unemployment benefit.  If this is so, it is a type of attitude which is completely outmoded.  It is completely wrong to see that type of thought in relation to this particular type of employment.  It is a category of employment that has been downgraded for too long and has suffered as a result and the Department should set a lead in their attitude to the rest of the community in regard to this type of work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="751" /> It is a serious hardship on a person in domestic work who might not be trained for any other employment and who finds herself out of work through no fault of her own, not to get unemployment benefit.  She will not qualify for unemployment assistance so far as I know and she is driven back to look for home assistance. This again may or may not be paid, depending on the subjective assessment of an official of the health board and for an insured person, and a domestic worker is an insured person, to be left to depend on the subjective charity of a local authority official is, to my mind, altogether wrong and does not stand up in this day and age when we are becoming so conscious of our duties to the less well off sections of the community and professing to have the ambition to bring our benefits into line with those prevailing throughout the rest of Europe.</P>
    <P>As I say, it is a serious gap in the services provided by the Department with regard to domestic workers. It is, in fact, more than a serious gap; it is an actual scandal, a scandalous situation, and it is regrettable that although the matter has been raised frequently, the Minister has not seen fit to take any steps to rectify the position.  I appeal to him again to take the necessary steps to rectify it. I do not think legislation is necessary because the matter can be cured by regulation.  These regulations should be made without any delay whatever.</P>
    <P>The next matter that I would like to mention is one I have raised before. It relates to the whole administration of the occupational injuries benefits scheme.  I make no apology for raising it, though I may have to be boring by virtue of repetition because the operation of this scheme is causing a certain amount of hardship to injured workers.  I should like to briefly recap on what the situation was before the occupational injuries scheme was introduced.</P>
    <P>Prior to that if a workman sustained an injury in the course of his employment, and this was separate altogether from any question of negligence or his common law rights, he sought his <Col N="752" /> remedy through the Circuit Court. The Circuit Court tried the case in much the same way as it would try any litigation coming before it.  The Circuit Court made certain findings. It would make a finding of total incapacity or of partial incapacity or it could dismiss the workman's claim on the ground that there was no incapacity proved.  It could also be dismissed on the ground that the accident did not happen in the course of the worker's employment.  That was a rare enough finding.  If the court found total incapacity it made an award of a weekly sum which was altogether inadequate but that was not the court's fault because the weekly sum was prescribed by statute. At least the workman knew exactly his position.  He had his finding of total incapacity and there had been a hearing in open court in which the workman had the benefit of trained advocates.  He had the satisfaction of knowing that his case had been heard by an independent arbiter in the person of the Circuit Court judge, a person skilled in listening to two contending cases and making his mind up impartially as between them.  He had the benefit too, of having both the medical evidence for himself and the medical evidence adduced by the employer sifted by the advocates on each side.  Generally, there was a feeling of satisfaction after a Circuit Court hearing that the case had been thoroughly and justly tried.  The result was inevitably unsatisfactory because of the low level of award which the court was empowered to give but, apart from that, the finding left a feeling of satisfaction, a feeling that justice was done and was seen to be done.</P>
    <P>If the court found, on the other hand, that the workman was only partially injured or was making a recovery the court could make a finding of partial incapacity and it would direct the workman to return to work. But if the workman could show to the court that there was no suitable work available to him, that his partial incapacitation prevented him from obtaining suitable employment &mdash; and in 99 cases out of 100 it did because the average person coming before the <Col N="753" /> court on a workman's compensation claim was a manual labourer and no employer wants a manual labourer unless he is 100 per cent fit&mdash;generally the position was that he had not any difficulty in satisfying the court that he was unable to obtain light work. The court then had power to make a finding of partial incapacity but could order it to be treated as total.  The workman then went on receipt of full benefit again even though it was recognised that he was not fully incapacitated. Nevertheless, the workman was entitled to maximum benefit. Again, it was not the court's fault that this maximum benefit was a ridiculously low figure.  So the position remained.  The employer, if he felt that the workman's condition should have improved, was entitled to have his case reviewed at any future date by the Circuit Court.  Again, if the workman was out of benefit for unduly long and thought that his incapacity entitled him to go back to court he, too, could come back for review.</P>
    <P>That would be in the situation where the court decided that he was not entitled to benefit.  Each party had a right to come back for review and likewise each party had a right to come to a settlement and to redeem the weekly payment.  If the workman felt it would be more to his advantage to negotiate with the employer, he was free to do so and the employer was free to meet him and pay him a lump sum.  That ended the workman's claim for good and all.  The workman, in making that decision, had the benefit of his medical and legal advice.  Very often it was an equitable end to a claim particularly the type of claim where there was a finding of partial incapacity which was being treated as total.  The workman might, perhaps, have some other source of income or the lump sum which he could get by negotiation might start him in a small line of business or some other occupation which would suit his partial incapacity.</P>
    <P>Some years ago it was decided to remove this entire scheme of workmen's compensation from the ambit of the courts and bring it within the jurisdiction of the Department of <Col N="754" /> Social Welfare and we had set up the occupational injuries code that we now know.  As it is, it is not working as fairly in favour of the workman as the old workmen's compensation worked under the courts.  I may be accused of special pleading in so far as my profession brought me into the courts but I can assure the Minister that my remarks are not motivated by any selfish professional interests.  At present if a workman is injured in the course of his employment he is initially entitled to occupational injury benefit for six months.  The rates are prescribed by regulation and are considerably more generous than were the rates under the old workmen's compensation code.</P>
    <P>That was not the fault of the code, that was the fault of the statute, the fault, if you like, of the Minister's Department in that they did not revise those weekly payments upwards.  They have now done so and the weekly payments are not inadequate, I do not say they are generous, and the workman is not substantially worse off during his injury than when he was employed.  After six months his occupational injury benefit ceases and he becomes entitled to disablement benefit provided his injury still continues and at this stage he has a medical examination for the purpose of assessing the extent of his disablement.  These examinations are carried out by the medical officers of the Department of Social Welfare.  I do not want to be unjust to those officers but I feel bound to voice what I hear and that is widespread criticism of the findings made by these officers.  Very often findings are made which seem to have no connection with the facts of life.  Findings are made in relation to an injury which would suggest that the person with that injury should be back at work when common sense indicates the opposite.  There is considerable dissatisfaction with the medical referee system.  Whether the referees are constrained by the system or whether this is the way in which they practise professionally I am not prepared to say.  I do not know.  All I can tell the Minister is that there is considerable dissatisfaction with the medical referee system.  In practice, if the workman is dissatisfied with the referee's assessment <Col N="755" /> of his degree of disablement he is entitled to appeal to an appeals officer.</P>
    <P>This has to be contrasted with the previous system where the hearing was before a Circuit Court judge.  The appeals officer is an official of the Department.  I am not saying that he would not be independent or that he would not give his decision entirely unbiassed or impartially as between the workman and the Department. What I am saying is that he does not appear to the workman to be impartial and, consequently, justice is not seen to be done even if it is being done.  It is a serious fault in the system that allows a citizen to come into contention with a Department of State.  It is essential for the citizen's confidence in the institutions of the State that he would realise that justice is being done.  This system of appeals to an appeals officer on the assessment of disablement benefit or the degree of disablement does not permit this to be done.  The hearing is before an appeals officer, usually in a room of an employment exchange. The workman is entitled to attend and may bring with him a legal adviser.  He is entitled also to produce medical evidence.  He may be sworn or may not be sworn.  The format of the hearing is informal and is one sided in the sense that the appeals officer is hearing only the workman's case.  The appeals officer's questions are directed to probing the validity of the case that the workman is putting forward and the main part of the hearing consists of questioning by the appeals officer.</P>
    <P>While this may be the proper fulfilment of the function of the appeals officer, it gives to the workman the impression that the questions asked are antagonistic towards him.  Of course the questions must be slightly antagonistic if they are probing of their nature.  It would be far better if the format of court procedure could be introduced at that stage so that there would be somebody in court to make the case on behalf of the Department rather than having the <Col N="756" /> appeals officer appear to be making the case.</P>
    <P>It would be an improvement in the present system if the medical evidence obtained by the Department could be adduced at the hearing of the appeal and that it could be subject to cross-examination by or on behalf of the workman.  In my opinion the right of the workman to bring a legal adviser is only a sop because there is nothing that a legal adviser can do other than present the case to the appeals officer, to whom the facts of the case are already known so that whatever the representative might say would be superfluous.  Examination of the workman is conducted by the appeals officer.  There is no medical evidence to the contrary and consequently the medical evidence, which is the kernel of the case, is not available to be questioned by the workman.  That creates a feeling of dissatisfaction and a sense that less than justice is being done in these cases of appeals against the degree of assessment of disablement.  This is a matter that requires consideration by the Department.</P>
    <P>One of the better features of the old workmen's compensation code was that there was a full hearing.  There were two sides in contention and there was a full sifting of all the facts relating to both sides&mdash;the employer and the workman.  When a case had been dealt with there was the feeling that justice had been done.  This is missing from the present procedure and I suggest to the Minister that there is an urgent need to restore it, otherwise the confidence of workmen in the present system is being shaken.  I do not think that that is the intention of the Department of Social Welfare.  They would not wish that to be the case because the motivation in changing these cases from the courts to the Department was to secure a better deal for the workman. To some extent this has been the case because the benefits were increased, but that could have been done through the courts.  In another way it has not been an improvement because the workman's right to argue his case and his entitlement to seeing justice being done have been diminished greatly.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="757" /> Also, instead of having the assessment of disablement made by an independent tribunal in the person of the Circuit Court judge after hearing the merits and the medical evidence of a particular case, we now have a situation where there is a scale of disablement laid down.  This is both self-contradictory and ridiculous.  If the medical officer examines a workman and ascertains that he has lost one foot and has an end-bearing stump, instead of some independent person deciding on what is the capacity of that man for work, a regulation says that the person is 30 per cent disabled.  Again, if a workman loses one eye and if there are not any complications, he is held to be 40 per cent disabled.  However, if he loses the vision of one eye he is held to be only 30 per cent disabled.  The whole point of having an eye is to be able to see through it.  So far as the workman is concerned he is in the same position whether he has no eye or whether he has an eye through which he cannot see.  Consequently, the degree of disablement should be the same.</P>
    <P>Apart from that contradiction between the two rates there is the difficulty that it is impossible to set objecttively degrees of disablement.  Each case must be assessed separately in the light of the medical evidence available, in the light of the capacity of the workman, of his background and environment and of the opportunities available to him.  These things are not being done.  There may be some cases in which the scale of assessment works generously in favour of a workman but in my experience it works to his detriment.</P>
    <P>Degrees of disablement are arrived at irrespective of the earning capacity of the workman.  I was amazed to hear recently from the Department that the test is not one of earning capacity.  In the case of one man who had a back injury there was a finding that he was able for some work.  It was pointed out to the Department that a manual labourer suffering from a back injury is not capable of any work or, at most, of very light work but that there was no light work available.  It was an injustice to that man, as was pointed out also to the Department, to assess him as being capable of light work when such <Col N="758" /> was not available.  The Department's reply was that the test is his capacity for work and not whether work is available to him.  Again, this is a change from the days of the workmen's compensation code.  Under that code this man could have been assessed as being partially incapacitated but the court was entitled to treat the disablement as total.  There seems to be no analogous provision under the occupational injuries code and this results in serious hardship to injured workmen.</P>
    <P>I would suggest to the Minister that these prescribed degrees of disablement should be scrapped.  I find it very difficult not to find anomalies in the system. If a person loses all of the index finger of either the right or the left hand his degree of disablement is assessed to be 14 per cent.  There is a great difference between losing the index finger of the right hand and that of the left hand. An important consideration, too, is the person's occupation.  The full and proper use of an index finger might be essential but that is not provided for in the regulations.  There is the position, also, where the amputation of a foot, provided it resulted in an end-bearing stump, is assessed at only a 30 per cent disablement.  This does not take into account numerous extraneous factors which could prescribe that the loss of a foot would, in effect, be a 100 per cent disablement.  Yet we go back and we find that loss of a hand and a foot represents 100 per cent disablement. That is fair enough.  It is quite obvious that that must be so, but it seems to me that any person who losses a foot must be more than 30 per cent disabled. Amputation below the knee with a stump extending five inches is only 40 per cent disablement.</P>
    <P>This schedule of prescribed degrees of disablement is riddled with contradictions. It is quite impossible to provide degrees of disablement in a vacuum.  The degree of disablement can only be assessed in relation to the disabled person.  It is not possible to do justice and to say that because a person suffered such a type of injury he must thereby be X per cent disabled. That person's injury must be examined in the context of his own innate strength, in the context of his <Col N="759" /> employment, of his education, of his capacity for retraining, and it is most unjust to try to provide a table of disablement.</P>
    <P>There is one serious omission from the table of disablement, if we are to have one, that is, no provision whatever is made for the condition of a psychosomatic illness which very often ensues following a serious physical injury. If a workman suffers a severe amputation, or a chronic back injury, he may be so long out of work that, while the clinical symptoms may disappear, there will be strong and definite psychosomatic symptoms, so strong and so definite&mdash;and while they may be subjective, nevertheless they are medically recognised&mdash;that the workman is as incapable of working at this late stage as he was when he sustained the injury.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether the Department are entitled to take that into account.  It certainly is not listed in the prescribed degrees of disablement, but it may be possible to take it into account where there is common case that there is 100 per cent disablement or where the Department's referee finds 100 per cent disablement.</P>
    <P>These are some criticisms I make of the occupational injuries code, criticisms which I think are valid and justified.  I have made them before, and I will continue to make them until such time as the matters concerned are rectified or ameliorated. It is not beyond the wit of the Department to devise answers to meet the criticisms.  If the criticisms are not valid I should be interested to hear a reply to them, and reasons why they are not valid, and why they are not sustainable.  I should be anxious to hear are there very serious administrative grounds for refusing to rectify them.  We are entitled to hear these things because this is the Department of Social Welfare, the emphasis being on welfare.  These matters have to do with the welfare of the injured workman.</P>
    <P>When the medical referee examines an injured workman&mdash;and I make a distinction as between an injured person and a sick person&mdash;at the end of the initial six months' injury benefit, <Col N="760" /> it should be compulsory that this examination should take place in consultation with the injured person's own medical adviser.  The background knowledge of the man's history which his own medical adviser must necessarily have could be of immense assistance to the Department's referee in making his diagnosis.  It would give confidence to the injured workman that this was not a one-sided operation and that justice was being seen to be done in that sphere anyway.  This would involve a simple administrative change.  It might involve the payment of some guineas to the workman's own medical adviser but, when we consider the millions which are being spent under the new health boards, those few guineas would be well spent.</P>
    <P>The next point I want to make is in regard to future social welfare benefits. It is admitted&mdash;it cannot be denied&mdash;that our benefits are considerably less than those prevailing not merely in Europe but in another part of this country.  Next spring in our Budget we will have a tremendous opportunity to redress that imbalance in so far as our Exchequer will be saved the agricultural subsidies which we pay out to our farmers at present. It has been calculated that the saving will be in the region of £30 million.  I would impress on the Minister that the way to spend this saving is on the weaker sections of the community, on the social walfare recipients.  I would ask him to have the Government make a firm commitment at this stage that this Exchequer saving, this sum of £30 million, will be spent on bringing our social welfare payments up to the standards pertaining in other parts of Europe.</P>
    <P>They will not be able to do that completely but there are certain fields in which they could give substantial increases.  It would be a matter for the Department with their intimate knowledge of their own subject, to recommend to the Minister where the increases should be given.  It would be a matter for him, I suppose, having regard to the political exigencies of the current situation, to decide where they will be given and at what rate.  There is no doubt, to my mind, <Col N="761" /> that the way the £30 million should be spent is on increasing social welfare benefits to help the members of our community who are, by definition, less well off.  They will be pensioners, persons in receipt of unemployment assistance, people who are ill, people who are injured, and parents of families.  It is in these areas that this money should be spent.</P>
    <P>I would suggest to the Minister that it would be good for morale and it would be a big psychological weapon in the battle against inflation to be able to say: &ldquo;Come next spring your benefit will go up by X per cent.&rdquo; It would be an important factor in any discussions that may take place over the next months in regard to Northern Ireland.  One of the big complaints up there is: &ldquo;Why should we join with you down there when we would be so much worse off?&rdquo; If at this stage we could say we will have £30 million next spring and it will be allocated to bring up all these services, that would be to our advantage. The Minister should make that decision and pronouncement now.  He should say clearly that the money will be used for that purpose.</P>
    <P>Some time ago the Minister announced that wage related benefits would be introduced.  I am very glad of that.  It was suggested in Fine Gael's policy as long ago as 1965, as far as I recall, when it was pointed out that, unless social welfare benefits were wage related, serious injustice could be done to a person on a comparatively high wage if we had to drop from that to a low sickness or injury benefit.  We have had the announcement and we look forward to seeing it being implemented.  I urge the Minister to implement it as quickly as possible.</P>
    <P>I should like to see the age of pension reduced.  We must reduce it if we are to be in line with Great Britain and the rest of Europe.  This, again, was suggested in Fine Gael policy as far back as 1965.  It was suggested that, as a first step, the qualifying age for an old age pension should be reduced to 67 years with a view to eventually bringing it down to 65 years.  It was spelled out in that policy statement in 1965 how this could be done.  The <Col N="762" /> financial implications were spelled out. I suggest that now is the time to follow the lead given.  It has been followed in regard to wage related benefits and I would ask the Minister to reduce the qualifying age for old age pensions to 67 initially and, if possible, to 65. There has been some progress in that retirement pensions have been introduced at 65.  That is a welcome development and there is no reason why old age pensions should not come in at a lower age at the moment.</P>
    <P>I should like to pay tribute to the officers of the Minister's Department, particularly those whom I might describe as the officers in the field.  My experience of social welfare and investigating officers is that they approach their work in a humane and understanding spirit.  They understand the ordinary problems of ordinary people. They are able to converse and communicate with ordinary people.  As I say, they bring a spirit of humanity and tolerance to their work.  It has been brought to my attention that a certain section of the officers are prejudiced <i>vis-á-vis</i> their colleagues; these are officers who have recently retired. There was a retrospective pay increase for social welfare officers and supervisors. This award has been paid to serving officers.  The arrears have been paid, but the award has not been paid to those who retired.  This is an injustice. Now that they have retired and are in receipt of lower incomes it is important that justice should be done by them.  Any arrears due should be paid immediately.  The amount must be comparatively small in relation to the total budget for wages and salaries. I urge the Minister to insist on his colleagues in the Department of Finance paying these officers without delay.  They gave many years of loyal service and they deserve in their retirement to get whatever is coming to them and get it quickly.  Indeed, they should get it in advance of even serving personnel.</P>
    <P>Another point I would like to mention is in relation to recognition by the Department of deeds of family settlement.  Up to some years ago the Department would not recognise a transfer of a farm by a father to <Col N="763" /> a son or an aunt to a nephew if the Department was of the opinion that the transfer was effected so as to qualify the transferor for an old age pension.  In other fords, if the transferor transferred his farm he then had no means and was technically <i>prima facie</i> entitled to an old age pension.  If the Department felt the transfer was carried out for this purpose, it could ignore it and could assess the applicant with the value of the farm, notwithstanding its transfer. There was a softening of this policy some years ago.  Transfers were always recognised in the case of small farms but, as I say, there was a softening of this policy and, by and large, transfers of this nature are now accepted and the transferor qualifies for an old age pension.  But there are still some cases in which the Department is not prepared to recognise this settlement.  If certain rights are retained, perhaps rights of residence, rights of support, rights to weekly payments, these may have the effect of disentitling the transferor or reducing the amount to which he is entitled.  Sometimes these rights exist only on paper and, after a number of years, when the transferor is satisfied the new arrangement is working well, he may have to release these rights, possibly to encourage the transferee and make his title absolute. He may have to release the rights in order to leave the title documents free to the transferee to obtain money on the strength of them.</P>
    <P>In these cases, particularly in the case of farms of larger valuation, the Department will not recognise these transfers or outright settlements and it still takes the view that they are affected in order to qualify for a pension.  I am aware that facts may be adduced to show that is not the case, but it is extremely difficult to produce facts to show the contrary if the Department wants to believe something else.  The amount involved in such transfers is so small in relation to the Minister's total budget that all settlements and releases of charges retained under settlements should be recognised for pension purposes.  This <Col N="764" /> is desirable socially.  It is desirable that the older generation should pass control to the younger generation as early as possible.  Young farmers are now much more mature and well capable of managing large farms and it is socially desirable that they should be put in control at as early an age as possible.  One way to speed up the process would be for the Department to recognise these transfers and accept that the transferor, having parted with his property, is entitled to an old age non-contributory pension.  I urge the Minister to arrange that all such transfers are recognised by his Department.</P>
    <P>As I said, I pay tribute to the work of the Minister's officers, particularly those in the field.  The Department has to deal with many areas of considerable sensitivity.  Because of problems of accountability, both personal and financial, it is necessary to devise schemes applicable on a global scale and, when that is necessary, then there are bound to be sensitive areas, hard cases which are missed under the bureaucratic system.  That cannot be avoided because of reasons of accountability. Nevertheless, I would ask the Minister when any of these hard cases or sensitive areas not covered by the regulations come to light to deal with them sympathetically and, if possible, to amend the regulations to let these come within the ambit of social welfare. I ask that without a great deal of hope remembering that the Minister refuses to regard a divorced wife as a deserted wife.  I think that is a shocking blot on the record of his Department.  It makes one despair of the goodwill of the Minister.  I urge him to remember that welfare should be the keynote of his Department rather than the strict interpretation or implementation of a rule or regulation. He will always have the backing of the House and the public if his Department is seen to administer its affairs humanely and without regard to the strict letter of the law but with a high regard for the spirit of the law.</P>
    <P>There are great opportunities for the Department to ease the lives of a great many who have it hard.  The officers in the field do their best but <Col N="765" /> they are constrained by the regulations. The Minister has power to ensure that the regulations do not work hardship and I appeal to him to use his power to ensure that.  I would also ask him to place domestic workers on the same level as all other workers and I would ask him to look at the system of appeals in the case of disablement benefit assessment. These are two areas in which there is room for improvement.  I have indicated the problems.  It is for the Minister to devise the solutions.  Solutions can be devised to ensure that justice is not only done but is seen to be done, particularly in the case of injured workmen.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. J. Brennan) Joseph Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. J. Brennan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to pay tribute to the constructive approach to the workings of my Department and to those Deputies who made useful suggestions for the benefit of the working of the Department or the expansion of the social welfare code in the immediate future. Most Deputies are aware that we are about to accelerate the pace of development and expansion of the social welfare code.  I am not trying to be naïve, neither am I being unkind, when I suggest that many speakers appeared to be trying to &ldquo;jump the gun&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would ask Deputies not to be always running down our schemes.  I have occasion to attend conferences abroad on social welfare every year; there was one not so many weeks ago in The Hague.  I have opportunities to compare schemes from the different countries.  One thing universally accepted is that our rate of progress in the field of social welfare in recent years compares favourably with that of any country in the world.  I am not saying we are up there equal with the other countries, but I cannot help offering anybody for his own comment the fact that in 1963-64 we were spending £45,500,000 on social welfare and that this year, which only takes account of budget increases for a short part of the year, we shall be spending £154 million.  In a full year the figure would be over £170 million. These are figures which cannot be <Col N="766" /> talked away, in a small country with the resources available to us.  As Deputy Desmond pointed out at the start of his long speech on social welfare, by any standards what we are spending is commendable.</P>
    <P>The argument immediately made against that is: &ldquo;Look at how the cost of living has risen in those ten years.&rdquo;  I have before me the entire rates under all the headings on social welfare which are available to anybody for the 1962-72 period.  To those who say we are only keeping step with the rise in the cost of living, I would direct their attention to the different schemes in that period.  Take unemployment assistance alone.  In 1962-72 the cost of living index went up to 72½ per cent.  The increase in unemployment assistance in that period went up 350 per cent.  This has been the trend under every single heading in the code.  Those who say we are merely keeping step with the rise in the cost of living are completely and utterly wrong and are merely denigrating the scheme for some ulterior motive.  If we take the later years, the increase over the amount that would be warranted by the increase in the cost of living has been even greater, particularly in the last year.  We have reached the stage where we can look back with pride on the progress made in recent years, not merely in the improvement of rates but in the expansion of the scheme to bring more people under the social welfare umbrella.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: I hardly think the Minister is saying that in the period in question old age pensions, for instance, went up by 350 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: What he is saying is that the amount spent on social welfare in general went up by that amount&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>The percentage increase is given here.  During that period old age pensions went up by 217 per cent, and in the case of over 80 classes, taking the recent increase, <Col N="767" /> by 248 per cent, which, compared with a 76 per cent increase in the cost of living, is very creditable.</P>
      <P>Most people are aware that as the result of recent happenings we are about to accelerate that pace considerably in the immediate future, and everybody is jumping on the bandwagon to suggest all the things that might be done.  Deputy Desmond has brought out a white paper, hurriedly he admitted.  I like to see people doing their homework.  It all helps to rock the public conscience into a sense of responsibility which, in the last analysis, is what I depend on as to how far you can take, how far you can hurt, before the people object, in order to get money to finance schemes.  As regards producing a paper, a child of ten years can sit down and recite a litany of all the things we would like to have in social welfare.  I could go further than most as a result of my being intimately associated with social welfare matters and working daily on what we are anxious to do.</P>
      <P>Social welfare and social services are very much confused.  Those who advocate that there should be a higher percentage of gross national product for social welfare, that it should be doubled or trebled, must remember that there are other things which come under the heading of social services, of social policy, and which are entitled to their priorities too.  To what extent do we slow down on the education policy, which is very much a social policy? To what extent do we slow down on the housing of our people?  Practically every Department of State has to some extent a social side to its expenditure and its policy each year to which there must be particular regard.  As a member of the Government, I am concerned with social welfare, which is only one branch of the social services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Although I am more concerned with looking forward today than in looking back and defending, I am still happy in looking back at the rate of progress made in the past ten years, indeed, in the past 50 years.  I do not see that much can be achieved by exchanging political slogans and abuse across the floor of the House.  Deputy <Col N="768" /> Desmond talked about the White Paper of 1947 or 1948.  If I were to deal with this on the basis of a political discussion, I would ask what happened when the Coalition Government came back into power a few years afterwards.  It is very easy to produce white papers and schemes and talk about them, but we have to face realities. When we are talking about social welfare we are talking about the redistribution of wealth and we must have regard to the sources from which it springs.  The rate at which we can expand social welfare depends on the rate at which we can expand the sources from which wealth springs. I do not think my social conscience is any less generous or ambitious than any other person's.  Nothing would please the Minister more than to be able to announce that he would double every scheme we had, extend them and do all the things that people from time to time suggest should be done.</P>
    <P>Recently, I met an old woman who commended me for the free travel scheme.  She suggested that if umbrellas were supplied which could be used in going from the house to the bus it would be a great help.  This indicates the infinite range of things people think of.  It is a matter for the Minister to decide where the priorities should lie in using the money available to him.  As a result of our decision to accede to EEC we anticipate a certain rapid expansion of the social welfare code.  The Department officials are taxed to capacity&mdash;indeed we are quite short of staff&mdash;examining various schemes, working out priorities and directions in which expansion should take place in the immediate future.  In many fields it is quite easy to decide where greater assistance is needed, but there are other schemes not yet in operation which require a tremendous amount of work.  To bring the home assistance scheme to the present stage has taken months of study and the compilation of masses of figures and data which are necessary even for the submission of memoranda to the Departments and the Government. I am satisfied that very definite progress in this respect has been made.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="769" /> We have a few opportunities of discussing social welfare each year and I regret that some Deputies criticised my short introductory statement.  On reflection, I am sorry it was not much longer because it is easier for the Minister to pour a great deal into the introductory speech than wait to reply to points made afterwards.  It was not my purpose to conceal any information, but I am aware that annually there is a Social Welfare Bill before the House. This was dealt with in July before the Recess when there was opportunity for long discussion.  We now have the Estimate and there is a Supplementary Estimate and altogether there are at least three occasions in the year, apart from other legislation, for discussing social welfare.  Soon in this session I hope we shall have the pay-related benefits scheme which will provide a further opportunity for discussion under that heading and related fields.  Opportunities for discussion are therefore many and I anticipate even greater opportunities in the years ahead.</P>
    <P>I have announced that the pay-related scheme immediately brings me to the point where I would wish to abolish the £1,600 income limit on insurability. As a natural corollary I anticipate the extension of social insurance to the self-employed and non-employed and all sections of the community. We shall ultimately be operating entirely in the field of social insurance. This will present many problems but will also bring many benefits and relieve us of many headaches.  The one I think of immediately here is the means test which is so frequently attacked and is made a political football in this debate and by every social commentator. While we have limited resources available on the assistance side of our scheme&mdash;and those are the schemes which are 100 per cent financed from the Exchequer&mdash;we must have means tests.  We must ascertain the categories qualified to receive benefits in accordance with the legislation and regulations of this House.  While those regulations exist it will be the duty of Department officials to see that they are complied with.</P>
    <P>The previous speaker suggested in regard to marginal cases failing to <Col N="770" /> qualify that more discretion should be allowed.  If discretion is allowed merely to take account of cases of hardship it means completely disregarding the regulations provided and we should find ourselves in the position where nobody could defend anything being done in respect of these schemes.  The only service provided where there is discretion of a type is the home assistance scheme which we are now planning to up-date and bring more into line with other schemes.  I should hope that we shall be able to retain the element of discretion by which a man looks at a situation and says: &ldquo;Benefit is needed here&rdquo; and gives it without having to decide whether the limit is this, that or the other.  That service is at times very much denigrated and is frequently referred to as the service with the stigma attached to it, but it is a scheme which enables the home assistance officer to decide when there are cases of hardship and he can give temporary or permanent assistance to counteract it.  I hope the element of discretion will be retained or even extended.</P>
    <P>The whole concept of social welfare rather appeals to politicians because it is a field in which one likes to do better than the other.  Whatever Minister is in power and however much he may think of nice things he would like to do and improvements he would like to make, he must always have regard to available resources and priorities.  He must also have regard to the means of generating the wealth from which will come the benefits he wishes to give.  Some people talk as if this problem does not arise, that we can get any amount of money to finance any scheme without regard to the source from which it comes.  We hear talk of signs of affluence, the amount of money spent on luxuries, in lounges and other places, but we must remember that even the man who drinks a bottle of stout is contributing very considerably to the revenue from which these benefits derive.  When one comes to consider taking extra revenue from these sources there is a great deal of opposition and one must have regard to the danger of reaching the point of diminishing returns, <Col N="771" /> which can very easily be reached if there is a temporary recession in the economy.  These are facts that are always present and they limit what we can do and the rate at which we can do them.</P>
    <P>We are now entering a new phase when extra moneys will be available to us.  This will be a welcome opportunity to go a little faster in reaching some of the things that might otherwise not have been reached for a few years.  I would hope that the tempo of improvement will increase.</P>
    <P>Mr. Brian Faulkner yesterday talked about the great gap between the social services in the two parts of Ireland. Considering the rate at which that gap has been closing in recent years, it is obvious why he whistles passing the graveyard.  We do not have an empire to call on to subsidise us.  We have our own resources.  We have developed them, to the great disappointment of those who suggested some years ago that we would never be a viable economy.  If there is one thing more than another that has astounded people it is the success which the Twenty-Six Counties has achieved in every sphere, particularly in social policy, in recent years.  It is not many years ago that we were under the jurisdiction of mother England and had very little social benefits. Those of us who grew up in large families, when there were no benefits, sometimes have to smile when comparisons are made and criticisms are levelled against the schemes that we operate.  We think of how short a time it is since there was no such thing as social welfare, with the exception of the few shillings a week of old age pension.  We have come a long way pretty rapidly.  We have identified the areas where progress can and will be made.  I do not think we have anything to worry about.</P>
    <P>As I said when answering a question in the House the other day, to those people who talk about the difference in rates or scope of social welfare as between this State and the other portion of our country, I would say that if the question of reunification is agreed, <Col N="772" /> the equalisation or bringing up to standard of social welfare schemes will not be the obstacle that will prevent its taking place.</P>
    <P>There are not many people on social insurance at the present time.  I hope the developments we foresee and are preparing will enable us to move into that field as quickly as possible.  We are sometimes accused of being too ready to follow what other countries are doing.  I do not see anything wrong in learning from mistakes made by other countries or in copying successes they have achieved, in taking the good parts of schemes operated in other countries and rejecting those aspects which are not acceptable or which have not proved to be successful.  Many experimental schemes have been operated by other countries and have been found not to be successful.  It would be very foolish of us not to take examples that are available to us.  Most Members of the House, if not all, would agree with me that there are some features of the social welfare codes of other countries that we would not be prepared to copy <i>in toto</i>.  On the other hand, we operate schemes that other countries do not operate.</P>
    <P>Our schemes cover most of those persons who, due to no fault of their own, are unable to earn a livelihood. There may be anomalies here and there which we try to eliminate.  We make an effort every year to improve the schemes which are in operation.</P>
    <P>Many of the speakers referred to individual cases and to particular anomalies, some of which I propose to deal with now.  Deputy Cooney this year again made adverse comparisons about the assessment in occupational injuries cases.  The occupational injuries benefit is one of the more recent social welfare schemes and compares favourably with the corresponding scheme in any other country.  Deputy Cooney did not make any complaint in that respect.  The Deputy suggested that the old system, where the applicant went to a circuit court judge and medical evidence was given on both sides and there were qualified advocates, and the applicant had the benefit of an arbitrator in the person of a judge who made the award, was infinitely better <Col N="773" /> than the present system of having our doctors make the assessment of the degree of disability from which a person is suffering as a result of occupational injury.</P>
    <P>I do not accept that there is such a great difference.  Deputies will remember the delay in bringing cases before the courts, the hardship that could sometimes result before decisions were reached.  We have impartial medical referees who discuss and consult amongst themselves.  They have fixed standards of degree of disability. There is a slide rule by which they assess disability.  They allow a certain percentage for loss of an eye or a limb or a finger, and so on.  I do not think that people suffer injustice under that scheme as compared with the old system of assessment by a Circuit Court judge.  Our medical people must keep this matter under review from time to time in the light of their experience.  They have no particular desire to minimise occupational injuries.  Their duty is to make an impartial, honest, careful assessment of the degree of disability suffered.</P>
    <P>Deputy Creed complained of the difficulties experienced when a book is recalled for adjustment and the delay in the issuing of the new book. We had discussions about this matter in the Department recently.  I shall not go into all the details of problems which may arise in this matter but I think it is possible in cases of that kind to expedite the issue of the new book.  I would point out to the Deputy that in all the cases that we do not hear about the new book is issued expeditiously.  It is only those cases in which there is delay that we hear about.  I would hope that there would be a minimum of delay and, perhaps, no delay at all.</P>
    <P>Most Deputies referred to our failure to accept the transfer of the farm to the son for the purpose of granting the old age pension and suggested that we should not wait until the deeds were available but that immediately a move was made in that direction, we should accept it as <i>bona fide</i> and award the pension accordingly.  We do not wait until it <Col N="774" /> is finalised, as particularly those Deputies with legal training will know, but one must wait until there is some positive proof that it is a <i>bona fide</i> transfer without waiting until the actual registration takes place.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: I am afraid the Minister waits until it is lodged for registration.  If he is referring to my contribution, I did point out that in some cases, due to the title being defective or lying in the family for ages, it is not possible to register the deed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that when it has reached that stage of development where registration is applied for, we move.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: That is so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>And there can be very long delay, as the Deputy will know, in having registration effected from the date it is applied for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: I fully accept that the Minister acts on the deed when lodged for registration but the case to which I was drawing attention was the case where the title has been in a mess for maybe 50 years or where somebody is missing and it is not possible to lodge the deed for registration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not enter into a legal discussion of the case now because one could run into a case where the person transferring was not the owner at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: I would not expect the Minister to do so but his advisers will be familiar with the type of case I am talking about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>We try to facilitate persons as much as possible when we know that there is a <i>bona fide</i> transfer, even though it is not finalised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Deputy O'Leary complained about the waiting days and mentioned the case of persons who periodically have to go off sick.  He was seemingly not aware that in these recurring cases, <Col N="775" /> the waiting days do not apply.  Within 13 weeks from the previous illness, the waiting days do not take effect. They are paid from the first day, the date on the certificate.</P>
    <P>Deputy Lenehan made an apparently very valid point when he asked why we do not pay under our children allowance scheme the same amount for the first child as for the others and also made the point that there is more cost in respect of the first child than the second.  Originally the children's allowance scheme was to come to the assistance of persons with increasing families and the first and second children were not included. In England and in the Six Counties nothing is yet paid for the first child and we are one of the few countries, if not the only country, which makes a contribution in respect of the first child.  However, one of the schemes under consideration is this scheme which did not secure an increase in the last budget because it was under examination by an inter-departmental committee for the purpose of finding out to what degree selectivity could be brought in and by that means enable us to give more generous allowances to the more needy families. I hope that this will be the first scheme I will be able to have improved when the opportunity presents itself.  It will be in the next budget, I hope, and account will have to be taken of the fact that it was not improved last year.  Whether we get a degree of selectivity without a means test is a matter I have not yet decided but I have made up my mind, perhaps not finally, that there should be no means test whatever, whatever other methods we may adopt to produce selectivity.  I would even take a chance and have it paid in the same general way as at present without selectivity rather than have a means test.</P>
    <P>Deputy Desmond covered the entire scope of the White Paper.  I have no intention of dealing here with the White Paper because most of the things mentioned in it refer to matters which I have mentioned in the House time and again in relation <Col N="776" /> to the direction in which our schemes must develop.  He did make reference to the Garda Síochána and suggested that some members, those with over £1,600, should be permitted to have cover.  This is an approach made by the Garda authorities to me and I recently signified my willingness to meet a deputation from their representative body in relation to the problems which they envisage or improvements which they would like to have made, now that they have been permitted to be contributors under the insurance scheme.  It is a question of their looking for credits to enable those who have gone over the £1,600 mark to become voluntary contributors for widows' pensions.  This is something I would be prepared to consider, always keeping in mind that there are many other categories in the same position, such as Army officers, but if I manage to have the limit abolished in the near future, here again the problem will not arise at all as abolition would meet the requirements in this respect.</P>
    <P>There were complaints about the allowances under the prescribed relatives scheme.  I should remind the House that I brought in this scheme in the first instance to meet a particular type of case where the members of the family found themselves working, or married, or away from home, and one girl usually found herself having to look after the parents and for that reason did not leave or, in some cases, had to come back.  That was the first move towards this prescribed relatives scheme and like every other social welfare scheme one can immediately expect demands for its extension and improvement. This was no exception.  We set about paying it only to those who had to give up insurable employment; I extended it to those who, in any event, were caring for the aged parents with nobody else in the house and then, this year, it was extended to the male relatives.  It has now reached a stage at which I get complaints from anybody or everybody who seems to think that if he or she has old age pensioners in the house, whether parents or other relations, or otherwise, he or she should be paid for looking after <Col N="777" /> them, irrespective of who is living in the house.</P>
    <P>One of the most frequent types of case in respect of which we have complaints is where the son is married and bringing up a family in the same house.  He is very lucky to have the use of the house and no doubt he has had the farm signed over to him. He would have to live somewhere anyway. He lives there with his father, mother, aunt or uncle who is drawing a pension.  On top of that he thinks he should qualify under this scheme and be paid for looking after the person. This scheme was intended for old people who would be living alone if it were not for some person who stayed there to look after them.  That is the spirit of the scheme and we would like to stick as closely to that as possible.  Where the son is looking after a parent, as Deputy Lenehan mentioned, and is drawing unemployment assistance, it is very difficult for him to prove, on the one hand, that he is capable of, available for and seeking work and, on the other hand, that he must stay at home continually to look after the parents.  It is perfectly obvious that this is not logical.</P>
    <P>Some Deputies spoke of prosecutions. In my opening statement I gave an account of a great many prosecutions during the year mostly in respect of persons drawing disability benefit and working at the same time.  People are very compassionate when it comes to cases of this kind but we either have regulations or we have not.  If we could eliminate all the abuses it would leave more money available for the genuine cases.  I must admit that particularly in the field of disability benefit there are a great many cases of malingering and of the scheme being abused.  There is the person drawing disability benefit and working at the same time or the person drawing disability benefit who is not disabled at all.  In the working of the scheme we have many reasons for knowing that this is so.  We meet the case where immediately a person finds something particularly suitable in the way of work he can get a final certificate immediately and proceed to work, whereas if he had not found it he would still send in certificates that <Col N="778" /> he was disabled.  Those people seem to get certificates quite easily.</P>
    <P>I discussed this with the medical profession on more than one occasion. A doctor pointed out to me that if a man comes in to him and says that he has a bad pain in his back who is he to tell him he has not.  If a man comes in and says he has very serious intestine trouble and the doctor says he has not the man could die from a perforation the next day.  The diagnosis in many cases must be in accordance with the statement made by the patient.  The fact remains, and it is no secret, that people succeed in getting certificates almost any time they want them.  Very often our doctor and the patient's own doctor disagree about the condition of a particular person.  It can be said that we err on the side of humanity in these cases but there are a great many abuses in this field.  If we had less of them we would have more money available for those who are genuinely in need of it.  The number of prosecutions has increased in recent times.  These will have to continue to take place if we are to try to get a sense of responsibility into those who think they can get away with abuses.</P>
    <P>Deputy Desmond referred to our need to proceed with reciprocal agreements regarding social welfare with the member states of the EEC.  He must have forgotten that from next April there will be a common policy, to a great extent, with regard to welfare payments.  A recipient will bring his rights from one country to another. This will even apply to children's allowances, which were not covered by any reciprocal agreement we had with the UK in the past.  This will apply to all EEC countries.</P>
    <P>The question of board and lodging has been overstressed by many people who spoke.  If we do assess 5p a week for a person who has good quality board and lodging with relatives or other people, one must differentiate between a person who is living in a house freely and one who is paying rent.  There surely is a vast difference in income here and it must be measured by some means.  When my predecessor brought in the provision that a person with no means would get 25p extra, which still applies, we were <Col N="779" /> criticised for assessing the means too rigidly.  Deputies seem to forget that prior to this being introduced the case was frequently made here that there were people in receipt of old age pensions who were very much different from others in that they had absolutely nothing.  You could not compare a pensioner living with a comfortably-off family, although he had no income or property of his own at that stage, with a man living alone in a rented cottage. A good case was made that there should be some differential payment in the case of those with no means. In deference to that the nil means payment was brought in.  Then we were criticised for allowing 5p a week for free board and lodging or in the case of a man who had a garden and so on. The whole purpose was to identify the real hardship case where the person had no means or friends to come to his assistance.</P>
    <P>In days gone by old people expected that when they got old they would be looked after by their families in their own armchairs by the fireside.  They brought up their families and they expected that they would look after them in their old age and make them happy and comfortable.  That would seem to be disappearing to some extent.  Many people seem to think that their parents should be the responsibility of the State and when they talk about the inadequacy of the amount they are receiving they seem to jettison the idea of responsibility towards their parents or relatives.  There is nothing we could give to an old person that would be appreciated as much as would a little care from his own family.  I have great admiration for those social workers who try to give to old persons who have no relatives a little personal care and attention to compensate for what they could expect if they had relatives.</P>
    <P>There is a growing tendency to expect the State to take over entirely what up to now was the responsibility of family and relatives.  I often hear the question: &ldquo;Am I expected to keep my father on £5 per week&rdquo;?  Some of us had to keep our parents while getting no assistance from anywhere but we were proud and happy to do so.  I <Col N="780" /> should hate to think that affection for parents has disappeared.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: The case I mentioned concerned an applicant for unemployment assistance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy referred to two cases which I shall have examined individually.  In relation to the case of the Deputy's constituent who is serving a jail sentence there is an examination being carried out to see if there is anything further we can do in the matter.  Liberal minded as I am, I think that perhaps we are reaching the stage where criminals in our society tend to be glamorised.  Of course, there must be better jails, better conditions and treatment.  However, if a man is unfortunate enough to lapse and find himself in jail there is much to be said for ensuring that his social welfare record is not broken so that when he becomes rehabilitated, social welfare benefits would be available to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: I gave the Minister two specific cases but the third concerned an applicant for unemployment assistance who is living with his brother-in-law.  This man is seeking employment but while he is with his brother-in-law he has free lodging which could be assessed at £6 per week.  He has that as a charity from his brother-in-law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy will let me have particulars of that case in writing I shall look into it again, although we have considered it already. The Deputy is prone to raise cases for which there is no precedent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: I make a note of the odd cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I remember on one occasion he raised the case of an adopted boy who, in fact, was not adopted.  There was nothing in the social welfare code to cover the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The usual complaints were made regarding red tape and bureaucracy. These complaints are always made glibly and in a manner that would suggest that very harsh regulations are imposed by the Minister on the unfortunate persons who must seek <Col N="781" /> benefit.  I would like to dispel that myth.  Many times I have reminded our investigation officers that they must carry out their tasks in accordance with the regulations laid down by this House but at the same time I let them know that I wish them to approach persons in a manner that will assure them that these investigation officers only want to help them. There have been many instances where our officials have advised persons of benefits to which they were entitled but of which they were not aware.  The object of a visit by an investigation officer is to ascertain whether a person qualifies for benefit and to ensure that nothing is being concealed that ultimately would rebound.  Solicitors in this House must be aware of the number of estates that are surcharged due to means not being revealed at the time of making an application.</P>
    <P>Bureaucracy, or what is referred to as red tape, is nothing more than a set of regulations designed to ascertain the qualifications for benefit of any applicant. I should hate to think that people would regard our social welfare officers as monsters.  They should be assured that the officers are only there to help.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan) Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick (Cavan)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>(Cavan)</i>: I would not advise the Minister to put that on his Christmas cards to the old age pensioners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>At the same time it is only fair to point out that investigation officers are sometimes confronted by very slick people.  I recall a home assistance officer telling me that one woman on whom he called went out with her dog and turned out her cattle on the pretext that they belonged to a neighbour and had strayed on to her property.  There is no necessity to resort to such antics because a person will be given any benefit to which he is entitled.  The officers are trained for the work they do and I would like to dispel once and for all the idea that some people have of them as being big, bad wolves.</P>
      <P>I do not consider it necessary to go into any further detail regarding the points raised by Deputies during the debate.  Most Deputies harped on matters of which I am well aware.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="782" /> There is always an inclination to exaggerate small anomalies that may occur in respect of various schemes.  I would ask the House to remember that the percentage of our Vote which goes on administration compares favourably with any other Department of State.  Ours is a big Department that deals with thousands of cases each day.  Therefore, it would be less than human if there were not some delays and some mistakes also. We are endeavouring constantly to minimise these delays and to eliminate the mistakes that inevitably occur. I hope that we shall be able to proceed on those lines more rapidly in future.  We are short of personnel but we have an application with Finance at present for many extra staff to deal with the various schemes that we must proceed with in the immediate future.  We have a problem also of accommodation.</P>
    <P>The Department has grown and will continue to grow.  We must have the personnel if we are to give the service.  As I said on the Estimate here last year, I went especially to Newcastle-on-Tyne to look at the computerised system they have there, one of the most sophisticated computer systems in the world.  I was disappointed to find that it did not reduce the number of staff very much, if at all.  It gave a more expeditious service to the people.  Naturally, they deal in larger numbers than we do.  When we would be talking in thousands, they would be talking in millions of recipients. They gave us every facility to study their system.  The officials who accompanied me spent some days there.  As I say, I was disappointed that it did not make for a reduction in personnel but it did give a better service.</P>
    <P>In the pay related scheme we will have to use the service of a computer. We have made arrangements with another Department for this to be done.  It entails considerable problems but I am most encouraged by the fact that we have broken new ground.  We have got another means of identifying people to whom we could not get through before.  This system will enable us to expand and make progress in many fields in the future.  The development of the social <Col N="783" /> welfare schemes, apart from the improvement of the rates which is a simple matter which can be done at any time, the expansion of the system, and the movement towards bringing all sections into the social insurance scheme are now in sight.  We have at least found a means of getting through to get contributions from all the people concerned.</P>
    <P>Deputy Desmond pointed out the huge amount we could get from contributions if we put one penny on the stamp.  It is quite true that we would get in £600,000 odd, but whenever we increase the stamp it is done on an actuarial assessment calculated to bring in just what we want to pay out.  We always leave the Exchequer to make up the balance of which the fund is short in the year.  It has never dropped below 30 per cent and, indeed, has kept very much above 33? per cent in recent years.  When by an addition to the stamp we get in a fair amount of money, any increase in the cost of the stamp is calculated to bring in only what it is estimated will be the outgoings.  If we find at the end of the year that the calculations were on the generous side, with the new benefits coming in, which now inevitably come in each year, we can make an adjustment with regard to the addition to the cost of the stamp in respect of other schemes in the light of experience in the past. At no time are we taking more than we need as the Deputy might seem to imply.  In fact, we have never taken enough to meet the requirements of any scheme.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="784" /> I do not think it is necessary to deal with any further points which were raised.  When the pay related Bill comes before the House Deputies will have an opportunity of discussing some aspects of social welfare again. I hope that in any bidding which takes place with regard to future social welfare serious regard will be taken of the resources available to us and that we will always identify the means which will be used to provide the money which is the only difference between our having the best scheme in the world and our having just what we have at present, or what we hope to have in the years to come.  The only difference is the resources available to us.  If we could disregard many other priorities and other social services which require a lot of money, and concentrate entirely on the one area, perhaps, we could do a lot better, but I do not think anybody in the House would be prepared to accept that.  All these things are necessary and we must bring them along to the best point we can, using prudently all the resources we can muster to bring them to that stage.  I am happy that we can now envisage a more accelerated rate of progress in the time immediately ahead and a movement into schemes which we were unable to implement in the past.</P>
    <P>Motion to refer back, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <P>Vote put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>The Dáil adjourned at 4.15 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Tuesday 7th November, 1972.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>