<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="29" Month="Jan" Year="1958" Vol="48" No="15" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 29 Eanáir 1958" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 29 January 1958" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1327">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1327" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Nomination" RHead="of Senator">
    <Title>Nomination of Senator.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá orm a rá go bhfuil an Taoiseach tar éis Lughaidh Breathnach d'ainmniú, le réamhchead uaidh féin, chun bheith ina chomhalta de Sheanad Éireann le go líonfar an folúntas a tharla de dheasca báis an tSeanadóra Seán Ó Maoláin, Aire Talmhaíochta.</P>
      <P>Féadfaidh an Seanadóir Lughaidh Breathnach a shuíochán a ghlacadh anois.</P>
      <P>I have to announce that the Taoiseach has nominated Mr. Louis Walsh, with his prior consent, to be a member of Seanad Éireann to fill the vacancy caused by the death of Senator Seán Moylan, Minister for Agriculture. Senator Louis Walsh may now take his seat.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Business as on the Order Paper and, if necessary, to sit to-morrow to complete it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is a good idea.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Agricultural Institute Bill," RHead="1957&mdash;Committee Stage">
    <Title>Agricultural Institute Bill, 1957&mdash;Committee Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we take up consideration of the Committee Stage of this Bill, I wish to say that I consider amendment No. 9 standing in the name of Senator Quinlan, as being out of order and it may not be moved. It tends to impose a charge on State funds which is not permissible in an amendment by a Private Member.</P>
      <P>The Senator has been communicated with in the matter.</P>
      <P>Section I agreed to</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1328" /> SECTION 2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In line 13, before &ldquo;horticulture&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;dairy science.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This, like a number of other amendments, has been put down mainly for the purpose of elucidation.  I should like to know if there is any reason why dairy science was not coupled with horticulture, forestry and bee-keeping as the nearest adjuncts to agriculture? The view may be held that dairy science is so much a part of agriculture that there is no need to mention it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has given the reason.  It is that agriculture includes dairy science.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 2 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 2:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2), line 31, after &ldquo;land&rdquo; to add &ldquo;buildings and equipment&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This amendment arises another minor question as to whether &ldquo;land&rdquo; really covers buildings and equipment as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer is in the affirmative.  It does.  Apparently from the legal point of view, it is wise to put in &ldquo;land&rdquo; in cases like this for safety sake, and &ldquo;land&rdquo; then includes buildings and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Taoiseach say where the word &ldquo;talúntas&rdquo; comes from?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator would know very much more about that than I do.  Evidently, it is one of the words associated with land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Have we not got the word &ldquo;talmhaiocht&rdquo; in official use already for agriculture?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I can only say that I am not responsible for it.  It is the word regarded by the translation staff as the most suitable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1329" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems very strange to me that the translation staff should have adopted one word and then, for the purpose of this Bill, adopt another.  I understand the way it is arrived at, but it seems to me that, from the point of view of language in general, and of the Irish language in particular, there should not be in our statutes two separate words to denote agriculture.  We talk about &ldquo;An Roinn Talmhaíochta&rdquo; and here we talk about &ldquo;An Foras Talúntais&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is in combination with &ldquo;Foras&rdquo; that it is regarded as the better way of putting it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>But it is a completely new word.  Is déantús é.  It is a make-up.  It is an invented word, is it not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, I am afraid the Senator would know more about that than I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I can pledge my word it is an invented word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an abstract form, but we may have an occasional growth&mdash;as we do have in other languages&mdash;where you have an original word and you get a slight variation of it.  What it means is obvious to anybody. There is no difficulty in understanding it because anybody would see at once that the word &ldquo;talamh&rdquo; is its root.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 3 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 3:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2), paragraph (h), line 28, to delete &ldquo;and organise&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;or procure the provision of&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It does seem to me that there is a difference in drafting here between paragraphs (i) (j) and (k).  Paragraphs (i) (j) and (k) say &ldquo;disseminate, or procure the dissemination of&rdquo;; &ldquo;publish or procure the publication of&rdquo;.  I thought that in paragraph (h) <Col N="1330" /> it should be &ldquo;provide, or procure the provision of&rdquo; courses.  In other words, I should not like to feel that the institute was committed under paragraph (h) to providing the courses directly by itself, that it would have the opportunity of procuring the provision of courses where they could be provided by other bodies.  I think that was more or less the general feeling on the Second Reading of the Bill.  With regard to the word &ldquo;organise&rdquo;, I just thought that that was implicit in &ldquo;provide&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Naturally, I have discussed this matter and have examined it and the general feeling is that &ldquo;organise&rdquo; means not merely organise itself but arrange that other bodies would do the work.  &ldquo;Organise&rdquo; is a very broad word.  As read out, it does not follow the same precise form of words as in the following subsections, but I think there can be no doubt about it that the word &ldquo;organise&rdquo; means that the institute could do it or get it done by others as long as they arrange for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>In any event, it is not clear from the whole tenor of sub-section (2) of this section that this is a list of things which the institute may do and the institute has power to do what Senator Quinlan suggests in the amendment&mdash;to procure the provision of courses.  There can be no doubt of that from this sub-section and from other parts of the Bill.  This particular paragraph, (h), does not make it obligatory upon the institute to provide courses of study themselves. Presumably, they may do it themselves but they may also see that other people do it or make provision for other people to do it.  The whole general tenor of sub-section (2) is that they may do any of these things or they may get any of these things done.  Is that not correct?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is my interpretation and the interpretation of the lawyers also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach's explanation meets my point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1331" /> Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 4:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2), before paragraph (j), to insert a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>() provide suitable lectures on agriculture and the results of agricultural research in schools and colleges.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 7 and amendment No. 4 deal with the same point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure the House will be agreeable to allow the Senator to discuss amendments No. 4 and No. 7 together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>These two amendments speak for themselves.  Various speakers on the Second Stage of the Bill complained about a shortage of graduates in agriculture who would be suitable workers under this institute in the years to come.  It is in the schools that we want to interest the young people in agriculture.  We want not alone to be able to pick the cream of them for the institute but to have far more graduates going back on the farms.  They would have their theoretical work done in the schools of agriculture and their practical work done, to a great extent, on their own farms.  By these amendments we could look forward to seeing far more agricultural graduates going back to work on the land.  I think Senator Quinlan mentioned on the Second Stage that there were 20 graduates walking the streets without a job but I am not proposing these amendments with a view to filling jobs.  My amendments are designed with a view to having graduates going back to work on the land.  We shall probably have enough graduates to be able to pick the best. I want to see that there is a surplus, as it were, so that the best can be picked for research work and that there will be many more graduates going back on the land.  It is in the schools that interest in agriculture can be started.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A headmaster or teacher could invite these lecturers to the schools to give lectures on agricultural topics and very likely he would be the person to distribute, and would take an interest <Col N="1332" /> in distributing, suitable literature for the schools if it were available.  The amendment would allow the institute to pay the travelling expenses of the director or member of the council or agricultural instructor that they might send to a school.  I think that is all it would entail in the matter of expenses. Probably they would hold themselves available to give these lectures where a headmaster or the head of a school would ask for them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no doubt that it is desirable that the results of research should be disseminated through the universities down to the teaching bodies but the emphasis in this institute is on research and its business would be to disseminate the results of research.  The teaching bodies would, no doubt, be affected in their teaching by the results of research, by what has been learned, by new things discovered, but this is not a teaching institute as such and it would not be the business of the institute to make information available in a form suitable for schools.</P>
      <P>The whole question of the teaching of agriculture to young people is of very great importance.  It has been more than once suggested that agriculture should be taught in the primary schools.  It certainly should be taught in the vocational schools and in any other extension bodies that are teaching in rural areas but it would not be desirable that this institute should take upon itself the responsibility of arranging the results of research in such form that they would be available for direct teaching in the schools. We shall have to allow that to operate through the process, first of all, of making the results of the research known, which, as a research institute it will do, and then the teaching bodies, from the University Colleges down, will be made aware of the results of the research and they will have to arrange the form in which it is to be used in the classes that they teach.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 5:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In sub-section (2), paragraph (j), <Col N="1333" /> line 34, before &ldquo;results&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;progress and&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>I am assuming that &ldquo;results&rdquo; would mean final results.  I should like to see some publication made of the progress and the aim of the work on which a research team is engaged.  To judge by the whole section, one would think they would work away in the dark so far as the rest of us are concerned until they would get a result they were aiming at.  If a bi-annual publication were made in relation to their work, and how far they had got, then, possibly, they could get a great amount of assistance from agricultural colleges or even agricultural instructors.</P>
    <P>Take research on a veterinary subject, for example.  If a publication were made, say, every six months in some official veterinary journal of the progress they were making and, perhaps, the difficulties they were encountering, I think they might quite easily get a lot of assistance from veterinary surgeons throughout the country.  I have in mind in my amendment that they should publish more frequently and not just the final result.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is a matter that could safely be left to the governing body of the institute itself&mdash; the director and the council.  I do not think they will wish to hide their light under a bushel.  Anyhow, they will make annual reports and, if they wish to do so, they can use any other means of letting the public know what they are doing.  I do not think we ought to make it obligatory on them to publish progress reports.  There will be opportunities for considering the work being done.  There will be annual grants. There will be opportunities for considering their reports and there will be opportunities even here in the Seanad and in the Dáil.  At any rate, I do not think it is desirable to make it obligatory on them to publish progress reports.</P>
      <P>They must be expected to publish the results of their experiments.  It is desirable that they also should do what the Senator says&mdash;and I think it can be done otherwise, without making it obligatory.  It will follow naturally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I was prompted to put down this suggestion as a result of my <Col N="1334" /> own experience.  Since I became a member of this House, I have received a large volume of papers in relation to some activities of the Department of Agriculture.  Before coming to this House, I was ignorant of the fact that a lot of that work was going on.  I have in mind now, in particular, veterinary surgery.  If other persons engaged in that line were made aware that work was proceeding in relation to a certain point they might possibly be able to give very valuable assistance arising out of cases which would come before them in their own business or their own practice.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 6 and 7 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 8:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (3), line 41, before &ldquo;or&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;agricultural teaching&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The Second Reading has shown that it is the Government's intention to have faculties of agriculture.  It might be a good idea if there were some means of co-ordinating the activities of these faculties or at least getting a coordination of their programmes on which we might expect the Agricultural Institute to give some advice at a later stage when it is functioning.</P>
      <P>My query here is: is this sub-section wide enough to allow the Agricultural Institute to give such advice, if requested by the Minister?  The same holds, also, in relation to agricultural teaching in the agricultural schools&mdash; both the private agricultural schools and the Government schools.  It might be well if the institute could express an opinion on whether the teaching in these schools was really meshing-in with the requirements for agricultural research and development on the farms and also whether the pupils were attuned to helping the advisory officers in their regions and, in general, playing the part that students of an agricultural school should play in furthering the position of their less fortunate neighbours.  Is it necessary to insert &ldquo;agricultural teaching&rdquo; or can the section be stretched to that interpretation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1335" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think there is need for any stretching of the section. If the Minister wishes to get advice on any matter in relation to agriculture, he can ask for it.  If he wishes to get advice as to the best course to be pursued in the agricultural colleges, he can ask for it.</P>
      <P>With regard to the wider field covered by the Senator, I doubt very much whether it would be altogether advisable to put the institute in a position in which they would have to pass judgment upon the courses in the University Colleges.  According to the scheme of this Bill, its influence on University Colleges must be a moral influence&mdash;by meeting the members of the faculties of agriculture for the various colleges and by discussing these matters with them.  The results of the research, and publications, will also have their effect.  I do not think you can give them any direct powers. The other point is covered.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 9 is out of order, for the reason stated.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 4 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Profesor Hayes Profesor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Profesor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to express my agreement with what the Taoiseach said on amendment No. 8.  I take it that one of the first duties of the institute would be to elaborate a broad programme of agricultural research for the whole country.  The nature of the research must be related to the agriculture in which we are engaged and to the lines of development which would be deemed by the institute to be most favourable to our economic improvement.  Therefore, it seems to me that, from the wording of this section, and from what has been said by the Taoiseach in the course of the Second Reading debate and, indeed, again to-day, the first thing the institute will have to do is to survey the facilities available for research at present both with regard to personnel and to physical facilities including buildings at existing centres and, in the light of that information, to arrange for funds to ensure that, as <Col N="1336" /> far as possible, the extension for research on proper lines at these places will proceed correctly. Therefore, it would appear that the institute should not, in the very beginning, proceed to set up either a building or extensive buildings or expensive offices until it has determined for itself the best course to pursue.</P>
      <P>Most certainly, the relationship of the institute with existing faculties in present centres of research should first be established and, in the first instance, it would appear that the institute will determine what can be done with the existing facilities and then proceed to supplement them.  The amount of money available is not really very great.  Therefore, it should be spent in the most economical way possible. The best possible use should be made of the facilities which exist at the moment before any expenditure is incurred on the provision of further buildings or further laboratories or anything of that particular kind. I think that is the framework of the Bill.  This is the operative section of the Bill and I think that is correct in the light of what the Taoiseach has said.  I hope I am right in thinking so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no remarks to make on Senator Hayes's statement just now.  I think he is interpreting the situation fairly accurately.  It certainly corresponds to my mind on the matter.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 5</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 10:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before sub-section (3) to insert a new sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>The chairman shall be the chief officer of the institute and shall control and direct the activities and staff of the institute subject to the general direction of the council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The object of this amendment is two-fold&mdash;first, to express the view that it is not desirable that there should be a chairman appointed for a period of three years&mdash;with remuneration and with certain rights and therefore presumably with certain duties&mdash;and at <Col N="1337" /> the same time a director.  It seems to me that that arrangement is almost bound, human nature being what it is, to lead to a clash.  That is my view.</P>
    <P>Apart from that, if that view does not find favour with the Taoiseach and the House, I should like to get some information as to the reason for making a change from the Bill of 1956, which provided a director only.  I put the amendment down in this form because it was the only way in which it seemed to me I could bring these matters before the House.  I am sorry I have to discuss the director to some extent.  Presumably he must be a scientist of wide knowledge, high experience and repute.  If it is proposed that the chairman should also be a scientist&mdash;I do not know whether it is or not&mdash;it would appear to me you would be almost bound to have a clash.  There would be a certain amount of divided authority and the situation would not be such as to get the very best possible results from the institute.</P>
    <P>That is the reason why I put down the amendment, which puts it the other way round&mdash;that the chief officer of the institute should also be the chairman of the council, and that he should have under him the direction of the activities and staff of the institute, subject to the general control of the council.</P>
    <P>I put in the word &ldquo;general&rdquo; which Senators will remark is not in Section 7 (2) which reads:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The director shall be the chief officer of the institute and shall control and direct the activities and staff of the institute subject to the direction of the council.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>As originally in the Bill, as drafted and introduced, the phrase was &ldquo;general direction&rdquo;.  The word &ldquo;general&rdquo; was deleted&mdash;I am not quite clear why.  It seems to me that if you keep the word &ldquo;general&rdquo; you give the director more power&mdash;which I think he should have.  He should be under the general direction of the council but not under their direction for specific day to day matters.</P>
    <P>I should like to know what kind of person is envisaged as chairman and what is in the Taoiseach's mind and the mind of the Government with <Col N="1338" /> regard to the different functions which the chairman and the director are to carry out.  For example, under Section 5 the chairman shall be appointed by the President&mdash;that is, by the Government&mdash;he shall hold office for such term not exceeding three years, and on such terms and conditions (including terms of remuneration) as may be determined by the Government at the time of his appointment.  The fact that he is getting remuneration means that he has to do something more than preside at four or six meetings in a year. I am anxious to find out&mdash;I am not interested in the remuneration side&mdash; what functions it is proposed to give the chairman and how they differ from those which Section 7 proposes to give to the director.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The difference between this Bill and that introduced by the previous Government is that this is a different approach on this matter. Some people may think it better to have the whole thing run by one man, while others may take the view that it would be much better that policy and so on should be decided by a group rather than by an individual.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This institute is being set up with the ultimate aim of serving the agricultural community here in our own country.  Research is only a means to an end.  I admit you can have research by individuals who are thinking of much more fundamental things and who have not the immediate utilitarian end in mind at all.  This is intended to be a practical instrument for the improvement of agriculture in this country and to serve the agricultural community. If research is to be done, one must look for the best scientist to do it &mdash;and he must be an organiser, too.  When we considered this Bill first with a view to bringing it in, we considered that the Bill which originated from the previous Government laid too much stress upon the scientist who was to be the head or director of the technical side of the work.  We felt it would be much better that the whole policy of research for the benefit of agriculture here should be decided by a body such as the council&mdash;where there would be representatives from the Government, the <Col N="1339" /> Department of Agriculture, the universities and also the farming community through their organisations. We thought such a body would be better fitted to decide the directions in which research should be pursued.</P>
    <P>I know the technical sides will come in, but having set out the immediate aims, the council would have a scientific expert to try to achieve those aims.  Therefore, the idea was that the council would be really in the saddle and have the ultimate determination of policy.  They would be sensible men and realise that where they were not expert they would have to depend upon the expert advice which they would be given&mdash;judged, of course, by their own common sense and knowledge and the aims they had in view.  We thought it very much better to have this arrangement under which there would be a council which, by the foundation Act, this Bill, would be really masters and the others would have to act as the agents or servants of that body.</P>
    <P>I am asked what the function of the chairman should be: I would say he need not necessarily be a scientist.  I would envisage him as a man who had a good knowledge of agriculture and the agricultural needs of the country, a man who by his intellectual capacity and training would be able to appraise proposals which might be put up by the technical department for the carrying out of any particular aim set forth by the council.  Therefore, he would not necessarily be in the narrow field, confined to a scientist.  In his general knowledge he should have such knowledge as would enable him to understand the nature of research work and what it implies.  He should be a man of ability with particular knowledge of agriculture in this country.  In that case we do not have to combine in one person the highly technical skill that would be required of the director with the ordinary knowledge and common sense of the person who had a good acquaintance with agriculture in this country.</P>
    <P>I have not any particular person in mind.  Neither have the Government, <Col N="1340" /> but I am indicating the sort of person I should like to find.  He would be, so to speak, a sort of standing committee during the time between the meetings of the council.  Day by day he would have to attend to such things as might be delegated to him by the council in so far as they would have powers of delegation, so that he would really be the companion, so to speak, of the scientist.  It is true, of course, that human relations do not work out as we desire them to, but if we are careful in the selection of the chairman and of the scientist I do not think any real difficulty will arise.</P>
    <P>In any case, there will always be the possibility of appeal to the council.  A director can have an appeal to the council; he can put proposals before the council and he can have these proposals considered.  While there is a risk, as Senator Hayes suggested, I think that on the whole we must make up our minds as to which system we want.  I think this system is preferable to the proposal in the other Bill&mdash;the one to which I think Senator Hayes would have us revert.  I have examined this as dispassionately as I could.  So have the Government.  We are of the opinion that this is the better system.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I favour very much the division of power as suggested in the Bill.  First of all, agriculture is very diverse.  It is connected with so many other faculties that no one man has the intellectual completeness in science to be able to run the Agricultural Institute as his private company, as it were, and the introduction of a chairman will give the opportunity of putting a fresh viewpoint into the institute.  While the Taoiseach said the chairman need not necessarily be a scientist, I should like to feel that would be the exception.  I should like to feel that the chairman would really be somebody engaged in agricultural teaching or in agricultural advisory work or in some other big branch of agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think that the lay technical man, the professional administrator, would provide a very good counterpart to the director in this institute.  I think we will provide the chance of an occasional <Col N="1341" /> disagreement between the director and the chairman even though both may be scientists.  We must take the chance that there will be such disagreements rather than tie the institute up in any conflict between pure administration and pure science.  I think that with common sense the two offices can work well together.  In American universities it is the practice that when the president of the university comes to a meeting of the governing body he must sit in the corner and be there to answer questions when asked by the governing body who are very definitely the ruling force.  As I have indicated, I am very much in favour of subdivision.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach began by explaining that the director must work under the council.  That, I think, is contained in my amendment&mdash; that he must be subject to the general direction of the council.  I realise he could not be otherwise.  The Taoiseach suggested that the chairman should not be just a narrow scientist.  The chairman, of course, will be a chairman in the first place, a person to preside at meetings, a person who must know how to conduct meetings, who will see that decisions are arrived at and that they are accurately recorded and efficiently carried out.  For that job you will require a person who knows the duties of chairmanship.</P>
      <P>According to the Taoiseach's statement we shall also require a person familiar with administration because, as I understand it, the administration of an office staff will be rather the business of the chairman than of the director.  If in addition to these two qualities the chairman requires a knowledge of agricultural problems also, it will be very difficult to find a chairman because in that context he must presumably be a practical farmer and as well be acquainted with the scientific basis of farming.  I know there are such people but I believe they are rather few.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Quinlan envisaged a situation in which we would have a new chairman every three years.  I am not so sure that is sound and I do not think it was ever intended that the <Col N="1342" /> director of the institute should be in the position, as has been suggested here by Senator Quinlan, that he should direct the institute as if it were his own private business.  Of course that is not so, because both in this Bill, in the previous one and in my amendment the director would be under the direction of the council.</P>
    <P>I agree that the decision the Taoiseach has reached was arrived at <i>bona fides</i> and with the purpose of giving us the best possible institute, but it seems to me there are serious difficulties in the way of finding the type of person we want.  I still do not see, and I do not think anybody sees, precisely where the line of demarcation is drawn between the functions of the chairman and the director.  However, I have explained my view on the matter and I am afraid I cannot do more about it except to express the hope&mdash;because the matter is of immense interest to us all&mdash;that the matter will work out in the very best possible way as between the chairman, when appointed, and the director, when appointed.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>I am hesitant, for a number of reasons, to express any view on this section, though it is a vital part of the Bill.  It is not the kind of instrument at all I would have chosen.  I hope it will work.  This discussion on the section seems to me to be like a discussion about the European Free Trade Area.  Nobody knows how it will work.  It was a very good thing that Senator Hayes put down his amendment in regard to the chairman.  I think it is inherent in a plan where you have two people who may be regarded as of equal competence in their own fields that you have a clash of personalities.  This clash of personalities is quite common in this country.  The Taoiseach has not made it quite clear what his mind is or what is the mind of the Government with regard to the manning of the institute, with regard to the director and the chairman.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There will be a great deal of difficulty in the way of getting rid of prejudice against this institute.  There has been a fair amount of controversy <Col N="1343" /> about it up to the present.  Many of the people who are interested in it do not know how it will function.  Its functions will be distributed around so many bodies and authorities in the country that the part each will play will not be too easy to grasp.</P>
    <P>It is vital therefore that as regards the personnel of the institute the director and chairman should have outstanding qualities to recommend them.  I am disposed to support Senator Hayes's view in regard to the importance of having one person, but with this note of warning: There are very few people available in this country to do this work.  I would say that the Taoiseach should act in the same way in this connection as in regard to the Institute for Advanced Studies&mdash;look for the very best people available to us anywhere in the world. The prestige of agricultural education, let us say what we like about it, is not very high amongst thoughtful, progressive Irish farmers.  That is for reasons into which I do not propose to go here, the product partly of our history, our lack of finance, our insular position and many other reasons.  If we are to give this institute the prestige which it ought to have to command the confidence of the most thoughtful amongst us, right from the beginning, we ought to get the very best person we can buy in any country in the world.  I have heard agricultural scientists from New Zealand talking here and it is no reflection on our own scientists when I say that we have not got their equal here.</P>
    <P>As regards looking for a scientist as a director&mdash;and science in relation to agriculture is a very wide field indeed &mdash;Senator Hayes's suggestion would be impossible of operation because it would be inadvisable to bring a foreign scientist into the country who had been working in the field of agricultural science for years and make him chairman of a council of Irishmen. For that reason, the Taoiseach's plan is a better one.  Perhaps he has in mind what I am suggesting&mdash;at least I would hope so.  If it could operate like that from the beginning, the institute would get a tremendous start. <Col N="1344" /> We are in so many groups and cliques in this country that if we are to put this institute on the plane on which it ought to be, then for the sake of agriculture and the future of the nation, we ought to look elsewhere for something we have not got amongst ourselves, and that is no reflection on our own people.</P>
    <P>In regard to the chairman, the Taoiseach has indicated that he need not be a scientist.  Of course, he need not be a scientist, but if there are people here who have a close acquaintance with science, it would not be any harm to have them.  There are people in Ireland who are tremendously interested in agricultural science and have given evidence of their interest and confidence in that field over the years.  I do not think I hold with Senator Quinlan that you can go out amongst the advisory services or out amongst some other of our services teaching in the agricultural field and bring in somebody to be chairman of this council.  If you went out to draw your chairman from that field, he might not be a very good chairman and a number of the people on the council might themselves demonstrate that they were much better informed and knew more about the problems involved than did the chairman himself. That would be a rather invidious position for a chairman to occupy.  However, if we are to have somebody with a knowledge of science, it would be an unfortunate position for a director to be in&mdash;I am speaking of a director who would be regarded as being highly competent in his field&mdash;if he were to come into his council and his chairman and to find that his language was Greek to them.  There ought to be, through the chairman, the possibility of an interpreter to the council.  Therefore, the kind of person you would have as chairman ought to be competent as such, but he ought to have other qualifications as well.</P>
    <P>These two people will have a profound influence on the attitude of the institute to the problems of the country in future.  There are other matters I wish to raise in regard to the council, but perhaps I should not do so on the amendment.</P>
    <Col N="1345" />
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Hardly on the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach knows better than most of us in this House that this new institute is starting out under difficulties.  There are many sceptics, and it will not be an easy task to restore confidence on that higher plane in agricultural thought because I am afraid some of us were turned off the road in the beginning.  Much is yet possible through the decision which the Taoiseach and his Cabinet will make with regard to these two people.  People of the standing which I urge we ought to get can be found and no effort should be spared to find them.  The Taoiseach can then be proud of his achievement in piloting this Bill through, but if he fails there, I am afraid the institute will have great difficulty in making for success in our generation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of information, may I say we have many very highly qualified scientists, especially people who have gone abroad to work in other countries?  I should like to quote a recent phrase of the Taoiseach that we should not hide our light under a bushel.  I welcome the coming in of outside scientists and I have an amendment down to facilitate that.  On the other hand, I believe that our own can hold their own anywhere they go.  I might mention that the head of a section of O.E.E.C. is an Irish graduate.  The head of the Dairy Section in New Zealand holds a diploma for a two years' course from U.C.C. In America, there are several distinguished. Irish graduates.  Our numbers may be small but our people have proved that when they get the chance and the facilities they can hold their own with anybody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say that there is no doubt that the chairman will require to have a number of exceptional qualities, just as Senator Hayes has said; but if the Senator seeks to make him a scientist as well, he is going to add a further quality to the others, that is that he will know his own subject, that he will have <Col N="1346" /> a professional scientist's knowledge in his own subject, which is agriculture. I take it if we can get a man who is an agricultural scientist and has proved himself in that field, that is the sort of man we want, but if we have to combine that quality with the qualities Senator Hayes said the chairman should have, then it is going to make it still more difficult to choose your man.  There are two very important posts to fill and, in my opinion, it is easier to get the two filled than to get one filled because with one you have to try to combine in the scientist the other qualities.  Many of them may be found in scientists, but they may not be found because the person who is a professional scientist and who has devoted himself to his work has possibly concentrated so much on it that he has not got the way of dealing with men which people living in less restricted atmospheres may have.</P>
      <P>However, we can argue about that for a very long time.  There are two points of view and we have taken the present one.  I believe on the whole that it is the better one and I can only say that we have no particular people in mind.  I have not got any and the Minister for Agriculture has not got anybody in view.  The question of personnel was not discussed.  There is no outstanding person who would obviously be the person to be chosen as chairman.  We do not see any outstanding man; although there may be one and I do not see him but that may be my fault.  I think in this matter we should follow the scheme of the Bill and have the duties divided.  I would say the duties of the director would be to look after the strictly scientific side of the work.  On the other hand, I would say the chairman would have to look after the dissemination of the information gained, to try to see that the members of the council were fully alive to current proposals in agriculture and to see that proposals of that particular type were not neglected by the scientific head.</P>
      <P>I think that the duties of the two offices are fairly well separated.  You will see the separation well if you ask: &ldquo;What is the scientist to do?&rdquo;  and keep your mind on what he has to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1347" /> The rest, you would say, is to lie with the chairman.  Although it is true that even under Senator Hayes's proposal, the director would be subject to the council, still it is an unsatisfactory position that a member of the council should also be subject to it, particularly if he were chairman.  If the council took a different view, it would be very awkward in administrative work afterwards. I think the general body will be for planning, advising generally, and deciding broad matters of policy and the scientist will examine any suggestions that may come to him from the council.  If you look at it that way, you will see work for both and there are duties where they come together and perhaps overlap.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to withdraw this amendment, but I think it was desirable to put it down for it has produced a very enlightening discussion. I readily agree there is something to be said on both sides.  In any event, we are somewhat clearer on the respective functions of the chairman and director.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 10, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 11 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 12:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (6), line 6, after &ldquo;office&rdquo; to add &ldquo;at the request of a two-thirds majority of the ordinary members of the council&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I just want to bring the council and the institute into the picture.  I wish that the council of the institute, by a reasonable majority, could make a recommendation to the Government to have the chairman removed.  If there was a serious clash between the chairman and the director and if it reached such proportions that some action had to be taken, then we take it that the first body that would be cognisant of the need should be the council of the institute itself, and the council, excluding the chairman.  I just want to know could the machinery for the removal of the chairman give some say to the council?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1348" />
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>It would help me to judge the merits of this amendment, if the Taoiseach would clarify a certain number of points.  The chairman is appointed by the President.  That seems to differ from the ordinary procedure where an appointment is made by the Government.  I wonder would the Taoiseach say why the President is brought into the picture for this appointment? Then again, the appointment is made for a maximum period of three years. Three years appear to me to be a very short time, particularly when there is no reference in the section to reappointment. I notice that for the ordinary council members the Schedule provides that they can be reappointed, but I do not notice that particular provision for the chairman.  Of course it could be said that it is not really necessary to provide for reappointment, that he could be appointed for three years, again for another three years and so on, but reading it there and putting it side by side with the provisions for the ordinary members, it would appear that the intention is to have appointment for three years only and that there will not be a reappointment. I wonder would the Taoiseach kindly clarify these points for me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the appointment being made by the President, it is, of course, true that the President, in practically all cases, except in those in which he acts under the powers given to him by the Constitution, acts under powers given by the Government.  Partly because of the prestige of the office of chairman, the appointment will actually be made by the President.  This practice has been followed in a number of other cases, in the appointment of judges and, in some instances, professors in the Institute for Advanced Studies.  It is common practice when important posts are being filled in that way on Government advice, that they be given the prestige of appointment by the President himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As to the question of removal, there would probably be some remuneration and there is also the question of successive Governments.  One of the reasons why a period of three years is <Col N="1349" /> thought to be desirable is that it will mean, if there are different Governments, when the three-year period ends, these different Governments may have the opportunity of making appointments.  I do not think there is anything to prevent any Government from advising the President to reappoint a chairman.  I do not know why the other provision was specifically put in, that is, that the ordinary members could be reappointed.  It would be too much of a pointer to the Government to say that the chairman could be reappointed.  It might hold out hopes, where hopes should not be entertained.  Though I had nothing to do with the drafting of that part of the Bill, I think it is just as well to leave it as it is.  I do not think it makes any real difference.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>In the case of a request, would it be common procedure for a request to come from the council to the Government saying that it would be impossible to carry on with the chairman?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Remember some members of the council will be appointed by the Government and you may be perfectly certain that the Minister for Agriculture will be sufficiently interested in the work of the institute to keep in reasonable touch with its doings.  Clashes like that, when they occur, are generally resounding and they are heard.  I think, if clashes such as the Senator has suggested, occur, the Government would not need to have its ear to the ground to know what is happening.  I think it is not desirable the section should be amended as suggested by the Senator.  When the Senator says &ldquo;two-thirds&rdquo;, he does not indicate what way it is to operate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it then there is no doubt in any of our minds, with regard to this important post, that neither of the two political Parties would in any way be guilty of putting a man into the chairmanship just because of his political connections, or removing an existing chairman because the Government might change in the meantime?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1350" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope not, but it could happen that you would have two very very good men, each of whom could be chosen, and one might have indicated a slight inclination towards one sort of policy in regard to agriculture in general, and the other an inclination towards a somewhat different policy.  I do not think, however, we need have any real fears about this and I personally prefer the short term rather than the long term.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I was concerned with the short term more than the three-year period.  It has not been our practice to remove chairmen just because a Government has changed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe I can say, with a fair amount of experience in changes of Government, that if a man is doing his work particularly or exceptionally well, I do not think he will be changed.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 5 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>There are some interesting things about sub-section (8). It is framed very properly, of course, to give powers to the Government to determine by what method the nominees of the agricultural and rural organisations will be chosen by these organisations.  What shall I say of these organisations?  They are fluid and very often numerous, and it seems to me that the appointment of representatives could be difficult.  I suppose we will have to wait until we see the regulations that are made, but the body itself is a small one and five representatives is a considerable number.  I know claims were made for a greater number still, but the very wording of sub-section (8) indicates the difficulties which this Government, or any other Government, would experience in finding people for nomination, if that is the proper word.  I do not know if we are entitled to any information, or if it is right to ask for any information, but I think the nomination of these people will cause considerable difficulty. I do not know if the Taoiseach contemplates that the Government of the day would have a choice, or <Col N="1351" /> whether they would perforce have to take persons nominated to them by the agricultural and rural organisations.  I would rather deal with that sub-section by itself, though I have something to say about sub-section (9) also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnobháin Seán Ó Donnobháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnobháin</NameTxt>
      <P>This sub-section puzzled me to some extent also.  You have a five-four-three system.  There are five to be appointed from the agricultural and rural organisations and Senator Hayes has mentioned the difficulty in choosing them. I did not catch whether he said they were numerous or humorous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I said they were fluid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnobháin Seán Ó Donnobháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnobháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I said I did not know if he said they were numerous or humorous.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Not humorous, no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnobháin Seán Ó Donnobháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnobháin</NameTxt>
      <P>There are five nominess to come from these organisations, four from the universities and three to be direct appointees of the Government, but yet it is the Government nominate them all.  The four University Colleges will nominate, or send up names, to the Government and there will have to be a system devised whereby the rural organisations can send up five names.  The section seems to read that the Government must be satisfied with those nine names sent up to them and they will then supplement those nine with three other appointees, probably from the Civil Service.  I agree with Senator Hayes there may be a difficulty in selecting the five representatives of the agricultural and rural organisations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to that point and the problem confronting the Government in the selection of representatives from the agricultural and rural organisations, I wonder if the Taoiseach can enlighten us further? We know that a group of farm organisations have already met the Minister for Agriculture on this point. Whether they got any enlightenment or not, I do not know, nor do I know if there is any clarification of the Government's views with regard to <Col N="1352" /> the regulations under which the five members are to be selected, and how many farm organisations are to be consulted in regard to the selection of these nominees.</P>
      <P>I am quite satisfied, no matter what you do in regard to this matter, there will be farmers and farm organisations very dissatisfied.  It is regrettable that they all cannot be got together into one body so that they could do their work together, as is done in Britain and elsewhere.  However, it is not so here.  What divides them I just do not know.  They are like our political Parties&mdash;as much divided by personalities as by anything else.  It is just one of the tragedies of the country at the moment, but it will create very great difficulty.  Consequently, I would welcome whatever the Taoiseach has to say by way of enlightenment and I am sure the farm organisations will welcome it as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry I cannot give the Senator very much enlightenment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="Mr. Baxter Mr. Baxter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Baxter</NameTxt>
      <P>Tell us what you know.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>You know quite as much about it as I do.  I told the Minister for Agriculture: &ldquo;Get busy, because if you want to be ready with your Order when the Bill is law, there is a great deal of preliminary work to be done.  Try to divide them into sections where you can so that it would be reasonable that each of these sections would nominate one member to the council.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is a problem which has come up time after time when we have been dealing with rural organisations and, more specifically, with farmers' organisations. One of our great difficulties is that we have not so far evolved an organisation which could be said to be representative of agriculture as a whole.  However, I think we are moving in that direction, bit by bit. I am sorry to say I cannot say what will be in the Order, except to say that the Minister is busy trying to find the necessary foundation, if we can find it. I hope we can.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One would like to have an alternative. <Col N="1353" /> If I had to do it myself I would look around these various organisations, see where there were suitable people and pick them, if they were obviously interested in agriculture and interested in particular branches of it.  I would just pick them for their ability.  But if you did that, it would be immediately rejected.  If the Government were to do it without getting nominations, it would be said that the Government were going to pack the council, that the persons picked would not be farmers and that it would not be representative of the farming community at all.</P>
    <P>The only way in which you can do it is to have unity afterwards, it is sections.  Divide it into five sections, if it can be reasonably done.  Try to put them into five classes and then try to bring these five classes together so that each section will nominate. It is an extremely difficult problem, I admit.  It is one of the things which offer most danger to the quick starting of the institute&mdash;that and the selection of the chairman and director.  Everything else would be reasonably plain sailing.  I am sorry I cannot enlighten the Senator any more.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is just one danger in all those nominations by specific bodies, that is, if the council is to have unity afterwards, it is essential that the members elected should really cease to feel connected directly with their organisation and should feel that they are selected on this as one of a team of 12 to do a job.</P>
      <P>I had experience recently with an outside member of our governing body in the university.  He said to me: &ldquo;One thing that really amazes me is the way you professors come in here to the governing body and oppose tooth and nail a decision arrived at by the Academic Council, that you sink your opposition in the governing body.&rdquo; I would like to feel that the same freedom would prevail among the ordinary members of the council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make a comment on sub-section (9).  It seems to be an example of the counting <Col N="1354" /> of heads by democracy.  There are four University Colleges in the State and each is given a representative.  I am not proposing any amendment.  I hope it will work out all right, but I think it is right to point out there is only one working faculty and seat of agriculture in the State and that is at University College, Dublin.  It has been there for more than 30 years.  It is the largest university college in the State and it gets only one representative, although it has an agricultural faculty actually working.  I think it is rather curious to allow something like &ldquo;one man, one vote&rdquo; to work in this particular way.  It may be all right, but from the point of view of practical acquaintance with the kind of thing with which the institute is dealing, one would imagine that there are more facilities at University College, Dublin, owing to the facts, than anywhere else, but it gets only one representative.  I am just pointing that out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to that, in the Senate of the United States, you have a small State represented equally with a large State, although I know you have a proportional counting of heads in the other House.  It is very difficult in these cases to make proportions and deal with them in accordance with numbers.  I think the present provision was in the original Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It was in the original Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>On the whole, it was felt it was the best way to deal with the situation.  If the one man is at all representative of the institution, he ought to know fairly well what is happening in that institution.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 6 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 13:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before Section 7 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There shall be paid, out of the income of the institute, to a member of the council ordinarily <Col N="1355" /> resident outside Éire such remuneration as the Minister may determine. </P>
    <P>The wording of this new section speaks for itself.  We might like to nominate some person from outside the country on the council.  He might happen to be a specialist in some branch and might happen to be available. It might be very useful to be able to appoint such a man, but the difficulty is he might feel he should get a fee for the appointment.  He might attend only five times in the year, but I think it would be worth while to pay a fee to such a man for his advice to the council.</P>
    <P>The only difference between this amendment and the amendment in Senator Quinlan's name is that I leave it to the Minister to determine what that remuneration might be because I thought it might be embarrassing for a council of mostly unpaid members to fix a fee for someone coming from abroad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is in line with the general discussion on the Second Reading of the Bill where, I think, there was a very large measure of agreement in the House that we should make the fullest possible use of outside help and, seeing that the Agricultural Institute is modelled to a great extent on the Agricultural Research Council in England, it would be a great help to have somebody from England who understands both the strength and weakness that is in the present Agricultural Research Council in England.  It would be well worth paying such a man, and I think men are available who would be only too anxious to help.  I can think of several who have come here and lectured in the past; they would be very reasonable in their demands, asking merely what would cover their expenses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have had also great help from the United States at all times and from their many distinguished scientists. We have had their advice in the drafting of this Bill and for the first few years it might be a nice gesture on the part of the Government, and it <Col N="1356" /> would certainly contribute a lot to the ultimate success of the institute, if the Government would use one of its three nominations to appoint some person from the United States to the council of the institute.</P>
    <P>Below the council there must necessarily be a research council and I think there, especially, outside scientists could make a tremendous contribution. We may not be able to get them to come here and work 12 months of the year for us, but if they would come and spend just a day or two days meeting and having discussions with the director and his staff, such people would be invaluable on one of the committees that will necessarily be set up by the Agricultural Institute.</P>
    <P>In putting down my amendment I had the benefit of knowing of Senator Cole's amendment and I just thought that the matter was not quite so grave that it might be left to the Minister. I regarded it as an ordinary financial decision that the council itself should be capable of making.  However, I have no hard views on that but I am really concerned that we should recognise the principle of bringing in outside help&mdash;as you might put it&mdash;on a part-time basis.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I altogether agree that it would be very foolish not to avail of whatever information and knowledge are at our disposal in any country and particularly in the countries that have been mentioned, in Britain and the United States, but I think that to avail of that information or knowledge it is not necessary that the person we want should be a member of the council.  I think it is better that the council should consist, in the main, of Irish people and that if we do want foreign assistance&mdash;and I am sure we desire it&mdash;the council of the institute can get it by asking these people to come along and give scientific help.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is no reason why such persons should not come here as consultants; there is no reason why, if there is somebody in the Agricultural Research Council in Britain whose views would be of value, he should not be consulted <Col N="1357" /> or asked to come here.  His expenses can be paid.  There is nothing to prevent the council paying the expenses of those who may be asked to give scientific advice here.  I believe the advice required can be got in that way.  It is a different matter to appoint a person as a member of the council.  I need not go into it, but all sorts of difficulties might arise if we did that.  I think it is better that such people should be available as scientific advisers and that can be arranged&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it clear that there is power in the institute to pay for assistance of that kind?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would say so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>That would be contained in the powers of sub-section (2) of Section 4, that they can make a grant?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>And in the expenses section also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>There is something more than expenses.  Senator Cole and Senator Quinlan both contemplated that persons from outside the jurisdiction of the State might be brought in and that it would be worth paying not only their travelling expenses and subsistence but also fees and I take it, in this generality of powers in Section 4, the institute would have power to pay such persons?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel certain it would.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Members of the council?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>No, not members of the council.  I am adopting the Taoiseach's suggestion that the council can invite such people here if they are not members of the council and can pay not only expenses but also such fees as may be agreed on.  I take it that is possible?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am practically certain it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to move my amendment.  I merely put <Col N="1358" /> it down to reiterate what we expressed on the Second Reading of the Bill&mdash; the desirability of getting in as much outside help as we can on what I might call a part-time basis.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 13, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 14 not moved.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 15:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), line 28, to delete &ldquo;a director&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;directors&rdquo;, and in line 29 to delete &ldquo;Director&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Directors&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>To my mind this is the way out of the difficulty of chairman and director. Some of my remarks perhaps would apply to the amendment which Senator Hayes has put down.  I thought it would be a very difficult matter to distinguish between the chairman and the director but we have the chairman appointed by the President.  Perhaps that is right but then we have the director who is to be &ldquo;the chief officer of the institute&rdquo;.  That was my difficulty and I thought that perhaps by appointing more than one director, not alone would it solve that difficulty but that it would also be more appropriate to the work that was being done.</P>
      <P>He controls the activities of the staff but the Taoiseach himself has said that the director would be a highly skilled man.  We might have a highly skilled man in veterinary research and yet he would not be highly skilled, and would probably know nothing about, plant breeding, to take two more or less opposite branches.  For that reason I would suggest that we should have directors, and that perhaps some man might be appointed on the veterinary research side to deal with animal diseases and that sort of thing and that another man might be appointed, when the time came that it would be necessary, to deal with plant breeding, plant diseases and such botanical subjects.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If you could find a man who would have sufficient knowledge to deal with <Col N="1359" /> all those sides of the institute's work, well and good, but I do not think it is possible.  I do not think any man would be likely to specialise in the different branches the institute may be dealing with.  If we appoint a man skilled in one branch he would not be able to report back to the council in the technical language that perhaps the members of the council would demand.  Undoubtedly, there will be men on the council who will be specialists in their own line and if we have a general director more or less as the link between them and the research workers, he will not be able to answer questions before a council meeting or report in the technical language that perhaps some of the members might demand.  I envisage a man who was himself taking part in the research work being appointed a director over the work that was being done on those lines in different centres.</P>
    <P>Take the case of research carried on in Dublin and Cork.  I envisage saying to one of the chief workers: &ldquo;You shall be the director of this work.  You can co-ordinate and compare and report to the council.&rdquo;  Take another case.  Supposing the institute were asked by the Minister to tackle some fairly immediate, let us say, veterinary problem that arose.  If there were two teams of workers, you might like to put both teams working on the same problem.  A director who was a general director&mdash;and a director under the Bill must be a very general man&mdash;would not be able to co-ordinate and compare the work of those two teams and report to the council in detail in technical language on the work that they were doing.</P>
    <P>Research work in this country, necessarily, would be carried out at varying and scattered centres and a director who was in charge of all the research carried out by the institute would not be qualified to gather in reports and translate them or might have difficulty in doing so if he were merely a general administrator, possibly qualified in one branch or two branches but not in every branch and he would not be in a position to report to the same extent as the specialist to the council.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1360" /> Again, it might be desirable to import a director for a term, a man who had carried out certain research work in England or America, if we were starting where they had left off.  It might be very useful to have such a person as a director for a time.  I would suggest that by appointing a chairman and giving him the general administration and appointing directors with more scientific knowledge of the exact activity they would be engaged in, the best results would be achieved.</P>
    <P>We have discussed Senator Hayes's amendment and I do not want to repeat what I have said but I think there will be a certain amount of difficulty experienced if the chairman and director are both more or less general, able men but not specialists.  My amendment would produce a director as a specialist over the activities allotted to him.  He might be a director only for a short term until some problem would be solved or until they had advanced as far as they could go and he could then go back to his ordinary duties or combine the directorship with his ordinary duties.  It would be a much more satisfactory position to have a technical, highly skilled man over each branch who could report in technical language to the members of the council who are qualified to inquire into the activities of that branch.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Most of what the Senator has said will, of course, happen in practice.  Undoubtedly, there will be research sections and in each section there will be some person who will be in control.  These will, in fact, be acting as the Senator has said but I do not think we should give them a title here or regard them as completely independent.  You do want to have some co-ordinating head and the director that is mentioned in the Bill is to be the chief person to co-ordinate the work in the various sections, to see that there is no overlapping.  It is quite possible that there may be two sections, A and B, and the same sort of research might very well fall under either of the sections.  It would be well to have somebody who would say: &ldquo;Although you, A, can claim that it should come into your section and section <Col N="1361" /> B can claim that it can come into theirs, on the whole it is better that it should be done by such and such a section&rdquo;.  That is a rough example of what occurs to me.  There will be heads of the various sections, of course.  The only thing is, are we to give them the name &ldquo;director&rdquo;?  Are we to give them a statutory title here?  I do not know what name will be given to them ultimately. They will be the chiefs of the different sections but the director that we have in question here is to be the head person over all the sections, not having any one particular section under his control, but operating in a supervisory and advisory capacity over the lot.</P>
      <P>The Senator has given an example once or twice by reference to veterinary science.  This Bill is not intended to cover it.  There are difficulties in regard to the veterinary situation at the moment and they will have to be resolved differently but it is not intended in the main that this Bill should cover it.  It is not mentioned as one of the sections of agriculture or branches associated with agriculture that are covered.  There is a good deal that can be said on both sides.  This is extraneous to the amendment but I thought there might be some misapprehension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I only took that as an example.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg your pardon. I was afraid, as the Senator used it twice that there might possibly be a misunderstanding and I should not like the Bill to be passed with any misunderstanding about it.</P>
      <P>I think, therefore, that to have several directors, each having independent access to the council, would create difficulty and it would really mean that the chairman would have to do the work that is intended to be done by the director at present.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 16 was consequential on amendment No. 15.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 16 and 17 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1362" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 18 and 20 may be discussed together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 18:</P>
      <P>In sub-section (3), line 35, to delete &ldquo;for such term and.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This is really an amendment of sub-section (9) of Section 7.  In other words, it seems wrong to appoint a director for a certain term of years and then give the council power to dismiss him. I ask leave to withdraw the amendment now because I am satisfied with the amendment proposed by the Government to Section 9.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 19:</P>
      <P>In sub-section (3), line 35, after &ldquo;term&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;not exceeding seven years.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I indicated on the Second Stage that this matter was something that ought to be considered.  The powers of the director are somewhat limited in this Bill but, in spite of that, the success of the institute will depend largely, if not entirely, on the qualities of the director and this amendment is aimed at securing, I hope, the type of director who would be most competent.  The director would have to co-operate with various types of personnel in charge of research in the country, in a number of institutions.  He must be able to give balanced decisions amongst diverse interests.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He has also other functions as well. He must have a wide acquaintance with the agricultural industry and with scientific literature.  He must be a scientist with a width of knowledge rather than an accurate acquaintance with a particular line of work.  It would be very difficult, as has already been indicated by the Taoiseach, to get a person possessing these qualities. It might perhaps be desirable to consider whether you could not appoint such a person for a limited period or get a person seconded for a limited period rather than appoint him for good.  You might have a situation where the directorship would be filled by a person who, after years, would be found to be undesirable but who <Col N="1363" /> had disconnected himself entirely with his employment.</P>
    <P>At the beginning of the National University in 1908 the British Government appointed a commission.  That commission appointed a number of professors and lecturers on a seven year basis.  I think all were reappointed at the end of the seven years but it gave an opportunity of seeing what they were like.  There are difficulties both ways.  It is difficult to get a man to leave a post which he may hold for life to go into a post which may last only seven years.  This is a matter of very great importance. A person appointed for seven years could be given certain rights, even certain pension rights.  It might easily be discovered for scientific reasons or reasons of competency or even psychological reasons that the director was not suitable.  Therefore, a shorter period than life might be desirable.</P>
    <P>The matter is one of complexity and difficulty but it would be better that he should be appointed for a seven year period than for life.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to urge this amendment pretty strongly.  On the one hand, we are all agreed that we want to get the best possible man as director.  However, that means also that, in five years' time, we should like to feel we had then the best man possible as director, or in 15 years' time&mdash;at that point&mdash;that we had the best man at the helm.  We are all agreed on that simple proposition. Our feeling for our fellow man is such that we do not like to displace anybody and it somehow blurs our vision. In other words, we want to guarantee the livelihood and the prospects of the director&mdash;and quite rightly so.  We feel that, unless we are prepared to do that, we will not get the best possible man at the present moment.  It has been said that the field is limited at present. It is.  I feel, however, we can get a good director at present.  Nobody can guarantee that the man we appoint in a few months' time will, in seven or ten years' time, be superior to other men who will be around in ten years' time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1364" /> If the first director does the job of launching the institute effectively, I think he should not take it as any reflection upon himself if, after a certain period, he is assigned to some less arduous task.  In fact, after the hurly-burly of getting the thing launched, and the many cares of the directorship, I could appreciate a situation in which it would be very nice for the director to retire into some type of research professorship where he would not suffer any diminution in salary and where he would be able to carry on and do very useful work in a research capacity.  From that point of view, I urge that we should impose some time limit.  At the end of such time, of course, the council would have the statutory obligation of reviewing the situation&mdash;of seeing if they think the present occupant should be renewed for a further period or if it would be better that he should take over some other post, suffering no diminution in salary, and whether there are other young men around very eager and likely to make a very good job of it. From that point of view, my amendments Nos. 19 and 21&mdash;and also the subsequent amendments in relation to superannuation&mdash;are all linked together.</P>
    <P>I urge that we give very strong consideration to this matter.  The risk of being saddled not with a dud&mdash;I would not class any appointment we might make as being that of &ldquo;a dud&rdquo;&mdash;but the risk of being saddled with a man one degree less good than a man we could get in ten years' time is too great to take when we can prevent it now and make it appear as if no reflection is placed on a director if he is retired to some less arduous job afterwards.</P>
    <P>In picking a democratic Government, we take our Taoiseach and Ministers for a maximum of five years.  We are quite satisfied that that system works.  We do not even guarantee their livelihood afterwards.  I suggest we take care of the livelihood of the director in this way and ensure that we have conditions in which we can get the best man at each period.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>About the analogy of people who go up for election for political office, the law of supply and <Col N="1365" /> demand settles that.  I am afraid that the question of supply and demand will not settle that of finding a first class and suitable director.  If we were asked here in the Seanad to undertake the task of getting the best director available, we should like to be fairly free in relation to the conditions that would be imposed upon us at the start because we do not know who are the people from whom the selection would have to be made, and what are the conditions in which they would find themselves&mdash;what it may be necessary to do, what term, and so on, you may have to offer in order to secure the services of the best person.</P>
      <P>I think the considerations mentioned by the Senators who have spoken would be very clearly before the minds of any body, whether the Government on the one hand or the council on the other hand, in trying to get a suitable person as director.  I think they would be anxious to have as short a period as possible in order that they might see what the director was like.  Reappointment would be possible after a period.  I am very much afraid of statutory limitations.  It might happen that they would just debar you from doing what you want to do, namely, to get the best.  In this matter, I think it is wiser for us to leave the bodies charged with the responsibility of trying to get the best as open a field as you can in the belief that they will work for the best interests of the institute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think that life appointments are very likely.  I think that if we could do what was done by the Dublin Commission when the National University was founded&mdash;as was referred to by Senator Hayes&mdash;if we could get a person for a period of seven years or less it would be the most desirable thing.  However, we do not know, until we examine the field, the conditions under which we can get the best man.  Although I see the reasons why Senators wish to shorten the period, I would plead to leave it open because these considerations must of necessity be before the minds of the bodies that will be responsible for the <Col N="1366" /> selection of this very important officer. In the long run, we will have to depend for the welfare of this institute on the ability of the council, the patriotism of the council and their singlemindedness when it comes to the question of appointments.  The one object to keep in mind, is the good of the institute.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>According to what is set out here the council can impose such terms on subsequent directors?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The first director is appointed by the Government and the Government has to consider the terms of appointment.  There is one grave danger here.  When the Government are arranging terms there is this matter of precedent in Government service.  Will the director of this institute be graded as a principal officer or as assistant secretary of a Department?  We should like to feel that the salary concerned would not in any way be tied by precedent.  If we want to get the best man possible the grade should be equivalent to at least that of a secretary of a Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it there is no precedent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is without precedent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>But as far as Finance is concerned&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The precedent in Finance is that they will get a man for the lowest figure at which they can possibly get him, and I think the Taoiseach will agree with me on that.  If Finance could get a man for 2½d. per day, they would take him and they would write a long memorandum to explain that he was the best man available.  However, there is something in what the Taoiseach has said, that the Bill has a certain flexibility in it, that by leaving open the terms upon which people are to come, the proper conclusion could be reached, and that a period of seven years might be detrimental.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am impressed by the Taoiseach's <Col N="1367" /> argument, both in regard to the first director and the directors to be appointed by the council.  It depends upon the age of the person, upon the pension he has already accumulated, if he is already in the service of a university or in any other service in which he has accumulated pension rights.  I would not be prepared to press my view upon the matter.  I can see you have to consider certain people and you have to consider what terms they are prepared to come on. But I am afraid there is no precedent and I would not think it would be desirable that we should say that this person should get a particular type of salary.  I would like to see him getting a good salary.  If you got an extraordinarily good man you might have to pay him a particularly good salary.  Since the amount of money involved in our agriculture is very great, I think nobody would begrudge a suitable person almost any salary he would want.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will there be some limitation on the period of the first director?  Will he be subject to reappointment after a specific number of years?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot, of course, say in advance what would be the terms and I cannot speak for the Government, not having consulted them, but I can indicate that would be my own approach to it.  I would prefer the appointee to have a preliminary short period with the right, if possible, of being considered for reappointment. A good man who would feel confident he could make good would not object to a short term.  I would be more interested in having the term short than in having the salary small so that the man could prove himself. If we appoint a person from outside he might have to prove himself under entirely different conditions from the conditions in which he is accustomed to work.  In general, if my voice would be the determining one, I would say I would try to secure the best man possible for the shortest possible period, that is, a preliminary period, and if I had to pay more on that <Col N="1368" /> account for that period, I would be willing to do it.  As I have said, I do not like the statutory limitation.</P>
      <P>I would like to tell Senators that the considerations which they have put forward will be kept in mind by the Government when they are making their appointment and I believe that, in the nature of things, they will be kept in mind by the council in relation to the subsequent appointments.  This Bill has been very carefully examined and, except for pressing reasons, I should not like to change it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the assurance given by the Taoiseach.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 20 and 21 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 22:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (5), paragraph (a), line 44, to delete &ldquo;or gratuity or both&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;and or gratuity, and or research appointment&rdquo;. </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 22 and 23 may be taken together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>These two amendments could be met by enabling the director, while enjoying superannuation, to have some research appointment at the institute.  What I am endeavouring to do is to safeguard the livelihood of the director in the eventuality of his being asked to make way for somebody else as director.  I felt it would not be quite reasonable to pension a man off at 50 or 55 and that it would be far better if he were given the opportunity, up to the normal retiring age of 65 or 70, of working in another capacity, say, research, for the institute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>That can be done without having it mentioned in the Bill.  The less we put in the Bill the better.  It is a sort of constitution for the institute and we ought not to go into narrow particulars.  If a good man is on the point of retiring from the position of director, if he is a <Col N="1369" /> specialist in a particular branch there will be no difficulty.  I can see no reason why he would not be attached to the institute as a research man. The Senator, however, has made a suggestion as to whether a thing like that should or should not be written into a superannuation scheme.  That is worth examining, but I do not know what the result of such examination will be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 23 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 24:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (8), line 3, to delete &ldquo;not&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I am putting forward the amendment in order to provide that the director shall be a member of the council.  It seems to me that the director will be a person of great importance in the work of this institute and that he should be a member of the council, that he should be present at council meetings, as of right, to put his views. We have that commonly in governing bodies of university colleges.  At meetings of such governing bodies academic people are present.  In this institute it would be no harm at all to have the director present to put his views directly to the council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The director of this institute will be responsible for very important work. In the nature of things, he will be a very responsible person and I think the council should have an opportunity of seeing him and hearing him at meetings as a member.  There are plenty of precedents for it and, for that reason, it seems to me that the proviso directly forbidding him to be a member of the council should be deleted.  I believe he should be a member of the council and that whatever consequential amendments are necessary to achieve this, such as enlarging the council to 13 members instead of 12, should be put through. I think there are a great many arguments in favour of allowing the <Col N="1370" /> council to hear the director as a member.  As it now appears, the members of the council will be people of experience, people with their own views as to what line the institute should go on, and the more intimate and close contact they have individually with the director the better.  I have two amendments, one that the director shall be a member of the council and the other that he shall have the right to attend and be heard at the council.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that I must again find myself on the other side of the fence from Senator Hayes. You can argue in favour of Senator Hayes's amendment which provides that the director shall be a member of the council, but the nature of this setup, if I may use these words, is that the council is in control and that the staff, from the director down, are subject to the council.  Anybody who has had the experience of being a member of a committee will realise how difficult it is to criticise, quietly and objectively, a person who is there present before the committee.  In this case it may happen occasionally that the council may have to consider the work done by the director and might have to find fault with it or consider it among themselves.</P>
      <P>I think that the right to attend or to be a member would cause difficulties in the case of the director.  I think it is much better that, as a matter of convenience to the council, the director will be invited to attend but that he will not attend as an absolute right. There may be matters that the council would wish to discuss in the absence of the director.  As the Bill stands they can do so, but if they have any problems on which they want advice they can have the director present to explain proposals.  If they are debating difficult questions they can ask his advice as an expert from the research side; they can ask him to clarify matters and thus enable them to arrive at decisions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That will mean that the director will be asked to come to say 90 per cent. of the meetings.  I would not put it as a right that he should attend because I do know that occasions occur, particularly <Col N="1371" /> in the case of a principal officer like that, on which it would be desirable that matters should be considered in his absence, thus giving the members an opportunity of expressing their opinions.  On the whole, I think it would be best to have the council the masters and the rest subject to them, so to speak.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach's view of the director is rather a lower view than the one I hold.  If the director is to be asked to attend meetings normally, then the occasion when he is not asked will be a red light to the director.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so, but if I were chairman I would be very careful at the start to have it made clear that the director would be summoned only for specific purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It occurs in a great many cases that the council of this kind of institute contains members of the technical staff, particularly the technical director.  I think that is the better arrangement.  However, if I cannot accomplish that I must be satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is somewhat different here.  Take the Attorney-General. He is not a member of the Government.  I do not think it could be thought that he attends meetings of the Government as a right.  However, no Government would deal with matters of law or be foolish enough to carry on meetings involving such matters without the presence of the Attorney-General.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder whether the Taoiseach thinks the Government is more or less sensible than a gathering of farmers and scientists?</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 25 not moved.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 26:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (9) and substitute the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1372" /> The council may, with the consent of the Government, at any time remove the director from office. </P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to explain that the terms &ldquo;incapacity&rdquo; and &ldquo;misconduct&rdquo;, mentioned in the sub-section as it now stands, cause a great deal of difficulty.  You might want to remove the director for reasons not covered by these terms. At the same time, you would want to give the director reasonable security and it was felt that if there was common agreement on the one hand between the Government, who would be more or less apart, and on the other hand the council, which would be in immediate control, reasonable security would be provided.  On the other hand, there passes over to the council from the start, from the moment he is appointed, a share of responsibility in regard to the director.  The director knows, from that on, that he is subject to the directions of the council. He knows the council can approach the Government to agree to his removal if anything goes wrong.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 27, 28, 29 and 30 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 7, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 8 and 9 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 31:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2), paragraph (a), line 43, before &ldquo;for&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;including the provision of equipment&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>This is mainly for elucidation.  I should like to feel that the facilities to be paid for out of capital funds included equipment&mdash;because at present that is likely to be very expensive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure the Senator that that is covered.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 32 not moved.</P>
      <P>Sections 10 and 11 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1373" /> SECTION 12.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 33:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (3).</P>
      <P>The amount of capital involved is by modern standards not very much, something less than £1,000,000.  That may be expended in the first eight or ten years of the life of the institute&mdash; certainly in some short period&mdash;and after that the State endowment of the institute will have to take account of both the capital needs and the running costs.  I felt that Section 3 more or less put a bar on the State contributing to such capital cost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is true that it is not intended in the Bill that the capital expenses should be taken into account in the State grant.  I would remind the Senator that we are not as well off as he thought&mdash;the capital fund is only £840,000, and not £1,000,000.</P>
      <P>I envisage this operating in two stages.  First of all, there is the period in which the capital expenses will be met from this particular fund which is made available now.  When that has been exhausted, the time will come when the State will have to deal with capital as well as ordinary running expenses.  For the present it is much better, I think, to leave this as it is. When that day comes, a capital grant will have to be made independently. Until then, it would be better to work on the basis that the capital expenditure will have to be met out of the capital fund.</P>
      <P>It is no harm at all that the institute should realise that there are not vast sums of money available.  The £840,000 as a capital grant is comparatively small.  On the other hand, as the present Bill envisages rather a coordinating authority, the amount necessary will not be as great as if we were proceeding on altogether different lines.  I think we will have to leave it as it is with regard to expenses until the time arises in which capital will have to be provided by the State.  It is better not to mix the two ideas at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1374" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the intention of the Government, then, that when the capital fund has been exhausted the capital cost of the institute will have to be met by the State?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Unless we get rich friends to endow us or get industries to endow research&mdash;or agriculture may do it, as the agricultural community might of itself see that it would be to its advantage to make contributions&mdash; I am afraid that, under the circumstances as they are, the demand will be made on the collective community, on the State.  Senators may be perfectly certain that when that day comes there will be enough voices raised in regard to the capital equipment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 12 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 34:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In paragraph (e), line 52, before &ldquo;and&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;, fellowships&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Section 2 makes provision for the granting of fellowships.  That is a very commendable provision.  I have been wondering whether it should not be mentioned in this section also.  Section 2 states the institute may provide for fellowships.  I wonder whether the cost should not then be a charge on the income of the institute and, if so, whether it is necessary to mention here both scholarships and fellowships.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that would lead to misunderstanding.  The word &ldquo;fellowships&rdquo; here really is a type of degree, it is an honorary title, it does not carry with it any special fund and there is no special cost.  For instance, if we had a post-graduate student from one of the colleges coming up and pursuing a course of research in the institute with the idea that he would be awarded a fellowship as the result, then the cost of that research can be borne in the ordinary way, but for fellowships as such I do not think there is any particular cost.  It is the award of a title.  If the gaining of <Col N="1375" /> that title involves research, the cost can be met in the ordinary way.  Of course, there is a cost for scholarships, because there you have to pay the individuals sums of money for subsistence and other allowances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I took it on first reading that fellowships involved some type of recognition, if someone were doing outstanding work and continuing to do it on behalf of the agricultural institute; and that as well as being an honour, carrying a certain amount of prestige and glory of its own, there might be a certain monetary award as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>If the institute wants to make payments for continuing research work to a person who has been awarded the title of fellow, they can do so; or if he is of sufficient standing he could be put on the research staff in the ordinary way, if he applies.  I think it would be a mistake for us here to attach to a fellowship anything other than making it a mark of having done commendable work of a high standard in some particular branch of the sciences in which the institute is concerned.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 13 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 14 to 19, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 35&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before Section 20 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>A quinquennial (or decennial) review shall be undertaken into the workings of the institute, including its relationship with the advisory services, the universities, the agricultural schools and vocational education by a commission, one-third of which shall be nominated by the institute council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>At present we are embarking on an experiment, setting up this Agricultural Institute.  We hope it is going to do a great deal, but I think it <Col N="1376" /> would be wise that in some five or ten years' time we should have an investigation to see how it is doing and what else it could do and, in general, how it could be made to serve the country better.  I should like to feel that when such a review takes place, it will not be regarded as a vote of &ldquo;no confidence&rdquo; in the institute, but that rather it will be regarded as something that was laid down when the institute was set up originally.</P>
    <P>I should like to see that principle applied to all bodies, to universities and every other body.  I should like to see a periodical review so that, when it took place, we would not feel that it was a vote of &ldquo;no confidence&rdquo; but that it was something inevitable, something statutory.  As well as that, any group outside that felt critical of the body could store up their criticisms, document them and so forth, knowing that they would have a chance some time in the near future of presenting their case.  It would make for far better relations in general and lead to fewer newspaper controversies by groups attacking some existing bodies, if one felt that there would be a time and a place where one could present one's criticisms and suggestions for improvements.</P>
    <P>I feel this applies especially in the case of the proposed Agricultural Institute. For instance, many of us would like to see the advisory services in closer association with the institute, but I think it is more prudent at the present just to set up the institute and let us see how it develops.  Maybe in five years' time it would be obvious that it can have a much closer association with the advisory services, and similarly with the agricultural schools and the faculties of agriculture.  At this stage, we should make provision for this review and I would like it to be a continuing affair, so that it would take place not merely in five years' time but again in another five or ten years' time after and so on.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no doubt that the Senator has made a case for a review, but again I am worried about making these things statutory.  Of course, the Senator will have to make <Col N="1377" /> up his mind whether it is a five or ten year period he wants.  On the whole, I think there is no use in trying to provide for everything for the future in a Bill like this.  Remember that annual grants have to be got.  The Minister for Finance and the Minister for Agriculture will be brought in when the council is looking for increased funds, or funds to meet their programme. They will have to justify that programme, and if a sum is being devoted, they will have to have an Estimate in the Dáil, and there will be ample opportunity for criticism then, if you like, but if there is anything more detailed, I think we should leave it to the future.</P>
      <P>I must say I have been impressed by the arguments put forward.  On the other hand, I should not like to be responsible for something which is quite new, and undoubtedly, if the amendment were adopted here, it would set a headline which might be adopted in a number of places. Whether that would or would not be wise, I would like to consider further. I would ask the Senator not to press this amendment, though, of the amendments put forward, it is the one that perhaps would impress me most.  On the whole, I think we would be wiser to leave the successful working of the institute to the council and to the cooperation which it is going to get from the colleges.  If it is not going to make good, I am afraid that efforts of this sort will not be made easy in the future.  I have great hopes that it will be successful.  I recognise how difficult the task is which this council has before it, to co-ordinate work in a number of institutions which pride themselves on their independence and autonomy and the professors of which are particularly sensitive to any interference with their rights to do their work in their own way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think we should leave it as it is and not go looking ahead.  What the suggested review would mean would be a very full examination of the whole working of the institute.  We will hope for the best, but if such a review is found necessary, it will be possible to set it up any time.  I agree that setting up a commission at a particular time <Col N="1378" /> seems to indicate that there are some serious faults there.  The chief value of the amendment is that it would be regarded as a routine matter, if it was inserted here, but otherwise it would be regarded not as routine but as a sort of condemnation in advance, so to speak.  However, we have other institutions which have managed to survive that sort of thing and I think we will face the future with hope.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I am rather disturbed by something the Taoiseach said in his reference to the Estimate coming before the Dáil, that the matter could be raised there.  The point I want to question is whether the institute will have the same autonomy as the universities?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Whenever there is a question of a public authority paying out money, its representatives have a right to assure themselves, speaking in a general way, that the money is being well spent and you cannot deny that right to them.  You cannot say it is just a question of putting up the money.  Whether it be £1,000,000, or whatever sum it is, you simply do not vote it and let it go at that.  No representative of the people will accept that position.  Those who have charge will try to resist examination in detail but you cannot prevent discussion in the broad sense if the representatives of the people want it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The grants to universities are statutory grants and objection has been taken to discussion of particular matters of university administration on the Estimate for statutory grants.  However, in the case of the institute it may be that the Minister for Agriculture, in agreement with the Minister for Finance, will give specific grants in certain years, and I do not think there is any method of giving those grants without their expenditure being discussed.  The matter will come under discussion now and again in the Dáil.  The money in this case will be in the Appropriations Bill and could be discussed here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would be very chary of accepting Senator Quinlan's amendment.  A commission tends to be leadránach, it <Col N="1379" /> tends to be tedious and long-winded, and I doubt very much if a statutory commission is the appropriate way to review the work of this body.  That a particular commission should discuss its progress perforce every five or ten years I do not think is the best way of accomplishing the desired results.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach has agreed that the principle in general would be desirable if we could introduce it.  How can we introduce the principle here?  How can we take the stigma away from commissions?  I believe there have been something like 15 commissions in the United States during the past 50 years to inquire into the workings of the various Government Departments.  These are matterof-fact instances in the working of a democratic country.  To get a commission here we have to get headlines in the papers, charging that the body to be investigated is failing to do its duty. We have to prove that the body is guilty before we can get a commission whereas, if we got a commission in a democratic way of life, it would be a great step forward.  That is why I put down this amendment in the present instance.  I wonder would there be any use in leaving the amendment stand to the Report Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think there would be time.  There is a very very wide principle involved in the Senator's amendment and I would be just a bit afraid of accepting it here before we examined it thoroughly and saw all the repercussions there might be from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>What can we do to bring about that state of affairs?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter for consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is in the hands of the House at the moment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 20 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1380" /> SECTION 21.</P>
    <P>Government amendment:&mdash;</P>
    <P>Section to be deleted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I urge the Seanad to delete this particular section.  I found on examination it was much too wide, and I do not think it would be profitable to have it here at all.  If any actions arise, the institute will have to make the same provision for the people who are working for it that any ordinary employer would have to make.  I do not see any way out of it. I tried to find out what was the origin of this section and I must confess I found no good answer.  Accordingly, I put it forward as an amendment that this section be deleted.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 21 deleted.</P>
      <P>Section 22 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 23.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 36:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 8, line 37, to delete &ldquo;Agricultural Institute&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Agriculture (An Foras Talúntais)&rdquo;. </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am moving this amendment because I think it is only right when we give an Irish title to an institute such as this that wherever the institute is referred to in our public documents as far as possible we should have the Irish title.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I speak on this matter with a certain amount of reluctance because I feel I am destroying an illusion that exists, that if you put Irish words into English speech you are in some way furthering the Irish language.  I do not think you are and as a person, who has, in this case, the misfortune to know both languages, I think this section will now be a horrible medley of both. This Act, if the amendment is accepted, may be cited as &ldquo;The Agriculture (An Foras Talúntais) Act&rdquo;.  That, to my mind, is a dreadful combination of words.  It has two definite articles, one in Irish and one in English, and <Col N="1381" /> it is almost impossible to say if you happen to know the Irish language. The Taoiseach has given us in this Act a new word for agriculture.  It seems to be a specially made-up word.  You are going to have &ldquo;An Foras Talúntais&rdquo; in brackets and you are going to have &ldquo;Talmhaíocht&rdquo; in other places.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  You will probably have &ldquo;Agriculture&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>You will have two different words in some instances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>In slightly different contexts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I think agriculture is agriculture in all contexts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>But the institute&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Whether it is an institute for agriculture or a reaper and binder, agriculture is the same thing.  This will get you into the same difficulty as you have in &ldquo;An Tóstal&rdquo;. I saw a beginning to an article, &ldquo;In this our second An Tóstal&rdquo;.  That is a horrible jumble of words.  There is no value whatever in this kind of thing. I know it gives the impression that you are making progress but it is certain that languages are not made by Act of Parliament.  Languages are the creation of a nation, not of a committee. That is the overwhelming and only argument for preserving and reviving Irish.  It was made by the Irish nation.  This kind of thing does no good at all but it is an interesting fact that the very reverse does no harm. When an Irish speaker who has a feeling for the language, for its construction and its rhythm, uses an English word or words, he does no harm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To illustrate that point, I recall that when I saw a road being repaired on the way to Helvic I said to a man working there: &ldquo;Shil mise go raibh bothar nua le déanamh&rdquo;; the answer he gave was: &ldquo;Níl an tairgead ann.&rdquo; I asked: &ldquo;Dé chúis ná fuil?&rdquo; and he said in the course of his reply: &ldquo;Sé airgead na gCounty Councils an chéad rud a thabharfaidh.&rdquo;  That is quite a different thing from saying: &ldquo;Financial <Col N="1382" /> collapse will first occur in the Comhairle Conntae&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>But the whole idea that you are doing good by this kind of amendment is wrong.  In Tipperary, where Irish is gone, they have any amount of Irish words in English.  That makes their own English more flexible but it does not further the cause of the Irish language.  I do not want to be academic but I can assure the Taoiseach, and he knows himself, the definite article is a very treacherous thing.  There is a combination of them here that certainly constitutes a monstrous medley.  It may be all right as a veneer for certain people who think they are doing good but I do not think it does any good.  The Act should be cited for what it is, the Agricultural Institute Act.</P>
    <P>I assure the Taoiseach that nobody with a sense of language&mdash;and the Lord gifted me with that, at least&mdash;would accept this horrible phrase: &ldquo;This Act may be cited as the Agriculture (An Foras Talúntais) Act, 1957.&rdquo;  It is daft.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Hayes's remarks force me to refer to an article in a section we passed previously. I commented to my colleagues that it showed the English language to have a greater mix-up of words than anything in the Irish language.  It is sub-section (3) of Section 7, which deals with the director of the institute. It says that he shall hold office &ldquo;for such term and on such terms and conditions (including terms of remuneration) as may be determined by the Government&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I am told that is legal phraseology. I do not blame anybody outside saying, after reading that: &ldquo;Are these people all illiterate?  In one half-inch they put the word &lsquo;term&rsquo; three times and having two distinct meanings.&rdquo; It is more grotesque than the example quoted by Senator Hayes in connection with the title.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Bad English is no excuse for a monstrous medley of Irish and English.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Senator Hayes could have made a better case than he has been making.  I think he <Col N="1383" /> spoiled it by exaggeration.  If you look up the short title of a number of Acts you will find that there is in brackets a sub-title indicating more specifically the subjects with which they deal.  In the brackets in this instance you have the particular subject, namely, the Irish for &ldquo;institute&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>The desire is that when institutions and so on are set up, if possible they should be given the Irish title.  It gets that much into the ordinary currency of speech.  I do not agree with Senator Hayes at all that it is a horrible medley of words I think all languages have to grow&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>They do not grow like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and they grow through the exigencies of having to express certain things.  The Irish language has to grow to deal with all sorts of new things that crop up. Words like this are only giving the language a greater flexibility.  &ldquo;Talúntais&rdquo; is not an ugly word to pronounce. It suggests at once association with the land.  I see no difficulty about it at all. It is not a medley of Irish and English. You have the word &ldquo;agriculture&rdquo; because that is the general title to a whole lot of other Bills coming under that description.  In the brackets you have the specific title which is very common in the short title of Bills.  I understand the Senator's outlook and I know we will not agree.  I do not think there is any use in attempting it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Mo chreach is mo chás.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SCHEDULE.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 37:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete paragraphs 1 and 2 and substitute a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One third of the ordinary members of the council shall retire in rotation <Col N="1384" /> every three years, and shall not be eligible for immediate re-election.</P>
    <P>This is a point which was raised by many speakers on the Second Reading, the desirability of getting a certain amount of change.  We have a rather unhappy history in our committee life in this country.  Once a man gets on a committee, if he succeeds in getting re-elected once, we feel we really should not disturb him from that on; he can live only another 30 years in the job.  This is an effort to try and break that cycle here especially as the membership of the council is limited to 12.  It means that one-third of the members, four, retire every three years.  It is not very much of a change.  If you make them ineligible for re-election, they still may come back at a later stage but not for the first period afterwards.</P>
    <P>In regard to the council of the institute, of course the council has a number of committees and if a member has been really distinguished on the council his services need not be lost; he will still function very effectively on some of the committees of the institute. Besides, even if he were divorced altogether from the institute, if he is a good man there are many more committees in Ireland other than the council of the institute.</P>
    <P>To try to break this tradition is something we should seriously consider. The great monastic orders, with the wisdom of ages behind them, regard nobody as indispensable.  You are re-elected for one period and then you must serve one period in the ranks again.  That has given vitality and leadership to the councils of the great religious orders&mdash;a leadership and a vitality that could do much for the agricultural institute.  I would urge the amendment strongly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given a good deal of consideration to this amendment since the Seanad last met.  I even got a draft amendment to try to meet the idea but it would have to be very much more complicated than what the Senator thinks.  Finally, I came to the conclusion that an amendment on those lines is not necessary in the case <Col N="1385" /> of a body composed of three separate elements.</P>
      <P>You have the universities.  There may be a certain amount of stability in the members sent up from the universities, I do not know.  Then you have the persons directly selected and approved by the Government.  With a possibility of changes of Government, the elements here are likely to be changed.  There is a possibility of change.  Then you have the nominations from the farming community.  I think in the nature of the composition of the council itself, there are the prospects of reasonable change in the personnel.</P>
      <P>I then came to work out the complicated system that would have to be substituted in order to have rotation.  You would have to consider the three bodies and try to arrange that some would drop out at some stage of the term of three years and others at another stage, and when I had given all the thought I considered necessary, I finally came down on the side of leaving the thing alone, as otherwise we were only introducing complications which would not always work in the one direction, because whilst you might produce continuity, you could, on the other hand, disturb a continuity it might be desirable to retain over a period, so when you balance the arguments, <i>pro</i> and <i>contra</i> in this case, I came to the decision to leave the thing alone.  I would urge that on the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we take it that the Government would encourage in some way or other rotation in the selection of these members?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be very hard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I would say that it would be very dangerous for a Government to urge anything like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>You would get the reaction immediately that we would be interfering with the right to nominate the best person.  If you have a large number of organisations and divide them into sections, it is quite possible you might get a satisfactory solution if you were not able to bring them all <Col N="1386" /> together at once.  The moment you say: &ldquo;You, to-day&rdquo; the people who go on to-morrow will not like it.  On the whole, my experience in all these things is that if you try to arrange particular things and look too far into the future, you are going to be disappointed.</P>
      <P>There are a lot of things where when you try to achieve a certain good a lot of other evils come at the same time as the good and destroy its value. On the whole, we ought to leave it alone.  I should like, perhaps, while I am speaking&mdash;it is not quite relevant to the present issue&mdash;to refer to a point one Senator made with regard to the possibility of the reappointment of the chairman.  He is a member of the council and, as such, is eligible for reappointment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The suggestion might go a long way towards meeting Senator Baxter's fears in regard to the fact that a number of rural organisations might be dissatisfied.  If a number of them are promised they cannot get a nomination this time but may get it next time, it would get over the immediate difficulty.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SCHEDULE.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 37:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In paragraph 6 (2), line 13, to delete &ldquo;may&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;shall&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Must the council order meetings, if requested?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are prepared to accept the word &ldquo;shall&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Schedule, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Taoiseach desire to go on with the Report Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1387" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in the hands of the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been decided to meet to-morrow, and, unless it is very inconvenient for the Taoiseach, I suggest we should take the Fourth and Fifth Stages as the first business to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I will be able to manage that all right.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Thursday, 30th January, 1958.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at 6.5 p.m. and resumed at 7.15 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Co-operation between Twenty-Six" RHead="Counties and Six Counties&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Co-operation between Twenty-Six Counties and Six Counties&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Seanad Eireann requests the Government to set up a commission or to take other decisive and energetic steps to consider and report on the best means of promoting social, economic and cultural co-operation between the Twenty-Six Counties and the Six Counties.</P>
      <P>That is the motion I have the privilege of proposing.</P>
      <P>There is a significant and deliberate omission in the wording of this motion: there is no mention of politics.  Why?  The reason, I think, will be clear to everyone.  It is this: because in the narrower sense of the word &ldquo;politics&rdquo;, especially in matters of Government and matters of allegiance, there is&mdash;I think we would all probably agree now, rather reluctantly &mdash;no prospect of immediate co-operation with the Six Counties.  In fact, I would say there has been no progress in the political sphere in the past 36 years, so far as reconciliation or conciliation are concerned.  At the moment, there is no encouragement from the leaders of the Six Counties to try for closer political co-operation. So far as they are concerned, the political door is bolted and barred at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>But it seems to me there are other doors open to unity of action, if not to unity of Government.  These doors are <Col N="1388" /> standing open, I think, in matters of economic, social and cultural co-operation, and I hope to prove that these doors are open in a moment or two. In what follows, I shall make no reference at all to political matters, to matters of loyalty and allegiance.  I shall make no reference at all to the ancient rights and wrongs of Irish history.  I hope that others will refrain from referring to political and historical matters, too.  I know we all feel very deeply on them and for good reason.  But I am convinced that if this debate to-night is to serve a genuinely constructive purpose, it should avoid the political and historical approach.  Let us enter by the open doors and not try to batter down the bolted door.</P>
    <P>I shall now try to substantiate my opinion that the door to co-operation in economic, social and cultural matters is open.  First&mdash;and perhaps it will suffice for complete proof&mdash;I shall offer a quotation from a speech by the Northern Ireland Prime Minister, Lord Brooke borough, as reported in the <i>Irish Times</i> of 14th November, 1957. He was speaking about the policy of the political leaders in Northern Ireland and this is some of what he said. I quote:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We&rdquo;&mdash;he means the leaders of the Six-County Government&mdash;&ldquo;have done everything in our power to achieve a situation in Ireland where North and South, each respecting the rights of the other to pursue its own destiny, could co-operate on a friendly basis in a way that would be advantageous to both.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In the rest of his speech, Lord Brookeborough made it very clear that the Unionist leaders would not consider any change in the present constitutional position, but his speech clearly indicates to me that in social, economic and cultural matters, rapprochement and co-operation between the Six Counties and ourselves is feasible, and feasible now.  What I shall go on to argue is that we should seize this opportunity at once.</P>
    <P>Many members of the Seanad may be thinking at the moment that in fact there is a good deal of co-operation <Col N="1389" /> along these lines already.  Let me remind the Seanad of some of the forms which this co-operation takes.  In economic matters we have had the joint work on the Foyle Fisheries; we have had the Erne hydro-electric scheme; we have had the co-operation &mdash;now not so happy as it was&mdash;in the G.N.R., all very definite examples of friendly and valuable co-operation.</P>
    <P>In social matters, most of us know that, in athletics, there are many crossBorder organisations&mdash;Gaelic football, rugby football, hurling and a good many other forms of athletics&mdash;but unhappily&mdash;and this is one of the things our inquiry should look into&mdash;for obscure reasons, in other forms of athletics, there are differences, some of them quite recent.  Why, for example, is there the animosity in cycling; why can we not unite in ploughing competitions?  I do not know the precise answers to that.  An inquiry could find out and tell us and perhaps heal the divisions.</P>
    <P>In social and cultural matters, there has been some co-operation too and we have some excellent societies which have encouraged this co-operation.  I should like to take this opportunity of expressing my admiration, and possibly the admiration of other members of the House, for the Irish Association for Cultural, Economic and Social Relations. This is a most worthy body which has been working for many years to bring North of Ireland people and people from the Republic close together and they have to a very great extent succeeded.  I do think that that is the kind of work we should study and encourage.</P>
    <P>Again, the Churches, of course, both Catholic and Protestant, recognise no border, that is the major Churches&mdash;a very striking point.  Some business firms, I think, extend both ways across the Border, but fewer far than there used to be.  That seems to be a subject for inquiry, too.</P>
    <P>In education, there is a paradoxically happy situation in many ways. One might think that, in education, the separateness would be most forced and most rigorously exacted.  One would think wrong, for, as a matter of <Col N="1390" /> fact, good education, higher education, is on the side of unity and friendliness. It is the half-educated, not the uneducated&mdash;very often the uneducated are as sensible as the educated&mdash;who like the divisions and enmities, in my opinion, and that seems to be borne out by the position at the moment.  It is a very remarkable thing that the Irish National Teachers' Organisation recognises no border.  In the universities, there is some very close co-operation. There is one very striking example which may not be familiar to members of the House.  It is this: Magee University College in Derry is closely affiliated to Trinity College, Dublin, as well as to Queen's University, and every year sends us some excellent North of Ireland students to finish their courses in Trinity College, Dublin&mdash;very striking, considering that most of their grants come from the Northern Government.  Yet, there has been no successful attempt, and I doubt if there has been any serious attempt, to break the connection between Trinity and Derry in that way.</P>
    <P>Also, North of Ireland scholarships, county council scholarships and others, are, I believe, tenable in National University.  They certainly are in Trinity.  There also are some interuniversity societies which foster meetings between professors of most universities, both North and South.</P>
    <P>As Senator O'Quigley said at a meeting of the Seanad last December, we should, and could, do a great deal more to promote this most useful form of co-operation and working together in the universities.  Here I should like to quote from a very striking and encouraging article which has been produced by a young Irishman within the last couple of months.  I refer to an article by Mr. Donal Barrington called &ldquo;Uniting Ireland&rdquo; which was originally published in <i>Studies</i>, in the winter number of 1957, which has now been published separately as the first of the Tuairim pamphlets published by the Tuairim Association.  If anyone in this House has not read it, I do urge them to read it with care.  It is a most salutary and sensible article from a young man.  It is a most encouraging phenomenon in our time.  This is what <Col N="1391" /> he says about promoting unity in education:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;In the educational field, there are already some points of contact. Both Unionist and Nationalist students attend Queen's University, Belfast, which seems to help in fostering an increasingly enlightened approach to Northern politics.  Moreover, several hundred Unionist students come to Dublin each year to study at Trinity College, which can, and does play, an important part in bringing Irishmen together.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I should perhaps mention that Mr. Barrington is a graduate of University College, Dublin, the National University. He goes on to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;A corresponding number of Northern Nationalists come to study at University College, Dublin.  This makes it all the greater pity that there is so little contact between two universities which are not a quarter of a mile apart.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>He means, of course, the two universities in Dublin.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Each university has its own tradition and there may be important reasons why each should retain its independence.  But there seems to be a strong case on political, economic and academic grounds for closer co-operation between the two universities, particularly in the faculties of Arts, Law, Medicine and Science.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That co-operation bears directly on the unity we desire to foster.  It happens that most of the 300 odd Northern Ireland students in Trinity College are probably of Unionist extraction and that most of those who go to the National University are of Nationalist extraction.  If they could meet within the orbit of the two universities, it would do much to promote intellectual understanding between both sides of the Border.  What is essentially desirable in all these organisations is that Nationalist and Unionist, Catholic and Protestant, should work and play, learn and teach, earn and spend, together in a friendly atmosphere.  It is the difference of lives, not the difference <Col N="1392" /> of laws, that is real partition. The universities could do much to change that difference of lives.</P>
    <P>I mention three other forms of co-operation which already exist.  I am sure our hearts were warmed&mdash;and I know the hearts of Northern Ireland people were warmed&mdash;on the two occasions and I think, probably more, that our fire brigades went to the rescue in the case of fires across the Border.  A narrow stupid politician would say: &ldquo;Do not cross the Border.&rdquo;  None of us took that point of view.  From the point of view of friendship, those two cross-Border forays have done a great deal of good indeed.</P>
    <P>Here is another example&mdash;not an entirely happy one and I shall not emphasise it: our police have worked together on certain occasions.  If that has a political reference, I shall not dwell on it.  However, it shows that the machinery of co-operation exists in various ways.</P>
    <P>The schools at the Border show evidence of striking co-operation.  I quote from the <i>Irish Times</i> of 30th December, 1957, in which there is an article which says that, out of 91 pupils in Northern Ireland at a voluntary school in County Derry, 73 were from the Republic.  In other words, the Northern Ireland Government was paying for 73 students of the Republic and apparently not greatly objecting to it.  Similarly, there are a few schools of ours along the Border which receive students from Northern Ireland and no hard words are spoken and, as far as I know, no complaints are made. That is a very sensible arrangement.</P>
    <P>In my reference to schools, perhaps I may refer also to a remarkable fact brought to light by Dr. Conor Cruise O'Brien in an article in the same number of <i>Studies.</i>  It is a small thing, but I think it is very significant.  He tells that in a Protestant school in the Six Counties, a class of 26 boys aged from 13 to 14 years was asked to write an essay on Ireland.  They were expected to comment on unity or Partition, whatever their point of view was. The result was this.  Nine of those boys were positively in favour of unification in principle.  One was positively against it and the rest were non-committal.  It <Col N="1393" /> is remarkable that of the ten boys who expressed a positive opinion, nine were in favour of re-unification in principle.</P>
    <P>It is clear that a fair amount of co-operation already exists in social, cultural and economic matters.  Some of it is a survival from pre-Treaty days, &mdash;the Churches, athletics, university co-operation to same extent.  On the other hand, most of the post-Treaty efforts at co-operation have, to my mind, been scattered and opportunistic, almost casual.  These post-Treaty efforts have been designed to deal with crises as they arose, not planned in advance.  That is the reason why I am proposing this motion, primarily.  If thought and planning were applied to the present situation, it seems to me that there could be very much improvement.</P>
    <P>The aim, then, of the proposed inquiry would be to study the existing forms of co-operation and explore how others could be developed&mdash;to consider why some kinds of co-operation have failed and other kinds have succeeded, and to explore further possibilities. The House may wonder what are the other possibilities and wonder whether I can give specific cases where co-operation is urgently called for&mdash; cases which the Northern Ireland people would recognise as demanding attention.  I think I can mention a few, though I shall not dwell on them.  The first, as the Taoiseach has already suggested, is the tourist trade, as separation on that is doing us harm.  We could have much better propaganda, if we could advertise tourism for the whole country.  Secondly, in matters of transport&mdash;I am afraid that the news in the newspapers about transport is rather sad in so far as one of our main arteries of unity has just been blocked. I am not commenting here on a matter of policy, but on the need for co-operation in matters of transport and communication.</P>
    <P>Matters of agriculture obviously need joint study.  Take, for instance, the marketing of Irish goods abroad. Then there is the most promising plan of the Minister for Industry and Commerce for all-Ireland free trade.  It is full of difficulties, of course, but it is a <Col N="1394" /> most promising plan in theory, and I hope he will go far with it.</P>
    <P>Lastly, and perhaps most important, Ireland as a whole&mdash;North and South&mdash; should consider its joint responsibilities and possibilities in the face of the proposed European Free Trade Area.  We are obviously a unit, economically, as far as Europe is concerned, and we should really think together on this matter.  I think the Northern Ireland economists realise they will have to think with us as well as with Britain on that proposed free trade area.</P>
    <P>Here, now, is the essence of my argument.  This motion aims at substituting a policy of planned and progressive co-operation for the present opportunistic and casual co-operation in economic, social and cultural matters.</P>
    <P>Now, I think, we come to the crucial question.  Will the Northern Unionists welcome such an effort, or will they regard any attempt at planned co-operation of this nature as a kind of Trojan Horse for the destruction of the northern citadel?  That, I think, is the crucial question.  Here, we should examine our own motives&mdash;our own motives in this House and the motives of people in the Republic as a whole.</P>
    <P>If we in this House and in the Republic regard unity of life and unity of work as less important than political unity, less important than unity of Government, then all efforts of the kind I am suggesting would be futile and insincere and the Northern Ireland people, I think, would rightly reject them.  Surely we have enough sense to see, especially in the light of our own relations with Great Britain, that friendly neighbourliness is better than a strained or forced political unity?</P>
    <P>I speak perhaps with some sympathy in this matter.  I was born in Belfast. I have spent most of my life in the Republic and my ancestors, going a good way back, have come from the Twenty-Six Counties.  Therefore, I can perhaps see both sides a bit.  My own view is that if full economic, social and cultural co-operation could be achieved, the problem of political <Col N="1395" /> organisation would solve itself.  I would even go so far as to say it would hardly matter.  It is unity of life, not unity of law, that I consider supreme.</P>
    <P>To return to the crucial question: Will the Northern Ireland Unionists welcome and support any efforts we may make to achieve the co-operation I suggest?  Well, it is anyone's guess, I suppose; but I think that there is a fair chance.  I have already quoted what Lord Brookeborough said.  He has said he is prepared to &ldquo;co-operate on a friendly basis in matters of mutual advantage&rdquo;.  That is clear enough.  Besides, I would bank on this &mdash;the Northern Unionists are sensible and businesslike people.  If there are practical advantages to be gained, they will join.</P>
    <P>I would hope that they would regard this motion and its results, if they are positive, in the light of business talks, business joint conferences.  I should like them to think of themselves as one big business firm and of us as another big business firm.  We would like to amalgamate: they do not want to amalgamate; we are both doing the same business to a great extent; we can do things by consultation and co-operation to the benefit of both firms. It seems to me that, in terms of business practice, it is an attractive proposition.  They know we want amalgamation; we know they do not want amalgamation.  We can accept that position.  Certainly, in my own mind, in making the present proposal, I would say it means absolutely no political commitments to any Northern Ireland Unionist who comes and helps us&mdash;absolutely no political commitments. We would have to emphasise that in our invitation.</P>
    <P>We may hope, then, I think, that the people of Northern Ireland may be inclined to co-operate for purely practical reasons&mdash;to co-operate, as Lord Brookeborough put it, &ldquo;on a friendly basis in a way that would be advantageous to both&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>To return to the inquiry, if we agree that it is worth undertaking and may lead to some success, we must give serious thought to the way it will work.  How should it go about its job? <Col N="1396" /> First of all, much of the success of such an inquiry will depend on the personnel, on the people who are working together on it.  Something more than intelligence, more than good judgment and more than experience will be needed in this inquiry.  We need people of varied loyalties, varied points of view, from both the North and the South, if it is really to succeed.  If a group of ourselves from the Republic get together and put ideas from our point of view, they probably will not work&mdash;unless some of us prove to be unusually imaginative and unusually sympathetic.  If we have a genuine representation from the Unionists of Northern Ireland, there is a chance that it will work&mdash;and, in fact, the very participation will be a practical form of co-operation and unity, even if it got no further.  Therefore, if possible, we certainly should have some Northern Unionists, not necessarily politicians&mdash; perhaps not politicians&mdash;but they should be true-blue Northern Unionists, as members of the inquiry.  It would be no use having just Northern Nationalists and people from the Republic&mdash;no use at all, I think.</P>
    <P>There is another class of persons living in this country&mdash;and their numbers are increasing&mdash;which I think we should enlist in an inquiry of this kind and in other inquiries.  These people have been neglected, for fairly obvious reasons, but I suggest we are being foolish in not including them.  The retiring age for members of the British Colonial Service and the British Service in general is now rather low. Dozens of highly trained, highly experienced British Colonial administrators are coming to live in Dublin and in Ireland.  If we can enlist the service of one or two of these from time to time, I think their experience and intelligence would be extremely valuable. We all probably can name some of them&mdash;ex-chief justices, ex-colonial secretaries, and so on.  We may not like these titles, but they are good men; they are lovers of Ireland; and they are citizens of our country, eager to serve.  I should like to see them serving not merely in an inquiry of this kind but in many other spheres.</P>
    <P>The make-up of the inquiry, then, as I see it&mdash;perhaps a commission, perhaps <Col N="1397" /> something else&mdash;should be people of varied loyalties, varied points of view and people of varying professions &mdash;businessmen, farmers, teachers, scientists, labour representatives, writers, lawyers, industrialists, economists and so on&mdash;not primarily political at all costs.  There may also be a few politicians, either part-time or whole-time, if you like, but they must be politicians who are prepared to cut out politics in that sense as far as this inquiry is concerned, if it is to succeed. If the political slant is brought in, if an attempt is made to construct a Trojan Horse out of this inquiry, we will be wasting our time and might as well drop it.</P>
    <P>How will they go to work if we get them together?  As I suggested, they will study the existing successes&mdash;like the Irish Rugby Football Union, the G.A.A., the Churches, the Irish National Teachers' Organisation, and so on&mdash;how did they succeed when others failed?  They will analyse the sources of failure, in activities like international cycling and ploughing. Why have they failed?  They will explore the possible developments I have mentioned.  They will publish a genuinely constructive and realistic report, a report looking to the present and to the future, a report which does not refer to and does not even think of past grievances.  The watchword of the inquirers, I suggest, should be: &ldquo;Planned and Progressive Co-operation.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There is a parallel to this kind of thing and it may be worth our while thinking of it for a moment or two. The Council of Europe at Strasbourg in its early days thought that a federation of Europe would come quickly, that there would be a united states of Europe.  At least, many members of the council hoped for that and the United States of America, I know, was pressing very strongly in 1951 for a united states of Europe right away. I had some things to say on the matter &mdash;they were not popular, but I said them&mdash;because I thought at that time a united states of Europe was hopeless &mdash;and in fact that was so.</P>
    <P>The Council of Europe at Strasbourg might have folded up fairly quickly <Col N="1398" /> when they found that a united states of Europe was not going to come quickly. There was no advance on the constitutional line, but they very sensibly did something else.  They turned to economic co-operation, social co-operation and cultural co-operation, leaving aside the political and constitutional issues.  In six or seven years, they have produced very remarkable feats of unity in those spheres.  We have the remarkable union of Belgium, the Netherlands and Luxembourg in Benelux, working very close together.  Now there are six nations, some of them formerly bitter, hereditary enemies&mdash; the Germans, the French and the Italians&mdash;working together in the closest economic co-operation.  We have other examples in the cultural sphere and in the social sphere, examples of genuine European co-operation in those spheres where political co-operation was impossible. Similarly in Ireland at the moment, advance on the political line is held up. Advance on the other lines could be, I think, just as quick as in the Council of Europe and just as effective if we planned it and worked it in the right way.</P>
    <P>I must say something personal here. It was a very great inspiration and encouragement to me when I went into the Council of Europe in Strasbourg in 1951 and saw hereditary enemies go in side by side together&mdash;the Germans and the French, the Greeks and the Turks, the English and the Irish, with their flags flying together on the same building&mdash;because they had agreed to work together in matters where co-operation was possible, in economic and social matters as well as in cultural matters.  That could quickly happen in Ireland if we went about it in a similar way.</P>
    <P>I have not very much more to say. Other members of the Seanad will, I feel sure, add their arguments to what I have said and some will produce arguments against it.  I shall be eager to hear what they have to say and shall be glad to reply.  I should like to emphasise this: I want to repeat my firm conviction&mdash;I have had a year to think over this, and so has the Seanad, because this motion was put down in <Col N="1399" /> January of 1957&mdash;that an energetic move of this kind is at least worthy of trial now in 1958.</P>
    <P>It is over 100 years since Thomas Davis offered Ireland a policy, if not a plan, for an Ireland united in mind and purpose.  No Government in this country has had the courage or the wisdom to make his conciliatory policy a reality.  We have tried arguments; we have tried threats; we have tried hostile propaganda.  All have failed. They have done more harm than good. After 36 years should we now not try, as this motion suggests, to think out a better way?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCole" hpid="Mr. Cole Mr. Cole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cole</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally second Senator Stanford's motion.  It is rather difficult for me to speak after the Senator and my remarks on the motion will be brief.  The motion suggests that we leave all aspects of politics, and possibly geography, out of the question and that we concentrate instead on attaining a renewal of friendship between ourselves and the people of Northern Ireland through the promotion of the social and cultural gifts which are common to us, North and South.  Those are the terms of the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If we examine the position that obtains at present it seems there are three alternatives facing us.  The first one I do not wish to deal with. The second alternative is to look for all or nothing, and the third is to adopt the motion proposed by Senator Stanford and to carry out its proposals. To my mind, these are not really alternatives.  There is not one of them we can accept at the present time if we are to live in harmony with Northern Ireland but the last one&mdash; the motion of Senator Stanford.  Unfortunately, there are several things, several voices, that rather hinder us from carrying out the terms of the motion.  The first is that there are people in this part of the country and in the North who wish to continue, and who do continue, to give utterance to spiteful and hurtful references on every possible occasion against the other part.  How often do we see in our own national newspapers&mdash;and I <Col N="1400" /> make no exceptions&mdash;very good articles spoiled by perhaps an exaggerated reference, perhaps an unnecessary reference and sometimes even an insulting reference, to the other part of the country?</P>
    <P>Those are the things that will hinder a commission of the sort suggested here.  How often do we find in the newspapers a report of a speech made by a county council back-bencher or by some unimportant person at a street corner, a speech that may be insulting and the importance of which may be exaggerated in our newspapers to such an extent that it seems to be the policy of the part of the country in which it is made?</P>
    <P>Recently, the Taoiseach appealed for greater co-operation between this country and Northern Ireland.  Possibly in reply to that speech the Prime Minister of Northern Ireland made a speech in which he made reference to closer relations between Northern Ireland and the Republic.  I have not got the reference at the moment but I should like to quote briefly from that speech:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;For many years I have advocated co-operation between ourselves and the Republic based on the recognition of each Government.  I believe that a new spirit would prevail if that were accepted.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Later, the Prime Minister of Northern Ireland said: &ldquo;I repeat, we are prepared to work with the Republic on the basis I have previously outlined.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Those suggestions, coming immediately after the Taoiseach's appeal, form the essence of what we look for in this motion.  There you have both sides aiming towards the same thing. Even though these two speeches did not at the time get the display they were entitled to in the newspapers, they show there is a feeling on both sides and that there is a demand on both sides for social, economic and cultural co-operation.  There are certain sections in the country who are prepared to barter this co-operation for perhaps a few votes at an election or for cheap applause at a meeting.</P>
    <P>Surely our patriotism or nationalism means a little more than spiteful references, <Col N="1401" /> references which have never succeeded in getting us anywhere and which will be always irritating.  Could it not mean that we would like instead to co-operate with our neighbours and with the whole world for that matter and to share our economic, social and cultural gifts with them?  How often have we found&mdash;and I make no apology for making this reference&mdash;that things are said with the object of trying to do something in the name of the Churches, in the name of religion?  So much is said with an appeal to religion behind it which, to my mind, has no reference to religion at all.  I am reminded of a supposed saying of an Archbishop of Canterbury years ago who was faced with execution.  He had previously been a great supporter of the King and he is reputed to have said: &ldquo;If I served my God as I have served my King, He would not have deserted me in later days.&rdquo;  I feel many of us in this country might say at some future date that if we had served our God as we have served our Church we might be much better off.  Finally, I would ask the Seanad to support this motion and try to accept it in the letter and in the spirit.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. Barry Mr. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Professor Stanford's resolution has my sympathy and my support, my sympathy because I think he will get only verbal enthusiasm for his proposal, and my support because it is never too soon to begin thinking on right lines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I doubt if a commission would be the most useful way of setting about this work.  I believe there are more direct methods at hand.  As a back-bencher in Dáil Éireann three years ago I made four proposals to the then Government.  I said we should set up a trade commission in Belfast, invite northern people to set up a trade commission in Dublin, admit goods of Northern Ireland origin at the lowest possible tariff, and build our ships on the banks of the Lagan.  I knew, of course, what I said would not be listened to and I tried to sit back and find out why what seemed to be simple and elementary things that should be done could not even be considered; what sleep-walking dream we were in down here that had let this problem <Col N="1402" /> grow and become more insoluble as the years went by.  I decided it was really because the big Parties in this Republic are completely bound by the set pattern of the past as imposed upon them, and that, I think, is the greatest tragedy of our time.  Some of our leaders have been there quite a long time; the nature of the revolution has meant that the majority of the men in our Parliament who took part in the revolution are still in Parliament; young men have not found it easy to get into that Parliament, and young ideas and new ideas cannot find a place to flourish.</P>
    <P>I was very glad that Senator Stanford referred to the Barrington Pamphlet.  I was very much impressed by it and any Senator who has not read it should do so.  I agree with him that in any of our dealings with the people in the North we should certainly give no impression that we are attempting to create or use a Trojan Horse.  We should talk to them as Irishmen without any double talk, but, above all, we should work with them. After all, we do play with them and it works out pretty well and I think they like playing with us.  We should buy goods from them and sell our goods to them, and we should certainly have our ships built by their workmen.</P>
    <P>From now on we should abandon all the catch-cries, and if we do all these things we might escape from the straitjacket that history has imposed upon all of us down here and up there as well.  We are told the Orangeman is very set in his ways and cannot change.  But the world is changing and I think we have changed a bit ourselves down here.  Can anybody tell us what the next five years will bring? In Europe there is a changing pattern in many spheres, economic, defensive and national, and it will affect us.  May I say for Senator Stanford's comfort, in case he gets depressed by the reception his motion receives, that he should keep going because as somebody once said: &ldquo;Even in Ireland the impossible frequently comes to pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>As a Senator representing the trade union movement, I must rise to support this motion.  It is a <Col N="1403" /> fact that the Irish T.U.C. caters for unions with members on both sides of the Border and in spite of Partition it has been possible for delegates from these various unions, North and South, to co-operate.  Probably the most important and encouraging development in that respect is that there is every chance that the split in the trade union movement will be healed on the basis of having affiliation from unions catering for all workers, whether they come from the North or the South and that there will be one congress of trade unions in Ireland irrespective of any Border.  It is in the light of that background and of the fact that the T.U.C. has, year after year, called on the two Governments to co-operate on social and economic problems that I rise to support the motion.</P>
      <P>I think that our difficulty on this side of the Border in regard to co-operation is a fear that, by co-operating with the people in the North, we in some way recognise the existence of a separate Parliament, a separate State, and in some way prejudice our own stand on the question of the unity of the country.  I do not want to go into what might be termed the political problems.  Senator Stanford is very wise to advise that we should not go into that aspect, but I would like to say that this fear of co-operating with the other people has had the unfortunate result that the barrier of the Border seems to be rising higher and higher year after year.  Any of us who have experience of the North and the South must get that unfortunate impression, that, as year follows year, we are tending to drift farther apart. If we do not face up to the problem, if we do not overcome our fears in this respect, then it will be more difficult, to put it at its mildest, to get genuine co-operation between both parts of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It could be that we suffer from another sort of fear, a political fear in the sense of the Party political problems. None of us wants to say anything that might hurt people who have extreme views, but I think we shall have to have courage and I think it would require courage, courage which <Col N="1404" /> is there for the asking&mdash;not physical courage but moral courage&mdash;to face up to this problem and to say, irrespective of what blame may be put on us or what odium may be cast on us&mdash;we might be called unpatriotic or anti-nationalist&mdash;that we in the Seanad are in favour of the utmost co-operation between both parts of the country.  We should say that we are not afraid to take the initiative, perhaps to face snubs, and to keep on overcoming those snubs, and to keep trying to get genuine co-operation between both sides of the Border, between all Irishmen, whether from Belfast or Cork.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise to support what has been said in favour of this motion and I should like to express my approval of the fact that it has been brought before us.  I think it represents a courageous and hopeful effort to ensure that something, even in a small way, can be done in order to show goodwill in an effort to bring a little bit closer together the two parts of our country.  I do not believe in the present situation that we need renounce our hope of one day seeing all Ireland united and of taking our place as a united island among the countries, perhaps as a federated Europe.</P>
      <P>As one Senator stated things are changing, we are changing and other people are changing.  I think for the present it would be healthy for us to recognise, in all humility, that a duty devolves upon us to make such a union possible and also attractive for the North as well as for us.  The best way of doing that is by the method outlined by Senator Stanford; free co-operation in whatever field such co-operation proves feasible.  There is one field among those referred to about which I would feel a little doubt, and that is the economic field, because I know we are conditioned by the fact of being a separate entity and having separate tariff policies.  I recognise that co-operation in that field would be difficult, but by no means impossible. In the other fields mentioned co-operation is certainly possible and could bear rich fruit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have read with admiration the <Col N="1405" /> paper of Mr. Barrington and I think he writes with courage and with charity, and with great clarity of vision about a problem which some people in this country do not dare to look at in an unimpassioned way.  His thesis, as I understand it, is that we ought to give up blaming Britain, and if we do blame Britain we should give up blaming Britain alone for the present situation and we should make it clear to the Government of the Six Counties that we do not intend to try to coerce them into union with us, nor to try to get Britain to try to coerce them to come in with us&mdash;in other words, that we should make it clear to them that we recognise the present position, and that not only will we not make an attempt to have them, but we do not think it possible for them to be, coerced by us, by Britain or the I.R.A. or anybody else, to join with us.</P>
    <P>I think he suggests also that we ought to cease to employ, both on this side of the Border and on the other side, the argument that all our ills spring from Partition; that the reason we cannot solve this problem or that problem is because &ldquo;our country is divided&rdquo;.  I think he suggests that that convenient excuse is too often put forward on both sides of the Border, and that the existence of the Border is too often used as a pretext for not tackling problems which are quite capable of being tackled within the ambit of our present situation.  In other words it is untrue to suggest that the existence of the Border is a major factor in whatever failure has been ours to grapple with the problems besetting our people.</P>
    <P>I think the vast majority of the citizens of the Republic&mdash;I say that advisedly because the issue has been tested, it was tested in the recent election&mdash;do not want a policy of force to be employed against the North.  I know there are some who say that: &ldquo;All we ever got was got by force&rdquo;, but those same people refuse even to recognise the value of what in fact was so obtained in this country, as represented by the Houses of the Oireachtas. It is also obvious, too, that if we were so silly as to appeal to the tribunal of force there would be rather a tacit suggestion that we would also be prepared <Col N="1406" /> to abide by its verdict.  I do not think any of us in this House, nor many people outside it, would really want the methods of force to be used, and, therefore, the far more healthy methods suggested by Mr. Barrington, and Senator Stanford here this evening are the ones to which we must turn, methods of persuasion, if you like, preliminary efforts of co-operation, and a genuine effort on both sides of the Border at peaceful co-existence.  In order to set about that I feel that on both sides we must recognise the present basic facts, the facts of the situation, the facts of the Border itself, and the existing facts both in the North and in the South.</P>
    <P>Some of these facts may be awkward for us to recognise.  Some of them may be awkward for the Unionist Government to recognise, but I think a healthy basis for future conduct would be provided by a preparedness on our part to see things as they are. In relation to the Six-County area we must recognise that something like 64 per cent. of the inhabitants of that area want that area to remain a part of the United Kingdom.  There are all kinds of arguments against that, all kinds of emotions involved, all kinds of tests as to whether they have any right to think such a thing, but I am convinced that we should not conceal from ourselves the fact that 64 per cent. of the people in that area do desire Partition.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator is now going very much outside the terms of the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept your ruling, a Chathaoirligh, but I should just like to suggest, in that case, that if it were possible for us to accept the situation, if I might quote, &ldquo;being resolved mutually to aid one another in a spirit of neighbourly comradeship&rdquo;, then I feel real progress could be made in the various fields that have been mentioned. &ldquo;Being resolved mutually to aid one another in a spirit of neighbourly comradeship&rdquo;&mdash;I am quoting from the 1925 Agreement which was signed on our behalf and ratified in this House and in Dáil Éireann in December, 1925, &mdash;the agreement which consolidated <Col N="1407" /> the Border and recognised its present line.  I am aware, of course, that there was a large feeling against such an agreement, against such a spirit of neighbourly comradeship on such a basis, but I think we must recognise that that agreement was ratified by us by 71 votes to 20 in the Dáil, and that the Government that ratified it in 1925 remained in power for another seven years after that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is again going outside the terms of the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry, a Chathaoirligh, but it seems to me if we were to aim at co-operation, my argument is that we must recognise the basis for the situation as it now stands.  It is essential also for us to recognise that a restricted form of franchise in local elections, which was abolished in the rest of the United Kingdom by the Labour Government in 1946, is still obtaining in the Six-County area to the detriment of nationalist voters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>May I direct the Senator's attention to the terms of the motion and to the feeling of the House, of the proposer and seconder particularly, in what they desire in regard to this motion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I bow to your ruling, though I rather regret that it is not considered in order to examine, as I have been trying to do, the basis for the present situation. However, I shall leave out that portion of what I intended to say; but it does seem to me that what we can usefully do now is to accept, however regretfully, the present situation; to look at it as it is; to accept, in other words, the <i>status quo</i>; I personally would be inclined to say: under protest in relation to Fermanagh and Tyrone, who never asked to be separated from the rest of Ireland, but to accept it nevertheless, even with that protest, as it were, and to work in order to make this Republic of ours, over which we have complete political and economic control, a place from which Irish men <Col N="1408" /> and women will no longer emigrate at the rate of 40,000 a year.  We should work to make it a place to which they will be eager and proud to be enabled to return in pride to live and work in decency and health here.  I feel it is our duty, in aiming at co-operation with our neighbours in the North, to aim at providing a way of life here for all our citizens in which we can be proud to invite them at some future date to join us.</P>
      <P>If we are going to appeal to the North, and when I say appeal to the North, I do not mean at governmental level, but on the various levels referred to by other Senators, cultural, social, athletic and so on&mdash;if we are to appeal to the North to develop further the very real measure of co-operation that already exists, as Senator Stanford pointed out, I think there are many of our problems of unemployment, poverty, under-production, and sometimes alas under-education, upon which they can help us and upon which, perhaps, we can help them. Many of them are, however, problems which we must solve ourselves, before we can decently invite our brothers to join us in a united Ireland.</P>
      <P>I think that in the solving of these problems&mdash;and they in the North have their problems too&mdash;in the solving jointly of our several problems we can seek their help, and offer our help and co-operation, and I believe that in such co-operation we can both learn for the good of the whole island the very simple lesson of what is meant in practice by neighbourly comradeship.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to say much on this motion, but I feel that I ought to speak on it because I am of a generation which is not the generation of most of the people in this House.  I welcome the putting down of a motion of this kind, for the reason that it is an effort to do some thinking about the question of Partition. I believe that too little real thought has been given to the whole subject.  If one were to go through the public Estimates, one would see a great deal of money devoted to a whole lot of matters concerning the running of the country.  In particular, one would see a great deal of money <Col N="1409" /> devoted, and properly so, to the revival of the Irish language.  That, the Taoiseach has said many times, is perhaps the more urgent of our two great national problems.</P>
      <P>But I do not think that, in the public Estimates, you will find any specific attention given to examining the various problems associated with the partition of our country.  It may be that in the Department of External Affairs, the Department of Industry and Commerce and other Departments of State, consideration must of necessity be given to the impact of Partition upon all our problems; but dealing with the question of Partition as the first, even the more urgent, of our two great national problems, it does not seem to me that sufficient time and thought have been given to the question.  There is no doubt that, unless time and thought and money are spent on a problem of this kind, solutions to it will not be found.</P>
      <P>For that reason, I think that this motion contains elements which are very desirable.  Some effort in some direction should be made to ease the solution of Partition.  The method suggested in Senator Stanford's motion is one which would prepare the ground and certainly would get people's minds thinking on broader terms in relation to the whole question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The manner in which Senator Stanford has opened this debate rather precludes one from considering other steps that might be taken.  He has left out all political considerations.  Senator Sheehy Skeffington found considerable difficulty in discussing this motion without bringing in political considerations, and so do I.  For that reason, I find myself somewhat restricted.  But I would think that the motion is somewhat remarkable for the antithesis it contains.  I should have imagined that if there was one way of not dealing energetically with a problem, that way was to set up a Government commission. It rather surprises me therefore to find the Senator suggesting that the Government should set up a commission. I think that commission would have interminable wrangling and would probably end up, if constituted <Col N="1410" /> on the basis he suggests, with a majority report coming from the people on this side of the Border and a minority report from the people on the other side of the Border, and not leading us very much further.</P>
    <P>In regard to the whole question of social, economic and cultural development, I think there is much that can be done.  I do not say that the Government itself is the best medium for bringing about these desirable changes. The establishment of a commission by the Government immediately imports into this motion political action. If it does not necessarily do so, I think it would be so interpreted by people in the Six Counties.  Therefore, I think the establishment of a commission by the Government would import into the whole matter the political considerations which Senator Stanford urges us to keep out of the debate.</P>
    <P>The Government could take decisive and energetic steps otherwise.  Those of us who have grown up under an Irish Government have perhaps got too much of one side of the story. There is no party to any dispute that has right on its side all the time.  I venture to suggest that if there was a recognition that perhaps the other party to the dispute might not be wrong all the time and that there might be possibly some justification for their point of view, however wrong they might be, we might make more progress in dealing with questions of cultural, economic and social relations between ourselves and the Six Counties.</P>
    <P>It would also diminish that aspect of our relations with the Six Counties which Senator Cole was discussing&mdash; the outbursts, by what he called the people at the street corners, which could give the impression that that is the view of the majority of the people in this country.  I think that by reorientating our view, by, perhaps, a more dispassionate writing of history and by more emphasis on the real bonds that exist between ourselves and the Six Counties, we might get further along the road towards easing the strained relations existing at the present time.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1411" /> I think that a commission is not the way to deal with it.  There are other ways in which the Government, through the agency of its different Departments of State and the different organs at its disposal, might create a better climate.  Any person who in his ordinary business or profession meets people from the other side of the Border will find that they are decent people, meeting them at that level.  I venture to say that the differences existing between the people in this country and the people in the North in relation to the Partition question are an exaggerated form of the differences existing between the members of the different political Parties in this country.  Still, members of political Parties in this country can co-operate and join together.  By a greater number of exchanges between people at cultural, social and, perhaps, economic levels, I think the differences which are imagined to exist will probably diminish in time, as people meet more frequently.</P>
    <P>At present we are all interested in seeing whether there will be summit talks and we all hope that, if there are summit talks, they will lead to an easing of world tension.  The differences between ourselves and the North are small compared with the differences that exist between the democracies and the eastern <i>bloc.</i>  If we have regard to that fact, to the hope we all have that these differences can be smoothed out and that increasing contacts between the nations of the west and east will result in peace in our time, we ought to have hope that the time will come when Partition will be ended and that, by promoting the relations which are urged in this motion, we will go some distance along that road.  For that reason, I would support the motion as a step in some direction to bring about the ending of Partition.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I was anxious to hear the views of different Senators. There is no doubt but that the majority of the people in this part of the country desire co-operation in the matters indicated by the motion.  I, <Col N="1412" /> too, was glad that the motion did not deal with the political aspects but it is true, as Senator O'Quigley said, that it is political facts that brought about the present situation and that help to maintain the present position. Senator Sheehy Skeffington found it difficult to keep within the barrier also.</P>
      <P>I do not want to go against the spirit of the mover of the motion who, as he pointed out, very carefully restricted the sphere of this debate.  All I can say on it, having listened to the views which he has expressed, is that I share them very largely but I do not think that the method which has been suggested in the motion will be one which would achieve success.  The moment the Government, as has already been pointed out by some Senators, sets up a commission of this sort it is immediately given a political aspect and unless you could have people in the other part of the country setting up part of the commission and co-operating in it, I do not think it would be of any use.</P>
      <P>If you could get a combined commission then it would be of the greatest value, that is, if the two Governments agreed on setting up a commission to examine in what direction we could have greater co-operation in regard to economic, social and cultural matters.  It would be a tremendous step forward but I do not see that happening.  If I saw the slightest hope of it happening I would certainly be very glad to encourage that hope and to seize any opportunity that would be presented in that regard.</P>
      <P>The Government is in duty bound&mdash; certainly in my opinion and in the opinion of the present Government&mdash;to do everything in its power to foster economic, social and cultural relations, but any attempts that we have made have not been very successful.  They have been limited in their scope, but that is not due&mdash;I do not want to talk altogether for our side&mdash;to any unwillingness on our part.  I think it is due to the fact that there has been no response of any kind except in the limited sphere that has already been mentioned.  I hope there will be greater response in the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>If any body is to be set up to <Col N="1413" /> examine the lines upon which you could extend any co-operation that exists at present, along the economic, cultural and social lines, I think it will have to come from groups of private individuals, from <i>ad hoc</i> arrangements between groups of business men, cultural societies and bodies interested in social matters; for instance, from the cultural side it would be possible to get both the Six Counties and the Twenty-Six Counties to agree in regard to matters of sport.  It is to the advantage of the people of the country as a whole that any divisions that can be ended should be ended. The next thing on the purely business side must come, I think, through business organisations.</P>
    <P>I fear that a commission set up by the Government would not effect the purpose but would be harmful to the very purpose at which those who put down the motion are aiming.  The commission would be suspect from the start, I fear.  Therefore, I would urge on the Seanad&mdash;whilst we agree in principle that further consideration should be given to the method by which the idea might be brought to fruition &mdash;in passing this motion, we would not achieve what is designed.</P>
    <P>From the point of view of the Government, whilst I would certainly not like for a moment that it should be thought that we are against the idea of the co-operation referred to, I would not like to think that the Government, in response to this debate, would be bound to set up a commission. I cannot see the personnel of the commission.  If you could get people from the other side to nominate half of it, then certainly, if there was co-operation, it would be of great value. I am afraid I do not see that.  I cannot support the motion as it is, that is upon the basis of setting up a commission.</P>
    <P>There is, of course, an alternative mentioned in the motion, that we should take energetic steps.  Now the question is what are the energetic steps that are envisaged, what are the energetic steps that the Government can take.  As far as we are concerned, we never ceased, whenever an opportunity <Col N="1414" /> presented itself, to be willing to co-operate.</P>
    <P>The question of free trade within the island is very attractive, but we have the difficulty there that, since the Six Counties are politically at the moment a part of Britain, whatever arrangements might be made for the free trade with the Six Counties must take that fact into consideration.  I do not know whether it is possible.  I think it has been examined to some extent.  I do not know whether it is possible, by arranging about the origin of goods and so on, to limit the free trade to goods that would originate within the Six Counties.  It is worth examining certainly, but I do not know that it is quite feasible.  It has been a difficulty in the past.  You had this union between the Six Counties and Britain, and if our industries in this island were to thrive, if they were not to be smothered in their infancy, we had to protect them against the developed power of Britain's industrial machine.</P>
    <P>I am in the difficulty that I do not think that anything would be gained by passing the motion as it stands, by recommending the setting up of a commission and by urging the Government to do that which it is only too willing to do already.  I dislike very much having to oppose a motion of this sort except on the ground that it is not feasible.  I think the purposes aimed at are admirable, and we would all support them.  I assure the members of the Seanad that the Government will support these aims, but to put that into practice is not so easy.</P>
    <P>Strasbourg has been referred to as an analogy.  It would be an analogy if we had some assembly in which you had representatives both of the Six and Twenty-Six Counties.  That is where the Strasbourg analogy fails, it seems to me.  I was there in the first week at the council, I think, and I was one of those who believed, considering the situation, that it was not at all feasible to have a political federation such as was aimed at by very many. There were some there who were actually forming parties, regarding it already as a Parliament of Europe.  I feel that was a dream as far as present conditions are concerned.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1415" /> In fact, I think I expressed the view that the best way to bring about that sort of solidarity which would ultimately be expressed in a federation would be to take particular problems or spheres of action and get unity, where unity was likely to be possible. Here, if there are any directions in which unified effort would be possible, that would also hold.  You had at Strasbourg, at any rate, representatives from the various countries of Europe, including France and Germany, and you had present individuals from these countries, and people could meet there, and in that you had the first step taken&mdash;the representatives had met together.</P>
    <P>We have not real representatives of the various shades of opinion in the Six Counties and shades of opinions here meeting together.  In the 1920 Act, an attempt was made to have a Council of Ireland in which you would have representatives from the different parts coming together.  The existence of that, even though at the start it might not have very great power, would ensure that these people came together and would supply what Strasbourg supplied, a coming-together of authoritative representatives of the two parts.  Even though it was not on a fair proportional system, the mere fact that they were coming together would give a centre on which to work.  If such a body existed, we would not have to speak of one side setting up a commission, and I would not have to appeal for another half to come from somewhere else.  It would be there already.  That body would naturally seek to bring about, between the two parts, that co-operation which has been suggested here.</P>
    <P>Having heard what has been said, I suggest that the Seanad should not proceed further with this motion and, if what is aimed at is to be done, I think it has to begin by <i>ad hoc</i> arrangements between cultural, social and economic groups.  Certainly, as a member of the Government, I would welcome such a coming-together, but how to start it or get it going is the question.  If there was the desire on the part of these groups and if they <Col N="1416" /> wished to do it, they could come together very easily, but I have seen no evidence or desire on the part of groups to do so.  Where that desire exists the way is open.</P>
    <P>I would further suggest that no good purpose would be achieved by passing this motion, because the moment the Government took action, it would be suspect from the start and possibly would do more harm than good.  As far as other energetic measures are concerned, I assure the Seanad the Government will be only too happy to take such measures in this direction if there is any hope of their success.</P>
    <P>One point has been made&mdash;and it is a good point.  It has been asked: Has there been a systematic survey of the situation and of the facts to see whether, and in what direction, co-operation is possible?  That is the duty of the Departments of State. Knowing the policy of the Government as a whole, the various Ministers would naturally be interested in finding out what the possibilities were in these various directions.  That side of the work will certainly be done.  The examination can take place, and if anything of value, or anything that would seem to be of value, emerges, the present Government&mdash;and I am sure any Government that would be here&mdash;would be only too anxious to consider it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I should first like to express my gratitude&mdash;and I am sure I am speaking for the House&mdash;to the Taoiseach for spending so long with us to-day, listening so carefully to what we had to say and answering by such a conciliatory speech.</P>
      <P>If I may, I should like to comment on one or two of his remarks, but, first of all, I should like to emphasise one or two valuable things that have been said earlier in the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I noticed the silence as well as the eloquence in this debate, and a colleague has pointed out to me that it was a significant silence, in this way, that, with perhaps one exception&mdash;and also the exception of the Taoiseach, whom I regard as timeless and ageless &mdash;he does not come into the age group I am going to mention&mdash;only one <Col N="1417" /> speaker of over 50 has spoken this evening.  Is it not rather strange that the young people have spoken with high representation, but there has not been a word, except in one quarter, from the wisdom of the aged ones?</P>
    <P>I find something symptomatic in that. The Taoiseach has an ever-young mind &mdash;I am not expressing my own opinion in saying that, but the opinion of many of us&mdash;but why did not at least some of the wiser and experienced leaders of the two chief Parties give us the benefit of their wisdom this evening? It saddens me greatly.  I do not think it is a good sign.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>Silence is sometimes golden.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not see that that much-quoted proverb is going to change the significance of what I have said.  I feel there is a holding back here: there is a caution, a fear of committing themselves, which is natural in the members of a big Party, but if we are to solve this problem, can we do so in the terms of a Party motion?  We cannot, and I deplore the silence of the wise grey heads of this Assembly.  I am a grey head myself, but not necessarily a wise one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has said it for me, but I was about to say it myself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish I could see into the minds and the hearts of the older ones, the experienced ones who kept silent this evening.  That is where the secret of our problem lies, here, now, and for the next ten years. Perhaps in ten years' time there will be a difference.  Possibly they have looked into their hearts and made up their minds, but they have not given us any indication.  Possibly, there are difficulties that we do not see but I wish they would have the frankness to tell us what they are.  After all, we are a vocational Assembly representing agriculture, industry, commerce, administration and we have them all more or less silent as far as the older generation is concerned.  I am glad one member of the Cultural and Educational Panel, Senator Barry, did speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To take what was said rather than <Col N="1418" /> what was unsaid&mdash;which it would be unfruitful to speculate about&mdash;I welcome Senator Barry's support and Senator Cole's support.  I am saddened when the one senior who spoke to us speaks of the proposal as impossible here to-night.  Heavens!&mdash;impossible for us to sit down and take thought for practical co-operation&mdash;impossible! Yet, he was frank and he was sympathetic.</P>
    <P>Senator Murphy gave us a healthy sign.  Labour, I believe, will become more powerful politically in this country. It ought to become more powerful politically in this country.  I hope he speaks for the younger generation of Labour.  I see hope there.  He said something that we must face and, with due respect, I will mention it again in commenting on the Taoiseach's statement.  We must at times be prepared &ldquo;to face snubs&rdquo; from Northern Ireland.  It will be hard to do, but I think it will be a sign of the stronger person, the person of greater conviction, that we are prepared occasionally even to be snubbed by them.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Quigley spoke&mdash;and he is perhaps the youngest of us&mdash;and there were signs of hope there too.  He agrees that there is need for time and thought and money to be spent on this problem, if solutions are to be found.  The only people who will find the money for it, I am pretty sure, at this stage, will be the Government.  Will they find it? He says, and the Taoiseach agreed, that a commission would be a mistake, that a commission, more or less, is the negation of energetic action.  Well, generally, that is so.  Perhaps I am an idealist, but I think a good commission could be energetic and could produce a practical proof of the desire to co-operate, but perhaps he is wiser about that.</P>
    <P>I only mentioned the commission in passing.  I deliberately did not put it into the motion because I did not want to tie either myself or the House in any way.  But I want some action, official action, now.  And if it is not going to be a commission, what is it going to be?</P>
    <P>Senator O'Quigley suggests that certain <Col N="1419" /> Government Departments should take the matter up.  I agree.  I think that would be just as good if they will take it up officially and if they will be seen by the public in general to be doing an energetic job quickly, not merely doing the job but seen doing the job.  If it gets into the secrecy, at least for a while, of a Government Department, much of its efficacy will, I think, be lost.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach very generously said that he shared my views on the whole. But he thought the method was wrong, that a commission would be suspect, as a governmental move, from the beginning, while a combined commission appointed by the North of Ireland Government and our own Government would be ideal.  Then he said he thought the second was impossible. Well, he is a very wise statesman, but is it not conceivable that we could make an overture here and now, risking a public snub from the North of Ireland Government, asking can we have a joint commission on this matter?  Let it be done publicly, with suitable preparation, of course, and let Lord Brookeborough, if he likes, eat the words that he has spoken within the last couple of months and, more or less, say: &ldquo;Although I said we want to co-operate, we do not want to co-operate.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I do not think acceptance of such an offer is an impossibility.  I think politically it would be a bold deed.  I also think that politically it might succeed. As a Senator said, the world is in a flux at the moment.  People's minds are shifting and changing, and a practical move towards co-operation, a practical indication of the desire to work together with our neighbours, might succeed.  I am quite sure the Taoiseach would not like in any way to comment on this but may I urge him personally, and I hope I am speaking for some others, that he might at least privately sound the possibility of a joint commission.  I would like it done publicly.  I would rather our Government did it and was snubbed than have it done <i>in camera.</i>  But perhaps we are not prepared to accept that&mdash;and I realise the implications from the point of view of Party prestige <Col N="1420" /> that would result perhaps from a snub.  An unkind hostile Party might make a great deal of such a snub.  I realise most of that but I still think it would be a bold statesmanlike action and I cherish the hope that our present Taoiseach would consider it.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Murphy and I am glad he said it&mdash;he is a young man &mdash;we must be prepared to be snubbed at times.  I have great sympathy for that.  I belong to what was once a privileged kind of people in this country, although I was too young to enjoy the privileges.  But my parents did and our people before that.  Our policy now must be much the same as I have advocated for the country to-night. We of the once privileged people will have to be prepared to be snubbed for the deeds of a generation before.  The more sensible of us realise that, and go about being snubbed, if necessary.  If anyone snubs me in the Seanad, I say: &ldquo;All right.  I am paying the price for some massacre committed by somebody perhaps 500 years ago.&rdquo;  But I assure the Taoiseach and you, Sir, that being snubbed sometimes is worth it, if one has the conviction that it is the right thing to do, and I think a lot of people in this country will accept that point.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach's suggestion is this, that groups of private individuals, private citizens, should take the necessary steps.  I must be frank.  I speak with great deference.  I think that is no good.  I think that simply is passing a buck which is primarily a Government buck.  That is what I believe. Private citizens will not have the prestige.  They will not have enough moral support; and the powers, the secret powers, that are working against unity in this very Republic will frustrate them.  I am not talking about secret societies or anything of that kind.  I am talking about people who know full well that they will lose money, prestige or jobs, or that there is a risk of it, if unity comes in Ireland to-morrow.  They will be able to hold down any private groups of citizens very effectively if it has not official backing.  And much as I would be eager to do anything I could as a private citizen to promote unity, I do <Col N="1421" /> not think it would carry the necessary weight.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach referred to Strasbourg and showed me that there was not an exact parallel there.  But he mentioned the Council of State.  Very well.  Why not summon the Council of State, constitute the Council of State this year?  The North of Ireland Government, I understand&mdash;the Taoiseach will correct me if I am wrong&mdash;is bound to constitute that Council if we take the necessary steps, or it was so bound.  Is it perhaps because of the change in our status to the Republic that this no longer holds?</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not sure but I think that it was in 1925 that it was put aside.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I withdraw my suggestion.  In that case it does not arise.  The Taoiseach mentioned the need for a systematic survey and a Senator suggested it.  Yes.  Would some Government Department undertake that, specifically and energetically, right away and make it public that they are doing so?  That would be something.  That would be action, at least.  I think that they should do it, that money should be set aside in the next Estimates, in a Supplementary Estimate, if necessary, for the purpose of promoting or studying the possibilities of co-operation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is one other drastic step that I suggest.  I will not press it for obvious reasons.  Some time ago an anti-Partition council or committee was set up, under semi-governmental support, I think.  All right.  I do not think it did any good.  Some people may think it did.  That is a matter of opinion.  It did its best.  From what I know, I think it was a harmful best on the whole.  Their intentions were right, their methods wrong, the results, I think, negative.  Very well.  Let the Taoiseach and the Government set up a pro-co-operation committee.  He can think of another title.  Mine is a very poor one.  But the positive side of anti-Partition is pro-co-operation.  Let a suitable title be thought out, the same backing given to it, an all-Party backing if possible, as was given, I <Col N="1422" /> think misguidedly, to the anti-Partition committee.  Then we would be getting somewhere.</P>
    <P>I want action of some kind because, in fact, what the more committed Government Senators implied by their silence to-night is: better for the Government to do nothing.  Similarly the Parties have tacitly indicated that their point of view is: better for the Parties to say nothing.  It amounts to that.  There was no representative speaker from the front bench.  Does that mean no response to-night, no vote, no Government action, only the pious hope that some private citizens will get together and think up something very nicely?  I think it would be a great pity.  I hope something more will come of this debate to-night than that.  I am sorely tempted to ask for a division, but I shall not do so because I realise that it would be misinterpreted.  I know, and the whole country knows, that, in different ways, all are united on the principle behind this.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach has kindly said he agrees.  There is only a difference about methods.  If the House will allow me, I shall withdraw the motion without pressing for a vote, but I hope some of the suggested lines of action will be pursued soon, energetically or publicly.  Otherwise, are we to wait for another ten or 15 years?</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be completely out of order if I said just a few words now in answer to one point?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach may intervene.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonDeValera" hpid="The Taoiseach Eamon de Valera">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I here and now&mdash;I am taking a very big responsibility without consulting my colleagues&mdash; wish to state that we on this side are quite prepared to take part in a joint commission to examine the possibilities indicated by the Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Taoiseach would take the initiative, it would be a most brave and noble thing to do. In personally requesting such a commission, he might do a great service to the country.</P>
      <P>Motion, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Dundalk Railway" RHead="Works&mdash;Motion">
    <Title>Dundalk Railway Works&mdash;Motion.</Title>
    <Col N="1423" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That in the opinion of Seanad Éireann workers in Dundalk Railway Works should enjoy the same compensatory arrangements, in the event of their becoming redundant before or after their absorption by the Dundalk Engineering Company, Ltd., as those guaranteed to C.I.E. workers by the Minister for Industry and Commerce in Dáil Éireann on 27th November, 1957; and further that an arrangement should be made by that Minister with C.I.E. and the Dundalk Engineering Company, Ltd. to ensure that the work of repair and maintenance on that part of the present G.N.R. Board organisation situated in the Republic shall continue to be carried out in Dundalk after the G.N.R. Board ceases to function.</P>
      <P>I propose to take the first half of this motion now and then to deal with the second part.  It refers to a statement in Dáil Éireann by the Tánaiste to the effect that certain C.I.E. workers would be covered by compensatory provisions.  These compensatory provisions are contained in the Fourth Schedule, Sections 39 and 40, of the Transport Act, 1950.  There is no point in going through a lot of legal jargon.</P>
      <P>I would refer the House to a statement by the Tánaiste in the Dáil on Wednesday, 27th November, 1957, as reported in the Official Report, column 1059.  In it, we get, with great clarity, a statement of his intention. He is reported as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I want now to deal with the position of railway workers.  The House is aware that under existing legislation relating to C.I.E. there is a right to compensation given to every worker who loses his employment or whose conditions of employment are worsened by reason of the closing down of railway lines, the withdrawal of services, or because of the dieselisation programme.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Then followed some remarks with regard to whether or not this could be expected to take place: it is not necessary to bore the Seanad with the whole <Col N="1424" /> quotation.  Further down the same column the Tánaiste continued:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The Government have decided that the proposals for legislation which will be produced will provide for compensation based upon these existing statutory scales but subject to abatement where a displaced worker finds full-time employment either with a Government Department, with a local authority, or with a State-sponsored body.  It will provide also that the compensation will continue, where it takes the form of a pension, until the worker reaches 65 years and makes the necessary arrangements to ensure that a worker receiving a compensation pension will remain in credit under the pension scheme and qualify at 65 to receive the full retirement pension.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>For the benefit of Seanad Éireann, I will give a short example of what it would mean in the case of a man in C.I.E. employment who becomes redundant. I will take the case of a man earning £8 a week.  If that man had been in the employment of C.I.E. then, under the provisions of Sections 39 and 40 of the Fourth Schedule of the Transport Act, 1950, he would become a recipient of a compensatory pension of £147 10s. per year until he reaches 65 years of age and then he would qualify for the normal retirement pension. If he were an employee with 20 years' service he would qualify for £201 per year compensatory pension until he reaches 65 years and then he would qualify for the normal retirement pension.  That was a rather fair approach by the Government.</P>
    <P>It is common knowledge that, for many years, the railways have been a subsidised branch of our Government undertakings.  They have been a Government undertaking.  I submit that the G.N.R. is no different from C.I.E.  I submit that there is a very direct parallel with this situation where, as a result of a decision taken simultaneously in Belfast and Dublin, there is to be redundancy in the Dundalk Railway Works which, since January 10th last, has become the Dundalk Engineering Company, <Col N="1425" /> Limited.  I submit that the position of a railway employee in C.I.E. who has become redundant because of the closing down of railway lines, the withdrawal of services or the dieselisation programme has been provided for and that the worker in the Dundalk Engineering Company Limited has a great moral right to the same compensatory arrangements.  I submit that the Government should take another look at the situation for those compensatory arrangements for the workers in Dundalk who become redundant. If they do not do so, I think 400 or 500 families in Dundalk will be placed in a position of penury while, if they had been working for the same sort of Government undertaking under a different name, they would at least have been given something which would allow them to rehabilitate themselves in the world after their position in life had been taken from them.</P>
    <P>To give an idea of what sort of prospect the Government holds for these gentlemen, it is right and proper that I should give some quotations from what the Tánaiste said.  I give these quotations now in no destructively critical spirit.  I give them in no spirit of disappreciation of the Tánaiste's work or character or ability.  I provide them merely to give an idea of the situation because I believe the members of Seanad Éireann, not living in the area and having many other things to consider as well as railway troubles, would benefit from a few quotations from what the Tánaiste said in relation to these matters.  As reported at column 741 of the Official Report of Dáil Éireann for Wednesday, 20th November, 1957, the Tánaiste said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;When the new company was set up and, while these other discussions and negotiations were going on, it was directed, on the assumption that the arrangements for the leasing of the shops to the company would be satisfactorily concluded, to consider and investigate all possibilities for the development of commercial engineering activities there on a scale which would hold out a fair prospect of maintaining employment in the shops.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Note the words &ldquo;a fair prospect&rdquo;.  A <Col N="1426" /> worker in Dundalk now has a fair prospect of employment, but he has no guarantee of employment, nor has he the same opportunity or the same hope of constant employment as the man working in Inchicore or on the C.I.E. system.</P>
    <P>In column 742 of the same speech he went a little further and said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I want to be most careful in not creating any impression that the arrangements made to date put beyond doubt the future of the Dundalk shops.  The board of the new company have been given an immense and very difficult task indeed. Neither they nor I can guarantee success.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>It is in the face of these things that we locally, as public representatives, feel we must draw, in a respectful, responsible and disciplined manner, the attention of every public board and body of which we are members to the position that exists in the Dundalk workshops to-day.</P>
    <P>Lest the clarity of the approach of the Tánaiste to this problem should suffer, I should also like to quote what he said about compensation.  He said in column 751 of the same speech, in reply to Deputy Norton, just after Deputy Norton had finished speaking:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Oh, no; on the legal aspect of that I could not have been more definite.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The legal aspect of the matter under discussion was whether or not the G.N.R. railway employees were entitled to compensation.</P>
    <P>My whole case hinges on the point that a railway worker is a railway worker, whether he is working on the permanent way, or for C.I.E. or in the workshops in Inchicore or the workshops in Dundalk.  I hold that in a situation where our railways have had to be subsidised, there is a moral responsibility on the Government&mdash;when the hard work has to be given, when misfortune falls and when there is declining trade&mdash;to treat all employees equally, to give each and every one the same opportunity to continue in their employment, the same opportunity for advancement and promotion, the same <Col N="1427" /> risk of being disemployed and, if disemployed, the same compensatory provisions or the same retirement pension provisions as are enjoyed by his fellows.</P>
    <P>To follow on, on the difference between a worker in the Dundalk workshops and a worker in C.I.E.  I should like to give you one or two other quotations.  On 20th November, the Tánaiste had stated that there was considerable redundancy in C.I.E. Now, on 27th November, he wanted to make it quite clear that he had reconsidered his statement and that there was not a question of considerable redundancy. He made the statement that there was 30 per cent. redundancy which was denied absolutely later and the quotation I have here is from column 1061, to give us the figure of 30 per cent. redundancy in C.I.E.:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I have mentioned already that the C.I.E. Board estimate that 30 per cent. of the workers employed on the operation of the railways in its system are surplus to actual requirements.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I am sure the House will believe me when I say that that statement was denied explicitly by the Tánaiste the following week.  He said there was no such thing as 30 per cent. redundancy and that he had been in error when he said so on 27th November.</P>
    <P>A colleague of mine in public life who has contributed very largely to it in Louth&mdash;namely, the present Minister for External Affairs&mdash;spoke on October 28th in Dundalk and said:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;With goodwill and co-operation between employers and workers I hope that anyone viewing this situation ten or 20 years hence may view it not as the disaster it now appears to a great number of men anxious for their own future and the future of the town but that out of it a great industry will grow and prosper.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I share that hope and I might say I share that view; but what is to happen these men and these families in the area who will be thrown out of employment in their hundreds in the next two or three months, without any <Col N="1428" /> compensatory provisions?  I put it to the House that there is a very great difference between one man or ten men of a certain type being unemployed in a district and 100 or 200 men of a very specialised type being unemployed in a particular district.  Is it not true that those men have literally no opportunity in that district of securing alternative employment?  If it is true, is it not necessary that the Government should approach this matter in the very same way as they approached C.I.E.?</P>
    <P>Just because it is a fact that, in the Transport Act of 1950, there are enshrined compensatory provisions for one section of railway employees, should not the other section get similar treatment, even though in the Great Northern Railway Act, 1953 no such provision is enshrined?  Should the Government not face up to their moral obligation in this regard?  My motion here is not put down with a view to taunting them or annoying them, but merely with a view to asking Seanad Éireann to convey to the Government by their speeches and statements that it is the view of Seanad Éireann that these men should get the same provisions.</P>
    <P>That deals with the first half of my motion.  The second half refers to the work which remains to be done on maintenance and repair on that portion of the G.N.R. Board line in the Republic after September, 1958.  Since I put down the motion, there has been some change and some clarification in the state of affairs.  In order to give Seanad Éireann the exact nature of this change, I will quote part of a letter which is now public property.  It was inserted in all the local papers and some of the daily papers and therefore it can be quoted.  It was sent by Mr. Percy Reynolds to the Town Clerk of Dundalk on November 18th, 1957.  I quote the centre portion of the letter&mdash;and in its own context:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I am afraid, however, that when the G.N.R. Board is dissolved there will be no work for Dundalk on the maintenance and repair of locomotives, rolling stock, and bridges, as this work will be done, in the Republic, by C.I.E. and, in the <Col N="1429" /> North, by the U.T.A.  These organisations will also maintain their own road vehicles.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That was a very serious matter for the workers in the workshops in Dundalk.  We all hope this new company will blossom forth into something that will employ more men than there are there at present; but we know, as was clearly outlined by the Tánaiste, that a very difficult task has been given to the directors.  It will be a very extraordinary thing if these gentlemen can produce, in 12 months or two years, in the competitive field we have to-day, a business which can employ the greater portion of 1,000 men.</P>
    <P>It has been estimated that if all the maintenance and repair work on the permanent way and the rolling stock and the locomotives and the bridges that remain to the present G.N.R. Board&mdash;it will, of course, be amalgamated with C.I.E. in September&mdash;were done in Dundalk, then there would be work there for 300 men.  That would give this new company quite a start. It would mean that the load would not be quite so severe.  We local representatives in that part of the country were keen and anxious that this would be done.</P>
    <P>After many representations, Mr. Reynolds issued a statement on 10th January last, some of which I now quote from the <i>Irish Independent</i> of that date:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Agreement has been made with the Board of C.I.E. that the rail and road rolling stock of the G.N.R. which were acquired by C.I.E. in December would be continued to be maintained to the greatest possible extent at the Dundalk Works.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That does not cover locomotives or the permanent way and it does not cover the bridges.  I do not know what proportion of the work now being done in Dundalk is represented by the work done on locomotives, bridges and the permanent way, but I know some workers in the locomotive shop consider that it is quite a big proportion. Why do we not consider that the railway workers employed in the workshops <Col N="1430" /> are individual employees of the Government over a number of years, that they are entitled to the same hope of continued employment as are workers in other railway workshops, and surely when half or 60 per cent. of the railway line, rolling stock, locomotives, bridges and road vehicles have been removed from them by the action of the Northern Government, they should be given all the work that remains on the portion of the line which was theirs and which is located in the Republic after September, 1958?</P>
    <P>The statement by Mr. Reynolds is merely that the specific works he mentioned will, whenever possible, be done in Dundalk.  I would suggest that the Minister for Industry and Commerce meet Mr. Reynolds, the chairman of the new company, and the unions concerned in order to make an arrangement whereby Dundalk will get its fair share of the work in respect of the proportion of line that remains in the G.N.R. system.  Morally, these men are entitled to more than that as railway workers.  They are entitled to the same opportunity of work and employment as railway workers elsewhere. However, this motion does not ask for that.  Neither was that asked for at any protest meeting held in Dundalk.  All these men are asking for is that they get a fair share of the work and that work will not be given elsewhere, to the detriment of Dundalk. If the Government can see their way to providing this fair share of employment, the people of Dundalk will reciprocate and the new company will find willing workers and co-operative effort.  I am asking the Government to remove despair and depression. I am asking them to give the people of Dundalk an even break.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOQuigley" hpid="Mr. O'Quigley Mr. O'Quigley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Quigley</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to second the motion.  I will not take up the time of the House in dealing at length with it. This might seem to be a motion related to local circumstances only, but I think that, quite apart from the fact that it deals with only a limited section of the population, all members of the House will have the greatest sympathy for people who find themselves faced with redundancy or the <Col N="1431" /> prospect of unemployment, due to no fault of their own.</P>
      <P>The transport system in this country over a great number of years has given cause for serious concern, and despite the best efforts of all Governments at different times to establish economic and efficient transport in this country, the inevitable results that this motion discloses come about and people find themselves in a very awkward position. Senator Donegan realises, as everybody must, that it is not easy for the Government to compensate these people, but equally so it must be realised that people who find themselves in employment to-day and unemployed to-morrow will find it extremely difficult to find the wherewithal to carry on.</P>
      <P>Therefore, it is not asking too much to demand that some compensatory arrangements be made to deal with the position of people who find themselves faced with this problem.  I think it has always been accepted as a principle in a great deal of legislation that where people are affected in their employment by the action of a Government or Governments, every effort is made to safeguard their rights.  We were dealing earlier to-night with the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, but the Treaty of 1922 provided, in Article 10, that civil servants of the British Government who were in this country would be entitled to remain on under the new Government established in the Irish Free State, or, if their conditions of employment were materially worsened under the Irish Free State Government, would be entitled to compensation.</P>
      <P>There is a whole series of legislation dealing with the position of transferred civil servants under the Treaty.  Provision for compensation is made in legislation dealing with the E.S.B., with the amalgamation of gas companies and in our own C.I.E. Act of 1950, to which Senator Donegan has referred.  This compensatory arrangement is provided for in the event of redundancy in the C.I.E. system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would seem altogether inequitable <Col N="1432" /> that, in the event of redundancy in C.I.E., the public at large, including the employees of the Dundalk Railway Works, should have to pay for the compensation of employees of C.I.E., and that people employed by the G.N.R. who became redundant should get no compensation.  Equity and fair play demand that they be treated equally.  Admittedly, there is no legislation in existence at the moment, but there is no reason why that legislation could not be introduced in connection with the rearrangements being made on the basis of the statement made by the Tánaiste towards the end of last year.</P>
    <P>There has been a great deal of sympathy expressed by public representatives, by the local Press, and so on, with these workers.  I think we all have that sympathy, and, in spite of the admitted difficulties which face the Government, some hope of compensation to enable these people to adjust themselves to the new circumstances should be held out.</P>
    <P>With regard to the second part of the motion, it seems that that is only an arrangement that could and ought to be made between the Board of C.I.E. and this new company.  While the Minister for Industry and Commerce may have no statutory functions in the matter&mdash;I imagine he has not; I would have to have an opportunity of looking up the matter&mdash;I am certain that if he took appropriate action, he would achieve the position advocated so strongly by Senator Donegan, that modicum of work which would be necessary to create stable employment in the new company.  For these reasons, I would commend this motion to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Such a lot has been said here and elsewhere about compensation for C.I.E. and G.N.R. employees that the impression has been created that there is some El Dorado and that all these people will get compensation.  There is a difference between what Senator Donegan is asking for in this motion and what he really means.  Senator O'Quigley started bringing us down to earth, but we have not quite landed there yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What is the position in regard to <Col N="1433" /> compensation for railway workers generally?  There is a whole tradition of legislation since 1924 and all the Acts dealing with public transport since then, amalgamating existing undertakings and setting up new undertakings, have provided for compensation for the employees who might be made redundant or suffer a diminution of their emoluments arising out of the relevant event.  That is exactly what is being overlooked now in all this talk.  The last C.I.E. Transport Act of 1950 provides in Section 38 (4), which is the relevant section:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Where the board is unable to offer to a person (being a person to whom this section applies and whose retention in its service is unnecessary on the ground of redundancy) suitable alternative employment in its service, then, notwithstanding anything contained in this section, his services may be dispensed with by the board and, in that case, he shall be paid by the board, compensation calculated in the manner set out in the Fourth Schedule to this Act.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In other words, if he cannot be offered alternative employment in the new undertaking, he is entitled to compensation. There is also provision for compensation where a railway service is discontinued or a branch line closed and the employees made redundant as a result.</P>
    <P>What is happening in regard to the G.N.R.?  The board was set up under the Act of 1953.  It is a joint board presided over by the Minister here and the Minister in the North.  The lands in the Republic are vested in the Minister and the Dundalk workshops are vested in the G.N.R. Board, which is, I underline, a joint board.  Legislation, presumably, will have to disestablish the board created by the 1953 legislation, and it seems that the lands or the other assets, apart from the Dundalk engineering works, will be vested in C.I.E., whilst the Dundalk workshops will be vested in the new undertaking which has been set up, the Dundalk Engineering Works, Ltd.</P>
    <P>In such a situation, it is usual in vesting the property under legislation, <Col N="1434" /> to transfer the relevant staff.  Therefore, we would expect that in the forthcoming legislation&mdash;and I think the Minister has indicated that in his speech&mdash;the staff of the G.N.R. in the Republic will be transferred to C.I.E., and if the new C.I.E., 1958, cannot offer them alternative employment, they will then be entitled to compensation.</P>
    <P>There is one thing being forgotten which is clouding the issue completely with regard to Dundalk.  Compensation provisions do not cover redundancy arising out of loss of traffic, arising out of commercial changes. They cover only redundancy arising out of the relevant event, namely, the transfer.  Therefore, people who are transferred to C.I.E. and to whom C.I.E. will say: &ldquo;We cannot give you employment&rdquo;, will be entitled to compensation; but there is no provision&mdash; nor do I think it was the Minister's intention to make such provision&mdash;for compensation in the event of people losing their employment next year or the year after because of a drop in traffic or because of other developments.</P>
    <P>The Minister cannot justifiably avoid making similar provision for the staff of the workshops in Dundalk.  I agree with Senator Donegan that they should be treated equally with the other employees of the G.N.R. and other employees of C.I.E.  As I said at the outset, I do not think that is exactly what he means nor what the people in Dundalk are expecting and hoping, because even though the bulk of the staff in those workshops have already become employees of the Dundalk Engineering Works, which has leased the workshops from the G.N.R. Board, there will still have to be some mention of that undertaking in the legislation, particularly in regard to the pension rights of those people.</P>
    <P>I think the Minister should provide for compensation for them in exactly the same circumstances, namely, that if the Dundalk Engineering Works, Ltd., cannot offer them alternative employment, they might be entitled to compensation in the same way as people on the rest of the undertaking, who would not be offered alternative employment <Col N="1435" /> by C.I.E., would be entitled to compensation.  The danger in Dundalk&mdash;what is feared there&mdash;is redundancy arising from that transfer, a redundancy from the failure of the new undertaking to establish itself in the export market and a failure to get sufficient work.  Redundancy arising out of such a situation is not provided for in any sort of transport legislation.</P>
    <P>I share with Senator Donegan the hope that the Dundalk Engineering Works will be successful and will find it possible to provide full time employment for all who have up to now been employed by the G.N.R. in Dundalk. I hope that the Minister, if he reads the report of this debate, will bear in mind that there is an atmosphere in Dundalk at the present time which is complicated by doubts as to what the future holds, and complicated as well by an idea that they should get compensation for any further recession in trade.  The people there told me they are anxious to get on with the work, to see some stability and some certainty&mdash;perhaps no definite guarantees about their employment but at least to have some understanding of what is to happen in the hope that they will be able to get on with the work.  I am told at the moment that the situation is that nobody is managing and nobody is working, and that is not in the interests of either the staff or the new undertaking.  I know it is difficult with a change-over like this to get established but the quicker they get established and the quicker they get working, the better it will be for all concerned.</P>
    <P>I would urge on the Minister that, in equity, the people concerned in the workshops in Dundalk are entitled to the same treatment as other employees of the G.N.R., or employees of C.I.E. I would certainly hope that it could be got across to all concerned exactly what would be involved, what is provided for in former legislation and exactly what could be expected in the forthcoming legislation.  I am sorry that the Minister, or his Parliamentary Secretary, is not here for this discussion because he might have been able to clarify the position or might have <Col N="1436" /> found it possible to give some undertaking or assurance in regard to the question of compensation at Dundalk.</P>
    <P>In regard to the second part of the motion, again I think too much might be hoped for or expected here.  The Dundalk workshops of the G.N.R. were the workshops for all of the G.N.R., both north and south.  They did all the work required for the whole railway and also for the road vehicles, the buses and lorries in the Republic. The G.N.R. has been reduced in size by the closure of the secondary lines and it will be further reduced by cutting off the Northern Ireland section. It is quite easy to see, therefore, that there is already a loss of work for the G.N.R. as such, a contraction of work.  There is now no need to repair the same number of wagons or to have the same building programme as formerly. The suggestion is that the work for that small portion, and it is only a small portion, should continue to be done at Dundalk.  From my knowledge of the situation, that cannot provide a great deal of employment in Dundalk; nevertheless it should be retained, if at all possible, in order to provide some employment.</P>
    <P>Again, I think too much is expected in that direction because quite obviously when a merger of two undertakings is completed there can be, for example, a utilisation of diesel engines over the whole system and less need to turn out more rolling stock. By a contraction of branch lines, for instance, you have more carriages to spare and less need for work like that. I do hope that an arrangement can be made to keep that work at Dundalk in order to provide employment for the people there.</P>
    <P>Again, I am sorry that the Minister or his deputy is not here.  I hope he will have regard to what has been said and that he will find it possible to make some announcement to clarify the position in regard to compensation in the Dundalk workshops.  I am saying that the problem is not insuperable; it is not as difficult as might be expected, but there is not, at the same time, the over-all guarantee that some people think should be provided.</P>
    <Col N="1437" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be possible for the Minister to be here to-morrow, if we adjourned the debate now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We have to adjourn now&mdash;it is 10 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister be available to-morrow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1438" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it should be conveyed to him that it is very important.</P>
      <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Thursday, 30th January, 1958.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>