<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="15" Month="Mar" Year="1956" Vol="45" No="16" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 15 Márta 1956" DateEnglish="Thursday, 15 March 1956" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1433">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1433" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is intended to take business as on the Order Paper, and I may say that it is understood that the Central Fund Bill will conclude in the other House not later than Tuesday evening and, therefore, we shall be meeting next Wednesday.  I take it the House will have no objection to considering the Central Fund Bill on Wednesday next?  There will also be available the Supplies and Services Bill.  I take it an endeavour will be made next week to conclude both these Bills?  The following week is Holy Week.  I have also a report from the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it the intention to try to get through the agenda to-day, and if not, will the Seanad be prepared to meet to-morrow for the purpose of finishing the agenda, several items of which have been before us for quite a time?  In view of what Senator Hayes has said, it appears that we shall be dealing largely with the Central Fund Bill and the Supplies and Services Bill next week, and I should like to know whether it is hoped that we may get through this agenda to-day, and, if not, whether it is the intention to use our right to meet to-morrow morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is our intention to endeavour to get through the business to-day, but it is not the intention to meet to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I urge the advisability of reconsidering that?  Yesterday, we were very harsh upon people who absented themselves from work for one day and lost 20 or 30 years' pension rights.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1434" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us keep to the business of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it would be wise for the House to meet to-morrow. The following day is St. Patrick's Day and Senators would be leaving town.  I think we should have plenty of time next week to dispose of the business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>My suggestion was that we meet to-morrow morning, as is provided for in the Standing Orders, which would allow Senators to go home in the afternoon in time for St. Patrick's Day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>There should be a restriction on the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The intention is to adjourn this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Report of Committee on" RHead="Procedure and Privileges">
    <Title>Report of Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The committee have considered the reference made by the Seanad yesterday to the committee of amendment No. 3 to the Local Government (Superannuation) Bill, 1955, with regard to the ruling of the Chair.  The committee concurs unanimously in the ruling given by the Chair on amendment No. 3.  I take it that report is agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that the Minister told us yesterday, in relation to that particular paragraph, that it would not be either the intention or the effect of this paragraph to decrease State expenditure or save the State money&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I am asking whether the committee adverted to the reply to the question I asked the Minister, whether it was the intention, or would it be the effect, of this paragraph to save money for State funds.  He said, no, it was not, implying that if you deleted it, it would not increase the charge on the State funds.  Did the committee advert to that reply?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1435" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not in a position to inform the Senator of the nature of the committee's deliberations. The committee which is a pretty representative committee was unanimously of the opinion that the ruling yesterday was correct and that is all that can be said about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>May I take it that the answer to my question is: &ldquo;No; the committee did not advert to this Ministerial reply?&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say that this is a most unfair remark by Senator Sheehy Skeffington and I take exception to it?  The committee is a representative committee and I think it is deplorable that Senator Sheehy Skeffington should assume that any proceedings of the committee should be deprecated in that way.  I deplore this regrettable tendency shown by certain Senators only for the past year or two to delay the business of the House. Every day we lose five or ten minutes. If more deference were shown to the Chair and to the committee, it would be for the good of the House and the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Senators Senators">
      <NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is: That the report, as submitted by Senator Hayes, be agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Senator Sheehy Skeffington rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us have no more suggestions, but get on with the business.  Senator Skeffington is challenging the decision of the House in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>This question has been decided by the House and Senator Skeffington has no right to speak about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I would prefer the Chair's ruling to that of Professor Hayes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the <Col N="1436" /> House has come to a decision and Senator Sheehy Skeffington is not only being ignorant but also inexcusably and characteristically rude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I was asking for a ruling from the Chair.  So far, I have only got a ruling from Senator Hayes, which I regard as being out of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the point?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it agreed that we accept this committee report? I take it that, to that question, it is possible to make an answer, and that is what I was endeavouring to do.  If I am ruled out of order by the Chair, I am prepared to accept the Chair's ruling, but I do not appreciate being ruled out of order by Senator Hayes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter has been decided, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any debate allowed on that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prisons Bill, 1956&mdash;Second" RHead="and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Prisons Bill, 1956&mdash;Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Everett) James Everett">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Everett)</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this Bill is to provide for the temporary detention of prisoners in lock-ups provided in Garda stations or in other places being places designated for the purpose by the Minister for Justice.</P>
      <P>There is accommodation for some 1,520 prisoners in the prisons situated in Dublin, Portlaoise, Limerick, Cork and Sligo.  For several years past, the daily average number of prisoners in custody has been falling steadily.  In 1946, the daily average was 683, last year it was only 396.  There is, therefore, in the five prisons much more accommodation than is required and it is consequently proposed to close the prisons at Cork and Sligo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The daily average number of prisoners in custody in Cork and Sligo prisons in 1955 was 15 and eight respectively. <Col N="1437" /> This was not exceptional, the daily averages have been very low for a number of years.  Cork prison will be closed on 1st April and Sligo prison a little later.  When these prisons are closed there will still be accommodation for over 1,200 prisoners.</P>
    <P>It is proposed, when these establishments are closed, to have prisoners who are at present committed to Cork and Sligo prisons committed to either Limerick or Mountjoy prison.  This will result, particularly in the case of Sligo, in long distances having to be travelled when prisoners are being brought to courts on remand, or following conviction or remand to prison, and it may no longer be feasible, in some cases, to convey all such prisoners to a prison or to court without spending a period somewhere <i>en route.</i></P>
    <P>Under the law as it stands, unconvicted and unsentenced prisoners can be temporarily detained in Garda Síochána stations when being produced in court, but a convicted prisoner must be taken straight to prison.  When Sligo prison is closed it might be impossible, say, in a case being tried in Donegal, which was not disposed of until a late hour to bring a prisoner straight to Dublin.  For this reason, there is provision in the Bill to authorise the detention of prisoners in lock-ups pending their removal to prison. It is also necessary to authorise detention not merely in Garda stations, but in such lock-ups elsewhere as may be designated by the Minister for Justice because requisite accommodation may not always be available in a Garda station.  It is the intention in Sligo to convert two of the existing prison cottages into a suitable lock-up.  This lock-up will be used mainly for the housing of remand prisoners and prisoners for trial who must be brought from Dublin the day before they are due to be produced at courts in centres situated in the Counties of Donegal, Sligo and Mayo.</P>
    <P>I am sure the House will agree that the Bill is necessary and I commend it to them for favourable consideration.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very satisfactory to <Col N="1438" /> note that this Bill is required in order to reduce the number of prisons needed in the country.  It is satisfactory to realise that this steady reduction in prisons has been going on for a number of years and that the number of prisons now required is so small.  I note that there is only an average of 400 prisoners detained at present and that the accommodation which will still remain will be four times that number.</P>
      <P>The fact that there will be no prison now between Sligo and Dublin is indicative of the fact that crime, particularly in the northern areas, is extremely rare.  The fact that there is only an average of eight prisoners in Sligo, which caters for a number of the northern counties, as against 400 for the whole country, shows that Donegal, for instance, is the most crimeless county in the whole State. That is not to be wondered at because the reputation we have in the North for being law-abiding citizens is very well known.  I should like to ask the Minister in this connection will there not be a further imposition on the ratepayers in Donegal by reason of the fact that they are responsible for the cost of the transport of prisoners to the nearest prison.  If prisoners have now to be removed from Donegal to Dublin, via Sligo, say, it will, in my opinion, be a rather severe imposition on the rates as formerly there was a prison in existence in Sligo Town.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator mean the taxpayer?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The ratepayer.  There is provision each year in the estimates of the local authority for the transportation of prisoners.  There will be quite a number of parts of Donegal which now will be over 200 miles distant from Dublin because I take it that prisoners will not be permitted to be transported through Northern Ireland.  They will therefore have to go via Sligo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill also sets out that prisoners may be detained in places designated by the Minister, apart from Garda barracks.  I wonder would it not have been more desirable if the Minister had actually set out in the Schedule to <Col N="1439" /> the Bill the places which he will designate as lock-up places, because otherwise the Minister can apparently designate any place at all, and this House will be giving him permission to decide where at any time prisoners may be detained.</P>
    <P>Also in the Bill it is stated that, while a case is at hearing, the prisoner may be kept in a lock-up that is in a Garda barracks or in one of these places designated by the Minister. Would that mean that a prisoner may be detained for a long period, much longer than the 48 hours set out in the Bill, because a case may be at hearing for a week or two weeks on account of long depositions that may require to be taken?  A case may be going on for a number of days, even in the Circuit Court, and do I take it from the Bill that, after 48 hours, the prisoner is required to be removed to a prison, or that he can be kept for a much longer period than 48 hours in one of the lock-up places set out in the Bill, because Section 1, sub-section (b) says: &ldquo;While a case in which he is involved is at hearing&rdquo;?  I wonder does the further sub-section (c) govern that and, therefore, that the prisoner must be brought back, say, to Mountjoy after 48 hours?</P>
    <P>As I said at the outset, from the fact that the incidence of housebreaking and motor car offences is possibly on the up-grade, it must follow that crime, other than those, is steadily going down.  Again, for that reason, I say how pleased I am, and, I am sure, the House is, at the fact that this Bill is regarded as necessary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>We should all recognise that the situation with regard to crime and convicted prisoners and prisons, as outlined by the Minister, is eminently satisfactory and may well give us reason for pride.  I notice that Senator Walsh took the opportunity of indulging in that pride to some extent on a local basis, and described Donegal as apparently, from these figures, &ldquo;the most crimeless county in Ireland&rdquo;.  I suggest to him, however, that there might be another explanation.  It may be that the Donegal lawyers are the best in Ireland and consequently most likely to get their clients off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1440" />
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the case last night, but not to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>The request of the Minister based upon this situation is a reasonable one, but our acceptance of it ought to be conditioned by certain considerations.  The Minister is asking, under Section 1, to have the right to have a prisoner detained temporarily in a lock-up in a Garda station or some other such place. The word &ldquo;temporarily&rdquo; is, as Senator Walsh has pointed out, fairly vague, and might again, as under paragraph (b), refer to a period considerably longer than 48 hours.  That strengthens my main concern to-day, that is, that there should be a very careful examination by the House and by the Minister of the quality of the accommodation provided in those various lock-up centres situated in Garda barracks, or the new ones to which he referred.  I realise that, as has been made clear by the Minister, this Bill will give power which will, in the main, be used in relation to country or non-Dublin barracks.  Nevertheless, if we look at lock-ups in some of the country or Dublin barracks, we have certain misgivings as to whether they are quite what they might be.</P>
      <P>I made it my business, knowing that this Bill was coming up to-day, to visit two suburban barracks and two city central barracks, Pearse Street and Store Street, for the purpose of examining personally the accommodation afforded there, and assessing whether it seemed to me reasonable that we should give the Minister the right to have people detained there for 48 hours or more, or, if not there, at any rate, in country barracks which might be comparable and to which similar standards might apply.  I also visited the Bridewell, and I want to say something about that presently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the four barracks that I did visit, I found the cell accommodation, in my opinion, grossly inadequate for the accommodation of prisoners, even for a short period.  I found the cells dismal, and sometimes airless, as in Pearse Street, for instance&mdash;the sleeping accommodation a wooden plank bed even with a mattress and blankets, and the lavatory accommodation being <Col N="1441" /> in the cell, quite unsurrounded by any cubicle and incapable of being flushed from inside the cell, which means that it might remain unflushed for several hours in fact.  I was assured, and I believe truthfully, in all those barracks that these cells are never used overnight, and that the most they are used for is a few hours and that the prisoners are invariably sent, even in the middle of the night, to the Bridewell.</P>
    <P>Nevertheless, I could not fail to have some doubts about the power given here which could be used in relation to all such barracks, and to feel that we ought as legislators not to be quite happy about any assurance that the powers asked for would not be used in fact in such circumstances.  Furthermore, I could not help wondering whether the Minister could assure us that, in the country and provincial Garda barracks, the conditions are quite immeasurably better than they are in the four barracks I happen to have visited.</P>
    <P>In neither of the suburban barracks that I visited, and in which I was assured again, and, I am sure, truthfully, that prisoners were never kept for more than four hours, were there two cells provided, so that men and women prisoners, if there were such, and if they were to be housed in cells, could be housed only in the same cell. Even if it is only a matter of a few hours, I cannot help feeling that such accommodation, tolerated at present, even though it may be deplored, is not satisfactory.</P>
    <P>Furthermore, I noticed in each of those barrack lock-ups, that there is no theoretical official provision for the giving of food to prisoners.  A prisoner may send out for food at his own expense, if he knows his rights and has money, but I think, though I speak subject to correction, that there is no money grant given to the barracks for the purpose of providing food or drink to a prisoner, while he is so detained. I know that, in practice, the way in which these prisoners are treated is humane, and I would even go so far as to suspect that not infrequently Civic Guards put their hands in their own pockets where they think that a <Col N="1442" /> prisoner deserves to be helped in that way.</P>
    <P>I suggest that the Minister ought to be able to assure us that, with these extended powers, he will see to it that there will be provision for the giving of food to detainee prisoners not in a position to send out for it.  I would remind the Seanad that these men and women concerned, whether detained in the Bridewell or in Garda lock-ups, are detained for crimes of which they are presumed to be innocent until they are tried and convicted.  They are people who are being detained temporarily, and who are as yet, in the eyes of the law, presumed to be innocent.  In this connection, I also took the liberty of looking at some of the accommodation offered to the Gardaí and in particular I noticed the type of accommodation which they have in Store Street Station.  It seems to me that the conditions obtaining there are materially so extremely bad as to make one wonder if the Gardaí are presumed guilty&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is dealing merely with temporary accommodation for prisoners and not with Garda barracks.  The Senator may discuss this Bill only in so far as it relates to the accommodation for the temporary detention of prisoners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I merely wanted to suggest that if the Gardaí have not got reasonable accommodation, it can hardly be expected that the prisoners will have much chance of better treatment.  I should like to urge on the Minister that he devote his attention to that matter of Garda accommodation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to turn to the question of the Bridewell, which is the main place of detention for remand prisoners in this country.  Some years ago, the Irish Association for Civil Liberties set up a committee to visit the Bridewell, and, with the permission of the Minister and the Department, they visited it in 1952.  They made certain recommendations on that occasion and a similar committee visited the Bridewell in 1953 and again made certain recommendations.  All these recommendations were related to <Col N="1443" /> the conditions obtaining there for the prisoners.  I should like to mention what struck the committee as being necessary to improve the accommodation for presumed innocent prisoners on remand in such a detention place.  The first thing that seemed to us to be necessary was a recognition that such prisoners, however obstinate or aggressive, or however guilty or ignorant they might be, had certain fundamental rights as prisoners, and while it was felt that it would not be possible to provide them with a long list of rules and regulations, it was suggested to the Minister and the Department at the time that perhaps a very brief leaflet might be handed to them, indicating their rights, to see a solicitor, to have food sent in to them, and so on.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator now dealing with temporary accommodation for prisoners, or does he desire to widen the scope of the debate to deal with prisoners generally?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I am dealing with Section 1, which relates to the detention of prisoners in Garda stations and their temporary detention in places like the Bridewell.  I submit that, in considering the temporary detention of prisoners in a remand prison, I am in order in dealing with the conditions under which these people might be detained.  I think it is essential that we should consider what these conditions are.  I may say that a very large number of these conditions in the Bridewell have been most satisfactorily altered, but I should like to mention that we submitted suggestions to the Minister about a number of things which seemed to us to be basic essentials in regard to the detention of prisoners.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The second point mentioned by the committee in its report was that of heating these places of detention, and a third was the question of sanitation. There seemed to be two things necessary in regard to the latter, the first being that there must be some privacy in a place where sometimes as many as six or a dozen persons were being detained in one cell, and the second that the lavatories should be capable <Col N="1444" /> of being flushed from inside the cells. Another thing which seemed to be necessary and desirable was that ordinary whitewashing of the premises, and painting, should be carried out regularly, no matter what ill use might be made of it by some prisoners.  We found that some portions of the inside of the Bridewell had never been whitewashed, but remained the same crude concrete as when they were put up.  It was also felt that there should be provided some facilities for the prisoners to wash themselves and to see themselves. In other words, it was essential that there should be a mirror as an essential part of the accommodation provided.  It seemed to us that a person who was being detained for 48 hours, if he had not facilities to wash and a mirror in which to see himself, would almost, of necessity, present the appearance of a most disreputable person when he came before the court.</P>
    <P>Finally, it was considered that the ordinary prison visitors should go to these places from time to time.  I may say I have, since those reports were made, visited the Bridewell and I have been extremely favourably struck by the way in which the whole conditions there have been altered since this second Civil Liberty Report of 1953.  I may add that it becomes apparent that the Department and the Minister and his predecessor were concerned about the things on which we reported and did their very best to have the recommendations carried out.</P>
    <P>I mention the Bridewell here, as the largest place of detention in the country, but the same facilities for prisoners should be provided in regard to other Garda lock-ups.  I should like to state then that there has been a very considerable improvement in the Bridewell.  The lavatory accommodation is partly partitioned off and is now capable of being flushed from inside the cells.  The whole place has been repainted and the concrete floors have been properly surfaced.  There is more washing accommodation, and the whole atmosphere of the accommodation for the Gardaí has also been radically altered to bring it more into keeping with the work which has to be done there.</P>
    <P>One point which remains, and which <Col N="1445" /> the Minister might consider, is that of the issue of some sort of leaflet to the prisoners describing for them in simple terms just what are the rights of the detainees in such lock-ups.  It seems to me that it would be a simple thing to provide this, and it would be something that would be very helpful to ignorant prisoners.  The other point in relation to this matter is whether the Minister will consider asking the prison visitors to make regular visits to these lock-ups and places of detention.</P>
    <P>Senator Walsh raised a point about what is meant in Section 1 by the word &ldquo;temporarily&rdquo;.  I think one might rather have had something more definite like 48 hours, but this might well mean something considerably longer.</P>
    <P>It might be a question of one or two weeks.  I should like clarification on that.  I would be tempted almost to ask the Minister to qualify that word &ldquo;temporarily&rdquo; by some such phrase as &ldquo;but in no case for more than...&rdquo; so as to give a time limit to it.  If there is no stated time limit, that greatly strengthens what I say about general conditions.</P>
    <P>Secondly, I would ask the Minister to give an undertaking, as I am sure he will, in relation to the old and the new lock-ups, which I was interested to hear him mention here to-day, that provision will be made for conditions for prisoners and for Gardaí which will allow him in all conscience to permit such detention without grave hardship &mdash;to ensure and to promise us that, in such detention prisons, there will be civilised conditions, both for those people who are detained and for those who are detaining them, civilised conditions in relation to food, sleep, sanitation, heat and knowledge of their simple rights.</P>
    <P>We are asked in Section 2 to repeal Section 23 of the General Prisons Act, 1877, which laid it down that the Commissioners of Public Works should &ldquo;provide and maintain&rdquo; such &ldquo;proper accommodation for the temporary detention of prisoners as the Lord Lieutenant shall direct&rdquo;.  I think most of us will recognise that the &ldquo;direction&rdquo; of the Lord Lieutenant in that matter left a great deal to be desired.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1446" /> I conclude, therefore, with the hope that the Minister and his Department will &ldquo;direct&rdquo; far more comprehensively, and more understandingly and sympathetically, in relation to these matters, than the Lord Lieutenant did in his day.  I believe that the Minister can and will give us such an assurance.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Cíosáin Éamon Ó Cíosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Cíosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Bille an-bheag iseadh í seo agus dá bhrí sin ní dóigh liom gur ceart go mbéadh aon díospóireacht leathan uirthi.</P>
      <P>I take it that we are not permitted to have a general discussion on the prison system operating in this country on this rather restricted measure and that we are just making provision to meet the situation that will arise as a result of the closing of two prisons&mdash; one at Sligo and the other at Cork.</P>
      <P>Of course, like Senator Walsh, I would express satisfaction that the number of prisoners is declining in this country.  However, before one gives expression to total satisfaction in that regard, one would have to find out exactly what the reason for it is.  Is it due to a falling-off in the incidence of crime in this country, or is it due to what has been stated here, that is that certain able lawyers can secure the acquittal of people charged with certain crimes in certain parts of the country?  There could be a third reason and probably it is a more realistic one.  It is that in some cases it appears that there is excessive leniency in dealing with people who are brought before the courts.  It would appear also, to me, at any rate, that there is not that uniformity that is desirable in dealing with people of that kind.  I will refer to one incident, without giving the full particulars.  A person was brought before the District Court and was to be given a sentence of six months, but, at his own request, he was allowed to travel to Dublin and was given £3 out of the poor box to enable him to travel to Dublin.  On his way to Dublin he committed two further robberies of the kind for which he had been brought before the District Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a lot of gratitude in that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1447" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>I am just mentioning that case to show that this decline in the incidence of crime, or this supposed decline, could be due to the leniency that is being indulged in in certain quarters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think you would look on that as a basis for discovering whether or not we have an increase in crime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>It is just as much a basis as the other things we have heard.  I agree with the Senator, however. I am just mentioning it as another possible reason.  I do not want to widen the discussion on this measure.  I just want to say that I do not share the concern of the previous speaker about the conditions that obtain in the Garda barracks in the country, and so forth, for the temporary detention of prisoners. Hitherto, unconvicted and unsentenced people could be detained for a certain length of time in these places.  If the conditions obtaining in these places have been good enough for unsentenced and unconvicted people, why should they not be good enough for convicted and sentenced people?</P>
      <P>I do not know if the Minister has given us an indication of the use that will be made of the vacated buildings in Cork and in Sligo when this measure passes.  I think that is a legitimate question to ask.  I suppose these buildings can be regarded as county council property.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not referred to in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the other speakers, I am very pleased to hear the Minister announce that it is no longer necessary to maintain the number of prisons we have had in the country.  We got rid of one in my own county a considerable time ago.  I think the people in Cork and in Sligo can make just as good use of the building and site as the Galway County Council propose to do with theirs.  The point that brings me to my feet is that we have heard, particularly last night, concern expressed for the ratepayers of the country.  As Senator Walsh has already pointed out, the ratepayers are <Col N="1448" /> charged with the travelling expenses of prisoners until such time as they are sentenced.  Now, under the new proposals, while the closing down of those prisons will amount to a considerable sum in saving to the Central Fund, it will, on the other hand, place on the ratepayers in each of the counties where there is no prison being maintained an additional expense, and that expense will occur from their being compelled under legislation to meet the charges of the transfer of untried prisoners.</P>
      <P>I think this whole question will have to be reconsidered.  In former times, when this provision was first made, it probably was introduced somewhat on the lines of the Malicious Injuries Act &mdash;something as a deterrent, in the hope that local authorities, rural district councils and boards of guardians, might take a deeper interest, because they would have to meet the charge of the cost of the transport of prisoners. Now, when we are changing that whole system and, despite all the talk about decentralisation, when we are about to centralise our prison system, we should reconsider the position and relieve the ratepayers of the charges they are compelled to pay as a result of this Bill.</P>
      <P>I would go part of the way&mdash;and only part&mdash;with Senator Sheehy Skeffington in requesting, if it is necessary, that the Minister and his Department should seriously consider and ensure that the facilities provided in the new cases of detention and in the local Garda barracks will be of a type suitable for the reception and detention of the persons concerned.  We are not dealing in this Bill entirely with persons who are being convicted of any particular crime.  The Bill is one dealing, in the main, with untried prisoners and persons who are only arrested on suspicion or are awaiting trial, and, as the Senator pointed out, after all, we must accept that they are innocent until they are found guilty. That being the case, we should ensure that they are treated as such persons. I do not hold out that there should be any more severe treatment meted out to persons when they are sentenced, except that which the law and which our present system provides for.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1449" /> I think it very undesirable, both from the point of view of the Garda authorities and from the point of view of the prisoners themselves, that prisoners should be detained for any considerable time, and I would consider, while we may say that we cannot avoid having the period of 48 hours, no person should be detained in a Garda station any longer than 48 hours.  It places a strain on the Garda themselves. It is a thing they do not like. I have never met a Garda or sergeant of the Guards who is in any way anxious to have prisoners under his charge.  It is not that they are not anxious to treat them as reasonably as they possibly can and give them the best facilities that are available, but sometimes these facilities are not all that we desire.</P>
    <P>We are giving the Minister power to create new places of detention.  The Minister has not given us any indication of where these places of detention will be located, or as to how they are going to be run, or whether they will come under the inspection that is carried out under our present prison system by the prison visiting committee. There is also the question of the length of time.  &ldquo;Temporary&rdquo;, as other speakers have pointed out, can mean any length of time.  I think the Minister should qualify this word &ldquo;temporary&rdquo;, so that the prisoner himself, or whoever may be acting on his behalf, may be better aware of what we in this House intend the Act to be.  We cannot consider it in this Bill, but the Minister can bring the matter before his colleagues in the Cabinet and have this question of the new burden that is going to be placed on the local authority as a result of this Bill considered and some steps taken to relieve the local authorities of the charges now about to be placed on them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanRuane" hpid="Mr. S.T. Ruane Mr. S.T. Ruane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S.T. Ruane</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like briefly to associate myself with remarks that have been made by different Senators as to the conditions in the country that have led to the opportunity for the State to close down several prisons.  I would not like, however, to feel that the decrease in <Col N="1450" /> crime is due to any of the reasons given by Senator Kissane.  I do not think that leniency to criminals has ever been responsible, in so far as crime is concerned, for checking it. Rather does it encourage crime, because certain people, if they feel that they can get off lightly, certainly do not cease from giving trouble to the authorities whose business it is to see that they keep the peace.  I would rather think that the cessation in crime is due to a highly developed civic sense on the part of the people of this country who now recognise that they have their own police force with whom they can associate and co-operate, since they are not in the same position as they were when we were under alien rule.</P>
      <P>In so far as the remarks which referred to the extent that this desirable change would be a burden on the rates are concerned, I am in thorough agreement with Senator Hawkins and Senator Walsh.  Now that the people in Mayo, Galway and Donegal, and other counties far removed from the prisons that will be maintained, have to make provision for the transport of prisoners to the prisons that will be kept in commission, such will put a severe tax on the ratepayers, who at the present time have many other responsibilities to shoulder.</P>
      <P>I really think that, as the cost of prisons and the cost of the police force is met out of the Central Fund, the cost of the transport of prisoners should also be a charge on the same source and not on the ratepayers of the country.  That is all I have to say on the matter, but I think that the Minister should not find it difficult to bring about the change, which would be very welcome to the people of the country at the present time, who certainly are saddled with a burden in the matter of rates that many of them can only shoulder with the greatest difficulty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a very desirable development in the country to see the prisons being closed down.  I think we should leave it to the Minister, and particularly to the humanity of the Guards, to see to it that those prisoners while they are detained, even for <Col N="1451" /> 48 hours, will be treated in the way that we would expect the Guards to treat them.  I can assure Senator Kissane that, so far as the Cork prison is concerned, very great use can be made of such a big institution, and it is desirable to have it in Cork for the many other things we are anxious to find accommodation for.  I think that we are raising too many hares about the cost of transferring prisoners from one area to another.  Surely it is a bigger burden on the people to maintain the prisons than it is to transfer prisoners from one prison to another. This is a development we can all welcome and I feel that everyone will welcome it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister in introducing this short Bill made a very short statement.  In that statement, he mentioned that, while it was not stated in the Bill, the intention was to close down the prisons in Sligo and Cork and provide alternative accommodation for prisoners on remand.  So much has been said about decentralisation and the removal of services from Dublin that I wonder it did not occur to the Minister to close down Portlaoise and Mountjoy, instead of Cork and Sligo, and have the services provided in Cork and Sligo.  That is what should be done if Ministers gave any serious thought at all to this question of decentralisation.</P>
      <P>I agree that there are services which the people of Sligo would value more than a prison service and I am sure the same applies to Cork.  Yet in areas, particularly in the West of Ireland, where you have a falling population, a service such as that would be valuable because it would tend to maintain an increased population by reason of the fact that the people who would provide the service would have to live, say, in Sligo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Under the Bill, the Minister proposes to establish lock-ups but the Minister did not tell us in his rather short statement who will be the janitor in the case of those lock-ups.  At the moment, in the case of Sligo&mdash;I am sure the same applies to Cork&mdash;the warders in the prison are responsible for the conduct <Col N="1452" /> in the prison and the maintenance of the prison.  The Minister mentioned that, in the case of Sligo, some of the adjacent buildings will be used for temporary detention for people on remand.</P>
    <P>Who is to be responsible in those buildings?  Is it proposed to hand them over to the Guards and, if so, who is to be responsible for their maintenance, in view of the fact that Senator Skeffington stated&mdash;he knew what he was talking about; I take it he does until he is contradicted&mdash;that there is no provision for the feeding of prisoners in our Garda barracks, except at the goodwill and charity of the Garda.  In view of that fact, I should like to know who is to be the janitor in the case of buildings which the Minister proposes to use in Sligo. Will some of the existing staff of Sligo prison be maintained there for that purpose or will they be handed over to the Gardaí?  I am sure the Minister will answer that question and give the necessary information to which the House is entitled.</P>
    <P>It may be argued by the Minister that detention will only be for a short period, 48 hours in some cases, but it ought to be remembered that prisoners on remand can be detained during a particular case which might last for weeks, or even longer in cases where long depositions would have to be taken in the District Court.  That would involve fairly substantial expenses which have to be paid by the local authority.  I hope it will not, but, whether it does or not, I join with Senators Ruane, Walsh and Hawkins in expressing the view that that cost should be borne by the Department of Justice out of the Exchequer and that it should not be saddled on the county councils, particularly since some county councils have no say as to where those prisoners will be detained or, where they will be committed to prison. These expenses should not be a charge upon the local authority.</P>
    <P>As things are, every local authority has to provide in their estimates for that contingency.  I think it is time the Department of Justice took responsibility for that.  Might I suggest, without going too far out of order, <Col N="1453" /> that there is the same question as regards juries?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad the Senator knows he is out of order, since there is nothing about the matter he now speaks of in the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not gone too far out of order, Sir.  I hope the Chair does not think that I try to make his position very difficult.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, no.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>As I say, I have often heard the same thing said in regard to juries.  However, I will not refer to that matter further as I realise I would be going outside the bounds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Out of jail, so to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>I should be very anxious to hear what the Minister has to say in regard to the proposal to equip some of the adjacent buildings in the case of Sligo and how they are to be manned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJamesOGorman" hpid="Mr. O'Gorman Mr. O'Gorman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Gorman</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a matter in respect of which one needs to be brief. It is a source of great gratification to every one of us to be informed by the Minister this afternoon that there is very little crime throughout the country and that there is no need for the retention of Cork and Sligo prisons. That is a matter that every one of us, as Irishmen, should be extremely proud of, in view of the fact that, throughout the past, the prisons in Sligo, Cork, Tralee, Limerick, Mountjoy and Portlaoise were crowded to the doors, whereas now, in the 20th century, two of the main prisons, Sligo prison in the West and Cork prison in the South, are about to be closed down. That is something for which every one of us has reason to be grateful.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Prisoners on remand in Cork were transferred to Limerick awaiting trial in the Circuit Court and it is far cheaper in the case of a prison like Cork, to close it down altogether rather than have the public or the State carrying the financial burden of transferring prisoners.  I think it is much cheaper for the country to have institutions like Sligo and Cork shut down <Col N="1454" /> rather than be faced with the financial burden of keeping them going.</P>
    <P>It is a source of extreme pleasure to every one of us to hear the present position.  Our prisons are very historical in that some of the finest Irishmen of this generation were confined in them.  Such is the case in regard to Cork prison and I would like to see a prison such as Cork kept as a museum and as a reminder to future generations of the men who gave their lives in the fight for Irish freedom 35 or 36 years ago.  It would be a pity to see such monuments of the past let out to anything else.  One thing that is really wrong with Ireland is that buildings like that, where many of our dearest and best passed away in far more unhappy days than now, are not preserved for the nation and turned into something in the nature of museums.  I would not like to see Cork, in view of the many sacred memories for Ireland it holds, done away with or perhaps turned into an industrial concern.</P>
    <P>We are all very glad of the need for the Bill.  It is a great tribute to Ireland and Irishmen that, in the year 1956, due to the high standard set by every Irishman, there is no further necessity for the retention of Sligo and Cork prisons.  The Minister should be commended on the fact that there is nothing to do but close them down.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RogerMcHugh" hpid="Dr. McHugh Dr. McHugh">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McHugh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure that there is no further need for rhetoric on the subject of prisons, but I would like to ask one question of the Minister, if he would kindly answer it now or on the Committee Stage: whether there is any provision for the inspection of such places as are intended to be used for the temporary accommodation of prisoners?  It is possible that there is some such provision in the Prisons (Ireland) Acts, 1826 to 1933.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like very briefly to join with the other Senators who have complimented the Minister on the introduction of this Bill.  On every occasion when the Minister for Justice has come before the Seanad, I have found him a most reasonable person who has satisfied us beyond any doubt on any amendment to a Bill that he has examined the position closely <Col N="1455" /> and asks for no more powers than he thinks absolutely necessary to carry out his duties.  I should particularly like to compliment the Minister.  Unfortunately there seems to be a tendency for other Ministers to take another position.  I hope later on, on another Bill, to say more about that.</P>
      <P>Section 1, which deals with the right of the Minister to detain temporarily in a lock-up provided in a Garda station or any other place, is long overdue, because I have heard complaints and read complaints in the newspapers on many occasions that district justices have been loath to detain particularly young people because there is no suitable place in which they can be kept for two or three days while awaiting trial.  I do not agree with Senator Sheehy Skeffington that if the Garda barracks were not suitable, we should have to provide accommodation in what would almost be grade A hotels.  We have an excellent police force, and I am satisfied that they do their work conscientiously and honestly, and that no member of the Garda is going to bring a person to court and have him detained, unless he is reasonably certain that that person is guilty.  I agree in principle that we should assume that a prisoner is innocent, until he is proved guilty, but that does not extend to saying that the Garda should not have power to detain those people while awaiting trial.  I should like to compliment the Minister on the Bill and hope that he will get all stages of it to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be a very rare occurrence to have prisoners detained for longer than a few hours.  The 48 hours was put in to provide an opportunity to consult a solicitor or counsel, or to cover an emergency taking place, whether it was a car breaking down or something like that.  The maximum would be 48 hours.  Senator Skeffington asked a question about the lock-ups.  The only lock-up we have in mind is in Sligo, where we are converting two warders' houses, and that will be similar to if not better than Sligo prison.  I can assure Senator <Col N="1456" /> McHugh that the inspection of lock-ups will be just the same as the inspection of prisons carried out at the present time by the inspector of the prisons service.  As regards the 48 hours, that provision was inserted to protect ourselves in the event of an emergency, so that there could be detention in any place other than a Garda station.  Our intention is to confine it to the larger stations, but if a breakdown should take place before we were near a Garda station, we took the power to have some other place for detention for the time being.</P>
      <P>I can assure Senators and the people in general that prisoners on remand will be supplied with food the same as an ordinary prisoner at the present time, the same as in the Bridewell, where they are supplied, even if they are on remand only for a week-end, with food and clothes.  We can assure Senators that we will have no ill-treatment in any way.  They will not be in charge of the Guards, but of the prison officials when on remand. I can also assure the Seanad that the conditions of the lock-ups will meet the requirements of anybody in the year we live in, with proper accommodation and proper sanitation and warders who will see that they will get proper food.</P>
      <P>Senator Walsh raised a very major point in connection with the ratepayers. There are eight prisoners in Sligo at the present time.  The county council would not be liable after the first order.  Any time they are brought back on remand, the expenses would be borne, as Senator O'Reilly pointed out, out of the Prisons Vote.  It would not be a charge on the ratepayers.  I believe myself that all the expenses in connection with it will be out of the Garda Vote, other than the first order to be made on the transfer of the prisoner.  That should relieve his mind.</P>
      <P>The temporary detention provision has been explained.  We are only holding people over in case of an emergency, or where they want to consult their lawyers, or where they are waiting in other cases for an order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the question of remand prisoners, they will be under the control of the <Col N="1457" /> warders here from Dublin or elsewhere. Sligo is the only place where there will be a lock-up.  It will meet the requirements of the Board of Works.</P>
    <P>Senator Sheehy Skeffington raised the question of the Bridewell.  I have a report which I could show the Senator, and I am sure he would be very pleased about it, from members of the visiting committee of Mountjoy who visited the Bridewell.  There were no complaints whatsoever, the heating arrangements were up to 180 degrees, and the prisoners there, men on remand, told the members of the visiting committee that other than the ordinary complaints a prisoner will make to anyone, they had no complaints to make as regards the food, the treatment they got, or the heating of the place. They were quite satisfied and had no objection.  It is an old building, but there are improvements being carried out.  I could show the report of the inspector not alone of the prisons but of the Board of Works and it would allay any feelings the Senator may have in connection with the matter.</P>
    <P>With regard to the question of what is to become of the prisons to be closed down, the Department and myself have not made up our minds yet in connection with it.  Many demands are being made, but we have power under the Act with regard to the use to be made of closed prisons. When a closing order does not order the handing over of a prison or portion of it to the local authority, the Minister shall retain the premises; the Minister may, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, use the prison, in whole or in part, for such purpose as the Minister thinks proper, which would include use by another public Department; the Minister may, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, let the premises for a period of not more than 99 years; the Minister may direct that the premises be handed over to the local authority. The expression &ldquo;local authority&rdquo; means the council of the county or county borough in which the prison is situated.</P>
    <P>Those are the matters to be considered by the Department, and we will try to meet the wishes of the people <Col N="1458" /> and of the local authority as far as possible.  I thank Senators for the assistance they have given me in connection with this Bill, and I hope the explanations I have given have satisfied them.  If there is any other point I have omitted, I am only too anxious to assure Senators that anything in my power or that of the Department will be done to meet the wishes of Senators that prisoners or persons on remand will be treated in a humane and Christian way.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to ask the Minister whether it is his intention that the same standard of accommodation as there is now in the Bridewell will be made available in other places of detention such as Garda barracks and lock-ups.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure the Senator that there will be no change, so far as I and the Department are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister in his statement said that certain premises would be handed over to the local authority, being the county or county borough authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not determining that matter in this Bill.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining stages to-day.</P>
      <P>Bill considered in Committee.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 1.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the following amendment:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In line 8 after the word &ldquo;temporarily&rdquo; insert the words &ldquo;in any case for not more than five days.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The section as it reads at present merely provides for temporary detention, and the amendment is designed to clarify that position and to ensure that the period of detention will not be more than five days.  I understood the Minister to say, in effect, that a prisoner would not be detained for more than 48 hours, and I would hope the Minister will accept the amendment which is simply a clarification of this word &ldquo;temporarily&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1459" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Would that amendment be unnecessary, because the word &ldquo;temporarily&rdquo; is in fact defined in paragraphs (b) and (c)?  In paragraph (c), it is stated that a person may be detained for not more than 48 hours, which is less than five days, and paragraph (b) provides for detention only for as long as the hearing is taking place.  I take it that it would be a rather rare case that would take five days.  Therefore, I suggest that this amendment is unnecessary.  To add the words &ldquo;five days&rdquo; would not carry it any further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFirmullaghOReilly" hpid="Mr. O'Reilly Mr. O'Reilly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Reilly</NameTxt>
      <P>Apart from the amendment being unnecessary, I can see very serious objection to it.  Provision is being made here to maintain a prisoner in a lock-up.  Suppose a person is being tried in the District Court in Sligo.  The taking of depositions could last six or seven days, and perhaps even eight.  In that case, if you were to accept the maximum period of detention as five days, it would mean that the prisoner would have to be taken each night to Mountjoy and brought back to Sligo the following morning. In addition to the extra cost, that would involve a great hardship on the prisoner.  I think, therefore, it would be better to leave the section as it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>In answer to both Senators, I understood the Minister to say that he did not foresee any circumstances in which a prisoner might be kept for more than 48 hours. It is obvious, however, that if an unconvicted person is to be kept longer, it would inflict great hardship, because, if he were alone in the lock-up, it could really amount to solitary confinement. I think it would be very useful to define to some extent the force of the adverb &ldquo;temporarily&rdquo;.  What I proposed to achieve was to have a limit of five days put on the period of detention. That, I think, is a generous allowance for all contingencies in the light of what the Minister told us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator pressing his amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1460" /> Sections 2, 3 and Title agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment)" RHead="Scheme, 1956&mdash;Motion of Confirmation">
    <Title>Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Scheme, 1956&mdash;Motion of Confirmation.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Scheme, 1956, prepared by the Minister for Defence, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, under Sections 2, 3 and 5 of the Defence Forces (Pensions) Act, 1932, and Section 4 of the Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Act, 1938, and laid before the House on the 6th day of March, 1956, be confirmed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="Minister for Defence (General MacEoin) Seán (Major-General) Mac Eoin">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (General MacEoin)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Defence Forces (Pensions) Acts, 1932 to 1949, empower me, as Minister for Defence, to prepare, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, pensions schemes for officers and men of the Army, and for members of the chaplaincy and nursing services.  Section 4 of the Defence Forces (Pensions) Act of 1932 lays it down that any scheme so prepared shall not come into force unless and until it has been laid down before each House of the Oireachtas and has been confirmed by resolution of each such House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The main purpose of the scheme now before the House is to provide increases in the retired pay of officers, in the pensions of non-commissioned officers and men and in gratuities payable to or in respect of both classes. These increases arise from Army pay increases which took effect as from 1st November, 1952, and the 1st November, 1955, and only those who were serving on these dates and who consequently got the benefit of such pay increases will qualify for increased benefits under this scheme.  I should explain that the Army pensions schemes do not directly link the rates of retired pay or pension for officers and other ranks with their rates of pay at date of retirement or discharge.  The rates laid down in the schemes for officers and other ranks are independent of changes in Army pay, <Col N="1461" /> with the result that, in order to give increases in pension to correspond with pay increases, specific provision by way of an amendment to the schemes must be made.</P>
    <P>Article 4 of the scheme provides for new percentage increases by rank on the retired pay of officers who retired or were retired since 1st November, 1952, and before 2nd November, 1955, and further increases for those whose retirements took effect on or after the 2nd November, 1955.  These percentages reflect the percentage increases in pay by rank since 1937, the year the principal scheme came into being.</P>
    <P>Article 9 deals with a group of soldiers who served in the Survey Company of the Corps of Engineers but who were transferred to the Reserve in 1940 in order to take up appointments as civilians in the ordnance survey.  This was part of a general scheme to get ordnance survey work established on a civilian basis.  The soldiers concerned were all long-service men who had not got the minimum period of 21 years' army service necessary in order to qualify for pensions under the Defence Forces Pensions Scheme.  Article 9 now waives the requirement in their case of the minimum of 21 years' service for pension and renders them eligible for pensions based on their actual Army service.  The pension will not, however, be payable until the persons concerned will have retired from their civil posts in circumstances entitling them to awards under the Superannuation Acts.</P>
    <P>Article 13 provides for increased rates of pension, including married pension, for N.C.O.s and men discharged on or after 1st November, 1952, and before 1st November, 1955, and further increases for those discharged on or after the latter date. These increases arise as a result of the pay increases granted as from the 1st November, 1952, and the 1st November, 1955, and reflect the percentage by which the rates of pay applicable as from these dates exceed the rates applicable as from September, 1946.</P>
    <P>Article 14 provides for corresponding increases in the rates of gratuities payable <Col N="1462" /> to N.C.O.s and privates who are discharged or transferred to the Reserve, on or after the dates mentioned, in circumstances not entitling them to pensions.</P>
    <P>I have explained only the principal provisions.  If any Senator requires any further information, I shall be only too glad to give it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think there can be any disagreement with the proposal before the Seanad to-day in relation to the provision being made for an increase in the pay of retired members of the Army.  I suppose that, in effect, it is an increase in their pension rates.  While we are in agreement with the general principle involved in the Order, I do not know exactly why there should be something like discrimination between the N.C.O.s and the officers.  I do not think I should say &ldquo;discrimination&rdquo; but I do not see why they should be considered on a different basis.  Maybe I have misunderstood the Minister in that regard and, if I have, no doubt he will be in a position to correct me.</P>
      <P>I should like to avail of this opportunity to say that it is a pity that the same generous consideration could not be extended to other people who rendered service to this country in difficult times.  I refer to members of the Old I.R.A. who are in receipt of pensions. I know that the members of the Old I.R.A. who were in receipt of pensions got one increase some time ago, but, having regard to the increased cost of living, and so forth, I feel that that matter should be reconsidered. I realise that this is not the time to deal with such wide matters and that there could not be a wide discussion now.  I welcome the provisions of the Order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should just like to support a point made by Senator Kissane.  I should like to hear an explanation from the Minister for what appears to be perhaps a different basis of calculation of pension for non-commissioned ranks and for commissioned ranks.  If I have understood the tables correctly, the increase for officers is established as a percentage <Col N="1463" />&mdash;I notice sometimes that the bigger the salary, the bigger the percentage &mdash;and the superannuation granted in respect of the other ranks, privates, sergeants, and so forth, is expressed as a money sum.  It is consequently very difficult for us here to assess, just how great, comparatively speaking, is the generosity involved in relation to these two different types of soldier.  I would agree with Senator Kissane that anything that implied two different measures, as it were, would be a thing to be deprecated.</P>
      <P>There is just one other point and it concerns the explanatory memorandum issued in relation to this scheme.  It explains Article 9 in a way that, I am afraid, still does not quite come clear to my mind with reference to certain long-service soldiers of the Survey Company who were transferred to the Reserve in 1940.  I take it I am right in assuming that they were compulsorily transferred to the Reserve.  The Minister mentioned it in his opening remarks and said it was for the purpose of encouraging the ordnance survey mapping to be organised on a civilian basis.  I think I am right in saying that these officers were compulsorily&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>This was a voluntary transfer?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I see.  The second point is that I understand the ordnance survey work done by these men was, in large measure, done for the benefit of the Department of Defence in those years.  It was mentioned in this memorandum that these men were recalled to Army service in 1941.  I take it that they were compulsorily called up?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Further on in this explanatory memorandum, in the same paragraph, it refers to something the Minister explained.  When it says that a person must have retired from his civilian post in circumstances entitling him to an award under the <Col N="1464" /> Superannuation Act, I think that means that he must have retired altogether&mdash;that he must have ceased work&mdash;before he receives such a pension award.  I am not quite sure. There is apparently a discrepancy because it would appear that there are other members of the ordnance survey in various other branches of the Government service, who, being soldiers who had up to 21 years' Army service, are now permitted to draw a pension, despite the fact that they are still working.  There would seem, at any rate, <i>prima facie</i> an element of injustice in preventing, under paragraph 3 of Section 9, certain officers from drawing a pension, because they are still working, while allowing some of their colleagues to draw pensions while still at work.  It is <i>prima facie</i> an injustice to preclude the survey officers from getting a pension in circumstances which are not considered sufficient in the case of officers or men, who, having done their 21 years with the Army, are allowed to draw Army pensions and at the same time to continue in other employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VictorCarton" hpid="Mr. Carton Mr. Carton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carton</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister why he has completely ignored the claim of the men who left the Army at the behest of the Minister in 1946.  In my experience as an ex-soldier, I was paraded and asked to leave the Army as early as possible and so facilitate the powers that be to get the Army back to the establishment they wished to have.  Those men who left the Army in 1946 have been brutally victimised since that time in relation to pension awards; and I, by virtue of who I am, am speaking for the 1922 soldier.  There are plenty of soldiers out now with pensions of from 15/- to 16/- a week.  I think the Minister ought to be reminded of that tragedy, in case he does not know of it already.  The persons who are being catered for now are people who have been catered for already since 1951, 1953, 1954, all through the years.  I am not objecting to these officers, non-commissioned officers, and men, although there is a peculiar desire on the part of legislators in this country to think of soldiers purely in the terms of officers.  I should like the Seanad <Col N="1465" /> and the Dáil once in a while to think of the N.C.O.s and men, or as they are described in the Act, &ldquo;other ranks&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>These men are in a bad way and do need some help in relation to the pensions they are in receipt of; and I am sure the Minister will listen to me when I say that they are, in the main, being victimised by their acquiescence in accepting the direction of the Minister in 1946, and leaving the Army to get themselves sorted out into civilian life.  In general, they are unorganised. No trade union can make any appeal for them.  They have an organisation &mdash;the Organisation of National Ex-Servicemen&mdash;that has no qualifications, other than social, to approach the Minister and ask that an appeal for these men be considered.  I, as an exsergeant-major of the Defence Forces, feel that it is my job here in the Seanad to speak on behalf of these N.C.O.s and men and to try to get some little recognition for them.</P>
      <P>In these days, when a raise of 2/- or 3/- in purchasing power in relation to the finances before 1939, is the equivalent of raising their pay by 6d. or 8d., I think we ought to forget once in a while the thousand-a-year people and think of the men who are cast into civilian life at 48 years of age, which is the period which they normally would have after 21 or 23 years' service in the Army.  These men are being entirely neglected.  Rather than go to any great length to embarrass anybody in this matter, I would make a special appeal for this House to ask the Minister to consider the men who left the Army in 1946.  These are the men&mdash;although it may not be taken generally&mdash;who helped to form this State in 1922, but they are forgotten men.  I would also agree with Senator Kissane that the men without whom nothing could be done are the men of the Old I.R.A.  I would agree with whatever Senator Kissane would say to help these men; but I am particularly concerned to appeal that these N.C.O.s and men be encompassed in any increase of pensions the Minister would be considering now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I make this final appeal to him.  I believe that the Minister is aware of the conditions existing in these cases. <Col N="1466" /> I will finalise myself on this by saying that, assuming a man joins the Army at the age of 18, he will complete his 21 years when he is 39 or 40.  An emergency occurs and he is retained in the service of the Army for six or more years.  He finds himself, at the age of 46 or 47, unsuited to the labour market.  These are the men I am appealing for.  These are the men with 14/- or 15/- a week.  Even though it be unusual, and even though the Department of Finance, which is closely associated with the Department of Defence, even though it may break down their peculiar barriers, give something to these men and forget the officers for a while it would be desirable.  I appeal to the Seanad to ask the Minister, and I appeal to the Minister, to consider these men because they are waiting to see what he is going to do for them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>I support the statements of the previous speakers and I know some of those men who were asked to leave the Army in 1946.  I am not speaking for the officers or for the brass-hats; I am talking about the rank-and-file members.  They went out on very small pensions at that time.  Mind you, the fact that they were in the Army was not such a great qualification for them when they were looking for jobs afterwards.  I know of cases where two of these men applied for a job.  They got the cold shoulder.  They were asked what army they had belonged to.  When they said it was the National Army, they did not get the job.  I can assure you that, if they said they had belonged to the English Army, they probably would have got the job.</P>
      <P>I agree with the last speaker that the Minister should consider the position of those men.  The present men, who are being catered for, are not in a very bad position at the moment.  They have been given a percentage increase which raises them far above the men I have in mind.  I appeal to the Minister to think of those men.  They are the men who stood in the gap of danger from 1922 until 1926.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very grateful <Col N="1467" /> for the manner in which this matter has been received.  The comments are helpful.  On the question raised by Senator Sheehy Skeffington in regard to the claim of those people in the ordnance survey, first of all, let me say that we train them in the art and craft of maps.  They did not remain with us for pensionable service. They were not entitled to anything. These vacancies arose and the posts were offered to them.  They could either accept or reject them.  Very properly and wisely, they accepted. They were very satisfied to get the appointments because they brought them into the Civil Service.  I do not know if there is a retiring age for them, but I presume it is 65 years, the same as it is in the rest of the Civil Service.</P>
      <P>What we propose to do under this scheme is to add this pension to their Civil Service pension when they get it, although we are not under any obligation to grant them a pension at all, because they had not reached pensionable service.  There are other soldiers who served 16½ and 17 years who will be going out and they will get nothing. They do not get any pension because they have not the qualifying service. That is the explanation.</P>
      <P>I think we are treating them rather generously and I take a poor view enough of the circular they sent round as if I were doing an injustice to them or the people who drafted the pensions scheme were doing an injustice to them.  That is not so.  This is a grant in regard to something to which they were not entitled under any scheme.</P>
      <P>With regard to the matter of increase, this is a system which has applied to the Army, the Guards and everybody attached to the Civil Service in regard to pay and pension.  When the Civil Service gets an increase in pay, automatically the percentage runs right through the whole system.  This scheme is only giving effect to what is already an established practice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>But tradition dies a very hard death and there is no reason why we should not change it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact that <Col N="1468" /> Senators have expressed an opinion that it should be changed is no harm at all to a Minister.  Indeed, it is of value to him because he can go back and say: &ldquo;This is what I was told when I proposed this.  The Senators take a poor view enough of it.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Very poor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I presumed that there was general agreement.  With regard to the questions raised by Senators Carton and Kissane, I do not think the Old I.R.A. should come in here.  God knows I have enough to deal with on this measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a headache.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think we need bother about the matter.  That will be another day's work.  I am aware of the difficulties and the hardships imposed on ex-servicemen of both periods.  Neither Government are unmindful of the service rendered to the State by the people who went out in 1946 when requested by the Government of the day.  I can assure the House that the whole question of the general revision of amounts payable to former N.C.O.s and men is still under consideration.  I have to plead guilty to this.  I had expectations that I would be in a position to say to Senator Carton and the organisation which represents the national ex-servicemen that I would be able to give an answer before this, but circumstances over which I have no control prevented me from doing so, but I can assure all concerned that the matter is under very active consideration, and that is a very good phrase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VictorCarton" hpid="Mr. Carton Mr. Carton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carton</NameTxt>
      <P>I heard it before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I mean it.  The matter is under active consideration at the moment, and, while I am not in a position to make an announcement in the matter at the moment, I hope I will be able to do so very, very soon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With regard to the question of the revision of smaller pensions, nobody will deny that pensions of 15/- or 16/- a week are completely out of keeping with the present-day value of money <Col N="1469" /> and increased cost of living, but, unfortunately, like everything else, that whole question for the Army is linked up with school teachers and civil servants.</P>
    <Speaker pid="VictorCarton" hpid="Mr. Carton Mr. Carton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carton</NameTxt>
      <P>Except, Sir, when you want them to die for you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>I know that is true, but the civil servants say they have to die also.  The whole matter is linked up with the wider question and if I were to get a decision on increasing Army pensions of 15/- or 16/-, then there would be good news for a great number of other people because school teachers and everybody else would be involved in the consideration on that big question.  I cannot move any faster than any member of the column to which I am now attached.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is not afraid of change?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="VictorCarton" hpid="Mr. Carton Mr. Carton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister will have to speed up the slowest vehicle in that column.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General MacEoin General MacEoin">
      <NameTxt>General MacEoin</NameTxt>
      <P>A sergeant-major has more opportunities to use both his voice and power than an officer has.  He can be more explicit and implicit in his language than an officer can and the sergeant-major knows that well.  The job of the commanding officer is to try to restrain the sergeant-major a little, if he can, but I am not trying to do that now.  I can assure the House of that.  The questions raised are important ones and I am fully aware of their importance and, if I might use the word, the equity of the claims made.  As I say, I can only move as fast as the rest.</P>
      <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local Government (Superannuation) Bill," RHead="1955&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Local Government (Superannuation) Bill, 1955&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following question:&mdash;&ldquo;That Section 10 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="RogerMcHugh" hpid="Dr. McHugh Dr. McHugh">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McHugh</NameTxt>
      <P>One point struck me since the adjournment in connection with the vexed question of Section <Col N="1470" /> 10, sub-section (1) paragraph (f). It refers to the words &ldquo;on which he absents himself from the place where he performs his duties under a local authority or refrains from performing those duties....&rdquo;  It has been brought to my notice that sometimes vocational teachers have deliberately absented themselves from performing certain duties which they hold are not really their duties, but which their senior officers hold are their duties.  To take a convenient example, sometimes in the vocational schools, extra lectures will be arranged for visiting lecturers, who sometimes have to display lantern slides or need attendance in some form or another.  On certain occasions vocational teachers have been ordered peremptorily to undertake looking after the lantern slides or handing round leaflets or other tasks which they consider are not, properly speaking, part of their duties, and they have deliberately absented themselves from those lectures and have incurred the displeasure of their senior officers.  It seems to me, therefore, that a certain injustice may be caused through varying conceptions of what in fact are the duties of certain local government officials.  I would urge the Minister again to reconsider this paragraph to eliminate the possibility of, say, a vocational teacher refusing to perform duties which he considers should not, properly speaking, be his and which in fact are not properly his duties, being penalised to the extent of losing 20 or 30 years of his pensionable service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. P. O'Donnell) Patrick O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. P. O'Donnell)</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the point made by Senator McHugh, if those are not the vocational officer's duties, then he is not absenting himself from the place where he performs them.  I think that is the very simple answer&mdash;that if they are not his duties, there is no obligation on him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RogerMcHugh" hpid="Dr. McHugh Dr. McHugh">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McHugh</NameTxt>
      <P>Supposing his senior officer says that they are part of his duties?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely there is a simple manner in which that can be decided.  When an officer is appointed, <Col N="1471" /> he is told what his duties are, that he has to teach certain subjects, and it will be very clearly laid down in his appointment what his duties are.  If he is asked to do something which is not part of his duties, he is not absenting himself from the place where they should be performed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>We still have not got a reply to the points raised on Section 10 last evening.  I was wondering had the Minister overlooked them.  He has not replied to the general debate, if I might say so, on Section 10.  He will recall that I accepted his assurance that paragraph (f) of sub-section (1) was designed to deal with individual discipline rather than group discipline, and I asked him to show us that by saying that he would appropriately amend that sub-section so as to exempt any action taken in support of a trade dispute.  The Minister probably has forgotten about that point, or overlooked replying to us, or giving us any assurance on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>As I pointed out to Senator Sheehy Skeffington the other day, I do not wish to use blackmail of any description on the House. If the Senator wishes the section so amended, and if this House wishes it so amended, I will consider the matter, but it must go back to the Dáil, and it means depriving those unfortunate people who will benefit by the Bill of one year's superannuation. If that is the wish of this House, I will accept it.  I am not in the least concerned.  I am not going to try to rush this Bill through the House.  I gave an undertaking that I would try to have the Bill enacted before 1st April, but I am in the hands of the Legislature, and if the House presses me to amend the section, I am completely in the hands of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I cannot accept that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot accept the second part of the Minister's statement at all, because he knows as well as I that if he were to amend it accordingly, <Col N="1472" /> it could be put through the Dáil with the consent of all Parties very quickly. I do not think there is great merit in his argument that that amendment would necessarily involve a year's delay.</P>
      <P>In regard to the first point, however, he may not know that the Seanad as such cannot amend this section along the lines I am asking, because of certain rulings.  We cannot put down amendments which would tend to increase any charge on the Exchequer, so that it is still back in his lap.  We cannot as a Seanad express an opinion because we cannot put down an amendment. I am only expressing my opinion, but I would like to see him, the Minister, put down an amendment, because I cannot do it myself and no other Senator can do it.  I do not know whether other Senators are of my opinion in this matter, that they also would like such an amendment.  I do not know how we can adequately express it to the Minister, except by getting up one after another and saying that we would like the Minister to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to see what I would describe as a change of heart on the part of the Minister in dealing with Section 10, which has been, I think, rightly, described in this House as a penal section.  There has been, in my opinion, a rather unrealistic discussion as to what should be done when workers belong to groups and when they do not, because when we pass legislation through the Oireachtas, we must always have the individual in mind, not whether he belongs to a group or does not.  The rights of the individual must be taken into account always.  Is it because a person belongs to a group or a certain organisation that he would be entitled to any more consideration than an individual who does not belong to any group or organisation? That is why I say that our approach to this matter has been on a somewhat erroneous basis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I had in mind those two words &ldquo;misconduct&rdquo; and &ldquo;unfitness&rdquo;.  In my opinion, the two words should not stand together at all, because, to my mind, at any rate, a person who would be said to be unfit is in an entirely <Col N="1473" /> different category from a person who would be said to be guilty of misconduct.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Misconduct or,&rdquo;&mdash;it is not &ldquo;and&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>But the two of them are subject to the same treatment by the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Not in regard to the refund of contributions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfitness is a greater fault than misconduct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>They are regarded as similar with regard to having their years of service calculated for pension purposes, and that is what I regard as a major consideration&mdash;wiping out the previous years for pension purposes. As I have said, I am glad the Minister has given consideration to the views of the Senators from the different sides of the House in regard to this matter. There should be no difficulty about having the Bill passed through the Oireachtas before 31st March, because we would be willing to give him all stages of the measure later this evening, giving him time meanwhile for the drafting of whatever amendment he considers necessary to cover the points made by Senators.  I think it could be done.  Where there is a will, many things can be done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamStanford" hpid="Professor Stanford Professor Stanford">
      <NameTxt>Professor Stanford</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to be one in the line who will, I hope, support Senator Murphy in this matter. I have been listening to the debate with care, and I have also watched the Minister with great care, and my impression is that he is beginning to see that perhaps what we are saying has justice behind it.  I agree with Senator Murphy and the others who put down an amendment to this clause that the term &ldquo;unfitness&rdquo; is dangerously vague. It could be used unfairly, in my opinion. Certainly, sub-section (f) seems to me too great a potential penalty for a possibly trivial offence.  I should say that possibly in the future the Minister might very greatly regret this clause if he leaves it in.  I can see its being very dangerously abused, and that people who will suffer under it may have a <Col N="1474" /> rankling sense of injustice fairly soon after it goes through.  I welcome Senator Kissane's suggestion that the House should allow the Bill through all its stages to-day, if the Minister would see his way to bringing forward a suitable amendment on Report Stage. I would urge him to consider it very seriously.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>One would imagine, to hear Senators speak, that this is some innovation, this &ldquo;penal clause&rdquo; as somebody has described it. I would remind Senator Kissane of the Local Government Act which was passed in 1941, and would particularly refer him to Section 25, sub-section (1) which deals with removal from office of an officer of a local authority.  I will give him the grounds on which an officer may be removed&mdash;sacked, in other words.  They are as follows&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>We know that that is there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>The section says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;For the purposes of this section the following shall be the statutory grounds for the removal of the holder of an office from such office, that is to say:&mdash;(a) unfitness of such holder for such office, (b) the fact that such holder has refused to obey or carry into effect any order lawfully given to him as the holder of such office, or has otherwise misconducted himself in such office ...&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is the law for the past 15 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg your pardon. Does it state there that all the years of service previous to that are to be wiped out for pension purposes?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a superannuation Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the point.  That is the fundamental issue between us. You are wiping out the previous years for pension purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the practice and is the law.  Supposing we inserted this particular clause, as the Senators suggest, it would not affect the Act of 1941.  It might affect a superannuation Bill, and it might <Col N="1475" /> affect some past superannuation, but it would not affect the existing law.  It has been suggested that this is something new.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>It is something new. There is no sub-section there in the 1941 Act that will deprive anybody of his pension rights, even if he is dismissed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the practice&mdash;that he was removed from office, otherwise sacked, and that is the law since 1941.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>That was 15 years ago. We are progressing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not amend it by amending this Bill.  Amending this Bill will not affect the grounds for removal from office of an officer under the 1941 Act.  That should be quite clear.  Somebody did mention last night that I may have overlooked this point, that this unfortunate person removed from office would forfeit all the contributions made by him.  That is not so at all.  I would refer Senators to Section 24 of the Bill which provides for the various circumstances in which contributions will be refunded and there will be no loss.  Section 24, sub-section (4) provides that:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Where a pensionable officer of a local authority having not less than ten years of pensionable local service ceases to hold his office for any cause other than misconduct, does not accept any other position service in which is capable of being reckoned under this Act and is not entitled to a lump sum and allowance under Section 15 of this Act or a marriage gratuity under Section 22 of this Act, the local authority shall return to him the contributions.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is, in the case of unfitness, the local authority is compelled to return the contributions.  Again, under sub-section (3) where a pensionable officer who has less than ten years of pensionable service ceases to hold office, for any cause other than misconduct, the local authority must return the contributions to him.  That makes it quite clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1476" /> It has been suggested to me that the House could give me all stages of the Bill this evening and that I should come back with an amendment on the Report Stage.  It must be remembered that, if we amend the Bill, it must also go back to the Dáil, which has two days more, one of which will be taken up entirely with the present Vote on Account, and I cannot visualise getting anything from the Dáil on Report Stage, if it is amended here.  If the House and Senator Kissane say that they are not particularly concerned whether we get it through&mdash;and I think Senator Murphy said something similar &mdash;if the House is not particularly concerned about passing the Bill through by 1st April, I do not mind.  I am willing to bow to the wishes of the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to correct one thing the Minister has just said.  I did not say that at all.  I said that we on this side of the House were anxious to have the Bill put through the Oireachtas before 31st March, and it is because I was anxious to have that done that I said that we would be prepared to pass all stages through this evening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to take any part in the debate on this section, though I am impressed by what was said by the various speakers.  I intervene purely for information because I am rather mystified about the extreme urgency of putting this Bill through.  I know that there are certain financial measures that have to be passed before the end of the financial year, otherwise the expenditure of money by the Exchequer becomes illegal.  I really want to know, because I have not quite followed the Minister's explanation, about the extreme urgency in having this Bill passed.  He says that he is not going to blackmail us into passing it, but, if we do not pass it, an awful lot of terrible consequences are going to fall on a great many innocent people.  It seems to me, if this is so, that we will have a moral obligation to rush the Bill through, even if we are not entirely satisfied with all its provisions.  I am asking in all innocence and with a desire to get information why that should be so.  I see that this Section <Col N="1477" /> 10 is in Part II of the Bill and I see in Section 4 that Part II of the Act shall come into operation on such day as the Minister by Order appoints for that purpose.  There is nothing there about 1st April.  Section 5 deals with Part III.  It is very complicated and it refers back to Local Government Acts.  I think probably that some of these Acts contain references to the 1st April as an important date in local government law.  I do not know.  I can see that possibility.  There may be something in Part III of this Bill which must be related to a year beginning on 1st April although, even in regard to that, I cannot see why an Act of the Oireachtas should not amend another Act of the Oireachtas.</P>
      <P>I should like to have explained why Part III should have to be passed next week before 31st March.  Whatever may be said about Part III, I cannot see why, when the Minister, under Section 4, can bring into operation Part II on any date he likes, we should be rushed in the discussion of Part II &mdash;which we are now discussing&mdash;under this threat of immediate and terrible war.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to make any threat at all.  I am merely trying to point out that if this Bill does not become law on 1st April then, if a road worker died or was killed in the course of his employment, for the next 12 months his widow cannot receive any death gratuity, because 1st April is the first day of the financial year and contributions will only be payable from the first day of the financial year.</P>
      <P>I have no urgency whatever with regard to this Bill, absolutely none. Let me make that clear.  I did not come here to steam-roll the Bill through the House, or anything else. I am not in the least concerned.  It is my duty to introduce the Bill.  I will not muzzle the House in any way.  If, as Senator O'Brien suggested, I am trying to stampede the House into passing the Bill, I will certainly withdraw. I have given the House an undertaking.  If they want me to, I will consider the matter.  That is all I can do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have heard the view expressed <Col N="1478" /> from different sides of the House that Senators are not particularly concerned as to when the Bill may come in.  You know the position.  Let it be clear.  I must go back to the Dáil.  I have to come back here&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is hardly fair to say that we are not anxious to have it done before 1st April.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Bill is amended here, you do not have to come back.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course I do.  I am trying to explain the procedure to Senators.  Far be it from me to explain to members of this House the procedure which they know much better than I do.  I have tried to budget for every available day of the Legislature and to have this Bill through, but I am not going to try to stampede the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry the Minister should have said he was not particularly anxious about getting this Bill through.  I know he is.  I believe he is as sympathetic and anxious to get this Bill through, for the sake of the people concerned, as any of us.  I am not very clear yet as to the reason why this first part is necessary, but the Minister says it is necessary and I must accept his word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am not prepared to risk the loss of the Bill, if the Minister assures the House that that will be the result, if the House insists on amending it at this stage.  I have no hesitation in saying that if this Bill came before us three or four weeks ago, we would all have done our best and I believe we would have succeeded in throwing out this sub-section.  However, I must take the Minister's word.  If he says very emphatically and very distinctly that our insistence on this amendment at this stage will mean that the people who are going to benefit&mdash;the road workers, the ordinary Part III people &mdash;will lose to the extent of one year's benefit, then I would not be a party to voting to have the amendment carried. However, I want it to be quite clear that that is the position&mdash;that the <Col N="1479" /> Minister would not in that case be in a position to have this Bill enacted before 1st April.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Mr. Kissane Mr. Kissane">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kissane</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no use in our trying to blow hot and cold on this measure.  At one time, we declare that it is desirable to have the Bill passed with the greatest possible speed and at another time we fall back and say that we have plenty of time to consider it.  I want to make my position clear.  I want to have this measure passed through the Seanad so that it will become law by 1st April. I can see no valid reason whatever why that cannot be done in the circumstances of the case.</P>
      <P>The Minister has just referred to the procedure as between Dáil and Seanad.  What happens?  When amendments are sent back to the Dáil, they are the first business to be considered on the first occasion the Dáil meets.  I want to impress that on Senators.  When amendments go back from the Seanad to the Dáil, no matter what other business has been ordered for the Dáil&mdash;I know this from experience&mdash;on the first day it meets, the first business to be considered is the amendments that come from the Seanad.  Therefore, there should be no difficulty whatever in getting this measure through before 1st April.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said that they would have to go back again to the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I go to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Dáil agrees to them, that finishes it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I will make it very simple, with the permission of the Chair.  Suppose we decide this evening that I will consider amendments.  I have to consider them; I have to consult my colleagues in the Cabinet; I have to come back here on the first day on which the House sits, namely, Wednesday next; I have to come back here with the amendments, if any. Senator Kissane is quite right.  I can <Col N="1480" /> go back to the Dáil on Thursday of next week.  We were told to-day it was doubtful whether the Dáil would sit on Thursday of next week.  I have to go back with the Bill, as amended.  I have no guarantee that the Dáil will accept this amendment.  I have no guarantee that they will not discuss it for a couple of days.</P>
      <P>In order to facilitate the passage of this Bill, I collected every possible group of political Parties I could find and consulted with them between the Second Reading and the Committee Stage of the Bill in the other House. Actually, I consulted some Senators. I let it be known that if any group wished to consult me, they could do so and I must say that the groups of all political Parties consulted me.  Some of their wishes I was able to meet; others I could not.  It was in order to shorten, if at all possible, discussion in the Lower House that I did that.  I must say that I got magnificent cooperation when it came to the Committee Stage of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that, arising out of what Senator Kissane has said, there will be time for us to meet next Wednesday, as we shall be meeting in any event, and to accept the amendments which the Minister will put before us along the lines suggested now, and to have those amendments before the Dáil in time for the Bill to go through before 1st April.</P>
      <P>When I asked the Minister, together with some other Senators, in April of last year, whether he hoped to be able to introduce such a Bill quickly, he said he hoped that he would be able to do so, and he did introduce the Bill before the summer recess of that year. The Second Stage of the Bill was not reached, however, in the Dáil, until December.  That represented a considerable lapse of time, though I do not blame the Minister for it.  The Bill did not, however, reach this House until March and I do not feel that it is quite fair to us to tell us now that we are going to lose a whole year, unless we pass it quickly and accept it without amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As most of us consider that the Bill <Col N="1481" /> contains at least one serious injustice, I would rather not give the Bill to the Minister now, and, if necessary, I would take the unpleasant step of waiting for a year in order to get a Bill from which that serious injustice has been removed, rather than that, in our rush to get the Bill quickly, we should allow it to go through with that injustice enshrined in it for many long years ahead, and not merely for one year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>We have reached the stage in the discussion of this section where the Minister is convinced of the justice of the claims made by the speakers on both sides of the House and he has now departed from the stand which he made first in defence of the section.  He has now tried to suggest that the powers already exist for the Minister and local authorities to deal with officers in their employment whom they wish to dismiss for one reason or another.  The main speakers in the debate have expressed a desire to have this section amended.  No member of this House can amend the Bill, unless the Minister introduces an amendment.  He has now reached the stage when he sees the justification of the demand of the House and he reacts by bringing in a new threat.</P>
      <P>The first line of his defence in that threat is the urgency of the measure. Let us examine what the urgency is. He expects to have the Bill in operation on 1st April.  A few moments ago, he suggested that if a road worker died after 1st April, his widow would not be entitled to the death allowance, because the Bill had not been passed. One would imagine from what he said that every servant of a local authority would be covered by the Bill on 1st April.  Last night, we had from the Minister a statement that very few local authorities in Ireland had yet given effect to the measure of 1948.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I said no such thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>He pointed out to Senator Hickey that even Cork County Council, the largest county council in Ireland, had not yet given effect to the provisions of the 1948 Act.  How then <Col N="1482" /> can the Minister substantiate his statement that, if this Bill has not gone through the House by 1st April, the widow of a road worker will not be entitled to the benefits?  This statement from the Minister is a threat that, if the House insists on its rights and amends the Bill, it will hold it up. Every Minister who has come into this House, no matter to what Government he belonged, has said that every Bill is an urgent Bill.  I do not blame them for that, but we, on this side of the House, went as far as we could be expected to go and made a very generous offer.  If the Minister is now prepared to introduce an amendment, we would be prepared to meet to-morrow in order to facilitate the early passage of the Bill and to have it in operation by 1st April.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I owe an apology to the House and to Senator Sheehy Skeffington.  I did give an undertaking in the month of April of last year that I would endeavour to have the Bill introduced before the summer recess and that I did.  Nothing further was heard of the Bill until just before Christmas, but the circumstances were peculiar and tragic.  My Parliamentary Secretary, the late Deputy Davin, was responsible for the initial drafting of the Bill and was most anxious to continue the drafting of it. Despite the fact that I knew of his physical condition, I did not wish to depress him in any way by taking out of his hands the drafting of the Bill or by seeking another Parliamentary Secretary.  I know that the late Deputy Davin had his heart and soul in the Bill and he deserves the credit for what the Bill contains.  I only took it up at a later stage.</P>
      <P>Let me say at the outset that I am not convinced by the arguments of the Senators that I should amend the section but if the Seanad wishes me to consider the amendments, I am prepared to go back and consider them. I have certain commitments in this matter.  I would have to consult my colleagues, provided I was satisfied that the amendment was necessary, and then I would have to come back here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Hawkins was right in pointing out that all local authorities did <Col N="1483" /> not adopt the Act of 1948, but this Bill will bring in many more beneficial widows than the Act of 1948 and it is for those unfortunates that I am trying to provide.  I should not like it to be thought for one moment that I had any personal interest in trying to stampede the House.  I have not. Every available legislative week since the Christmas recess has been occupied by me with this Bill.  I have got it before this House at the very first available opportunity on which I could. As I said at the outset, I apologise for the delay, but I am sure the House will sympathise with me in the circumstances in which it occurred.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is clear now that the feeling of the House is that sub-section (f) should be suitably amended.  The Minister earlier on said that, if it was the desire of the Seanad, he would undertake to examine suitable amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is as far as he went and I rather thought that Senators who assumed that he was satisfied that an amendment was necessary took too much for granted.  I think that is as far as we can press the Minister at this particular stage, provided we are all very clear as to what the position is and, that is that, between now and the Report Stage, the Minister being satisfied as to the views of the Seanad, will consider appropriately amending sub-section (f).</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 11 to 14, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 15.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 15 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>This is another section that contains an objectionable provision.  I feel that the sting has been taken out of it, in view of the position that has been reached now. Otherwise, I would certainly have a good deal more to say on this and perhaps on some other sections.  I do want to point out to the Minister <Col N="1484" /> that this also means that a pensioner's allowance may be reduced because of the necessity for a certificate that he has served with diligence and fidelity during his whole term of office.  That is an unusual provision in pension schemes that I have any knowledge of and, again, it is something in the nature of a threat to hold over a man's head, that he may be deprived of some of his pension, unless he gets this certificate.</P>
      <P>I imagine that if a man serves during the period of 30 or 40 years that he is retained in the service, it ought to be assumed that he has served with diligence and fidelity.  I do not see why it should be questioned at the end of his long service.  I do not know the significance of the word &ldquo;fidelity&rdquo; there, but it should not be questioned that he has done his ordinary day's work and he certainly should not have this threat hanging over him because it can be used as a threat by his superiors.  In a way it is humiliating that that should be hanging over him and that he should be waiting to get this certificate at the end of his career. Unless there is a file kept of his service, I do not know how the superior officer could, say, at the end of 40 years, be in a position to say that the officer always served during the whole 40 years with diligence and fidelity.  I do not want to dwell on it, but the objection is obvious.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>Are the words really necessary?  It could be &ldquo;to their satisfaction&rdquo; without putting in &ldquo;with diligence and fidelity&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Does it ever happen?  My experience in public life is not as long as that of some of the members here, but it goes over almost a quarter of a century, and I have never heard of any public servant, who was being pensioned, not getting his full service, with a request for added years as well.  I wonder is it only a precaution&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that the Minister must take in the case of a person who misbehaves himself grossly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not an innovation at all, as Senator O'Connell has <Col N="1485" /> pointed out.  The provision is the very same as in the 1948 Act.  The wording is the very same as in the 1948 Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I was speaking of other teachers' pensions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Unfortunately, the Senator is inclined to look at it only from the vocational teachers' point of view.  There are many more employees.  They are only a very small proportion of the employees of local authorities.  Under the Local Government Act, 1925, while it was mandatory on the local authority to grant a pension, there was a proviso and they could, at their discretion, grant the pension, subject to a maximum of two-thirds of the salary.  The local authority themselves had that discretion under the 1925 Act.  The wording of this present Bill is the very same as the Act of 1948.  In my opinion, the principal effect of this is merely a deterrent and is not a practical effect at all.  Another reason &mdash;if we had not got this, a man could be sacked without pension or given full pension.  We may have a line-ball case.  This is to give the man who is the line-ball case an opportunity of qualifying for a pension and, at the same time, it will ensure that the servant or officer will do his duty diligently and faithfully.  Is there anything wrong in that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>If he does not, he should not be employed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>That is just the point, but I am trying to protect them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Some of them do not and are still employed and getting away with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Your responsibility, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>No matter what profession we are in, we are expected to do our work diligently and faithfully. We are expected to do that, and, if we do not, then we should be penalised in some way.  It is just like the old story.  People object to being bound to the peace.  We are all bound to the peace.  We are all bound to keep within the law and if that little <Col N="1486" /> extra burden is thrown on us to give us an extra penalty for not obeying the law, we cannot object.  I think it is quite clear.  If a man does his job diligently and faithfully, he is entitled to full pension and, if he does not, he is entitled to have something deducted from it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 16.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 16 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>On Second Reading, I dwelt at some length on this point, that many officers will never get the maximum allowance, or the maximum lump sum in any case, which is provided for in this Bill.  As I explained, 45 years' service is necessary before the full lump sum can be obtained.  In the case I mentioned, the minimum age at entry is 21 and many officers do not enter until much later than that.  I do not want to go into that again at this stage, but I want to ask the Minister what is the provision in a case of that kind, under Section 13?  Section 13 is the section that deals with added years, but, as far as I can see, it would not be of much benefit.  It says that in no case can they give a greater service than 40 years.  So, I am afraid it would not be much good as far as the lump sum is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>It is in the case of professional service that added years would be given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>The body I mentioned specially was the vocational teachers. Is their service regarded as professional service?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesHickey" hpid="Mr. Hickey Mr. Hickey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hickey</NameTxt>
      <P>Are they covered by the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>They are covered by the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 13 would not benefit that particular body?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>We will have to leave it so.  We are quite sure that no <Col N="1487" /> member of that particular body can ever get a full maximum?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to go into details with the Senator, but suppose a man is a metal-work teacher and is not employed until he is 35 by the local authority, he has been employed by somebody up to then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed that the minimum age of entrants for vocational teaching is 21.  Therefore, he cannot make the 45 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>He goes very near it and somebody else may amend the Act.  I hope this will not be the last amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>There will be a lot to be amended.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 17.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 17 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should just like to make the point in relation to Section 17 which could also be made in relation to Section 22, that it seems unjust, in counting a person's pension rights, to exclude a period for which work was actually done.  It seems to me that the Minister is being a little unfair in being prepared to exclude any odd fraction of a whole year, to &ldquo;disregard&rdquo; it in the total, although it might represent work honestly done and service really given.  I would ask the Minister, as I understand he is considering possible amendments, whether he might not be prepared to accept such amendments as were put down by Senator Hawkins and myself &mdash;and, I think, by one other Senator&mdash; in regard to counting a person's service for what it really is, and not to &ldquo;disregard&rdquo; what might perhaps be a large fraction of a year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to join with the previous speaker in urging that point of view on the Minister.  I had an amendment down to the section, which was ruled out of order.  I think the last speaker has made a very good case and that the Minister should consider <Col N="1488" /> it between now and Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will support that, and I would say it is usual in superannuation schemes to allow for that type of <i>pro rata</i> service.  To simply say that, if a man has served a day short of the 364, he shall not benefit, seems to me to be a monstrous injustice. I think it is only right and proper that the pro rata service should be counted in.  The Minister may say that that would create some difficulty, but there is really no difficulty because this sort of calculation is all done by machines nowadays.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is notable for the fact that it marks a departure to some extent in a liberal direction from the policy of the 1948 Act and the method of dealing with odd fractions in dealing with years of service in calculating pensions and allowances in that case.  I would also refer the Senator to Section 12 of the Bill which provides that:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;the pensionable local service of a pensionable officer at any time shall be the period or the aggregate of the periods which under this part of this Act he is entitled at that time to reckon as service,&rdquo;</P>
      <P>and in that way odd fractions are reckonable.  It is a fairly liberal departure from the 1948 Act.  As I said a few moments ago, I feel confident that this will not be the last superannuation Bill which will be introduced, and as we go along we may become more liberal.  I certainly think I have dealt with the matter much more liberally than it was dealt with in the 1948 Act. I do ask the Senators not to press the point at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to ask on that point, are these fractions allowed only if, when they are put together, they make up a complete year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, or three-quarters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>Because it is only a complete year that counts, but you can use as many fractions as you have to make a complete year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, or three-quarters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1489" />
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>No, not three-quarters, because when you are calculating the pension, it is calculated by multiplying the number of complete years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I will refer the Senator to Section 13 (g) which says:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;where the aggregate service of the officer amounted to a number of completed years and a fraction of a year exceeding three-quarters.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>That counts as a year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>That refers to additions to pension for local officers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, and that is what we are dealing with under this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>No; we are dealing in this section surely with the pension to which the man has a right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing with Section 17.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>That deals with pensionable officers.  I do not see where the connection is with Section 13 (g) at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>If the case the Minister has made is in reference to Section 13, what is the purpose of Section 17?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 13 covers the calculation of all pension rights under Section 17; that is the connection.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 18 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not opposing the section now as I have already referred to the point I wish to raise.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 19 to 22, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 23.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 23 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1490" />
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the section which provides for the contribution. This contribution, as I pointed out on the Second Reading, is not, strictly speaking, a contribution; it is a deduction from the officer's salary, and to the extent that it is a deduction, it goes to relieve the rates.  I want to point out&mdash;and the Minister will pardon me for saying this as it can only have effect on an amending Bill later&mdash; that the finances of this are peculiar. The deductions that are made now help the rates or the Government for the time being, but in 40 years' time the whole effect of the load will fall on the generation then living.  It may not concern us then.</P>
      <P>Perhaps I can illustrate that better by giving an example.  A man enters the service now at, say, 20 years of age and his deductions of 5 per cent., we take it, are used to help the rates and so on, year after year.  In 40 years he retires and whatever local authority is there at that time will then have to bear the whole burden of the pension and allowances.  That is why, in superannuation schemes, usually there is a fund into which the money is put and allowed to accumulate all the time, so that when a man's pension is due it can be drawn from that fund.  I do not want to dwell on that now&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Senator would move the Adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been suggested that it might only take some ten or 20 minutes to finish this Bill and that we should continue and then adjourn until next sitting day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RogerMcHugh" hpid="Dr. McHugh Dr. McHugh">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McHugh</NameTxt>
      <P>We agree, if that suits the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think there is much more of a contentious nature to discuss.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is agreed that the House will continue on this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to the point raised by Senator O'Connell, I fail to see the difference in paying out 5 per cent. of the salary and retaining 95 per cent. or to reverse the procedure, instead of receiving 100 per <Col N="1491" /> cent of your salary, getting 95 per cent. I see no difference between that and receiving 100 per cent. and contributing 5 per cent.  It is a deduction, if you wish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I was only trying to point out the difference between having a fund specially kept from which pensions could be paid, and doing it in this particular way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Suppose you had a fund, I wonder what would be the value of the money in 20 or 30 years' time?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>That consideration will be there anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I would support Senator O'Connell as regards the wisdom of funding such money rather than piling up the eventual payments to be made out of the rates.  In these days, when we advocate saving as much as possible, there is a good deal to be said in favour of this money which is deducted from salaries and wages being funded together with similar contributions from the local authority, and it could even be borrowed by the local authority for the building of houses in the same way as certain superannuation funds are borrowed by other authorities.  The, money is refunded, and out of the fund, investments are made in Government loans, or E.S.B. loans, or loans of that kind for the development of this country.  I think there is a good deal of wisdom in that sort of procedure, in these days particularly. However, we cannot do anything about it now, except express our point of view to the Minister.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 24 to 29, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 30.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 30 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The House will probably appreciate the fact that there are probably more people employed by local authorities on road work than in any <Col N="1492" /> other type of employment, and the Minister is well aware that a great number of able bodied men in the undeveloped areas around the western seaboard are depending to a large extent on road work for a livelihood for themselves and their dependents.  That road work fluctuates considerably, owing to the system of county road improvement grants, where certain roads are to be made up.  Where certain main road improvement grants are involved, the Department suggests that a particular stretch of road should be made up and this means that there may be a considerable amount of employment in one area and not a great deal of employment in an adjoining area in the same surveyor's district.  Consequently, many workers in one area may have only about 150 service days in the year as against 300 days for other road workers because it was considered necessary to make up roads in their particular district.</P>
      <P>Consequently, it seems to be inequitable that each year should have to stand or fall on its own legs or, in other words, that the road worker must have 200 service days in each year, before that particular year can be reckoned for pensionable purposes. While a road worker may not be employed, he is drawing unemployment benefit, because he is available and willing to work, and that employment benefit is a source of maintenance for himself and his family during that period, and it arises therefore out of his employment.  If he had not worked for the local authority, he would not have the stamps which would justify him in drawing that employment benefit.  Considering this fact&mdash;that there is a considerable amount of road work which is admitted by the local authority not to be local authority work as such, in the sense that the local authority acts only as agents for the Board of Works&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Those days do not count.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I say&mdash; those days do not count.  The road worker does not appreciate what the Minister and I appreciate, that he is not going to qualify in respect of those <Col N="1493" /> days, despite the fact that he is employed on the type of work which he feels should entitle him to qualify for the 200 days' period set out.  I presume the same would apply, possibly, in connection with E.S.B. grants.  The Minister will be able to tell whether the E.S.B., which has a grant out of a particular fund to provide employment during the winter months where the employees are recruited from a list supplied&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not count, either.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Those days are a considerable number of the days in the year, and, if those are not to be counted, it would be difficult for people in those western areas to have a sufficient number of days in each year to qualify.  I would ask the Minister, therefore, to consider sympathetically reckoning it over a period of years, two or three years, rather than on each year because it is obvious that there will be years when that road work would easily make up 250 days and the minimum total number of working days set out is 200.  That is two-thirds of the year, and in view of what the Minister states&mdash;that these other employments coming out of this particular grant, are not to be reckoned&mdash;then it will be difficult for these men to qualify in each particular year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator appears to overlook the fact that the Bill merely provides for pensions for permanent employees of local authorities and I have gone as far as I could possibly go by defining permanent employee as one who has 200 service days in a year.  First of all, the 200 days' rule is a basic principle in Part III of the Bill and it is not practicable to depart from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The amendment which the Senator had tabled would, in any case, only apply to local authorities who have not adopted Part III of the 1948 Act, such as Cork.  In such cases, the amendment suggested by the Senator would enable a person to have his name entered on the register of pensionable servants, if in either of the two years preceding the date of the coming into <Col N="1494" /> operation of Part III, he had 200 or more service days.  In the Bill, he may have 200 service days in the year preceding the coming into operation of Part III.  In any other case, the average would make no difference.  He may have had over 200 days' service in the first year and over 200 in the second year, or he may have had over 200 in the first year and less than 200 in the second year, or he may have had less than 200 in the first year and more than 200 in the second year, and these are the only three sets of circumstances arising.  In the case of the first and second, his name is entered at the end of the first year and, in the case of the third, at the end of the second year.</P>
    <P>Taking an average of two years makes no difference in any of the three cases.  It is a basic principle, the 200 days, and it applies to permanent employees.  I know the type of person that Senator Walsh is worried about. He is worried about the type of worker who may have 250 days this year and 150 the next.  In my opinion, those workers are not permanent employees, because, once a road is made up, it takes five or six years before you need come back to it and consequently it will be five or six years before there will be employment in that locality again.</P>
    <P>This Bill is not designed for that type of worker.  It is designed for the permanent road workers, some of whom are known as &ldquo;surface-men&rdquo;, while others may be mobile workers who go from place to place around the entire district.  I think the Senator will agree it would be ridiculous to suggest that first of all we should give relief work for minor employment schemes to relieve unemployment and then make the relief work pensionable. If we have a patch of unemployment in a certain area, the Government gives a grant to employ men there during winter months.</P>
    <P>The Senator suggests that not only should we pay the men, but we should make them pensionable.  He says they are doing road work, of course.</P>
    <P>Let me give an illustration.  Supposing the Senator employs a gardener, but he has not got full-time <Col N="1495" /> employment for him and a neighbour up the street also employs the same gardener part-time, would it not be unfair to ask the Senator to pension that man simply because he is doing some work for the Senator's neighbour up the street?  I think it would be very, very unfair.  The man would not be, after all, a permanent employee of the Senator's.  He would be employed jointly by two different people and it would be unfair to ask one to pension him.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Supposing a county council is carrying out road work and a particular employee is employed by the county council for that purpose&mdash; we will keep it to roads&mdash;for 150 days; the money provided for that work is raised by the county council on the rates and these 150 days will be taken into consideration in calculating the 200 days.  Now, supposing that, for the remaining 50 days, he is still in the employment of the county council &mdash;and he is, as far as he is concerned &mdash;but is engaged on minor relief schemes, or works carried out by the county council on behalf of the Office of Public Works, he is paid out of moneys provided by way of minor relief schemes grants, or perhaps moneys provided by the Tourist Board, or by any body which may make a grant to the county council for the carrying out of particular works. That employee continues in the employment of the county council; the work is carried out by the same person; he is under the supervision of the same ganger; and he is paid from the same office of the county council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>But not out of the same fund.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Not out of the same fund but, as far as the individual worker is concerned, he is not interested as to where the money comes from; all he is interested in is the fact that he is in the employment of the same employer.  He is under the same ganger.  The general road work has been completed and he is transferred to some other type of work for 25 or 50 days, and, because he is one <Col N="1496" /> of the people chosen to continue working, he should have the right to be considered as registered under this scheme.  Remember, the number affected may be very few.  I do not think they would be anything like the numbers Senator Walsh had in mind. Now, in cases like that, I think a grave hardship would be inflicted on the people concerned.  Once they are in the employment of the local authority and the local authority adopts a scheme, irrespective of the work on which they are engaged and irrespective of where the money comes from, the number of days they are employed should be taken into consideration for the purposes of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>All I can say in reply is that, when they are employed on minor relief schemes, they are employed by the Special Employment Schemes Office; in other words, they are paid out of Central Funds.  Does Senator Hawkins suggest that the ratepayers in Galway or Donegal should superannuate employees of the State? Is that the suggestion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The employee would be contributing as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>And who else?  We all know what the burdens are to-day on the ratepayers.  Is it suggested now that the ratepayers in County Donegal should be mulcted to the extent of paying a contribution towards men who are employed by the State?  That is the suggestion that has been made.  I think we are being very generous in providing that an employee who is employed for 200 service days is entitled to a pension.  The Senators go further and say: &ldquo;That is all right. Give him the 200 days; that is reasonable.&rdquo; But the State may employ him for 150 days and the local authority for only 50 days.  Is the Senator's suggestion that the ratepayers should pay his contribution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  The Minister is trying to create a difficulty where no practical difficulty exists.  In the carrying out of works of the kind to which I have referred, a sum of money is made available to the local authority and that sum of money is provided to cover <Col N="1497" /> all works and expenditure in connection with a particular scheme.  Surely the proposition is not such a difficult one as the Minister suggests?  Could not whatever sum is involved in the paying of the contribution on behalf of the local authority be considered as part of the sum of money expended on the particular works?  The local authority is asked to carry out particular works on behalf of the Board of Works. During the emergency, for instance, they were charged with the responsibility of producing turf.  The county engineers were the persons in charge and there was a sum of money made available from the Central Fund to each local authority in respect of the carrying out of this work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>That is quite in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any difficulty in making provision, when certain works are to be carried out, for a specific sum, that in the drawing up of the estimates it should be taken into consideration that the men about to be employed on those works would be entitled, if they were continued in the employment of the local authority, to some small payment?  It would be a very small amount and even if the rates had to bear it, it would not be a great burden as the Minister suggests. We must consider the position of the worker who continues in the employment of the local authority doing certain work and being under the misapprehension that he is still entitled to benefit under the scheme, whereas, if he died even after 1st April of next year, probably, his wife and family would find out that, because on 31st March the county council transferred him to works under minor relief schemes or something else, they would not be entitled to benefit as they would have been had he died, say, on 2nd February, when, on behalf of the local authority, he was carrying out the work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>There would be no deduction for his contribution, if he was employed on minor relief schemes and he would know that by his pay packet.  We have already passed Section 2 of this Bill which defines what a <Col N="1498" /> service day is.  Section 2 states that:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;&lsquo;service day&rsquo; means:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) a day on which the servant worked in a wholetime capacity for one or more than one local authority, the work not being work (other than work in a supervisory capacity or work calling for special experience or skill which is not given to him by reference to the provision of employment for him or the relief of his distress) on any work or scheme of works the expenses of which are in whole or in part met from moneys provided by the Oireachtas for the relief of distress.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Having passed that section, there is nothing further I can say about it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 31 to 39, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 40.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>My amendment No. 14, to insert a new section before Section 45, refers to Sections 40, 41 and 44 and, with your permission, I will discuss those sections on the amendment. It refers to these three sections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Because it is in reference to the question of a death gratuity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I suppose we can permit the Senator to argue it, but the Senator will recognise that it is put down in the wrong place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>It was necessary to cover all three sections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We will permit the Senator to move it before Section 40.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 14:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before Section 45 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>( ) Notwithstanding anything contained to the contrary in Sections 40, 41 and 44 or any other part of this Act, a gratuity, in such cases where the sum does not exceed £300, shall be paid without production of grant of probate or administration to the <Col N="1499" /> widow of a deceased pensionable servant, in trust for herself and her family (if any) in accordance with law, or in the case where the deceased servant is a widower, then to his family equally.</P>
    <P>Under this Bill, before a death gratuity can be granted, it must be paid to the legal personal representative and I assume the legal personal representative is the person to whom grant of probate or administration has been issued.  Section 44 (2) states:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Where a pensionable servant of a local authority who has less than one year of pensionable local service dies, the local authority shall return the contributions to his legal personal representative.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I assume from that that the amount that would be paid would be a very insignificant sum.  It may be only a matter of a few pounds, but the cost of extraction of probate or administration would be approximately £11 or £12.  The cost involved might be greater than the actual amount the widow or the next of kin would be entitled to receive.  In the Post Office Savings Act of 1920, under Statutory Rules and Orders, No. 1532, it is provided that in the case of a deceased depositor, when the amount is under £100, the Minister may pay the amount to a person who has paid the funeral expenses or to his next of kin.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator quoting the full regulations?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Those are the regulations I have obtained from the solicitor to the Department.  The value of money in 1921 as compared with to-day was possibly three times as great and, consequently, I suggest it is not unreasonable to ask the Minister to agree that local authorities may make payment to the widow or to the family of a deceased pensionable servant where the amount does not exceed £300, without the necessity of going to the expense of taking out this grant.  The average pensionable servant is a person who is not a property owner. He is usually a road worker whose average weekly earnings would be approximately £5.  It would possibly <Col N="1500" /> be unnecessary for that person to have to go to the trouble and expense of taking out a grant of administration, if it was for the purpose of receiving his gratuity from the local authority and I consider that the local authority, with the permission of the Minister, should be empowered at its discretion to pay out that amount in such a case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am really surprised at Senator Walsh, who is a very well-known and practical lawyer, making this suggestion.  First of all, he made the suggestion that the cost of the administration might exceed the amount which will be payable.  Did I understand him to say that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would refer the Senator to the appropriate section in Part VI of the Bill which provides that, where it is less than £100, it can be paid out without a grant.  If the Senator had read the Bill, he would have seen that it sets out at Section 61 (e):&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;If the recipient or the officer or servant in respect of whom the grant is payable has died and a sum not exceeding £100 is due on account of the grant, probate or other proof of title of the personal representatives of the deceased may, if the local authority so think fit, be dispensed with and the sum may be paid or distributed to or among the persons appearing to the local authority to be beneficially entitled to the personal estate of the deceased, or to or among any one or more of those persons, or, in the case of the illegitimacy of the deceased, to or among such persons as the local authority think fit, and the local authority and any of their officers making the payment shall be discharged from all liability as respects any such payment or distribution;&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Surely that is what the Senator wants?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>£300 is the amount.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>He could first of all raise the £100.  We are doing exactly what is done under the Post Office Savings Act of 1920.  The Senator asks me to go further.  He asks me <Col N="1501" /> to amend the law governing wills in this country.  Supposing a workman has left a wife and family.  Supposing he may have some person dearer to him, and supposing he decides, by will, to leave his estate to that other person.  The Senator wants me to cut across the statute law of this country and say, irrespective of what the deceased wished to do in his will, that the local authority must pay this over to the widow and the children.  When the Senator considers that point&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I have considered it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I can see his colleagues' look of consternation that a member of their profession should suggest that we should disregard <i>in toto</i> the wishes of a testator or testatrix, as the case may be.  I have known cases in this country where wills have been disputed, and such cases are not unknown to the Senator.  These cases are fought very vigorously, and the principal test which a judge and jury applies to the validity and capacity of a will is: was the testator of sound mind, memory and understanding; did he make his will in the presence of two witnesses; and were they both present at the same time as the testator when the will was signed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Those are very solemn proofs, but the Senator wants me, by a section of a Superannuation Act, to cut completely across that and to say, irrespective of all that, irrespective of what the testator wanted, and irrespective of the solemnity of the occasion: &ldquo;You must not carry out the request of a man who earned his money; you must ignore that, and you must give it to the widow and to the children.&rdquo;  The widow may be an imbecile; she may be a person who is not capable of properly looking after or knowing the value of money.  The Senator is not unaware of such cases.  Let us not forget that any person in this country, where the estate is under £500, may approach the local customs and excise officer and, for a sum not exceeding £1, command the local customs and excise officer to extract a grant of administration. While that particular cheap method of law&mdash;with which I do not agree&mdash;is available, I do not think <Col N="1502" /> there is any necessity for amending the section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister briefly referred in the other House to this question of the local customs and excise officer extracting a grant of administration.  But I would like to point out that the number of excise officers in the country has been very much reduced in recent years.  I understand that, whereas there are approximately three excise officers in my county at present, there used to be eight or nine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>The solicitors are wiping them out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is well aware that there is no excise officer between Burtonport and Letterkenny, a distance of 40 or 50 miles.  He does not surely suggest that the unfortunate widow should walk into Dungloe to get a bus to Letterkenny, spend all day in the bus, and find that the excise officer was absent.  Or, if he were present, how is she going to get the necessary two sureties to obtain that grant?  In other words, it is practically unheard of now for any person to approach an excise officer in such a way.  In the village in which I live, there is no excise officer for a very considerable distance.</P>
      <P>The object of this gratuity was to provide for a widow and the family.  If that was the purpose which the Minister had in mind when he drafted this Bill&mdash;that it was intended for these dependents&mdash;surely it is not unreasonable that those people should now benefit.  It is not such a long time since legislation passed through this House to enable a widow, where there was intestacy, to get £4,000 instead of the previous £500 which the Intestacy Act provided.  When this matter was discussed in the other House, there was no reference whatever to Section 62, or to the fact that a local authority may pay, when the amount is under £100.  It is because of the discussion that took place in the other House that I brought this amendment at this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to delay this matter any longer. <Col N="1503" /> The only thing I would like to point out is that servants and officers of local authorities are not illiterate.  If they want to consult a solicitor, they do not go to his office on the day he is not in.  They do not travel six or seven miles.  They now write out their instructions and send it to their solicitor, or else ring him up and find out if he is in.  Having done that, they go on the day he is in.  It is not necessary to travel from Burtonport to Letterkenny to extract a grant of administration.  All that is necessary is to write and tell the customs officer what you want done.  He will send you a questionnaire by return, which you complete.  He will then send you a form, you walk into your next door neighbour&mdash;in every village there are commissioners for oaths&mdash;you swear the documents with your two sureties and you send them back to the customs and excise officer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that that is the procedure?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>Is he aware of that personally?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, I am. I blame the legal profession for not making this known.  It is a disgrace to them that they have not made it known.  I am going to ensure that the servants know about it because every local authority will receive from my Department a circular requesting them to inform servants that they have this legal right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I understood that we were to have finished this in 20 minutes, and that we would then adjourn for tea. I gather from the things that have been said&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is hardly a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>What was the decision?  I am afraid it was put in such a form to the House that some members are not sure whether we have decided to drop the whole of the rest of the agenda, or whether we are going <Col N="1504" /> to continue until we finish this, and then simply adjourn for tea.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>The proposal is to finish this Bill and then to adjourn until next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I may have been rather dense, but I did not understand that.  Had I understood it I should not have accepted it without protest.  We were told earlier that there would at least be an attempt made to get through the agenda.  I would be for adjourning only at ten o'clock in the ordinary way, even if we did not quite finish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>Some members have already left the House on that understanding.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>It was put before the House in a way that I for one did not understand, and I think I can claim that other Senators did not understand that either.  We understood that further consideration of this Bill would be deferred to the next meeting, but not everything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RogerMcHugh" hpid="Dr. McHugh Dr. McHugh">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McHugh</NameTxt>
      <P>There has been some misunderstanding about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdwardMcGuire" hpid="Mr. McGuire Mr. McGuire">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGuire</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the front bench on the other side understood there was to be this adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>It looks from the number in the House that quite a number understood this would complete the business for to-night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That was communicated to me outside the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to cause any embarrassment at this juncture, but we have only reached Section 40, and there are 71 sections and there are also some amendments to come.  I do not know how long it is likely to take, but perhaps some adjournment, even of a momentary character, might be welcome at this stage.  I do not see the rest of this going through within even an hour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The House apparently made an agreement to continue <Col N="1505" /> until it concluded this stage of the measure and not to adjourn for tea.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I am right in recalling that Senator Hawkins, in making the statement, uttered the hope that we would be able to finish &ldquo;in twenty minutes.&rdquo;  That was about 6 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrederickHawkins" hpid="Mr. Hawkins Mr. Hawkins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hawkins</NameTxt>
      <P>Or until such time as we would finish the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that we continue with this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in the hands of the House as to whether we should alter the arrangement, but as the two Front Benches agree, it is difficult to alter that arrangement.  With regard to Senator Walsh's amendment, do I understand the Senator to move that his amendment be inserted before Section 40?  The amendment is worded in such a way as to have it inserted before Section 45 stating: &ldquo;Notwithstanding anything contained to the contrary in Sections 40, 41 and 44...&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LouisWalsh" hpid="Mr. Walsh Mr. Walsh">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Walsh</NameTxt>
      <P>I am agreeable to withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Section 40 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 41 to 47, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 48.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 48 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryDavidson" hpid="Miss Davidson Miss Davidson">
      <NameTxt>Miss Davidson</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to raise a small point on this section.  Would the Minister consider amending it to require the local authorities to notify servants whose names are entered on the new register under this new section that their names have been so entered? That would enable servants to consider the financial implications of paragraph (a) of sub-section (3), that is to say, paying a year or two years' contributions in order to qualify for superannuation.</P>
      <P>If the Minister does not feel he could amend it, I wonder, when sending out a circular, whether he could see his way to ask the local authority to notify such servants of their rights under that section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1506" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>We hope to send an explanatory leaflet to the local authorities for distribution to every servant employed by them, but I should point out that they will get a better notice and that is the deduction of the contribution out of their pay packets.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryDavidson" hpid="Miss Davidson Miss Davidson">
      <NameTxt>Miss Davidson</NameTxt>
      <P>Will that be done?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be takeout. The Senator need not worry.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 49 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 50.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 15:</P>
      <P>In sub-section (5), to delete all words after &ldquo;section&rdquo; in line 26 to the end of the sub-section.</P>
      <P>It might save the House time if on amendment No. 15 I were to make the points I have to make in relation to amendment No. 17 also, because the principle involved is the same.  With the permission of the Cathaoirleach, I shall take amendments Nos. 15 and 17 together.  The amendment I propose is to Section 50, sub-section (5).  What I want removed is the last part of the provision.  Sub-section (5) says:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;A local authority shall have a discretion as to whether they will or will not enter into an agreement for the purposes of this section,...&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The part I want removed reads:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;subject to the proviso that they shall not enter into the agreement unless they are satisfied that the officer is in good health.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This relates to a man who wants to make an agreement with a local authority whereby he will sacrifice some of his pension, so that if and when he dies his widow will be able to draw something up to the time of her death.  That is a perfectly legitimate thing.  Some allowance should certainly be made for the widow.  The Bill, as at present before the House, would preclude from entering into such agreements people who, towards the end of their days of service, would not be 100 per cent. fit, &ldquo;in <Col N="1507" /> good health&rdquo;.  I suggest that those are the very people who would be most anxious to make provision for their widows.  Furthermore, I notice that sub-section (8) of this same section which I tried to cover in an amendment&mdash;the amendment was ruled out of order&mdash;makes it impossible in fact for the local authorities to lose money on this kind of transaction, even if the man is not in good health, because the Minister, under sub-section (8) may &ldquo;make regulations for the purpose of this section to secure that deductions from lump sums and death gratuities ... are not less than sufficient to meet the liabilities of local authorities.&rdquo;  Consequently, on an actuarial basis, the local authority cannot lose, no matter what is the health of the people wanting to enter into such an agreement for the benefit of their widows.</P>
    <P>That seems to me to be a very harsh condition.  Those who are allowed to give up some of their pension must give up at least enough to recoup the local authorities for what they are going to pay out on an actuarial average.  If any of them are not &ldquo;in good health&rdquo; towards the end of their days, they will not be allowed to make this agreement for the benefit of the widow!</P>
    <P>The same principle is involved in Section 51 which is covered by my amendment, No. 17.  It is with these considerations in mind that I beg leave to move amendments Nos. 15 and 17.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to amendment No. 15, it is quite evident that sub-section (8) clearly shows this is meant to be a self-financing scheme. It is true that local authorities may lose in individual cases but, over all, it is supposed to be self-financing.  The deductions from death gratuities and lump sums must, in general and taking one period with another, meet the pensions to be paid to widows.  That is the principle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Accordingly, if the scheme is to be even moderately attractive to the average officer, local authorities must avoid assuming liabilities in respect of what are known in insurance as &ldquo;bad <Col N="1508" /> risks&rdquo;, namely, officers whose health is bad.  It is obvious that all such officers would wish, if they could, to avail of the benefits of the section, but, if agreements were permissible in such cases, the deductions from lump sums and death gratuities to finance widows' pensions would have to be increased considerably.  The scheme would become valueless to the average officer in good health and valueless also to the officer in bad health.  No self-financing scheme of this nature can be run at moderate &ldquo;premiums,&rdquo; unless there is a weeding out of bad risks.  The mere fact that the deduction would be greater would frighten off the healthy officer, with the result that there would be nothing in the &ldquo;kitty&rdquo; for the officer in bad health.  Neither party would benefit.  It is the principle that &ldquo;bad risks&rdquo; should be weeded out. That is the only answer I can give the Senator on the particular point.</P>
    <P>With regard to amendment No. 17, it is the same principle, and I think the same answer covers the point made by the Senator.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RogerMcHugh" hpid="Dr. McHugh Dr. McHugh">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McHugh</NameTxt>
      <P>In relation to this amendment, there has been great emphasis placed on fidelity and diligence. How do you justify just a purely actuarial argument, an argument of finance of an insurance company that is simply operating for profit, when dealing with an officer who has incurred that ill health through 20 or 30 years of diligent and faithful service?  It is a cold-blooded outlook.  You must think of it, surely, in human terms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I confess that I have been shocked by the terms used by the Minister when he talks about &ldquo;weeding out bad risks&rdquo;, meaning that we must deprive the widows of &ldquo;bad risks&rdquo; of all pension rights and allowances!  I would deny the validity of his analogy, because an insurance company, when it is approached by a candidate for insurance, is almost always dealing with a relatively young person, with long years before him for the payment of premiums.  This is dealing with men in their sixties almost always, who are making such an agreement.  I suggest that it is unjust to demand that they <Col N="1509" /> shall be &ldquo;in good health&rdquo;, and I think it is supremely unjust to talk about &ldquo;weeding out&rdquo; bad risks.  That really means quite simply victimising the widows of people whose health has broken down in the service of local authorities.  I would urge the Minister very strongly to reconsider that, and perhaps to accept the validity of what I am saying, because it is obvious that, under the provisions of sub-section (8), the local authorities cannot lose, on an actuarial basis, taking one lot with another.  They are covered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I would ask that the two amendments be taken together and voted on together, because it is exactly the same principle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If we decide this issue, then we will have decided the other amendment as well.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Division.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Will those Senators challenging a division rise in their places?</P>
      <P>
        <i>Senators Sheehy Skeffington and McHugh rose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senators will be recorded as dissenting.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 16 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 50 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 17 not moved.</P>
      <P>Section 51 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 52 and 53 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 54.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 54 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryDavidson" hpid="Miss Davidson Miss Davidson">
      <NameTxt>Miss Davidson</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a section somewhat like the last one.  It applies to former servants of local authorities who have retired and who may be entitled to allowances under this Bill, provided they apply for the benefits of the section.  The question that strikes me is how such persons are to know <Col N="1510" /> that they are entitled to benefits, unless the local authority undertakes to notify them.  Could the Minister think of some way to amend the section to cover that, or would he by some means notify the persons, or get the local authority to notify them, of their right, because it depends on their applying for it?  Otherwise, they lose it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will appreciate that it is quite difficult to bring to the notice of the citizens of the country the law of the land.  It is very difficult to bring to the notice of each individual his rights.  For instance, I in my Department, and the Ministers for Health, Social Welfare, or Education do not know who the employees of local authorities are down the country.  We have not the vaguest notion.  But what we will do is this: on the suggestion of the Senator, we will notify local authorities that they should bring to the notice of their former servants and officers the rights they have under this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryDavidson" hpid="Miss Davidson Miss Davidson">
      <NameTxt>Miss Davidson</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 55 to 63, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 64.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 64 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I oppose this section for reasons which I made as clear as I could on the Second Reading.  I have said that in relation to the so called &ldquo;weeding out of bad risks,&rdquo; I was shocked by the Minister's words and attitude.  I must say here that I am horrified by this whole section.  This section deprives a man of his pension, if he has done a period of hard labour or served a penal servitude sentence in excess of 12 months. I made the point that you might make some kind of case for diminishing the pension of a man who has lived at the State expense in one of our luxurious jails for the time of his sentence, though not for diminishing the income <Col N="1511" /> of his wife and family, who are not lodged in jail with him.  But to deprive him altogether of his pension on his release from jail or on his conviction, as is the case, seems to me to be extremely unjust.</P>
      <P>I would ask the Seanad to consider what kind of people are concerned here.  These people are elderly people drawing pensions consequential upon many years of what up to then was considered honourable service, and they have been granted a pension despite the various regulations and pitfalls which might have excluded them, and having been for their declining years granted this pension, they commit some offence of which they are found guilty. A court deems a certain penalty warranted, and they serve their sentence. Having served it they come out and they have nothing in the world&mdash;no pension, and very little chance of getting employment at that age and in those circumstances.  Therefore it seems to me extremely inhuman that they should be deprived of their pensions, and that their wives and families in particular should be deprived of this source of income.  That, in fact, would be inflicting upon them a double punishment for the same offence&mdash;that they should be punished once by what the court regards as adequate, and a second time by what the provisions of this Bill lay down.</P>
      <P>I suggest that if the court says that such and such a sentence is adequate for this offence, once that sentence has been served the man ought to be able to come out with his head up and be entitled to his rights of pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister replied, as he was entitled to, referring to sub-section (3) of this section, which allows a local authority, when it &ldquo;thinks proper,&rdquo; to restore the allowance if the Minister &ldquo;consents&rdquo; to it.  The Minister referred to this right of appeal, and said that any element of injustice was removed by it because the Minister could always restore the pension.  But I would say in the first place that the Minister cannot restore the pension unless the local authority thinks fit.  I suggest that for the unfortunate man in those circumstances, having come out <Col N="1512" /> of jail, to have to go and persuade his local authority, and go to interview his county councillors or members of the corporation, for the purpose of getting them to decide that it was fit and proper to ask the Minister to consent to the restoration of his pension, is to subject him to humiliating conditions which are not warranted by the circumstances.  I suggest that is to subject him to humiliating conditions which are not warranted by the circumstances, and which, in some cases, would lead to all kinds of not very edifying lobbying.</P>
    <P>The Minister made it clear that he and his successors would always, in a case like this, when they were asked by the local authority, agree to give back the pension, provided that the convicted person showed himself contrite, and did not show himself to be in a frame of mind in which his offence might be &ldquo;continuing.&rdquo;  I suggest that in desiring to judge matters in this way the Minister is asking for too much power for himself and his successors.  I do not think that that sort of power should be vested in any one person.</P>
    <P>I am quite prepared to vest it in the courts, and if such a person is &ldquo;continuing&rdquo; the offence in the sense that he again commits it, then he can be brought to the courts, charged and, if found guilty, convicted and sentenced. However, to give a Minister power to decide whether or not sufficient repentance for his error has been shown by a man, before his pension can be restored to him, seems most unjust and even dangerous.  Furthermore&mdash;and I put this to the Seanad before and I hope the Seanad will agree with me now&mdash;I would regard a pension as being in a sense, a part of a salary, a deferred part of a salary.  I think many not very handsome salaries are accepted because portion of the salary is regarded as being deferred, and is to be used as pension.</P>
    <P>I regard pension rights as being part of the conditions of employment of a pensionable post.  I would regard the pension as something that has been earned, very like savings in the Post Office.  I think the Minister will agree with me that it would be very unjust <Col N="1513" /> to say that any man who served a jail sentence of a certain length should be deprived of all his savings.  Yet the Minister will probably recollect that that used to be the law, up, I think, to 1870.  It used to be the law in this country, under the British administration, that a man, on being convicted of being a felon, had to sacrifice all property rights.  As far back as 1870, however, it was recognised by the Legislature that it was an unjust concept that a man should be deprived of his property because of being convicted of an offence.  Therefore the 1870 Act changed that.</P>
    <P>I suggest that to deprive a man of his pension is to deprive him of a property-right which he has earned as fully as any savings which he has managed to put into the bank or Post Office.  The pension is part of the job. It is something earned, and to deprive him of it is to deprive him of a property-right vested in him by reason of his long service.  Consequently, I would urge the Minister very strongly to consider dropping this section altogether.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not true that when the question of loss of pension is at issue, in the case of a person being tried for an offence, that fact is invariably taken into account by the judge and due allowance is made in that connection in passing the sentence, whatever it may be?  I have seen quite a number of such cases.  Where the judge finds out&mdash;and he is bound to find it out; he would be told by the lawyer or the counsel for the person being tried&mdash;that if the prisoner is convicted and gets penal servitude for 12 months he will lose his pension as well, that fact is taken into consideration.  Consider a court passing a sentence and knowing that the prisoner will lose his pension.  I suggest that it must be taken for granted that, in such circumstances, a judge will sentence him to 12 months only if he believes the prisoner deserves it.  The loss of the pension is, therefore, part of the punishment he gets.  With regard to the period of 12 months, I suggest that in nearly all cases&mdash;except where the offence is very grave&mdash;the judge will <Col N="1514" /> not sentence a prisoner to 12 months or penal servitude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Senator Sheehy Skeffington very strongly on this matter.  I think that what the Minister said on Senator Walsh's amendment in regard to amending the law on wills is equally true on this section, because this section sets out to amend the criminal law.  The Minister professed great disapprobation at dragging in the law of testamentary disposition in this Bill.  It is equally objectionable to drag in a serious amendment to the criminal law on a Bill of this kind.  It is very unjust and goes against the whole spirit of the Irish law courts and the Irish Constitution.</P>
      <P>Over and above the statutory penalties which are provided for offences in criminal law, the Bill imposes an additional penalty not foreseen by the drafters of the original Acts.  Senator O'Connell has made a good point but, at the same time, I think it is two-edged and that it could be turned in our favour on this matter.  If the judge, in sentencing a person, takes into account the probability that he will be deprived of his pension, what he is really doing is taking into account something about which he is not completely certain.  The judge does not know whether, under sub-section (3), which we have been asked to take into account, the pension may or may not be restored.  Therefore, as there is the possibility that the pension may be restored, if the judge takes the loss of the pension into account in sentencing a person and if, at a later stage, an application is made to the local authority and the Minister under sub-section (3), it would be open to them to say: &ldquo;We would restore the pension but for the fact that the taking away of the pension has already been taken into account.  We would be upsetting the decision of the judge if we were to restore it.  The judge gave a certain sentence because he thought the pension would be taken away and now, if complete justice were to be done in this matter, if the pension were restored the person should be brought back again before the judge to get an additional sentence.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1515" /> It seems to me that a provision of this kind is exceedingly unjust.  It is inconceivable that it would apply in any private pension scheme, either contributory or non-contributory.  I cannot think of any case where a provision of this kind exists in any scheme.  As Senator Sheehy Skeffington quite properly said, these pensions are quasi-contractual. People gain them after years of service and accept lower salaries because the office carries a pension than they would in a similar office where they would have to make provision for their old age.</P>
    <P>There is no doubt at all about it that, from the legal point of view and from the Revenue Commissioners' point of view and from the financial point of view, a pension is deferred pay and that is part of the total consideration which a person gets for the work which he provides for the person by whom he is employed.  As Senator Sheehy Skeffington said, if people made provision for their old age in a different way, I think the Seanad would be horrified if they were deprived of their savings.  If a man were to take out an endowment policy which would provide him with a sum which would produce an annuity, retiring at 65, and if he were convicted of a criminal offence, if the insurance company were to say that they would not pay the annuity, I can see the outcry there would be by lots of people against the great injustice. Certainly the insurance company would not get away with it.</P>
    <P>If a man were to scrape up year after year enough money to buy investments he would not now be deprived of the income of these investments, if he were unfortunate enough to commit a criminal offence.  As Senator Sheehy Skeffington has said, up to a comparatively recent period, the felon lost all his property; there was complete confiscation of all property on conviction for crime.  That was dropped, and now I suggest that this principle which is enshrined in this Bill is, in its own way, quite as objectionable as that principle that was dropped many years ago.  We should be liberal.  We should be at least as liberal as the people who took away forfeiture for felony which was part of the common law.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1516" /> I want to make one more point. Senator Sheehy Skeffington has already made this point in a rather different way.  That is, that if this section is carried into effect, the people who pay the penalty for crime will be the dependents of the convicted person.  The convicted man himself will be maintained in more or less comfort in prison, but his dependents, his wife, children and other people depending on him, will not only be deprived of their income during the time that he is serving his sentence, but of the family income for the rest of his life.  It seems to me that is a very bad case of vicarious injustice, that if A. commits an offence, B., C., and D., who are innocent parties, should have to pay the price.</P>
    <P>I am not impressed by sub-section (3).  I agree with Senator Sheehy Skeffington.  In the first place, it involves a double appeal to two different tribunals, a double element of discretion.  He has to satisfy both the local authority and the Minister that the remission of the sentence&mdash; because that is really what it amounts to&mdash;is desirable and, if the crime is a crime that carries any sort of social stigma, the Minister and the local authority may feel that they are in some way or another condoning something which is disapproved of by public opinion in restoring the pension and, therefore, the scales would be weighted against the man.</P>
    <P>The last point I want to make is this.  If we are told by the Minister, as we may be told, that this penal clause is in other Government pension schemes, I am not impressed by that. If it is, then I say they should be amended.  Two wrongs do not make a right and I certainly think that this is a most unliberal and unjust provision. It offends against the whole spirit of the common law and the Constitution; it punishes a man twice for one offence and punishes innocent people for an offence they have not committed.  I call on the Minister seriously to consider dropping the section.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RogerMcHugh" hpid="Dr. McHugh Dr. McHugh">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McHugh</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to add one or two remarks in support of what <Col N="1517" /> Senator O'Brien has said.  I think it is an aphorism of Burke that magnanimity in politics is not seldom the truest wisdom.  If you are persuading public servants, on the one hand, that they should be diligent and faithful and, on the other hand, penalising them when they fall into bad health through being diligent and faithful and if you are, at the same time, providing that people will be penalised twice for the same offence, if they have the misfortune to go to jail, you will have a bad class of public servants developing in this country.  You have to be generous in these matters.  It pays off, if no other reason could be urged. You would have a more contented community and more contented servants serving that community.  To adopt the actuarial argument every time seems to me a great weakness in the Minister's case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>There are three reasons why I think this section is not a good section.  They have been given already and I do not intend to go over them again, but just to give a new angle on them.  The first is that the pension which would be cancelled by this section has been paid for by the officer through his contributions during his working time.  It may be said, of course, that he has only paid in half. That is true, of course, of any contributory pension fund, and in such cases there is no provision for cancellation of the pension for any reason after retirement of the official concerned. It is his in right and nobody can take it from him, no matter what offence he commits.</P>
      <P>In connection, with that point, it strikes me that if an officer has exercised the provision of Section 51, that is, has surrendered portion of his allowance, his wife may be entitled to part of the allowance, and I do not see exactly what will happen if Section 64 should eventually apply to that person.  Would he lose the surrendered portion?  Would it affect the portion he has surrendered to his wife?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the second point, I am sorry to disagree with my colleague, Senator O'Connell.  It is the point that the fact of the loss of pension would be taken into account by the judge dealing <Col N="1518" /> with the case.  It is wrong that this sort of thing should be brought to the attention of the judge.  He should judge on the merits and should not be persuaded to impose a different sentence, on the grounds that, if the sentence is 12 months, the person concerned will lose his pension.  That is bad in principle.  The person should be entitled to his pension by right, no matter how he offends afterwards.</P>
    <P>The third point is the question of appeal to the local authority.  We will all agree that it would be most undesirable that a man who was prosecuted, sentenced and lost his pension should then have to go to the members of a local authority, canvassing them to restore his pension.  It would be despicable. The offence may be very serious.  It would mean that he would have to go for judgment, not alone before the judge who sentenced him, but, when he comes out of prison, to go for judgment and appeal again to every member of the local authority.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  This is an executive function.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I stand corrected in that respect, but still it is most undesirable that he should have to appeal to the city or county manager and I do think that the Minister should withdraw the section.</P>
      <P>Might I make just one last point?  It is that the section is undesirable, though it probably would very seldom come into operation.  It deals only with people out on pension.  It would be most unusual that such people would be sentenced to imprisonment with penal servitude or hard labour, or sentenced to imprisonment for more than 12 months.  Even so, I think the section is undesirable and I do not think the Minister should press it.  I think he should withdraw it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to add my voice to that of Senator O'Brien in urging the Minister to accept the amendment.  I would prefer if an amendment could be put down on the Report Stage which might meet Senator Sheehy Skeffington's amendment. I remember making a statement on a Bill recently which I knew was out of order, but if this amendment is <Col N="1519" /> accepted, my statement here is in order, that is, that I deplore the procedure under which a Minister in another Department takes over the right of the Department of Justice.  If this section is incorporated in the Bill, the Department of Local Government or the local authority will be taking over a job which should be left in the hands of the Department of Justice.  It is entirely up to the courts to determine whether a person is guilty or is not guilty and to decide his punishment. The Department of Local Government should not be in a position to perform that duty.  Accordingly, I would urge very strongly on the Minister to accept this amendment and withdraw the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesCrosbie" hpid="Mr. Crosbie Mr. Crosbie">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crosbie</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to associate myself with the mover and supporters of this amendment.  I think the Bill will make a better Act, if this section is either amended or withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>One would imagine there was some innovation in this Bill and that, for the first time, a penal clause was appearing in it.  That is not so.  Under the Military Pensions Act, as amended by various Acts, the same provision applies&mdash;that, once a person is convicted, he automatically loses his pension.  That applies under the 1948 Act&mdash;the very Act we are trying to amend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there a contribution for military pensions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course there is.  It is one of the reasons why soldiers are paid so poorly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Would they pay 5 per cent. or 7 per cent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not tell you.  Under the 1948 Act which was introduced by my predecessor, the same penal clause exists, and again, under the Civil Service legislation, the same clause exists.  We are not trying to victimise individual pension rights of some juvenile.  We are dealing with a pensioner who is over 65 years of age and who is a criminal.  We are dealing with a mature man.  He must be convicted of an indictable offence <Col N="1520" /> by a judge and a jury and he must receive a sentence of 12 months or more.  Do not forget that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Or two months' hard labour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but the term of imprisonment must exceed 12 months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Any term of hard labour at all would suffice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>It must be an indictable offence, which is an important thing.  The man must be tried by a judge and jury.  That is very important. He is tried by 12 good and loyal and true men.  Remember when this man is convicted and sentenced, he is kept at the expense of the State.  I am quite serious.  The State contributes 50 per cent. of the expenditure of the local authority.  That includes expenditure on pension rights, and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RogerMcHugh" hpid="Dr. McHugh Dr. McHugh">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McHugh</NameTxt>
      <P>Extend that further and say, if he is hanged, he would have to pay for the rope.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us be serious about the matter.  You want this man to be given a pension while he is a convicted criminal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeOBrien" hpid="Professor O'Brien Professor O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>After he comes out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Immediately he is convicted, the executive officer of the local authority can there and then restore his pension to his wife and children, subject to the sanction of the Minister.  The pension may be restored forthwith, if the case is a necessitous one.  What is more, if there is an allocation of the pension as between the husband and the wife, it will not affect the wife's allocation.  I feel certain that any county manager or executive officer who may have powers delegated to him will automatically restore the pension to the wife and children, or to any other dependent in necessitous circumstances.  I think that is but reasonable.  When he comes out himself, the man may have his pension restored by applying to the executive authority and with the consent of the Minister. This is a contributory pension.  The <Col N="1521" /> man does not earn his entire pension. If he were contributing the full pension, he would be required to pay 15 per cent. of his salary, not 5 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>He loses it all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Not necessarily.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>Unless the Minister restores it, he loses the whole thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>He may lose it. But he may have been drawing it for a good many years while committing the same offence undetected.  We are dealing only with criminals and we are not punishing them.  We are giving to the local authority, subject to the Minister's consent, power to pay pensions to those who are entitled to them.  That is the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>The section gives power to take away the pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>The pension may be restored right off the reel.  I think that is reasonable.  It is exactly the same section as was incorporated in the 1948 Act and the same section as applies to military service pensions. Certain things have been said about lawyers.  The law agents of the Department of Local Government and of the various other Departments with whom I have consulted have all advised in favour of this section.  There have been no representations whatever from lawyers, who usually represent defence as well as prosecution, in favour of dropping this section.  I am not taking away from the very fine arguments put forward by the Senators in favour of this amendment, but I myself have some little experience of dealing with cases like this, and I can assure the House it is a very reasonable provision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not delay the House.  I speak again with some hesitation.  I did not mean to do so because I thought the case had been so cogently supported by other Senators, particularly by Senator O'Brien. But I feel driven to speak again.  When the Minister, as an argument for maintaining <Col N="1522" /> this section, tells us it was included in an Act which it has now become necessary to amend, that does not seem to me to be an argument at all, unless you take it as an argument for rejecting the whole Bill, because if we think that certain features of the 1948 Act were inadequate and should be changed, I would say this feature stands out among them, and we should take the opportunity of amending it that is offered to us by this Bill, with Section 64 omitted.</P>
      <P>The Minister's reference to this convicted person as being a criminal, and to the fact that he knew a lot about this kind of person led me to think even more that I did not like at all this decision about the restoration of pension rights being left in the hands of somebody with such an attitude.  I think the proper attitude to the convicted criminal who has served his sentence ought to be that he has every right to try and rehabilitate himself, no matter what the nature of his crime. I think we ought in all equity agree with that.  He should not be treated as a criminal or treated on any other terms, in all justice, than as an ordinary citizen.</P>
      <P>I see in the background of the Minister's attitude that the pension is regarded as a kind of charitable donation given to the officer who has worked for many years.  Most Senators who spoke agree with me that it is not a charitable donation, but something given as part of the salary and something for which the person concerned has worked.  It is a type of deferred payment and the Minister would not stand for his being deprived of it, if the man had put the money into an annuity or into savings.  I, consequently, propose this amendment and I would still hope that, perhaps, the Minister would accept it, and, if he does not, that the Seanad will pass this amendment and so amend the Bill in this way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I have listened to the Minister's speech and what he has said has completely convinced me of the justice of Senator Sheehy Skeffington's amendment.</P>
      <P>Question put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1523" />
      <Col N="1524" /> The Committee divided: Tá, 17; Níl, 7.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Burke, Denis.<br />Butler, John.<br />Carton, Victor.<br />Cogan, Patrick.<br />Davidson, Mary F.<br />Guinness, Henry E.<br />Hawkins, Fred.<br />Hayes, Michael.<br />L'Estrange, Gerald.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Lynch, John.<br />McGuire, Edward A.<br />O'Connell, Thomas J.<br />O'Reilly, Patrick.<br />O'Sullivan, John L.<br />Prendergast, Mícheál A.<br />Ruane, Seán T.<br />Walsh, Louis.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Bergin, Patrick.<br />Crosbie, James.<br />Douglas, John Harold.<br />Murphy, Dominick F.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">O'Brien, George<br />Sheehy Skeffington, Owen L.<br />Sheridan, John D.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers:&mdash;Tá: Senators Burke and S.T. Ruane; Níl: Senators Crosbie and Sheehy Skeffington.</P>
    <P>Question declared carried.</P>
    <P>Sections 65 to 71, inclusive, and Title agreed to.</P>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickFrancisBaxter" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Professor Hayes Professor Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Professor Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand from the Minister that he is anxious this Bill should become law by 1st April and, for that reason, he desires the remaining stages of the Bill now.  However, I will leave it to the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we had a solemn assurance from the Minister that he would consider amending Section 10.  We left it on that understanding. He gave that assurance this afternoon.  I think I was the last speaker and I summed up the position on which we left the section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is but right that I should explain the last thing I said on the section was that I had heard no arguments which would convince me.  I think I clearly stated that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>But that the Minister would consider it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>And I have done that.  I have considered it with my officials while the division was taking place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to oppose the suggestion that we should take the next stage now.  I feel that the Minister ought to be given more time to consider, since the time he has had so far has not produced fruit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly would not like to press the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Dr. O'Connell Dr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Dr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly was under the impression that the Minister did promise to consider.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. P. O'Donnell Mr. P. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well.  We will leave it at that, then.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Wednesday, 21st March.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 7.50 p.m., until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 21st March.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>