<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Fri" Date="18" Month="Dec" Year="1981" Vol="96" No="17" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 18 Nollaig 1981" DateEnglish="Friday, 18 December 1981" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1717">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1717" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. G. Hussey Mrs. G. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. G. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take items Nos. 1 and 2.  It is proposed, by agreement to pass all Stages of the Appropriation Bill and by Government motion early in the New Year to debate it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be appropriate for me to inquire if the Government propose to make a statement in relation to the position in Poland?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceOConnell" hpid="Mr. O'Connell Mr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in agreement with my colleague on the Labour benches.  I sought to address this matter to the Chair by means of raising it on the Adjournment. I understand that there are technical procedural difficulties with regard to that.  The situation is extremely grave in Poland at present.  It is a matter that affects us all.  If some means could be found whereby the House could advert to the situation before we break up for the recess, it would enhance the dignity and purpose of this House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with my colleagues in seeking some way in which the House could express a view on the very grave situation in Poland.  Since we are fortunate to have the Minister for Foreign Affairs in the House that might facilitate the possibility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1718" />
    <Speaker pid="BarryCogan" hpid="Mr. Cogan Mr. Cogan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cogan</NameTxt>
      <P>I too join with my colleagues in seeking some means of expressing our concern about events in Poland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Minister for Foreign Affairs (Professor Dooge) James C.I. Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Foreign Affairs (Professor Dooge)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government are very concerned about developments in Poland. This matter was discussed among Foreign Ministers of the Ten last Monday on the occasion of their meeting in London.  It was the subject of a statement by the Foreign Ministers of the Ten on Tuesday last.  Since then, we and our partners have been in close contact with one another. We are watching developments with some anxiety.  If at any time we consider the issue of a further statement on behalf of the Ten would contribute towards what we hope to see in regard to Poland, such a statement will be issued.  If the House wishes to discuss the matter at any time today or any other time I will be prepared to make myself available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a matter for the Leader of the House and the Whips to put down a motion and the Chair would welcome that initiative if it were to be agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. G. Hussey Mrs. G. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. G. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the leaders of the groups and the Whips discuss the matter in the course of the morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it agreed that such a motion be added to the Order of Business?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn" hpid="Mr. Quinn Mr. Quinn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quinn</NameTxt>
      <P>For today?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. G. Hussey Mrs. G. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. G. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Appropriation Bill, 1981 [ Certified Money" RHead="Bill ]: Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Appropriation Bill, 1981  [  Certified Money Bill ]:   Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BarryDesmond" hpid="Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. J. Bermingham) Barry Desmond">
      <NameTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance (Mr. J. Bermingham)</NameTxt>
      <P>The main <Col N="1719" /> purpose of the Appropriation Bill, as Senators are no doubt aware, is to give statutory effect to sums voted by the Dáil for supply services or, in less technical terms, for the ordinary services of Government Departments, both capital and non-capital, the money for which is voted on an annual basis.  It is essential that the Bill be enacted before the end of the year.</P>
      <P>Section 1 of the Bill provides for a payment of £10 from the Central Fund to make good an excess on the grant for Army pensions for the year 1979.  This excess arose due to delays encountered during the postal dispute in that year.</P>
      <P>Section 2 of the Bill, which is the principal section, appropriates to the specific services set out in the Schedule to the Bill the sum of £4,366,583,040 comprising of the original estimate of £3,767,441,000 and Supplementary Estimates of £599,142,030 and the excess which arose in 1979 of £10 mentioned in section 1.  In addition, it authorises the use of certain departmental receipts as Appropriations-in-Aid.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
      <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing Finance Agency Bill, 1981:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Housing Finance Agency Bill, 1981: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Minister for the Environment (Mr. P. Barry) Peter Barry">
      <NameTxt>Minister for the Environment (Mr. P. Barry)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a few copies only of my text as the Bill only came through the Dáil at a very late hour last night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The purpose of this Bill is to help many people who cannot obtain adequate mortgages at present to buy homes of their own.  It will provide the statutory framework under which a company, to be known as the Housing Finance Agency, will operate.  The company will <Col N="1720" /> be established soon after the Bill becomes law.</P>
    <P>The intention is that the agency will raise finance for housing mortgages on a self-financing basis.  The funds will be additional to the money which otherwise would be invested in housing.  In its first year of operation, the agency will raise £25 million to £50 million for these mortgages by selling State-guaranteed bonds linked to the rate of inflation and having a small real rate of return, to the operators of pension funds and life offices. A first-time purchaser of a new or an existing house with an annual gross income of up to £9,000 in the previous tax year may qualify for a loan of up to £22,500.  However, this sum will be increased to £27,000 in special cases.  The amount of the loan will be up to three times the borrower's annual gross income in the previous tax year or 90 per cent of the net value of the house, whichever is less.</P>
    <P>The borrower will be charged an index-linked mortgage rate, taking into account the real rate of return to the bondholder and the administrative costs of the scheme.  His actual loan repayments will be made on a pay-related basis.  For example, a person who takes out a mortgage equivalent to three times his gross income in the previous tax year may repay the loan over a period of about 25 years by annual instalments, each equal to 18 per cent of his gross income in the preceding tax year.  Taking recent trends in wage levels into account, this would be equivalent to about 15 per cent to 16 per cent of his current earnings. Where the loan is less than three times the borrower's income, the proportion of his pay taken in repayments may be less than 18 per cent.  The individual loan applications will be processed by local authorities by way of a graft on to their traditional SDA house purchase loan schemes.</P>
    <P>The idea of tapping institutional funds in order to give loan assistance to first-time house purchasers was put forward in a Fine Gael policy document published in October, 1980.  The proposals were also included in the party's policy document of last May and in the Programme <Col N="1721" /> for Government 1981-1986.  The reason underlying the new concept was the realisation that there is a need to open up some new source of house purchase finance because the existing sources of mortgage finance cannot meet the present demand for loans.  The point is relevant also that if a person earning £9,000 a year borrows £22,500 from a building society over 20 years to buy an existing house, his gross repayments in the first year, at current interest rates, would be £3,846, or 43 per cent of his income.  This is a tremendous burden.</P>
    <P>The Government have adopted a radical approach in funding the new scheme by providing in the Bill that the new agency may issue index-linked bonds having a real rate of return approved by the Ministers for the Environment and Finance.  At the outset the bonds will be issued only to pension funds and life offices and the issue will be on an auction or tender basis as regards the amount of the real rate of return.  The manner of repayment of principal and interest will be decided by the Ministers.  Provision will be made for a market in the bonds, but for the time being, this too will be confined to the pension funds and life offices.  Senators will agree that it is appropriate that the agency should be funded mainly by these sources; the terms of the bond issue will safeguard the investments made, mainly by small savers, in these institutions.</P>
    <P>While section 5 will authorise the agency to make loans to individual borrowers it is intended that for the time being local authorities will draw money from the agency and operate the scheme at local level.  Obviously there would be no point in arranging for the agency to set up a local branch network corresponding to those operated by building societies when 41 local authorities already efficiently administer house-purchase loans schemes throughout the country.</P>
    <P>In general, the new scheme is intended to help marginal house purchasers, that is first-time purchasers earning up to £9,000 a year.  This limit will be the gross income of the borrower, excluding the spouse's income, in the tax year preceding <Col N="1722" /> the date of application.  Many of these people find it difficult to obtain loans from other lending agencies.  Persons qualifying under the existing SDA loan scheme will be given the option of repaying their loans in accordance with the proposed terms.  In the course of time it is envisaged that the new scheme will prove so attractive to intending house purchasers that it could completely replace the present local authority loan scheme.  Under the new scheme, the maximum loans available from public funds will be increased very substantially.  In ordinary cases, the agency scheme will enable loans of up to £22,500 to be made, compared with the present maximum loan of £14,000 under the SDA scheme.</P>
    <P>Special categories of borrowers, such as a tenant of a local authority house surrendering the tenancy of his house and buying a private house, will qualify for a loan of up to £27,000, compared with £18,000 available to him under the SDA scheme.  The special maximum loan will also apply to the purchase of houses on certain islands off the west coast.  In the case of a loan for the acquisition of a house, the new limits will apply where the contract is not made before 16 December.  In the case of a loan for the construction of a house, the new limits will apply where the foundations were not completed before that date.  The new limits will be kept under review.</P>
    <P>It has been the firm policy of the Government to encourage the development of housing co-operatives.  As a positive indication of this policy and in order to promote activity by these voluntary bodies, the Government have decided that, where a bona fide housing co-operative builds houses on sites provided either by housing authorities or by the co-operatives directly, members of the co-operative who have annual incomes of up to £9,000 or are local authority tenants can qualify for loans of up to £27,000 under the new scheme, provided that at least 80 per cent of the new householders are otherwise eligible for house purchase loans under the scheme.</P>
    <P>Loans under the scheme will be advanced for the purchase of both new and existing houses and it is intended that <Col N="1723" /> the scheme will be open to both married persons and persons who are not married. Furthermore, an applicant for a loan will not, as in the case of SDA loans, be required to prove that he cannot obtain a house purchase loan from commercial agencies.  While the loan will normally be restricted to first-time purchasers, loans will also be available where a home-owner wishes to buy a bigger house because his existing house is unfit or overcrowded.  Loans will be made where a home-owner transfers to employment in another area and wishes to buy a house there.  In particular, a key industrial worker moving into an area will be facilitated.</P>
    <P>Loan repayments under the new scheme may be made on a pay-related basis.  Where a person borrows three times his gross income in the previous tax year, he may repay the loan over a period of about 25 years on the basis of 18 per cent of his gross income in the previous year.  This proportion may be reduced to 16 per cent, 14 per cent and 12 per cent where the amount borrowed represents 2½, 2 and 1½ times, respectively, the borrower's gross income in the tax year prior to his application.  The pay-related approach to loan repayments will usually result in the amount of the principal outstanding increasing in nominal terms in the early years, but in case there may be any misunderstanding, I want to emphasise that the amount of the principal outstanding under the proposed system normally declines in real terms when inflation is taken into account.</P>
    <P>It is necessary for me to emphasise this fact because it was clear from the reactions of some Deputies when the Bill was being debated in the Dáil that they had failed to grasp the implications of this aspect of the scheme.  In absolute terms the amount due by a borrower will increase &mdash; substantially so in some cases &mdash; in the earlier years of a loan.  But all the time his income and the market value of the house are increasing to the extent that he is safeguarded against any major loss in the event of his being obliged to dispose of the house.</P>
    <P>The outstanding feature of the new <Col N="1724" /> scheme is the way in which the real burden of repayments will be spread evenly over the duration of the loan.  This will make it possible for many persons to become home owners who otherwise could not undertake the extremely high repayments burden in the first few years of a conventional annuity mortgage.</P>
    <P>Another feature of the scheme which will be generally welcomed is that it will protect a borrower against the short-term effects of a loss of income due, for example, to sickness of unemployment, in that repayments required in any particular year may be restricted to the proportions of income to which I have referred, with the shortfall being made good in later years by the lengthening of the repayment period, if necessary.</P>
    <P>The total repayments will be calculated to ensure that the agency is self-financing, taking one year with another.  For this purpose they will be based on the agency's total costs, including the cost of servicing the index-linked debt.  At this early stage it would not be practical to predict if borrowing will in the long run prove to have been more or less expensive than borrowing on a conventional annuity mortgage.  That will depend on trends in inflation and mortgage interest rates in the future.  For example, mortgage rates exceeded inflation rates for part of the sixties, while the reverse situation obtained for most of the seventies. The upward trend in interest rates in the last year or so has resulted in the mortgage rate exceeding the inflation rate in some other countries.  In Ireland, while inflation rates generally are relatively high at present and may remain so for another year or two, the Government are determined to reduce inflation rates over the next few years.</P>
    <P>During the period 1973-1980, increases in average annual industrial earnings exceeded the rates of inflation by 3 per cent.  While increases in earnings are likely to be less than the inflation rate during the next year or so, earnings are likely to grow in real terms in the long run.</P>
    <P>In any event, of course, repayments will cease when the total amount required to cover the agency's costs have been <Col N="1725" /> repaid, even if this is well before the originally envisaged maturity date. Where a person qualifies for the mortgage subsidy of £3,000 spread over three years, it is intended that the borrower will transfer the subsidy payments to the lender, thereby reducing the amount of the loan outstanding and shortening the repayment period.</P>
    <P>In order to cut down red tape the income of a borrower's spouse will not be reckoned.  Borrowers will be free to make repayments over and above the specified proportions of income at any time if they so wish.  This will reduce the capital debt outstanding at that time and shorten the repayment period.</P>
    <P>Under section 6 of the Bill, the Minister, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, will be empowered to issue formal general policy directives to the agency.  The agency will, of course, be primarily responsible for formulating policies, but it may be necessary for the Minister from time to time to issue directives which relate to social and economic aspects of the agency's work.</P>
    <P>Under section 14 the agency will be required to meet its costs from its operations, taking one year with another.</P>
    <P>As regards the detailed provisions of the Bill, Senators will have noted the explanatory memorandum which was circulated with the Bill.  A substantial part of the measure relates to technical provisions similar to those which apply to most State-sponsored companies.  Section 2 provides for the formation and registration of the company.  Under section 3, the share capital will be £100 and this capital cannot be increased or reduced without the consent of the Minister for Finance.  Section 4 refers to the memorandum and articles of association and sets out the key objects of the company.</P>
    <P>I have already referred to section 5 in some detail.  Subsections (3)-(8) are based on the corresponding provisions of section 39 of the Housing Act, 1966, relating to the existing local authority loans scheme.</P>
    <P>I have also dealt with section 6.  Sections 7-9 are fairly standard provisions relating to the taking up of shares by the <Col N="1726" /> Minister for Finance, his rights as a shareholder and the disposal of any dividend etc. arising from such shares.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Finance occupies a central role relating to the capital and shares of the company.  I have in mind that when the company is being set up the board of directors will be drawn from persons with relevant experience in the commercial and public service.</P>
    <P>Section 10 enables the agency to borrow money up to a limit of £200 million. In the first year, borrowing may be of the order of £25 million to £50 million.  In particular, the agency may issue bonds. Section 11, which is a standard provision, empowers the Minister for Finance to guarantee borrowings and this would enable the agency to issue State-guaranteed bonds.  By virtue of section 10, guarantees will also be limited to £200 million.</P>
    <P>Sections 12, 13, 15, 17 and 18 are standard provisions.</P>
    <P>I have already referred to section 14 which requires the agency to be self-financing. Under section 16, any transfers of bonds, debentures and other securities issued by the agency will be exempt from stamp duty in the same way as transfers of certain loan stocks.  Before I conclude, I should say that I expect that applications for loans under the new scheme will be accepted within about six weeks.  The first bond issue will be made within about three months.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the Seanad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and perhaps I do so as one Munster person to another. Housing is a top-priority with every person elected to this House or to a local authority.  I seem to concentrate on health and education for various reasons but nine out of ten problems I am faced with relate to housing. I read the Bill and understand some of it but not all.  I do not think it is such a great measure.  When we left Government we had a good record of building 28,000 new houses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the new thinking in terms of financial assistance towards housing for the young, the old, and indeed everybody. Members of the Oireachtas who <Col N="1727" /> do not have the privilege of serving in local authorities may not know as much as we do about the problem of housing.</P>
    <P>The Bill has wide-ranging implications and I am worried about much of it.  Will the people who are really in need of houses apply for loans from the new agency and not read the small print?  I have in mind the tremendous cost of this money.  At this stage I want to make it quite clear that it is very dear money.</P>
    <P>The Minister suggested that at some time the agency will replace all local government schemes.  I do not agree with that.  People need homes.  They cannot rent them or if there are some to rent they are in absolutely dreadful condition. The rent of even the smallest flat for a young married couple is crazy and the Minister is well aware of this.  These people could go on a waiting list but that is something else because there are 500 applications for every 80 local authority houses.  The applicants then try to buy houses and that is where the money is needed.</P>
    <P>Here I want to put on record my tribute to the local authorities who have administered for many years a most successful SDA scheme.  I ask myself, why the change now?  Is this new agency needed because of local councils?  Do we need another unit in addition to all the sections we have at the moment?  I say this because I am worried about power moving from local government and local authorities.  I am not saying it because they made it possible for me to come here but because I have served on such an authority and I know of somebody who has served for very close to 32 years on such an authority.  I wish to put on record today the dedication of those men and women who serve very loyally.  I suppose in provincial Ireland they are the people next to the parish priest.</P>
    <P>The Minister referred to the cost of money.  Am I wrong in saying that in respect of a loan of £20,000 in ten years time a person could find himself owing on that house about £40,000?  It sounds mad but it could be true.</P>
    <P>I would like to ask if we could have the five-year plan which Fianna Fáil had in <Col N="1728" /> mind before they left government in the form of a White Paper.  I would like to see a long-term plan on housing again. Yesterday we had here a Bill on rented houses.  I did not have to wait until Senator Quinn and Senator Robinson spoke on Committee Stage to know that money must be provided for housing.  There is a new style coming into the Government's thinking.  I wonder if they are wise.  They have the attitude that the solution to all ills is a board of directors.  We had provision for a board of directors recently in the Youth Employment Bill and now we will have a board of directors to give everyone a home.  I have strong views about setting up boards of directors and more bureaucrats.  Maybe here we should take a lesson from the Coalition Government, that of more jobs for the boys. That may be something we will copy when we will get back into government in the spring.</P>
    <P>The Bill provides that the expenses incurred by the Minister in the administration of this measure shall be paid from moneys provided by the Oireachtas.  That seems to be down in small print in many Bills now.  We really do not know what will be the cost of administration.  Are there going to be offices and staff for this new agency?  If so, perhaps the Minister would have a word with the Minister for Finance who has a problem about decentralisation. If this is going to be a large unit put it in the mid-western region where we were promised decentralised offices.  Counties Clare, Limerick and Tipperary would gladly accept it.  When this Bill is passed will there be more money, the same money or is it a move of money from the Government to this new finance agency?  Are the SDA loans gone?  If they are, it is a dreadful mistake. Will this Bill affect the SDA loans on house repairs?  I would like to pay tribute to somebody who has done a tremendous job in the area of housing and that is Father Harry Bohan of the RHO.  He did much work in encouraging the building of houses in villages and in encouraging people to live in the villages.</P>
    <P>I support the Bill because it means houses for people but I have a reservation about the cost.  People talk about breakdowns <Col N="1729" /> in marriages but everyone must have a home.  It should be made clear to people getting finance from this agency that they know the price they will be asked to pay.  The Government gave the impression that they have all the answers. I am very worried about the cost.  I wonder if this Bill was necessary or needed? Should the Minister not have looked at units that were there?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to welcome the Minister to the House.  I have no doubt that he will be there later than next spring.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Bill and anything that will give a boost to the building industry. I have spent a good part of my life in the builders providers end of the industry and this £25 million or £30 million will be a great help.  The building industry serves many purposes.  It gives tremendous employment.  It is essential that people are able to provide their own houses.  Up to a month ago in my county we were three to four months in arrears with the payment of SDA loans but that situation has been straightened out.  People have to borrow by way of bridging loans from the banks but the banks do not treat these people very well.  In some cases they charge 18, 19, 20 and even 21 per cent and at the same time they are putting pressure on them to get the money which was not available.  If Fianna Fáil Senators realised what they put these unfortunate people through they would be delighted to see this money being put into the industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am concerned about some aspects of the Bill.  When Fianna Fáil introduced the £1,000 grant something happened and the price of land and building materials rocketed.  Part of it seemed to stem from the injection given to the industry. This will have to be watched but I do not know how that will be done.  If money is readily available for house building, inflation in the building sector will be higher than anywhere else.  I do not know the reason for this.  In recent years a large percentage of our building materials have been imported while, at the same time, similar products are manufactured in the country; for example, nails, slates, sheet <Col N="1730" /> lead and many more.  That came about when we joined the EEC when there was free movement of goods.  I do not know if people can be encouraged to buy Irish goods.  The cost of a door made in Ireland is £15 while the cost of the imported product is £12.  I do not know what can be done.  Of the money that is provided in this Bill, between 25 and 30 per cent will go outside the country if the import of goods continues at the present rate.  It will not serve the purpose it was meant to serve.  I feel I should bring this to the Minister's notice.  We get promises from all the political parties but nobody seems to do anything about the price of land. There is no political party or individual in this House who has a clean hand.  The situation is serious and we will have to do something about it.</P>
    <P>The legal costs involved when a person gets a loan are tremendous.  I think it would be advisable to set up some legal section, perhaps within this agency.  I have heard many complaints from individuals. If a person borrows approximately £20,000 from a building society to build a house and if his income is £8,000 a year he has to pay 42 per cent of his income on repayments on the interest. That is a situation that cannot be allowed to go on.  The one thing about this scheme is that borrowers are asked to pay more money at the early stages of the loan, perhaps prior to getting married although the scheme is not confined to married people.  Any young person can borrow. It is much easier for people to pay a higher rate at that stage rather than later.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill and I hope the Minister will be able to get it off the ground. I was glad to hear him say that we will have the applications available in the very near future.  I am sure it will have no effect on the ordinary SDA loans.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House and wish him every success in his new job.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am completely confused as to how this new agency is going to work and I am sure that most of the people who will be applying in the future will not have a clue as to what money they will need to meet their repayments under this new scheme. <Col N="1731" /> I would also like to join with Senator Honan in asking the Minister if this means the abolition of the SDA loans as we know them.  If so, it may create some problems that are not obvious now.</P>
    <P>I say at the outset that the provision of houses in this country is the responsibility both of the Minister for Finance and the Minister for the Environment.  It is their duty to provide finances for housing for those who are unable to provide them. The previous Government introduced the £3,000 subsidy grant and this was of great help to young people when purchasing houses.  In addition, they could get the £1,000 grant.  However, the present Government have abolished the subsidy and this will cause considerable hardship.</P>
    <P>The Bill is quite confusing and I am sure the Minister has found this to be the case.  People applying for the scheme will not know what it will cost them in the future.  The idea of linking the repayment of loans to a price index with a built-in inflation base is dangerous.  If trends continue in the coming years as they have for the past 25 years applicants will have to face problems in future years.  I am very worried about this aspect.  Credit for trying to bamboozle applicants must go to the civil servant who prepared this document.  I would not regard myself as highly intelligent but neither would I regard myself as stupid.  I could not calculate the amount of repayments any individual who may be applying for this loan will have to pay over a period.</P>
    <P>It is stated in the Bill that if a person gets sick or is unable for any other reason to repay the loan he may extend it for an additional four, five or six years but that does not help in any way.  Before they buy an article the Irish people like to know where they stand.  There may be other nations you could pull this one on, but Irishmen and women like to know the exact situation before they sign any document.  They will be guided by solicitors, who will probably know less, they will be guided by county councillors who will probably know more and they will be guided by the officials in the local authorities who will be operating this scheme. <Col N="1732" /> It is stated that the individual loan applications will be processed by local authorities by way of a graft on to their traditional SDA house purchase loan scheme.</P>
    <P>I will have to get the Minister to explain that one to me also.  It is also stated that a person taking out a mortgage equivalent to three times his gross income in the previous tax year may repay the loan over a period of about 25 years by annual instalments.  What about the small farmer in the west who is not recorded at all for any tax purposes?  How is he going to be assessed?  If you are going to go on statistics and tax returns, how are you going to assess the small farmer in the west whom Senator Hussey spoke about, who has an income of only £15 or £16 a week, or £1,000 a year?  How can you assess that farmer on a tax-return basis?  He will have no records, but he will be a first-time applicant for a loan under the scheme.  I can see major confusion as to how this is to be worked.</P>
    <P>Senator Reynolds mentioned the need for additional moneys because local authorities throughout the country had not sufficient moneys for the SDA loans which they had in operation.  They were not getting sufficient capital and delays were long in certain cases over the last number of years.  All local authorities could lend more money if it was available to them.  If this agency brings in additional money to supplement the moneys from the Department of the Environment then it will do one good thing.</P>
    <P>I want to issue a note of warning here. For the first time in my experience as a member of Mayo County Council we in Mayo are on the point of issuing orders for the eviction of people who are unable to pay back their existing loans.  I have checked this out with other local authorities and I find that the same situation exists throughout the county with young people who borrowed smaller amounts up to previous limits.  The maximum loan is £14,000 at the moment.  I always warned young people who came to me for advice to try to keep down loans because their repayments could be enormous and inflation and the demands on their pay packets would make it <Col N="1733" /> extremely difficult for them to meet their loan obligations.  Many people with loans of even £3,000 or £4,000 are unable to pay them back at the moment.  It will be very regrettable if such people have to be evicted.  Yet under this legislation we are going to hang not £14,000 but £20,000, £25,000 or greater amounts around the necks of young married people who will have responsibility for the repayments. That should be an indication to the Minister of the need for additional housing grants to offset the spiralling increase in the cost of housing.  The prices today will be higher tomorrow and the more quickly one builds the cheaper the house will be.</P>
    <P>Senator Reynolds was correct when he said the £1,000 grant was devoured by developers to a great degree when it was introduced.  It was a great boon to an individual builder building one house, but the people who really went to town on the £1,000 grant were the major developers in the cities and not the small builders who were building in rural parts of the country.  I would welcome any legislation which would ease the big burden on young people.</P>
    <P>A word much used in connection with the £1,000 grant is showing its head here again: the spouse.  That has become a great word around the country.  Everybody knows now what a spouse is.  A spouse was supposed to be attached to another spouse.  If the Government could take back that word easily without the attention of the media they would do so. They are trying to say now the spouse is not taken into consideration in regard to this loan.  The spouse does not mean anything here now.  The spouse, man or woman, meant a lot in the last decision of the Department of the Environment but the word is not in this document.  In this modern day the marital partnership may not be regarded as permanent.</P>
    <P>People who are not able to pay in a certain time can be granted an extended period which was not available under the old scheme.  Under this Kathleen Mavourneen system it can go on and on. It may work out at the end of the day although I am not sure that it will.</P>
    <P>I wish the Bill every success.  I will have more to say on it at a later date.</P>
    <Col N="1734" />
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Minister to the House especially since he brings us this legislation which is so badly needed. Many of us who have served on county councils over the last few years will realise the distress that many applicants have had to suffer under the present SDA loans system, not particularly on the issue of incomes and their limit.  Senator O'Toole mentioned the question of spouse, but he must have realised who created all this mess.  The decision to increase the money available on paper was very popular but they did not make the money available.</P>
      <P>I welcome this Bill as comprehensive legislation and good thinking.  I would like to highlight many aspects with the old SDA loan never catered for.  The first thing is the relationship between income and the amount of loan available: in other words, at present it caters for a category who were excluded from the SDA loan. Contrary to what the other side of the House believe, I understand that the SDA loans still exist and are available to the income groups entitled to them.  I treat with scepticism the criticism that single people are excluded.  The most needy must be catered for and the SDA loan caters for and was intended to cater for that category.  The minor adjustments that were made recently by the present Minister were absolutely necessary to make sure that very needy people, married people with families, could provide their own housing.</P>
      <P>Senator Honan described 28,000 houses as a great record.  I would question that figure, provided by the Fianna Fáil administration, as being a reality.  Certainly the west saw very few new starts last year.  The record is that until we got the OK from the present Minister that the moneys were available, not one new start was made in Galway County Council area last year.  I hope they can stand over that as a proud record in Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that was so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1735" />
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>The welcome aspect of the loan is the attractiveness of the repayments. Under the present system, whether it is an SDA loan or a building society loan the repayments in the initial stages are a crippling burden on people starting to establish a family home.  It is stated that it can be as high as 43 per cent of their income.  Here we have a maximum proportion of current income of 15 to 18 per cent.  That is very attractive to the person trying to get off the ground. Demand is by far the greatest in the initial stages after marriage and the establishment of a home.</P>
      <P>Much red tape was attached to the SDA loans with regard to titles and security. What are the requirements for the new loans?  The old system required two guarantors and the site and house had to be mortgaged in the name of the local authority.  Do these requirements still remain?  Very often people who had applied for loans found that they had to incur very great expenses on bridging loans until the legal transfer of the loan into the local authority's name.  I hope that this new Bill will short-cut the red tape and delay involved.</P>
      <P>At what stage will the payment of the loan be made and will the period of time for the sanctioning of the loan be shortened in comparison with the present situation? Most local authorities have to budget carefully in advance and an application after being processed is held until the finance is available.  That often entails a delay of six, eight or maybe 12 months in certain instances before the sanction is forthcoming from the local authorities.  It was always emphasised that applicants were advised not to start construction until they got the sanction.  While that was a good thing, very often in the time between the application for the loan and the sanctioning of it escalating prices caused an increase in the cost of the house of £2,000 or £3,000.  I hope that the long delays in sanctioning applications will be cut short.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The local authority are to be the agency who will make these loans available. Here the Minister realises that he is not in any way diminishing the powers or functions of the local authorities when he <Col N="1736" /> is making substantial proportions of this money available through the local authorities throughout the country. Therefore, local authorities need not worry about any reduction in their powers. I welcome the fact that the Minister has seen fit to operate this through the local authorities and I hope he will continue to see the local authority as the administrative agency for this scheme.</P>
    <P>The increase from £14,000 maximum in the present loan to £22,000-plus under the new scheme is welcome.  I fail to see why there is so much criticism from the other side of the House.  Senator O'Toole said that he did not like to see this great big burden hanging around a person's neck.  I would not say that it is a burden hanging around anybody's neck.  The availability and the acceptability of the finance is the big question.  People who are at present held up under the old system would gladly accept this scheme.  To say that it is a big burden around their necks for years to come is untrue.  You can borrow only £14,000 under the present scheme and you have to go, cap-in-hand, to some other agency like the bank to find the additional amount, or do I take it from the other side of the House that they intend to commit everybody to £14,000 houses and leave it at that? Where is the other finance to come from? It is not easy to come by, particularly for certain categories of people who have to look for the additional finance.  These very often are not the people the bank manager wants to see coming in, which initially they are forced to do to look for the rest of the money at exhorbitant interest rates.  The interest rates as quoted here are attractive in comparison with some of the very short-term lending available from banking institutions.</P>
    <P>On the question of the availability, the injection of the proposed £22 million in the current year will give an added boost to one of the most sensitive industries in the country, the building industry, which at the moment is progressing satisfactorily. Many of the other ancillary supply industries are also going well.  The number of people employed in the industries directly or indirectly related to the building industry will have to be increased.  We <Col N="1737" /> have heard over the past two or three years of great numbers of layoffs in industries related to the building industry.  We all must welcome the fact that the industry has got a tremendous boost and that employment which has had such a severe rebuff for the last two or three years will now get off the ground again.  The number of building firms that have gone to the wall over the last few years is a direct result of the industry being starved of finance.</P>
    <P>I congratulate the Minister on the timely introduction of this measure so soon after coming into office.  I hope the people who have been in a limbo situation for the last two years will now see an opportunity to go ahead and start the house to which they are entitled.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasHussey" hpid="Mr. T. Hussey Mr. T. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the other speakers, I welcome the Minister to the House and wish him success in his new portfolio. Anybody who comes to this House with good news for housing, social welfare and so on is very welcome.</P>
      <P>I welcome this Bill because I feel that it will in some way help to resolve the grave housing problem with which the country is faced at the moment.  The provision of housing is one of the most important social functions that any Government could be engaged in.  No matter how many houses we build &mdash; different parties and different Governments may claim credit for the provision of 28,000 houses, 30,000 houses and so on &mdash; we are only scratching the surface.  We have a very young population.  We claim that 50 per cent of our population is under 25 years of age.  We know too that the trends are changing.  Heretofore people provided themselves with a house before they decided to get married.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now young people are more inclined to get the bird first and find the cage afterwards.  The decision of the present Government to which I am completely opposed, to confine the provision of SDA loans to married people is not right.  That is a bad decision, and the Minister should look at it again.  Over the past few months I have met quite a number of young people who were anxious to build their own house, who were anxious to get married <Col N="1738" /> when they had that house built, but unfortunately they will not qualify for the SDA loans.  This is creating problems, regardless of what the Government might think.  Young people who show that kind of initiative should be encouraged to proceed rather than be stopped from providing those houses.</P>
    <P>I would not like to see the SDA loans done away with.  I hope when the Minister is replying that he will be able to clarify that point because one of the advantages of the SDA loans was that you had a fixed interest rate and people knew exactly what they were going to pay and they could budget for that.  In the new system that is not the case.  It would be very difficult for anyone to calculate what his final payments might be or what his overall payments over the 25-year period would be.  I have certain reservations about the setting up of boards of this kind because they are adding to the already overburdened bureaucratic system.  I can see no reason why the Department of the Environment could not carry out the functions being given to this agency.  We have seen in the past planning appeals taken away from the Department and Minister and given to a planning board.  I am not so sure that they have done any better job than the Minister would have done, and I see no reason why the Minister who is responsible to the electorate and who has to face the electorate every two, three or four years, should not be left with the final decision.  He is as capable of giving a fair and just decision as any planning appeal board.  The same would apply in cases like this.  In the Department of Agriculture responsibilities have been handed over to ACOT.  Again I am not so sure that that board can do any better job than the Department or the Minister responsible for running that Department could have done.  I am reluctant to give my blessing to the setting up of additional agencies like this.  It is making it more difficult for the ordinary people to get at those people.  We are setting up more faceless people.  The vast majority of the Irish people would prefer to approach the Minister responsible rather than have to go to a board or an agency such as this.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1739" /> Certainly the building trade needs a boost.  More than ever before there is a great need for the provision of new housing. Those of us who are doing our constituency work meet this every other day. Young couples come to us pleading for houses, couples who are trying to raise their families in flats and so on.  It is a very sad situation.  It is difficult for the Government to find money for everything, but this is one area where no public representative would grudge the allocation of the money.  I hope that the setting up of this agency will not mean that funds already invested in housing will be withdrawn. That would be a terrible thing to happen.  I would like to see additional money provided for the building of houses.  Not alone will this measure provide houses that are badly needed but it will also create employment in the industry and the other ancillary industries. This is important when our unemployment figures are so high.</P>
    <P>Again I welcome the Bill.  It will not be the answer to all the problems and I am sure the Minister accepts that.  I hope that as the Bill proceeds and as the administration of the Act proceeds, over the next six or twelve months, if there are anomalies and problems, the Minister, the agency or whoever is responsible will correct those problems, and that they will be monitored carefully and put right.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonalCarey" hpid="Mr. Carey Mr. Carey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carey</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with the other Senators in welcoming the Minister to the House.  I also welcome this agency Bill.  The intention of this Bill, as I understand it, is to be self-financing.  Other Senators did not place much emphasis on that fact. In today's economic state, surely an effort to provide some agency which can work without an immediate input from taxpayers is to be welcomed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Other Senators have dealt fairly adequately with the social need for housing. From my experience as a county councillor I would ask that in the administration of the scheme and the giving of directions to the local authorities there would be some relaxation in the schemes or guidelines drawn up to give sanction for these <Col N="1740" /> loans to applicants.  So many rigid judgments have been made of guidelines previously given.  For instance, no local authority will sanction a loan until the legal transfer has taken place.  Senator O'Toole is concerned about the west and we have many problems in the west about titles.  An easement in the title requirement for sanction of the loan would help greatly.</P>
    <P>I would like also to see, in the administration of funds, part of the funds allocated immediately, irrespective of whether the title matters had been drawn up or not.  Once planning permission has been given and an undertaking or contract has been drawn up &mdash; either between the previous owner of the site or his solicitor or representative &mdash; this should be sufficient for sanction of the loan.  Matters should then be let go ahead.  I would like to join with Senator Honan in her praise of the RHO and what that organisation is doing for the west.  Housing development is necessary and this Bill will be of great assistance to the RHO in providing houses for people who want finance urgently.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícháel Cranitch Mícháel Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícháel Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>Is é an chéad dualgas atá orm ná fáilte a chur roimh an Aire.  Is fear macánta, dea-bhéasach é i gcónaí, fear cumasach, agus gúim gach rath ar a chuid oibre fhad is a bhíonn sé in a Aire.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Go raibh maith agat, a Mhíchíl.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícháel Cranitch Mícháel Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícháel Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>I can truthfully say that I welcome this Bill to the extent that it will expedite the erection of more houses and will give a badly needed boost to the construction and house building industries.  If there is any industry that tends to create even more employment it is the building industry.  It makes the money go around, so to speak.  There are many ancillary industries supporting the construction industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Then there is the question of houses. I used to wonder years ago how it was that, with all the houses being built, there was still a great demand for them.  You would think, with a small population <Col N="1741" /> such as ours, that we would have come to saturation point years ago.  It looks as if we never will come to saturation point as far as house building is concerned.</P>
    <P>Of course, we have a wonderful distinction in this country &mdash; we all love to have our own house.  That sentiment was expressed for all time in the words of a beautiful little poem: &ldquo;A little house, a house of my own, out of the winds and rains way&rdquo;.  That is in our blood.  It is hard for us to realise how in EEC countries people are content to live all their lives in rented accommodation of some sort, in flats and so on.  We love to have our own house and that is very good, indeed.</P>
    <P>This Bill is designed to create an agency.  I am sure, as the Minister has something to do with it, it will be an excellent agency.  However, one always has a suspicion when one hears of a board, or an agency, or a corporation, or something of that nature being set up. One begins to think, perhaps a little uncharitable, is this just another gimmick to put something on the long finger?  In one section the Minister has given power to himself to advise this agency, as needs be.  Indeed, I am very glad of that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícháel Cranitch Mícháel Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícháel Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>In section 6, the Minister may, from time to time, with the consent of the Minister for Finance, give to the agency such general directives as to policy in relation to all or any of the objects specified in the agency's memorandum of association as he considers appropriate.  That is a very satisfactory clause.  Speaking of the memorandum, section 5 states that this agency may &ldquo;specify the class or classes of houses in respect of which such loans may be made&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister probably at this stage could not give us any details or any idea as regards the size of the houses he has in mind.  One thing I would warn against is having houses built that will eventually turn out to be too small.  There is a demand, of course, in certain areas for small houses suitable for retired couples and such.  Generally speaking, with a rising <Col N="1742" /> population we should not have the houses too small, because there is always a difficulty then in extending these houses.  I would hope that the Minister would hear in mind that new building materials are coming on the market every day, new insulating materials that help very much as regard reducing heating costs.  I hope that the regulations will be adequate to make sure that as a result of using the most appropriate materials heating costs in our future houses will be considerably reduced.</P>
    <P>There is one paragraph in the Minister's address which is rather disquieting, especially in view of the fact that figures have just been released showing that the rate of inflation is now well over 23 per cent.  The paragraph is that &ldquo;total repayments will be calculated to ensure that the agency is self-financing, taking one year with another&rdquo;.  That is excellent in itself.  Would that all agencies and semi-State bodies would be self-financing.  His address went on: &ldquo;For this purpose, they will be based on the agency's total costs, including the cost of servicing the index-linked debt&rdquo;.  That index-linked specification is new in the case of providing funds for a particular industry.  &ldquo;At this early stage, it would not be practicable to predict if borrowing will, in the long run prove to have been more or less expensive than borrowing on a conventional annuity mortgage.&rdquo; That sentence seems to be rather disquieting.  The Minister said then &ldquo;That will depend on the trends in inflation and mortgage interest rates in the future&rdquo;.  Well, as inflation is going at the moment and there seems to be no hope of stopping it, that could lead to very serious consequences.  I trust that the Minister, when replying, will make reference to the points I have raised.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBruton" hpid="Mr. R. Bruton Mr. R. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to join with the other Senators in welcoming this Bill.  It is important in that it is for the first time getting a contribution from the insurance companies into the area of housing.  For years, we have been unable to get money in from them because they have been able to give better returns to their depositors from other types of investment.  It is a welcome development, <Col N="1743" /> because there is no doubt that, in recent years, particularly, the building societies have been under strain in getting adequate inflows to finance our housing needs.</P>
      <P>I also welcome the Bill because it is filling a gap which has been very sorely felt in housing policy, that is, the problem of the lower income person who is purchasing a house.  Persons who are on council lists and usually on very low incomes, if they get housed have available to them a very generous differential rent scheme and very generous purchase terms.  The people who are unfortunate enough to be slightly above the cut-off point have been forced to bear very heavy burdens.  They usually have to get the loan, which at present at £14,000 is grossly inadequate to meet the cost of housing.  They are being forced to get expensive topping up borrowing.  The net effect has been that these people, with immense initiative in that they are prepared to go out and build for themselves in the rural areas, have been pulling the devil by the tail for years &mdash; especially during their early married years.  I really welcome this Bill in that it extends the availability of loans to people up to a £9,000 limit, and provides a realistic loan that will meet the full cost of the house and allows those people to make their repayments in a manner which they can afford.  For that reason, it is correct that the agency charge a real rate of return &mdash; a real mortgage rate.  This is a point which Senator Cranitch raised.</P>
      <P>There are generous assistances available to people who are borrowing to buy a house.  To pay tribute to the last Government, they did introduce this scheme of the £3,000 mortgage subsidy in the first three years, which is immensely valuable in that it relieves the early tough years. I do not share the anxiety of Senator Cranitch that it is unreasonable to ask a real rate of return on the mortgage rate, given the general subsidies that are available.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would ask the Minister to consider two other problems in relation to people buying houses, or building for themselves and that is, the question of solicitors' <Col N="1744" /> fees, which are still excessive.  They are moving up towards £1,100 on a new house.  I cannot see that the solicitors are providing an adequate service to justify that sort of a fee from a couple setting up on their own.  On a point Senator Hussey raised regarding the exclusion of single people from the SDA loan.  I have to differ from him on that.  We are dealing, in the SDA loan, with a highly subsidised interest rate.  It is down at 12½ per cent, away below a real mortgage rate.  It is incumbent on the Government to allocate scarce and highly subsidised money such as that to the place where it is most needed.  There is no doubt in my mind that the married person, or the person who is intending to marry within a very short time, is a much higher priority than single people who decide that they want a house of their own.</P>
    <P>I also welcome the fact that the Minister has sent a directive to the county councils saying that in the case where the income of the spouse, or the intended spouse, is only temporary, that would not be taken into account in considering eligibility for the SDA loan.</P>
    <P>This Bill is setting up an agency that finances through a mortgage rate and is offering a real rate of return.  That is not subsidised money.  Similarly, single people will not be barred from access to it.  That is a most welcome feature also, of the Bill.  The final point I would like to mention in regard to what Senator Hussey said about setting up a new agency, is that the welcome feature of this agency is that it will be comprised of persons with expertise in this area.  It will give a confidence to the insurance companies and pension funds which are taking up this offer, that it will be properly administered. I welcome it for that reason.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Minister for the Environment (Mr. P. Barry) Peter Barry">
      <NameTxt>Minister for the Environment (Mr. P. Barry)</NameTxt>
      <P>Firstly, I would like to say how pleased I am with the reception which this legislation has got in the Seanad.  I want to thank very sincerely those Senators who welcomed me here today.  This is my first appearance, in this Government, in the Seanad.  I also want to give an assurance to the Seanad that this is the only seat I will ever occupy in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1745" />
    <Speaker pid="TrasHonan" hpid="Mrs. Honan Mrs. Honan">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Honan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister never knows.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure Senator Honan that no matter what the fates have in store for me in the other House, I will not be seeking election here.</P>
      <P>I was struck by the concern of every single contributor to the debates on Second and Committee Stages in the Dáil and on Second Stage in the Seanad of every public representative to see that as many people as possible not alone occupy their own houses but, in fact, be proprietors of their own houses.  That concern spreads right across party boundaries.  I subscribe to the view that to occupy one's own house and to have a stake in it is a very good thing.  Things may change. There is not quite as strong a need in other countries to own one's own house. Certainly, in parts of the Continent, most people are in rented accommodation. Legislation forced on us by the Supreme Court earlier this year may mean that, in the future, there will be more investment in property for rent.  Deputies, Senators and, indeed, councillors rightly reflect the wish of most Irish people to own their own houses.</P>
      <P>I was struck by the deep knowledge of housing on the part of Deputies and Senators who are members of local authorities. Senator Honan asked about a White Paper being produced on housing.  A complete White Paper will be ready I hope, in the spring, summer or early autumn of next year.  I would hope to have agreement amongst the Whips of the parties in the Dáil and perhaps if there is an interest in the Seanad, to have at least a one day discussion, perhaps more, on general housing in the country, using the White Paper as a basis for that discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the two-day debate in the Dáil I learned a lot about housing from people who are actually dealing with applicants for houses at local authority level, SDA level, insurance company level and building society level &mdash; people who have to get mortgages from those sources.  It might clear our minds and we might find a lot of agreement across the Houses if <Col N="1746" /> we had a proper, lengthy debate on housing generally, to try to sort out where we should be going.  I hope that the White Paper will set down where we should be going with regard to housing right through the eighties and can be used at some stage as a basis for discussion.</P>
    <P>To continue along that line, I agree entirely with Senator Honan when she talked about the patriotism and general devotion of local councils.  I have said a number of times &mdash; most recently at the lunch I hosted for Senator Lawlor's association on Wednesday last &mdash; that I see the whole basis of democratic government starting at the local public representative and his intimate knowledge of his own area.  I certainly want to assure the Senator, as I have assured others, that it would be my objective, while Minister for the Environment, to push as much power as I can out of the Custom House and back down to local authorities. Side by side, or hand in hand, with the acceptance of that power goes the responsibility to exercise the power.  It is not all one-way traffic.  I will certainly be glad to do anything I can.  Indeed, it was the basis of my thinking when writing to the chairmen and mayors of the various councils in the last couple of months, asking them to have special meetings to see in what way local government could be reformed.  I have received some interesting observations, not from all the authorities yet, but I am sure that I will have received replies from all of them by the end of January, in which case I hope to come back to the Seanad again with some further proposals in regard to the reorganisation of local government.</P>
    <P>Senator Honan referred to the shortage of local authority housing.  That, of course, is correct.  I am afraid that, as Senator Burke mentioned, sufficient money was not provided earlier in the year to build enough local authority houses.  In fact, there is probably very rarely enough money available for local authorities but, in 1981, the amount was cut back quite significantly.  We managed to get some extra finance during the year and allocated more to them.  That was a very necessary step because, otherwise, there would have had to be lay-offs in <Col N="1747" /> local authorities or, indeed, in the sectors employed by local authorities in this regard.  Senator Honan referred to long-term planning with regard to housing and I have already referred to a White Paper. I hope that at some time we can arrange to have a suitable motion put down in the House where the White Paper could be used as a basis for discussion.</P>
    <P>Senator Honan also referred to house improvement loans.  These loans will continue to be administered by local authorities under the 1979 Housing Act.  The agency will be concerned with house purchase, rather than house improvement. Both Senator Honan and Senator Tom Hussey spoke about the fact that the agency would represent extra public funds for housing.  Indeed, the objective of the agency is to provide extra housing to fill a gap in the present structure, as Senator Bruton recognised, and to provide another option in the methods of getting funds when people in a certain income bracket experience difficulty in getting mortgages for houses.  This agency will, hopefully, be an assistance to them.</P>
    <P>Senator Reynolds rightly said that this will prove to be an injection of funds into the building construction industry.  That is correct and it is one of the reasons why I have been pushing a little bit to get this legislation through the Houses of the Oireachtas.  It is a measure that is very badly needed and I would hope that it will be operating in the next four or five weeks, so that we can accept applications from people wanting to purchase either new or old houses.  I do not think that any Senator mentioned the fact that funds from the agency can be used to purchase a second-hand house as well as a new house.</P>
    <P>Normally, people say that when public money is being made available, or machinery is being set up to provide money over which the Government have a control, it should be confined to new houses and I tend to agree with them. Before I came into the Department, I learned from people outside the public service, in the construction industry, that one cannot separate sectors of the construction <Col N="1748" /> industry; they are all tied together.  People who live in a second-hand house will but a new house if they can sell their existing house.  There is a link between all sectors of the housing industry.  Local authorities, under the SDA loans scheme, sometimes give loans for secondhand houses, certainly for people in local authority housing, but in this case any applicant, whether he be a local authority tenant or otherwise, can now apply to buy a secondhand house.</P>
    <P>Senator Reynolds also mentioned something about which I am extremely concerned and about which he has spoken to me privately on a number of occasions. Traditionally, we think of a house as being built of virtually 100 per cent native material &mdash; wood, cement, slates, nails all these things he listed.  That is changing, undoubtedly.  Senator Reynolds would have a better idea of how big the imports are and how significantly they are eating into the home market.  It is one of the reasons why all Governments of all shades have continually repeated that we must be competitive, not just because we want to sell goods abroad, but because we must also protect our home market from imports which now have a right to come into the country under our obligations under the EEC regulations.  It is something that we should all be very cautious about.  It is very difficult to blame a contractor or, indeed, an individual who in the example quoted by Senator Reynolds, is offered precisely the same door at two very different prices.  It is very hard to see how such a huge price differential exists.  The door which Senator Reynolds spoke about was sold in this country, hundreds of miles from where it was manufactured and processed, for £12, where the native Irish door manufactured almost on the spot is 25 per cent more expensive.</P>
    <P>Everybody connected with any manufacturing or processing business must remember that the more uncompetitive our goods become, not alone in world markets but in our home market, the more jobs will certainly be lost at home. The Senator gave a perfect example of this.  For years we believed correctly that almost 100 per cent of the components of <Col N="1749" /> a house were home-produced.  Now we find that this market is being eaten away, purely because our goods are not attractive enough in price to compete with goods from abroad.</P>
    <P>Senator Reynolds also referred to the price of land for building.  As he said, it is a thorny problem with enormous constitutional implications that have been the cause of concern to every local authority.  It is something for which a solution has to be found.  I, on behalf of the Government, have set up a special committee composed of people, including officials from my Department, with a deep knowledge of this problem.  We hope to come forward, as soon as possible, with a solution.  Certainly, there will be an attempt to solve this very difficult problem.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Toole said that the provision of houses is the responsibility of the Minister for Finance and the Minister for the Environment.  Is that true?  Is it the responsibility of the Government, either through the Minister for Finance or the Minister for the Environment, to provide houses for everybody?  I do not think it is.  The individual has the responsibility to provide his own house.  There are categories who cannot and never would be in a position to provide their own houses. The State has a responsibility there, obviously exercised through the Minister for the Environment and the Minister for Finance.  There are further categories for whom the State provides structures and means of getting finance.  Grants are part of the encouragement to build houses. But I am not sure that it is the responsibility of the Minister for Finance or the Minister for the Environment to provide a house for everybody.  I quite strongly disagree with Senator O'Toole on that. Perhaps he did not mean it quite as bluntly as I am putting it but that appears to be what he was saying.  It is the Minister's responsibility to organise the housing market and to provide houses for people who are not and never could be in a position to provide houses for themselves. After that, it is the individual's responsibility to provide and pay for his own house.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Toole also said that the <Col N="1750" /> mortgage subsidy scheme has gone bad. That is not so.  The mortgage subsidy scheme will still be available to people who qualify.  That is not quite as attractive a scheme when one reads the details as it appeared to be when it was announced.  I will not put it any stronger than that.  Anybody who qualifies for the mortgage subsidy scheme will get that subsidy.  The difference will be that it will be channelled back to the agency and will come off the debt owed by the borrower to the agency.</P>
    <P>The Senator also wanted to know what I meant by saying the operation would be grafted on to the SDA loan scheme. Local authorities have over many years operated the SDA loan scheme very efficiently and tribute must be paid to them in this regard as well.  I do not see any point in setting up a whole new range of offices throughout the country like building societies or banks to operate it.  The local authorities are extremely competent and I intend to use the expertise that is available in these offices to handle the loans and the agency.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke referred to the record of our predecessors in regard to housing, particularly local authority housing.  I have referred to that already and I accept what he says.  He and Senator Carey referred to the difficulty of the house and the site having to be mortgaged back to the agency and the red tape that has to be gone through before one can get one's money.  Unfortunately, I do not think it would be possible to cut much of that red tape.  The agency will be responsible to the Government and the Government could not be seen to be lending money to people without proper titles being established to the house and the land on which it is built.  But the agency will be able to help in that it will not be waiting for the completion of the house before giving out the loan but will give a series of payments throughout the building of the house. There is no intention, of course, of diminishing the powers of the local councils in that regard.</P>
    <P>Senator Burke inquired about guarantors.  Frankly, I am surprised that there are still local authorities looking for guarantors in this regard.  Most of them <Col N="1751" /> take a very sensible attitude to this.  They know most of their customers or they can make inquiries locally about any person looking for a loan from them.  I would hope that wherever this practice is still in existence, the local authority would desist from it.  The housing agency will certainly not be engaging in it.</P>
    <P>I agree with Senator Hussey when he said that he was reluctant to see more semi-State boards being set up.  I tend generally to share that point of view.  But this is quite exceptional because &mdash; and this point was made by Senator Bruton &mdash; for the first time we are getting into the housing sector money from pension funds and from life insurance offices which has not been available for housing. Obviously, when pension funds are invested it must be clear to the people who have money invested in them that the money for buying their pensions and which they have entrusted to the pension office is safely invested so that when they reach the age of 65 pensions will be available to them.  It is for that reason that I want this to be seen to be a responsible agency, properly funded and recognised not only by the people who get loans because they will be guaranteed by the Minister but also by the public who invest in pension funds, as an agency that has status and backing that will safeguard what is essentially their savings.</P>
    <P>Senator Cranitch welcomed the Minister's right to give instructions to the agency.  That is, in fact, one of the key clauses in the Bill; the Minister retains for himself the power to indicate to the agency how he would like to see the scheme operating.  Senator Cranitch is right to identify that.  He also inquired about the limits and the size of the houses for which money would be lent.</P>
    <P>There is a price limitation in that nobody can borrow more than £22,000. It could be argued that somebody who is building a house for £100,000 would make use of the agency to borrow the £22,000 and supply the balance of £78,000 himself.  It is most unlikely that somebody who would be buying that type of house would be using the agency because it is not an attractive proposition <Col N="1752" /> for somebody like that.  It was mentioned that, on the other end of the scale, somebody on £1,000 per year might use the agency.  Nobody on £1,000 a year would saddle himself with a debt of £22,000, no matter how attractive it was, or how long term the repayments were.  Somebody on so small an income certainly would not be buying his own house.  Generally, a grant is available to those people who would be using the agency funds and the grant is payable on houses from 35 square metres up to 125 square metres.  So in that sense the agency funds would be limited to nothing below 35 square metres and nothing above 125 square metres.</P>
    <P>I have already referred to the point, correctly identified by Senator Bruton, that is, the importance of, for the first time, getting pension funds into the housing market.  He also immediately spotted the reason for the exclusion of single people from various schemes.  Before I conclude I want to say that this new agency and the funds available through it &mdash; I mentioned this a number of times in the Dáil yesterday &mdash; will not be attractive to everybody as a means of providing money for themselves to build houses. Anybody who can afford to put together the deposit of £8,000 or £10,000 will still use the SDA loan scheme because, as Senator Bruton said, it is quite massively subsidised to the tune of 5 or 6 per cent, because the money is lent at 12½ per cent.  If one is earning under £7,000 a year one has a choice between using this scheme or the SDA scheme. The present trend is for people to get married much younger than heretofore so that it will not apply so much to young people who would find it difficult to put together the deposit now required under the SDA loans scheme, which is limited to £14,000 and the SDA type house would be £24,000 or £25,000.  So, taking off the grant and even the mortgage subsidy which is paid six months later, there is a big gap to be bridged.  Also, somebody who does not mind paying a very high percentage of his income in the early years may still go to a building society but on SDA houses people could pay £160 or £180 a month on an income of <Col N="1753" /> £8,000.  Many people cannot afford that. This provides an alternative way for both those categories.  That is that they will pay, in the initial years, only about 18 per cent of their income.  But the price for not having to put together a mortgage and for not being obliged to pay this high percentage of income repayments is that the shortfall on what they pay in the initial period is moved forward and becomes part of their debt to the agency and must be picked up as they go through life.  People who would be very attracted by this scheme are young people with no money who see themselves as not alone getting the normal wage increases through their lifetime but getting promotion in their jobs so that the salary they receive through their lives will be increasing.  There was a lot of doubt about its attractiveness yesterday in the Dáil.  I do not share that doubt.  Time alone will tell.  In the meantime I would like to thank the Senators for giving the Bill such a warm reception.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Housing Finance Agency Bill, 1981:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Housing Finance Agency Bill, 1981: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed that the operations of the agency will commence?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Minister for the Environment (Mr. P. Barry) Peter Barry">
      <NameTxt>Minister for the Environment (Mr. P. Barry)</NameTxt>
      <P>I would hope that the agency will be able to invite applications for loans in the next five or six weeks and that the first bonds will be issued in about three months time.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 3 and 4 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1754" /> SECTION 5.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 5 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>On the rate of interest, will it be a fixed or a variable rate?  If money is lent to local authorities, what rate will it be lent at to the authority and at what rate will the borrower be able to borrow it from the local authority?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>If at any stage in life the borrower went through a difficult patch and could not meet the repayments, what is the provision for such an eventuality?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this agency is to attract funds that would be inflation proof as far as the lender of those funds to the agency is concerned. That interest rate will have to be above the inflation rate of the moment.  Because the agency must be self-financing, that would be reflected in the interest rates being charged to the borrower.  But the borrower is protected from that inflation rate by the fact that he will be paying only a fixed percentage of his income throughout his lifetime.  Each individual transaction will be different because of different incomes and the length of time of the loan.</P>
      <P>In regard to Senator O'Rourke's point, if a person falls on hard times or loses his job, the period of the loan can be lengthened; it is unique in that respect.  The SDA loan does not take any account of that nor do the building societies.  With the SDA loan as with a building society loan one is committed to the repayment contracted throughout the lifetime of the loan no matter how one's circumstances change during that 20 or 25 years.  Under the agency one is committed to repaying the loan of course but one can reorganise the loan if one falls on hard times; the 18 per cent will apply to the new lower income.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I apologise for not being here earlier to have heard the Minister's speech but I have read it.  On that point, the Minister says that the £3,000 mortgage subsidy presently operated would go back to the lending agency to <Col N="1755" /> be spread over the operation again.  I fear that the full value of it would not be applicable to the applicant again as it would be directly now.  Has the Minister a fear that this agency will push the prices of houses through the roof?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>The applicant who is entitled to the grant will get the full benefit of it and as it is paid out by the Government, not as a £3,000 grant but over a period of time, it will be credited to the account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>An actual credit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  There is always some fear that the price of houses will rise as more money becomes available to people to buy them.  Until we can get the supply of houses to exceed the demand, as long as there is competition for houses and the money is there to fuel that competition, then the price of houses will move ahead.  As long as two people are looking for the one house and they both have money then the price of that house will go very high.  But if there are two houses with only one buyer then the price of those houses will come down.  We are continually striving to get ourselves into that position where the supply of houses will be greater than the demand.  That would be the real brake on the inflation in house price.  But as long as demand exceeds supply the tendency will be, unless we continually bring in controls such as the CRV system, for the price to move ahead.  We must be continuously on guard against that.  Also individuals must be on their guard to ensure that, in their enthusiasm to become house owners, they are not paying more than the house is worth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielKiely" hpid="Mr. D. Kiely Mr. D. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister not think that he will drive thousands of people towards local authority houses? Would he not agree that this scheme is directed completely towards the more well-off people in our community?  What about the man who gets into bad health and has to go on social welfare?  Will he have to pay the same 16 or 18 per cent or <Col N="1756" /> Whatever the rate is?  Does this not leave all sorts of loopholes for a man who is working today getting a reasonably large loan from this authority of £22,000 or £23,000, going on social welfare immediately and staying on it for the next 25 or 30 years and having his mortgage completely taken care of?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I would hope that there would be more discernment used in the issuing of these loans than to give them to somebody like that because no other agency would issue loans to people like that.  Contrary to what Senator Kiely is saying, this will not drive thousands of people towards local authority houses.  In fact, it might be beneficial in taking people off the local authority housing lists, people who are on them now purely because they cannot put together a deposit to buy their own house.  In that regard, it will have the reverse effect.  For the same reason it certainly is not geared towards the better-off.  In fact, the better-off would have no interest in a scheme like this.  It is the people who cannot put together a deposit, or people who are not willing to pay or, indeed, could not afford to pay 43 to 45 per cent of their income every year to a building society who would be attracted to this scheme.  The better-off will still go to banks, insurance companies or building societies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister mentioned the question of supply and demand.  On the question of availability of houses, under the present schemes of local authority housing the Department make it very attractive for the tenant to purchase that local authority house.  I have always been of the opinion that it would be better if the Department made it more attractive for that tenant to build his own house, having been a tenant for so long. There are at the present time some additional advantages that the local authority tenant has in so far as instead of getting £14,000 he can avail of an £18,000 loan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another scheme, the low-rise mortgage loan.  If, instead of actually losing the house to the local authority, the Department encouraged the tenant to <Col N="1757" /> build his own house by added incentives, so that when the tenant would be leaving that house it would be the property of the local authority again, that would alleviate some of the great housing problems that there are.  The unfortunate thing is that, very often, the local authority house is purchased by the existing tenant thus tying it up for good and all.  But if there was an added incentive of financial assistance to construct his own house the tenant could vacate his existing tenancy and make it available for future tenants.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I see the point Senator Burke is making.  He is suggesting that when a tenant who has been a tenant-purchaser moves out into a private estate the local authority should step in and buy that house from him at the market rate. Is that correct?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  At the present time there are very attractive schemes for the tenant to purchase the house.  Therefore he stays in that house and it is never available thereafter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>The logic of what Senator Burke is saying is that we should withdraw these special schemes for local authority tenants to purchase local authority houses&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>And transfer the money to more attractive individual construction purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I will look at that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the house area change under this Bill?  The Minister mentioned something about a ceiling of 1,246 sq. ft. that exists under the SDA scheme.  Does that change?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the SDA loan scheme repayments can be made on a 6-monthly basis or on a monthly basis. Does that change?  If an individual inherits a home and thereby becomes the legal owner of a dwelling which may be in very poor shape, is he deemed to be a first-time <Col N="1758" /> purchaser when he applies for one of the new loans under this heading?  Has the question concerning the spouse been cleared up?  Or does the same regulation as was introduced here recently obtain whereby one must either be married or must get the signature of one's spouse on all the documents being prepared?  Does that still obtain or do I take it that this is not necessary under the new scheme?  I hope this is so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBruton" hpid="Mr. R. Bruton Mr. R. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>In subsection (5) about default it is mentioned that in the event of default the house would go back to the housing agency as landlord.  What would be the terms of the tenancy there?  Would it be an ordinary local authority tenancy with differential rent and so on?</P>
      <P>-Subsection (6) seems to indicate that the agency or authority may use the house for purposes of its own and dispose of it as it thinks fit.  Is there any security of tenure for the person in the event of default such as in the case a Senator mentioned, where a person becomes long-term unemployed and cannot afford the repayments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to second-hand houses and persons who would be at present eligible for the mortgage subsidy scheme which replaced low-rise mortgage, would the same system of judgment of that person's eligibility for low-rise mortgage scheme now be used for the mortgage subsidy?  I am referring to that on behalf of people who are living in overcrowded conditions or bad circumstances.  Will the same conditions pertain for the suitability of that person for a loan under the housing finance agency as at present pertains under the SDA loan scheme from the county councils?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is quite a good trend, and an admirable one, where couples start off, perhaps, in a lower-priced house and, to use the fashionable term, through upward social mobility they are able to better themselves.  As their circumstances improve they improve their housing. Under this new scheme, for them to sell their house and buy another would not be as attractive and not as realisable as in <Col N="1759" /> the earlier SDA loan scheme, whereby after ten or twelve years the repayment amount is not so much and, therefore, they are able to see and cash in and buy again as perhaps their family would grow larger or as their circumstances would get better.  Does the Minister think that this scheme will strictly limit persons for their lifetime perhaps to one house regardless of how their circumstances might change.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I will take Senator O'Toole's point first.  In regard to the repayment period, that would really be a matter for the agency but I would imagine they will operate a choice of paying six monthly or monthly.  This option will be available.  It will be a matter for themselves. I answered the point about the square footage.  There is no limitation on the square footage of a house but, of course, there is a limitation in the sense that most of the people who will be applying for money through the agency will also be looking for the grant and there is a limitation on the grant.  There is a limitation in the sense that most of the people who apply for money through the agency will also be looking for the grant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Even if a person is building a house?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes. The Senator spoke also about a person who inherits a house. The scheme states that they must be first-time purchasers, not first time owners or occupiers.  The person who inherits a house will be making his first purchase through the agency and, therefore, he will qualify.  As regards the spouse, I was hoping to avoid politics &mdash; this is a much gentler place than the other House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not include it as a political ploy.  I should like to have it defined.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>In my case, she is about 5'7&rdquo;.  The inclusion of a spouse's income for the purpose of an SDA loan goes back to last March.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1760" />
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, the new regulation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a point of order but the Senator is entitled to make a contribution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Prior to this, single persons were eligible to apply for loans.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>No, that is the point I am making.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>The directive of 27 July&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>No, the directive of 6 March.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>There is confusion on this.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>Prior to the Coalition taking office a single person could apply for a loan and get it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinJOTooke" hpid="Mr. O'Toole Mr. O'Toole">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Toole</NameTxt>
      <P>That was a regulation brought in after June and not in March. That is what I want the Minister to define. Are single people eligible for this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought what Senator O'Toole was referring to was the fact that for the purposes of an SDA loan a wife's and husband's income are combined. They get special treatment inasmuch as they are entitled under this to get loans up to £27,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator O'Rourke made the point about people who have been accustomed to making a profit through the sale of their house and purchasing a new house. It will not be as attractive for them to do that now because they are not paying debts they owe in the first years of their mortgage and transferring them forward to later years.  It is an accumulated debt as far as they are concerned and if they sell their house the profit they make from the purchase time to the selling time <Col N="1761" /> would not be as great as if they did not owe this money.</P>
    <P>Senator Bruton spoke about subsections (5) and (6).  The same situation applies to SDA loans.  If somebody defaults on their debt the agency will have the right to repossess the house. The person will have no right of tenure at that stage but would have a right, because of being dispossessed, to apply for local authority housing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielKiely" hpid="Mr. D. Kiely Mr. D. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister speaking about evictions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no point in introducing that note at this stage.  I am not talking about myself or of the Senator as a county councillor or as a Member of this House evicting anybody from a house.  The normal practice is that if somebody cannot meet the repayments on his debt, be it a county council loan or bank or insurance company finance, the holder of the papers of that house is entitled under the law to repossess the house.  There is no point in trying to throw in an emotional phrase like eviction which is eighteenth century in concept as far as the Irish mentality is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielKiely" hpid="Mr. D. Kiely Mr. D. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not meant that way.  What I meant was that if a person gets into difficulty, which will happen in this case &mdash; for example, a person with a big income could become ill and be unable to meet his repayments &mdash; is there a guarantee that the agency will put him on the differential rent system and guarantee him his tenancy for life?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>They cannot guarantee his tenancy in that sense because he entered into a contract with the agency to repay, in the prescribed manner, funds which he borrowed from them to build a house, nor can the agency stop him selling the house as long as the funds are repaid. There is contractual right on both sides. If a man becomes ill he can go the agency and renegotiate with them the terms under which the loan will be repaid, for example, at the same percentage of a lower income over a greater number of <Col N="1762" /> years.  If that cannot be done he can be taken on as a tenant of a local authority house but not the same house.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make a point that Senator O'Rourke made earlier. Every time SDA loans are increased the price of building goes much higher than inflation at the time.  The famous £1,000 grant did exactly the same.  The Minister, in reply to Senator O'Rourke, said that where there are two houses for sale if there are three, four or five people to buy them, naturally the price will be much higher.  Building, for some unknown reason, perhaps for want of money, has eased off.  Nobody seems to be buying houses.  That is understandable because money is not available.  I am afraid that when this money becomes available the price of a house will increase substantially over inflation.  In the past 12 months our inflation rate was around 20 per cent.  If it was, I guarantee that in the building business there were price increases of at least 25 per cent if not more over the same period.  When the money becomes available these prices will go even higher than 25 per cent.  It has happened.  I do not know what can be done to prevent it from happening. There should be some machinery within the agency to monitor prices.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Each time the SDA loan rose, from 4½ per cent to 7 per cent to 9 per cent, the price of a comparable local authority house that a person might buy rose accordingly.  It would rise over the inflation rate at the time.  People will get the idea that because there is so much money available to a borrower the price of the house will go up.  We will be in a situation where the price of a house will be above the £22,000 envisaged as the loan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I share the concern of everybody about the prices of houses and how quickly they reflect other cost increases.  The prices of houses over the last seven or eight years have increased somewhat over the rate of inflation but not to a great degree.  There is a certificate of reasonable value administered by <Col N="1763" /> my Department.  This will be strictly administered to try to prevent what Senator O'Rourke and Senator Reynolds are saying, that when more money is made available it drives up the prices of houses. I suppose we will never have a perfect world where that will not happen.  I will instruct the agency and sharpen up the CRV section of my Department to ensure that this does not happen.  The rules will not be relaxed in any way when the agency starts to work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="UlickBurke" hpid="Mr. Burke Mr. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>In the case of a certificate of reasonable value being available for a new house, if the loan is used for the purchase of a secondhand house will there be some corresponding certificate of reasonable value and will the certificate of exemption still be available for a person who builds his own house?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, for the exemption. One could not give a certificate of reasonable value for a secondhand house. The Senator will appreciate that.  I hope to have somebody on the board of the agency who will have knowledge of the value of secondhand houses and will be able to give guidance in that regard.  The agency will have to get a valuation on second-hand houses as is done normally for lending purposes.  Locally the operators of the SDA office will know whether a house is value for money or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards the money for co-operative housing, in some county councils there is a scheme where the cost of the site of the house under the co-operative scheme can be added to the SDA loan.  Does the Minister envisage that the same scheme will operate for co-operative housing under the new agency?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>That scheme has finished.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Recently?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>No, January 1980.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Where they had the <Col N="1764" /> scheme or are continuing with it, will the Minister allow that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>It is nearly two years ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>In my county there were already schemes entered into and they allowed them to run.  Would the Minister not see that the same scheme should operate for co-operative housing? The cost of the sites was added on to the SDA loans.  Could this be done with the new housing agency?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>They are getting a much bigger loan than before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I know they are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is looking for something on top of that again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>It was a facility for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to help cooperatives and encourage them.  That is one of the reasons why the increased loan is available to them.  About 80 per cent of their members have incomes under £9,000 a year.  However I should not like to move them ahead of people in local authority housing.  The attractions of the scheme should be equal for both categories.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBruton" hpid="Mr. R. Bruton Mr. R. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the housing finance agencies be part of the public capital programme?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>No, public sector borrowing.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 7 to 9, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1765" /> SECTION 10.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 10 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister envisage that there would be an upper limit to the total amount available for borrowing under this agency?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  It is written in at £200 million at present.  The agency will also be getting in money as people start repaying mortgages.  If, for example, £25 million is borrowed next year, then it may take up to eight years to reach £200 million. During those eight years the agency will be getting money back as people start to repay their loans.  So, in fact, they would not reach the £200 million.  If in 15 or 20 years time, because of the depreciation of money, £200 million was thought not to be sufficient by the Minister of the day then he can go back to the Oireachtas and have it raised to £300 million, £500 million or whatever figure would be appropriate at that time.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 11 to 14, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 15.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 15 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceManning" hpid="Mr. Manning Mr. Manning">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Manning</NameTxt>
      <P>I am unhappy with subsection (1).  I accept the principle, which is the general practice, that directors of State agencies should not be Members of either House of the Oireachtas or of the European Assembly.  I know this cannot be changed now but perhaps it could be in the future.  When a director becomes a candidate he is disqualified from being a director.  This is undesirable.  There are people on boards of directors of State companies who would have a great deal of expertise to offer if elected to either House.  They will be discouraged from attempting to become candidates by virtue of this.  If people decide that a person is worthy of being a Member of either House, then of course that person obviously must cease to be a director but <Col N="1766" /> should be given the chance of being a candidate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielKiely" hpid="Mr. D. Kiely Mr. D. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>Can members of local authorities be directors of the agency?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardBruton" hpid="Mr. R. Bruton Mr. R. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Senator Manning.  As regards people working in the agency, I do not know why it is suggested that politicians are not fit to work in it or in any other body.  If the issue is that they are not capable of holding down two jobs, let that be the condition that is written into the law.  It is relevant in the Seanad where people are selected for their vocational interests.  People from a housing agency or youth employment agency would have invaluable contribution to make in the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatsyLawlor" hpid="Mrs. Lawlor Mrs. Lawlor">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Lawlor</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not agree with the last two speakers.  I should like to congratulate the Minister for inserting this clause.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I intend to disagree with it.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatsyLawlor" hpid="Mrs. Lawlor Mrs. Lawlor">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Lawlor</NameTxt>
      <P>This clause is a very good one.  It should be inserted into legislation dealing with all State boards and agencies. Members of the Houses could make very fine contributions but, on the other hand, would give a party political input.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with everybody who says that if one is a Member of either House one should not be on a board of directors.  I cannot understand why when one is nominated to be a Member of the Seanad one should automatically cease to be a member of a board.  The snag is that this is standard and one would have to go to every parish priest in the country and every Government Minister to get it changed.  It cannot be done in some legislation but must be changed right across the board.  I quite agree that mere nomination to the Dáil or Seanad should not <Col N="1767" /> debar one from being a member of a board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielKiely" hpid="Mr. D. Kiely Mr. D. Kiely">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Kiely</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator's question would rightly arise under section 2, the formation and registration of the Agency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>How many people will be on this board?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>The articles of association state between three and nine.  I see them as being representative of the public and private sectors.  We have not decided fully on it yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>Builders' providers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryORourke" hpid="Mrs. O'Rourke Mrs. O'Rourke">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. O'Rourke</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope that some representative of local authorities will be on this board.  I also feel strongly that there should be female representation because housing is particularly a woman's domain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That does not arise on this section.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 16 and 17 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 18 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister made reference to the way people would be paid. People should be paid about four times. Local authorities, building societies and everyone in the building industry would agree that there are very long delays in payment.  The board should do something to expedite payment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not arise under this section.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1768" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJReynolds" hpid="Mr. Reynolds Mr. Reynolds">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Reynolds</NameTxt>
      <P>I take the point but did not want to miss an opportunity to make the comment.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Sitting suspended at 1.20 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Situation in Poland:" RHead="Motion">
    <Title>Situation in Poland: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GemmaHussey" hpid="Mrs. G. Hussey Mrs. G. Hussey">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. G. Hussey</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann takes note of the present situation in Poland.</P>
      <P>This motion was tabled because concern was expressed earlier today from all sides of this House.  I believe this concern echoes that of the Irish people about developments in Poland, a country with which we feel a special affinity not only because it is fundamentally an agricultural nation but because of its religious ethos so similar to our own.</P>
      <P>It is at times like this it is brought home to us how high a value we should place on our hard-won system of parliamentary democracy.  This painful struggle in a country which has had too much suffering already in this century grieves all of us who must witness it, as we do daily on our television screens and in our newspapers. I am sure that in raising this matter today we all earnestly hope ways will be found to bring the Polish nation safely through this saddening and apparently deepening crisis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Minister for Foreign Affairs (Professor Dooge) James C.I. Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Foreign Affairs (Professor Dooge)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government, together with their partners in the European Community, are following events in Poland closely and with deep concern.  Following a discussion of the situation by the Foreign Ministers of the Ten during their <Col N="1769" /> London meeting, a statement was issued last Tuesday in the following terms:</P>
      <P>The Foreign Ministers of the member states of the European Community are concerned at the development of the situation in Poland and the imposition of martial law and the detention of trade unionists.  They have profound sympathy for the Polish people in this tense and difficult time.  They look to all signatories of the Helsinki Final Act to refrain from any interference in the internal affairs of the Polish People's Republic.  They look to Poland to solve these problems herself and without the use of force, so that the process of reform and renewal can continue.</P>
      <P>Foreign Ministers of the Ten are continuing to follow events in Poland with particular attention, and agreed to remain in close consultation on this question.</P>
      <P>We in Ireland have always felt a special kinship with the Polish people whose history and traditions have so many parallels with our own.  For this reason the Irish people feel with a particular keenness the general anxiety concerning recent developments in Poland.</P>
      <P>The concern in the past few days was added to by the scarcity of direct information from the scene.  As you will be aware, official Polish radio broadcasts yesterday confirmed that seven workers had been killed in clashes in Katowice. These deaths can only be seen as a tragic aggravation of a situation which has already brought Poland to the brink of economic and civil disaster.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the tense conditions of Poland today, it is imperative that those who have assumed primary responsibility for the maintenance of order and who wield the instruments of power should show the utmost restraint.  There is also heavy responsibility on the Polish authorities to respect basic human rights and freedoms in the most concrete way by not violating these rights in the defence of order.  It is of the greatest importance that the Polish people themselves should be allowed to resolve their internal social and political conflicts without interference or the threat of coercion from outside.  It is <Col N="1770" /> evident that the trial facing the Polish people is extremely difficult, but the task of restoring social peace and civic unity to Poland will only be achieved in an enduring way by a return to negotiation and reconciliation in which all elements of the Polish nation must be allowed to play their part.  This aim will not be served by large-scale official repression and violence.</P>
    <P>As I speak, the Review meeting of the Conference on Security and Co-operation in Europe is in session in Madrid. Virtually all the countries of Europe, including Poland, are represented there. The Helsinki Final Act, with which that Conference is concerned, contains a set of principles and a programme for action to which all the member states have given their solemn commitment.  The Final Act contains specific provisions with regard to human rights and fundamental freedoms which all states acknowledged should form the basis for a more secure and better life for all the peoples in Europe.  It is crucial to the future of the enterprise undertaken in Helsinki and for the credibility of detente in Europe that Poland be allowed to resolve its problems peacefully and without the use of force.</P>
    <P>The Irish delegation to the Madrid Conference will speak later today to stress on behalf of the Government the concern with which we view events in Poland and to reiterate the sentiments which we all share.</P>
    <P>The Government have already, through the EEC, provided a substantial amount of food aid to Poland and are concerned to ensure that this aid reaches the Polish people.  They are prepared to facilitate fully the efforts of non-governmental organisations in channelling food, medical and other humanitarian assistance to Poland.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are deeply distressed by the situation which has evolved in Poland in the past few days.  We have many things in common with the Polish people.  I know we say that about many countries but I think in regard to Poland it is particularly true.  Because we have so many affinities with them we are in a position to appreciate the position they <Col N="1771" /> are in at the moment, to sympathise with them and to feel for the crisis in which they are involved.  It is particularly sad that it should have happened at this time. It would have been critical and very sad at any time but in the Christmas season for a nation to whom Christmas means so much, for a country which has a deep religious feeling and for whom this season is of particular importance, it is particularly sad that it should have happened to them at this time.</P>
      <P>We have watched with admiration the struggle by the Polish people, by Solidarity, in recent months against doctrinaire policies, restrictive measures and particularly against the dead hand of Communist administration.  We have watched with admiration the struggle they have made to introduce at least an element of democracy into the Polish system.  All of us I am sure, hoped that that struggle would be successful and peaceful.</P>
      <P>The Minister has stressed that our policy must be one of advocating non-interference by the USSR and indeed by any other country and I fully support that policy.  Obviously, we cannot interfere ourselves.  It would be quite wrong for the European Community to interfere and, of course, most of all it is imperative that the USSR be discouraged from making any attempt to interfere.  This is a matter for the Polish people.  They must be allowed to resolve it in accordance with their own methods and views of how it should be resolved.</P>
      <P>A great deal has been achieved by the struggle in recent months.  We have been told by the present Polish Government that most of these achievements will be maintained, that there is going to be no effort to go back to the situation that existed before Solidarity came to take action.  I hope this pledge will be honoured and realised and that the struggle so far will not have been in vain.  All we can do is to hope and pray that the struggle, the sacrifice and the efforts that were made will have a successful and a peaceful outcome.  Our thoughts and prayers are certainly with the Polish people at this time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1772" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>The tragic details filtering out of Poland since the military clamp-down call for an urgent and sustained response from Ireland and elsewhere in the free world.  On behalf of the Labour group I join with the other groups in this House and with bodies such as the Irish Congress of Trade Unions in condemning the military take-over and calling for the immediate release of the many thousands interned since last Sunday.</P>
      <P>For most of us it is frightening to witness how ruthlessly a popular movement can be crushed by military power and how effectively a total media black-out can be imposed even in the eighties, the age of sophisticated telecommunications. However, as news has leaked out, it has only confirmed the worst fears: the deaths of at least seven miners in Silesia, hundreds injured in the course of struggies between the soldiers and workers or students in various Polish cities, and, ominously, the arrest and internment of as many as 49,000 Polish people in the space of five days.  These unfortunate people who are interned have been herded into two enormous concentration camps &mdash; one apparently outside Warsaw and the other in Gdansk &mdash; where they endure appalling conditions in sub-zero temperatures and are isolated from their families.</P>
      <P>But words and expressions of sympathy are cheap.  A more sustained effort and structured support from the West towards the Polish people are needed at this critical time.  Before the military take-over, and the purported justification for that take-over, Poland was collapsing under the combination of enormous foreign debt and gross inefficiency in the Government's administration.  The consequence for the ordinary people there was chaos: serious food shortages in the cities, lack of basic essentials in the shops, confusion and frustration everywhere. The West responded by sending food parcels and other essential items in.  Western banks were discussing ways and means of rolling over the overdue interest charges and the debt of somewhere in the region of 2.4 billion dollars falling due for repayment in 1981.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now the United States administration <Col N="1773" /> appears to be adopting a hardline approach on further supplies of food aid and the US banks seem to be emulating this with a similar hardline stance on debt repayments.  How can this help a beleaguered people and a collapsing economy? Is it not likely to lead to more repression and, thereby, to increase the prospect of Soviet intervention, with terrible potential consequences for peace and stability in the world?</P>
    <P>Ireland must use her voice and influence within the European Community, particularly in the context of European political co-operation, to urge a more flexible and humane response to developments in Poland.  This includes practical help both in the provision of food aid and other essential help to the Polish people, and also on working out arrangements for servicing the huge Polish debt to enable that economy to be stabilised.</P>
    <P>At such a critical time &mdash; when lives literally are at stake &mdash; we must be careful not to raise false expectations of western intervention, as happened with tragic consequences in Hungary in 1956.  But neither must we threaten such severe economic sanctions that we precipitate worse repression internally and increase the prospect of direct Soviet intervention. We should support the Polish community, the Red Cross and other agencies in this country in sending vital food and necessities to Poland.  We should work towards a collective European response which is more flexible, more mature and more humane than the stance presently adopted by the US administration.</P>
    <P>It is fair to say that there will be less joy at Christmas than usual this year in Ireland because of our own problems on this island.  But now we share the agony of the Polish people with whom we have, as has been mentioned, such affinity and links and a somewhat similar historical experience.  They must have not just our sympathy but our sustained support.  The opportunity to discuss our concern in this House forms part of that response.  I would like on behalf of the Labour group to express my gratitude to the Minister for consenting to be present in the House today so that we could express our collective concern.</P>
    <Col N="1774" />
    <Speaker pid="CiaranMurphy" hpid="Professor Murphy Professor Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Professor Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I share the expressions of concern at the grave situation in Poland.  Just now in the news it was reported that the Austrian Chancellor described it as the gravest crisis yet to threaten European and world peace.  On that score alone this motion is timely and I, too, appreciate the Minister's statement and presence in the House.</P>
      <P>I am speaking for a certain strand of public opinion.  I am not so sure I am speaking for my fellow Independent Senators because the definition of an Independent is, of course, that he is independent of other Independents.  I share the general sentiments, though not some of the loaded political emphasis, in the contributions I have heard.  It is true that there are historic affinities between Ireland and Poland.  In fact, it is of interest that 19th-century observers, political scientists and national philosophers found the comparison between Ireland and Poland even from the early 19th-century a striking one.  It is not necessary to labour the details of the comparison.  The affinity is there and we share it.  It was good to read that Ireland has shared in the general attempt to bring relief to the Polish people in terms of economic aid and the supply of credits for the purchase of intervention beef and so on.  As Senator Robinson says, we want more of this kind of thing.</P>
      <P>I am not so sure that we should go beyond that.  I am not so sure that we should lecture the Polish Government at present or that we should confidently express opinions about what should or should not be done in what is, after all, an internal affair.  Despite all the predictions of the hawks, the Soviet Union has not intervened in the past 18 months. Indeed, it seems to me that the Soviet Union should be given due credit for its prudence at least, if nothing else, in not intervening.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The west has not been without fault in the past 18 months in its attitude to the Polish crisis.  Unfounded hopes had been raised.  There has somehow been the vague suggestion that Poland can be converted into a western-style democracy. Certain hard realities have to be faced.  It <Col N="1775" /> may be possible to give socialism, indeed it is to be hoped that socialism will be given a more human face in Poland and elsewhere in the eastern world, but the Polish Government &mdash; and again I cite the RTE news I have just heard &mdash; have made it clear that socialism will not be undermined in Poland.  Senator Ryan referred to the hope that the struggle of Solidarity and so on over the past year or so would not be in vain.  A number of people in Poland would take the view that there has been a longer struggle to establish socialism in Poland and its fellow-countries in the eastern bloc and that that struggle is not going to be in vain.</P>
    <P>These are realities which perhaps appear unfamiliar from this particular perspective on the fringe of western Europe but nonetheless they are realities. I believe that the western press and western governments have been somewhat irresponsible, if you like, in raising unfounded hopes and in inflating the crisis in almost daily predicting intervention by the Soviet Union.  That kind of self-fulfilling scaremongering cannot but aggravate the crisis.</P>
    <P>I may say also that the concern for free trade unions came from some surprising quarters over the past 18 months; I mean from administrations like that of President Reagan, who is no lover of trade unions, free or otherwise, and indeed from some domestic opinion here, the same kind of opinion which says that trade unions should be put in their place, that they are getting above themselves and so on but who are full of enthusiasm for Solidarity in Poland.  There are certain anomalies and contradictions in our attitude towards these matters.  We should keep in mind that not only are the Poles going through their own agony but that they are a pawn in the east-west struggle also.  The Soviet Union is not the only interferer: it is the most obvious interferer but it is not the only interferer in the situation.</P>
    <P>I would like to quote from the Taoiseach's speech which was published in the Eighteenth Report on the Developments in the European Communities <Col N="1776" /> which we began to discuss yesterday.  The Taoiseach recalls how the European Council in Luxembourg a year ago stated that:</P>
    <P>The Polish people should be free to face their internal problems in a peaceful manner and without outside interference. Any other attitude would have very serious consequences not only for Poland but for the world.</P>
    <P>I could not agree more but surely those words are capable of more than one meaning?  That they &ldquo;should be free to face their internal problems without outside interference&rdquo; applies all around and very much so.  That is what we should keep in mind today and that is also why I am happy that the motion is phrased in this neutral manner.  There is, indeed, little more that we can do in this House than take note of the present situation in Poland.  It would be very ill-advised of us to pontificate on the complex dimensions of the problem in Poland, as ill-advised, let us say, as it would be for a Polish legislative assembly to debate the situation in Northern Ireland.</P>
    <P>I agree fully with Senator Robinson that the decision of the American administration to cease aid in these circumstances was an extremely retrograde one.  The giving of economic help is putting our money where our mouth is in this situation. Beyond that I would deprecate any tendency on behalf of people in this House to tell the Poles how they should conduct their business.  We must beware in this grave crisis of giving the impression that we are emulating the <i>Skibbereen</i><i>Eagle.</i> With these considerable reservations I share with my fellow Senators deep concern about events in Poland.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceOConnell" hpid="Mr. O'Connell Mr. O'Connell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Connell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like, too, to place on record my own and most Senators' appreciation of the manner in which this House has been permitted to have the Minister here and to discuss this matter. If we in this House are to play our part within the constitutional framework we must be able to address ourselves with immediacy to the issues of the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I welcome the Minister's statement and his reassurance that our Government are <Col N="1777" /> reiterating our country's position in line with our historic traditions.  It is also good to know that the members of the European Economic Community, representing, as they do in a group, the vanguard of the European tradition of constitutional democracy, liberty and respect for human dignity, have also spoken.  Whilst I agree very much with the analysis made by Senator Murphy of the practical realities of the situation and the need to maintain a practical balance, it is impossible for many of us not to reach this situation without some kind of emotional reaction.  The question that we must ask is what can we do?  Is there anything else but words that we can offer?  Bitterly and very acutely I am reminded of the experience which many of us had in 1956 when we listened in utter frustration and helplessness to the pleas for help, in effect unheeded, of the people of Hungary in somewhat similar circumstances. Associated with that is the bitter taste of betrayal, still felt in my mind 25 years afterwards, when we heard behind the rumble of the tanks of Soviet imperialism the news that Britain and France had gone into Suez to try in vain to prop up the last remnants of the older western European version of colonialism and also in effect to discredit in the eyes of the Third World the better aspects of our civilisation.  When we read, see and hear day after day in all parts of the world as well as in Poland that tyranny is still alive, that the inhumanity of man to man continues not just unabated but enhanced and made more obscene by the wonders of modern technology, we are reminded of the pessimism enshrined in the words of the poet Matthew Arnold in his poem <i>Dover Beach</i> which is to be found in the New Oxford Treasury of English Verse, page 377:</P>
    <P>Ah, love, let us be true</P>
    <P>To one another! for the world, which seems</P>
    <P>To lie before us like a land of dreams,</P>
    <P>So various, so beautiful, so new,</P>
    <P>Hath really neither joy, nor love, nor light,</P>
    <P>No certitude, nor peace, nor help for pain;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1778" /> And we are here as on a darkling plain Swept with confused alarms of struggle and flight,</P>
    <P>Where ignorant armies clash by night.</P>
    <P>If our history means anything, if the age-long struggle of our people has any significance, it is that even at times like this we must have hope.  We must reject the counsels of pessimism.  We must resolve again and again that we will create a world order in which cannot happen with impunity the kind of thing that is happening today not just in Poland but in El Salvador and Karamoja and in all corners of the world where men, women and children are striving to live as human beings: we must strive for a world order in which peace and justice will prevail.  If our independence as a nation means anything, it means that we should stand up and be counted in the councils of the world for such an order, not just in vague theoretical terms but at every practical opportunity that arises.  We must change the system or lack of system as it exists. We must replace the jungle of the world economic social and political order with something more approximating to the targets and objectives of human aspirations. It also means that we in this island, the representatives of the people and also the ordinary men and women of all Ireland must take responsibility for our own future and bring to this beautiful country peace and justice, not only for our own sake and that of our children but so that we can play upon the stage of the world the role for which our history has so evidently prepared us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichealCranitch" hpid="Mícheál Cranitch Mícheál Cranitch">
      <NameTxt>Mícheál Cranitch</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar an gcéad dul síos fáiltím roimh an Aire agus guím gach rath ar a chuid oibre.  Is fear fiúntach, consiasach, macánta é agus táimid faoi chomaoin aige inniu ach go háirithe as ucht teacht isteach anseo agus éisteacht leis an díospóireacht seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some years ago during a Mass at one of the smaller chapels in Lourdes I had the privilege of meeting a Polish group. After Mass we got into conversation with them.  The leader of the group had served with the Polish Army during the last World War and had spent some time in <Col N="1779" /> England and later in the Six Counties. What amazed me, apart from the extraordinary devotion of this man and his group, was his knowledge of our history. He was able to place into perspective very accurately our status here, our conditions, our ambitions, our dreams in the Republic and our ethnic groups in the Six Counties.  He had an extraordinary grasp of our history and of what we stood for and what we hope to achieve some day. That for me was proof positive of the affinity in spirit and in mind and to some extent in physique between the Polish people and ourselves.  We had the misfortune to be situated alongside very powerful neighbours, nations whose purpose seemed to be always to extend their own frontiers without respect for anybody else's frontiers.  We had that similarity between us.  Now our hearts &mdash; I speak not alone for this House but for the whole of Ireland &mdash; bleed for the Polish people.  They have a colossal struggle in hands to establish what we take for granted, freedom.  We can come into this House and speak our minds.  We can meet each other in the lobbies, we can be very friendly with everybody and we can respect everybody's opinion.  We argue and discuss, but we have that freedom. Long may it live.</P>
    <P>Conditions in such nations as Poland are very difficult for people such as ourselves to understand.  You have to meet these people.  I have experience also of having had some friends, athletes, at the Olympics in the capital of Poland's neighbour, a very powerful nation.  Everything was very orderly and nice but these athletes and their supporters sensed the utter lack of personal freedom.  Everything was as it should be, so to speak.  Nobody had permission to speak about anything. Again I say, long live our freedom.</P>
    <P>Our hearts bleed for the Polish people and the Polish nation's greatest son, his Holiness, the present Pope.  I would suggest that, along with sending out such a resolution as this, there are things we can do, things we cannot do, things perhaps we may not do; but in so far as it lies within the Government's power to give any aid they will have the support and <Col N="1780" /> the gratitude of all the Irish people.  The Minister for Foreign Affairs is a very understanding man and will take our views back to the Government.  We live in extraordinary times.  This could be a flashpoint in Europe.  Maybe it is a testing time, but when the dust dies down I feel that freedom will triumph.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasWhitaker" hpid="Dr. Whitaker Dr. Whitaker">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Whitaker</NameTxt>
      <P>In Ireland we have watched with hope and admiration the re-emergence of democracy in Poland under the leadership of Lech Walesa, and so it is with distress and dismay that we now see this movement being beaten down behind closed doors with loss of life and massive and cruel internment.</P>
      <P>Experience shows that once a revolutionary movement gathers force it becomes difficult to contain.  Initial successes widen the horizon of expectations and extreme and imprudent elements become harder to control.  To the outside observer it would seem wiser if Solidarity had not pushed so hard so fast, if they had been content to consolidate their gains and ensure, if they could, the incorporation of democratic elements into a compromise system of government.  It was unfortunate that their aim could in the latter days have been represented in an extreme form such as an immediate take-over of power.  Russia and Communist Europe generally are in too unstable a state, political and economic, for a challenge of this significance to be passed over.  Few people realise that the eastern bloc is even more depresed, more stagnant economically, than the western world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, nothing in any way excuses repression, whether direct or indirect. One must hope that Poland will not be invaded by Russia, that other powers will not intervene and that the Polish Army. Government and Communist Party will return quickly to a respect for human rights and recognise the need to reach accommodation with such a large body of their fellow-citizens.  They need to do this if there is to be any restoration of communal order or economic co-operation &mdash; and there has been very little of it for years past &mdash; to preserve the integrity of that long-suffering, admirably <Col N="1781" /> brave and patriotic nation.  All we can do here is strongly support all the efforts of our own Government and of voluntary bodies to bring medical aid and food supplies to the suffering people of Poland.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCarroll" hpid="Mr. Carroll Mr. Carroll">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carroll</NameTxt>
      <P>I have nothing to say that will in any way add to the range of discussion which has already taken place on this topic, but I am concerned that this assembly would be as objective as possible in talking about the terrible situation which exists in Poland.  I have been impressed by the presentation from Senator Murphy which took that point as its central theme: the necessity for this assembly to be as objective as we can be, bearing in mind the paucity of information and the lack of knowledge which exists as far as the Polish situation is concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have an immediate interest in the sense that I identify with the protest from the Irish Congress of Trade Unions declared yesterday at the imprisonment of trade unionists and the attack on the trade union movement in Poland.  I must add that I and some of my colleagues have inadequate knowledge of the scene there and insufficient knowledge of how Solidarity were going about their business and whether they were going too fast, too slow, too radical, too moderate or whatever.  We must be careful that we do not pass judgment which in time will not be able to stand up.  As well as decrying any imprisonment of trade unionists I also deplore very vehemently the interference of the military organisation in Poland or elsewhere.  When soldiers or a Government supported by military take over control, we are then at a very critical stage.  The oppression and other problems which flow from military control are to be deplored.  I fear that once military people take over they want to hold on to the type of power and control which that <Col N="1782" /> gives them and it then becomes increasingly difficult for the ordinary people to return to some semblance of democratic activity in which human rights and civil liberty will be accepted as the norm.</P>
    <P>My identification with the resolution is on the basis that I oppose strongly the imprisonment of people who are about their ordinary business of trying to educate each other and to contribute to economic, social, political, spiritual and cultural democracy.  Equally I deplore the intervention of armed forces to dictate policies or subjugate people in no matter what part of the world.  In that contest I also deplore the intervention of American forces in El Salvador or anywhere else by way of advice or influence, as I deplore the intervention of international finance in trying to control the destiny of a nation through the conomic power that is within their grasp.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Minister for Foreign Affairs (Professor Dooge) James C.I. Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Foreign Affairs (Professor Dooge)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to my colleagues who have spoken here today.  I assure them that the Government, and my Department in particular, will endeavour to keep as closely in touch with this situation as possible.  We will remain in consultation with our colleagues of the European Economic Community.  It will be of help to me and the Government in determining our attitude as this situation develops to have had the benefit of the views Senators expressed here today.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I take this opportunity to wish each and everyone of my colleagues the blessings and joys of the season, and continued success and prosperity in 1982.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 2.50 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>