<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="16" Month="May" Year="1951" Vol="39" No="13" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 16 Bealtaine 1951" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 16 May 1951" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1103">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1103" /> Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Dissolution" RHead="of Dáil">
    <Title>Dissolution of Dáil.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before entering upon the Orders of the Day, I have to make an announcement as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1104" /> I have received from the Secretary to the President a copy of the Proclamation issued on the 7th May, 1951, dissolving Dáil Éireann and summoning that House to meet on the 13th June, 1951.</P>
    <P>I have given directions to have the copy of the Proclamation set out <i>in extenso</i> in the usual manner in the Journal of the House.  Consequent on this announcement it will also, of course, be printed in the Official Report of Debates.  Following is the Proclamation:&mdash;</P>
    <P Just="Center">FORÓGRA</P>
    <P Just="Center">(PROCLAMATION)</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">De bhun comhairle a thairg an Taoiseach dom faoi Alt 2 d'Airteagal 13 den Bhunreacht, déanaimse, SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH, Uachtarán na hÉireann, leis seo Dáil Éireann a lánscor Dé Luain, an 7ú lá de Bhealtaine, 1951, agus Dáil Éireann (a mbeidh a comhaltai arna dtoghadh san Olltoghchán seo chugainn) a ghairm agus a chomóradh chun teacht le chéile i gCathair Bhaile Átha Cliath Dé Céadaoin, an 13ú lá de Mheitheamh, 1951, ar a 3 a chlog san iarnóin chun pé gnó a dhéanamh a cuirfear faoina bráid.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Pursuant to an advice tendered to me by the Taoiseach under Section 2 of Article 13 of the Constitution, I, SEÁN T. Ó CEALLAIGH, President of Ireland, hereby dissolve Dáil Éireann on Monday, the 7th day of May, 1951, and summon and call together Dáil Éireann (the members whereof shall have been elected at the forthcoming General Election) to meet in the City of Dublin on Wednesday, the 13th day of June, 1951, at the hour of 3 o'clock in the afternoon for the despatch of such business as shall be submitted to it.</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>ARNA THABHAIRT FAOI MO LÁIMH AGUS FAOI MO SHÉALA AN 7ú LÁ SEO DE BHEALTAINE, 1951.</entry>
            <entry>GIVEN UNDER MY HAND AND SEAL THIS 7th DAY OF MAY, 1951.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">SEÁN T. Ó CHEALLAIGH,</P>
    <P Just="Center">UACHTARÁN NA HÉIREANN</P>
    <P Just="Center">(PRESIDENT OF IRELAND).</P>
    <P>SEÁN UA COISDEALBHA,</P>
    <P>TAOISEACH.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Death of Nuncio" RHead="Apostolic">
    <Title>Death of Nuncio Apostolic.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>Since our last meeting the death has taken place of His Excellency Most Rev. Monsignor Ettore Felici, the Nuncio Apostolic, after a period of less than two years in residence here.  As direct representative of His Holiness the Pope and Dean of the Diplomatic Corps in Dublin, Monsignor Felici was naturally entitled to the respect and loyalty of our people.  But to those who had the honour of meeting him he appeared not alone as a man of great intellectual attainments, a distinguished diplomat in the long tradition of the Vatican but also a friendly, unaffected priest, full of goodwill towards our country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Seanad Éireann is the only House of the Oireachtas in existence at the moment and I am sure that all the members will desire to be associated with the many expressions of sympathy which have been offered to His Holiness <Col N="1105" /> on the passing of his great representative in Ireland.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Senators rose in their places.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad">
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take the Intestates' Estates Bill and the approval of the Sugar (Prohibition of Import) Order to-day and not to take the motions.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Intestates' Estates Bill," RHead="1951&mdash;Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Intestates' Estates Bill, 1951&mdash;Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Section 1 put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinODwyer" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In Section 2, line 16, after the word &ldquo;intestate&rdquo; to delete remaining words of section and substitute the following: &ldquo;shall be subject to the following provisions.  The widow shall retain a life interest in the property and at her death the relatives of the deceased husband shall be entitled to half the property, and the other half may be disposed of by the widow by will, or in the event of her dying intestate it shall go to her relatives.  In the event of there being no relatives of the deceased husband the entire property may be disposed of by the widow by will, or, if she dies intestate, it will go to her relatives.  In the event of the widow dying intestate and leaving no relatives the entire property shall go to the husband's relatives.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I considered the debate on the last day and looked carefully over the Bill and I came to the conclusion that it was altogether too drastic and sweeping. It is a measure which should not be lightly passed as it creates a big revolution.  It is not, as it was described, a mere technicality.  The point was raised that under the existing law a widow was harshly treated, and I thought that that objection could be met by putting down this amendment, the effect of which is that on the husband's death the widow maintains a life interest in the property and after her death it is distributed between her family and the family of <Col N="1106" /> the deceased husband.  That, I think, meets the case, and is more suitable and just than the proposal in the Bill. I ask the House to accept this amendment as being very fair to the widow and to the family of the deceased husband.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Morrissey) Daniel Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Morrissey)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I could not accept the amendment.  If this amendment were accepted&mdash;certainly, in respect of the smaller estates&mdash;it would make the widow's position much worse than it is even under the existing law.  Under the existing law, where the estate is valued at £500 or less, the widow is entitled to it in full.  Where the estate exceeds £500, the widow is entitled to £500 absolutely plus half the remainder. The Senator's amendment would worsen the position there.  That is one objection.  Another objection to the amendment&mdash;there are several&mdash;is that, in my opinion, it would involve a great deal of hardship.  It would involve a very considerable amount of expense and it is quite likely that the whole of the estate&mdash;particularly if it were a small estate&mdash;would be eaten up in legal expenses, expenses in regard to searches and, perhaps, litigation expenses.  It is bad enough at the moment, when searches have to be made and there is litigation often to establish the rights of the next-of-kin or the relatives of the husband.  But if you have to look for the relatives of the husband and of the widow, Senators who know the position in the country will have some idea of what that might mean.</P>
      <P>I think that this Bill is not too drastic.  Senators must always remember that this Bill does not in any way deprive the husband of disposing of his property as he so desires.  All he has to do is to make a will, just like any other citizen in the country.  He can dispose of his property legally in any way he so desires.  In the Bill, we say that if he fails to make a will, then the widow ought not to be handicapped, as has been the case up to this, and that she should be given the property.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Another point in connection with the amendment is, as the Senator will <Col N="1107" /> remember, that personal estate includes land for this purpose.  A life interest in it may be of practically no value to her.  The farm may be poor. In so far as the other assets are concerned, even money in the bank, they are of very little help to her.  She cannot touch the money in the bank and is entitled only to whatever interest is there.  The farm may be run down and it might require a certain amount of, shall I say, liquid capital.  For that reason, she may not be able to carry on in any sort of an economic way at all.  If she has only a life interest in it&mdash;and the money or other assets are not available, to her in a realisable way&mdash;I doubt if, having only a life interest, she would be able to raise any money to improve or even to maintain the farm.  I do not think we are doing anything revolutionary. I think that it was agreed, the last time this Bill was before this House, that we were doing justice, and no more.</P>
    <P>There are Senators here from rural Ireland who know, as well as I do, that there have been cases of extreme hardship. I suppose that we can all quote cases of a young girl or a young woman who marries into a place and has brought money into it.  Perhaps the place was badly in need of money or certainly badly in need of an industrious woman, prepared to work hard, and, with her own hard work, plus whatever money she brought in, to make the farm something which it had not been before.  It would be a grave injustice to her, and it would be a very poor return for the capital and labour she put into the farm&mdash;apart altogether from the natural affection which she gave to her husband during his lifetime&mdash;to accept the Senator's amendment.  I think the amendment goes much too far and I cannot accept it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MartinODwyer" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot agree with the Minister.  There will be cases of hardship on either side sometimes.  No matter what provision is made, there will always be cases of hardship.  I submit, however, that the more numerous and the more frequent cases <Col N="1108" /> of hardship would be where the property goes completely to the widow, leaving out the husband's relatives.  The Bill proposes to eliminate completely the husband's family and I do not think that that would be right.  I think the Bill goes too far.  I think it ought to be possible to soften the effect of the Bill and to retain for the husband's family some little claim to the land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. Morrissey Mr. Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Morrissey</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator says that there will be hardship, no matter what we do.  I think that there is a far greater certainty of hardship if we do not pass this Bill and change the existing law.  I can quite understand the Senator's point of view, because he has in mind the sort of tradition that is right through rural Ireland.  What he is really arguing is that, in the main&mdash; I do not say in every case&mdash;merely because they are relatives of the deceased, people who never contributed anything to the farm in many cases, but just because they happen to be nephews, nieces, cousins or something else of the deceased, should have a claim equal to, or greater than that of the widow.  I cannot see the equity of that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinODwyer" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>The widow's relatives would not have any legal claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. Morrissey Mr. Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Morrissey</NameTxt>
      <P>They may have. They may have contributed in some large measure to the fact that she was able to bring in a fortune to the farm. We know what happens in the country. I will not say that it is a common thing, but it happens that a woman will servive her husband by ten, 15, 20 or maybe 25 years.  Is that woman to be deprived&mdash;in effect she is deprived &mdash;of whatever money she helped to put into the bank herself, or of the entire use of it, for her lifetime?  That is what it amounts to.  She is deprived of the full use of it.  I cannot see a case for the Senator's amendment.  I cannot see a case for altering this Bill along the lines the Senator suggests without doing, in my opinion, an injustice to the widow.  There is nothing in this Bill that seeks in any way to deprive the owner of the farm, the husband, of his right so to dispose of <Col N="1109" /> his farm or the money in any way he likes, by will.  I think that that is the answer.  If the owner or husband wants to provide that his relatives should get it, or portion of it, there is nothing whatever to prevent him from doing so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinODwyer" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>We must go on the assumption that there will be very numerous cases where the husband will not make a will.  The position will continue, since most people have a strong aversion to making a will.  I do not see that the widow suffers any undue hardship at the present time.  I think the widow is amply protected under the present law.  She gets the first £500, even if that £500 represents the extent of the entire property.  After that she gets half.  By no stretch of the imagination can anyone hold that the widow is not amply provided for under the existing law.  As a matter of fact, she generally comes out best. I think my amendment would meet the position by securing the rights of the husband's family.  Under the Bill as it stands, that family will undoubtedly suffer hardship.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusOFarrell" hpid="Mr. S. O'Farrell Mr. S. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. S. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I suppose we ought not really to rush in one these rural issues.  However, having heard Senator O'Dwyer talking, I am convinced that the position of the widow under the Bill as it now stands will be much better than it would be if we were to accept the proposed amendment.  One objection I have to the amendment is that it would worsen the woman's position.  But there is another objection; I do not see why we should treat a woman as being inferior in any way to a man.  I have been surprised that the women Senators here have not seen fit to protest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Any man who marries any woman undertakes to endow her with all his worldly goods.  Senator O'Dwyer now proposes to give him a legal way out of giving her even half his worldly goods.  The principle objection that I see is that if a woman is entitled in case of intestacy to only a life interest and, at most, to will away half the property, as the Minister has said, she may live for 25 or 30 years after her <Col N="1110" /> husband, but having only a life interest and having the right to dispose by will of only half the property, that woman is doomed to live a widow for the remaining 25 or 30 years.  Conceivably that woman might have an opportunity of marrying again.  Conceivably she might marry again.  Who will marry a woman who has only a life interest in a farm?  Who will be prepared to come in and work that farm for her?  No man will come in and work a farm in which his wife will only have a life interest.  If there should be a family by the second marriage, that family will be thrown out on the roadside as soon as the mother dies.  That is inevitable. The result will be that the farm will have to be sold out.</P>
    <P>Under the Bill as it stands, the widow, who remarries, and the children of the second marriage will be immeasurably better off than they would be under Senator O'Dwyer's amendment.  He speaks of people who will not make will.  Whether or not they refuse to make a will in order to save the lawyer's fee I do not know. If, by not making a will, they save 7/6, the subsequent litigation, in an attempt to discover who should get what, will eat up the whole estate and it will cost many times more than the making of a will would cost.  I see no reason why a man should not make a will.  If he does not make a will, the obvious inference is that he does not want to leave the property away from his wife.  If he wants to deprive his wife of the property, he can do so very easily at present by making a will. Senator O'Dwyer's amendment would make us take the inheritance forcibly away from the wife and hand it over to somebody else.</P>
    <P>This amendment is so very wide in its terms that it would be quite impossible of implementation.  The amendment speaks of &ldquo;the relatives of the deceased's husband&rdquo;.  To what degree? To the 42nd degree?  There is no limit to the search that can be made all over the world for relatives.  There may be no second or third cousins, but there may be tenth cousins in existence somewhere.  The lawyers would continue the search so long as there was a 1/- left in the estate.</P>
    <Col N="1111" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I must admit that I have been too busy electioneering to go into this matter thoroughly and study it properly.  It is, of course, something with which we are all familiar.  I never thought I would find myself in the middle of an election campaign in agreement with both the Minister and Senator O'Farrell.  While the Minister and Senator O'Dwyer were talking I was thinking of the day I got married 23 years ago.  I remembered that part of the ceremony was a promise by the man to his wife: &ldquo;With all my worldly goods I thee endow.&rdquo;  In my opinion, when a man dies whatever he dies possessed of should go to his wife.  Equally I believe that if the wife dies whatever she possesses should go to the husband.</P>
      <P>I admit there is a tradition in existence.  Perhaps that tradition goes deeper in Senator O'Dwyer's part of the country than it does in the City of Dublin and the surrounding counties. We are all aware of the position that obtained up to 50 years ago in relation to holding possession.  After a death in a family, particularly in cases where there was no issue, it was quite a common thing for the relatives of the husband or of the wife to go in and hold forcible possession of a property. I think that was quite wrong.  I think that such action is contrary to all the concepts of the moral law.  As the Minister pointed out, one may have people coming in and claiming a property when they have no real claim whatever.  Yet those people had never done anything to help to build up the property or to maintain it.  That happened very often in cases where originally one or other side had objected to the match being made at all.</P>
      <P>The fact of the matter is that it is more or less a waste of our time to be discussing this Bill to-day.  It will probably never become law.  There may be a change of Government.  I think there will be a change of Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing in the Bill about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>There is not.  The people <Col N="1112" /> will look after that, in my opinion.  In the election campaign so far, the Minister for Education took it upon himself the other day to make a statement which has a certain bearing on this measure.  In my opinion, it was a most insulting suggestion but, since it happens to come in useful in this debate, I see no reason why it should not be used.  I hope it will not hurt anyone's feelings.  When the Minister for Education was speaking, he said that Mr. de Valera knew what the Red Indians thought.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That has nothing whatsoever to do with this Bill.  It is not related in any way to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure the House that I will make it relevant immediately. I will prove that what the Red Indians think has quite a bit to do with this particular Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a red herring.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamQuirke" hpid="Mr. Quirke Mr. Quirke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Quirke</NameTxt>
      <P>The fact of the matter is that the ordinary moral law and the common law operate just the same on the shores of Manhattan as they do in the counties of Tipperary and Wicklow.  I know a considerable amount about Red Indians.  Anybody who is not familiar with them should at least make a study of them before making public speeches about them. Where a white man marries a Red Indian under what is known as the common law and without going through any from of marriage whatsoever&mdash;church, registry office or anything else&mdash;and lives with her for a period of three years, if that woman dies the entire property automatically becomes the property of the husband. If the husband owns a property and marries a woman under what they call the common law and lives with her for three years, that property when he dies automatically becomes the property of his widow.  The sooner we approach that system the better it will be.  I know tradition dies hard.  I think any sane group of men must admit that while there are hard cases&mdash;we all know hard cases make bad law&mdash;we should in discussing this Bill take the long view.  We should realise that any <Col N="1113" /> legislation which we pass here may never become law.  A better Bill may take its place.  I think so long as we follow the natural law we cannot go too far wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyJosephODonova" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Senator pressing the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MartinODwyer" hpid="Mr. O'Dwyer Mr. O'Dwyer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Dwyer</NameTxt>
      <P>I withdraw the amendment, It has fallen on evil times, in the midst of an election.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Sections 2 to 5 inclusive, Title and the Schedule agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported to the House without amendment.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take the remaining stages now.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Sugar (Prohibition of Import) Order," RHead="1951&mdash;Motion of Approval">
    <Title>Sugar (Prohibition of Import) Order, 1951&mdash;Motion of Approval.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="Mr. M. Hayes Mr. M. Hayes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M. Hayes</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann hereby approves of the Sugar (Prohibition of Import) Order, 1951.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. Morrissey Mr. Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Morrissey</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been asked on behalf of the Minister for Industry and Commerce to put this Order before the House.  It is a formal Order which was first passed in 1936 and it has been made and confirmed by the Oireachtas every year since.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Captain Orpen Captain Orpen">
      <NameTxt>Captain Orpen</NameTxt>
      <P>There are some points in connection with this Order on which I want to be clear.  When the Order was first made to give monopoly powers to the sugar company in regard to the importation of sugar, I presume the object was to give a certain amount of protection and control to the sugar company.  Over the years in which this Order has been in existence the world position has changed very much.  From an answer to a question in the Dáil which is reported in Volume 123, No. 13, it appears that sugar was imported c.i.f. at a price of £49 10s. 0d. per ton for the highest grade, that is, with a polarisation exceeding 98 degrees.  In the same answer it was stated that the <Col N="1114" /> cost in bags, ex-factory, of home-grown sugar was £46 per ton.  In other words, the cost of a certain quality of sugar imported under this Order substantially exceeded the price ex-factory of home-grown sugar.  I think this monopoly by the sugar company can be justified, and I am not objecting to the Order as such, but I would say that, if under present conditions, it eventuates that we have year by year to import varying quantities of sugar from abroad, possibly 20,000 to 30,000 tons, and the c.i.f. cost of that sugar is substantially higher than the estimated cost of sugar as given by the sugar factory, it obviously would be good business to increase the home-grown acreage of sugar beet.  I suggest that to increase that home-grown acreage it is obviously necessary, in the light of the world position, to increase the inducement to grow sugar beet.  It seems to me from the few figures that have been available to Senators that for more than two years, if not for three years, the import price of sugar has been greater than the estimated cost of production of the home-grown article.  It is not easy to make these comparisons between imported sugar and sugar manufactured from home-grown beet because different qualities, different polarisation and all sorts of other factors enter into it.  When the margin between the two prices is not very great somebody comes along and gives you a reason to show that one or other is the most economic, but when the difference runs into the region of £3 or £4 per ton it is not easy to explain away these discrepancies.  I suggest that, with the present cost of imported sugar, it looks to the ordinary. man in the street as if there was room for a higher price for home-grown beet to induce our farmers to grow more sugar beet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. Morrissey Mr. Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Morrissey</NameTxt>
      <P>That is all right if you could have it both ways, but I did not hear anyone say, when we were importing sugar at a substantially lower figure than we were paying for home-grown sugar, that the people growing beet were prepared to accept a lower price.  One hears much the same plea in relation to wheat.  The fact of the <Col N="1115" /> matter is that, as the Senator knows, over the greater part of the period, sugar which we had to import cost substantially less than we had to pay for sugar manufactured from home-grown beet.  Costs have been varying&mdash;perhaps I should not say varying because there has been a constant upward tendency in the last two or three years in the price of imported sugar, but the Senator is aware that the price for home-grown sugar beet for the coming year has been increased substantially. I think the price paid at the moment, even though I say this in the middle of an election&mdash;I am sorry Senator Quirke is not here at the moment&mdash;is a very good price.  We have to import sugar, but I should say that approximately the amount which we import is re-exported as a manufactured article or as an ingredient in some other manufactured article which is exported.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Senator will be pleased to hear that since 1947 the home production of sugar has gone up from 64,000 to 86,500 tons and the consumption of home-grown and imported sugar, both for domestic and manufacturing purposes, has gone up from 79,000 in 1947 to 135,000 tons in 1950.  It must also be kept in mind, as far as imported sugar is concerned, that the taxpayer does not suffer any loss because, as I say, an amount equivalent to what we <Col N="1116" /> import is used for manufacturing purposes and the economic price for that is paid by the people who use it for manufacturing purposes.  The Senator will also remember that we are still selling the domestic ration in this country at 4d. a lb, so that it is probably the lowest-priced food commodity.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Captain Orpen Captain Orpen">
      <NameTxt>Captain Orpen</NameTxt>
      <P>The consumer gets the benefit of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. Morrissey Mr. Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Morrissey</NameTxt>
      <P>The farmer who is growing beet is getting a good price for it, and, remember, the farmer is getting more out of it than the cash price.  The Senator knows that as well as I do.  It is worth more to the farmer to grow beet than the amount he will get in cash, although the cash price is very good.  I think the Senator could only argue that the home price of any particular commodity should go up in relation to the imported price if he was prepared to concede that the price should slide the other way as well.  I doubt if he will be prepared to concede that.  However, this is a formal Order and the Senator says he has no objection to it.  He has made his point and I am afraid it is another Minister who will have to answer that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 3.45 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>