<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="20" Month="May" Year="2008" Vol="189" No="16" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 20 Bealtaine 2008" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 20 May 2008" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="805">
    <Col N="805"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title></Title>
        <P Just="Center">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Paidir.</i><br /><i>Prayer.</i></P><Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is No. 1, Statements on the Burma tragedy.  It is proposed that No. 1 will be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business and conclude not later than 5.20 p.m. with the contributions of spokespersons not to exceed 12 minutes, those of other Senators not to exceed eight minutes, Senators may share time with the agreement of the House, and the Minister to be called upon ten minutes before the conclusion of the debate for concluding comments and a response to questions from spokespersons.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>Last week we spoke about the unavailability of frontline services for children even for those at risk and about the lack of resources available to social workers.  I compliment the Leader on inviting the Minister of State with responsibility for children, Deputy Barry Andrews, to the House tomorrow to respond to the concerns we raised.</P>
        <P>We saw another aspect of services for children being exposed on last night&rsquo;s &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; programme on cyber bullying, which is very worrying.  The Department of Education and Science needs to issue new guidelines to schools and to get involved in training and support for teachers.  As evident from last night&rsquo;s programme, the isolation felt by parents and children is extraordinary.  People felt they could not do anything about the bullying to which they were exposed.  Unfortunately, one young woman committed suicide.  We need to do far more in this area.  Perhaps the Minister for Education and Science will come into the House to address this issue.</P>
        <P>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business in order that we can debate the housing market.  A social housing project has collapsed because the developer quit and major projects face an uncertain future.  We must feel for the communities which are so disappointed that these projects will not be delivered.  The future of social housing is at a crisis point.  The affordable housing schemes also face an uncertain future with the dramatic changes in the property market.  Will the Leader invite the Minister with responsibility for housing to the House to discuss this issue as soon as possible?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>It was interesting to hear the debate on the hijab taking place in other fora during the past week.  As a young child in Dingle, I recall that our teachers, who were nuns, were veiled.  At that time when women went to church, they always covered their heads with a hat, mantilla or a veil.  It was accepted as normal practice.  I make that point because the question of the wearing of the hijab by Muslim girls or women in Irish society needs to be addressed.  In the recommendations on Seanad reform, the Seanad was considered<Col N="806"/> an important place for debate.  The Minister has insisted there will be debate on the matter, which is good, but could we lead that debate?  I do not pretend to know the answers but I have views on the issue and would like to hear the views of others.  Everyone&rsquo;s view is important.</P>
        <P>I gave that example from my youth because practice becomes normality.  I followed the debate in France very closely, although I am not sure whether I was happy or unhappy with the outcome.  It challenges us in all sorts of ways in terms of whether it helps pluralism and integrates society or does the opposite.  One could argue both sides.  It would be very helpful to have a debate in which people could offer their views and in which the Minister who will deal with this, whether it be the Minister for Education and Science or the Minister of State responsible for integration, could engage in an open way without prejudice to what might happen.  Let us hear people&rsquo;s views.</P>
        <P>We have touched on three or four occasions on the issue of stem cell research.  Our colleagues across the water and in other European countries are grappling with this issue.  We are afraid to deal with it because we may not like the outcome.  I may have different views from others on the matter.  This is another issue on which we should lead the public debate.  We should let people hear both sides of the argument and inform society.  That is an important role for the Seanad.  We will have three debates on Statements this week.  As one who is privileged to attend Leaders&rsquo; meetings &mdash; although I am not a Leader &mdash; I am happy issues on which Members have asked for debate will be debated.  These are two further important issues.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">There is a clear need for a debate on the matter alluded to by Senator Fitzgerald, namely, the collapse in the past 24 hours of the so-called public private partnership housing projects at St. Michael&rsquo;s House, O&rsquo;Deveney Gardens and other areas of Dublin city.  It is not an exaggeration to describe this event as a parable of our times.  It tells us a number of things about where we are at this stage of our development.</P>
        <P>First, it tells us that at the time of an economic downturn, the first people to feel the brunt are the most vulnerable in our society, those whose communities have been ravaged by under investment, drug abuse, social exclusion and the lack of basic facilities.  We saw reference in the newspapers to schemes being abandoned.  I agree with Senator Fitzgerald that it would be no exaggeration to say that when we talk about schemes being abandoned, we are talking about communities being abandoned.</P>
        <P>Second, it tells us and brings into stark relief something many of us suspected.  It demonstrates the folly of our over-reliance, particularly in recent years, on the private sector to address pressing social problems and concerns.  We have become obsessed with outsourcing everything to the private sector and have little or no confidence in our ability or the ability of a properly funded public sector to take the lead in issues such as this.  This is what inevitably happens when we have such an obsession, over-reliance and naive belief in the private sector and trust it will set aside its basic profit motive and deal with and confront the issues.  I am tempted to suggest that instead of denoting public private partnerships, the acronym PPP should denote private profit prevails.  That is clearly what it means in the current situation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The third thing demonstrated by the collapse of the PPP should be of urgent interest to the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government and to Senator Boyle.  It relates to the reason given for the abandonment of these projects.  I have been told it relates to the downturn in the construction, but what was less well noticed were the other reasons proffered by Mr. McNamara for walking away from these projects, namely, that he must, rightly, observe the reasonable and necessary building<Col N="807"/> regulations with regard to energy conservation and apartment size that have been introduced in Dublin city.  It is interesting that he withdrew just at a time when the State and local authorities demand basic standards of design and size for apartments.  What kind of shoeboxes did he propose to build on those sites?</P>
        <P>There are sighs from those on the Government side and no doubt this will be an issue at the famous event in Galway at the end of July.  When we had this debate previously with the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, he sought consensus across the House on construction standards.  I said to him then that the most significant area of concern in that regard was the attitude of the people on his side of the House.  He needed to ensure his colleagues in Government would see to it that the construction industry and their friends in it would take the new regulations seriously.  The collapse in the PPP mentioned demonstrates to me, if not to the House, that certain elements of the construction industry, bigger builders and those who find themselves in the top two or three in the CIF&rsquo;s recent publication, do not take the standards seriously.  That is where the Minister&rsquo;s attention should be directed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I would prefer if Senators did not name construction people or anyone else outside of the House during debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the call for debate on the housing issue, but I am sure it cannot take place today.  We cannot expect an instant response in terms of having an available Minister.  The memorandum in terms of responsibility between Cabinet Members and Ministers of State has not yet been fully drawn up.  There still could be uncertainty over who has full responsibility and would be best to come into this House.  However the earliest possible opportunity should be taken to have such a debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Is nobody in charge?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Boyle without interruption.  We do not want another Cork debate across the floor.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Nobody is in charge.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I share the concern on some of the reasons cited.  We must be clear that a funding mechanism for the projects has collapsed and there is an onus on the local authority concerned and the appropriate Department to ensure a proper, appropriate funding mechanism is put in place.  The communities identified are in need of housing and these projects should be completed as soon as possible.  We should be cognisant of the views of the outgoing Comptroller and Auditor General, Mr. John Purcell, who expressed as his parting gift his reservation about an over-reliance on public private partnerships as a funding mechanism. If we need a lesson on that, the events of the past few days are a good example.  If the developers concerned cite the need for those in need of social housing to live in energy efficient houses of sufficient space as a reason not to proceed or involve themselves in such projects, they are not doing our society any good whatsoever.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NickyMcFadden"><NameTxt>Senator Nicky McFadden</NameTxt>
	<P>I raise the issue of turbary rights and the reaction of the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Gormley, to the report on the protection of our habitats and the most vulnerable and rare species.  Nobody is more protective of the flora and fauna of rural Ireland than the people who live in it and use it.  I ask for a very urgent debate on turf cutting for personal use <Col N="808"/>in the countryside.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NickyMcFadden"><NameTxt>Senator Nicky McFadden</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister, Deputy Gormley, seems to lay the blame for the damage and danger to these wildlife species squarely on the people who cut turf and I find that objectionable.  My telephone was hopping yesterday with calls from people who have spent years cutting turf, as did their families before them, without damaging the environment to the extent the Minister suggests.  It would be more in his line to consider the developers and lack of infrastructure from this Government.  For example, Athlone has no main drainage and no money has been forthcoming for the infrastructure to protect water.  Consequently, dirty water is destroying our countryside.  I call for an urgent debate on turbary rights because we are taking away the rights of the people of rural Ireland.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>RTE should be complimented as a public service broadcaster on its very courageous programme last night on bullying in schools.  It shows that public service broadcasting is very effective.  Those who contributed to the programme were very courageous.  Looking at the programme I felt some very vulnerable young people were involved and they should be given every support by the HSE, services and the schools.  I suggest every primary school&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is Senator Leyden asking the Leader for a debate?  Questions must be addressed to the Leader.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes, it would be worthwhile to debate this but as a matter of urgency I suggest to all school principals that this programme should be shown in every school in the country and a discussion had on what happened in that programme and the effect on young people.  This would bring it to the attention of the principals and others involved.  I call on the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Batt O&rsquo;Keeffe, to come to the House to discuss this issue and to determine what action will be taken.  There is no point in having protocols or procedures if action is not taken on the ground.  Quick decisive action on this must be taken by caring principals, and I again compliment RTE.</P>
        <P>I call on the Leader, Senator Cassidy, to ask the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Harney, to have a debate here on ongoing developments in the health service.  I particularly refer to the transfer of &euro;4 million funding away from palliative care in Roscommon County Hospital.  An eight-bed unit was promised and committed to and plans were under way to provide that service at Roscommon County Hospital.  Not only is the HSE proposing to withdraw acute surgery from the hospital, but this has probably resulted now in the proposal to remove the funding of &euro;4 million for palliative care, which has been organised by the Mayo-Roscommon hospice which raises approximately &euro;1 million a year for home help and home care.</P>
        <P Just="Left">As a former member of the Western Health Board, I feel one had more influence as a member of a health board than has any Member of the Oireachtas or, indeed, any member of the Government, as far as I can see, on the HSE.  There is definitely a democratic deficit as far as the activities of the Health Service Executive are concerned.  I know it constantly comes in for criticism in this House and many of the difficulties are not of its making now, but there is no consultation with anyone in this House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>It is the Senator&rsquo;s Government doing it.  It is Government policy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>The HSE was established with the support of Fine Gael.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt><Col N="809"/>
	<P>A lot of promises.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Leyden without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>It is Senator Leyden&rsquo;s Government.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>They have lost it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader of the House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Leyden cannot have it both ways.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;to invite the Minister, Deputy Harney, into this House to discuss this issue and other issues of relevance to the situation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Are they in Government or not?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The point is made.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>We are in a democracy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Does Senator Leyden support Government policy?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Fortunately, this Chamber is a democratic forum and we can raise issues such as this.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Does he support Government policy?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>We will not be dictated to by Senator Buttimer on what we raise in this House in the best interests of our constituents&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Does Senator Leyden support Government policy?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Buttimer, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and we will raise it here and in a different forum.  We have an opportunity in this House for more ongoing discussions as far as health is concerned, and the HSE should brief Members.  No Oireachtas Member in Roscommon has been briefed as far as the removal of funding&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>(Interruptions).</i></P>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>No Oireachtas Member in Roscommon has been briefed as far as the removal of acute surgery services to Ballinasloe is concerned.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The point is made.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>In fairness, Oireachtas Members have a right and a responsibility&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Have a go against the Government so.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;to be briefed and I call on the Leader of the House to arrange an early debate on the ongoing developments of palliative care.  Under that specific heading, we should discuss the outrage in Roscommon that we are losing this planned eight-bed unit which would provide tremendous service for those with very serious illnesses.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="810"/>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is for the debate later.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>I am sure Members of the House will join me in expressing the hope for a successful outcome to the convention on cluster munitions currently taking place in this city.  It is a sad reflection on the state of affairs that four of the five permanent members of the UN Security Council are not represented at this conference.  It is disappointing and I raised the matter with a member of the US State Department in Washington last week.  There is a serious question of example that needs to be shown by Western democracies in particular.  Some of the participants in this conference have had their lives changed irreversibly as a result of injuries sustained through cluster munitions and it is time that Western democracies, in particular, our friends in the United States and Britain, set an example.</P>
        <P>I am happy to note that among the 109 countries represented at this conference are 70 countries which use cluster munitions.  It is to be hoped that the outcome of these deliberations will set an example and that countries such as the US, China, Britain, Russia and Israel will awaken to their responsibilities, not just to their own people but to the international community, and that we will see an end to these horrible weapons of war which do no more than destroy innocent lives, sometimes many years after they have been dropped.</P>
        <P>I also mention in passing another sad story, which is that of children going missing in this country.  It seems we are in danger of having a&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is Senator Mullen asking the Leader for a debate on this?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.  I would like a debate on this.  It is good that we now have legislation which criminalises the trafficking of persons into this State for their exploitation in various ways &mdash; in the sex industry, in the labour market or, indeed, for the use of their organs.  I took part in the Seanad debate on the legislation and tabled several amendments.</P>
        <P>As we see, however, there seems to be a difference between Irish children who go missing in this country and the 300 or so foreign children who have gone missing.  The Health Service Executive has confirmed that five young Kenyan nationals have now gone missing.  It is feared that these children and others have been removed for trafficking and general exploitation.  This points up the need for more than mere legislation which criminalises human trafficking.  We need resources for the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and for those who act on our behalf to ensure this does not happen.In our debates on immigration, I hope we will not lose sight of the fact that there are often vulnerable people at the heart of this story.  We need to be serious about it and hopefully we can start that with a comprehensive debate on the subject in this House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGerardHanafin"><NameTxt>Senator John Hanafin</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I join the call for a debate on stem cell research.  The debate has been muddied to some extent, especially with the links made in the national media between <i>in vitro</i> fertilisation and stem cells.  There is no objection in pro-life circles to IVF, despite the impression that is out there.  However, there is a request for respect for the embryo.  It amazes me that after ten years and billions of euro spent, the only legally defined clinic to provide stem cells to adults or children who may need them provides adult stem cells, and that being X-Cell in Germany.  After all these years, they have not been able to stop the nature of the embryo which allows the stem cell to multiply and divide at a very fast rate.  Even though they tried to succeed, they failed and have caused cancerous growth.  Why do we have to go through all this again only inevitably to find out that it is simply not working?  Despite being ethically wrong, it does not work.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>Last week I spoke about the latest round of trade negotiations at the World Trade Organisation, especially regarding agriculture.  I stated that Ireland currently has a veto and that it will continue to have one after the Lisbon treaty referendum.  The Eu<Col N="811"/>ropean Commission has since confirmed that position, even though the Government has been slow to state its position and whether it would use the veto.  Notwithstanding the fact that the Commission has confirmed that position, we received a press release from Libertas which states that the Government and the Commission are lying on the issue.</P>
        <P>This must be met head on.  This organisation has lied about the position on abortion, despite the express wording in the treaty that it can have no effect on the abortion law in Ireland.  It has lied about the 12.5% corporation tax, despite the express wording in the treaty.  It is now lying about the position of agriculture and the WTO agreement.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to deal with this issue tomorrow during our debate on these negotiations with the Minister.  What position will the Government take on exercising the veto that exists?  The President of the European Parliament confirmed in this House the position on abortion, on neutrality and on the 12.5% corporation tax rate.  Libertas persists in leaving a doubt on these issues, despite the express wording of the treaty.  We need a clear and unequivocal statement from the Minister tomorrow, and that will assist the farming organisations.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Senator Marc MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>At the outset, I agree with Senator Regan&rsquo;s points on the Libertas statements.</P>
        <P>I would like to call for a general debate on housing.  In light of recent developments in Dublin, it would be appropriate to look at this.  There are a few public private partnerships and private finance initiatives which may have been planned, but which may be in danger now due to viability reasons.  I think we should debate that.  We could also debate the merits of Part V of the Planning and Development Act 2000, and the fact that it may need to be changed.  I am not sure we are getting the optimum results for which we had hoped.</P>
        <P>In welcoming the Taoiseach&rsquo;s recent announcement of a task force on reform of the public service, we in this House should have a debate on the issue.  Our views, which are many and diverse, could be of help to this task force.  As Senator White said, there is much farming out and subcontracting of many services to the private sector. Many of these surveys or consultancy reports may be better carried out by our public service, which may have the in-house expertise, making it more cost effective in these times of scarcity.  A debate on those issues would be greatly appreciated.</P>
      
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PhilPrendergast"><NameTxt>Senator Phil Prendergast</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to the House to discuss the awarding of contracts by the HSE to companies involved in very serious fraud in the US.  My worry concerns Quest Diagnostics last week and the dialysis unit for Fresenius this week.  This matter has serious implications for how we do our business.  I ask that this be debated urgently.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Senator Geraldine Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to organise for the Minister of State, Deputy Andrews, to debate bullying.  I know Deputy Andrews will be in the House tomorrow.  &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; must be congratulated.  We all know where we want to be on Monday nights when that programme is broadcast.  Everybody wants to watch it to get the picture.  We see the tip of the iceberg but the programme goes into the depths of the matter.</P>
        <P>Society should be fearful because of the scenes depicted on that programme and, as parents, we are horrified.  I was horrified and found myself thanking God that my children are out of the teenage stage and are now young adults.  I would be terrified as a young parent if I had children in second level school today.  Is it not terrible that the perpetrators get away whereas, for example, the two young girls from Wexford have dropped out of school and do not intend returning to full-time education because they are too scarred?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><Col N="812"/><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>This is not new.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Senator Geraldine Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>Bullying is not a new phenomenon.  It is an age old problem but the methods are new.  It is not about texting or the Internet, it is the age old problem of bullying.  I was taken aback when a teacher on the programme talked about the aggression of students and how some come to school with knives in their bags.  What will it be like when they are in the workforce?  Will there be fighting in the workforce?  This subject is worth a dedicated debate because it applies not only to students but also to adults in the workplace and, irrespective of whether we like it, it exists in this Chamber.  It is about time we let the bullies know this is not acceptable.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>I call for an interdepartmental debate on the social, personal and health formation of our young people.  This is the third time I have made the request.  I say this as a result of the &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; programme on cyber bullying.  I have raised the issue of bullying on numerous occasions.  This is the second major study in this country.  The Programme for International Student Assessment, PISA, reported that 43% of our children had been bullied in the current term.  Some 95 of the 4,500 children surveyed experienced physical violence in the term.</P>
        <P>We cannot load everything onto schools.  I received a call from a school principal this morning whose deputy principal broke down as a result of the programme last night.  Much help is needed by parents.  Parents have telephoned me to say they do not know what to do.  They also need guidelines and, in the context of the broad debate on the social, personal and health formation of our young people, we must examine how we can help parents.  We must examine the social debt owed to society by Internet providers, by Facebook and by Bebo.  They are making a fortune on the backs of our young people.  We are not managing to control them or to get anything from them to invest in our youth.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">3 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>I wish also to raise today the collapse of the social housing project for Dublin.  This is not new.  In Galway, there are 3,000 people on the housing waiting list, with people from the west side of the city, including Salthill, waiting ten years for a house and people on the east side waiting six years.  As funds promised last year by the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government will not be forthcoming this year, Galway City Council has had to take out a &euro;1 million bridging loan to complete its project.  The Department has reneged on its promises.  I ask that the Leader invite the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, with special responsibility for housing, Deputy Michael Finneran, to the House to discuss the issue.  We do not hear a great deal about housing in the Seanad, and we must address the issue urgently.  Galway City Council will not be able to meet even its Part V requirements from the money available to it this year.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator can make that point during the debate, if agreed to by the Leader.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>I second Senator Frances Fitzgerald&rsquo;s amendment to the Order of Business.  </P>
        <P>I support Senator Mullen&rsquo;s call for a debate on the issue of missing children.  Where is our outrage as a nation?  If I were living in another humane and civilised country and my child went missing I would want the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform and the Government to take the matter seriously.  I have not heard anything on this issue from the new Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform.  What resources are being put in place and what actions are being taken in this regard?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><Col N="813"/><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator has made her point.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Perhaps the Leader will ensure we get a response to this issue in terms of what the Government is doing about it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Senator Ann Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>I, too, call for a debate on the issue of bullying as shown on last night&rsquo;s &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; programme.  I watched the programme following which I contacted colleagues of mine in the teaching profession and asked for their views on the issue.  They all said that what is wrong is that society is breaking down.  The fundamental question of why this is happening remains.  </P>
        <P>I accept bullying is an old concept with which we have all had to deal.  However, what was shown on television last night is more than bullying.  There is a criminal and vicious aspect to what is happening now.  Fundamental questions must be asked.  Why are people so angry?  We need an interdepartmental debate on the matter between the Departments of Health and Children, Education and Science and Justice, Equality and Law Reform.</P>
        <P>I was unable to attend last week&rsquo;s debate on rural communities and how the quality of life therein has deteriorated.  However, I hope it is an issue that will come up for discussion during the interdepartmental debate in order that we can question what is going wrong and examine how we can curb this trend.  Many questions need to be addressed.  For example, in what way can our professionals assist in this regard, do we need more resources or professional back-up and where are we going wrong?  I do not know the answers.  Does anybody here know the answers?  We must conduct a brainstorming exercise on the matter to determine if we can come up with a solution.  I believe the matter can be addressed by way of legislation. I would welcome a debate on this issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I call Senator Norris.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order &mdash; I do so with some reservation &mdash; my colleague, Senator Regan, for whom I have a lot of respect stated earlier that the Libertas organisation, for which I have no axe to grind, lied on a number of occasions in respect of the current referendum campaign.  I assure the House I would be as quick to my feet were such comments made in respect of an organisation campaigning for a &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote.  The Libertas organisation is campaigning for a &ldquo;No&rdquo; vote.</P>
        <P>I heard a debate recently during which a spokesperson for Libertas&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P>How is this a point of order?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Mullen, on a point of order.</P>
    <HtmlBk SectId="2" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>I heard a spokesperson for Libertas say he was not making the case specifically on abortion.  I will now make my point of order and, I hope Senator White will support it.  A word such as &ldquo;lying&rdquo; should not be used whether it be in the context of an individual or an organisation in the conduct of a referendum campaign, particularly given that we are trying to have a rational and courteous debate on both sides.  I encourage Senator Regan to withdraw the remark and I ask the Cathaoirleach to rule accordingly.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOReilly"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Reilly</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Regan is privileged.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>To be fair and honest to Senator Regan, I did not hear him say &ldquo;lying&rdquo; but if he did I expect him to apologise and I ask him to clarify the matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I quoted from the Libertas press release &ldquo;Government and Commission lying over WTO veto&rdquo;.  I stated that if anyone is lying i<Col N="814"/>t is Libertas which has given out misinformation on abortion and the 12.5% tax rate.  It is an organisation which has serious question marks over its sinister nature when we read <i>The Irish Times</i> today.  Declan Ganley is in no position to interpret the Lisbon treaty for the Irish electorate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Regan has privilege and he should not descend to the level of organisations which he rightly castigates for using such language.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I would prefer if people were not named and I ask Senators not to use names.  I did not hear Senator Regan say &ldquo;lying&rdquo;.  He outlined what he did state on the matter and I would prefer if the word was not used.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>The people in question are not here to defend themselves.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I am dealing with the matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>I accept this.  The word was provoked by the wording of the Libertas press release.  We can talk about misinformation or misleading information and this is the essence of my statement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>On numerous occasions, I stated that I do not want any individuals mentioned.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>If the Punch and Judy show is over may I state that frequently in this House I stated that both Bush and Blair were liars and nobody ever stopped me.  Perhaps this is because they are.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>On the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>With regard to Libertas and the &ldquo;No&rdquo; vote campaign, Senator Regan referred to an interesting piece about the background of a number of these people.  A majority of them are employed by&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We are not having this debate on the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;an American armaments firm.  I will make this point.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We will debate the matter this week.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>This strengthens the point I made in this House with regard to my reservations about the military aspects of the Lisbon treaty and the development of the European armaments group and its desire to go into competition with the United States armaments industry.  This would be a clear explanation as to why people with links to the United States arms industry&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We are not having a debate on the Lisbon treaty today.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;do not want it passed.  I do not want it to pass, but for other reasons.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We are not having a debate on the Lisbon treaty on the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I was clarifying an issue for Senator Regan.</P>
        <P>I join with colleagues in calling for a debate on <Col N="815"/>the collapse of the social housing programme.  This calls into question our very values as a society.  We can have the Shelbourne Hotel and the Thornton Hall super-prison but apparently we are spancilled when we try to do something for the most disadvantaged sections of our society.</P>
        <P>I happen to live close to some of the areas concerned and I admire and respect the people there.  People living on Sean McDermott Street and Dominic Street got together, formed committees and negotiated.  Some of their houses and apartments have been vacated and have begun to be demolished.  However, once again the prospect of new housing is snatched away from them.  Apparently, one of the problems is the increased size of apartments and standards of heating efficiency.  This suggests that people are not entitled to a decent standard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is Senator Norris seeking a debate?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes, because the Government is responsible.  It allowed the housing industry to overheat and encouraged it by giving incentives to pals.  The new Taoiseach, Deputy Cowen, has a challenge to resolve this problem and reassure the Irish people that the standards are those of which he spoke so movingly in Clara, County Offaly.</P>
        <P>No. 38 on the Order Paper is linked because it is an attempt to face up to developers.  It is a motion in the name of some Independent Members on the location of the Abbey Theatre.  This situation has changed again because of the planning and development issues at the north end of O&rsquo;Connell Street.  There is an opportunity for our national theatre not to be hidden away at the behest of sectoral interests in the IFSC but to be placed where it belongs in the centre of the principal thoroughfare of Dublin.  Will the Leader ask the Minister responsible to come to the House to explain where the theatre will be sited?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I also support Senator Fitzgerald&rsquo;s call for a debate and I acknowledge Senator MacSharry&rsquo;s concern about the collapse of the social and affordable housing scheme in Dublin.  An urgent debate on this matter is needed.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Toole called for an honest and open debate on education and the form of dress, which I welcome, because there was a time when the uniforms of certain orders of nuns resembled the hijab.  Only their faces were visible.  If that is what people want, we must have an honest and open debate on it.</P>
        <P>The Leader is the conduit between the House and the Government and last week in reply to my question, he stated:</P>
        <P LI="1">Senator Coghlan asked me to clarify who is the Minister for arts. It is Deputy Martin Mansergh, a distinguished former Member of Seanad &Eacute;ireann, who was in the House last night. We are very proud of his new appointment.</P>
        <P FLI="0">On mature reflection, could the Leader further clarify this statement in the light of remarks made by the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Cullen?  I look forward to his reply.</P>
        <P>With regard to the protected habitats and species report mentioned earlier, I am more concerned about water pollution and water quality.  Damaging reports relating to the Killarney lakes&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Senator seeking a debate on water quality?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes, because significant upstream development in the form of afforestation has taken place resulting in fertiliser run off and silt build-ups.  Significant damage is done by detergents in septic tanks because of the phosphates they contain.  I make the plea to the Leader for the dev<Col N="816"/>elopment of phosphate free detergents because phosphates fuel the growth of algae which damage fresh water in our lakes and rivers.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator has made his point.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>We have witnessed what has happened in Galway and elsewhere with cryptosporidium in the water supply. This issue is vital and we need to focus on that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOReilly"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Reilly</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader make a statement on two important issues of public concern, namely, the statement in the leading article in today&rsquo;s edition of the <i>Irish Examiner</i> that alleged participants in insider trading are doing business unthwarted, thus damaging confidence in Irish business, and the misdiagnosis of patients in the north east and the administrative mayhem that has followed, resulting in enormous trauma for affected families?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>I am glad Senator Coghlan again raised the question regarding Deputy Martin Mansergh, the new Minister of State.  I am confused because nothing stated in the media or elsewhere is out of order.  The Minister of State has specific responsibility for the arts but the same situation applies in every other junior Ministry.  Sections of the media were trying to develop a little civil war regarding this appointment but no one understands the system better than the Minister of State because he spent 25 years in the Civil Service and he understands the protocol and the procedures.  I had an opportunity to have a discussion with him in Cashel over the past two days.  He is an outgoing individual and he loved a little cut and thrust in this Chamber.  He was as bemused as anyone by the manner in which his appointment has been presented.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>He will be well able to say, &ldquo;Yes, Minister.&rdquo;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>It is important at this stage that he be allowed to get on with his work.  It is possible that he attracts more of the spotlight than others because of his ability and efficiency.  I do not have any doubt that he will play a very significant and pivotal role where the arts and the Office of Public Works are concerned.  I also know that Senator Coghlan will welcome him with open arms to the many attractions which exist in the Kingdom.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Absolutely.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>We look forward to that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader for a debate on imprisonment, specifically the imprisonment of women.  In a week when Thornton Hall is in the news, it is time for us to take a critical review of the need for imprisonment and, in particular, the need for this super prison initially proposed by the former Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Michael McDowell.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>This prison seems to be forging ahead without anyone questioning whether we need these places.  I was going to use the &ldquo;L&rdquo; word but I hesitate to use it, other Members of the House having fallen into problems, so I will say that misinformation rather than lies have been told about the need for more prison places in this country.  The reality elsewhere shows us that if one builds bigger prisons, judges and sentences will fill them with people.  This is the sad reality and we need to reappraise whether we need this many prisons, especially for women.</P>
        <P>This week, we are fortunate to receive a visit from Baroness Jean Corston from the British House of L<Col N="817"/>ords who produced a very radical report last year on women in prison and who recommended, after a very thorough review, that prison places for women should essentially be abolished and that there should just be a small number of small detention units for women.  Otherwise, alternative sanctions should be used.  We could very much learn from the lessons of that report.</P>
        <P>I am happy to say that Baroness Corston will be visiting Leinster House on Thursday.  Deputy Mary O&rsquo;Rourke and I are hosting a meeting with her for all women Members of the Oireachtas.  I am sorry that we cannot invite any male colleagues interested in this issue to the briefing with Baroness Corston.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Why not?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I would be happy to meet them to discuss the issues at another time.</P>
        <P>The Jesuit Centre for Faith and Justice will also host a seminar on Thursday evening on the future of women&rsquo;s imprisonment.  This is an issue which we could very usefully debate in this House and could lead the way in calling for a critical review of women&rsquo;s imprisonment, as Baroness Corston has done in Great Britain.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the call by my colleague, Senator Fitzgerald, for a debate on the emerging housing crisis.  It is difficult to accept that as we reach the end of the Celtic tiger era, one of the issues which remains as significant a problem as it was when that era began in the mid-1990s is the housing crisis and the fact that tens of thousands of people are still looking for social housing.  A debate is urgently needed because while all these people are awaiting housing, there are thousands of vacant houses throughout the country.  There is a crisis in the housing industry.  A large number of houses are available for rental accommodation.  From a policy perspective, we certainly need flexibility, a little bit of imagination and a significant amount of investment.  The debate called for by Senator Fitzgerald is very urgent and I support her request.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPaulPhelan"><NameTxt>Senator John Paul Phelan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Leader for arranging a debate on the world trade talks this week.  I also wish to raise the issue of housing, which I raised last week, and the shortfall experienced by many local authorities, not just the collapse announced in Dublin with regard to social and affordable housing.  Many local authorities have seen a significant cut in their allotted funding for social and affordable housing.  The local authority in my area of Kilkenny has been advised not even to take Part V units that have been completed but rather to seek money from developers so that works that are already under way can be completed.  That is certainly not what was envisaged when Part V was initially brought into play.  It would be opportune for us to have that discussion.</P>
        <P>I was charmed to hear Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; defend his constituency colleague and former Senator, Deputy Mansergh, and his role as Minister of State with responsibility for the arts.  I will mention the name of a former colleague of mine, the former Senator, Feargal Browne, who on a number of occasions in this House when he was a Member raised the issue of drug driving.  A report commissioned and published by the insurance company Hibernian contained some startling information about the proportion of drivers under the age of 30 who had driven while under the influence of drugs.  About one third of those surveyed stated that they had driven while under the influence of drugs.  I call for a debate during which we should examine the possibility of introducing a drug driving test.  There is a test in existence in Australia and we should consider introducing it here.  The same survey indicated that 96% of those under 30 would not consider driving while under the influence of alcohol, which is a very contradictory finding <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i> the issue of drug driving.</P>
        <Col N="818"/><P>I join Senators Mullen, Healy-Eames and others who have expressed their outrage at the discovery yesterday that five girls from Kenya have disappeared without a trace.  I wish to express my absolute horror at the fact that they went missing last July but we are only now hearing of it.  The girls have been missing for ten months and it is completely unacceptable that they would just disappear off the face of the earth while in the care of the HSE.  We should have a discussion on this issue at the earliest possible opportunity.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>Last week in this House I called for a debate on the role of public private partnerships, particularly with regard to public housing and public infrastructure projects.  I called for that debate last Thursday because four of the enterprises that have been destroyed by the announcement today by Dublin City Council are in my constituency.  In recent weeks the negative perception and doubt regarding the status of those projects has been increasing.  </P>
        <P>Any debate conducted in this House must be clear on several points.  Senator Dan Boyle stated earlier that what has happened here is the collapse of a funding mechanism.  We must be clear that what happened today is a lot more serious than the collapse of a funding mechanism.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>For many communities in Dublin that have been bypassed by much of the economic growth and positive developments in our country in recent years, what has happened today is not merely the collapse of a funding mechanism but the collapse of hope.  Their confidence that local and national Government will take their concerns seriously and do something for them has also collapsed.  We should not stand up in this House today and assert that what has happened is the collapse of a funding mechanism when there are people in this city who were looking forward to new homes, who were right to expect them but who, because of events beyond their control, now find they cannot have them.</P>
        <P>If any Member of this House were to table a parliamentary question or to lodge a freedom of information request about the role of public private partnerships, he or she would be told the information is unavailable because it is commercially sensitive.  However, when something goes wrong with the operation of these schemes, we are the people who are &mdash; rightly &mdash; expected to stand up, show leadership and give confidence back to our communities that their hopes and aspirations can be delivered on.  Urgent action is required to deal with the devastation of five communities in our city.</P>
        <P>Within the EU, Ireland is one of the most reliant on public private partnership.  Most of Transport 21, for example, is reliant on their operation.  We must have a discussion about how they operate nationally, about the lack of information on them available to Members of the Oireachtas and on how they can be reined in to ensure they operate in the public interest.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senators Fitzgerald, Alex White, Boyle, Leyden, Healy-Eames, Ormonde, Norris, MacSharry, Bradford, Phelan and Donohoe all called for an urgent debate on the challenges facing the local authorities in Ireland regarding housing stock.  I congratulate the new Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government with special responsibility for housing, Deputy Michael Finneran, who was an excellent Senator before being elected to the D&aacute;il.  As a Senator, he was Government spokesperson on Finance in this House.  I understand the Minister of State has a budget of &euro;2 billion at his disposal this year.  </P>
<Col N="819"/>      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader should wait until he has done something before congratulating him.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>There are more places in Ireland than Dublin.  I am as <i>au fait</i> with the north inner city as any other Senator, with the exception of Senator Norris.  I look forward to arranging for the new Minister of State with responsibility for housing to come to the House to hear the serious concerns Senators outlined today.  However, this could not be happening at a better time in terms of the Government, councils and other local authorities securing value for money for such work.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader should tell that to the people concerned.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Allow the Leader to continue without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I advise Senator Donohoe that I am very close friends with the people in Sheridan Court, as Senator Norris will know&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>That will not get them a house.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and with the people in Gardiner Street and in Summerhill.  I am a neighbour to them.  The Senator should not think he is infallible in coming in here and&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>As the Leader is their friend&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>What kind of a response is that?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>They need homes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Allow the Leader to continue without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader is provoking interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I will ask the Senator to leave if he will not conduct himself.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>But the Leader is provoking comment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader is replying to the questions raised which he is entitled to do.  He did not interrupt anyone else.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The value for money that can be obtained by local authorities in regard to the building of houses and the number of contractors and top class tradespersons available is better than at any time during the past ten years.  I am sure this issue will be addressed head on and successfully by the Government and the Minister of the day.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnPaulPhelan"><NameTxt>Senator John Paul Phelan</NameTxt>
	<P>That is waffle.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the concerns about this matter expressed by Senators on all sides of the House.</P>
        <P>I also want to congratulate RTE on last night&rsquo;s &ldquo;Prime Time Investigates&rdquo; programme, as outlined by Senator Leyden.  The content of its investigation is a matter of serious concern to Members, be they Members of the D&aacute;il or the Seanad.  It highlighted the challenges that face our younger generation.  We must have a debate on this matter in the House as a matter of urgency during which we should cover Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s point on guidelines for schools.  These guidelines are important, as also pointed out by Senator Fitzgerald.  There is also t<Col N="820"/>he matter of the help the students, parents and boards of management must be given by the Department and by us as Members of the Oireachtas.  The Internet presents many new challenges for our young people.</P>
        <P>Senators O&rsquo;Toole and Coghlan called for a debate on school outfits and dress codes in schools.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>School outfits.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I call for silence in the House. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The new Minister asked the Minister of State, Deputy Conor Lenihan, to bring forward a report on this matter and the publication of such a report will present an opportunity for such a debate.</P>
        <P>Senators O&rsquo;Toole and Hanafin called for a debate on the up-to-date position on stem cell research, for which I have no difficulty in setting aside time.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator McFadden, my constituency colleague, highlighted the difficulties in terms of turbary rights experienced particularly by people in the midlands and the challenges facing generations of turf cutting families in the midlands.  I have good news for the Senator, namely, that the slane turf cutters, which are the family turf cutters, are not included in the regulations.  Those of us who were reared in the 1950s, when turf was the only means of fuel, and who spent time on the bogs of Ireland can return to traditional ways.  As the Senator is aware, sausage turf-cutting is not allowed, but she can tell all her friends and all those who voted for us 12 months ago that there is good news from Senator Cassidy that the old slane turf cutting is allowed&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NickyMcFadden"><NameTxt>Senator Nicky McFadden</NameTxt>
	<P>They will not consider that good news.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and they may have available to them, without any interference, their perches and areas of turf for future generations.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Leyden called for a debate on the HSE in regard to the services provided by Roscommon hospital.  I will allow time for a debate on the serious concerns he raised regarding that hospital.   The Senator was chairman of the former Western Health Board and brings to the House considerable experience of the challenges facing the providers of hospital facilities in the western region.  I have no difficulty in allowing time for such a debate.</P>
        <P>We would agree with the sentiments expressed by Senator Mullen regarding the cluster bombs convention that is taking place.  I understand it was the initiative of the former Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Dermot Ahern, to arrange for representatives of 107 countries to attend this urgently required conference.  I congratulate the Minister and everyone concerned in organising the conference.  I am pleased that representatives of 107 nations are attending it.  That speaks for itself.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senators Mullen, Healy Eames and John Paul Phelan called for a debate on children who are missing as a matter of urgency.  I can arrange to set aside time for such a debate and I will endeavour to ensure it takes place before the summer recess.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senators Regan and MacSharry raised the issue of Ireland having a veto at the WTO talks.  The issue regarding Ireland having a veto was correctly pointed out by Senator Regan, with whom I do not often agree but I must agree with him on this occasion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>That is a first.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I look forward to the new Minister, Deputy Smith, coming to<Col N="821"/> the House tomorrow for a debate on this matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader and Senator Regan are new found friends.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>He is not always wrong.  The Minister, Deputy Smith, will come to the House for the first time in his new role to clarify this issue in minute detail for the people of Ireland and they can then adjudicate on it.  I refer in particular to the hard-pressed and hardworking families, generations of whom have devoted their lives to agriculture.  Members of the farming community are the backbone of our country.  A major statement will be made by the new Minister tomorrow when he comes to Seanad &Eacute;ireann to clarify for the people of Ireland for once and for all the situation regarding the challenges facing the farming community to enable them to make up their minds and do the right thing when they vote in the Lisbon treaty referendum.  I look forward to the Minister&rsquo;s presence in the House and to a full attendance tomorrow for clarification of this important issue to the House and to the people of Ireland.</P>
        <P>Senator MacSharry called for a debate on the task force on reform of the public service.  Such a request is timely.  Given the experience of colleagues in the House, Senator O&rsquo;Toole in particular, in this area, I can think of no better person to guide and lead us on this issue&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and to determine how we can assist the Department and the new Minister in this challenge and task which has been taken in hand by the Government.</P>
        <P>Senator Prendergast called for a debate as a matter of urgency on the awarding of contracts by the HSE and outlined examples to the House.  I will arrange for such a debate to take place at the earliest possible time.</P>
        <P>Senator Norris called for a debate on motion 38, which provides, &ldquo;That Seanad &Eacute;ireann urges the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, in the light of the proposed redevelopment of a very large site at the north end of O&rsquo;Connell Street which includes the former Carlton Cinema, to take steps to ensure that the Abbey Theatre is located in the former Carlton site which all authorities agree is by far the best and most practical location.&rdquo;.  I have no difficulty in allowing time to debate this motion in the House and I will ensure it takes place before the summer recess.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Leader for that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senators Coghlan and &Oacute; Murch&uacute; raised the matter of the new Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Cullen, and the new Minister of State, Deputy Mansergh, our former Seanad colleague.  As Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; said, there is no more experienced person than former Senator, Deputy Mansergh, to take on this role.  I had the pleasure of being in Adare last Friday when the Minister of State was performing an official function and I met some of his officials in attendance to support our Irish colleagues playing for Ireland in the Irish Open.  I believe the Minister of State, Deputy Mansergh, will excel in his Department.  He is an eminent person.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>He is covering sports as well.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I look forward very much to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>He will roof the Rock of Cashel.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;his assisting all parts of Ireland not only Killarney.  I will<Col N="822"/> be in Killarney in the second week of July for the start of my holidays, as I am every year. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>We will meet again.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>No Seanad vote is secure.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I fully agree with the expectations of Senator Coghlan in regard to the former Senator&rsquo;s appointment to this portfolio.  Senator Joe O&rsquo;Reilly called on me to give my opinion on statements in the <i>Irish Examiner</i>.  I will come back to the Senator when I clarify the statements with the various Departments.  Senator Bacik called for a debate on prisons, improvements in prison services, prison facilities and on the proposed new prison.  I have no difficulty leaving time aside for such a debate.</P>
        <P>Senator John Paul Phelan called for a debate on drug driving testing and highlighted a document published in recent days.  I have no difficulty leaving aside time for such a debate.  To my knowledge, the only countries in which this testing takes place are New Zealand and Australia.  This relates to penalty points and random breath testing.  The committee responsible for this issue, which is probably the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Health and Children, should investigate how we can adopt best practice.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Frances Fitzgerald has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business that: &ldquo;A debate on the housing market be taken today.&rdquo;  Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 19; N&iacute;l, 24.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading>
        <YesVote pid="IvanaBacik">Bacik, Ivana.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaulBradford">Bradford, Paul.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaddyBurke">Burke, Paddy.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JerryButtimer">Buttimer, Jerry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaulCoghlan">Coghlan, Paul.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MauriceCummins">Cummins, Maurice.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaschalDonohoe">Donohoe, Paschal.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FrancesFitzgerald">Fitzgerald, Frances.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DominicHannigan">Hannigan, Dominic.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FidelmaHealyEames">Healy Eames, Fidelma.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="NickyMcFadden">McFadden, Nicky.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DavidNorris">Norris, David.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JoeOReilly">O&rsquo;Reilly, Joe.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JoeOToole">O&rsquo;Toole, Joe.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnPaulPhelan">Phelan, John Paul.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PhilPrendergast">Prendergast, Phil.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="EugeneRegan">Regan, Eugene.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrendanRyan">Ryan, Brendan.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AlexWhite">White, Alex.</YesVote>
        <NHeading>N&iacute;l</NHeading>
        <NoVote pid="DanBoyle">Boyle, Dan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MartinBrady">Brady, Martin.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="LarryButler">Butler, Larry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="IvorCallely">Callely, Ivor.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CiaranCannon">Cannon, Ciaran.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnCartyFF">Carty, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DonnieCassidyFF">Cassidy, Donie.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MariaCorrigan">Corrigan, Maria.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MarkDaly">Daly, Mark.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DeirdredeBurca">de B&uacute;rca, D&eacute;irdre.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnEllis">Ellis, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="GeraldineFeeney">Feeney, Geraldine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CamillusGlynn">Glynn, Camillus.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnGerardHanafin">Hanafin, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TerryLeyden">Leyden, Terry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MarcMacSharry">MacSharry, Marc.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="LisaMcDonald">McDonald, Lisa.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="BrianODomhnaill">&Oacute; Domhnaill, Brian.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FrancisOBrien">O&rsquo;Brien, Francis.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="AnnOrmonde">Ormonde, Ann.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="KieranPhelan">Phelan, Kieran.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MaryMWhite">White, Mary M.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</NoVote>
        <Tellers>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators J<Col N="823"/>erry Buttimer and Maurice Cummins; N&iacute;l, Senators D&eacute;irdre de B&uacute;rca and Diarmuid Wilson.</Tellers>
        <Decision><?oasys _is0p10- ?>Amendment declared lost.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="3" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <?oasys _cl14.5- ?><MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Tragedy in Burma:" RHead="Statements"> 
    <Title>Tragedy in Burma: Statements. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin"><TitleTxt>Minister for Foreign Affairs</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin</NameTxt>
	<P>Cyclone Nargis struck Burma-Myanmar on 2 and 3 May 2008 with winds up to 200 km/h, sweeping through the delta region and the country&rsquo;s main city and former capital, Yangon.  Damage from the cyclone was most severe in the delta region, where the effects of extreme winds were compounded by a sizable storm surge that destroyed an estimated 95% of housing.</P>
        <P>Yangon sustained a direct hit, which downed power and communications lines, and inflicted major damage to buildings.  Even now, more than two weeks after the storm, people remain largely without electricity, piped water and communications.  Many roads into and out of the city, as well as vital roads into the delta region, are still blocked by flooding or debris.  For much of the delta region, the most significant transportation is normally by waterway, and water transport infrastructure has been severely damaged.</P>
        <P>The toll of people killed, missing, or affected remains difficult to assess, with the numbers continuing to increase daily.  The UN estimates that more than 100,000 have died and almost 2 million are in need of assistance.  To make matters worse, further strong rains are forecast.  Some 24 million people, approximately 50% of the population, live in the cyclone-affected areas.  On account of the season, a major crop loss is not envisaged, but huge swathes of fertile agricultural land were inundated with salty water and will require significant time to return to normal.</P>
        <P>Enormous challenges are involved in mounting a logistics operation of the scale required to deliver sufficient levels of assistance to affected communities.  However, the major challenge to an effective response has not been created by nature, but by man.  It is the reluctance of the Government of Burma to accept international humanitarian assistance.  In the days after the cyclone, the Burmese Government refused to issue visas for international humanitarian workers and refused to allow humanitarian supplies to enter the country.</P>
        <P>As time passes, there is an increasing risk of serious health problems among vulnerable communities, particularly as a result of Government imposed delays in the provision of necessary aid.  It is feared that malaria transmission will significantly increase and epidemics will occur in many areas.  In addition, lack of access to safe drinking water and the near total absence of sanitation in affected areas will increase the risk of diarrhoeal diseases, including cholera.</P>
        <P>The denial and impeding of access has compounded what was already a severe natural disaster.  It was more than one week after the crisis before supplies seemed finally to be getting through, although the quantity is still nowhere near enough to meet the needs of the affected population.  Even when supplies have arrived in the country, the government has curtailed their distribution, often insisting on taking control itself.  This occurs despite the fact that, access permitted, the international humanitarian community has greater capacity and the necessary experience to distribute  supplies effectively.</P>
        <P>The Government in Burma has also continued to enforce its restrictive visa policy.  Some aid workers who have managed to obtain visas have been turned back at the airport.  Visas that have been issued have, in some instances, been for very short periods only, effectively rendering them useless.  Delivery of humanitarian aid in a crisis such as this is a complex task.  Without experienced international staff, delivery will not be as effective.  There have been some repo<Col N="824"/>rts in recent days that the Government of Burma-Myanmar has agreed to relax some of its restrictions on aid and relief workers from certain Asian countries.  While this would be a welcome development, we must wait to see if it allows in more supplies and staff.</P>
        <P>Last week, the EU Presidency convened a special emergency meeting of the General Affairs and External Relations Council to underline the severity of this crisis.  It is noteworthy that the terrorist attack of 11 September 2001 and the tsunami were the most recent occasions to give rise to the convening of such an extraordinary Council meeting.  In its conclusions the Council,<i> inter alia,</i> considered that without the co-operation of the authorities in Burma an even greater tragedy is threatened; fully shared the deep concern recently expressed by the UN Secretary General and UN bodies to help meet the humanitarian needs of the Burmese people; stressed its strong support for the efforts of the UN, the Red Cross and Red Crescent movements and NGOs to bring aid to the people of Burma and underlined the point that the effective delivery of aid must be monitored by expert humanitarian staff; and, while welcoming recent albeit limited improvements on the ground, called on the authorities in Burma to offer free and unfettered access to international humanitarian experts, including the expeditious delivery of visa and travel permits.</P>
        <P>The Council also expressed support for the visit to the region by the EU Commissioner for Development and Humanitarian Aid, Louis Michel.  During his visit to Yangon last week, Commissioner Michel met with several Ministers and sought progress from the competent Burmese authorities in ensuring access by humanitarian aid workers to the country and to the affected areas.  Issues he raised included visa extensions for humanitarian workers and access to the affected area for international relief staff.</P>
      
        <P>Ireland has been to the fore in calling for full and free access to the affected areas for relief supplies and workers and Irish embassies in neighbouring countries have made representations seeking their assistance in getting access for the international relief effort.  Ireland will continue to use its diplomatic influence to improve the access for both humanitarian supplies and workers.</P>
        <P>The United Nations Under-Secretary General for Humanitarian Affairs, Mr. John Holmes, arrived in Burma on Sunday.  While there he pressed the Burmese authorities for more access for UN workers in the relief effort.  Earlier, he met regional partners and members of the humanitarian community to discuss how they can assist the Burmese Government in scaling up its relief activities.  UN Secretary General Mr. Ban Ki-Moon is expected to visit the country tomorrow.  We are hopeful that after his visit there will be an improvement in the access situation.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">4 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>Some of our European partners have raised the possibility of invoking the &ldquo;responsibility to protect&rdquo; agreement, secured at the UN World Summit in 2005 as a means of intervening directly even without the consent of the Burmese Government.  We would support any initiative which would bring aid more effectively to those in need but it appears very unlikely that the necessary agreement could be found within the Security Council to act in this manner.  Frustrating as it is, there may be no practical alternative to continuing to press the Burmese Government to allow in the necessary supplies and international expertise.  The obstruction of the international aid effort by the Government of Burma is unacceptable and I call on it to immediately lift all obstacles to the delivery of urgent, life-saving assistance.  Every day and hour is critical.  Thousands of lives can still be saved.</P>
        <?oasys _cl14.5- ?><P>There has been one positive development this week.  The foreign ministers of the Association of South East Asian Nations, ASEAN, in their me<Col N="825"/>eting in Singapore on Monday seem to have prevailed on the Burmese authorities to promise to accept increased international aid for the cyclone victims provided it is channelled through regional personnel and organisations.  We await their implementation of this undertaking.</P>
        <P>The Irish Government&rsquo;s response has been rapid and effective.  The Government immediately made an initial pledge of &euro;1 million for emergency relief.  This is being channelled through established partners in emergency response, such as NGOs, UN agencies and the Red Cross.  We are ready to respond further.  In addition to this direct support to the emergency response, Ireland is also providing support through its substantial annual contributions to two key international funds designed specifically to provide immediate finance in response to sudden onset emergencies of this kind, namely the UN central emergency response fund, CERF, and the Red Cross managed disaster relief emergency fund, DREF.  Both funds, which were established to make financial aid available to their respective organisations to facilitate rapid response to humanitarian emergencies, have already released significant funds to this crisis.  This year, Ireland is the sixth largest contributor to the UN&rsquo;s CERF with a contribution of &euro;22.6 million and the second largest contributor to the Red Cross DREF with a contribution of &euro;2 million.</P>
        <P>On Saturday, 10 May we dispatched an airlift of essential humanitarian supplies from our stockpiles at the UN&rsquo;s humanitarian response base in Brindisi, Italy.  The airlift, which was co-ordinated by the UN Office for the Co-ordination of Humanitarian Affairs, OCHA and shared with Norway, landed in Yangon on Sunday 11 May.  On board were large quantities of essential non-food supplies such as plastic sheeting for temporary shelter, blankets, kitchen sets and mosquito nets as well as tents, water tanks and water purification equipment provided by Norway.  The supplies have been cleared and are to be distributed to affected communities.  Irish supplies formed part of an earlier airlift last week shared with the Italian Government, which also pre-positions supplies in Brindisi.  We are ready to make further shipments of our supplies if requested and access arrangements permit.</P>
        <P>I have asked that our rapid response corps be put on standby for early deployment.  The corps is a roster of skilled and experienced volunteers who make themselves available to deploy at short notice to humanitarian emergencies.  If requested, members of the corps will be deployed to work with our partners, the UN Refugee Agency, UNHCR, the World Food Programme and the UN Office for the Co-ordination of Humanitarian Affairs, UNOCHA.  My officials remain in ongoing contact with our partners who have a presence on the ground in Burma and those who are co-ordinating the response from Bangkok to obtain regularly updated information on the needs of affected communities.</P>
        <P>The further tragedy of Cyclone Nargis is that it is a natural catastrophe piled upon the man-made catastrophe that has already engulfed the people of Burma, created by the ruling military regime.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin"><NameTxt>Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin</NameTxt>
	<P>A country that was once termed the &ldquo;rice bowl of Asia&rdquo; has over many years been reduced to abject and desperate poverty in many of its regions by mismanagement, corruption and military offensives against Burma&rsquo;s own people.  A country rich in natural resources is now one of the ten poorest countries in the world, its wealth in precious metals, stones, minerals and hardwoods plundered by the military.  There is massive diversion of state resources towards maintaining the military elite, with 40% of the national budget spent on defence, while its health care system is ranked by the WHO as 190th out of 191 surveyed nations.  Chronic levels of inflation, notably a five-fold increase in fuel prices last August, sparked protests which were brutally put down by the military on 25 S<Col N="826"/>eptember.</P>
        <P>The people of Burma have long made clear their demands for democracy, freedom, justice and economic security but these aspirations have been met by censorship, rejection, intimidation and brutal force.  The overwhelming victory of the democratic opposition party, the NLD led by Ms Aung San Suu Kyi, in the 1990 elections was overturned by the military regime and opposition leaders, and anyone seen to be critical of the regime, imprisoned or otherwise silenced.  On 9 February 2008, the Burmese Government announced it would hold a referendum on a new constitution in May, to be followed by multi-party democratic elections in 2010.  The referendum is the fourth step in the regime&rsquo;s deeply flawed seven-step road map to democracy.  The previous step, drafting the new constitution, was a 14-year process, from which relevant political stakeholders, including the democratic opposition and representatives of ethnic minorities were excluded.  No real progress has been made in seeking to allay any of the international community&rsquo;s concerns that the road-map process is a political tool to guarantee a permanent role for the military in the future governance of Burma.  The decision of the Burmese Government to ignore this major humanitarian disaster and proceed in most of its territory with this already fundamentally flawed referendum must be definitively deplored.  Reports indicate the regime has sought to push through the new constitution with violence, intimidation and vote-rigging.  This referendum cannot in any way be regarded as reflecting the real wishes of the people of Burma.  It has done nothing to assist the long-term stability and democratic development of that country.  Rather, by prioritising the referendum over aid distribution, the regime has put at risk hundreds of thousands of lives.</P>
        <P>Ultimately, the only sustainable solution to the political situation in Burma is credible dialogue on democratic reform with the opposition and ethnic groups.  The Irish Government continues to support the role of the UN Secretary General and that of his special envoy, Dr. Ibrahim Gambari, who was appointed after the crisis of last autumn.  Dr. Gambari&rsquo;s good offices mission offers the best path to encourage the ending of the political crisis and achieving national reconciliation.  So far, the Burmese authorities have not engaged seriously with the UN.  It is vital that they do so.</P>
        <P>Burma&rsquo;s neighbours, including ASEAN members and China, have a key role to play in encouraging the Burmese regime towards genuine dialogue and reform.  Bilaterally and through the EU we continue to urge their proactive engagement in pressing the Burmese regime towards national reconciliation, dialogue and democracy.  While, particularly last autumn, some of Burma&rsquo;s neighbours exerted a more active influence than heretofore, this has not so far been as sustained or effective as it needs to be.  Both Dr. Gambari and UN Secretary-General Mr. Ban Ki-Moon have stressed the importance of tangible action by the Burmese regime, and have rightly made clear that the patience of the international community is running out.  We believe the Security Council should be engaged in efforts to find sustainable solutions to both the immediate and longer-term problems facing the country.  In the meantime, I cannot but strongly condemn the behaviour of this brutal regime that continues to put its own survival ahead of the lives of its citizens, to rule on the back of violence and repression and to ignore the aspirations of its people for freedom, justice and democracy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I take the opportunity to congratulate the Minister and wish him well in his new portfolio.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMartin"><NameTxt>Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I join the Leas-Chathaoirleach in wel<Col N="827"/>coming the Minister to the House and congratulating him on his appointment as Minister for Foreign Affairs.</P>
        <P>I offer my sympathies to the people of Burma and China on the tragedies that have befallen them over recent weeks.  In China, in excess of 30,000 people were killed when an earthquake of 7.9 magnitude hit Sichuan province and in Burma, Cyclone Nargis left almost 134,000 dead with an estimated 2.4 million destitute.  We can only imagine the horrors that face the survivors and the families devastated, and the struggle to rebuild lives in communities ripped asunder by these tragedies.</P>
        <P>Many of us have rightly been critical of the regimes of both countries over their human rights records, and especially their treatment of minorities and their lack of democracy.  However, let me put on record my praise for how China has dealt with its catastrophe and my strong criticism of the behaviour of the Burmese military.  China reacted to its crisis with openness.  It was willing to receive all the help and support offered by other nations, placing the rights of its people to survive above any sense of political and governmental pride.</P>
        <P>Worldwide we have experts in the non-governmental sector who know how to deal with natural disasters, as the Minister stated.  These are people who know from direct experience what needs to be done in the immediate aftermath of such disasters.  They know from all too many past experiences how to assemble aid and get it to the people speedily, what health problems will arise for survivors and how quickly these problems surface.  Faced with a disaster of biblical proportions, China acted courageously and immediately, and many who might otherwise have perished survived because of that swift action.</P>
        <P>Would that the Burmese military had shown the same willingness to place the needs of their people above the ego of their regime.  Sadly, they did not.  The regime shut out the world at a time when it needed the help and support of other nations.  It slammed the door on the non-governmental organisations which could have helped save lives and which so desperately wanted to do so.  The staffs of those NGOs, who could have helped, are prepared for all that follows from such disasters &mdash; the spread of disease, the appearance of malnutrition and the emotional trauma of people losing whole families.</P>
        <P>Two weeks on, we have a man-made calamity which resulted from what was a natural disaster.  British Foreign Secretary, David Miliband, perhaps summed it up best when he told BBC One&rsquo;s &ldquo;The Politics Show&rdquo; that hundreds of thousands of survivors were at risk.  He stated: &ldquo;A national disaster is turning into a humanitarian catastrophe of genuine epic proportions, largely because of what I would describe as the malign neglect of the regime.&rdquo; The Minister, Deputy Martin, stated something similar in his speech in the House, and I welcome those remarks.</P>
        <P>The International Federation of the Red Cross has told us that the aid getting to the victims in Burma was nowhere near the level required.  Almost two weeks later, with hundreds of thousands of people in a large part of the country facing a crisis which is growing deeper by the day, the Burmese military regime still refuses to allow aid workers in, leaving ships laden with aid in the seas off Burma waiting for permission to land.  It is an appalling vista.</P>
        <P>When a Sky News team managed to get to some victims, having circumvented the virtual news blackout the regime had imposed, their report now stands as a powerful indictment of the military regime.  Their reports showed bloated bodies floating through the floodwaters and other horrific sights.  They showed people, left to themselves by their uncaring government, having to throw ropes around the corpses and pull them away from populated areas.  One old woman recounted how a military flight had dropped aid down to the hundreds below.  The aid was four packs of noodles.  It hardly could be called a token.  It could even be called an insult.  The people of Burma do not need insults.  They need food, a<Col N="828"/>id and medical supplies.</P>
        <P>However, the Burmese regime knows all about insulting its citizens.  Since 1962 the people of Burma have had to endure a brutal military dictatorship.  It has long shown its contempt for the Burmese people.  Mass murder of civilians to protect the power of the military has become standard conduct.  Hidden behind the guise of a one-party state the military for decades ran the state as their own fiefdom, using its natural resources to line their own pockets while leaving millions in dire poverty.</P>
        <P>When, in the first democratic elections in 30 years, the people of Burma elected the National League of Democracy to govern them under Ms Aung San Suu Kyi, winning 392 out of 489 seats in parliament, the military refused to hand over power, imprisoning Ms Aung San Suu Kyi for decades.  She is still imprisoned.</P>
        <P>The exploitation of the people of Burma by their military dictators has seen 800,000 subject to forced labour, leading to a threat from the International Labour Organisation to seek &ldquo;to prosecute members of the ruling Myanmar junta for crimes against humanity&rdquo; over the continuous forced labour of its citizens by the military.</P>
        <P>Only last year, yet more protests against the dictatorship, this time by Buddhist monks, were brutally repressed.  I recall the debate in this House on the situation in Burma after those protests.  Perhaps it is hardly surprising that the Burmese military have been so willing to treat their own people with such contempt that they would not allow international NGOs to help the survivors in their desperate plight.</P>
        <P>Recent reports suggest that the death toll may run to 140,000.  The United Nations has projected that 1 million people may have been left homeless.  The World Food Programme has stated that: &ldquo;Some villages have been almost totally eradicated and vast rice-growing areas are wiped out.&rdquo;  The World Health Organisation has reported outbreaks of malaria in the worst affected areas.  UN Secretary General Ban Ki-Moon expressed, &ldquo;deep concern, and immense frustration, at the unacceptably slow response to this grave humanitarian crisis&rdquo;.  Ban called, &ldquo;in the most strenuous terms, on the Government of Myanmar to put its people&rsquo;s lives first&rdquo;, and yet the military during those crucial early ten days would not let aid, either in terms of manpower or food, be delivered to its people.</P>
        <P>The US military tell us that about 11,000 servicemen and four ships are in the region for a military exercise and could be harnessed to help, yet it was not until 13 May, ten days after the disaster, that the first US military plane carrying 14 tonnes of food and medical supplies was allowed to land.</P>
        <P>NGOs, going on the record of Burma&rsquo;s military, were wary of handing over aid to the military.  &ldquo;The delivery of relief supplies can&rsquo;t be left entirely in the hands of Burma&rsquo;s abusive military, or aid simply won&rsquo;t reach those most in need,&rdquo; according to Mr. Brad Adams, Asia director at Human Rights Watch.  He also said: &ldquo;Without independent monitors on the ground, we can&rsquo;t be sure the aid is reaching those most at risk.&rdquo;  Those fears are justified, as Human Rights Watch explained.  Human Rights Watch confirmed an Associated Press report in which high-protein biscuits supplied by the international community had been seized by the military, and low-quality, locally produced substitutes were delivered instead to communities in need.  Even at times of crisis the Burmese military cannot resist trying to steal from its citizens.</P>
        <P>Human Rights Watch also reports that CNN footage showed a US aid plane being unloaded by Burmese men wearing T-shirts with a &ldquo;USDA&rdquo; logo.   The logo is that of Burma&rsquo;s Union Solidarity Development Association, which is a mass-based governmental organization deeply implicated in political repression and human<Col N="829"/> rights abuses in Burma.  Burma&rsquo;s Government often tried in the past to impose co-operation with the USDA on international humanitarian agencies operating in the country.  The International Red Cross code of conduct stipulates that aid must be given impartially, calculated on the basis of need alone, without adverse distinction of any kind.  It also states that unimpeded access to affected populations is fundamental, while those providing assistance are expected to ensure appropriate monitoring of aid distribution and to conduct assessments regularly of the impact of disaster assistance.</P>
        <P>The code of conduct also sets out recommendations for governments of disaster-affected countries.  Governments should permit proffered assistance and facilitate rapid access to disaster victims.  They should waive visa requirements or ensure they are rapidly granted.  Relief supplies and equipment should be allowed free and unrestricted passage and should not be subject to usual import licenses or taxes.  Given its record, it is hardly surprising that the Burmese military seems so unwilling to obey these basic rules on humanitarian aid.  I hope that China, which has recently witnessed its own natural disaster, will now see the Burmese junta in a different light and exert the strongest possible pressure on it to allow all international agencies into the country to administer aid to all who need their help and support.</P>
        <P>I would like to take this opportunity to compliment the Irish NGOs and departmental officials who are co-ordinating aid relief from Bangkok.  Let us hope that much needed aid such as food, water and medical supplies will eventually reach the impoverished people of Burma, who are persecuted on a daily basis by this cruel and savage regime.  Let us hope they will eventually see democracy in their country.  We spoke about this regime only a couple of months ago in this House, and we hope that the aid will eventually reach these people.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Before I call on the next speaker, I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Power, on his first appearance in this Chamber.  I congratulate him and I wish him well in his new portfolio.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Senator Ann Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State and I congratulate him on his new appointment.  As Government spokesperson on foreign affairs in this House, I look forward to working with him and doing what I can to help him when he is in this Chamber.</P>
        <P>I welcome the opportunity to say a few words on the crisis in Burma.  I join with others in offering my sympathy to the Burmese people.  Cyclone Nargis, which occurred on 2 and 3 May, caused huge destruction, injuries and loss of life.  It occurred under the dictatorship of the all-powerful Burmese military regime, and I understand from reports that the authorities there had 48 hours&rsquo; notice of the cyclone, but had no contingency plans to help vulnerable people.  This struck me as very serious.</P>
        <P>I looked at the map to see the area destroyed, which is known as the delta area.  The cyclone destroyed communication lines and inflicted damage on buildings.  Roads and waterworks were destroyed, while there is no water or electricity.  This occurred under the watch of the military regime.  According to UN and Red Cross estimates, it is feared that more than 130,000 people have died, while more than 1.5 million people are in need of assistance.  I also understand that 50% of the population live in the cyclone affected areas.</P>
        <P>There are major challenges in mounting this operation to deliver sufficient levels of assistance to the affected communities.  The Government in Burma is refusing to accept international humanitarian assistance.  There are still major health problems two weeks after the cyclone, and the vulnerable communities are suffering due to a lack of access to drinking water or san<Col N="830"/>itation, while the risk of disease is colossal.  While I acknowledge that some supplies finally seem to be getting through, they are nowhere near enough to meet the needs of the affected population.  The Burmese Government has been curtailing this distribution and will not allow those experienced in providing aid relied to go into the country.</P>
        <P>Burma is a rich country, with great natural resources in metal, stone and minerals.  These resources are being plundered by the junta, which is diverting state resources to maintain the lifestyle of its members.  Of the 50 million people living in Burma, 30% are very poor and operating below the poverty line.  They are malnourished and they have no education.  With this background, how can we get aid into the country?  It is only right that we make known our views about democracy and on how we can assist these people.</P>
        <P>The regime made promises that the country would move towards democracy, with a planned referendum followed by elections.  The decision of the Burmese Government effectively to ignore the major humanitarian disaster and to proceed with this referendum in most of its territory can only be deplored.  It clearly indicates that the Government was more worried about itself rather than the lives of the people in the country.  The referendum will not reflect the real wishes of the people of Burma, and the new constitution is a sham.  Prioritising the referendum over aid distribution clearly indicates that the continuation of the military junta and the lifestyle of Burma&rsquo;s rulers is more important than the lives of the most vulnerable, who do not seem to matter.</P>
        <P>We need dialogue on democratic reform.  The UN Secretary General must get involved and we must bring the Burmese Government to the table.  We must call on the country&rsquo;s neighbours, namely, China, India and south-east Asian countries such as Thailand and Indonesia to push for this reform.  We in Ireland will continue to do everything we can through the EU to urge proactive engagement in pushing the Burmese regime towards democracy.</P>
        <P>The obstruction of the international aid effort by the Burmese Government is simply not acceptable.  We welcome the contribution by the Irish Government of &euro;1 million for emergency relief.  That has been channelled through the NGOs, UN agencies and the Red Cross.  I also welcome the support, through its substantive annual contribution to respond to emergencies, of the UN central emergency response fund and the Red Cross managed disaster relief emergency fund.  The purpose of these is to facilitate the rapid response to humanitarian emergencies.</P>
        <P>There is a great sense of volunteerism in Ireland, for which we are known.  We have dispatched non-food humanitarian supplies of plastic sheeting for temporary shelter, blankets, mosquito nets and tents to be distributed to the affected communities.  The rapid response corps is on standby, ready for deployment to humanitarian emergencies.</P>
        <P>The people in Burma have long made demands for democracy, freedom of expression and justice but these aspirations have been met by censorship.  Those critical of the regime were imprisoned or otherwise silenced.  The Burmese authorities have isolated the cyclone areas from the rest of the world and expelled foreign aid workers.  Only a trickle of international aid is reaching the 2 million people made homeless.  Through the EU Presidency, an emergency meeting of the General Affairs Council has been convened to underline the severity of the crisis alongside the UN Secretary General and to express support for any initiative to help those affected.</P>
        <P>I acknowledge the strong support of the efforts of the UN Red Cross and the NGOs to bring aid to the Burmese people.  It is important that this aid be administered and monitored by experienced humanit<Col N="831"/>arian staff.  I urge the Burmese authorities to facilitate access to the international experts and expedite delivery of visas and travel permits.  Ireland has come to the fore in calling for full and free access to the affected areas through embassies in neighbouring countries and will continue to use diplomatic influence to improve the situation.  Knowing that China has experienced its own earthquake, it may be able to push for access to humanitarian aid.  I deplore what has happened.  I am reading the newspaper reports every day and cannot say strongly enough how much each of us must push for democracy in a country that has been so silenced through the years.  Through the UN, the EU and the General Affairs Council we may be able to push forward moves to bring reform.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I join with my colleagues in welcoming my former comrade on the Joint Committee on Transport, the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Power, to the House.  I congratulate him on his elevation and also Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin on his assignation to the Department of Foreign Affairs, which is a plum job in Government, even though one must sometimes confront difficult and tragic situations such as this.</P>
        <P>This is one of the situations where we are all united.  I listened with great interest to the thoughtful contribution of Senator Cummins and also to the considered view of Senator Ann Ormonde.  I compliment her on continuing to speak when she had some difficulty, which she courageously managed to overcome.  It is welcome that she put her views on the record because it makes it clear that from the Minister down we are all singing from the same hymn sheet.</P>
        <P Just="Left">This was a natural catastrophe.  A series of elements must be considered because this was predicted.  Two, three and four years ago people talked about the places that would be most vulnerable in the world in terms of global warming and the change in weather systems.  A low-lying delta region, the Irrawaddy Delta, was obviously one that would be focussed on.  This has happened before and General Than Shwe ran away from the place where he created the capital, Yangon.  He would not face his people in the moment of tragedy.</P>
        <P>I am often harshly critical of the Chinese Government and its approach but what a contrast there is in the way the Chinese leadership rolled up its sleeves and showed solidarity with its people when it was confronted by a parallel disaster.  That disaster has repercussions for this situation because Chinese attention is understandably and inevitably diverted from its neighbour to coping with its own situation.  China will be less able to co-operate with the rest of the world in exerting pressure but it is part of the key.  It has given massive military aid to the Burmese Government, which I deplore and regret, and is involved in trade in oil and gas.  China is a key player, so this is a double tragedy.</P>
        <P>The existing situation was awful.  Thanks to the regime there has been accelerating poverty &mdash; an impoverishment of its people &mdash; ever since it got into power.  It continues to persecute all the democratic elements, the best known of which is the heroic woman Aung San Suu Kyi, of whom, I am sorry to say, we have heard little during the recent crisis.  I sincerely hope her well-being is protected and that we ensure this through our diplomatic agencies.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Before this cyclone occurred, 75% of the people lived below the poverty line and one third of Burmese children were at least moderately malnourished.  The army had the largest forcibly conscripted child soldier element in the world.  They cared little for their own people but managed to stagger on because of resources and links with surrounding countries.  Thailand has the highest trade balance with the Burmese, principally because of the Thai Government&rsquo;s purchase of natural gas, which is considerable.  Thailand is the principal country propping up of the Burmese regime.  In 2005, the Burmese Government imposed a massive increase in the domestic price of the essential supplies of oil and gas<Col N="832"/>.</P>
        <P>Last autumn, we discussed the riots that took place when a peaceful demonstration led by Buddhist monks was savagely attacked and repressed by the Burmese Government.  I drew a contrast between the behaviour of the Chinese Government and the Burmese Government but there is also an internal contrast to be drawn between the ruthless efficiency in the way they galvanised military resources to repress their people and their impotence in confronting this disaster and coming positively to the aid of their people.  It is an obscenity that they leave planeloads of aid, food and medical supplies stranded on the tarmac in surrounding countries, that they inhibit the issuing of visas and that they continue their profligate lifestyles despite the fact that the Burmese people are suffering.</P>
        <P>There is a role of dishonour, a role of international shame that does not stop with members of the Burmese junta.  After the repression and violence visited on the Burmese people, India, China, Malaysia and Thailand continued to negotiate financial arrangements with the Burmese junta.  Perhaps they thought this was &ldquo;constructive engagement&rdquo;, a phrase I first heard in the context of dealings with the military regime in Burma but, does it work?  When Burma joined the Association of South East Asian Nations, ASEAN, in 1997 there were 210,000 Burmese refugees in neighbouring countries.  Before the cyclone hit and, following this &ldquo;constructive engagement&rdquo; by the ASEAN countries, this figure had almost tripled to 750,000.</P>
        <P>I referred earlier to the issue of oil.  The situation in this regard is instructive and interesting and goes back as far 1871 when the British, who do not have a particularly good record either, were in control and the Rangoon Oil Company was established.  During the closing decades of the last century natural gas was discovered.  Various groups were involved including the British, French and the Americans.  The American companies involved, Texaco and Unocal, behaved in a  brutal manner and collaborated with the military junta in the exploitation of the natural resources.  This is important because it calls into question the words of President Bush and his wife.  Correct though they were, the source of those words actually pollutes them because they have no moral status whatever.</P>
        <P>I will provide another contrast for the House, namely, that between President Bush&rsquo;s fine words in chiding the Burmese authorities and his record with regard to Hurricane Katrina.  The manner in which he abandoned his own racially inferior groups, as no doubt they were seen in some sections following the hurricane, is a mirror image of what happened in Burma.  Let us consider further Unocal, the oil company to which I referred  earlier.</P>
        <P>In 1996, a human rights suit was filed against Unocal by local villagers whose men were conscripted, forcibly dislodged from their land and whose women were raped, with their children taken away as soldiers.  This was to facilitate the construction of a $1.2 billion gas pipeline to take natural gas into Thailand.  The suit was settled by Unocal in 2004, which means it admitted a degree of liability, as a result of the unearthing of the situation by international agencies.  One woman gave personal testimony of how the soldiers came to her home, shot her husband and killed her baby.  Others said their neighbours had been executed in front of them because they refused to leave the area Unocal wanted and so on.</P>
        <P>In 1995, the United Nations put out warnings about serious human rights abuses following which Texaco left Burma but Unocal remained and continues to retain a 28% share in the pipeline.  Members may wonder where this is leading;  it is leading directly to the Bush Administration.  The US State Department acknowledged that slave labour was being used and defended Unocal against the suit taken by the local villagers because it believed it was inimical to United States foreign policy and, in particular, to the so-called war on terror.</P>
        <P>There are lessons for us all.  The international community need<Col N="833"/>s to get involved in the way we have.  I was interested to hear the outrage expressed by the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Martin, whom I have known for many years and who is usually moderate and diplomatic, in the final paragraph of his speech when he excoriated the regime in Burma.  I pay tribute to the local people about whom we have heard very little.  They have had to struggle through mud and wreckage.  We have all heard the descriptions of forests pelted by the cyclone to such an extent the trees were like groups of stalks and of the stench of death coming from the corpses.  The scale of the disaster is such that approximately 130,000, possibly 200,000 or 250,000 people have been affected.</P>
        <P>One phrase seems to sum up the scale of the devastation.  Even the efforts now being weakly consented to by the Burmese authorities were described by a local Burmese man as, &ldquo;Like throwing sesame seeds at a hungry elephant&rdquo;.  That is the scale of this disaster.  It is welcome that we are all united in our support for the tragic situation in which the Burmese people find themselves and in condemnation of the regime there.  I hope to God that tragic as is the situation, it may at last put the skids under that lousy government.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to share time with Senator de B&uacute;rca.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and congratulate him on his appointment.  I am sure responding to issues like this will be grist to his mill however unpalatable are the events that lie behind it. </P>
        <P>Scientifically, the reasons violent weather events occur are fairly well known to us though philosophically and theologically probably less so.  There is no easy, political answer as to how they should be dealt with.  A number of years ago, the United States, the most prosperous nation in the world and most open and democratic, failed to deal adequately with the effects of a hurricane in New Orleans.</P>
        <P>At the same time this catastrophic event happened in Burma, the Chinese Government, a government with a number of foreign policy difficulties and human rights violations within its own borders, has responded quite well to a similar catastrophe.  It has done so by showing an openness not shown by the Burmese authorities.  Its acceptance of &euro;1 million in aid from Ireland is a sign of the recognition by the Chinese authorities for the need to accept assistance from whatever source to deal with what is a human catastrophe.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The difficulty is that Burma has been always a closed state, run for the interests of a select few.  I recall as a teenager my father bringing a wall chart from the <i>National Geographic</i> magazine showing the peoples of South East Asia, not alone in Burma but in Thailand, Laos, Cambodia and Vietnam.  We have learned since then not only about the systematic political crackdown on the forces of democracy represented by Aung Sang Suu Kyi but also the ethnic violence perpetrated on people like the Karen people in Burma.  Yet, in a natural catastrophe like this, it seems to heap insult on a people living a miserable life that we in the developed world have failed to respond adequately.</P>
        <P>Some months ago, we discussed in this House the failure to adequately support an internal uprising in Burma largely led by Buddhist monks.  Now, a short time later we find ourselves speaking about what is a benighted country in terms of its recent history.  That said, however odious the regime that exists there, we must put aside our political differences and try to use every means at our disposal to ensure assistance gets into Burma as quickly as possible.  It is more than a little frustrating to hear that 300 peo<Col N="834"/>ple from ASEAN countries are being allowed in by the Burmese Government and that a conference by the United Nations and ASEAN will be held next week in order to decide how best to get aid in to the country.</P>
        <P>We must do things differently and better.  On every ground, the Burmese regime is failing its people and its country.  However, we must put this aside and use whatever mechanisms and resources are available to us as a country, which has some stock in terms of international relations, to assuage the misery inflicted on the Burmese people.  It has been admitted already that some 80,000 people are dead, a further 60,000 people are missing and millions are affected by displacement.  We need to be practical and thanks to the existence of the Burmese Government, what we are doing is far from adequate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdredeBurca"><NameTxt>Senator D&eacute;irdre de B&uacute;rca</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  Like my colleague, Senator Boyle, I wish to express my party&rsquo;s concern at the aftermath of Cyclone Nargis in Burma.  An estimated 128,000 people are dead and a further 1.5 million are at risk of disease and starvation.  The international community is having difficulty providing the type of aid which countries subject to natural disasters such as cyclones are usually willing to receive.  The junta in Burma appears to regard the admission of Western aid specialists as a political threat rather than as the vital assistance from the international community which it represents.  It presents the question to the international community as to how we respond.</P>
        <P>Two issues are raised.  The first is whether the international community has the capacity to act quickly, as my colleague Senator Boyle stated, rather than have a slow and inadequate response to a serious humanitarian crisis.  The second is what the international community does in exceptional circumstances such as these where the government of the affected country whose population is at serious risk of further massive loss of life does not accept the international aid available to it.</P>
        <P>The first issue was adequately dealt with in an article in <i>The Irish Times</i> this morning which called for the establishment of international emergency services.  This also seems to be reflected in the thinking when the Lisbon treaty was put together.  The establishment of a European voluntary humanitarian corps is one of the provisions of the treaty and it anticipates a rapid and effective response to a natural disaster such as that which occurred in Burma.  The European Union is ensuring it has the legal basis to be able to respond and the ability to develop the capacity to do so effectively and in a coherent way.</P>
        <P>The article in <i>The Irish Times</i> argues in favour of the need for such a response capacity at international level and the United Nations seems to be the appropriate body.  The European Union&rsquo;s attempt to develop this capacity within its structures is welcome but we need such structures at UN level so we can respond to natural disasters.  If we accept that the type of threats presented by climate change and global warming will occur more frequently, it is right and proper that the international community puts these structures in place.  Will the Minister of State raise this within the Council of Ministers and at the United Nations and allow the idea to gain currency?  We need to see it happening sooner rather than later.</P>
        <P>A more sensitive issue is that of intervention where a government, such as the Burmese junta, refuses to accept the aid offered by the international community despite the desperate and awful circumstances in which the population finds itself.  In such circumstances, we must put in place a new legal framework within the structure of the UN to allow for intervention in the interest of the common good where extraordinary circumstances prevail.  This is not to underestimate the principle of national sovereignty.  The territorial sovereignty of any State is well established in international law.  However, exceptional circumstances can arise and we should have consensus within the internati<Col N="835"/>onal community in this regard.  I hope Ireland will play its part in raising these issues within the Security Council and in other UN structures.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Senator Ivor Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>This is the first debate on foreign affairs we have had since my friends and colleagues, the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, and the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Power, took office and I wish them every success in their new portfolios.  As Chairman of the Oireachtas Sub-Committee on Human Rights, I am glad to have this opportunity to contribute to this important debate.  We are all deeply saddened by the terrible tragedy which struck Burma.  However, we are equally angered by the uncaring response of the Burmese military junta to the humanitarian needs of the millions of people whose lives have been devastated by the destruction of the cyclone.</P>
        <P>On 2 May, much of southern Burma, particularly the area surrounding the delta of the Irrawaddy River, was struck by a powerful cyclone.  The effects were devastating along the entire coastal region of the country but particularly in the low-lying delta area.  Thousands of people were killed, many of whom were drowned by the sheer force of the cyclone and the rapidly rising waters in the delta area.</P>
        <P>Cyclone Nargis has left an enormous human tragedy and massive physical destruction in its wake.  The exact number of those who died is as yet unknown.  It is estimated that the figure could be approximately 78,000 people with many more still missing.  Today, a national newspaper quoted a figure of 128,000.</P>
        <P>The UN believes that approximately 2.5 million people were affected by the impact of the cyclone.  Their homes, often poorly constructed, were either extensively damaged or in many cases simply blown away by the force of the cyclone.  The poor infrastructure could not withstand the strength of the storm.  Roads are still blocked by flooding and debris is making access by water to the worst affected region difficult.  Some of this debris is dead bodies.</P>
        <P>Millions are fleeing the affected areas because there has been no adequate response by the Burmese military junta to their plight.  People are short of food, have little or no clean water and are woefully short of medical supplies.  Entire villages are still cut off.  People have been traumatised by their experience and their future is a fight for survival.</P>
        <P>In many cases children have nothing to eat and there is a serious threat of water-borne diseases from the many human and animal corpses rotting in the water.  While limited amounts of aid have been distributed and aid agencies state that approximately 250,000 people have received rations, 150,000 people are reported to be in refugee camps and up to 1 million people have received no aid or support.</P>
        <P>I contrast this with what happened in the aftermath of the tsunami which hit much of south-east Asia at the end of 2004.  This was another devastating natural disaster with more death and destruction on an horrific scale.  The images of the tsunami, which also struck without warning, are still fresh in our minds.  However, we also recall the instant and immediate reaction of the international community to this terrible catastrophe to help those whose lives were shattered and whose livelihoods were destroyed by the tsunami.</P>
        <P>From around the world, assistance and aid poured into those places where the tsunami struck.  Food and medical supplies were flown in.  Aid workers from the United Nations, international humanitarian agencies and aid agencies around the world rushed to the region to help.  Ireland was one of those countries quick to respond and offer assistance.  Roads and bridges were quickly constructed to allow aid and aid workers access to remote areas where much of the infrastructure had been destroyed.  There was a universal outpouring of sympathy for those who had suffered from the t<Col N="836"/>sunami and this sympathy was backed up by humanitarian action.  No restrictions were placed on those who wished to help, and rightly so.</P>
      
        <P>What is happening now in Burma could not be more different.  My understanding and perception of various reports I have read is the reaction of the Burmese military government up to now has been to do everything in its power to block international aid and international aid workers from reaching those most in need of aid, which is disgraceful.  Instead of welcoming international aid and assistance, the military government has over the past 18 days put obstacles in the way of those trying to help those who need it.  Visas have been denied to aid agencies and the aid that has made it through has been woefully inadequate to meet the needs of the people.  Journalists have been denied visas and those who have secured entry into the country must operate in a semi-clandestine way concealing their whereabouts or risking expulsion.</P>
        <P>The behaviour of the military junta to date is tantamount to a violation of the human rights of the Burmese people.  It is reprehensible for a government to deny its own people access to food, humanitarian aid and medicine when they most need it and it is immoral to refuse to allow international aid and aid workers enter the country to help those whose lives have been devastated by a natural disaster.  The lack of action by the Burmese authorities has rightly been condemned by the international community as showing a flagrant indifference by a government to the fate of its own people.  It is the responsibility of a government to look after the well-being of its people as best it can.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">5 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>The military government in Burma is putting its own interests and survival before the basic needs of its people.  This behaviour must be condemned without equivocation.  Last September we witnessed the brutality of the military authorities in Burma to any dissent when they viciously put down protests by Buddhist monks.  Their behaviour over the past two weeks demonstrates they fear that the crisis caused by the cyclone could add further fuel to the deep and genuine discontent of the people against the repressive military regime that has ruled the country for so long.  There are indications over recent days that the outrage of the international community and intense diplomatic pressure on the Burmese authorities are beginning to have a limited impact.  This represents the lowest possible response by the Burmese authorities to the pressure rightly put on them.  Neighbouring countries will do everything they can to help relieve the terrible plight of the Burmese people.  However, this limited action by the Burmese military authorities only confirms they are determined not to allow major western aid agencies and their highly skilled aid workers into the country.</P>
        <?oasys _cl14.5- ?><P>French, American and British ships lie off the coast of Burma with large consignments of food aid and other supplies on board.  The authorities have refused these ships permission to offload their supplies in Burmese ports.  The agreement reached yesterday in Singapore will prevent the delivery of these much needed supplies.  Unless the Burmese authorities make further concessions, these supplies will remain on the high seas, which must be condemned.  Later this week, the Secretary General of the United Nations will visit Burma and he will convey to the Burmese military authorities the concern of the international community on what is happening in Burma.  I hope he will convince them that the slight opening they have agreed to in Singapore can only be seen as a first step and is in no way a sufficient response to the calls from the international community for greater access to Burma.  He must convince the Burmese generals that their obligations to their citizens would be best served by allowing the ships unload their supplies.  He must also demand that UN aid agencies and other international aid agencies and aid workers be permitted immediate and unrestricted access to those areas.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Col N="837"/><Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to share time with Senator Bradford.  I welcome the opportunity to contribute to the debate on the ongoing political and humanitarian crisis in Burma following Cyclone Nargis and the inaction of the Burmese government in relieving the catastrophe.  The authorities were busy trying to ensure their referendum was passed and they were uncompromising in this regard, stating there was a 99% turnout with a 92% acceptance rate.  Under the terms of this so-called constitutional reform, 25% of seats in the parliament will be reserved for members of the military junta, which means, in future, constitutional reform can only proceed with their agreement.  The junta is a disaster for the Burmese people who suffer terribly under this dictatorship every day.  The latest visible symptom of this is the government&rsquo;s inaction following the cyclone.</P>
        <P>The authorities are totally disinterested in helping their people and they are more interested in the control of information than the distribution of food.  A BBC news report of Burmese state news coverage of the disaster prominently features members of the junta handing out aid while, according to Associated Press articles, they have renamed the aid to make it appear as if they provided it in the first instance.  Burmese television has not carried footage of the disaster.  Death tolls or the numbers displaced have not been mentioned.  It was only after the Chinese declared a period of mourning for the lives lost in the earthquake there last week that the Burmese authorities declared the same for their country.  On the basis of the limited access provided, approximately 130,000 people have died but that number is increasing daily.</P>
        <P>Many others have been affected throughout the Irrawaddy delta.  Up to 2 million people have been displaced and they have lost their homes while being subject to potential disease.  The UN has four essential objectives in ensuring facilities are in place following a natural disaster: access to food, access to shelter, medical support against diseases and access to safe and clean drinking water.  All are seriously lacking in the aftermath of this disaster owing to the major obstacle put in place by the military junta.  Water supplies have been affected and people are crowding into monasteries to access water which is contaminated because of animal and human carcasses entering the water.  Disease, fever, diarrhoea and malaria are spreading at a merciless rate and children are most at risk.  Food supplies are at a worrying level.  The UN said in the past 14 days the price of rice had increased by 50%, even though prices were very high, which was one of the reasons for riots last year.</P>
        <P>A tiny proportion of the food aid that has been delivered has reached the affected people because the military authorities are hoarding the food.  In recent days, the government announced it would permit aid from its Asian neighbours but that will not be sufficient.  The doors of the regime must be thrown open completely to permit food in from the rest of the world.  Human Rights Watch and Amnesty International have highlighted Burma as one of the worst human rights violators in the world.  It does not have a functioning independent judiciary, Internet access is limited, children are engaged in forced labour and human trafficking is also common.  The authorities control political dissent by imprisoning their opponents, and everyone will be aware of the case of Aung San Suu Kyi .  The EU has put a significant trade embargo in place to ensure the regime is not supported, but this has not stopped a number of companies.  One French company continues to trade with Burma but it is before the courts accused of breaking the embargo.  As a member state, Ireland must ensure it does not deal with countries engaged in profitable activity in Burma.</P>
        <P>We must do everything we can to ensure the Trojan work of the UN is supported.  We need to provide all the help we can and we need to ensure we exert all the pressure we can.  I welc<Col N="838"/>ome the Minister of State to the House and I am glad the Minister for Foreign Affairs was present for the debate earlier.  It is essential aid gets through as soon as possible.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator Hannigan for sharing time.  I welcome the Minister of State to the House and I congratulate him on his new appointment.  I wish him well in this responsible job.</P>
        <P>A little ray of hope arising from the tragedy that has befallen the Burmese people is the international community giving serious attention, political and otherwise, to the situation in the country.  The light is shining on Burma, which was a forgotten country in a sometimes forgotten region.  However, because of the media attention, people at least are aware not only of the scale of the current tragedy but are beginning to become acclimatised to the scale of the political problem, which is at the core of all the problems faced by the Burmese people.  Burma is ruled by a repressive regime.  Historically, the response of all repressive regimes to any natural disaster is to shut the doors and keep out the international community.  Repressive regimes do not like international attention being drawn to their countries at a time of difficulty because it causes too many questions to be asked.  At least now, the international community in its response to the plight of the Burmese people is beginning to ask the necessary political questions.</P>
        <P>In his contribution, the Minister referred to what he called the &ldquo;responsibility to protect&rdquo; agreement or clause, which stemmed from the UN world summit in 2005.  The responsibility to protect is a very important issue.  If the international community exists as a genuine grouping and if the UN is to have any degree of influence &mdash; we have discussed that matter so many times here on previous occasions particularly in respect of Iraq &mdash; surely we must be in a position to in some way trigger that mechanism because we have a responsibility to protect and intervene in whatever way possible.  Food, medical and emergency supplies of all descriptions are necessary but we also have a responsibility to try to bring about political change and dialogue.</P>
        <P>Perhaps we must acknowledge that there have been tiny steps forward in Burma.  We cannot call it regime change but we can call it political change.  This must be very much encouraged and continued because the people of the country in the long run cannot survive under this repressive regime.  In the very short term, it is a question of immediate food, medical and support aid.</P>
        <P>I congratulate the Government on its efforts to date but much more is required, including from the international community.  At EU and UN level, we must try to keep the attention focused on Burma.  We are aware of what is happening in China but at least there is a better domestic response there.  It is an opportunity for us to take some small advantage of this tragedy to keep the light shining on Burma, its people and its regime and look for the necessary reforms which the people are demanding and for which they have voted but which they have not been allowed implement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I call on the Minister of State to conclude.  I welcome him to the House, congratulate him and wish him well on his appointment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PeterPowerFF"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Peter Power</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for his good wishes and those of all Members who have spoken in the brief time that I have been in the House.  I am delighted that this is my first opportunity to address the Seanad on this critically important issue in respect of an unfolding humanitarian disaster.</P>
        <P>I found all the contributions by the Members very interesting, particularly those of <Col N="839"/>Senators Cummins and Ormonde, which were very thoughtful and reflective and showed a clear understanding of the strategic issues at play, as did the contribution of Senator Norris who had a very good and clear understanding of the geopolitical problems that exist in that region of the world that prevent aid from getting through.  Senators Bradford, Boyle and de B&uacute;rca touched on the deep and unanimous frustration throughout the House about the inability of us as an individual country, the EU and the international community to act in a way that gets aid to the people most at need quickly.  This was a thread throughout all the speeches.  It is the crux of this issue and should be the central point of our discussions.</P>
        <P>As Minister of State with responsibility for overseas aid and development, we will not be found wanting as a nation, especially as the situation unfolds and becomes more clear.  We have already committed significant funds.  It is practically an unprecedented situation in terms of humanitarian disasters in that as an international community with all of the knowledge and information-gathering facilities available to us, we are at a loss to know the full extent and the potential horror that is taking place in the Irrawaddy Delta.  That is what makes this a unique and very difficult situation.</P>
        <P>I reiterate the condolences of the Government and the people of Ireland to the people of Burma, especially the families of the thousands who have died in the wake of Cyclone Nargis.  The enormous scale and destruction of the crisis in Burma has not yet been fully defined and detailed assessments have been hampered by infrastructural damage caused throughout the region.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There is little doubt, however, that the relief effort has also been hindered by man-made obstacles, specifically obstacles to access imposed by the Burmese Government.  Together with our EU partners, we have pressed neighbouring countries to use their influence to ease the restrictions the Government of Burma has placed on the flow of international aid.  We are strongly supportive of the visits to the region of EU Commissioner Louis Michel and UN Under-Secretary-General for Humanitarian Affairs, John Holmes.  We very much look forward to the visit of UN Secretary General, Ban Ki-moon, later on this week.</P>
        <P>Already, there have been some positive signs.  In response to pressure from the neighbouring ASEAN group, it appears that the Burmese authorities have agreed to an increased flow of aid to those in need provided that such aid is channelled through regional personnel and organisations.  In this unfolding disaster, I do not think any of us here in this House or throughout the country are concerned about how the aid is delivered.  The humanitarian imperative is that it is delivered now.  That will be the focus of my energies and efforts and those of the Government in the coming weeks.</P>
        <P>Further delays in the provision of humanitarian relief cannot be countenanced.  No further time can or should be lost in meeting the enormous needs in terms of food, drinking water, shelter, sanitation and medicines of the affected communities.  Together with our EU colleagues we again urgently call on the authorities in Burma to take immediate action to facilitate the flow of aid to its own people.  They are in desperate need and urgently require relief offered by the humanitarian community.</P>
        <P>A common thread through all the contributions is the stark contrast between the approach taken by its near neighbour China, which has a history of perhaps not engaging with the international community, and that of Burma.  In stark contrast, China has shown what I believe is a modern and enlightened approach to its own humanitarian disaster in respect of which we also send our thoughts and condolences.  China recognises modern realities and has welcomed aid, which is in marked contrast to the Burmese Government.  In that <Col N="840"/>regard, we have called and continue to call on the governments of China and neighbouring countries such as Thailand to use their strategic influence in the area to affect change urgently.</P>
        <P>For its part, Ireland has responded early and decisively to the disaster.  Our stocks of relief goods, which are designed for rapid response in situations such as this, have already been shipped to the area and are on the ground.  We have pledged an initial &euro;1 million in response to the disaster.  I reiterate that this is an initial response and we will not be found wanting should the need arise.</P>
        <P>In addition, we have been approached by Concern to activate a special Irish Aid emergency response fund to this crisis.  This is a two-year pilot programme which provides for a special fund from Irish Aid, my own section of the Department, to our three main NGO partners which can be activated by simple telephone call approval.  I have approved the necessary relief of funds under this provision and look forward to those funds reaching the people in need on the ground as urgently as possible.</P>
        <P Just="Left">If the Burmese authorities live up to their undertakings to their ASEAN neighbours, we should quickly have a clearer picture of the scale of the disaster and of the level of need.  We stand ready to respond further over the coming period.  Our partners in the humanitarian community, the UN, the NGOs and the Red Cross, which operates in Burma in immensely difficult and trying circumstances, deserve enormous credit and recognition by this House and praise from the international community for what they are doing.  They have our full support and encouragement in their efforts to save the lives and rebuild the lives and livelihoods of those affected by this appalling tragedy.  Ultimately, although Cyclone Nargis has brought so much suffering to the people of Burma, the callous behaviour of the Burmese Government in the face of such an outpouring of goodwill and assistance from the international community has exacerbated this awful human tragedy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Senator Ann Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>Tomorrow at 10.30 a.m.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 5.20 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 21 May 2008.</adjournment>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
