<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="26" Month="Jun" Year="2008" Vol="190" No="7" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 26 Meitheamh 2008" DateEnglish="Thursday, 26 June 2008" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="519">
    <Col N="519"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title></Title>
        <P Just="Center">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Paidir.</i><br /><i>Prayer.</i></P><Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad"> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have notice from Senator Paschal Donohoe that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to provide an update on the public private partnership housing project in Dublin and to provide details on discussions between his Department and Dublin City Council on dealing with this crisis.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Shane Ross of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Finance to reinstate Leinster Lawn to grass.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Finance to request the Financial Regulator to have discussions with the banking sector on the pressures arising at present on mortgage holders and business customers.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>There are storm clouds behind the Leader.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>We have some back-up material if anyone steps out of order.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Is it the Holy Spirit?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re the Employment Equality Act 1998 (Section 12)(Church of Ireland College of Education) Order 2008, back from committee, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, motion re the Planning and Development Regulations 2008, back from committee, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of No. 1; No. 3, motion re the Planning and Development (Amendment) Regulations 2008 from the Department of Environment, Heritage and Local <Col N="520"/>Government, to be referred to committee without debate at the conclusion of No. 2; No. 4, statements on the Abbey Theatre move, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 3 and to conclude within 60 minutes, during which spokespersons may speak for eight minutes and other Senators for six minutes, and on which Senators may share time with the agreement of the House; and No. 5, Prison Development (Confirmation of Resolutions) Bill 2008 &mdash; All Stages, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 4.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>One year ago our party and the Government laid out competing visions for what should happen with the economy and the future of the country.  On Tuesday, 1 May 2007 the then Minister for Finance and now Taoiseach, Deputy Brian Cowen, stated in reference to the plans Fine Gael had for the future of the economy and our intentions had we formed a Government that he intended to burn us slowly on a barbecue.</P>
        <P>My question for the Leader is, who is taking the heat now?  Given where we now stand, and the statement made by the Taoiseach last night on the need for painful corrective economic action, it is clear who is not taking the heat at the moment.  It is not the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Mary Coughlan, who is paid per week what many would aspire to earn in a month.  It is not the Minister for Finance, Deputy Brian Lenihan, who upon attaining one of the most important and prestigious offices of the State is now lamenting his misfortune at getting there.</P>
        <P>In the absence of a clear vision and statement from the Government on the state of the economy and, more importantly, a clear and detailed plan regarding what will happen, we are now operating in a vacuum.  We hear rumours and leaks regarding what will happen on vital projects which will make a difference to the futures of the people we seek to represent.</P>
        <P>I raise two issues which serve as examples of such hearsay.  There was a statement in a newspaper today referring to the metro north project.  The article appears with a quote from an unnamed source stating metro north will be cancelled and, in any case, is seen as something of a luxury in the first place and will be the first to go.  The project referred to is currently the largest infrastructural project in Europe, yet there is a quote in the public domain referring to it as a luxury.</P>
        <P>The second point is that the project, which is of vast scope and size, is currently in the final throes of a tendering process.  The Government is leading that process to try to get the best value for money.  What is the status of the project?  In light of leaks of this nature, how can we be sure that the Government is confident that it has the ability to deliver the project well?</P>
        <P>The second example I wish to give relates to the issue of public private partnership housing projects throughout Dublin, which I have raised in the House previously.  The Leader has great experience and knowledge of many of the areas in which the projects are to be located.  Perhaps he is able to appreciate the need to deliver these projects with real immediacy.  When I was talking this morning to the leader of one of these regeneration projects, he told me that he knows of people who have had to eat their dinner off their laps for many years because the units they are living in are so small and in such poor condition.</P>
        <P>The people associated with the projects have taken the hard decision to engage in community consultation.  They are trying to create a vision of how their communities can become better places in which to live.  A month has passed since it was announced that the leading tenderer for these projects might not be able to deliver them.  The communities in question are no clearer on what is happening.  The Government needs to step in and say what is going to happen.</P>
        <P>Some people say that economics is the science of allocating scarce resources between competing demands.  I suggest that politics is the art of doing that.  My party has made it clear many <Col N="521"/>times this week that the Leader of the House and his Government colleagues need to recognise what is happening to the economy.  The Government should publish a detailed plan outlining what it intends to do about these problems.  In the absence of such a statement, a vacuum develops in which leaks and rumours can thrive.  Those who are most in need of leadership from the Government are those who are suffering most.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I raised yesterday the whole question of where the economy is going.  I called on the Taoiseach to make a statement on the matter.  I am glad he made a few points last night.  They will be of some assistance as we try to do what needs to be done.  I welcome his comments to the business leaders of Ireland, some of whom earn over &euro;1 million a year.  He suggested that the lectures they have been giving to the rest of us about the need to take pay cuts represent a good example of how not to make progress.</P>
        <P>I found it difficult to accept the remarks made by IBEC yesterday, in the absence of an examination by that organisation of what its members are paying themselves.  It is not fair to try to pass all the pain to the other side of that table.  We need all the economic indicators to be outlined clearly.  We need to know where we stand and the scale of the problem.  We need to be told what the Government&rsquo;s objectives are.  We can then tell people what we are trying to achieve in terms of interest rates, economic growth and inflation.  In such circumstances, it will be possible to get agreement on what needs to be done.  If people succeed in meeting certain objectives, we will be able to share the benefits which will accrue.  We will need to focus on people on lower wages, particularly the minimum wage.  I am glad the Taoiseach mentioned such people.  He was right to emphasise that the most vulnerable people in society have to be looked after.</P>
        <P>Senator Donohoe was equally right to argue strongly that we should not write off projects under the national development plan on the basis of their scale.  If they are necessary, they are necessary.  Other projects, such as the programme of investment in computerisation in the education system, have stopped.  We cannot allow infrastructural deficits to develop.  I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the matter.  As Senator MacSharry said some weeks ago, if the Seanad can help in any way to make this process work, that should be facilitated.  People from all sides should be encouraged to make points like those which have been made by Senator Donohoe today and Senator Fitzgerald yesterday.  People on the Government side have also made worthwhile contributions.  We should hear what needs to be said and engage on such issues.  We need to force people to make their arguments stand up.  We should look at possible solutions.  If we can be of any assistance in that way, we are prepared to be helpful.  If we cannot be helpful, we will walk away from it and let them do it across the road.</P>
        <P>I wish to raise an issue I have been highlighting here for four or five years, with very little progress.  I refer to sole traders who employ their spouses on a full-time basis.  The workers in question pay PRSI at the A rate, but they are not entitled to many important PRSI benefits, such as the contributory old age pension.  This problem affects those who are working for all sorts of sole traders, such as farmers and accountants.  It is wrong.  I would like a case to be taken at EU level.  It has been suggested that the system operates in this way because we cannot be sure that one is telling the truth when one says that one&rsquo;s wife is working for one.  It should be possible to check whether a person&rsquo;s spouse is really working for that person.  If the work is genuinely being done, the person who is doing it surely should be entitled to the same employment rights as a person who does not happen to be married to the sole trader for whom he or she works.</P>
<Col N="522"/>
        <P>This issue needs to be dealt with.  The IFA has raised it on a number of occasions.  I would like all politicians to consider it.  I have raised this matter today in the context of the launch of a document yesterday by the Minister for Social and Family Affairs.  While the document gives more information in this regard, it does not come close to offering a solution.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I am pleased the Minister for Transport is meeting his Northern counterpart today to discuss the mutual recognition of driving bans imposed in the North and the South.  It is good to hear that they are close to agreement on the matter.  I would like to highlight the related issue of the mutual recognition of penalty points.  I understand that the two Ministers are some way apart on that matter.  As someone who regularly travels on the M1 between Dublin and Belfast, I am reminded on a daily basis that the mutual recognition of penalty points would increase safety on our roads.  I encourage the Minister, Deputy Dempsey, to do all he can to find a way forward on this issue.</P>
        <P>As someone who has strong links with Cork, I was concerned to read in this morning&rsquo;s <i>Irish Examiner</i> about toxic waste issues in the county.  My father was one of the last people to be born on the island of Haulbowline, so I am familiar with that area.  The newspaper report indicates that up to 500,000 tonnes of toxic cancer-causing waste are on the island.  This is a cause of real concern to the people of places like Cobh and Ringaskiddy.  Residents have joined Navy officials in expressing concern about the matter.  The Deputy Leader of the House has been campaigning for a clear-up to be undertaken on the island.  It is particularly worrying that his party colleague, the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, has sanctioned the cover-up of the waste.  We need a clean-up, rather than a cover-up.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister, Deputy Gormley, to come to the House to make an immediate statement to allay the fears of the people of Cork.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>The imminent publication of the national broadband strategy is eagerly awaited.  We need universal broadband access if we are to shield ourselves from the storm outside.  We also need to invest in education.  I was disappointed to read this morning that our schools have just one computer for every ten children.  It was worse to read about the age of the computers in question.  Some 20% of the computers in our schools are over six years of age.  We continue to expect our children to use clapped-out equipment even though the Leinster House computer policy document, a copy of which I have in my hand, states that computers are deemed to be worthless after four years.  How can we expect our young people to lead the world in the future if they are not being given the learning tools they need?  I would like the Minister to come to the House to update Senators on the information technology strategy for schools that is being pursued under the national development plan.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I will now call those Senators I missed yesterday.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I join Senator Hannigan in asking the Leader to bring the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to the House next Tuesday, as a matter of urgency, to debate the 500,000 tonnes of toxic waste in Cork about which we learned this morning.  This is a matter of some concern to people in Haulbowline, Cobh and the areas surrounding the Great Island of Cork.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>No local issues, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="523"/>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>We need a major debate on the matter, particularly as Cork Harbour is the pharmaceutical capital of Ireland.  Have the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government and the Minister, Deputy Gormley, been involved in a cover-up?  For how long have they been aware of this problem?  What have they done about it?  Like Senator Hannigan, I believe we need a big clean-up and an investigation.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the role of the Health Service Executive in light of this morning&rsquo;s report that there has been an increase of 14% in the number of staff in our amalgamated health service.  The Leader is a man of great experience and immense knowledge.  Can he explain to me and to the people how we have gone, following an increase of 18,421 administrative and management staff, to 106,272 employed in administration?  There is an increase from 16,137 at the end of 2004 to 18,042 now.  Can the Leader explain how an amalgamated health service that has seen an exponential growth in middle and senior management is now operating a pay freeze and cutting recruitment in front-line services?  I would like to hear his response.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NickyMcFadden"><NameTxt>Senator Nicky McFadden</NameTxt>
	<P>I join my colleagues, Senators Hannigan and Buttimer, in condemning the terrible situation in Cork Harbour and, like them, I request the Minister to come to the House.  I attended a graduation ceremony in the National Maritime College last week and it is a fine establishment.  I am aware of the huge catchment area which has 20,000 people living and working between Ringaskiddy and Cobh.  It is a scandal to have toxic waste lying there, possibly harming the health of all those people.</P>
        <P>Yesterday I wished to speak about addiction and those who are addicted to gambling.  <i>The Irish Times</i> covered this subject comprehensively yesterday and I applaud it for doing so.  I ask the Leader to organise an urgent debate with the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Dermot Ahern, who is on the record as saying that he intends to liberalise our gambling laws, especially those concerning casinos.  This would create a new form of legislation with regard to this serious issue in our country.</P>
        <P>I am not a killjoy and I know that many people can gamble in moderation and enjoy it.  As a nation, however, we are in denial regarding the considerable problem of gambling addiction and the heartache it causes.  We do not even have a psychiatrist in this country who has expertise in this area.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NickyMcFadden"><NameTxt>Senator Nicky McFadden</NameTxt>
	<P>That is a terrible indictment of this country.  I am concerned about on-line gambling.  The national lottery proposes to go on-line and sell tickets that way which I find to be a worrying trend.  I will not say whether I am for that or against it but I believe we must have an informed debate in this House.  That is what this forum is about &mdash; to debate all such issues.  We have a fantastic horse breeding industry in Ireland.  The ideal is to benefit from the benefits that industry brings and ensure we clamp down on the thugs.</P>
        <P Just="Left">While I was on holiday last year I was in a massive casino.  It is a terrible sight to see elderly people stooped over slot machines, putting in their money and afraid to go to the toilet or to eat in case the machine paid.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Las Vegas.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NickyMcFadden"><NameTxt>Senator Nicky McFadden</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not want to see that in our country.  I ask that we have this urgent debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="524"/>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>On Tuesday there were three shootings on the streets of Dublin.  Statistics show that many such crimes are carried out by people on bail.  We had a referendum on bail laws.  I wonder if that achieved what was intended.  If not, why not?  What action are we to take as legislators to ensure we get what that referendum was intended to produce?</P>
        <P>Gangland figures in prison are orchestrating crime.  A large number of mobile phones have been found in our prisons.  This should be monitored regularly because we cannot have such ganglords managing crime from prison.  That is the last thing this country needs now.  One would think that when such criminals are in prison, that should be the end of it during their period of detention.  That does not seem to be the case, however, because they are still operating.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I did not contribute to the debate yesterday although I wished to speak on the Bank of Ireland situation.  For that bank to reduce staff stock issue from 6% to 3% is a most provocative and unacceptable act.  It does not surprise me that staff are considering strike action as a result of that move by the bank.  We should condemn the Bank of Ireland for this act and ask it to reverse its decision as a matter of urgency.  It is not in the interest of its staff, of good industrial relations or of the community as a whole.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PearseDoherty"><NameTxt>Senator Pearse Doherty</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to echo a call I made last week, a call made by many Senators in previous weeks and in recent days, to have a debate on the economy.  I especially call on the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Coughlan, to come to the House and speak about the current job losses taking place across the State.  Members of Opposition parties, including myself, have pointed out repeatedly that this was going to happen.  The Government dug its head into the sand and told us there was nothing to worry about.</P>
        <P>Yesterday we had to sit here and listen to lectures from the Government benches telling us we must do the patriotic thing in terms of the economy.  My party and I have no problem doing that.  However, I ask those who call on the Opposition in this way to define what the patriotic thing is in terms of the economy, considering that this Government has presided over substantial wealth over the past decade. We can see the ways in which it has squandered it.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">11 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>When I consider patriotism, I think of one of the most important documents in Ireland, the Proclamation of the Irish Republic in 1916 and what the men and women signed up to at that time.  The Proclamation mentioned equal rights and opportunities, cherishing all the children equally and pursuing the happiness and prosperity of the whole nation and all its parts.  That is what patriotism is.  The Irish economy, steered by this Government over the past ten years, has failed on those three counts.  The Government has enriched those who were rich and has widened the gap between the wealthy and the poorest in the State.  Infrastructure is crumbling and there is no broadband.  All these problems exist and we will highlight them in a future debate.</P>
        <P>I have called many times for a debate in this House on education.  It is fitting that we should have a debate before the summer recess with the new Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Batt O&rsquo;Keeffe, on the needs of education in this State.  We see the Minister participating in the biggest cutbacks in education since the 1980s.  The fact that one third of our 4,000 schools is on the schools building programme list and that the Minister has not announced such a list since the beginning of this year is appalling.  Schools throughout the length and breadth of this State were promised and have received tenders&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We can have that in the debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PearseDoherty"><NameTxt>Senator Pearse Doherty</NameTxt>
	<P>There are schools where windows are nailed shut, where rodents are taking over&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="525"/>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should keep that for the debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PearseDoherty"><NameTxt>Senator Pearse Doherty</NameTxt>
	<P>I appeal to the Leader to understand the severity of the situation and to ask the Minister for Education and Science to come to the House&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator has asked the Leader for a debate and we will wait for his reply.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PearseDoherty"><NameTxt>Senator Pearse Doherty</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">On a separate matter, we all know that to have a strong economy we need a skilled workforce.  Unfortunately, we have a downturn in the construction industry which has been highlighted.  What is happening now is that those who are losing their jobs in that industry, who wish to go back to reskilling and avail of the back to education allowance, cannot do so because they must be unemployed for six months to qualify for that grant.  I ask the Leader, in the light of the considerable job losses in low-skilled industries, particularly manufacturing and the construction industry, to invite the Minister for Education and Science to the House to deal with this loophole and permit those who wish to reskill to be able to avail of the back to education allowance.</P>
      
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>We need a debate on the economy but it needs to be well argued and constructive.  There is no doubt issues arise but it amazes me when people talk about cutbacks in education given that education expenditure increased threefold to fourfold within the past decade.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>So has the population.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Walsh without interruption.  He did not interrupt any speaker.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaudieCoffey"><NameTxt>Senator Paudie Coffey</NameTxt>
	<P>What about the leaking prefabs?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I was at a meeting in my local hospital last week in respect of which vested interests argued the case on specific issues.  There were consultants, in both private and public practice, who are probably earning &euro;500,000 per year.  If circumstances are as they portray them, how come there were 60,000 people working in the health service in 1997, with an overall budget of &euro;3.5 billion, while there are 120,000 staff this year, with a budget of &euro;15 billion?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should ask the former Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>There are no efficiencies.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>Nobody in the hospital could answer&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>It is the Senator&rsquo;s Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>There is no delivery.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;why this is the case.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Walsh without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>We now have more complaints.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator has summed it up.</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="526"/>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Walsh&rsquo;s party has been in Government for the past ten years.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Walsh without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>Serious issues arise regarding value for money and productivity in the public service.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>For the past ten years&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I keep raising these issues and hope they will comprise an important focus of our debate on the economy.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader arrange a debate on speed limits at an early date?  The roll-out of the speed cameras is moving ahead.  If, when this is complete, we have not reviewed the illogical speed limits that apply in many parts of the country, there will be widespread disaffection among motorists regarding the implementation of the policy.  We want a climate of compliance that ensures motorists will remain within speed limits.</P>
        <P>I travel on a greatly improved road network, including motorways and a very high-quality dual carriageway.  The high-quality dual carriageway is up to motorway standard but the 100 km/h speed limit that applied on the ordinary winding single carriageway that existed before it was constructed has not been changed.  This is ludicrous.  We are spending considerable amounts of capital and this is partly so the driving public, particularly commercial motorists, can benefit.  Thus, we can become more competitive economically.  It is an essential part of improving the economy in any case.  I would like the Minister for Transport to be invited to the House to answer questions on this issue.</P>
        <P>Seven or eight years ago, I was told by the then chief executive of the National Roads Authority that this matter would be dealt with very speedily in respect of the Arklow bypass.  The authority has very highly paid executives who should be turning their attention to such issues, which are very easily resolved.  Addressing them would assist in the overall development of the economy on foot of the considerable investment made under the national development plan.  We want to benefit from the investment and want people to be sensible and intelligent in doing so.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Given that today is International Day against Torture, will the Leader facilitate a debate in the House on the use of extraordinary rendition and the role of Shannon Airport in this appalling practice?  Amnesty International is holding a special event today in Buswells Hotel, to which colleagues would all have been invited, at which a number of Irish actors will be reading from a book entitled &ldquo;Poems from Guant&aacute;namo: The Detainees Speak&rdquo;, which contains poems written by inmates in Guantanamo Bay.  This is an important event that will highlight the practice of extraordinary rendition.  Amnesty International is calling on Senators and Deputies to participate in the formation of an interparliamentary group on rendition that would take up the issue and lobby the Government.</P>
        <P>It is appropriate to debate this issue given that we heard this morning that the US Department of Homeland Security has, in an extraordinary move, requested permission to have a base at Shannon Airport for compiling data on persons on Irish private airplanes in the jurisdiction of Ireland.  It is requesting unprecedented access and we should not give it.  It is important that we debate this matter before the recess.</P>
        <P>The Amnesty International event is at 11.30 a.m. in Buswells Hotel.  On the way there, colleagues might consider dropping in to another event, which is being hosted by the All Party Oireachtas Interest Group on Sexual and Reproductive Health and Rights, Population and Development.  The event deals with population, reproductive health, environment and the mil<Col N="527"/>lennium develop goals. It is an important event at which experts will be present to brief colleagues on the links between population growth and the fulfilment of the millennium develop goals.  I would like a debate on this, if not before the recess, certainly early in the autumn.  Irish development aid has an important role to play in the achievement of the millennium development goals worldwide.  We need to consider the issue of population growth very seriously and determine how best we can meet the goals and facilitate reproductive rights in the developing world, particularly those of women.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>I call for a debate in the House and a national debate over the coming months on funding for third level education.  In Ireland there is no shortage of rhetoric about the knowledge society and our aspiration to be world class.  The reality, unfortunately, falls well short of the rhetoric.  By most indicators, our universities are significantly constrained by comparison with leading international institutions.</P>
        <P>On a per-student basis, real funding has been reduced by one third over the past ten years.  In addition, very little money is available for the maintenance and upgrading of the physical infrastructure for third level institutions.  All of this is unsustainable if there is a real objective to be world class.</P>
        <P>Investment in education is not a tap that can be turned on or off as circumstances require.  Failure to invest now will disadvantage an entire generation of people in the future.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Senator Ivor Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>The strategy of the Government is to have a knowledge-based economy as well as an education system with a bright future.  We need to devise a strategy of diverse funding and alternatives to public funding.  We need to make private funding not just an idea but a reality if we want future generations educated in our world-class system.</P>
        <P><?oasys _dc18- ?>One of the most critical questions concerns how we will compete internationally.  Our aspiration is to have 70% of the second level cohort entering third level education.  At present, only 60% are doing so.  Some 40% of young people cannot afford to participate in third level education.<?oasys _dc0- ?></P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>They are dropping out at second level.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>They are paying the taxes that are paying for the 60% who participate.  The system is socially unjust.  I call for a serious national debate on how universities will be funded.  The cream and the intellectuals of this country will want to go to Cambridge, Yale or Harvard if we do not invest in our third level sector.  I thank the Cathaoirleach for his patience.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>I want to be associated with all the remarks on the urgent need for a debate on schools and ICT.  The Taoiseach has always said he is committed to the national development plan and the roll-out of infrastructure.  Critical infrastructure is being lost to schools.  The Taoiseach promised us a soft landing but we now realise it was a joke.  Where is his commitment to the national development plan if he can be seen to allow Batt O&rsquo;Keeffe to pull information and communications technology from schools?  My main reason for speaking today is a matter of national significance pertaining to public health.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>In respect of Ministers, the Senator should not use their Christian names or surnames without giving them their full title.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Gabh mo leithsc&eacute;al.  I apologise.  I referred to the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Batt O&rsquo;Keeffe, whose presence is required in the House.</P>
<Col N="528"/>
        <P Just="Left">My main reason for speaking today is a matter of national significance pertaining to public health.  I ask the Leader to use his good offices to intervene with the Minister for Health and Children and establish urgently what is happening regarding the BCG immunisation programme for sixth class pupils nationwide.  Although schools will close tomorrow, I have received calls from hundreds of children across the city and county of Galway who have not received the BCG vaccine.  As the Leader is aware, tuberculosis is on the increase.  However, people from Lisheenkyle national school, to name a single example, have told me in recent weeks that it has not received the BCG for three years in a row, and I have checked this out with the Health Service Executive.  Something unusual is happening in this regard.  Having researched the issue, I am aware there has been a shortage of the vaccine but the parents involved are very worried.  I am unsure whether this is a national problem but it certainly is a problem in Galway city and county.  I ask the Leader to revert with an answer by next week because I must acquire this information.  How will children gain access to the BCG vaccine?  As I learned this morning that this could take 15 months, it is a serious issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Senator Ivor Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>As today is International Day against Torture, I acknowledge and pay tribute to all those who work in this area and who highlight human rights violations.  Equally, I pay tribute to a former Member of this House, Dr. Maurice Manning, who heads the Irish Human Rights Commission, together with his team.  The commission has done Trojan work during its first ten years.  I wish its staff, as well as everyone else who works in this area, continued success and good wishes on this special day.</P>
        <P>I listened with interest to a number of Members who spoke in respect of a debate on the economy.  I look forward to such a debate taking place.  There appears to be a certain focus on industry leaders and their pay and salary scales are being cherry-picked.  I recognise, appreciate and welcome those who have taken great risks and who have placed their families at great risk.  They took financial risks and helped fuel the economy.  Moreover, they generated wealth and contributed to the redistribution of that wealth.  I would like to think that recognition will be given to such people during the debate on the economy.</P>
        <P>Members received something of a lecture today from the Sinn F&eacute;in Member, Senator Doherty, on the squandering by Fianna F&aacute;il of the country&rsquo;s money and wealth in recent years and on its failure to cherish the family or the children.<b> </b> If any political party is responsible for not cherishing the family or the child, it is not on this side of the House.  Speaking on International Day against Torture, other people in this House, who are neither on this side of the House nor in the main Opposition parties, have questions to answer in that regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator&rsquo;s point is made.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Senator Ivor Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>Without getting carried away, a debate took place on the economy before the previous general election and one leader was seen to have failed to have any economic policies, namely, Senator Doherty&rsquo;s leader.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator&rsquo;s point is made.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Senator Ivor Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to obtain for me information relating to the National Treatment Purchase Fund.  It is a tremendous scheme from which great numbers of people have benefited.  However, some regions have not been able to tap into it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NickyMcFadden"><NameTxt>Senator Nicky McFadden</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="529"/>
      <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Senator Ivor Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>While Members may know the reasons, one must try to find a solution to them.  However, the problem must be outlined clearly.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>I request a debate on the provisions of the Government&rsquo;s proposed civil partnership Bill because I believe Members should discuss the Bill before it comes to the House to be considered.  Even after my short time in the Seanad thus far, I have learned that by the time a Bill comes to the House, it has been pretty much done and dusted and matters have been put to bed.  However, I am concerned about the serious unfairness and inequality the Government seems willing to countenance because of lazy thinking in the Bill&rsquo;s preparation.  I heard Senator Hannigan&rsquo;s comments in this regard yesterday and while I respect his point of view, I am concerned by the lazy thinking, which may have been exacerbated by a certain dose of political correctness.</P>
        <P>It seems that in the name of equality, the Government now proposes to introduce four categories of people that I can think of.  The first two categories are married couples and same-sex couples, who will enjoy a range of rights.  The third category is that of cohabiting couples, who will enjoy fewer rights despite the possibility that among some cohabiting couples, one party may wish to marry while the other does not.  Bottom of the pile will come those who are not necessarily romantically involved but are mutually dependent and who have made sacrifices for each other.  I refer to the carer who has lived for years and looked out for a loved one who may not be a blood relative but who will be obliged to pay a tax on anything he or she might inherit.  It appears, to paraphrase the former Senator Martin Mansergh, who now is a Member of the other House, that the State has been rushing back into the bedroom in this regard and appears to be about to perpetrate massive inequality.  Is this how we will cherish the children of the nation equally?  It is time for a debate and such issues must be considered in a cool-headed way that does not give into vested interests as a prime reason but seeks to do justice on behalf of all the citizens of the nation equally.  I hope such a debate will be facilitated soon.</P>
        <P>In addition, I was glad yesterday to hear Members on all sides of the House worrying and talking about excessive regulation from Europe.  We may be on the point of having a new and fresh debate about our relationship with Europe and I hope the two-hour debate held on the Lisbon treaty last week will not be the end of the matter.  I heard the points made by Senator Alan Kelly of the Labour Party.  He appears to seek a protocol on jam jars and labelling and listening to Senator O&rsquo;Donovan&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>That is incorrect.  Senator Kelly said the opposite.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>On the Order of Business, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>The eurosceptic is coming out in the Senator.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>I referred to a protocol that would exclude us from excessive regulation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>The eurosceptic is coming out in the Senator.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator O&rsquo;Donovan appears to be worried about eggs.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>On the Order of Business, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>He may wish to break free from the yoke of Europe completely, if Members will pardon the pun.  I hope we will not do so because we need Europe and need to be good Europeans.  I also hope, however, we now will have the courage to have a debate in this House.</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="530"/>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Senator to conclude.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>I am finishing now.  There should be a debate in this House about exactly what measures we must agree with our European partners in order that Ireland can be fully integrated in Europe but also with the independence it needs to guarantee equality of life for its citizens and the right to determine certain matters which it regards to be issues for itself.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGerardHanafin"><NameTxt>Senator John Hanafin</NameTxt>
	<P>While I would be slow to suggest regulation, I ask the Leader to write to the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food because a pressing need has arisen in respect of bio-fuels, requesting that the food part of the bio-fuel crop should be preserved and that the plant extract should be used for bio-fuel.  Ireland produces absolute surpluses, as do other countries, such as America, where 30% of its productive area is being used for bio-fuels at present to produce 3% of its energy needs.  At a time of world food shortages and high commodity prices in food, it is time to regulate the area in order that the food component of the bio-fuel crop is preserved and the plant extract is used for bio-fuels.  This is a simple request on which Ireland could lead the world as a food-producing nation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>The penny seems to have dropped with the Taoiseach regarding the economy.  One reads of corrective action now being taken.  In managing the economy, those responsible must understand it and must have experience of managing an economy in different economic circumstances.  However, the Government only has experience of managing the boom.  It even has failed at that, to judge from the evidence of &euro;10 billion wasted on such projects as decentralisation and infrastructure.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>Who created the boom?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>Where was it wasted?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaudieCoffey"><NameTxt>Senator Paudie Coffey</NameTxt>
	<P>Fianna F&aacute;il inherited it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should specify where it was wasted.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Regan, without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>The Government could not spend matches.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Order, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>While I appreciate&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should list the projects on which it was wasted.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is upset.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Regan, without interruption.  There already have been calls for a debate on financial matters, so I ask the Senator to brief.  I also hope to get two or three more speakers in.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>I have only started, but I will be brief.  I appreciate we will be having a debate on the issue, but I would like to make a point to the Leader about the Taoiseach, the T&aacute;naiste and the Minister for Finance.  Where is their experience of managing an economy in difficult economic circumstances?  Do these people have qualifications in economics?  Do they have experience in business, banking, finance or commerce?</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="531"/>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>We had a fellow here in the 1980s who had all that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>How can we have confidence in the Taoiseach or his Minister for Finance to manage the recession if they have failed to manage the boom?  There is a contrast between the current Government and those of Garret FitzGerald, Alan Dukes and John Bruton, who had the qualifications and the experience of managing an economy in the kind of circumstances which exist today.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The point is made.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>This Government has a lack of experience and qualifications and has a very poor track record over the past ten years.  How can we have confidence that it will manage the economy in this recession?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is taking poetic licence with the economy and those who run it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>He is only telling the truth.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to consider having a debate on Northern Ireland.  When I planned to raise this the other day, I was going to say it would be a good time to talk about the positive things because the killing has finished.  Unfortunately, we all saw what happened two days ago when a young man was killed, reportedly by the INLA.  I only hope that does not bring us back to the terrible years of all those killings.</P>
        <P>I wanted a debate on Northern Ireland so we could talk about the positive things that have occurred.  I read today that penalties for driving offences will be co-ordinated between Britain and Ireland, and between North and South as well.  There have been benefits in food safety, with the holding of an all-Ireland forum in that area, as well as in tourism.  There are so many win-win situations that it is worthwhile considering such a debate.  In the past, we tried to get an agreement on penalty points, but that has not occurred yet.  Those of us who know County Louth well can see the Northern cars increase their speed as they cross the Border because there is no danger of obtaining penalty points in the South.  I would love to see a debate on Northern Ireland.  It should be a positive debate, in spite of the killing that took place the other day.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaudieCoffey"><NameTxt>Senator Paudie Coffey</NameTxt>
	<P>I listened with interest to the views of Senators on the economy and the challenges that lie ahead.  It is important we can express our views.  I know the Leader takes those views on board and it is important we are constructive in our debate on the economy.  Our track record on this side of the House attests to that.  We have always been constructive in protecting the economy and we have stood by the State on economic issues.</P>
        <P Just="Left">We are now facing challenges in climate change, given the demanding targets we have set ourselves for the next ten years.  We need to debate those targets and the impact they will have on our economy.  Three areas that contribute to greenhouse gas emissions in this country are transport, agriculture and industry.  We need to get down to the fine detail on what impact emission reductions will have on those three areas.  Senator Donohoe already mentioned the metro north project.  If that is to go down the tubes, it will have an impact on how we are going to achieve our greenhouse emissions.  We will continue to have high emissions from oil-burning vehicles.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The economy is heavily dependent on agriculture, which has huge potential for growth due to food security issues.  Our agricultural sector contributes more than 20% of our total greenhouse gas emissions.  We cannot put our agricultural sector at a disadvantage if we are to cut <Col N="532"/>our emissions in this area because the EU depends on our food produce.  Greenhouse gas emissions from the agricultural sector across the EU are only 9% of the total amount, which is not too large.  I would hate to see the agricultural sector in Ireland under threat owing to these targets.  That is the type of detail we need to discuss in any debate on our economy.  Food security is a significant issue, so we must also take that into account.</P>
        <P>The Taoiseach heads up the Cabinet committee on climate change, so it would be interesting to hear the detail of the negotiations of Irish team, be they carbon credits or greenhouse gas emissions.  I hope the impact on our economy will be taken into account in any debate on this issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Senator Paddy Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I would like the Leader to arrange a debate on the funding of local authorities and the proposed Green Paper on those authorities.  The majority of local authorities are cash strapped, so there is an urgent need for a debate.  In the aftermath of the Lisbon treaty, will there be 13 seats or 12 seats at stake in the next European elections?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Senators Donohoe, O&rsquo;Toole, Doherty, Walsh, Regan and Coffey all called for a debate on the economy.  I have already said that we will have a lengthy debate on this issue before the summer recess.  The OECD report will be discussed in the House next Wednesday at 3 p.m.  There is no difficulty in giving as much time as is required to discuss this issue before the summer recess and to let the Government hear the views of the Senators.  Some very experienced Senators played a major role in forming the national understanding 21 years ago.  The challenge over the summer will be getting a new agreement, and the two most important words are stability and certainty.  That is where we need to go over the next three to five years.  I wish everyone well in their task of getting Ireland out of this global downturn.</P>
        <P>There is much frustration in the House as Senators from all sides want to see something that will give us hope for the future.  The Government is awaiting the figures for the first six months which will be published later this week.  They cannot be good, but we have been here before and have presided over a great change in our country.  We have seen substantial spending on roads, education and health and we know that we cannot continue if the money is not coming in.</P>
        <P>I will not score points because I am too long in the House to know that those who made a contribution&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Sounds like a bumpy ride ahead.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>He is in trouble.  The Leader is in denial.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader, without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I will say this.  I congratulate the Irish people for their foresight and wisdom in returning a Government that delivered to them when it was in power.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NickyMcFadden"><NameTxt>Senator Nicky McFadden</NameTxt>
	<P>What would it be like if there was a general election in the morning?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Imagine what it was like in this House when interest rates were at 17%, inflation at 15%, 50,000 people a year were emigrating&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>It was the Leader&rsquo;s Government.  He can bring in Ray MacSharry.  He did not offer many criticisms back then.</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="533"/>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and the national debt doubled between 1983 and 1987.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>He did not have many criticisms then.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Buttimer should allow the Leader to reply.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>We can go back to 1977 and Jack Lynch. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>There will be no going back to 1977. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>We can all go back in history. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator will recall reading about VAT on shoes when he was going to school. </P>
      </Speaker>
        <P FLI="0"><i>(Interruptions).</i></P>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>On the Order of Business now, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>The Taoiseach and the Minister for Finance cannot agree this morning on what to do. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Buttimer, please refrain and allow the Leader to respond to the Order of Business. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The former Senator Dino Cregan, a very responsible, decent and honourable Member of this House for many years, who played a major role in having Senator Buttimer elected here, would have heard from his generation when Fine Gael reduced the old age pension by 25% when in power at one time.  So we do not want to change&mdash;&mdash;-</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>That is right, look into the past.  See how the Leader&rsquo;s Government handles things. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NickyMcFadden"><NameTxt>Senator Nicky McFadden</NameTxt>
	<P>Fifteen years in Government. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I just want to give the House the benefit of being fair to all sides. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We do not want history lessons, either. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>If they are going to give it, they must also learn how to take it. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>We shall give it all right, do not worry, and we can take it, no bother. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaudieCoffey"><NameTxt>Senator Paudie Coffey</NameTxt>
	<P>We can take it, but we can give it, too.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>(Interruptions).</i></P>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senators, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader please deal with the economy? </P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>(Interruptions).</i></P>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Donohoe, who is very level headed, listens to the Leader when he asks serious questions, and I compliment him on that.  I know he has a great future <Col N="534"/>and I look forward to serving very many years with the Senator in the House.  I hope some of his colleagues take example from his sense of responsibility, and how he conducts himself here. </P>
        <P>As regards Senators calling for a debate on housing, I am pleased to say there will be a special debate in the House with the new Minister of State with responsibility for housing, Deputy Michael Finneran, on Tuesday week, 8 July.  This is a very important issue for discussion and I am responding to the requests made of me in this area.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Toole dealt with the question of sole traders, including people who are employed and married to traders.  This is an important issue, particularly as regards everyone in a family making a contribution towards keeping the business going.  I fully agree with the sentiments expressed by the Senator and we should make every effort to have this included in our pre-budget submission in September or October, when we come back for the autumn session.</P>
        <P>Senator Hannigan pointed out that the Minister for Transport was meeting his counterpart in Northern Ireland and we want to wish him well.  The Minister, like the Senator, comes from the royal county.  We certainly wish the Minister well in his deliberations there today.</P>
        <P>Senator Buttimer expressed his great concern as regards the toxic waste in Cork.  This is a serious issue and we support the call of all Senators on the Minister to hear what can be done.  I shall endeavour to have this further clarified in the House before the summer recess.  As regards the points made on the importance of broadband in schools and the entire roll-out strategy, this is one of the greatest challenges facing the country and none of us is satisfied with the progress to date.  That is to put the position on the record and I have no difficulty in trying to have this debated also.  Time will be of the essence, however, because there are so many serious issues to be addressed, such as the economy and the fishing industry, which must be discussed in the House.  I now have a timeframe for the housing debate, and I also want to inform the House that we shall have statements on Zimbabwe in the Seanad next week.  Many people are seriously concerned about this, but I do not want to say too much because the election is taking place there today.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>It is not an election. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senators will have an opportunity to express their views next week on the serious difficulty in Africa.  Senator Buttimer outlined startling figures regarding the HSE, given this modern age of computerisation.  We shall have another debate on the HSE as soon as possible.  Senator McFadden called for a debate on gambling addiction and the changes that are being contemplated by the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform as regards the gambling laws.  This is a timely call and I have no difficulty in arranging for such a debate to take place. </P>
        <P>With regard to matters that are relatively important but which we will not have time to slot into the diary for the next two weeks, perhaps those parties with access to Private Members&rsquo; time might include some of them under that slot.</P>
        <P>Senator Cummins called for a debate on crime, particularly in relation to experiences in recent days.  I support the Senator in his call, and compliment him on highlighting the big challenge to society.  I also want to compliment the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na on what it is doing to enhance, help and assist society in this regard.  Senator Cummins has been very strong and forceful in this area as well.  We shall have the debate on crime very soon, if at all possible.</P>
        <P>On the issues highlighted by Senator Cummins regarding the Bank of Ireland, I hope all sides can reach a successful conclusion.  Consultation and negotiation has got to be the order of the day and strike action should not be contemplated, if at all possible.  I wish the hard <Col N="535"/>working and dedicated staff, which the bank has had down through the years, well in bringing this to a successful conclusion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Doherty highlighted a very important issue as regards reskilling and upskilling.  A few weeks ago I made known my views to the House on the challenges facing F&Aacute;S.  If there is a six months delay before a person can qualify for a back to education allowance, this should be examined immediately, as should the 75%-25% funding.  It should be 100% funding because if companies have their backs to the wall in terms of keeping their businesses going, they certainly need all the assistance they can get.  If F&Aacute;S has got a significant allocation for retraining and upskilling between now and 2020, now is the time to make some of it available.  In my little village, Castlepollard, almost 600 people are now unemployed, which is a serious statistic in north west Meath, where there is very little happening as regards jobs.  As Senator McFadden knows, we used to have Bord na M&oacute;na, the ESB and many great employers, but they are no longer there.  Everyone needs to play his or her part.  The need for reskilling and retraining must be considered as a matter of urgency, as was pointed out to the House this morning.  I urge Senators to make this part of the discussion on the economy next week to ascertain if matters can be changed without further delay. </P>
        <P>Senator Walsh referred to the national development plan and spoke about the need for national speed limits to be updated.  The National Roads Authority is responsible for this and it is not a major job.  Once the cameras come into operation, if everyone is seen to be playing his or her part, I am sure motorists will be only too willing to do likewise.  Having 40 mph speed limits on a dual carriageway is unacceptable.  In some places the speed limit is 30 mph, or just under 40 kph.  This is unacceptable, since a dual carriage should have a 100 kph limit, and then everyone can play his or her part in complying with the speed limits.</P>
        <P Just="Left">As today is International Day against Torture, Senators Callely and Bacik called for a debate on rendition.  I can agree to that as well as to setting aside time for a debate on overseas development aid.  Senator Mary White outlined to the House in some detail her serious concerns about funding for third level education.  It is time for this to be reviewed, particularly in areas where jobs are to be found, such as science.  Ireland must be made more attractive for the brains of Europe to be educated here and to hold on to their intellectual property rights.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>The Government is not committed to such a project because it is cutting ICT funding for schools.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I did not interrupt the Senator.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>The Government is simply not committed to that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>We are the envy of Europe in job creation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>The Government is not committed because it is cutting ICT in schools.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Healy Eames, please allow the Leader without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>A Chathaoirligh, if I have to name someone in the House, I will.  We have asked Senators to understand when they ask a question, we must respond.  As former <Col N="536"/>Chairman of the committee on enterprise and small business, I had the experience of travelling practically the world.  I am giving the House the benefit of that experience.</P>
        <P>To me, the greatest transformation in technology is the Blackberry device.  It was created by two young people in Waterloo University, 25 miles outside of Toronto.  They, in turn, have established a campus which offers the intellectual property rights in perpetuity to the innovators and creators of new technologies.  It has the highest success rate in America and Canada&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>We want Irish people to do that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Senator please listen?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Please, Senator Healy Eames.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>With respect&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Senator to resume her seat.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">&mdash;&mdash;we are having a denial of the current economic situation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Senator to resume her seat and allow the Leader to reply on the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>If we can have that success and have Ireland as the base for intellectual property rights to be retained by the institutes of technology.  These institutes, such as those in Letterkenny, Carlow, Athlone and Sligo, have been the bedrock of educating the poor man&rsquo;s child and providing the opportunity for third level education which most of us never had.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader has my full support on that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Please, Senator Healy Eames.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of information to the House, Senators may not interrupt the Leader in his responses on the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is correct.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>It has not been known before.  It crept in during the last Seanad and was certainly not there before that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader should tell that to his constituency colleague.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I believe there is a tremendous window of opportunity in the technology sector which Enterprise Ireland supports.  We should explore the possibility of following the same course with intellectual property rights as Waterloo University for institutes of technology in the whole island of Ireland.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I commend Senator Mary White on bringing this to the attention of the House.</P>
<Col N="537"/>
        <P>I agree with Senator Healy Eames that the BCG vaccine is a serious matter and I will take it up with the Minister for Health and Children after the Order of Business.  I will return to the Senator when I hear further on it.</P>
        <P>Senator Callely called for a debate on the National Treatment Purchase Fund.  I have no difficulty in facilitating the Senator&rsquo;s request in this.</P>
        <P>Senator Mullen called for a debate on civil partnership.  I have no difficulty in having time set aside for this.  The Senator could ask Senator O&rsquo;Toole to take it on the Independents&rsquo; Private Members&rsquo; time before the recess.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not have that option.  Would Fianna F&aacute;il oblige me by bringing it forward?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Fianna F&aacute;il has Private Members&rsquo; business in the final week but I do not know which grouping has it next week.</P>
        <P>Senator Hanafin made a good suggestion for a debate on bio-fuels and the opportunities for alternative energy supplies.  With the agreement of the Whips, Fianna F&aacute;il could have this debate in its Private Members&rsquo; time in the final sitting week before the summer recess.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Quinn called for a debate on Northern Ireland which I will try to facilitate at the earliest possible time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order, I also asked for a debate on Europe.  Can that provide for?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">A point of order can only be made on a procedural matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Leader for responding to our request for a debate on the economy.  He said the debate would take place next Wednesday and would be on the recent OECD report.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not a point of order.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>Next Wednesday the Government will publish the Exchequer returns.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not a point of order.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>I suggest next Wednesday&rsquo;s debate centres on the Government&rsquo;s view on the economy as opposed that of the OECD.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>What about the debate on Europe I requested?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>No, I am dealing with the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader confirm the Seanad will not be moving this year?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>My understanding is that the Seanad will not be moving this year.  I will have an official statement on the matter for every Member as quickly as possible.</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="538"/>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>So we are safe physically for the next year.  It will not fall down on us.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Employment Equality Act 1998:" RHead="Motion"> 
    <Title>Employment Equality Act 1998: Motion. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft:</P>
        <P LI="2">Employment Equality Act 1998 (section 12) (Church of Ireland College of Education) Order, 2008,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is0p11- ?><?oasys _ix ?>copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 27 May, 2008.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Planning and Development" RHead="Regulations 2008: Motion"> 
    <Title>Planning and Development Regulations 2008: Motion. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:</P>
        <P LI="2">The Planning and Development Regulations 2008,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is0p11- ?><?oasys _ix ?>copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 16 June, 2008.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Planning and Development (Amendment)" RHead="Regulations 2008: Motion"> 
    <Title>Planning and Development (Amendment) Regulations 2008: Motion. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:</P>
        <P LI="2">The Planning and Development (Amendment) Regulations 2008,</P>
        <P FLI="0"><?oasys _is0p11- ?><?oasys _ix ?>copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 25th June, 2008, be referred to the Joint Committee on the Environment, Heritage and Local Government in accordance with paragraph (2) of the Orders of Reference of that committee, which, not later than 3rd July 2008, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 72, and Standing Order 74(2) shall accordingly apply.&rdquo;</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="2" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Abbey Theatre:" RHead="Statements"> 
    <Title>Abbey Theatre: Statements. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Martin Mansergh, to the House. He is well used to it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Arts, Sport and Tourism</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>The Abbey Theatre is a vital national cultural institution.  Historically, it was a flagship of the cultural revival, which preceded independence.  After independence, it was the first cultural institution to be in receipt of a State subsidy.  It staged then and since Irish plays of world stature, other plays of great distinction and significance, as well as some classics of world theatre.  It helped in the 20th century to create an outstanding literary reputation for Ireland that it did not previously have.</P>
<Col N="539"/>
        <P Just="Left">There is an important, if subtle, distinction between a national theatre and nationalist theatre.  Synge and O&rsquo;Casey wrote for a national, rather than a nationalist, theatre.  The Abbey has been a place where many of the best dramatists, players and producers from every tradition and outlook have come together with pride in a common cause.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The difficulties of running a national theatre, then and now, in an Irish context are not to be underestimated.  From time to time, they been aired in the press.  A former Senator under the Free State, W.B. Yeats, expressed it in verse:</P>
        <P LI="1">When we are high and airy hundreds say</P>
        <?oasys _mv-5- ?><P LI="1" el="0">That if we hold that flight they&rsquo;ll leave the place,</P>
        <?oasys _mv-5- ?><P LI="1" el="0">While those same hundreds mock another day</P>
        <?oasys _mv-5- ?><P LI="1" el="0">Because we have made our art of common things.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I welcome the interest shown in the future of the Abbey by many Senators, including Senators Coghlan and Norris.  Senator Norris wrote to me regretting that he cannot be here for this debate; we had some banter about it on the Order of Business in March 2007.</P>
        <P>Growing up, I can still remember an older generation lamenting the physical absence of the theatre from Dublin over a 15-year period after the 1951 fire.  Se&aacute;n Lemass, when laying the foundation stone of the new theatre in 1963, paid tribute to O&rsquo;Casey&rsquo;s plays for doing &ldquo;a great deal to moderate animosities and to enable people to live and laugh together after the Civil War&rdquo;, and to Yeats as &ldquo;a man of high and lasting patriotism&rdquo;, adding that the same could be said of Lady Gregory and Edward Martyn.</P>
        <P>The Abbey Theatre in its second building has served the country and this city well for what will be near on 50 years.  It has within limits been adapted and refurbished over the years, with the enlarged first floor bar service jutting out over Marlborough Street, and the new seating.  I was there on Tuesday night as a guest with my wife at the premiere of Brian Friel&rsquo;s adaptation of Chekhov&rsquo;s &ldquo;Three Sisters&rdquo;, including, I suspect, the addition of some humorous touches not in the original.  Over the years the Abbey Theatre has staged the works of many important contemporary dramatists such as Brian Friel as well as maintaining and reinterpreting the Irish classic repertoire.  Nothing I have said should detract from the excellence of other theatrical contributions and traditions in this city and indeed in this country, but it is the needs, role, and responsibilities of the Abbey Theatre we are discussing today.</P>
        <P>Physically, the Abbey Theatre building is not ideal by today&rsquo;s standards, with limited facilities backstage and below stage, inadequate air conditioning and a fairly cramped foyer space.  There has been a consensus for a number of years that a new building is needed, and the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Martin Cullen, has a keen interest in advancing the project, as did his predecessor, Deputy John O&rsquo;Donoghue.  While policy is determined by the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Martin Cullen, for whom I am deputising, the tendering and construction are supervised by the Office of Public Works in collaboration with the Department of Arts, Sport and Tourism.</P>
        <P>In 2006, the Government decided to procure a design for the new Abbey Theatre at a site in George&rsquo;s Dock by way of an international design competition, IDC, to be managed by the OPW.  Based on the outcome of the IDC, the new theatre for the Abbey is to be procured by way of a public private partnership, PPP, project on a build, finance and maintain basis.  This site was chosen following an extensive exercise conducted by the Office of Public Works which involved the examination of a number of options, and the project is being progressed on the basis solely of the George&rsquo;s Dock site.</P>
        <P>Among the options reviewed were rebuilding at the current site, with acquisition of a number of adjacent properties down to the river; access from O&rsquo;Connell Street to the back of the old <Col N="540"/>Carlton cinema site; a site on Parnell Square; and a site across the river in the south docks area.  In most cases, practical reasons, including the likelihood of prolonged delay, ruled out the other alternatives.  The choice of location is a question that is now settled.</P>
        <P>The site at George&rsquo;s Dock was provided by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority.  An international design competition was one of the conditions of the offer of the site by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority.  Arising from the Government decision, an inter-agency steering committee was set up to oversee the project.  The committee is chaired by the Department of Arts, Sport and Tourism and comprises representatives of the National Development Finance Agency, the Office of Public Works, the Abbey Theatre and the Dublin Docklands Development Authority.  A project team, chaired by the Office of Public Works and comprising representatives of the same agencies as the steering group, has also been established and is overseeing the arrangements for holding the international design competition and advancing the PPP process.</P>
        <P>The Office of Public Works has asked the Royal Institute of the Architects of Ireland to organise the competition.  The competition regulations are nearing finalisation.  The technical documentation for the competition must be very carefully specified, in particular the detailed accommodation brief for the new theatre.  Work on that is nearing completion.  A jury for the international design competition was appointed late last year. The jury has representatives from the Department of Arts, Sport and Tourism, the Office of Public Works, the Dublin Docklands Development Authority, the Arts Council and the Abbey Theatre.  It also features international figures in the architectural and theatre worlds.  It is expected that the design competition will be launched before the end of 2008.  The IDC will be carried out in two phases.  Phase 1 involves seeking expressions of interest from architect-led design teams, from which a maximum of 15 teams will be required to submit designs in phase 2 of the competition.  The winning design will be selected by the jury.</P>
        <P>Technical, legal, insurance and financial advisers have been appointed to guide and advise the inter-agency teams in the procurement of this epoch-making and crucial project.  A theatre consultant and an acoustic consultant have also been appointed.  Furthermore, a process auditor is in place in accordance with Department of Finance guidelines.</P>
        <P>The project is complex and there are myriad factors to address in making progress on it.  It remains a priority for the Department of Arts, Sport and Tourism and the Government in the programme for Government and in the national development plan.  The same teams progressed the National Concert Hall PPP to competition initiation stage last week, and those resources will now be used to advance the Abbey Theatre PPP.  When the winning design has been chosen, the National Development Finance Agency, in conjunction with the OPW, will oversee the PPP procurement process in accordance with PPP guidelines.</P>
        <P>Both the Minister, Deputy Cullen, and I are confident that when the international design competition is complete in some years&rsquo; time, we will have a world class design for a new iconic landmark building for the city, and the new quayside theatre will be a dynamic structure reflecting Dublin&rsquo;s growing reputation as a global capital of culture and creativity.  It will be readily accessible by public transport &mdash; the future Luas line will run beside it &mdash; and there is also a footbridge across the river.</P>
        <P>As Senators will have seen from this morning&rsquo;s newspapers, a Dublin docklands expansion plan was launched yesterday and there is no doubt that cultural facilities ought to be part of that vast new area of the city.  At the same time it is very accessible from the existing city centre and is a fine location which I visited yesterday.</P>
<Col N="541"/>
        <P>With the Minister, Deputy Cullen, I look forward to a new national theatre building that makes a bold and visionary statement about modern Ireland while at the same time acknowledging the historic significance of the Abbey Theatre to Irish life over more than a century.  The Abbey will continue to be a national cultural institution that acts as a magnet to draw our citizens and visitors alike towards enjoying the inspiring drama and creativity our country and heritage has to offer.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for his contribution on this important topic.  I am struck by the fact that we are discussing something that is of enormous value to us all.  The Minister of State did a great job in acknowledging the wonderful literary and historical heritage of the institution we are discussing.  He acknowledged that it was the first state-subsidised theatre in the world throughout a period of our history when there were so many other competing demands on our resources and limited revenue.  Bold and courageous vision was shown by the people who were involved in it at that time and we owe it to them to ensure that vision continues in the next stage of the Abbey&rsquo;s future.</P>
        <P>I listened with great interest to what the Minister of State said but it is a case of Hamlet without the prince because some of the most important questions people have on this project were not answered in his contribution.  I will deal with some of those questions shortly while also reflecting on the Minister of State&rsquo;s contribution.</P>
        <P>I have much personal fondness for and attachment to the Abbey Theatre.  I suspect that, like many other people, my first introduction to the theatre was going to the Abbey Theatre with my family as a young boy and watching those great mysterious figures created by Brian Friel and Chekhov entertain people and describe other worlds to them.  That gave many people the gift of appreciating the theatre, and it is incumbent on us to get these decisions right because we will live with the consequences of them for many years to come.</P>
        <P>I am glad the Minster of State touched upon the announcement made today by the Dublin Docklands Development Authority.  It is a very exciting plan.  I am fortunate to have both the Abbey Theatre and the docklands in my constituency.  To see the Dublin Docklands Development Authority come forward with a &euro;4.5 billion exciting, innovative plan, given the times we are in, is the clarity and leadership we need.  It is wonderful to see this happening and to see Paul Moloney taking the lead on this.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">12 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>In such a climate and environment, we cannot accept that everything is fixed.  I wish to reiterate the argument regarding the future location of the theatre as there are two points which must be considered in any discussion.  I believe there is still an overwhelming argument for locating it on the site at the top of O&rsquo;Connell Street.  I am aware this suggestion has been made many times by my predecessors but two points have changed when discussing O&rsquo;Connell Street.  First, there are now very exciting plans &mdash; which I hope will happen &mdash; regarding the transport links for O&rsquo;Connell Street and in particular for the upper end of O&rsquo;Connell Street.  Metro north will have a metro stop on Parnell Square and there will be a Luas interchange on O&rsquo;Connell Street.  It is a fact that the public transport linkages planned for that end of O&rsquo;Connell Street will be ahead of developments in the docklands.</P>
        <P>Second, since these discussions were last taking place there is now movement on the planning future for the top end of O&rsquo;Connell Street.  A developer has lodged what in many ways is a progressive planning vision for that end of the street.  Given that our predecessors had the insight and courage to establish a State-subsidised theatre, I would like to see the State step in and offer a vision for all of Dublin and not just for the docklands.  Part of this vision should be to have a cultural institution of which we are all proud, regardless of whether or not we are theatregoers, accessible on the main street of our capital.  This is so pressing that we should <Col N="542"/>never lose any opportunity to raise and debate the issue, particularly when so many other things are being changed.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State has acknowledged the process taking place but the most important question which has not been answered is when will the Abbey be open.  If the Minister of State&rsquo;s current plans are to be implemented, can he clarify to the House today when this will happen?  This is the most important piece of information needed and it is regrettable that this information is lacking in the Minister of State&rsquo;s opening statement.</P>
        <P>I refer to the future of the Peacock Theatre which is situated beside the Abbey Theatre and is part of the Abbey institution.  The Peacock Theatre has been at the forefront in looking after young, new and diverse playwrights.  When I had the time I used to enjoy going to see the Saturday matinee performances when the theatre would introduce new playwrights and give them a chance to establish themselves and become known.  It is vital to recognise we are not just talking about the Abbey Theatre, which looks after the work of the great and proud names the nation has been lucky to have produced but also we must find some way to ensure there is a channel for diverse new writers which the Peacock has offered so many times in the past.</P>
        <P>It is vital to address the point regarding diversity on the board of the Abbey Theatre.  Regrettably in the past there have been some difficult and unfortunate developments regarding the finances of the theatre.  My hope is that this has all been resolved.  As the Government looks at the management structure of the theatre in a new location &mdash; which I still hope will be in O&rsquo;Connell Street but I am aware this might not be the case &mdash; I suggest this could be an opportunity to revisit the financial and management structures of the Abbey Theatre in order to categorically assure ourselves that when the organisation is lucky enough to be in a wonderful location which I hope we can all visit, it will have the structures and experience to make the very best of the opportunity it will be given.</P>
        <P>My final point is indirectly related to the location of the Abbey Theatre.  I have been very impressed by and proud to see the new theatres and cultural institutions dotted all around the country, including the Dra&iacute;ocht theatre in Blanchardstown with which I am most familiar.  These institutions have been at the vanguard of introducing theatre and new forms of art to communities that otherwise would not have the opportunity to experience them.  I would love to see the Abbey Theatre and its company become involved in this area.  The theatre is our national theatre both in terms of where it is located &mdash; which is what we are discussing today &mdash; but also in terms of what it should do for the country as a whole and not just for those lucky enough to live near it or those lucky enough to be able to afford to travel to it.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State has already acknowledged the national importance of the Abbey and I hope he will take this opportunity to state that given the developments that have taken place in O&rsquo;Connell Street and the northside of Dublin, he will examine the possibility of ensuring this wonderful institution can be more centrally embedded in our capital city and take this opportunity to discuss the future of the Peacock Theatre and what can be done to ensure the Abbey flourishes in all the towns of our country so that everybody has the opportunity to experience what so many of us have been able to experience.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Martin Mansergh, to the House and to wish him well in his new and very responsible position as Minister of State with responsibility for the Office of Public Works.  He is the person who will be responsible for much of the Government investment during the years ahead.  I have no doubt that his stewardship will not be found wanting in any way because his practical experience as adviser to various Taoisigh will stand to him when it comes to dealing with the problems associated with being in the OPW.</P>
<Col N="543"/>
        <P>The Minister of State outlined the proud history of the Abbey Theatre as the National Theatre.  Its establishment was the first move in the attempt to bury political divisions and it made a significant contribution in that regard.  It also provided the first opportunity for some of our greatest people such as Synge and O&rsquo;Casey and later, John B. Keane and others, who have made significant contributions to theatre in this country.  I remember the rural halls where plays were performed on Sunday nights during Lent.  These were the plays which had been performed previously in the Abbey Theatre and they were performed by people in our own community.  We all have fond memories of those performances, similar to Senator Donohoe&rsquo;s memories of the Peacock Theatre.  Some of these local people were excellent actors but they were amateurs who rather than act professionally wanted to remain as amateurs and they regarded acting as a hobby.  They made a significant contribution to the community.</P>
        <P>Senator Donohoe referred to the number of small new theatres dotted around the country in the most unusual places.  Some of them are making a significant contribution to the cultural life of the areas in which they are located.  Some people may not believe this but County Leitrim with a population of 30,000 has three theatres, one in Carrickallen, one in Carrick-on-Shannon and one in Manorhamilton.  Their productions are an asset to their local communities and they become focal points for the community and for those who want to be involved in cultural and arts events.</P>
        <P>I can understand Senator Donohoe&rsquo;s preference for moving the Abbey to the top of O&rsquo;Connell Street rather than to the designated site in the docklands.  There is a certain merit in his suggestion.  However if we go looking for a site at the top of O&rsquo;Connell Street, our successors in 20 years&rsquo; time will be still talking about it.  The one advantage for the Abbey now is that a designated site is available for the project.  Let us ensure this building is so well designed that it will be on every postcard and every representation of Dublin.  Like the Sydney Opera House, it should attract international respect as a feature of the community.  Some people might argue that a time limit should be placed on this project but time limits are dangerous.  If it runs one day over time somebody will be shouting &ldquo;You&rsquo;re late&rdquo;, but it is more important that the project should be right.</P>
        <P>Some 15 different groups are involved in examining the design project, which will provide a wealth of opportunity to the assessment board.  It will prove that whoever wins this competition will have designed what is accepted by everybody as being the best symbol for this city.</P>
        <P>We must also ensure that the funding is properly managed because we saw slight problems regarding funding for the Abbey over the years.  In future, the board must take a lot of responsibility for how the theatre is run.  In saying that, I am not being critical of previous Abbey boards.  No one wishes to see a situation, which developed before, where questions are raised.  People of the highest integrity were challenged for the wrong reasons and in some cases for personal reasons.  We want to ensure that does not happen again.</P>
        <P>We should examine whether we can widen the Abbey&rsquo;s remit to give young people the opportunity to become involved in the theatre.  The list of those who progressed through the Abbey and made it onto the world stage is phenomenal.  The international success of former Abbey actors is acknowledged and appreciated by everyone.  I hope that opportunities will be given to young people, especially those now leaving various colleges, to enable them to move further up in the acting world.  I also hope the Abbey will have a direct policy of giving opportunities to emerging playwrights.  It might not be any harm to include in any future control parameters, the commissioning of a minimum of ten new plays per year.  That figure may sound high, but if one can get ten new playwrights contributing work to the Abbey one would be doing exceptionally well.  New playwrights need to reach the big stage in order to establish a national reputation.  In Ireland, the biggest stage is the Abbey&rsquo;s.</P>
<Col N="544"/>
        <P>I encourage the Minister of State to complete this project as quickly as possible.  If feasible, time limits should be set for the submission of project plans.  When one design is finally accepted, a further time limit should be put on its completion.  Those in charge of PPPs know that the sooner they get the doors open, the sooner they begin to get some return on their investment.  That aspect is imperative, so I ask the Minister of State to take that course.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Mansergh, to the House.  It is appropriate to have these statements on the Abbey Theatre&rsquo;s move.  I agree with the viewpoint that the Abbey would be better situated in the centre of Dublin, but I have great sympathy for the viewpoint of the Minister of State and his Department.  I happen to know that when a site was selected in Parnell Square not that long ago, it was made impossible for the Department to buy the required site extension.  I am fearful of making any move away from what has been decided on the docklands site, although I would have preferred a city centre site.  I still believe Dublin city centre could do with another theatre at this time. </P>
        <P>A number of points raised in this discussion are worth responding to, particularly the issue of funding.  While previous speakers did not say otherwise, I would like to put firmly on record the fact that the Abbey&rsquo;s finances have been put in order by the current board.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>Those finances are substantial and sound, which is an accepted, acknowledged and audited fact.  It is also recognised that the theatre is totally dependent on the State and the Arts Council, but its finances are in order.  </P>
        <P>Where do we go next?  I appreciate the points made by the Minister of State and I agree with him on the system of selecting the best design.  I am fearful, however, that in the current climate it could prove to be another disaster for the northside, like metro north, if for some reason the Government decided to pull back from this proposal.  This is where we can learn from our past.  The Minister of State will, no doubt, be aware that when the current Abbey was being designed by the architect, Michael Scott, there was an approved and agreed design, which unfortunately coincided with a downturn in the economy.  Consequently, the plans for the Abbey were changed and it became a compromise.  They aimed to make it a theatre and conference centre but it turned out to be a half-way house.  It was a very bad design which has eventually had to be changed completely.  It is a tribute to the current board that it is now being redesigned with a change in the seat layout so that it is now far more comfortable than it ever was.  The lesson to be learned is that, while we made a mistake the last time &mdash; to coin a phrase &mdash; let us not disgrace ourselves again in this particular case.  We should learn from the last time and get it right now.  The Minister of State&rsquo;s job, with responsibility for the arts, will be to fight to protect that part of the Government&rsquo;s policy and plans for the future.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Previous speakers referred to new writing and the Abbey does accept such writing.  The reason it can never be a commercial theatre like the Gate is precisely because it is a showcase for new talent, including writing which is hard to get staged.  That point inadvertently arose in the last speaker&rsquo;s contribution.  John B. Keane was kept out of the Abbey until he was a major national figure.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I discussed this matter with him on many occasions.  The fact that he did not get his opportunity in the Abbey during those years was something that hurt him so often and for so long.  As a number of speakers have suggested, the Abbey must be the place <Col N="545"/>for new writing.  We should support, acknowledge and appreciate what it has to do.  While the Abbey Theatre is not there to make money, its finances must be well handled.  It must mind the pennies and get value for money; there can be no pulling back from that.  If we accept the suggestion of taking a certain amount of new writing talent in the course of a year, we must be able to pay the price for that because not all those plays will be successful.  We must deal with the fact that some of them may play to empty houses.  </P>
        <P>It should be recognised that the Abbey does commission new material from young playwrights, such as Marina Carr, Colm T&oacute;b&iacute;n and, more recently, Conor McPherson.  Such material has been encouraged by the Abbey, while other commercial theatres could not take the risk involved.</P>
        <P>The Abbey is there to inspire us in whatever way through its engagement with theatre-goers.  It is there to comment on society and to entertain us also.  The Abbey&rsquo;s current Chekhov play, &ldquo;Three Sisters&rdquo;, is a commentary on society today.  We need to see that it is there to develop for society.  It is not commercial.  It is a showcase for new Irish talent.  It is there to nurture new writing and creativity, to give space to new playwrights, and to expose the rest of us to the best that is happening in Irish creative theatre.  In that sense, it also needs to go even beyond new writing to the area of experiment.</P>
        <P>I recall a time not that many years ago when there were two great pieces on in the Abbey and in the Peacock, one a well-known Leitrim writer&rsquo;s only play and the other by a well-known Dublin writer about the heroin society.  Both plays were destroyed by the critics.  I thought they gave a complete and supportive view of Irish society at the time.  John McGahern was so hurt by it he never wrote another play.  It was panned and written-off by the <i>Sunday Independent</i> of all newspapers.  It was described as not being pure theatre and being melodramatic.  Melodramatic was exactly the reason given for the non-acceptance of John B. Keane&rsquo;s plays all his life.  I remember saying to John McGahern that they said the same to John B. Keane.  At least the Abbey gave John McGahern the opportunity to write a play, which I believe will find its place again.  It also gave Dermot Bolger the opportunity to produce a piece of theatre which showed the low-life of Dublin drug society around Finglas, as it was at the time, and other things.  This was a commentary on Irish life.</P>
        <P>The last play to finish in the Peacock in recent times was a commentary on public life and corruption in public life.  It does not matter when it was written.  Shakespeare can be produced today and be a comment on today&rsquo;s life if it is produced in a particular way.</P>
        <P>All in all, I welcome the points made by the Minister of State, Deputy Mansergh.  This is an important debate.  I wish him well in his Ministry and also in developing the Abbey as quickly and as effectively as possible.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Senator Ann Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to share my time with Senator Cassidy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Senator Ann Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Mansergh, and wish him well in his new brief.  I sat beside him for a few years and it is nice to see him back in the House in his position to debate this subject.</P>
        <P>I grew up with the Abbey Theatre in so far as when it was adjacent to Leinster House where my father was, I, as a child, used be brought there.  He loved the theatre, and as a young child I found myself many times being at the theatre with him.  Therefore, I have very fond memories of the old Abbey Theatre.</P>
        <P>I am delighted to make a contribution to the debate on how we best bring it forward and relocate it.  I was disappointed when I realised it was going to George&rsquo;s Dock.  I had looked at <Col N="546"/>the other options too and thought ideally it would have been great if it had been left where it was if that was possible because of the access to O&rsquo;Connell Street.  I thought the Carlton cinema area of O&rsquo;Connell Street would have been an ideal location as well.  I go regularly to the Gate and it would have been nice if they had been able to complement one another.  Parnell Square was also an option.  Having studied the Minister of State&rsquo;s speech, I realise that this site is the only one that they can fast-track and get on with, and that is what we must look at.</P>
        <P>It must be a significant landmark, not alone for our city but for the country as a whole.  I am glad an international competition was held to ensure the best specifications, design and acoustics.  I visit the Abbey and I am aware the space is inadequate.  The foyer is crowded and usually at the beginning of a night one cannot move.  It is important for the national theatre that we would take all those aspects into account.</P>
        <P>I listened to some of the other speakers.  It is so important that we encourage young talent and reflect society in Ireland.  Education should play a part in stimulating interest in young artists and how best we can bring it all together.  We have a country of young playwrights and people who are interested in theatre and who have the personality to reflect society.  The Abbey should reflect that kind of thinking.</P>
        <P>No doubt the docklands site is the one we must go with, but the transport infrastructure must be put in place.  I do not like it down there.  It must improve considerably.  As it stands, I would have to take a taxi.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>It might be cheaper to buy a flat down there.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Senator Ann Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>I am concerned about the lack of transport infrastructure and restaurants.  People who are out for an evening like to have all that infrastructure in the area.  Otherwise it would be a bad site.</P>
        <P>I welcome the debate.  We need a landmark, a place to which we can all look in the future, in which our schools and young educated people will be able to reflect their interest, and which reflects Dublin&rsquo;s growing reputation as a global capital of culture and creativity.  I hope the future development of the Abbey Theatre will reflect all those.  It is important we get it right.  We have a golden opportunity and I am pleased the Minister of State will be one of the key people steering it ahead.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I, too, congratulate Deputy Martin Mansergh on his appointment as Minister of State in charge of the Office of Public Works.  I look forward to working alongside him.</P>
        <P>A landmark cultural centre is what we want for the Abbey Theatre.  I agree with fellow Senators that the best place for it by a mile is O&rsquo;Connell Street.  Everyone in Ireland knows how to get to O&rsquo;Connell Street and the people feel comfortable coming there.  One can mention all the other grandiose places in Dublin and people will tell you that they must go to them because they sound nice, but they never go because we all are creatures of habit.</P>
        <P>The number one location must be O&rsquo;Connell Street and the Government owes it to the Parnell Square area, where very little, except the Hugh Lane Gallery, has been built over the past 50 years.  I recall that when Government brought in a capital allowance scheme for Parnell Square, not one block was put on top of another in Parnell Square East during that seven year period.  Something serious must be done.</P>
        <P>Given that we will have the transport question answered at both ends of O&rsquo;Connell Street, and if it is at all possible, surely the &euro;1.25 billion project being discussed for the Carlton cinema site on O&rsquo;Connell Street must include a cultural centre.  Why not have the Abbey Theatre <Col N="547"/>located there?  We want the likes of an Albert Hall or Sydney Opera House in O&rsquo;Connell Street.  We do not want to hide it in any old place in Ireland.  We want to have somewhere of which we can be proud.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Given my considerable experience in the entertainment world, the most important part of the Minister of State&rsquo;s speech was when he said a theatre consultant and acoustic consultant have been appointed to the team.  How many magnificent projects have been a disaster when it comes to the control of sound because an acoustic consultant was not appointed initially?  I congratulate everyone associated with it.  We could not have better people than the Office of Public Works handling the project.</P>
        <P>The proposal to put it anywhere other than O&rsquo;Connell Street is not giving the best opportunity.  I know what happened in some of the other areas in which those who owned the establishments got greedy, but surely this can become part of the planning process before Dublin City Council.  Dublin City Council has some of the most committed and dedicated people in the world working for it.  They are doing a magnificent job in the interests of the people of Ireland and the capital city.</P>
        <P>As someone from Castlepollard, I acknowledge the contribution of the Pakenham family to the Gate Theatre, especially the late Edward Pakenham and his wife.  I was born next door to their estate and the Minister of State knows of this family.  I know what the family did for the Gate Theatre in very difficulties times.  They collected pennies to keep the theatre open.</P>
        <P>Much has been done to keep the culture experiences of the Abbey Theatre, the Gate Theatre and the Peacock Theatre alive.  People have worked day and night to keep the doors open.  This is a tremendous challenge and a great opportunity and we have the right Minister of State in the right place and at the right time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I am glad of the opportunity to speak and welcome the Minister of State.  I agree with many of the other speakers that the Abbey Theatre has a legacy which must be honoured with the building of a fitting and tasteful structure capable of housing the quality productions we have come to expect from the theatre.  The Minister told us earlier this month that the Government is now committed to building at George&rsquo;s Dock and that the new theatre will be a public private partnership, PPP.</P>
        <P>It is essential the choice for the redevelopment of Ireland&rsquo;s national theatre is suitable and that the location is appropriate for a proper theatre facility.  It must reflect the importance of theatre and the role it plays in Irish culture.  The Abbey Theatre must be the flagship theatre for the country.</P>
        <P>I am not convinced the location is wrong.  I do not believe it is necessary to have the Abbey Theatre in the city centre.  Reference was made earlier to the Sydney Opera House which is not on Oxford Street, Sydney, but in Beenelong Point.  The Albert Hall is not on Oxford Street, London, but in Kensington.</P>
        <P>The site must be able to cater for the demand of people going to it.  It needs good transport links and to be accessible and well signposted.  Its current location is beside a Luas stop and many buses pass by.  As long as similar facilities are provided in George&rsquo;s Dock, I do not see a huge problem.  We expect to see improved transport links to Spencer Dock, which is close by, and this will help.  Transport links can be included as a condition of planning approval.  I will push for that but I do not have a huge problem with the location.</P>
        <P>I agree with the former Minister, the Ceann Comhairle, Deputy John O&rsquo;Donoghue, who spoke about the issue a couple of years ago.  When he was Minister he said the facility should be a modern theatre complex with up to three stages &mdash; a main stage and two similar smaller stages &mdash; which, in effect, would be similar to the existing situation with the adjoining Peacock <Col N="548"/>Theatre and that this would help nurture the rapidly growing number of small theatres in the Dublin region and allow them access to this stage.  Since the unfortunate closure of Andrews Lane Theatre, access to smaller stages has become more difficult.  Hopefully, the redevelopment will help to fill that void.</P>
        <P>The new Abbey Theatre needs to be able to cater for mainstream theatre productions and to house new and innovate sets and lighting designs.  If it does that, it will go a long way towards meeting the needs of the city.</P>
        <P>I refer to the plans for the old Abbey Theatre site.  Will it be sold off?  If so, does the Government have a specification for what the site should contain or will it simply be sold off whereby the market will decide?  The plan for the new site is a little open-ended.  The Minister of State said it will be a PPP and that it will be a design, build and maintain.  Who will own the theatre?  Will there be any stipulations in the tender documents as to whether potential developers will have to hand back the site after a minimum period of time?  Will it be left to developers to come up with ideas on it?</P>
        <P>We need to see some risk transferred.  The whole propose of a PPP is to transfer risk to the private sector.  We could do that by doing design and build.  I am not convinced about the maintenance aspect.  We have seen PPP failures here in the past, including the recent public housing one.  I worked on a PPP in the UK, Metronet, which folded during work on the London underground.  I am not convinced this is the way forward and we need to be sure it is clearly thought out before we go down this route.  It cannot be an excuse to remove expenditure from the capital budget and transfer it to ongoing operating costs.  I would appreciate hearing the Minister of State&rsquo;s comments in that regard.</P>
        <P>I am very excited about the new theatre and hope the Government engages in this redevelopment with proper foresight and planning.  I look forward to seeing a new Abbey Theatre opening in the next few years.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome this debate which Senators requested for a number of reasons, including the uncertainty in regard to the site, which has been reflected here.  The Minister of State said the decision has now been taken.  Will he clarify that because there is uncertainty in the media and among Abbey Theatre staff?  If there is uncertainty about the site, there are all sorts of implications.  However, if the decision has been taken, let us tell everyone and plan appropriately for it rather than talk about O&rsquo;Connell Street, what might have been the best site, and about the fact O&rsquo;Connell Street needs a theatre of the standing of the Abbey Theatre.</P>
        <P>We asked for a debate because we need to discuss the site and to give the Government our support for this flagship cultural project, which all Senators fully support.  Even in these difficult economic times, we want to see this development.  The project has great potential.  However, I wish to raise some concerns raised by my colleague, Deputy Olivia Mitchell, during the week.  I am concerned about the timeframe and about the fact three Ministers have been involved in this project to date, namely, the Ceann Comhairle, Deputy John O&rsquo;Donoghue, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan and the Minister, Deputy Martin Cullen.  It was also in the 2002 programme for Government.  There has been a slow erratic approach to this project and perhaps the Minister of State will explain why that has been the case.  What are the barriers and the problems?</P>
        <P>We face a new economic situation and there are new tendering rules for the refurbishment of this House.  Will these new rules apply to the tendering process for the Abbey Theatre?  If so, will that cause further delay?  Will the Minister of State make every effort to ensure this international competition, which is an excellent idea and which was part of the prerequisite for the new site, does not mean a delay of several years?  He referred to the results of the inter<Col N="549"/>national competition in some years&rsquo; time.  Was he suggesting the competition will take several years?  I would be very concerned if that was the case.</P>
        <P>The previous speaker spoke about PPPs, which are running into difficulty.  What is the thinking on the PPP for this new development?  Will the Minister of State reassure us in respect of those questions and on the funding side?  It is really about a decision on funding and timeframe for delivery.  That is what everybody involved in the arts cares about as far as the Abbey Theatre site is concerned.</P>
        <P>If the site of the theatre is to be in the docklands, there is huge potential there.  All one needs to do is to look at the South Bank in London to see the range of cultural institutions brought together there.  Although we are focusing on the Abbey Theatre and a potentially wonderful new building which would meet all its needs, we should be also aware of the potential for the docklands site to become a hub for cultural development, whether for film or music.  Hopefully, this possibility could be kept in mind for the site in better economic times and when the economy starts to grow again.</P>
        <P>I wish to see the development of further links between the Abbey Theatre and communities, especially with schools.  I have had direct experience of links between the Abbey and schools through my son, who is an actor.  It is critical that there is engagement between the theatre and artistic young people.  For too long our education system has not given artistic and creative people opportunities to develop or bring out their talents.  Thankfully this has begun to change in recent times with changes in school curricula and the development of new theatres and community arts groups.  We have seen more potential and opportunity offered to young people who show a significant interest in the arts in Ireland.</P>
        <P>We have seen tremendous talent in acting, music and the whole range of artistic endeavours of which we can be very proud.  The Abbey has played a significant role in fostering this talent.  I wish to see the Abbey get the necessary resources and the opportunity to develop in the years ahead.  It is clear some of our theatres have difficulty surviving at present.  While we are delighted to have such a range of theatres in the suburbs of Dublin and throughout the country, many are having difficulties, including financial difficulties.  As previous speakers have said, it is clear the Abbey will need ongoing support from Government and the Arts Council.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State, Deputy Mansergh, has support across the House for this project.  We have questions about the timeframe and delivery along with some key questions about the public private partnership.  However, this is a project everybody supports and I wish the Minister of State the best of luck in bringing this project to fruition.  However, I urge him to be as transparent as possible regarding the design competitions and any barriers he many be facing in the delivery of this project.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Arts, Sport and Tourism</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank Senators Paschal Donohoe, John Ellis, Joe O&rsquo;Toole, Ann Ormonde, Donie Cassidy, Dominic Hannigan, Frances Fitzgerald and all Senators for their contributions in what has been a very good debate.  I am delighted the matter has been subject to a proper debate.  Several Senators, especially Senator Hannigan, paid tribute to the role and importance of the Abbey and I do not believe anybody here questions those sentiments.</P>
        <P>On the question of the proposed location, I repeat that the choice of location is a question that is now settled.  One can naturally debate what might have been.  There were difficulties with the Carlton site because of the value of property on O&rsquo;Connell Street and there would, probably, only have been a narrow entrance through the back of the site.  There would have been difficulties and constraints in creating the type of landmark building there that was <Col N="550"/>mooted.  There would also have been financial and economic considerations.  Sometimes the ideal is the enemy of the good and, in any case, the decision has been made.</P>
        <P>A point was made about transport.  One consideration for theatres throughout the world is a preference for not having an underground system nearby, or noisy trams rumbling just outside the door, as they can be heard inside during the performance.  The Luas is being constructed very close to, but not right on top of, the theatre site at George&rsquo;s Dock and it will be the ideal distance from it.  There is also a train terminal there as well, so the new site will be very accessible.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Peacock Theatre will, of course, be alongside the Abbey in the new building and there is no question of the new theatre being reduced to one performance space.  I accept the Peacock provides scope for young writers and for more experimental writing.  Along with playwrights, authors, artists and politicians, I have been panned by the <i>Sunday Independent</i> and, I daresay, many Senators here have been as well, but we must get beyond that.</P>
        <P>With regard to timing, each stage of the process, including the invitation to tender stage, will have a timeframe.  It is difficult to say exactly but I and, I am sure others, hope to see the project completed in some years&rsquo; time.  The process would take a minimum number of years in any case.  As with the National Concert Hall these projects cannot be delivered overnight.</P>
        <P>Senator Fitzgerald mentioned the number of Ministers involved and it reminds me of Horace&rsquo;s tag, <i>Ars longa, vita brevis</i>.  Art endures, but life &mdash; especially political life &mdash; is short.  There will, probably, be more than one senior and junior Minister involved before the new Abbey opens its doors.  Within limits, the reason the site was chosen was to get on with the project, but at the same time it is important to get it right rather than rush it, because it will be there for a long time.</P>
        <P>I take Senator Ellis&rsquo;s point about the importance of a spread of theatres throughout the country.  There are several in County Tipperary as in County Leitrim and they make a significant contribution to the local area.  There are many theatre groups in towns, but there are also performances that tour and it would be agreeable if this continued.  In the old days, when the country was much poorer than now, companies often toured.  Nowadays, this does not seem to happen which is a pity, especially with the availability of venues.  There are some exceptions, for example the Opera Theatre Company tours throughout the country.</P>
        <P>Regarding public transport, there seems to be no difficulty providing early morning trains and so on into Dublin, starting from their destination at 5.30 a.m.  However, there seems to be greater difficulty providing public transport out of Dublin late at night.  It would be easier for those living some distance from the capital, who do not necessarily want to drive long distances, to use the facilities available if late night public transport was provided.</P>
        <P>The old Abbey site will of course be sold.  No doubt it will be pretty valuable, depending on the state of the property market at the time of sale.  This will help finance the project.</P>
        <P>The new Abbey will be in State ownership, there is no doubt about that.  The public private partnership will relate to the building and maintenance but not to the ownership of the theatre.  The issue of governance was raised and as one of the Senators pointed out, it is mainly an issue of the past that has now been substantially rectified.  I thank Senators for their support.  We all want to see the project come to fruition.  I do not have a problem with cultural facilities being spread in different locations around the city.  The Gate Theatre, which is a very fine theatre, is just around the corner from O&rsquo;Connell Street.  It does not seem to me to be absolutely essential for the Abbey Theatre to be practically opposite it.  Not all of us are familiar with the new part of the city that is being developed along the docks.  I do not think people will have difficulty finding the new Abbey Theatre, particularly if it is close to a Luas stop.  I would like people to <Col N="551"/>be encouraged to travel to the new district of Dublin to get familiar with it.  When I passed through the area in question yesterday, there did not seem to be any shortage of restaurants there.  Senator Norris wrote to me about the evils of speculators and their effect on theatre sites, etc.  If we bring theatre and art to the financial world, perhaps that will help to make a difference.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>It will not do any harm.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>Beware of the barbarians.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="3" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prison Development (Confirmation of Resolutions)" RHead="Bill 2008: Second and Subsequent Stages"> 
    <Title>Prison Development (Confirmation of Resolutions) Bill 2008: Second and Subsequent Stages. </Title>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>As no limits on speaking time during the Second Stage debate were made on the Order of Business this morning, I ask the Acting Leader to specify how long Senators will have to speak.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Senator Diarmuid Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>Spokespersons will have ten minutes and all other Senators will have five minutes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BarryAndrewsFF"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Barry Andrews</NameTxt>
	<P>A confirmation Bill to confirm the resolutions passed by both Houses of the Oireachtas is a requirement of section 26 of the Prisons Act 2007.  This Act provides that if the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform decides to proceed with the construction of a prison using the consent development process provided for in the 2007 Act, a resolution of both Houses of the Oireachtas approving the proposal is required.  An Act of the Oireachtas confirming the resolutions is also required to proceed with the development.  The legislation before the House provides that confirmation and represents the final stage in the process.  Senators will be aware that resolutions providing for the development of the prison were passed in the D&aacute;il on 17 June and in the Seanad on 18 June.  The resolutions, which contain all the relevant detail, had first been discussed in this House on 29 May.  They were discussed in detail by the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women&rsquo;s Rights on 4 and 17 June.</P>
        <P>The Bill before the House is straightforward.  It contains just two sections &mdash; section 1 confirms that the resolutions were passed by the D&aacute;il and Seanad and section 2 sets out the Short Title.  As I have said, we are dealing with the approval of a major prison development under special procedures set out in the Prisons Act 2007.  In many respects, it is a more open, transparent and democratic procedure than the &ldquo;normal&rdquo; planning procedure for prison development.  Before the 2007 Act was agreed, all prison developments were governed by Part 9 of the 2001 planning and development regulations, under which the Minister is the deciding authority.  The new procedure that was introduced by the 2007 Act includes a requirement for an environmental impact assessment and public consultation.  The procedure vests final approval in the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
        <P>I wish to speak about the prison development itself.  The construction of a new prison is essential if we are to deliver real and substantive improvements in our prison system.  Mountjoy Prison is a Victorian structure, built in 1850 for short-term convicts awaiting transportation to Tasmania.  Its accommodation is substandard &mdash; there is no in-cell sanitation and it is overcrowded.  The constrained size of the site restricts the development of prisoner programmes.  In the past, Senators have drawn attention to some of the problems facing the prison system.  The new development at Thornton Hall is an essential part of the solution to such problems, <Col N="552"/>as it will eliminate the &ldquo;slopping out&rdquo; system that exists in Mountjoy, replace that prison&rsquo;s substandard and overcrowded accommodation, provide state-of-the-art prison accommodation and offer facilities for education, training and rehabilitation.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The design of the new prison will yield the maximum rehabilitative benefit, as it involves a collection of institutions.  It will maximise the operational benefits associated with having one perimeter wall and a single central stores and maintenance service.  Some people have described the prison as a &ldquo;super-prison&rdquo;.  This is simply not accurate.  By international standards, it is no more than a medium-size prison.  The scale of the individual modules is small.  There will be no more than 48 prisoners on any landing in the prison.  There will be an emphasis on keeping prisoners in small groups to ensure that the prison environment is safe and well managed at all times.  New prisoners will be assessed on their committal to determine the level of risk they pose and the most appropriate regime for managing their future integration into society.  The most dangerous and violent prisoners will be assigned to high security facilities, while those who pose less risk will benefit from a lower security regime.  As they progress, prisoners will move to step-down facilities in a more appropriate prison regime.  The modular design of the new development will allow ringleaders and rival gang members to be easily segregated.  This is essential to lower the potential for inter-prisoner violence.</P>
        <P>The physical layout of the new prison means we will be able to provide a much safer and more secure environment than exists at Mountjoy Prison.  The structure of that prison has led to difficulties in introducing mobile phone blocking systems there.  The location of Mountjoy Prison in an urban setting and on a crowded site makes it difficult to stop illicit materials entering the prison.  The design of the new prison will make it much easier to restrict illicit materials entering the prison.  The Irish Prison Service is rolling out a drugs policy and strategy.  Initiatives under the strategy include the provision of detoxification, methadone maintenance, education programmes, addiction counselling and drug therapy programmes.  Under the strategy, existing drug treatment programmes will be expanded and enhanced.  Nurses, a psychologist, 24 dedicated addiction counsellors and other staff, including prison officers, will be recruited.  In light of these enhanced supports, and the single cell occupancy in the new prison, the prison will provide a much more supportive environment for the rehabilitation of drug addicted prisoners.  As all prisoners will have an individual cell, at least for the foreseeable future, there will be a huge increase in the levels of personal safety of individual prisoners.</P>
         <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">1 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>Although the prison system is an essential part of our social and rehabilitation structures, the location of a new prison is seldom welcomed by local residents.  We have listened carefully to the concerns of the local community.  We are addressing the concerns in a broad variety of ways.  Access to the new prison development will be via a dedicated road running from the old N2 main road.  The construction of this access road will be prioritised.  Extensive car parking and visitor facilities will be provided.  A dedicated bus service will also be provided.  The construction of the sections of the boundary wall nearest to local residents will be prioritised to minimise the impact of construction work on them.  The use of the R130 road will be restricted.  A construction environmental plan is being prepared for the development.  Visually treated concrete will be used in the wall to make it less obtrusive.  Timber fences of 3 m in height are being erected around the car parks on the west of the site, the car parks are being redesigned and light fixtures in the car parks are being reduced and modified.  Planting areas are being widened and increased.  There will be increased planting of larger and mature trees and relocation of the wall further back by up to ten metres along portions of the exterior.</P>
     
        <P>These development conditions are a balanced and a considered response to the issues raised during the consultations with the local community and as reported by the rapporteur.  My <Col N="553"/>Department and the prison authorities will continue to liaise in a positive way with the local community as the building work progresses.</P>
        <P>The rapporteur received 130 submissions, most of which came from the local community.  His report identifies the main points raised in the submissions.  All the relevant documentation has been laid before each House of the Oireachtas.  Great care has been taken to ensure all the correct procedures have been followed and that due regard has been had to the environmental impact assessment and to the results of the public consultation, in particular as set out in the report of the rapporteur.  After consideration and the review of expert advice, it was decided the alterations were not material in the sense envisaged by section 24 of the Prisons Act 2007.  The changes had very little effect on the overall development but nevertheless are of significant benefit to local residents.</P>
        <P>As I have mentioned, there is a range of different facilities in the prison plan.  Separated from the male adult prison and from one another, there will be a female facility and a dual purpose block that is reserved on a contingency basis for 16 and 17 year old males.  As well as a central administration centre and stores, there are work training, library, health care and gym facilities and playing fields.</P>
        <P>In the 1990s because of pressure of numbers, the so-called revolving door mechanism was introduced with many prisoners being given temporary release simply to make room for new committals.  By 1996, 20% of the prison population was on temporary release. I am proud to say that Governments of which I have been a member took action so that today this figure is down to a more reasonable 6%.</P>
        <P>If Thornton is not built, our prison system will simply not have the capacity to deal with future needs.  The capacity of Thornton is based on projected prisoner numbers for the period up to the year 2015.  Even though the projections envisage an increase in numbers, they propose that our prison population rate per 100,000 inhabitants will reduce as our overall population increases faster than our prison population.</P>
        <P Just="Left">A final point on numbers, the development is designed for 1,400 prisoners in single cell occupancy.  However we must allow for the unforeseen and, after all, Mountjoy Prison has remained in use for more than 150 years.  Therefore the cells in the new development are designed to be large enough for double occupancy and the services are designed to cope with up to 2,200 prisoners without any major structural change.</P>
        <P>For the purpose of the environmental impact assessment it was necessary to take the most extreme scenario and hence the environmental impact assessment cites a figure of 2,200 prisoners.  However, I again emphasise the intention for the foreseeable future is to operate the prison with no more than 1,400 prisoners.</P>
        <P>I also want to clearly state that the new development at Thornton is not intended to  be a signal that prison is viewed as the only or even the most desirable sanction to be imposed in respect of criminal behaviour.  It is the courts that ultimately decide on the numbers committed to prison.  The Executive has no direct say in the matter and the Irish Prison Service must accept and implement the decisions of the courts.  The majority of persons convicted of criminal offences do not receive a custodial sentence.  The courts make liberal use of alternative sanctions to custody.  These include fines, probation, compensation orders, supervision orders and community service orders.  As a result, when one compares the prison population rate per 100,000 inhabitants, Ireland has one of the lowest rates in Europe and just half that of England and Wales.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Government&rsquo;s commitment to non-custodial sanctions is evidenced by a 30% increase in the size of the probation service, the establishment of the National Commission on Restorative Justice, the review of the community service scheme and the bringing forward of legislative <Col N="554"/>proposals on fines.  The misleading impression is frequently given that our prisons are full of people being imprisoned for non-payment of fines.  It is simply not true.  For example on 23 May this year, out of more than 3,500 prisoners only seven people were in prison solely for the non payment of fines.  We must recognise that the numbers are so small they do not have any real effect on the overall prison population.</P>
        <P>Similarly it is simply not true to say that if more prison spaces are built, they will be automatically filled.  If one examines the rate of committals to prison since the foundation of the prison service it is clear there is no link between increases and decreases in committals and prison spaces.  The rate of committals to prison is determined by the courts which make decisions without regard to prison capacity.</P>
        <P>Specific concerns have been raised about the D&oacute;chas Centre.  It is a comparatively recent building and very well designed and its success is proof of what the Irish Prison Service can achieve in a modern purpose  built prison setting.  However, we must recognise that since the opening of D&oacute;chas in 1999 there has been a serious issue with overcrowding and it is now the most overcrowded prison in the State.  On 1 May prisoner numbers exceeded bed capacity by 30% which is not sustainable.  It would be neither operationally nor economically effective to maintain the D&oacute;chas Centre in Mountjoy and provide for a second women&rsquo;s prison at Thornton.  The design at Thornton Hall takes full advantage of all the best lessons we have learnt from the D&oacute;chas Centre and applies them on a larger but still moderate scale.  It will have single occupancy domestic style accommodation based around courtyards and will have three separate sections in order that women on remand will be kept separate from sentenced prisoners.</P>
        <P>I would also point out that at Thornton, women prisoners will be further away from  male prisoners than they are at present in the Mountjoy complex and will be completely segregated from male prisoners.  Women constitute a very small proportion of our total prisoner population, less than 4% and I do not envisage any significant rise in that percentage.</P>
        <P>The most common situation whereby a person may be detained for immigration reasons is the case of persons refused permission to enter the State or pending deportation and there is a strict limit on the period for which they may be detained.  At present such persons are detained in a prison, normally Cloverhill, along with other prisoners.  The facilities at Thornton will be such that people detained for immigration control reasons will be accommodated completely separately from remand or sentenced prisoners, in line with best international practice.</P>
        <P>At present 16 and 17 year old male prisoners are held in St Patrick&rsquo;s Institution which is part of the Mountjoy complex.  Like Mountjoy, this facility has outlived its useful life.  The Government is committed to ensuring that persons under the age of 18 are not kept in the same institution as adult prisoners.  In March this year the Government approved plans to develop new facilities at Oberstown, Lusk, County Dublin to provide detention facilities for 16 and 17 year olds.  If these facilities are not ready in time, rather than leaving 16 and 17 year old prisoners in dilapidated and poorly serviced accommodation in St Patrick&rsquo;s Institution, we will, as a contingency measure, move them temporarily to brand new purpose built accommodation in Thornton.  They will be completely isolated from any adult prisoners in a manner which complies with our international obligations.</P>
        <P>We are going to provide vastly improved facilities in small scale modules but with the better services and economies of scale associated with clustering a number of institutions on one site.  The development at Thornton will radically improve our prisons by doing away with prison overcrowding and sub-standard accommodation.  It will significantly increase prisoner safety and will make society safer.</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="555"/>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for his presentation and welcome him to the House.  It is the first time I have had an opportunity to discuss a policy issue with him.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There is no question a new prison is needed and it must be of the highest standard.  I appreciate that the process which has gone through the Oireachtas on Thornton Hall essentially has been a planning one.  I have difficulties, however, with the manner in which the process has proceeded.  Various submissions have been made by outside bodies regarding the prison and prison policy.  There has been no meaningful response to these submissions, however, from the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform.</P>
        <P>The Thornton Hall proposals contain many good elements, for instance, the separation of prisoners, the individual cells, the self-contained accommodation and the space for work training education and rehabilitation programmes.  The reality is that there are no commitments in respect of these matters.  What we have is a prison that will detain asylum seekers, that will close down the D&oacute;chas women&rsquo;s prison and that will imprison minors in a prison designed for adults.  It will incarcerate the mentally ill because of the transfer of the Central Mental Hospital, which is against all representations and professional advice given to the Minister.</P>
        <P Just="Left">For these reasons, we have difficulties with this proposal.  We support the construction of a modern prison complex but we believe that, before this Act is passed, the Minister should outline the prison policy to be pursued in this new prison.  We need assurance that it will not be a repetition of the past or a continuation of existing prison policy which is a dismal failure.  The reality is that there are drugs in our prisons.  If a drug-free person comes into prison he will invariably leave prison a drug addict.  That is the most obvious test of the failure of current prison policy.</P>
        <P>A comprehensive programme of rehabilitation must be outlined.  Not only do we need the space, we also need evidence that the programmes will be implemented and funded properly.  There should be education and training, integrated sentence management and a comprehensive drug detoxification programme.  These are the prerequisites for effective prison policy.</P>
        <P>We have received no comfort from the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform regarding these matters, nor any commitments or assurances.  When dealing with this project, it is incumbent on the Minister to establish how prison policy will be administered in what is intended to be a modern complex with facilities of an international standard, as opposed to the appalling standard of accommodation in prisons such as Mountjoy, which poses a risk to prisoners and the administration of effective prison policy.  It is for these reasons that Fine Gael has difficulty endorsing the proposal outlined by the Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LisaMcDonald"><NameTxt>Senator Lisa McDonald</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the opportunity to discuss this Bill.  When discussing the motion on the prison, I said a modern stand-alone prison is badly needed in the State.  It should be provided on a secure site where prisoners can feel safe.  This may sound like an oxymoron but it should be considered given the Dickensian conditions in Mountjoy Prison, from which prisoners sometimes emerge worse than they were before going in.  District Court judges and other members of the Judiciary throughout the country are reluctant to impose custodial sentences because of the conditions in Mountjoy, despite the fact that they are needed in many cases.  Therefore, the new prison needs to be constructed and put into operation as soon as possible.  Thus, we can concentrate on the issues the Irish Prison Service will be dealing with, including education, training and rehabilitation.</P>
        <P>We must not forget the need to rehabilitate prisoners so they can re-enter society because they are sometimes homeless on leaving prison and thus end up being put back in.  This cycle needs to be broken.  With new modern facilities such as those proposed for Thornton Hall, we <Col N="556"/>will be in a position to deliver in this regard and bring our penal code into line with international best practice.</P>
        <P>When discussing the motion on the prison, Senator O&rsquo;Toole referred to its name.  Have there been any developments in this regard?  We should name the prison as soon as possible so it will not be referred to as &ldquo;Thornton Hall Prison&rdquo; by the media.</P>
        <P>I welcome the fact that the prison will have a library, health care room and gymnasium.  These will give prisoners something to do, improve their health and assist in readmitting them to society.  I hope it will prevent them from getting involved in further crime.</P>
        <P>That prisoners will be housed in separate rooms is very important.  As we know from Mountjoy Prison, communication and overcrowding among prisoners can lead to trouble.  The Irish Prison Service deserves our support in implementing the penal code.  To date, we have not been able to operate according to best practice.  The facilities and physical layout of the proposed prison, with its eight blocks, mean it will be easier to prevent the use of illegal mobile phones and drugs.  The practices that obtain at present must not be allowed in the new purpose-built prison.</P>
        <P>I was very interested to hear Mountjoy Prison was built to facilitate the short-term housing of convicts being sent to Tasmania.  I did not realise this.  It explains part of the problem we have been having with the prison.</P>
        <P>Our current system is ineffectual and the new prison is badly needed.  I welcome the fact that the Department is to consider immediately the Oberstown project for minors in Lusk.  Minors will be housed temporarily in Thornton Hall, which I do not support, but, when the new project is completed, as outlined in the speech of the Minister of State, it will address people&rsquo;s concerns.</P>
        <P>At present, many of those who argue not to have a larger prison claim we are failing to consider other aspects of penal policy, including rehabilitation, community sentencing and the paying of fines.  However, we live in a society in which people can and do commit serious crimes.  The number of serious crimes is rising and we therefore need more prison spaces.</P>
        <P>Our sentencing policy cannot be implemented fully at present and we consequently need more prison spaces so prisoners can be incarcerated for the full terms to which they are sentenced.  Our next task should be to consider sentencing and the new facility will assist us in doing so, such that society will be safer and citizens will have more respect for the Judiciary and not commit crimes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I have already congratulated the Minister of State, Deputy Barry Andrews, on his appointment and wish him well.  I wish he had different business on hand today than that with which we are dealing.  I declare an interest in that the proposed prison will effectively be in my back garden.  My views are coloured as a consequence.</P>
        <P>I have often been asked about my view on the prison.  It is very simple; I have always said the prison is to be located in the wrong place.  However, I never opposed it for a number of reasons, first because it was my brother in law who sold the site.  This was his right and I do not object at all to his doing so.  Second, the prison is to be in my own back garden and I do not like the idea of NIMBY politicians.  Although I dislike the location of the site, the decision thereon was taken democratically by the Government.  I will have to accept this if this Bill is passed.  My neighbours are very upset over the proposed prison, as much because of the impact on their community as anything else.</P>
        <P>Our vote on this Bill will not be a vote for or against the prison but a vote on the confirmation of the planning process.  The process is quite flawed because the needs outlined in the Bill <Col N="557"/>have not been met.  The Minister of State said he listened to the views of local community representatives.  In this regard, Senator McDonald referred to the name of the prison, and I thank her for that.  I raised this issue four times and made the point that the community is very small.  I do not know if Members understand there is no pub, shop or business community in Kilsallaghan.  There is a riding centre, the Thornton Park Equestrian Centre, which tells me it is losing business.  Residents&rsquo; addresses include the names &ldquo;Thornton&rdquo; or &ldquo;Kilsallaghan&rdquo; and there are only 23 to 30 houses.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State&rsquo;s colleague, the Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Conor Lenihan, agreed with me that it is not unreasonable to change the name, as did the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Dermot Ahern.  I ask again today that the name be changed.  I do not understand why the prison cannot be called &ldquo;the new Mountjoy&rdquo; until another name is chosen.  That is the obvious thing to do and it would make sense because Thornton Hall is being preserved.  One of the better aspects of this planning process is that Thornton Hall is being preserved and will be outside, rather than on, the prison site.  Consequently, it makes no sense to use that name.  In addition, this matter is important to local residents.  However, although the Minister of State said that people are listening to residents, this constitutes an example in which they are listening but are doing nothing.</P>
        <P>Amenities are another reason for concern.  Were a planning authority to do what Members are doing at present, it would ask what benefits were coming back to the community.  In previous speeches during recent years Ministers have stated that amenities would be made available in the locality.  However, they were not.  Ministers spoke of facilities such as playing fields, access to libraries, etc.  However, nothing has been given back to a community that will be overwhelmed by this development.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State should understand this area lacks footpaths.  There are no footpaths in Kilsallaghan and people go for walks along the road.  Although it is close to the city, this is a rural community.  Will footpaths be provided?  As local residents have asked for them, would it not have been possible to build a footpath or walk along the planted hedgerow area?  Does that sound like an unreasonable demand from local people to the Minister of State?  However, given they asked for something that has not come to pass, how can the Minister of State assert they are being listened to?</P>
        <P>The question of the height of the wall has been raised.  I have asked this simple question four times, namely, why is the wall 7.2 m high?  That is as high as or slightly higher than, the wall in the Chamber.  It will be located close to houses which have a surrounding landscape of fields at present.  This will be a complete change.  The view was the wall either should be lowered or moved back.  I do not know the reason for the height except the Department decided on it.  One of the flaws in this process is that the Department can decide without giving reasons.  I guarantee the Minister of State that whatever responses his advisers are preparing for him at present, they will not provide him with an answer to this question.  They will state that this is how matters always have been done, as though one should still be using quills.  As I noted, the wall will be higher than the Berlin Wall.</P>
        <P>I have to hand the planning specifications for a recently constructed prison in the United Kingdom, Ashford Prison.  Unlike what has been done here, every aspect has been outlined in it, from drainage to everything else, including the size of the attenuation tanks to hold the water.  On the proposed site, there will be 100 acres on which there no longer will be drainage.  We already have floods every year in our area.  The water no longer will drain through the land but will be collected.  The Minister of State is good at maths and should work out 100 acres, or 4,840 slat cearnach an acra.  He should work out how many cubic metres or gallons of <Col N="558"/>water are involved, what size the tanks should be and where they should go.  He will be informed that attenuation tanks will be used, which will let it off lightly.  However, Senator de B&uacute;rca will understand from an environmental point of view that one still will not get that volume of water through the 20 in. pipes used in the locality at present.  No one has explained such practical simple matters to the residents.  Were one dealing with a local authority, one would not get away with it.  That is what is wrong with this process.</P>
        <P>As an aside, the overall wall height in the aforementioned Ashford Prison is 5.6 m.  I am sure Senator de B&uacute;rca will be interested to learn that the prison&rsquo;s specifications stated it would be constructed with an exposed aggregate finish, for which a locally-won gravel was likely to be used and the final appearance would be agreed on, etc.  The requisite detail is present.  However, I cannot get answers to these simple questions, which simply is wrong.  I considered other prison projects in what one might call less educated or civilised parts of the world.  In Burma, the outside wall of Insein Prison is 20 ft. in height.  In East Timor, the last prison built by the United Nations development programme has a perimeter fence that is 5.2 m high and so on.  If I had sufficient time, I could cite other places in which the technology available to people nowadays makes such heights unnecessary.</P>
        <P>Members should remember that inside this wall there will be a <i>cordon sanitaire</i> of approximately 30 m or 40 m.  Consequently, it will not be a question simply of throwing drugs over the wall.  One would be obliged to throw them over the 7.2 m wall and across a distance of a further 40 m.  Thereafter, one would be obliged to hop up over another wall before someone could deal with them.</P>
        <P>It is very difficult for local people to understand how this can be achieved.  Of course there is local recognition and appreciation of the fact that the dedicated road mentioned by the Minister of State has been included.  This constitutes a significant improvement.  However, another issue in respect of the planning becomes clear if one looks at a map.  The site is off the N2 and it has been stated that the R130 and other local minor roads, which are tiny, will not experience additional traffic.  I asked the Minister, the next time he travelled from Dundalk, to try to drive to the new prison site without using some of these minor roads from Balbriggan, Malahide, Swords, Portmarnock or Portrane, where a certain number of prison officers probably will live.  It cannot be done unless one travels down to the M50 and back out again.  I make this point to the Minister of State as an example of how local people believe they are not being given full information.</P>
        <P>On the prison planning map, little red dots, of which there are only 24 or 25, signify residences.  I asked that each house should receive a visit from the prison authorities to explain what was happening.  I asked that they would explain the height of the wall and whether there would be noise pollution or light pollution at night.  I refer to the question of a Garda presence.  I note the Minister of State did not mention the welcome proposal to build a new Garda station.  I hope I am not to take from his failure to mention it in his speech that it has been dropped.</P>
        <P>I refer to type of vegetation or shrubs.  While there is no point in having screening for three months of the year, it is not necessary to have evergreens either.  One could use evergreen oak, holm oak, blackthorn or beech, that is, trees that do not lose their leaves during the year.  Moreover, they also are Irish planted trees and broadleafs, etc.  Such issues must be discussed and implemented in order that screening is present throughout the year.  These are simple matters.</P>
        <P>I refer to local walks, footpaths and bridle paths.  When I arrived there 30 years ago, ours was the first new house to be built in the sense that all the other houses were either farmhouses or had been built by the local authorities.  Of the 23 houses, lest people think this is a rich and <Col N="559"/>well-off community, more than half were built by local authorities.  Three generations of the same families have lived in these houses.  My family shared college apartments with people whose grandfather worked for my daughter&rsquo;s grandfather on a farm.  This is an established local community.  Any new houses have only been constructed in the past 20 years.  There is no estate or anything like that.</P>
        <P>Will traffic calming measures be put in place?  The drainage needs should be explained to local people.  I do not expect the Minister of State to have the answer in this regard.  Will the authorities, as was promised previously, visit each house?  People are worried about security.  Will these houses receive a security upgrade?  These are simple matters.  As for local walks, footpaths and bridle paths, the only industry there is horse training.  Arkle came from Kilsallaghan.  Horses used to be broken in along the roads, including racehorses that finally finished up at Cheltenham and elsewhere.  This no longer can be done.</P>
        <P>I refer to another question to which I did not receive an answer.  An enormous town is being built.  My neighbours should be given special consideration and priority and there should be positive discrimination in their favour in respect of jobs or employment in the area.  It is not too much to ask and it could be done easily to show a commitment to the local area.</P>
        <P>I again ask that the Irish Prison Service should visit each local house.  There are three local groups, namely, the concerned residents, the Rolestown-St. Margaret&rsquo;s Action Group and a third group who live where the new waste water treatment scheme is to be located and who have particular needs.  All three groups should be kept in the loop.  Moreover, some people are not part of such groups and should therefore have the same authority.</P>
        <P>In his response, the Minister of State should tell me whether I sound unreasonable in anything I have sought.  Do I sound unreasonable in respect of any issue that I have put before the Minister of State on behalf of local residents?  How can the Irish Prison Service be a good neighbour if it is unable to deal with such simple things?  People will be unable to go for walks because of the excessive traffic volume on the road.  I will not go into the other issues.  These are not major issues and they should be conceded to people generously and easily.  I did not even mention sewage, with which the local authority must deal.  There is no sewage treatment in Kilsallaghan and the local houses must be connected.  I believe they also will receive a commitment in this regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdredeBurca"><NameTxt>Senator D&eacute;irdre de B&uacute;rca</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the opportunity to debate this Bill.  Senator Boyle has already spoken about the prison at Thornton Hall in the Seanad several weeks ago.  He made it clear that the Green Party has qualms about the location of this prison.  We accept a decision has been made and we are prepared to live with it.  We agree there is a need for a new prison and we are very aware of the Victorian conditions in Mountjoy, the unacceptable practices of slopping out, the substandard accommodation and so on.  We recognise there is a need for a new prison and we welcome that this prison will have state-of-the-art facilities.  It will accommodate 1,400 prisoners and an especially welcome feature of the prison is single cell occupancy, which will be a major improvement.  The Minister of State also mentioned that if necessary, the cells could take double occupancy and the numbers accommodated by the prison could rise to 2,200.  However, it is envisaged that single cell occupancy would be maintained and the numbers kept below 1,400.</P>
        <P>I welcome other planning decisions, such as the provision of a dedicated bus service to the prison.  I also welcome the provision of work training facilities, a library, health care facilities, a gym and a playing field.  All of these definitely should form part of any modern, state-of-the-art prison.</P>
<Col N="560"/>
        <P Just="Left">I am glad to hear that Ireland remains one of the EU member states with the lowest rates of imprisonment.  I hope that situation is maintained and that the emphasis in our criminal justice system will be to look for alternatives to incarceration.  We are all very aware of the problems that arise regarding incarceration and recidivism.  We should always be looking constructively at policies that avoid these problems.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State spoke about the detention of non-nationals, which is a very important issue.  He said that the facilities at Thornton Hall will be such that people detained for immigration control reasons would be accommodated separately from remand or sentenced prisoners, in line with best international practice.  I must say that best international practice would dictate that it is not a good idea to locate asylum seekers in the same location as those who are incarcerated for serious crimes.  The Green Party is very concerned about the proposed location of the reception centre for people seeking asylum status at the Thornton Hall site.</P>
        <P>Ireland has a long history of emigration.  If Ellis Island had been a detention centre in its day, we would be very disturbed that some of our ancestors were held in close proximity to criminals.  They were only trying to escape very difficult circumstances in this country and looking for opportunities elsewhere, just like the immigrants who come to Ireland today.  I have no difficulty with the idea of detention centres and of processing the claims of these people, but locating them on the same campus as a major new prison is something we should reconsider.</P>
        <P>Like many other Senators, I have been lobbied about local issues at Thornton Hall.  Local residents need roads and footpaths in the area upgraded.  They also want to ensure the visual impact of the prison perimeter would be minimised, that construction activity would only occur between 7 a.m. and 7 p.m., and would not occur on Sundays.  They are concerned about the existing proposals for the emergency exit, which is located in a densely populated area.  The name of the prison is also an issue, as residents would rather a more neutral name than that of the local area.</P>
        <P>A local liaison group will be established immediately prior to the commencement of construction.  It will involve residents, the Irish Prison Service, building contractors and Fingal County Council and will hold monthly meetings.  It is good practice that the State is involved in any new development so I ask the Minister of State to consider it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  We debated this issue about two weeks ago with one of his colleagues.  I raised four key issues that day, namely, the proposal to relocate the Central Mental Hospital there, the proposal to relocate the women&rsquo;s prison there, the size of the prison and detailed design issues regarding the site.  I will not go over old ground but I received a response from the Minister which does not fill me with any confidence about the assessment that was undertaken on the decision to locate the women&rsquo;s prison and the Central Mental Hospital there.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State does not accept that this will be a super-prison, as it is only designed for 1,200 and can almost double its capacity to 2,200.  The likelihood is that before we know it, 2,200 people will be put there.  I am very concerned that this is effectively a super-prison.  In his report into the Strangeways riot in Manchester, Lord Woolf stated that a maximum prison size should be 400.  The chief inspector of prisons in the UK, Ms Anne Owens, refers to anything with a capacity of more than 2,000 as a super-prison.  Therefore, we need to call a spade a spade.  This is a super-prison.  The debate should be about whether we need a super-prison and whether it is the right way to rehabilitate people by putting them in such large prisons.  Perhaps it is the way forward; I do not know.  However, we are not doing anyone any good by ducking the debate.  I would prefer to see an explanation on why we need to see a prison built with a capacity for more than 2,000 people.</P>
<Col N="561"/>
        <P Just="Left">I also want to talk about some detailed issues, many of which have been covered before.  I live close to the area, and some people from the area are in the Visitors Gallery.  It is impossible to find one&rsquo;s way around the local roads.  There are no footpaths and there is very little signage.  We need to spend money on the local road network to ensure people can find their way to it, but local residents should not be inconvenienced.  The perimeter must be in place before the prison site is constructed.  The residents are also asking for a planning condition that work on the construction site would take place only between 7 a.m. and 7 p.m.  We need to ensure trucks do not wait outside before 7 a.m., as that happens all over the north east at the moment, disturbing the sleep of local residents.  Construction routes should avoid local schools such as those in Bellewstown and Lismullen, which are right next to the proposed site.  These schools suffer from heavy construction traffic, so we must take account of this.</P>
        <P>I support Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s call for a change in name.  Calling the prison Thornton Hall does not do anyone any good.  A working title could be the new Mountjoy, or perhaps the Charles J. Haughey correctional institute.  I do not mind.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><NameTxt>Senator Diarmuid Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>What about the Proinsias de Rossa centre?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>We need to get away from calling it the Thornton Hall prison.  Let us have a debate on the name.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should have respect for those who made an immense contribution to the country.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Hannigan, without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I have two final points to make.  I do not accept it is impossible to keep drugs out of prison.  We have a fantastic opportunity, with a new prison, to design it so that we can limit access to drugs.  I ask that particular attention be concentrated on that.  There is sufficient space for rehabilitation.  I am glad to see some proposals for the use of playing fields and the like.  There is a large site, so let us use it for rehabilitation purposes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and I am glad of the opportunity to speak on the Bill.  As Senator Hannigan has said, I regret there has not been more time to debate the proposed construction of the new Mountjoy Prison, or if we are in the business of naming it after individuals, perhaps we should call it the Michael McDowell Prison since he was the Minister who seems to have come up with the idea for it.</P>
        <P>I want to speak against the adoption of this Bill for a number of reasons.  The first, and perhaps the most significant, is in relation to the size of the prison.  The Minister of State has addressed the issue of whether it is a super-prison, and clearly, when one looks at prison policy in Ireland in the context of Irish imprisonment, to date, this constitutes a super-prison.  It is certainly on a much larger scale than we have ever seen constructed in this country before and will concentrate a number of different carceral institutions on one site.</P>
        <P>I also want to take issue with something said by the Minister of State in terms of imprisonment rates.  It is a matter of some pride that we have a low imprisonment rate, by international standards, per 100,000 of the population in jail on any given day.  The figure is approximately 3,000 on any one day.  However, our committal rate is somewhat higher.  That is the absolute number of persons committed to prison in any one year.  There we see a very different figure, equivalent to 10,000 persons committed to prison in any one year.  On women prisoners the figures are in stark contrast.  The Minister of State has pointed out that there are, on average, 106 women in prison in any given day in Ireland, representing less than 4% of the overall prison population.  However, in 2006, some 960 women were committed to prison, representing <Col N="562"/>almost 10% of the overall committals figure for that year.  Again, the absolute figures perhaps give a truer picture of the scale of imprisonment.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Clearly, what we are seeing are large numbers of people imprisoned for short sentences.  Ideally, these are people who should not be in prison at all.  If we have a true commitment to rehabilitation in Irish sentencing policy, and I am pleased the Minister of State said we do, then we need to put our money where our mouth is and invest more heavily in the Probation and Welfare Service and alternative sanctions, not imprisonment.</P>
        <P>What we is enormous sums of money being devoted to the building of a new carceral institution as opposed to resources being spent on the probation and welfare service and non-custodial sanctions.  This Bill is a wasted opportunity to carve out a new direction in sentencing and prison policy.  It is true the Executive cannot have a direct role in how many people are sent to prison, but it is also a fact that in making legislation and putting policy into practice, the Executive and the Legislature have a very strong indirect effect in terms of the numbers of people incarcerated through, for example, mandatory minimum sentences, the building of prisons and so on which ensure more people will be sent to prison.  It is unfortunate, therefore, that we are seeing the building of this new institution with up to 2,200 places being provided.</P>
        <P>I raised this matter at the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality, Defence and Women&rsquo;s Rights and I am concerned to know what will trigger the double occupancy cells of which the Minister of State speaks.  I know he said it is not envisaged that the 2,200 maximum will be filled in the foreseeable future, but again we must be concerned that if we build a prison on this immense scale, it will be filled, with more people being imprisoned as a result.</P>
        <P>There is one issue of which we need to be aware, even if the Bill is passed, and it is something of which I hope to continue lobbying on a cross-party basis.  I know there are party colleagues of the Minister of State who feel strongly about this.  I shall continue to lobby to prevent the new women&rsquo;s prison going ahead on this site.  It is important we look again at the principle of the imprisonment of women.  We had a seminar very recently in Leinster House, hosted by Deputy Mary O&rsquo;Rourke and I, where we heard from Baroness Jean Corston, author of a very influential UK report on the imprisonment of women.  She suggests prison should only be a last resort for women, and only for those who commit crimes of violence.</P>
        <P>Again, I do not believe we need a larger prison to be built.  Women prisoners do not suffer from the same appalling conditions men do in Mountjoy.  The D&oacute;chas Centre is less than ten years old and there is a strong case to be made for retaining it on its present site.  I raised this before and was told the reason we needed to build a new women&rsquo;s prison was because of overcrowding in D&oacute;chas.  I am reliably informed that a large number of the women in prison in D&oacute;chas are there because of immigration related matters.  Certainly, very many of them are there for short periods and more than half are not there under sentence.  We need to look again at the profile of the women being sent to D&oacute;chas and provide alternatives to prison for women.</P>
        <P>The new prison envisaged for women on the new Mountjoy site will, once again, be a closed institution.  There is no facility in this country for open prisons for women and no facility for smaller custodial units &mdash; the type Baroness Corston recommends &mdash; for those few women offenders who commit crimes of violence.</P>
        <P>I have no choice but to oppose this Bill because it sets out the wrong direction for our penal and prison policy.  It is unfortunate we are missing an opportunity.  Instead of developing a whole new super-prison on a greenfield site, we should use the very detailed plans developed by the Office of Public Works some years ago under the predecessor of the former Minister, Michael McDowell, to redevelop that site on true rehabilitative principles.  We should look at <Col N="563"/>an overall prison policy that aims to reduce the numbers in prison and in particular to reduce the use of imprisonment for those who commit crimes that are not violent.  I urge the Minister of State to take on board my remarks about the women&rsquo;s prison, even if the Bill is passed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister of State to the Seanad.  When I was elected to this House 16 years ago, one of the very first Bills I had to consider was a prisons Bill.  I recall that I did not know what to do, since I had no experience in this area, having been involved in a different way of life before that.  I decided to look for the customer in every Bill.  For a health Bill, I would look to the well-being of the patient.  In the case of an education Bill, I would look to the well-being of the student.  When I came to the prison Bill, I had to reflect on what was best for society as a whole.  I came to the conclusion very early on in this regard that the best interest of the prisoner was rehabilitation and this should be one of our objectives.  A second objective should be to frame legislation that acts as a deterrent to others.  If we are going to send someone to jail, its function is not just to rehabilitate but also to act as a deterrent.  A third one, of course, is punishment, to ensure the prisoner thinks twice about what he or she has done.</P>
        <P>I was very impressed to read in <i>The Guardian</i> yesterday about the Hassela reform centre in Sweden, which I had not heard of before.  If I may, I would like to quote from the article, &ldquo;Island of last resort&rdquo;, by Irish journalist, Maggie O&rsquo;Kane.  It states:</P>
        <P LI="1">The most striking thing about the Hassela reform centre, apart from the apple blossom, the thick white candles burning on the breakfast tables and the smell of old wood from the ancient eaves of the dining room, is the silence.  Sixty teenagers with criminal records, drug problems or a history of antisocial behaviour live here in Gotland, Sweden, in and around a beautiful wooden house with a conservatory stretching back into the garden.  A trampoline sits on the lawn and a barbecue still charred from a recent feast is by the back door.</P>
        <P LI="1">The &ldquo;students&rdquo;, as they are called, are part of one of the world&rsquo;s most striking youth detention centres.  They live in the main house or in smaller houses scattered throughout the village.  Occasionally, there are &ldquo;challenges&rdquo; &mdash; the Irish boy, for example, who tried to hold up the post office with a knife, then went back to apologise &mdash; but for the most part, this small Swedish community accepts the 60 or so students who live in its midst as kids who need help to straighten themselves out.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I gather when I read further that we might even use this model in Ireland for the rehabilitation of young people.  I mentioned this because I had been looking for the customer in every particular Bill and on reflection discovered that there were a number of different objectives to aim at.</P>
        <P>One we missed out on at that stage, or at least I did not think of it until later, was the protection of our citizens.  There are prisoners from whom the rest of society has to be protected.  It is not enough to talk about prison as rehabilitation, a deterrent or punishment.  It must also protect society from such prisoners and there is a danger that we only think of the soft rather than the hard options.  We must ensure society is protected because there are prisoners in incarceration who are a danger to society.  I do not know the answer to this.</P>
        <P>I have listened carefully in the debate to arguments about the need for such a large prison versus the need to consider all the options as regards whether prisoners can have visitors when they live so far away from the jail.  Will there be a bus service for prisoners&rsquo; families to visit them?  Is there a danger this could encourage the smuggling of drugs and mobile telephones into prisons?  We have seen some of the real dangers in prisons where we have not had control in this area.</P>
<Col N="564"/>
        <P>This is a challenge and one we cannot take lightly.  There is a balance between rehabilitation &mdash; resolving the problems of those citizens who have decided to be criminals or fell into bad ways &mdash; and protecting members of society from those who are violent.  There is no easy answer to this.  This is a worthy debate to ensure we do not rush into decisions without giving proper attention to and recognising the various options in this area.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BarryAndrewsFF"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Barry Andrews</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senators for their contributions.  I know they have been through this matter before and are probably tired debating it.  There are two elements to this debate &mdash; the physical infrastructure of the prison and how it will affect locals and our general prisons policy.</P>
        <P>Senator Quinn referred to the issues influencing sentencing.  He did not refer to the restorative element of sentencing, that is putting the victim of crime back into the position they were before the crime occurred.  That was central to points made by other Senators.  They were concerned there was no focus on the restorative and rehabilitation elements of sentencing policy.  A commission on restorative justice has been established.  The Government&rsquo;s policy is to seek other types of sentences, in particular non-custodial types.</P>
        <P>As Senator Bacik rightly pointed out, the majority of sentences are short-term ones.  There is a reasonably good base upon which to build a strong rehabilitation structure.</P>
        <P>Senator Regan referred to integrated sentence management, which is part of the national development plan for dealing with prisoners.  In the next session, I hope to introduce the spent convictions Bill to encourage rehabilitation and encourage prisoners to move out of recidivism.  Recidivism rates are high.  The organisation, Business in the Community, does much work in helping ex-prisoners to find employment, re-integrate into society and avoid a cycle of re-offending.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Conor Lenihan, believes it would be a good idea for the local residents to consider the name for the prison.  Senator O&rsquo;Toole asked if he sounded reasonable; he always does to me.  It would be reasonable to allow the local residents to determine the name of the prison.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>In the meantime, every document on the prison from the Government needs to have a name.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BarryAndrewsFF"><NameTxt>Deputy Barry Andrews</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator will note I have deliberately not mentioned TH in my contribution.  It should be a name with which local people will be comfortable.  All politicians are accused of the NIMBY syndrome but Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s electorate is far beyond Kilsallaghan so it is difficult to accuse him of it.  He just wants to walk the bridle paths there in peace for the next several years.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">2 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>The majority of traffic going to the prison will be from Dublin and the M50.  My impression is that the prison will not have an adverse impact on local residents.  Liaison with the local community was raised by Senator de B&uacute;rca which is a sensible suggestion.  In my experience with major developments, local people tend to run scared from developers.  In this case, the State is the developer and there should be some way of ensuring constant communication with local residents on the development.  Development levies usually assist in developing footpaths, etc.  In this case, there should be some way of improving other infrastructural standards in the area.</P>
        <P>The perimeter wall will consist of an existing hedgerow, a tree screening band of 20 m in depth, a fence and an internal road and then the wall itself.  In any case, the wall will be 15 m to 30 m from the boundary of neighbouring properties.  This should provide some solace for <Col N="565"/>local residents.  While I appreciate Kilsallaghan is a rural setting, people live quite happily in the lee of the Central Mental Hospital and Mountjoy Prison.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>What about the height of the perimeter wall?  The Minister of State said he would tell me why it will be 7.2 m.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BarryAndrewsFF"><NameTxt>Deputy Barry Andrews</NameTxt>
	<P>I did not say I would tell the Senator why it will 7.2 m.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Minister of State tell me he does not know?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BarryAndrewsFF"><NameTxt>Deputy Barry Andrews</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is being unreasonable now.  If Members are concerned about the prison accommodating up to 2,200 prisoners, it would be short-sighted for the Government not to anticipate possible changes in prison population.  Mountjoy Prison has lasted for 150 years.  Some Members are concerned about meeting international standards.  By any measure, the proposed prison will exceed them.</P>
      
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put.</P>
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 20; N&iacute;l, 16.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading>
        <YesVote pid="JohnCartyFF">Carty, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DonnieCassidyFF">Cassidy, Donie.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MariaCorrigan">Corrigan, Maria.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarkDaly">Daly, Mark.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DeirdredeBurca">de B&uacute;rca, D&eacute;irdre.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnEllis">Ellis, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="GeraldineFeeney">Feeney, Geraldine.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="CamillusGlynn">Glynn, Camillus.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnGerardHanafin">Hanafin, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarcMacSharry">MacSharry, Marc.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LisaMcDonald">McDonald, Lisa.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianODomhnaill">&Oacute; Domhnaill, Brian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DennisODonovan">O&rsquo;Donovan, Denis.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FionnaOMalleyPD">O&rsquo;Malley, Fiona.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="NedOSullivan">O&rsquo;Sullivan, Ned.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AnnOrmonde">Ormonde, Ann.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="KieranPhelan">Phelan, Kieran.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</YesVote>
        <NHeading>N&iacute;l</NHeading>
        <NoVote pid="IvanaBacik">Bacik, Ivana.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulBradford">Bradford, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaddyBurke">Burke, Paddy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JerryButtimer">Buttimer, Jerry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MauriceCummins">Cummins, Maurice.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaschalDonohoe">Donohoe, Paschal.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FrancesFitzgerald">Fitzgerald, Frances.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DominicHannigan">Hannigan, Dominic.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FidelmaHealyEames">Healy Eames, Fidelma.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="NickyMcFadden">McFadden, Nicky.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="RonanMullen">Mullen, R&oacute;n&aacute;n.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JoeOToole">O&rsquo;Toole, Joe.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnPaulPhelan">Phelan, John Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FergalQuinn">Quinn, Feargal.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="EugeneRegan">Regan, Eugene.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="ShaneRoss">Ross, Shane.</NoVote>
        <Tellers>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Diarmuid Wilson and D&eacute;irdre de B&uacute;rca; N&iacute;l, Senators Eugene Regan and Ivana Bacik.</Tellers>
        <Decision><?oasys _is0p10- ?>Question declared carried.</Decision>
      </Vote>
    <HtmlBk SectId="4" />
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Now.</P>
        </Speaker><P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
        <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Question put: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
        
<Col N="566"/>
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 20; N&iacute;l, 17.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading>
        <YesVote pid="JohnCartyFF">Carty, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DonnieCassidyFF">Cassidy, Donie.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MariaCorrigan">Corrigan, Maria.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarkDaly">Daly, Mark.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DeirdredeBurca">de B&uacute;rca, D&eacute;irdre.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnEllis">Ellis, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="GeraldineFeeney">Feeney, Geraldine.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="CamillusGlynn">Glynn, Camillus.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnGerardHanafin">Hanafin, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarcMacSharry">MacSharry, Marc.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LisaMcDonald">McDonald, Lisa.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianODomhnaill">&Oacute; Domhnaill, Brian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DennisODonovan">O&rsquo;Donovan, Denis.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FionnaOMalleyPD">O&rsquo;Malley, Fiona.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="NedOSullivan">O&rsquo;Sullivan, Ned.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AnnOrmonde">Ormonde, Ann.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="KieranPhelan">Phelan, Kieran.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</YesVote>
        <NHeading>N&iacute;l</NHeading>
        <NoVote pid="IvanaBacik">Bacik, Ivana.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulBradford">Bradford, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaddyBurke">Burke, Paddy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JerryButtimer">Buttimer, Jerry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MauriceCummins">Cummins, Maurice.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PearseDoherty">Doherty, Pearse.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaschalDonohoe">Donohoe, Paschal.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FrancesFitzgerald">Fitzgerald, Frances.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DominicHannigan">Hannigan, Dominic.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FidelmaHealyEames">Healy Eames, Fidelma.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="NickyMcFadden">McFadden, Nicky.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="RonanMullen">Mullen, R&oacute;n&aacute;n.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JoeOToole">O&rsquo;Toole, Joe.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnPaulPhelan">Phelan, John Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FergalQuinn">Quinn, Feargal.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="EugeneRegan">Regan, Eugene.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="ShaneRoss">Ross, Shane.</NoVote>
        <Tellers>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators D&eacute;irdre de B&uacute;rca and Diarmuid Wilson; N&iacute;l, Senators Ivana Bacik and Joe O&rsquo;Toole.</Tellers>
        <Decision><?oasys _is0p10- ?>Question declared carried.</Decision>
      </Vote>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>De M&aacute;irt seo chugainn ag 2.30 p.m.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. </Title>
  </MainHeading><Line />
  <?oasys _cl13- ?><MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Private" RHead="Partnerships"> 
    <Title>Public Private Partnerships. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalDonohoe"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Donohoe</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister of State back to the House and thank him for taking this matter which concerns the current status of the inner city Dublin communities that were affected by the collapse of public private partnership projects.  When the process collapsed a number of weeks ago, the issue appropriately generated a significant profile both politically and in the media.  In the meantime, however, two factors have arisen which prompted me to raise this motion on the Adjournment and seek a comment from the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government.  First, there is a continuing lack of information for the communities concerned as to what the next stage of the project will be.  This is not meant, nor should it be taken, as a criticism of Dublin City Council, but that council now finds itself dealing with a scale of issues that goes beyond anything it could have expected.  The situation is placing the council in an extremely difficult position, while it is seeking to provide leadership to the local community on the timing of future plans.  Factors such as inter-bank lending and the amount of debt that development companies may incur are beyond the council&rsquo;s control.  The council is finding it difficult to ascertain what the next appropriate step is and, more importantly, to take any such steps.</P>
<Col N="567"/>
        <P>The Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government must take as active a role as possible in supporting Dublin City Council to resolve this issue for the sake of the communities involved.  Last Friday, I had a number of engagements with the affected communities and it is difficult to overstate the degree of despair among those involved in the projects.  These people have spent many years engaging in a process to come up with good designs for their local communities, which have been under great pressure due to anti-social behaviour and local economic decline.  The plan was swept away just as there was a glimmer of hope and local people were looking forward to seeing the projects come to fruition.  In one case, buildings that were due to be replaced were demolished.  The Government should visibly and proactively support the work of the city council in trying to bring the projects to a quick conclusion.</P>
        <P>I will conclude with an observation of a resident to whom I spoke this morning about this issue.  I also raised this matter on today&rsquo;s Order of Business.  He made the point that for many years residents in such communities have been eating dinner on their knees because of the small size of their homes and the conditions therein.  Dublin City Council is facing a severe problem that affects these local communities.  It is vital for the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, together with the leadership and expertise that the Government should be able to muster, to do all it can to support the council and the residents in tackling this grave problem.  I would appreciate it if the Minister of State could confirm that the Government recognises the scale and gravity of this issue.  More importantly, however, the Minister of State should update the House on what the Government can do to resolve this matter, both for the council and the residents who have been so gravely disappointed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Finance</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  I accept the depths of public concern he has expressed and the importance of the social issue.</P>
        <P>The future of the five PPP projects in question remains a matter of high priority within the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government and Dublin City Council.  At the outset, I want to reiterate the point that has been made previously by my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Finneran, that public private partnerships are just one approach being used by local authorities to deliver social housing.  In addition to the provision of capital funding for new construction projects, authorities continue to expand their housing output through the Part V mechanism, and through long-term leasing arrangements.  Funding of &euro;1.2 billion has been made available by the Exchequer to support the national social housing investment programme this year.</P>
        <P>Dublin City Council, in particular, has an ambitious social housing programme for 2008, which is not in any way affected by the recent announcement.  Some &euro;250 million, or 21% of the total capital allocation nationally, has been allocated to fund housing construction and regeneration activities in the Dublin City Council area and this support will ensure continued strong performance in the delivery of social housing during the year.</P>
        <P>Regarding the five PPP regeneration projects in question, the Department of the Environment, Heritage, and Local Government continues to liaise closely with Dublin City Council as it works toward agreement on the next steps for the projects.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In the first instance, I emphasise that the residents of these areas continue to be at the centre of all our considerations.  The city council has assured the Department of its commitment to working with its tenants to explore options for moving the regeneration forward and for addressing current housing needs.  Accordingly, the council is endeavouring to relocate the remaining residents of these estates.  Alternative accommodation has been already identified for the residents of St. Michael&rsquo;s Estate, and offers are being made.  The city council has also met the regeneration boards for these areas to apprise them of the current situation.</P>
        <P>The city council is engaged in a broad consideration of the social, economic and legal implications arising from the indications given that the projects will not now proceed as planned.  Following its discussions with stakeholders and the developer, the council will put forward <Col N="568"/>alternative proposals in order that the process for the regeneration of these areas can proceed.  In this context, discussions with the developer are ongoing and I hope these result in clear options for moving forward.  It is not possible at this stage, however, to determine the exact route that will be taken.  I assure the Senator and the House that the Department of the Environment, Heritage, and Local Government will continue to engage actively with the council in this regard.</P>
        <P>Against the background of the viability of the wider PPP regeneration programme, the Department has, I am informed, established a multi-agency group to examine the economic and other factors that were cited by the developer as presenting significant challenges to the PPP model.  Nevertheless, the Government is confident that the PPP concept still represents a positive and economically efficient means of supporting sustainable communities through encouraging social, income, and tenure mix.  In the future, private finance, in whatever form this takes, will be necessary to achieve these sustainable mixed communities if we are not to return to the age of sprawling, mono-tenure social housing estates, which we now know contribute significantly to economic and social deprivation and in some cases many other problems.</P>
        <P>I re-emphasise that the recent announcement will not impact on the wider social housing programme for the city council. With regard to the future of the regeneration projects concerned, the city council continues to be committed to engaging positively with the residents of these areas and the Department of the Environment, Heritage, and Local Government will continue to work closely with the city council to move forward these projects as quickly as possible.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Leinster" RHead="Lawn"> 
    <Title>Leinster Lawn. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">This matter relates to a matter with which I am sure the Minister of State, Deputy Mansergh, will be familiar, namely the need to restore Leinster Lawn to its former glory by restoring it to grass and removing the car park.</P>
        <P>The Minister will be aware that it was dug up in 2000 and made into a car park.  It was probably before his time here but if I am wrong, he can correct me.  It was declared at the time to be a temporary measure, and it was the Taoiseach who came into the D&aacute;il and said so.  One of the conditions of the planning permission at the time was that it would be restored to grass.  It appears we in Leinster House, the OPW or the Government, are in breach of the planning permission because no effort has been made to restore it.</P>
        <P>While I do not want to make political points, I suppose this tells us a certain amount about our priorities, namely, that Members and staff of Leinster House should be given precedence over the requirements of the environment and the obvious wishes of the people of Dublin and elsewhere.  I have had &mdash; as I am sure have other Members &mdash; several representations on this issue from people who look in and ask what on earth are we doing with a car park where there was a beautiful lawn.  I have always said it will be restored.  I have been saying that now for eight years and nothing has happened.</P>
        <P>There were plans at the time to build an underground car park.  The answer for many years was that the car park was on the way and that car parking on the lawn was temporary.  The Minister of State might be able to reassure me that that plan is shelved, is about to be shelved, or is still somewhere in the Estimates of the Department of Finance.  My guess is it will never happen.</P>
        <P>There are many ways to approach this.  One could just do it and tell those who use the car park spaces that they must park elsewhere.  One could give quotas to Members.  I would be interested to see a list of those entitled to use the car parks in Leinster House.  One must be realistic about this.  There are ways to restrict it, and not just by starting with staff or Members.  Spouses of Members and ex-Members use it regularly.  On a sitting day it is chock-a-block.</P>
<Col N="569"/>
        <P>We must decide on our priorities.  Nearly eight years down the line from this temporary arrangement we need a serious commitment from the Minister of State that Leinster Lawn will be restored quickly, and that it is not dependent on some mythical two-storey car park underground that will never be built.  This commitment was given to none other than Deputy John Gormley &mdash; who is now a Minister and would be interested in this project &mdash; in 2005 when he was told the underground car park was about to be built.  Nothing has happened three years down the line.  Perhaps the Minister of State could give us some comfort.  It is imperative, if we make commitments of this sort to the electorate, that we set some sort of an example.</P>
        <P>It is also not beyond the realm of possibility that we, ourselves, make some sacrifice.  I have a parking space in the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food because I have offices there, but I would be prepared to give that up in circumstances where it would have to be shared.  Given these times, we must make sacrifices, not just in terms of salaries, perks, etc., but also in terms of the privileges we enjoy as Members of this House, if it is in the public interest.  That is not meant to sound pious in any way.  It is practical.</P>
        <P>I ask the Minister of State to commit to a date and to the price that must be paid to restore to green lawn that beautiful space outside the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator Ross for raising an important issue, with which, on a personal basis, I had some dealings as a member of the Commission of the Houses of the Oireachtas up to May 2007.  Walking to and from the Department of the Taoiseach, I would have seen the transformation-excavations which took place in 1999.</P>
        <P>Part of Leinster Lawn was temporarily converted into a car park in 1999 to facilitate construction of the Leinster House 2000 office development.  This building was required to provide adequate office accommodation of a good modern standard for Members and staff of the Oireachtas, and it did so.  It was necessary to provide compound areas for the building contractors close to the location of the works and this resulted in the displacement of permanent car parking places in that vicinity.  The temporary solution to the displacement of these places was temporarily to resurface part of the lawn for car parking.</P>
        <P Just="Left">It had been intended to restore the lawn after the Leinster House 2000 works were completed.  However, at that time, there was a plan to initiate the construction of an underground car park to accommodate the total parking requirements of the Oireachtas.  This underground car park was to be located under Leinster Lawn.  Given that planning for the underground car park was proceeding, it was considered that spending money on the restoration of the lawn, only to dig it up again within a short period of time to facilitate construction of the underground car park, would have been a waste of taxpayers&rsquo; money.  Had the underground car park proceeded, Leinster Lawn would have been fully restored and all surface car parking removed underground.  In the event, the underground car park did not advance at that time.  There were several unresolved issues and it can be regarded as off the agenda.</P>
        <P Just="Left">It was decided in 2002 to proceed with the total refurbishment of the Kildare House office block on Kildare Street, which now accommodates many of the staff and facilities, including a cr&egrave;che, supporting the Houses of the Oireachtas.  It was necessary to take over the car park area in Kildare House for the building contractors compound areas, thereby displacing the car parking facilities for the building.  As a result, it was decided to further postpone restoration of Leinster Lawn to accommodate the displaced car parking facilities on the temporary car park area until the Kildare House project was completed.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In 2004, at the direction of the Oireachtas, the car park at Kildare House was converted into printing facilities servicing the needs of the political parties and Members of the Oireachtas.  This resulted in the permanent displacement of the car parking facilities in Kildare House and those displaced continued to park on the temporary car park on Leinster Lawn.  The various phases of work at Kildare House, including the printing facilities, were completed in 2006.</P>
        <P>The ultimate solution to the car parking requirements of the Oireachtas, which are determined by the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission, is an underground car park and this <Col N="570"/>remains the objective but clearly not in the short term or, I suspect, in the medium term.  However, planning for this has been further interrupted by the discovery that major works are necessary in the historic Leinster House building to address serious structural defects that have come to light following detailed engineering surveys.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Total replacement of all electrical and mechanical installations is also necessary.  Unfortunately, undertaking these works will necessitate the relocation of all staff and facilities from the building for the duration of the works and this will require the siting of builders compounds, temporary accommodation, etc., on the Leinster Lawn area.  The effect of all this is to postpone yet again the restoration of Leinster Lawn.  It is not possible yet to say definitively when these major works will be undertaken as this will be a decision for the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission.</P>
        <P>The information accompanying the planning documentation, which was on public display, specifically stated that the lawn would be reinstated on completion of the new building works.  That did not happen for the reasons outlined.  Implicit in the permission, which was granted by the Commissioners of Public Works under Part XIII of the Local Government, Planning and Development Regulations 1994, is that the lawn will be restored.  The Office of Public Works is committed to the eventual restoration of the lawn to its original state.  Like Senator Ross, I am anxious to see that happen but given the situations and constraints which have arisen and the considerations I have outlined, it is difficult to see that happen in the immediate future.</P>
        <P>Apart from the restoration of the lawn and the knock-on implications, he raised wider issues which merit consideration.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  Perhaps he will consider those wider considerations because they are important.  The car park is too full at all times.  The Minister of State&rsquo;s reply was factually accurate and he gave us a long list of reasons Leinster Lawn has not been re-sown with grass.  I do not accept the latest reason.  I do not believe it is necessary to take up Leinster Lawn to restore part of this House.  If this House fronted on to a road and Leinster Lawn was not there, we would find another way to do it.</P>
        <P>The Minister of  State knows as well as I do that this will go on forever.  This is an old building and one will always find an excuse for restoration.  Problems will arise <i>ad infinitum</i>.  I would like an assurance from the Minister of State that the lawn will be restored within the next five years.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>It is not possible for me to give an assurance of the type sought by the Senator.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>What about ten years?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>The long-term objective&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>Fifteen years.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;has been&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;Twenty years.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;stated.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>Twenty five years.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>What am I bid?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>It is disappointing but I thank the Minister of State.</P>
      </Speaker>
<Col N="571"/>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>This is not a mart.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Banking" RHead="Sector"> 
    <Title>Banking Sector. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise this matter on the banking sector.  I welcome the Minister of State, whom I have not met before but whose reputation proceeds him.  I congratulate him on his appointment to the Department of Finance.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State will be well aware that we need a major debate on the role of the banking sector.  I say that in the context of two issues, the first of which relates to the credit squeeze affecting regular customers of banks and business people.  Banks seem to put profit before people.  They are only interested in making profits and in cutting cost margins to do so.  The Minister of State will agree this comes after a period of time in which banks were like lobbyists trying to give away money.  They wrote to people offering different types of credit and incentives to buy cars, to go on holidays and to extend their homes but now they have changed their cant from, &ldquo;We want to give you money&rdquo; to &ldquo;We need to get money from you&rdquo;.  In many ways it is like &ldquo;Charlie and the Chocolate Factory&rdquo; in that there is a chocolate bar for everybody but it is then taken away.</P>
        <P>Why is pressure being put on people when not long ago banks were writing to them to give them money?  Banks need customers but they have raised interest rates and restricted access to overdrafts and other types of credit.  As the Minister of State will know, this is having a profound impact on consumers.  How does the Minister for Finance propose to involve the Financial Regulator in this crisis in the banking sector, which is affecting people?</P>
        <P>The decision by Bank of Ireland to cut its staff share allocation from 6% to 3% is unjustified and driven by greed.  The staff of Bank of Ireland have been treated very badly and unfairly.  I say this as a customer of the bank with an account.  The staff have made significant sacrifices in the past decade.  Almost 2,100 jobs have been lost through its voluntary severance plan, along with outsourcing, relocation and the closure of branches.  It has reached the stage in some banks where when one walks in, there is a queue out the door because of a lack of staff.  I pay tribute to the staff of the Bank of Ireland.  They are its most valued ambassadors and the company does not realise this.  I very much like going to the bank in Wilton or University College Cork because the staff there are friendly, welcoming and provide a great service.</P>
        <P>Why do the banks treat staff and customers badly?  I look forward to the Minister of State&rsquo;s reply.  We must have confidence in our banking sector.  We need to generate money in the economy to sustain it.  I do not blame the Irish Bank Officials Association for serving strike notice on Bank of Ireland in July.  The staff have been treated shabbily.  The banks need customers and staff and they need to improve morale.  What plans does the Government have to engage with the banking sector and especially with the Financial Regulator?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DrMartinMansergh"><NameTxt>Deputy Martin Mansergh</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator for raising very legitimate issues.  Like him, I am also a customer of the Bank of Ireland and I, too, pay tribute to the staff there who deal with me.  By way of declaration of interest, I have a daughter who works for the other main banking group.</P>
        <P>At the outset the Senator will, I am sure, accept that Ireland&rsquo;s full integration into the global economy and financial system has brought us significant benefits in trade and investment and has helped underpin the most sustained period of economic and social progress we have ever experienced.  However, we must recognise that as a small, open economy with a financial system that has achieved an international standing and profile, it is inevitable that the uncertainty and disruption of global financial markets that has emerged over the past year and has had a significant adverse effect on world economic performance will also impact adversely on our own financial system.</P>
        <P>Internationally, wholesale credit markets, where banks access money for onward lending to business and individuals, have tightened considerably.  Liquidity has become more expensive and less available.  While Irish banks have insignificant exposure to the sub-prime products that <Col N="572"/>initiated the change in financial market conditions, they cannot be immune from its broader effects any more than the insurance industry was some years back in the aftermath of the tragedy of 11 September 2001.</P>
        <P>Within this overall changed financial environment, it is important that banks and other lending institutions adopt a prudent approach which focuses on long term interests, taking account of the increased cost of money and the more challenging international economic circumstances.  Notwithstanding several authoritative assessments of the robustness of the Irish banking sector based on our economic success of recent years, it is vital that banks and other lenders adapt their lending criteria to meet these changed circumstances.  It is also important that lending proposals meet the twin tests of being economically sustainable in the current circumstances and borrowers being able to meet their repayments.  I note that in the first quarter of 2008, banks extended 28,500 new mortgages with a value of &euro;6.3 billion, 75% of which went on new purchases.  While the level of mortgage lending is down compared with 2007, it still represents a very significant level of credit provision at a time when the residential property sector is undergoing an adjustment that is widely recognised as being necessary and appropriate.</P>
        <P>We should recognise also that there has been significant growth in competition in the banking sector in recent years, with new entrants to the sector and the introduction of new and innovative products.  While we all have to seek out the best deal to meet our needs, I expect neither the Senator nor borrowers would proffer thanks for lending that did not have regard to present realities.</P>
        <P>I am well aware that access to credit is an essential requirement for large and small businesses, especially in the start-up phase.  Although important, it is not the only requirement or the most important one.  Details of a recent survey for the Small Firms Association, which ranked concerns of small businesses for 2008, listed finding finance to grow as No. 8, coming after concerns such as economic uncertainty, managing costs, and increased competition.  Overall credit growth since the beginning of the year has amounted to &euro;9.5 billion, underlining the fact that credit continues to be made available where sound business cases are advanced.  One senior banker recently remarked that banks are not in the business of closing down profitable companies for short-term gain.</P>
        <P>The Senator will be aware from the appearance of the Central Bank and Financial Services Authority of Ireland at a meeting of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Finance and the Public Service that the Central Bank and the Financial Regulator are actively engaging with banks to make certain they act quickly and prudently to ensure the effective functioning of the financial system through the current period of uncertainty.  The Senator will note that the banks are themselves to appear before the Oireachtas in the coming days.  I hope that dialogue will be a positive one where the important and sensitive issues in question can be discussed, recognising the importance of maintaining financial stability and responding to the credit needs of the country.</P>
        <P>We are in a period of almost unprecedented international financial dislocation.  However, by keeping up a shared commitment to maintaining economic and financial stability and responsible management of credit, we can ensure our long-term economic prospects are maintained and assured.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 2.55 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Tuesday, 1 July 2008.</adjournment>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
