<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="7" Month="May" Year="2008" Vol="189" No="11" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 7 Bealtaine 2008" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 7 May 2008" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="537">
    <Col N="537"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title></Title>
        <P Just="Center">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 12.30 p.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Paidir.</i><br /><i>Prayer.</i></P><Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad"> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have received notice from Senator Paddy Burke that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Health and Children to outline the facts surrounding the discrepancy between the hospital figures and her Department&rsquo;s figures in relation to the number of breast cancer procedures carried out in the past 12 months in Mayo General Hospital, Castlebar, County Mayo.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Education and Science to address the need for a new school building for Ballygarvan national school, Ballygarvan, County Cork.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Shane Ross of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Transport to outline if the M50 barrier free tolling scheme scheduled to commence in August 2008 is on track for commencement and if he proposes to retain any function in relation to the setting of toll rates.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Michael McCarthy of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Finance to immediately allocate funding to provide floodlighting at Ballinacarriga Castle in Dunmanway, County Cork.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Pearse Doherty of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Education and Science to address the unacceptable situation whereby school secretaries and caretakers across the State are receiving disparate rates of pay and the fact that these workers, if they are not covered by the Department&rsquo;s 1978-79 scheme, are, in many cases, paid below the minimum wage.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and I have selected those raised by Senators Burke, Buttimer and Ross to be taken on the conclusion of business.  The remaining Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <Col N="538"/><MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Today&rsquo;s business is No. 1, the Twenty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution Bill 2008 &mdash; Report and Final Stages; and No. 2, motion re information for voters.  It is proposed that No. 1 will be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business and that No. 2 will be taken without debate on the conclusion of No. 1.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>This afternoon I wish to make two points about the events of today and of the past month.  Deputy Bertie Ahern has taken a marathon lap of honour to which much attention has been paid.  I congratulate him on his address to the Joint Houses of the US Congress and on being the fourth Taoiseach to do so and on yesterday&rsquo;s opening of the Battle of the Boyne visitors&rsquo; centre.  As we know, Deputy Brian Cowen will announce his Cabinet later today and much attention will be given to the personalities who will make up the Government in the coming months. </P>
        <P>I would not like the departure of the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan, to go without comment or recognition of his time in Government.  He is a man of great courtesy and capacity and will be a serious loss.  I wish him well in his recovery from his illness and congratulate him on what he has achieved to date.</P>
        <P Just="Left">As leader of the Opposition in the Seanad, I wish to point out that the long goodbye to the Taoiseach and the anticipation of a new Government end today.  After today, we must return to normal politics.  We must return to tackling the challenges facing people every day, the challenges of the health service, crime, child care, education, the cost of living and quality of life, all key issues.  For the past number of years we have had the programme for Government held up as what the Government is working towards, but everything has changed now and the programme can no longer take care of  the challenges facing us.</P>
        <P>The Government and the new Cabinet must recognise that tax receipts are down and the programme for Government is not being implemented.  They must stop hiding behind the now defunct programme and bury it.  They must now come to us with new information and a set of clear and immediate indicators of how they will shelter Ireland from the global slowdown, how they will deal with the negative equity affecting many families and young housebuyers, how they will turn the hospital situation around so that patients will no longer be afraid to go into hospital and will have renewed confidence in the health service.</P>
        <P>In the immediate term, we must see action from the new Government on the Lisbon treaty.  If we do not see a strong campaign from the Government, the treaty will be lost.  Such a decision would be an assertion by the people that the Government is out of touch and has not tackled the issue coherently.  I urge the Leader to bring the message to the Government that we on this side of the House want to see an active and strong Government campaign to ensure the Lisbon treaty is passed by the people.  The Government will have our support on the treaty.  Fine Gael has been very active in its efforts to ensure the treaty is passed.</P>
        <P>We want to hear from the new Taoiseach and his Cabinet how they intend to deal with the critical issues I have outlined, issues faced by every family in the country on a daily basis.  There is huge disappointment that the Celtic tiger has not helped people to get better hospital and education services.  Those are the issues this House must discuss.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to speak to the Government about doing whatever it can at European level at the Council of Ministers on the situation in Burma.  It is a terrible tragedy.  Some 20,000 people are known to have died and 40,000 are missing.  I heard Mr. John O&rsquo;Shea of GOAL speak about the difficulty GOAL is having getting aid into the country and asking the Government to use every action it can to try to get the junta in that country to allow aid in.  I ask the Leader to bring the issue to the House and perhaps we could bring a motion before the House.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="539"/>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I join with Senator Fitzgerald in sending good wishes to the retiring Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern.  I did not have the opportunity to praise him in this House.  I listened to some of the ceremony at the Battle of the Boyne site and was very struck by memories which came to mind to which nobody else has referred.  I recalled a moment during a difficult period of the peace process when the Taoiseach said something that attracted the ire of Dr. Ian Paisley, who threw a tantrum and demanded a withdrawal and an abject apology.  It showed an extraordinary degree of statesmanship that the Taoiseach did not allow his self-importance to stand in the way of this and he gave a humble apology.  I would not have had the moral courage to do that, and this was the single event that struck me most about his career.  I also send good wishes to Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan who, as Senator Fitzgerald said, was always a courteous and efficient Minister.  I hope his health continues to improve and that he goes on to other appointments, perhaps in Europe or elsewhere.  I wish the incoming Taoiseach, Deputy Brian Cowen, good fortune.  He is heading into choppy waters financially and we must all support him, as Fine Gael very honourably did in the past on the Tallaght strategy, if he takes the correct decisions.  The situation facing the country is serious.</P>
        <P>I would like to turn to the other issue Senator Fitzgerald raised, namely Burma.  Coincidentally I was at a performance of a play called &ldquo;The Lady of Burma&rdquo; in the Helix theatre by a very brilliant young English playwright of Irish extraction, Mr. Richard Shannon.  It was immensely moving and raised in my priorities the question of Burma.  I had intended to raise it this week but little did I know the tragedy that would hit Burma and its people.  It is very important the Government uses whatever diplomatic muscle it has to ensure aid and personnel are got in.  It is extraordinary when we think back to October last year when we discussed the riots in Burma and the ruthless military efficiency with which the junta mobilised personnel in that country to suppress its own people.  I hope it is able to find similar efficiency in assisting its people and not in repression.  I welcome the fact that it belatedly cancelled the 10 May referendum.  It would have been an insult to any sense of morality or decency if it had gone ahead with that in light of the tragedy that probably involves at least 60,000 people.  We need to examine that situation and I would welcome a discussion on it.</P>
        <P>I have been very closely examining the meteorological reports and analyses, and underneath the incident is the phenomenon of global warming.  There is no doubt that Cyclone Nargis is one of the predicted by-products.  Underneath that is the elephant in the room, the subject nobody will address.  Apparently no moral, political or spiritual leader has the guts to confront the disastrous population explosion that will get worse.  We will have more of these and nincompoops, including people in this House, will say one can create a mathematical model whereby the entire population can be fed.  Perhaps one can, theoretically, in an academy, in a laboratory.  However while we are doing this tragedies will occur, people will starve and there will be a disaster.  Let us look not just at the immediate prospect but the underlying disastrous situation, namely population explosion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlanKelly"><NameTxt>Senator Alan Kelly</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Eamon Ryan, to come to the House to debate mining in this country and particularly the after-effects of the mining industry in the past 50 or 60 years.  There are a number of distressing stories that this House, and the Oireachtas, need to consider.  People&rsquo;s lives are being affected by toxic lead and other substances that were allowed to enter the air in a number of areas throughout the country.  I refer especially to the Silvermines area.  An environmental clean-up is required.  The by-products of the mining industry are affecting people&rsquo;s lives detrimentally and this needs to be addressed.  I ask the Leader to facilitate a discussion on this.  There are other examples of the worrying after-effects of mining, such as those affecting the Ballingarry miners, some of whom have been waiting up to 30 years for <Col N="540"/>compensation for the effects of their work.  Their lives have been detrimentally affected and a number of them are no longer with us.  I hope the Leader can facilitate a discussion on this.</P>
        <P>I request the opportunity to ask the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment what policies are in place for inward investment through IDA Ireland.  I recently attended a meeting with this organisation and I was shocked by its statistics on the numbers of jobs throughout the country and the major differences in the areas of focus for inward investment.  Obviously, investment is aligned with the national spatial strategy.  However, we must be realistic and accept that communities in areas that do not have a hub or gateway are still hoping for inward investment that will provide jobs.  It was confirmed to me that the board of IDA Ireland is to align investment with the spatial strategy.  If this is the case, there are a number of areas, including some not unfamiliar to me and the Cathaoirleach, that will not benefit.  Is there a need for the IDA and the Government to focus on commuter infrastructure, as I was told at this meeting?  We have been told commuting is now a natural way of life, which is something I do not accept.  If this is the case, the Government could at least come out and say it.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader ask the Minister for Health and Children if and when the Teamwork report on acute hospitals will be published?  I have my doubts it will ever be published as it is such a politically sensitive issue.  I do not want to see the report being introduced by stealth as the Hanly report was.  Perhaps the Leader will reply to me on this.  I am concerned about accident and emergency, elderly care and surgical procedures in these hospitals and I am concerned the Teamwork report will be brought in by stealth.</P>
        <P>As one of the Opposition spokespersons on tourism, I wish to be associated with the good wishes expressed by other Members towards the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan.  I wish him well in his retirement.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to be associated with the comments of other Members on the retirement from the Cabinet of Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan.  As a Member of the other House I had the dubious privilege of shadowing him in his capacity as Minister for Social and Family Affairs.  He always had a disarming tactic of agreeing with much of what I had to say and acting on several of the contributions that were made, which in politics is not playing the game at all.  I also had the opportunity of becoming quite familiar with him during our joint incarceration last June when we were negotiating the programme for Government.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Senator still incarcerated?  He is behaving that way.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I was negotiating out of a prison sentence so that others might feel entitled to enjoy that experience.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Is the Senator still in Government?  What about the people across from him?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Boyle did a very good job.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Boyle without interruption, please.  The Senators can meet in Cork and have this debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I have suggested a venue on several occasions.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>We cannot have it in Cork, a Chathaoirligh.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Buttimer is running for heckler of the year.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="541"/>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>I might point out that is not the type of contribution that Deputy Brennan would make in either House, but that is beside the point.</P>
        <P>I also join the comments of other Senators on Burma.  It is important for whoever the Taoiseach decides should have the foreign affairs portfolio as of today that he or she is given the strongest possible message from the House that we would like to see action quickly.  It is fair to say that the developed world has already failed Burma in the last year and now that a natural disaster has occurred, it behoves us to put whatever means are at our disposal to alleviate the distress of that country.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>I, too, would like to be associated with the words of goodwill and good wishes for the Minister, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan.  I found him to be very courteous.  He is a Galway man and I would like his contribution to be noted.</P>
        <P>I call on the Leader to facilitate a cross-departmental debate in this House on the social, personal and health issues affecting young people in this country.  Very important issues such as parenting and the important role that parents play must be addressed.  Drugs and alcohol come under that banner.  The Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children, Deputy Pat Carey, is on a very useful tour around the country at present to see if there is a need for a single strategy for drugs and alcohol.</P>
        <P>Bullying must be examined.  In a recent study of 4,500 young people, 43% said they had been bullied during the current term.  Physical violence had been experienced by 90.  That is a large number of young people experiencing physical violence today in Ireland.</P>
        <P>Regarding suicide, as law makers we must look at a very serious issue, namely, the regulation of social networking sites such as Bebo and Facebook.  I can tell the House that Galway is in shock right now.  A young man took his life at the weekend having left his goodbye note on Bebo written in the past tense.  Bebo and Facebook are making millions in revenue out of young people every year from advertising.  They give nothing back to society or to youth in terms of social infrastructure.  I ask the Minister, gabh mo leithsc&eacute;al, the Leader&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator know something that I do not?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Would the Leader love to be Minister?</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>(Interruptions).</i></P>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>Many are called.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">He would not be the first in the Seanad.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to facilitate a cross-departmental debate.  That would mean bringing to the House the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Mary Hanafin, the Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children, Deputy Pat Carey, and, again, the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Mary Harney.  Let us examine the question of taking responsibility.  As Senator Fitzgerald said, it is now time to move on and address the serious issues affecting our young people.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>Senator Denis O&rsquo;Donovan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I wish to put on the record, briefly, my sadness that our Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern, is moving on today.  There is sadness because of his close connections to west Cork.  His mother hailed from Bantry, his father from Tracton and his grandmother came from Whiddy Island.  In that regard it is a sad day for my part of the world.  I wish him luck in his retirement.  I also add my voice to those who, very properly and <Col N="542"/>magnanimously, spoke from the other side of the House congratulating the Minister, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan, on his success and wishing him luck in his retirement as well.</P>
        <P>I urge the Leader to have a debate on the fishing industry as soon as is practically possible.  I raised this matter in the House before.  Again, I wish to express my serious concern.  Substantial stocks of Irish fish are leaving Irish waters, especially those taken by Spanish fishermen who have quota rights.  I have no faith that the management, controls and policing of the landing of such stocks and quantities of fish are being monitored, particularly in Spain.  This may be a European matter but I believe we need an urgent debate on it because there seems to be over-regulation and excessive policing of Irish fishermen.  Somewhere along the line the strain that causes will have its effect, not alone among fishing communities but on rural Ireland in general.  I am deeply concerned.  I do not believe there are proper controls of the fish taken from our waters, especially in Spain.  It is criminal and unfair and the wrong people, Irish fishermen, are being targeted.</P>
        <P>I call for a debate on rural Ireland.  There is a suggestion that the legal alcohol limit may be further reduced.  I am not advocating drink driving in any way.  As someone who worked in the courts for years, I know the damage that is done.  However, before we react in a knee-jerk fashion on this issue, a proper survey should be undertaken on the effects of such curtailment in rural Ireland.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Even if it must come, a proper rural transport system, which is available in patches throughout rural Ireland, should be buttressed and made more available so that people in remote areas, on peninsulas and on islands do not suffer in the future.  There is far more to people being killed on our roads than alcohol.  Drugs, speed and other attitude problems play a role.  If the alcohol limit was reduced to nil, there would still be deaths on the roads.  I am concerned that such a reduction may have an unnecessary, serious adverse effect on parts of rural Ireland.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I want to see an audit by IDA Ireland of what has been achieved over the past decade of success in the economy in rural towns throughout this country.  Large areas of population such as Cork city, Dublin and Galway have their successes in the creation of jobs.  Parochially, I am concerned about the lack of jobs in places such as Dunmanway in west Cork, Skibbereen and Bantry &mdash; to name those of just one county.  I wonder whether the Minister involved could undertake an audit of what has been achieved and the road plan of the industrial development authority over the next five to ten years for remote rural towns throughout the country.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Visit of Former" RHead="Cathaoirleach"> 
    <Title>Visit of Former Cathaoirleach. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Before I call the next speaker, I welcome into the Distinguished Visitors&rsquo; Gallery former Senator and Cathaoirleach, Brian Mullooly, a long-time Member of this House.  Brian, you are welcome to the House today.  I hope you might give a few tips to the Members on their contributions.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of Business" RHead="(Resumed)"> 
    <Title>Order of Business (Resumed). </Title>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the contributions made by Senators Fitzgerald, Norris and Boyle on Burma.  The television pictures and the radio reports are distressing.  Those of us in the western world have let the people of Burma down badly in the past 18 months.  It behoves the Government, at European Council of Ministers level, to intervene on behalf of them to get emergency aid to the area as a matter of urgency and to get the visa regulations waived so that we can assist them.  That is a matter of extreme urgency and the Leader will find no fault from this side of the House in that regard.</P><Col N="543"/>
        <P>This is a day of new beginnings.  I hope the Leader will manage to appoint a new Minister for Health and Children because the Government has presided over a failed health strategy, illustrated by the fact that yesterday was National Asthma Day and we have no national strategy for asthma.  There are 470,000 people suffering from asthma in this country and Ireland lies fourth in the world asthma league.  It is a shame and an indictment of the people opposite that we do not have a national strategy on asthma.  We need one as a matter of urgency.</P>
        <P>I hope the Leader, who I believe is well in with the new Taoiseach, will keep bringing him cups of tea.  I ask the Leader to bring him to the House so that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>On the Order of Business please, not on cups of tea.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I am on the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>There are no cups of tea.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>We need a debate on the programme for Government, which is a failed document.  Senator Boyle has left the Chamber.  The Green Party is now smug in Government but the mudguard is falling off the bike.  There is no co-ordination, for example, on balanced regional development.  The second city of this country is losing out badly.  I seek an urgent debate on the programme for Government.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>What about the Mullingar accord?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I support Senator O&rsquo;Donovan&rsquo;s call for a debate on community life.  Community life in the ten years of the Celtic tiger boom has been altered by this Government.  We need an urgent debate on community life, not just in rural Ireland but across the country.  People deserve leadership which they have not been getting.  We need an urgent debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn"><NameTxt>Senator Camillus Glynn</NameTxt>
	<P>I join those who paid tribute to the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Brennan, who is not seeking a Cabinet position.  I wish the outgoing Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern, the very best of luck and thank him for all he has done for this country, and I wish Deputy Cowen every success.  The central word will be &ldquo;success&rdquo; because in anything he has touched thus far he has been a great success.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">1 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P>I ask the Leader to invite to the  House the Minister with responsibility for housing.  Over many years the taxpayer has provided fine accommodation for those in need of housing.  People like me are asked every day to exhort the powers that be to bring in legislation which will take definitive control over unruly tenants and neighbours.  This is the exception rather than the rule.  People say there is legislation covering this issue, but it is not working effectively.  There are many people in housing estates who have been advised by the local authority and by the Garda to move out.  Why should a family minding their own business be made to move out, while the troublemaker is allowed to remain?  That is putting the cart before the horse and it is not acceptable.</P>
        <P>I ask that a debate be held on this issue urgently and that the Minister of State, Deputy Batt O&rsquo;Keeffe, bring forward definitive proposals which can tackle what is a serious and growing problem.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PhilPrendergast"><NameTxt>Senator Phil Prendergast</NameTxt>
	<P>Last week I spoke about the dispute involving the Psychiatric Nurses Association and I am very disappointed that the HSE has not made any meaningful attempt to address the substantive issues.  Claims to the Personal Injuries Assessment Board are assessed on the basis of societal norms, but the compensation scheme offered to psychiatric nurses represents just 12%-15% of that norm.  The nurses are not looking for a Rolls Royce <Col N="544"/>compensation scheme, but they are not looking for a yellow pack scheme either, nor do they want to be treated less favourably than any other human being.   I urge the management of the HSE to meet soon, because there will be a further escalation of this action from next Monday.  People that are greatly in need of professional standards of care will be very disadvantaged if this problem is not addressed sooner rather than later.</P>
        <P>There are currently 3,598 children on a waiting list for adolescent psychiatric beds, yet we have only 12 such beds.  The intention is to have 30 beds by the end of 2008.  Those who need emergency treatment are seen and referred, but there are still almost 3,600 on that list.  That is a sad indictment of the state of our health services.  It needs to be addressed because there are people who cannot leave their children out of sight due to a fear of what might happen.  We are constantly talking about suicide and so on, but that is cold comfort for those living with the threat of it at their door.</P>
        <P>I wish the outgoing Minister, Deputy Brennan, all the best and I hope the new Taoiseach will choose a replacement who makes something very special of the Department and will give it a reasonable increase.  The Arts Council has done a great job for the Government and it needs a Minister who will give a realistic re-appraisal of exactly what is going on and who will obtain realistic funding.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I join with the Cathaoirleach in welcoming here today the former Senator Brian Mullooley, after 21 years of service to this House.  We also welcome former Deputy and Senator, Martin Joe O&rsquo;Toole, who is also returning on this very historic day.</P>
        <P>I wish the Taoiseach every success.  He is retiring only as Taoiseach and is not retiring from public life.  He will be prominent in the years ahead.  He has great experience and is one of the most popular leaders this country has ever had.  We are very fortunate in Fianna F&aacute;il to have the calibre of person like Deputy Brian Cowen to replace him.  I am fortunate in being the only Member of this House to have served under six Taoisigh, five of whom were from the Fianna F&aacute;il Party. That is unique, and it is also unique for the Cathaoirleach to be in his position today.  I look forward to the events later in the day.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Senator to address his remarks to the Leader on the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I want to be associated with the best wishes that have been extended to the Minister, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan.  He is a wonderful, brilliant, intelligent Minister and he was a great general secretary of Fianna F&aacute;il who led us to victory in 1977 and was responsible for me being a D&aacute;il candidate that year.  I thank S&eacute;amus for that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I remind the Senator that we are on the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate that but this is a special day, as the Cathaoirleach will acknowledge.</P>
        <P>The commemoration at Arbour Hill this morning was a wonderful occasion and start to the business today.  I compliment Reverend Christopher Jones, Bishop of Elfin, who gave a wonderful homily.  I hope it will be published and distributed throughout the country, as it was a great assessment of where we were, where we are and where we are going.</P>
        <P>I would like to be associated with the comments on Burma.  The Government reacted quickly in pledging &euro;1 million in support, and I know it will give more.  Whatever assistance we give is vitally needed.  It is an international tragedy.</P><Col N="545"/>
        <P Just="Left">Will the Leader request the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Gormley, to at least consider the following possibility, although I am not advocating it to a great extent?  The Lisbon treaty referendum will be held on 12 June.  I ask the Minister to consider using the e-voting system on that day, given that 500 million people will be waiting for the results.  People will be asked to vote &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; or &ldquo;No&rdquo; in the referendum.  It will not be that complicated.  It would be a good occasion on which to use the electronic voting system.  It is a vote on the Twenty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>The equipment would have to be taken out of storage. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government needs to consider this system afresh.  The referendum will be on 12 June, the count will take place on 13 and 14 June and 500 million people will look at our results following the election.  It would be a wonderful indication of our progression if we could give the results one or two hours after the close of polls on the evening of 12 June.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>I want to follow up on Senator Fitzgerald&rsquo;s mention of the Lisbon treaty.  I spoke at a number of Fine Gael public meetings this weekend.  It is evident there is a lack of information and a certain apathy about this treaty and the referendum.  Also, a message has gone out that it would be a disaster &mdash; that was the language used by the Minister of State, Deputy Roche, who is leading the campaign for the Government &mdash; for Europe and for Ireland if this treaty failed.  That frightens people and is considered arrogant because it suggests they have no choice in the matter other than to vote &ldquo;Yes.&rdquo;  It is the wrong approach to the referendum.  It needs to be explained to people what is in the treaty.  The misinformation which has been put out by the &ldquo;No&rdquo; campaign has raised genuine concerns about Europe and certain aspects of it.  They are the genuine concerns with which we have to engage rather than tell people they must vote &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; because to do otherwise would be a disaster for Europe.  The Minister of State has used that language in this House, and it is unfortunate.</P>
        <P>The incoming Taoiseach, Deputy Cowen, has an opportunity to win this referendum, but the message must be changed from one of disaster to one of explanation and sweet reason.  He also might consider changing the Minister of State with responsibility for European affairs who is leading this campaign, given the negative reaction to his approach to date to this referendum.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>He has done excellent work.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I did not intend speaking on the Lisbon treaty but I must say that I listened to the Minister of State, Deputy Roche, speak in this House and I was thrilled with the manner in which he handled the debate here.  He interacted with everybody in the House, he had his finger on the pulse and had a complete understanding of what the Lisbon treaty is about.  After having listened to him, I made the same point to people outside this House, namely, that we are particularly fortunate to have such an erudite and focused Minister leading this campaign.  I am sorry to disagree with Senator Regan because we are neighbours in one way in another part of the country.  I felt I had to say that because I have the opposite view of the Minister of State, Deputy Roche, to that which the Senator expressed.  I have also heard the Minister of State interviewed on radio and television programmes.  He presents a robust message, but he is prepared to listen to every question put.  The use of the word &ldquo;disaster&rdquo; in the event of a &ldquo;No&rdquo; vote was necessary as there was a degree of apathy and lack of interest apparent.  The Minister of State was correct to point out that it is not simply a matter of flipping a coin and voting &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; or &ldquo;No&rdquo;.  The issue is more important than that and the comments were necessary so that people would engage in the debate at this stage.  The comments of Senator Eugene Regan have been helpful, too, in focusing attention on the issue.</P><Col N="546"/>
        <P Just="Left">I join in the good wishes expressed to the outgoing Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan.  We were fortunate recently to have the Minister in the House for the debate on tourism, which I found helpful.  I pay tribute to him because in my experience Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan throughout the years has been especially quiet but at the same time very energised with any portfolio which he held.  He was always accessible and available for discussions.  His most recent portfolio, namely, the Department of Arts, Sport and Tourism includes the inspirational aspects of the work of the State and Deputy Brennan has handled these so well.  I wish him well and I am sure we will hear more of him in some other context and in another forum in future.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I too welcome the former Cathaoirleach, Mr. Brian Mullooly.  I was delighted to see him looking so well.  He set a great standard in the House which has been followed by other Cathaoirligh since then.</P>
        <P>I, too, congratulate the Taoiseach on his achievements in office and wish him well for the next stage in his career.  I was in Washington during the visit of the Taoiseach last week and was very impressed by what I saw.  He made a wonderful speech to the Joint Houses of Congress and I attended two other speeches that he made on the visit.  I do not know if he made other speeches but the impact he made, the influence he had and part of the reason we have been so successful in reaching agreement in Northern Ireland is because of the personal contacts of the Taoiseach and his interaction with individuals, which was apparent on the visit especially with Ms Nancy Pelosi, the speaker of the House of Representatives.  This relationship is only one of a number the Taoiseach has been able to cultivate and which have been invaluable to Ireland.</P>
        <P>I was unaware of the illness to the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan, and was disappointed to hear of it.  As Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; said, he has been very efficient and competent in the roles he has undertaken, but he also has a great sense of humour.  There were at least three occasions when I spoke to introduce him and he said that he always liked to speak after me as it was not necessary to lower the microphone.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader draw to the attention of the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, whoever he or she will be, the concerns of relatives of missing children, especially those in Europe?  I am aware of one instance where the relatives of one missing child in a European country found that the Schengen information system was not in operation.  This is a system set up by the police forces of the various countries and when someone is sought, either a missing person or a criminal, the information is passed to all the other police forces covered by the Schengen information system.  I know of one case where this information was not passed on.  If we allow one child to slip through the net, there may be others.  I do not know how the system works but the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform should take an interest in this matter to ensure that the Schengen information system between the police forces is in operation to ensure we do not have a situation where children continue to go missing.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdredeBurca"><NameTxt>Senator D&eacute;irdre de B&uacute;rca</NameTxt>
	<P>As with other speakers, I record my concern about the humanitarian crisis in Burma.  I agree with Senator David Norris who mentioned climate change and the fact that cyclones which have killed more than 22,000 people to date are clearly linked to the phenomenon of global warming.  It is likely we will see such humanitarian crises recurring across the globe in the coming decades.</P>
        <P>The Lisbon treaty was mentioned and one of its provisions deals with the establishment of a European voluntary humanitarian aid corps.  This will be a positive development which will develop the civilian capabilities and assets of the European Union as well as the military assets <Col N="547"/>which are more familiar to most people.  This will be a role which the European Union more than likely will be called upon to play on an increasingly regular basis in the future and which we should encourage people to support.</P>
        <P>I ask that the incoming Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food be invited to address the House on the important issue of agriculture.  I make this request in light of a recent report which was sponsored by the United Nations, had the backing of the World Bank and was part-funded by a number of large biotechnology companies.  The report studied the future of world agriculture.  Four hundred scientists participated in the compilation of the report.  It took four years to complete and is a comprehensive examination of global agriculture.  One of its findings was on the issue of GM.  The debate about genetically modified foods has been heated.  GM has been discussed in the context of increasing food yields.  The findings of this report suggested that GMOs do not offer any real potential for increasing food yields for parts of the world where hunger and starvation are serious problems.  It would be important to address this issue of GM in any debate on agriculture because it is an issue that is slipping in the back door and farmers are being encouraged to think of GM crops as being some kind of magic fix for some of the food problems and food shortages we will face in the future.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaudieCoffey"><NameTxt>Senator Paudie Coffey</NameTxt>
	<P>I have listened on many occasions to Members from all sides of the House criticising the HSE and the services it often does not deliver.  This happened again today and I concur with Senator Prendergast&rsquo;s views on the psychiatric services where there is a significant deficit.  </P>
        <P>The Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Mary Harney, once referred to the HSE as a big ship that would not be turned overnight and how right she is.  I remind the Minister of who it was created, constructed and designed this ship, namely, the HSE.  It is certainly a ship that is overburdened with administration.  I do not think there were any voluntary redundancies; instead many new administrative grades were created.  It is costing a fortune to maintain and run the HSE.  Professor Drumm has been appointed captain of the ship but it seems to be going around in circles.  It is rudderless and going nowhere and it is certainly not reaching the people it should, namely, the citizens of this State.  They are stranded without the services they deserve.  It is lurching from crisis to crisis.  I refer to the record of misdiagnosis of cancer, trolleys in wards and the lack of psychiatric services.  Members on all sides of the House agree that it is unaccountable, it lacks transparency and we are not getting the service we deserve from it.  I ask the Leader to arrange a debate not on the services but on the HSE&rsquo;s structures and how it was put together.</P>
        <P>There is a job of work to be done.  I am not sure of the figure but more than 100,000 people are employed in the HSE.  Many of those very good people work on the front line.  I feel sorry for those people, the nurses, doctors, physiotherapists, who are delivering a service on the front line and who are criticised in public fora such as this.  I feel sorry for those people because they are overburdened and overworked.  We need to look under the stones of the HSE and find where the real inefficiencies lie.  I appeal to the Leader to invite whoever is the Minister for Health and Children to the House to debate the structures of the HSE and to see if a better model can be found which is more effective and more responsive to the needs of this country.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I endorse the call for a debate on the marine made by my colleague, Senator Denis O&rsquo;Donovan.  The Leader may not know that I raised this issue last week because he was busy with international duties supporting the Taoiseach.  I suggested we should have issues pertaining to the marine brought under one remit.  This request for a debate was gracefully refused by the Cathaoirleach on the basis of a lack of ministerial responsibility&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>No direction. </P>
    <HtmlBk SectId="2" />
    </Speaker><Col N="548"/><!--Fix-->
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I was asking that this time around, the Leader of the House might bring it to the attention of the new Taoiseach that the House has an interest in the marine and that we would like all matters related to it consolidated under one Minister.  The Minister for Transport should come to the House in the near future to discuss this issue, which is of particular interest to me.</P>
        <P>I wish to acknowledge the extremely significant events of yesterday.  Anybody with an awareness of the history of this island could not have imagined a decade ago the variety of people who stood yesterday on the site of the Battle of the Boyne, with the Taoiseach leading the welcome to communities from throughout the island.  When the Taoiseach-elect, Deputy Brian Cowen, is <i>in situ</i>, I ask that the Leader invite him to the House as soon as possible for a discussion on how to consolidate the continuing efforts to build relations between the peoples of this island.  The Taoiseach made the point that the manner in which we respect the views of others, particularly minorities, will determine what life is like for the citizens of this island in the coming years.  We generally consider the issue of accommodating minorities as one that is relevant to Northern Ireland.  However, there are other minorities on this island and we must find some way of embracing the opportunities and challenges this presents.  Our discussion with the new Taoiseach should consider the links &mdash; cross-Border, cross-community, in education and so on &mdash; that will facilitate the growing mutual respect among all the peoples on this island that was fostered by the Taoiseach.</P>
        <P>I join in the good wishes extended to the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Brennan, on his decision to step down from office.  I knew him well in his role as Government Chief Whip when I was a Member of the other House.  He has done much good work in the areas of arts and tourism.  I agree with Senator Prendergast that the Arts Council must continue to develop its role in the future.  However, we must acknowledge that the significant increases in funding for the Arts Council are yielding results.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I concur with the points made by other Senators on the situation in Burma.  I assure the Minister for Foreign Affairs that we will be supportive of any measures he takes to alleviate the hardship in that country.</P>
        <P>I congratulate Sean McSharry, the ten year old who has become the youngest European to conquer Mount Kilimanjaro.  I am aware of the difficulties he faced because I reached the summit in January.  I nearly killed myself in the process.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>It is good for us all that such a fate did not befall Senator Hannigan.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>Sean McSharry&rsquo;s feat bodes well for the incoming Taoiseach.  The day before the coronation of Queen Elizabeth II in 1952, Edmund Hillary made the first conquest of Mount Everest.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>He did not do so alone.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LiamTwomeyIND"><NameTxt>Senator Liam Twomey</NameTxt>
	<P>Was Senator White there with him?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>Queen Elizabeth II has enjoyed a long and happy reign.  I wonder whether the incoming Taoiseach, Deputy Cowen, will enjoy the same.  We hope his reign will be good for the people of Ireland but I am sure he will forgive me when I express the hope that it is not as long as that of Queen Elizabeth II.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="549"/>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Senator Ann Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the former Cathaoirleach, Mr. Brian Mullooly, to the Chamber.  It is always good to see former colleagues visiting the House.  I hope I will do the same when my day comes.</P>
        <P>I endorse the points made by colleagues in regard to the crisis in Burma.  The debate on the Lisbon treaty affords us an opportunity to discuss the EU&rsquo;s role in providing humanitarian aid.  We must work closely with Europe in the context of globalisation and climate change.  This is an area to which we should give careful attention.</P>
        <P>I have observed the work being done by the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs, Deputy Roche, to promote the Lisbon treaty.  There is no doubt he is making an impact.  I recently attended a meeting at which he explained himself clearly.  Everybody who attended that large meeting came away satisfied that he had outlined exactly what is expected of us in regard to the referendum campaign.</P>
        <P>I am sorry to see the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Brennan, stepping down from office because of ill health.  I have known the Minister for more than 25 years.  I began my political life working with him in the constituency of Dublin South, where I stood alongside him in four elections.  I know his workload, efficiency and effectiveness. He has tremendous ability in terms of organisation.  He is stepping down just for a short term.  I wish him a speedy recovery and I have no doubt he will be back with us in a short time, perhaps in another role.</P>
        <P>I congratulate the outgoing Taoiseach and wish him well in the next stage of his career.  I wish the new Taoiseach every success and look forward to seeing him in this House when he comes in to debate whatever issues are pertinent at the time and I look forward to our working closely with him on those issues.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The time is practically up and a number of speakers are offering.  I ask Members to be brief and I will try to allow in the few who are left.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PearseDoherty"><NameTxt>Senator Pearse Doherty</NameTxt>
	<P>Listening to the debate, some of those on the &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; side of the Lisbon treaty are starting the blame game already although we are 50 days away from the referendum.  Some are blaming the Government for not doing enough, others are blaming the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs, Deputy Dick Roche, and want him sacked from leading the campaign, while others say we should use a flawed and unsafe electronic voting system to count the votes just in case we cannot get rid of the Government and the Minister of State, Deputy Dick Roche, in the meantime.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Senator Paddy Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>We need the Minister of State, Deputy Dick Roche.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PearseDoherty"><NameTxt>Senator Pearse Doherty</NameTxt>
	<P>The reality is that people on the &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; side are beginning to understand that the misinformation being issued will not wash.  We heard misinformation from the previous speaker that it is all about climate change.  The Lisbon treaty is not all about climate change.  Six words that have been inserted by the Irish Government into a massive document deal with climate change.  The Lisbon treaty is about other issues.  I welcome the fact that the Technical Engineering and Electrical Union this week has called for a &ldquo;No&rdquo; vote in the Lisbon treaty.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader facilitate a debate, to which he agreed two weeks ago, on the issue of school secretaries and caretakers, some of whom are paid less than the minimum wage?  They are in Donegal, Sligo, Limerick and other regions.  Many school secretaries and caretakers are unable to avail of the benefits under the Department of Education and Science scheme.</P>
        <P>I support the call for a debate on the fishing industry.  It is important to have that debate not only for the larger vessels but also because of the impact on the driftnet and draftnet salmon <Col N="550"/>fishermen who have been put out of business since the decision of the Government last year.  The Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Deputy Mary Coughlan, is tipped for promotion within the Cabinet this evening.  As a Donegal Senator I wish her well.  I hope she signs a statutory instrument that will bring to an end the criminalisation of the fishermen before she leaves that office, if indeed she does.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I endorse the call by other Senators in regard to Burma.  I urge the Department of Foreign Affairs to press the EU and the United Nations to urge the military junta to allow aid workers and non-governmental organisations into the country to help with the disaster relief and to issue visas as soon as possible to NGOs in Ireland such as GOAL and Concern.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Yesterday was an historic day.  I joined my party partly because of our policies on Northern Ireland which was the reunification of our country by peaceful means and with the consent of the majority in Northern Ireland.  That was at a time when some in Fianna F&aacute;il wrestled with the whole area of peaceful means and constitutional politics, whether it was right or not.  The area of consent certainly was heresy at that time.  That is why I believe yesterday was an historic day.  We heard a Fianna F&aacute;il Taoiseach speak of respecting the traditions of each area of the country and living in peace and harmony on this island.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>He did not just speak about it; he created it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I make those remarks not to score any political points but because it is an area of which the Taoiseach should be justifiably proud.  In that context I ask the Leader for a debate on Northern Ireland within the next few weeks or so.  This is an opportune time to have such a debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister is waiting since 1.30 p.m. and we must conclude at 2 p.m.  The Minister is not available after 2 p.m.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I can call the Leader to reply but there are a few speakers offering.  The reason I allowed some time was that tributes were being paid to someone who is retiring.  I will call three final speakers.  It will not be possible to allow other Senators to contribute.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>Today is a historic day on which we bid farewell to one era and usher in a new one.  I join my colleagues in thanking the outgoing Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern, for all he has done.  His greatest legacy will be to have brought peace to the island of Ireland.  I also welcome the new Taoiseach, Deputy Brian Cowen, who, like the Cathaoirleach, is an Offaly man.  Many people from the county are in and around the grounds of Leinster House today.  </P>
        <P>A number of terms capture the character of the new Taoiseach.  He is an inspirational figure, an extremely energetic motivator and a man of exceptional organisational skills.  I wish him well in the office of Taoiseach.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State at the Department of the Taoiseach, Deputy Dick Roche, who was before the House last week, is also an energetic man and an enthusiastic proponent of the Lisbon treaty.  He has explained the text to members of the public and politicians and we should stand behind him.  He is doing an excellent job and deserves our full support.</P>
        <P>Yesterday, 250 Irish businesses, members of the Business Alliance for Europe, publicly endorsed the Lisbon treaty.  These companies represent 2.1 million Irish employees.  Senators <Col N="551"/>should consider how the House can be used to better promote the referendum due in four weeks.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to be associated with the tributes paid to the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan, who will retire today.  The Minister played a positive and constructive role in politics and was always amenable to accepting suggestions made by the Opposition.  Several years ago, for example, he accepted my proposal to change the term &ldquo;old age pension&rdquo; to &ldquo;State pension&rdquo;.  While it may not have been an issue of great significance, it demonstrated his ability to listen to Opposition voices.  I hope he enjoys many more years in other political roles.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to reflect again on the need for an urgent debate on the World Trade Organisation talks.  In recent days, Commissioner Mandelson has issued a further unhelpful statement in which he underplayed what he is determined to do to Irish agriculture.  Not only is he the greatest threat to the passing of the referendum on the Lisbon treaty, he is also a major threat to the future of Irish agriculture and tens of thousands of jobs.  Given that &ldquo;veto&rdquo; is the only word he understands, the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, whether Deputy Mary Coughlan or her successor, must indicate his or her willingness to stop the destructive Mandelson proposals.</P>
        <P>I agree with the suggestion made by several speakers, including Senator Buttimer, that the new Taoiseach be invited to the House to outline his policies on a broad range of issues.  Senator Fitzgerald noted the issues facing the Government.  The Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern, made a valedictory address to the House several weeks ago.  It would be interesting and informative if the new Taoiseach were to come to the House at the earliest possible date to outline his proposals and policies.  I ask the Leader to raise the issue at the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LiamTwomeyIND"><NameTxt>Senator Liam Twomey</NameTxt>
	<P>With the eyes of 500 million Europeans upon us, the only disaster likely to befall us on 12 June would be if we brought the electronic voting machines out of storage.  They are best left alone and we should stick to pen and paper for the referendum.  </P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Donovan has taken a consistent and correct position on an important issue on which there is cross-party agreement, namely, fisheries.  Serious problems have emerged in this area, one of our greatest natural resources.  Despite the publication of the Cawley report on fishing, little action has been taken to protect our fisheries, both inland and at sea.  Provided it is protected and conserved, the fishing resource renews itself.  Fisheries could become an even larger economic sector if we protected them properly.  I call on the Leader to arrange a debate on fisheries.</P>
        <P>I extend my best wishes to the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan, on his retirement today.  The self-congratulation we have heard from the Government benches in this House and the Other House for the past month will have to stop tomorrow to allow the Government to get back to business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>I, too, wish to be associated with the well-deserved tributes to the outgoing Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern, and the outgoing Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan.  In their dealings with Members from all sides and in the performance of their duties in both Houses I have always found both men to be conscientious and diligent.  I wish them well in future.</P>
        <P>When does the Leader expect the designated land Bill, which is intended to curb the exorbitant cost of land, particularly for public projects, to be published?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I apologise to Senator Francis O&rsquo;Brien whom I overlooked.  </P>
      </Speaker><Col N="552"/>
      <Speaker pid="FrancisOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Francis O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>I join other speakers in extending good wishes to the Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern, and Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan.  Yesterday, when the Taoiseach met the First Minister, Dr. Ian Paisley, at the Battle of the Boyne site, was a great day for Ireland.  I was one of the lucky few to be present and it was wonderful to be there.  It was a wonderful day for all the people of this country, North and South.  I extend my best wishes to the incoming Taoiseach, Deputy Brian Cowen.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Many Senators expressed their appreciation of the great efforts made by the outgoing Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern, on behalf of the country.  I was honoured to represent the Seanad in the House of Representatives in Washington last Wednesday.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader was well observed. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Allow the Leader to continue without interruption. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>It was an experience I will never forget.  The Taoiseach made a tremendous contribution and wonderful speech.  The event attended yesterday by the outgoing Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern, and outgoing First Minister, the Reverend Ian Paisley, at the Battle of the Boyne site will make its mark for generations to come.</P>
        <P>I worked closely with the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy S&eacute;amus Brennan, particularly in the period from 1997 to 2002 when I was a member of the legislation committee, which the Minister established at the time to streamline the priorities of Ministers and the business of both Houses.  The committee was also the instrument used to enable a large proportion of legislation to be initiated in the Seanad.  Deputy Brennan has a great intellect and is a wonderful person to work with.  His terrific ability has been underestimated.  I wish him well and look forward to working with him again.  I also welcome the incoming Taoiseach, a near neighbour and lifelong friend, Deputy Brian Cowen.</P>
        <P>A large number of pressing issues were raised by Senators.  However, the Minister of State is waiting to come before the House and I gave him my word the House would try to complete our consideration of the Twenty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution Bill 2008 before 2 p.m.  With the permission of the House, I propose to respond tomorrow morning to all other matters raised.  I ask the leaders to meet me after the Order of Business to agree an all-party motion on the tragedy experienced by the people of Burma.   I thank Senators for their understanding on this special day.</P>
        <P>I welcome former Senator, Mr. Brian Mullooly to the House.  He and the late Senator Se&aacute;n Fallon taught me most of what I learned in the Seanad.  It was a great honour and privilege to serve under his stewardship and it is lovely to see him on this important day.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="An Bille um an Ocht&uacute; Leas&uacute; is Fiche ar na mBunreacht" RHead="2008: An Tuarasc&aacute;il agus an Ch&eacute;im Dheiridh"> 
    <Title>An Bille um an Ocht&uacute; Leas&uacute; is Fiche ar an mBunreacht 2008: An Tuarasc&aacute;il agus an Ch&eacute;im Dheiridh. </Title>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Twenty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution" RHead="Bill 2008: Report and Final Stages"> 
    <Title>Twenty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution Bill 2008: Report and Final Stages.  </Title>
        <P>Tuairisc&iacute;odh an Bille gan leas&uacute; chun an breithni&uacute; deiridh a dh&eacute;anamh air.</P>
        <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
        <P>Tairgeadh an cheist: &ldquo;Go rithfear an Bille anois.&rdquo;</P>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P><Col N="553"/>
      <Speaker pid="AnnOrmonde"><NameTxt>Senator Ann Ormonde</NameTxt>
	<P>I congratulate the Minister of State, Deputy Roche, and wish him well over the next couple of weeks.  I assure him I will work closely with all the groups to which I have been assigned.  We will win this referendum.  Some 160 of the 166 Deputies and most Senators are working to have it passed.  If we all put our shoulders to wheel, we will get it passed.  I wish the Minister of State well in taking the lead and in fronting this campaign.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State and his officials for bringing this legislation forward.  It is of paramount importance that the referendum is passed on 12 June.  Most of us will be out on the hustings over the next four to five weeks to convince the people that a &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote is the right thing for this country and for Europe.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DeirdredeBurca"><NameTxt>Senator D&eacute;irdre de B&uacute;rca</NameTxt>
	<P>I acknowledge the work the Minister of State has done to date in promoting the Lisbon treaty.  This needs to be a priority for all of us.  The new Cabinet will be announced today and we should all focus on putting all the very positive aspects of the Lisbon treaty to the public because there has been much misinformation about, and misinterpretation of, some of the provisions of the treaty.  It is up to all of us, including high profile Ministers, to push the treaty as much as possible in order that there will be no doubt in people&rsquo;s minds when they go to vote on 12 June that voting for the treaty is the right thing to do for Ireland.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I congratulate the Minister of State on the work he has put into having this Bill passed with such speed.  I was unable to be here last week for the debate but I heard that he was able to respond and be sympathetic to the views even of those opposed to the Bill.  I congratulate the Minister of State on the passing of this Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlanKelly"><NameTxt>Senator Alan Kelly</NameTxt>
	<P>Speaking on behalf of the Labour Party, I am glad this Bill has been speedily passed.  I echo what Senators have said in that it is important that following today&rsquo;s events, the Government settles down and pushes the referendum as much as possible in a very concrete way.  The Minister of State can be assured that the Labour Party will support the treaty 100% and will run an energetic campaign throughout the country.  We will provide whatever support is requested from us.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>Unfortunately, I did not have the opportunity to speak on the Bill but I put on record my strong support for the Minister of State&rsquo;s proposals.  I congratulate him on his efforts and his personal commitment to Europe which we have seen down through the years.  The Minister of State knows as well as I do that he, his Government colleagues and the rest of us face a difficult task ensuring the passage of the Lisbon treaty.  There is no issue of greater importance to the people than the passing of the Lisbon treaty to ensure Europe works better and that Ireland continues to play a very strong role and benefits from its role in Europe.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Almost daily we hear and read much about the US presidential election which is of some significance to us but is insignificant when compared with the debate and vote on the Lisbon treaty.  We must focus attention on that and I offer my full support to the Minister of State.</P>
        <P>The farming community feels angry and threatened, although it would be the first to acknowledge that Irish agriculture has benefited enormously as a result of EU membership and can benefit to the same degree in the future.  The World Trade Organisation talks are a separate issue but, unfortunately, politics brings events together and those talks are bearing down in a very negative way on what those in rural Ireland and the farming community are thinking.  It is incumbent on the Minister of State, the Government and the new Taoiseach to give the strongest possible reassurance not only to the farmers but to the hundreds of thousands of people in rural Ireland whose jobs are so dependent on agriculture.</P><Col N="554"/>
        <P>We must use every opportunity to reiterate that we will not allow Commissioner Mandelson to pressure the Government and the European Commission.  We have one window of opportunity, which will last for a few weeks at most, and we must insist that the Mandelson proposals are not forced through.  We must be willing to use the veto and to show our power in Brussels.  It is a major issue in regard to this treaty vote, although I know there are many others.</P>
        <P>I wish the Minister of State well.  He will have the support of the majority of this House and the other one.  As he said previously,  the same forces said &ldquo;No&rdquo; in 1973 and during the debates on the Maastricht and Amsterdam treaties and they are wrong again.  It is very important that Ireland votes &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; and that all of us apply our political weight to support the Minister of State and the Government in having this referendum passed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DickRoche"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Dick Roche</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank Senators from all sides who participated in this debate.  Picking up the points made by Senators Kelly and Bradford, there is nothing before the people over the next four weeks which is more important than this issue.  We will make a decision not only for ourselves but for 500 million other people.  We will make a decision which will not result in the world coming to an end on 12 June but which could make things work much better for us beyond that date.  Picking up the final points made by Senator Bradford, it is critically important we deal with the fact the World Trade Organisation talks and the Lisbon treaty are two separate issues, and I will refer to that in a moment.</P>
        <P>I am very grateful to the Opposition parties, in particular, for their support for the Bill in this and the other House because this is an issue which should unite us all and which goes to the heart of our well-being and our future.  If Europe works well and prospers, Ireland undoubtedly prospers too.  However, if Europe falls behind and if it is forced to continue to operate and to struggle on with decision-making processes which have been in place for 50 years, it will not prosper.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The debate has underlined the widespread support for Europe which exists in this country.  The Lisbon treaty will provide for benefits to continue to flow to Ireland, despite what the detractors of the treaty say.  To set ourselves apart from our 26 European Union partners by rejecting this treaty would be a highly risky move, especially at a time of global economic uncertainty when an effective European Union has such a key role to play in promoting the shared interests of all the people of Europe.  An effective European Union is critical to this country.</P>
        <P>Following our work today, the people will have their say in the referendum.  The Government has worked very hard to produce a number of informative balanced documents, an explanatory pamphlet, a detailed White Paper and a 24-page bilingual guide, which is being delivered house to house.  Phenomenal work has also been done by the Forum on Europe and we now have the Referendum Commission with a &euro;5 million budget and a specific remit to explain the facts.</P>
        <P>Our vote next month is vital, but not simply because the rest of Europe is watching.  That is not a good reason to vote one way or the other.  It is vital because the decision we take on 12 June will send a message about us to international investment decision makers observing us.  It will send a message about what we believe about ourselves and our future in Europe.  Our decision is vital because it tells us something about ourselves.  I believe our decision will show the Irish people retain their underlying positive attitude towards Europe.  It will confirm the view of the people that our interests as a nation lie in a vote of confidence in the Union.  It will show also, despite or perhaps because of the insecurities and uncertainties that exist, that the people know we can best forward our interests in concert with our European neighbours.</P><Col N="555"/>
        <P>It is vital that on 12 June we vote about facts, the future and not just the past.  I say this because I believe past performance is the best indicator of future behaviour.  I find it difficult to understand the conspiracy theories that somehow or other suggest there is someone in the European Union lying in wait to ambush us and do us injury.  The European Union has done nothing but good for the country and being part of and at the heart of Europe has done nothing but good for the country.  We have become a self-confident, progressive, dynamic economy because we are at the heart of Europe.</P>
        <P>There is a need to respond to those events that have inspired the 27 European member governments to agree the Lisbon treaty.  Eleven members have already ratified the treaty.  In those countries where ratification has taken place, the process has been overwhelmingly positive.  The vote for the treaty in the European Parliament has also been overwhelmingly positive.  The vote of confidence in 27 sovereign governments has been unanimous.</P>
        <P>We all know that Europe&rsquo;s future well-being and prosperity cannot and should not be taken for granted.  We know there are challenges facing us today which Europeans can ill afford to shirk.  Globalisation, decent employment, climate change, energy security and mass migration are only some of the challenges we face as we go into the 21st century.  We cannot hope to deal with these challenges alone.  Not one of the 27 countries in the Union can resolve these problems on its own.  However, there is genuine hope that all our interests will be better reflected if we combine our efforts to deal with the challenges.  The reform treaty will help us do this.  It will make the Union more effective and democratic and ensure equality of treatment between member states exists as a reality.  It will ensure the vital national interests of each member state are recognised and respected.  The Government accepts that the treaty is complex in format.  In this respect it is no different from any other treaty.  However, its aims are simple: a more efficient, more effective and more democratic Europe.</P>
        <P>I encourage members of all political parties to engage as strongly as possible in this vital debate on the future of Ireland and its future in Europe.  We have a duty to do this, all the more so because of the unprecedented level of misinformation and confusion being sown about the treaty.  Not all of that confusion or misinformation originated within our island or State.  Eurosceptic media from another island are attempting to achieve a purpose they could not achieve on their own island in our debate.  We listened last night on one of our radio programmes to a eurosceptic, a former Cabinet Minister from another Administration, saying he felt he had the right to ask the Irish people to vote &ldquo;No&rdquo; on his behalf.  We spent 800 years getting to a point where we can determine our future.  It is up to him to look after his future within his jurisdiction.</P>
        <P>We have a responsibility not to allow arguments to prevail that have no foundation in the facts of the treaty.  Never before have we witnessed such an assault on the Union or on any organisation which Ireland has willingly joined.  In this debate, we have witnessed tactics and tabloid coverage of a variety which is out of step with past Irish norms.  The electorate has been told by opponents of the treaty that it would abolish referenda.  That is not the case and the people who put forward that argument know it is not the truth.  The people have been told this treaty will end our national control on corporation tax.  Opponents of the treaty have argued recently they never said the treaty would get rid of our veto but that it would damage it.</P>
        <P>Opponents of the treaty have made extraordinary claims about Article 113, in particular about five words that have been added to the end of that article.  They should take the time and the trouble to read that article.  Even the busiest of businessmen must have time to read six and a half lines.  If not, he should read the first five words of Article 113 which make it clear that the Council, when making decisions in this area, will make decisions by unanimity.  Therefore, the veto is protected.  What is even more damning in terms of the analysis is that <Col N="556"/>people say they are worried about Article 113 having effect on our corporation tax.  Article 113 specifically refers to indirect taxation.  The additional words, therefore, do not have the connotation or outcome being suggested.</P>
        <P>What disturbs me most is the suggestion being made to good and decent people that if they vote &ldquo;Yes&rdquo;, this will allow abortion or abortion services to be introduced in Ireland.  Many charges could be made that would irritate me but this one irritates me above all.  Of all the untruths being told in respect of the treaty, this is the untruth I find most distressing.  I have told the House previously that I am opposed to abortion but I respect the fact that others have different views.  I happen to be a practising Christian and I believe this is not the way forward.  I respect the fact that people have other opinions.  However, it is wrong for people to set out to mislead the people and suggest that somehow or other we will lose the protection we have in our Constitution because of this treaty.  This is a detestable tactic.  I want to see factual debate on the issues in the coming weeks.</P>
        <P>I respect the fact there are people who believe we should not be in Europe.  Of course there are people with a view different from mine and as a democrat I respect that.  However, there is a responsibility on us all that if we are conducting debate, it should be calm, accurate, dignified and, above all, truthful.  I am convinced the people will weigh up the arguments and decide to renew their faith in the voluntary European project which has helped us to increase our prosperity.  It has provided an environment in which our children could find work at home.  It created some of the conditions for peace to blossom on this island.  It has increased our own control over many aspects of our lives and has respected our national traditions and interests.</P>
        <P>Fate more than choice has placed the key to Europe&rsquo;s future in the hands of the Irish people.  We are the only people who will be asked to vote individually on the treaty.  We should continue with what we know &mdash; a successful formula which has served the country and the people well.  We should not contemplate rejecting the treaty for no discernible national advantage.  We should stick with the European Union and with the course in Europe we have mapped for ourselves over 35 years.  We have several times been urged to turn our backs on Europe, for example, to reject the Single European Act, to reject the Maastricht treaty or the treaties of Amsterdam and Nice.  On each of those occasions the people voted &ldquo;Yes&rdquo;, Europe benefited and Ireland gained.  The same choice faces us now on 12 June.  This is a major decision about our future and Europe&rsquo;s future.  We need to get it right.  The &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote is not just the best vote to make, but the only vote that will serve Ireland&rsquo;s purpose, Europe&rsquo;s future, and the future of all of our people.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Cuireadh agus aonta&iacute;odh an cheist.</P>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="R&aacute;iteas faoi Eolas do V&oacute;t&aacute;laithe:" RHead="Tairiscint"> 
    <Title>R&aacute;iteas faoi Eolas do V&oacute;t&aacute;laithe: Tairiscint. </Title>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Statement for Information of Voters:" RHead="Motion"> 
    <Title>Statement for Information of Voters: Motion. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Tairgim:</P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;GO nd&eacute;anfar an r&aacute;iteas at&aacute; leagtha amach sa Sceideal a ghabhann leis an R&uacute;n seo a fhorord&uacute; mar eolas do v&oacute;t&aacute;laithe de bhun alt 23 d&rsquo;Acht an Reifrinn 1994 (Uimh. 12 de 1994), i nd&aacute;il leis an togra chun Airteagal 29 den Bhunreacht a leas&uacute;, at&aacute; ar &aacute;ireamh sa Bhille um an Ocht&uacute; Leas&uacute; is Fiche ar an mBunreacht 2008, agus is &aacute;bhar do reifreann bunreachta.</P><Col N="557"/>
             <P Just="Center">An Sceideal</P>
        <P FLI="1">1. Is &eacute; at&aacute; beartaithe leis an mBille um an Ocht&uacute; Leas&uacute; is Fiche ar an mBunreacht 2008&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>a</i>) na fo-ailt seo a leanas a chur isteach i ndiaidh fho-alt 10º d&rsquo;alt 4 d&rsquo;Airteagal 29 den Bhunreacht:</P>
        <P LI="3">&lsquo;10&deg; Tig leis an St&aacute;t Conradh Liosp&oacute;in ag leas&uacute; an Chonartha ar an Aontas Eorpach agus an Chonartha ag bun&uacute; an Chomhphobail Eorpaigh, arna sh&iacute;ni&uacute; i Liosp&oacute;in an 13&uacute; l&aacute; de Nollaig 2007, a dhaingni&uacute; agus tig leis a bheith ina chomhalta den Aontas Eorpach a bhuna&iacute;tear de bhua an Chonartha sin.</P>
        <P LI="3">11&deg; N&iacute; dh&eacute;anann aon fhor&aacute;il at&aacute; sa Bhunreacht seo dl&iacute;the a d&rsquo;achtaigh, gn&iacute;omhartha a rinne n&oacute; bearta a ghlac an St&aacute;t, de bh&iacute;thin riachtanais na noibleag&aacute;id&iacute; mar chomhalta den Aontas Eorpach d&aacute; dtagra&iacute;tear i bhfoalt 10&deg; den alt seo, a chur &oacute; bhail dl&iacute; n&aacute; cosc a chur le dl&iacute;the a d&rsquo;achtaigh, gn&iacute;omhartha a rinne n&oacute; bearta a ghlac an tAontas Eorpach sin n&oacute; institi&uacute;id&iacute; de, n&oacute; comhlachta&iacute; at&aacute; inni&uacute;il faoi na conartha&iacute; d&aacute; dtagra&iacute;tear san alt seo, &oacute; fheidhm dl&iacute; a bheith acu sa St&aacute;t.</P>
        <P LI="3">12&deg; Tig leis an St&aacute;t na roghnuithe n&oacute; na roghanna a fheidhmi&uacute; a shocra&iacute;tear le hAirteagail 1.22, 2.64, 2.65, 2.66, 2.67, 2.68 agus 2.278 den Chonradh d&aacute; dtagra&iacute;tear i bhfo-alt 10&deg; den alt seo agus le hAirteagail 1.18 agus 1.20 de Phr&oacute;tacal Uimh. 1 at&aacute; i gceangal leis an gConradh sin, n&oacute; a shocra&iacute;tear faoi na hAirteagail sin, ach beidh aon fheidhmi&uacute; den s&oacute;rt sin faoi r&eacute;ir cead&uacute; a fh&aacute;il roimh r&eacute; &oacute; dh&aacute; Theach an Oireachtais.</P>
        <P LI="3" Just="Left">13&deg; Tig leis an St&aacute;t an roghn&uacute; a fheidhmi&uacute; chun a &aacute;irithi&uacute;, i nd&aacute;il leis an bPr&oacute;tacal maidir le seasamh na R&iacute;ochta Aontaithe agus na h&Eacute;ireann i dtaca leis an limist&eacute;ar saoirse, sl&aacute;nd&aacute;la agus ceartais at&aacute; i gceangal leis an gConradh ar Aontas Eorpach agus leis an gConradh ar Fheidhmi&uacute; an Aontais Eorpaigh (ar a dtugta&iacute; an Conradh ag bun&uacute; an Chomhphobail Eorpaigh tr&aacute;th), go scoirfidh s&eacute;, go hioml&aacute;n n&oacute; go p&aacute;irteach, d&rsquo;fheidhm a bheith aige maidir leis an St&aacute;t, ach beidh aon fheidhmi&uacute; den s&oacute;rt sin faoi r&eacute;ir cead&uacute; a fh&aacute;il roimh r&eacute; &oacute; dh&aacute; Theach an Oireachtais.</P>
        <P LI="3">14&deg; Tig leis an St&aacute;t aont&uacute; leis na cinnt&iacute;, leis na rialach&aacute;in n&oacute; leis na gn&iacute;omhartha eile arna nd&eacute;anamh&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="4">i faoi Airteagal 1.34(b)(iv),</P>
        <P LI="4">ii faoi Airteagal 1.56 (a mh&eacute;id a bhaineann s&eacute; le hAirteagal 48.7 den Chonradh d&aacute; dtagra&iacute;tear i bhfo-alt 4&deg; den alt seo),</P>
        <P LI="4">iii faoi Airteagal 2.66 (a mh&eacute;id a bhaineann s&eacute; leis an dara fomh&iacute;r d&rsquo;Airteagal 65.3 den Chonradh ar Fheidhmi&uacute; an Aontais Eorpaigh),</P>
        <P LI="4">iv faoi Airteagal 2.67 (a mh&eacute;id a bhaineann s&eacute; le fomh&iacute;r (d) d&rsquo;Airteagal 69A.2, leis an tr&iacute;&uacute; fomh&iacute;r d&rsquo;Airteagal 69B.1 agus le m&iacute;reanna 1 agus 4 d&rsquo;Airteagal 69E den Chonradh ar Fheidhmi&uacute; an Aontais Eorpaigh),</P>
        <P LI="4">v faoi Airteagal 2.144(a),</P>
        <P LI="4">vi faoi Airteagal 2.261 (a mh&eacute;id a bhaineann s&eacute; leis an dara fomh&iacute;r d&rsquo;Airteagal 270a.2 den Chonradh ar Fheidhmi&uacute; an Aontais Eorpaigh), agus</P>
        <P LI="4">vii faoi Airteagal 2.278 (a mh&eacute;id a bhaineann s&eacute; le hAirteagal 280H den Chonradh ar Fheidhmi&uacute; an Aontais Eorpaigh),</P><Col N="558"/>
        <P LI="3">den Chonradh d&aacute; dtagra&iacute;tear i bhfo-alt 10&deg; den alt seo, agus tig leis freisin aont&uacute; leis an gcinneadh faoin dara habairt den dara fomh&iacute;r d&rsquo;Airteagal 137.2 den Chonradh ar Fheidhmi&uacute; an Aontais Eorpaigh (arna leas&uacute; le hAirteagal 2.116(a) den Chonradh d&aacute; dtagra&iacute;tear san fho-alt 10&deg; sin), ach beidh aont&uacute; le haon chinneadh, rialach&aacute;n n&oacute; gn&iacute;omh den s&oacute;rt sin faoi r&eacute;ir cead&uacute; a fh&aacute;il roimh r&eacute; &oacute; dh&aacute; Theach an Oireachtais.</P>
        <P LI="3">15&deg; N&iacute; ghlacfaidh an St&aacute;t cinneadh arna dh&eacute;anamh ag an gComhairle Eorpach chun comhchosaint a bhun&uacute;&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="4">i de bhun Airteagal 1.2 den Chonradh d&aacute; dtagra&iacute;tear i bhfoalt 7&deg; den alt seo, n&aacute;</P>
        <P LI="4">ii de bhun Airteagal 1.49 den Chonradh d&aacute; dtagra&iacute;tear i bhfoalt 10&deg; den alt seo,</P>
        <P LI="2"> i gc&aacute;s ina mbeadh an St&aacute;t san &aacute;ireamh sa chomhchosaint sin.&rdquo;, agus</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>b</i>) an fo-alt seo a leanas a scriosadh as alt 4 d&rsquo;Airteagal 29 den Bhunreacht:</P>
        <P LI="3">&lsquo;11&deg; Tig leis an St&aacute;t an Comhaont&uacute; maidir le Paitinn&iacute; Comhphobail a tarraing&iacute;odh suas idir Ballst&aacute;it na gComhphobal agus a rinneadh i Lucsamburg ar an 15&uacute; l&aacute; de Nollaig,1989, a dhaingni&uacute;.&rsquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="1">2. M&Aacute; THOIL&Iacute;ONN T&Uacute; leis an togra, cuir X os coinne an fhocail T&Aacute; ar an bp&aacute;ip&eacute;ar ball&oacute;ide.</P>
        <P FLI="1">3. MURA dTOIL&Iacute;ONN T&Uacute; leis an togra, cuir X os coinne an fhocail N&Iacute;L ar an bp&aacute;ip&eacute;ar ball&oacute;ide.</P>
        <P FLI="1" Just="Left">4. Is f&eacute;idir c&oacute;ip den Bhille a ini&uacute;chadh n&oacute; a fh&aacute;il saor in aisce in aon Phost-Oifig.&rdquo;</P>
        <P FLI="1">I move:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;THAT the statement set out in the Schedule to this Resolution be prescribed for the information of voters pursuant to section 23 of the Referendum Act 1994 (No.12 of 1994), in relation to the proposal to amend Article 29 of the Constitution which is contained in the Twenty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution Bill 2008, and is the subject of a constitutional referendum.</P>
        <P Just="Center">Schedule</P>
        <P FLI="1">1. The Twenty-eighth Amendment of the Constitution Bill 2008 proposes&mdash;</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>a</i>) to insert the following subsections after subsection 10&deg; of section 4 of Article 29 of the Constitution:</P>
        <P LI="3">&lsquo;10&deg; The State may ratify the Treaty of Lisbon amending the Treaty on European Union and the Treaty establishing the European Community, signed at Lisbon on the 13th day of December 2007, and may be a member of the European Union established by virtue of that Treaty.</P>
        <P LI="3">11&deg; No provision of this Constitution invalidates laws enacted, acts done or measures adopted by the State that are necessitated by the obligations of membership of the European Union referred to in subsection 10&deg; of this section, or prevents laws enacted, acts done or measures adopted by the said European Union or by institutions thereof, or by bodies competent under the treaties referred to in this section, from having the force of law in the State.</P><Col N="559"/>
        <P LI="3">12&deg; The State may exercise the options or discretions provided by or under Articles 1.22, 2.64, 2.65, 2.66, 2.67, 2.68 and 2.278 of the Treaty referred to in subsection 10&deg; of this section and Articles 1.18 and 1.20 of Protocol No. 1 annexed to that Treaty, but any such exercise shall be subject to the prior approval of both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
        <P LI="3">13&deg; The State may exercise the option to secure that the Protocol on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (formerly known as the Treaty establishing the European Community) shall, in whole or in part, cease to apply to the State, but any such exercise shall be subject to the prior approval of both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
        <P LI="3">14&deg; The State may agree to the decisions, regulations or other acts under &mdash;</P>
        <P LI="4">i Article 1.34(b)(iv),</P>
        <P LI="4">ii Article 1.56 (in so far as it relates to Article 48.7 of the Treaty referred to in subsection 4&deg; of this section),</P>
        <P LI="4">iii Article 2.66 (in so far as it relates to the second subparagraph of Article 65.3 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union),</P>
        <P LI="4">iv Article 2.67 (in so far as it relates to subparagraph (d) of Article 69A.2, the third subparagraph of Article 69B.1 and paragraphs 1 and 4 of Article 69E of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union),</P>
        <P LI="4">v Article 2.144(a),</P>
        <P LI="4">vi Article 2.261 (in so far as it relates to the second subparagraph of Article 270a.2 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union), and</P>
        <P LI="4">vii Article 2.278 (in so far as it relates to Article 280H of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union),</P>
        <P LI="3">of the Treaty referred to in subsection 10&deg; of this section, and may also agree to the decision under the second sentence of the second subparagraph of Article 137.2 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union (as amended by Article 2.116(a) of the Treaty referred to in the said subsection 10&deg;), but the agreement to any such decision, regulation or act shall be subject to the prior approval of both Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
        <P LI="3">15&deg; The State shall not adopt a decision taken by the European Council to establish a common defence pursuant to &mdash;</P>
        <P LI="4">i Article 1.2 of the Treaty referred to in subsection 7&deg; of this section, or</P>
        <P LI="4">ii Article 1.49 of the Treaty referred to in subsection 10&deg; of this section,</P>
        <P LI="3">where that common defence would include the State.&rdquo;, and</P>
        <P LI="2">(<i>b</i>) to delete the following subsection from section 4 of Article 29 of the Constitution:</P>
        <P LI="3">&lsquo;11&deg; The State may ratify the Agreement relating to Community Patents drawn up between the Member States of the Communities and done at Luxembourg on the 15th day of December, 1989.&rsquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="1">2. IF YOU APPROVE of the proposal, mark X opposite the word YES on the ballot paper.</P><Col N="560"/>
        <P FLI="1">3. IF YOU DO NOT APPROVE of the proposal, mark X opposite the word NO on the ballot paper.</P>
        <P FLI="1" Just="Left">4. A copy of the Bill can be inspected or obtained free of charge at any Post Office.&rdquo;</P>
 </Speaker>
        <P>Cuireadh agus aonta&iacute;odh an cheist.</P>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Tomorrow at 10.30 a.m.</P>
      
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters.</Title>
  </MainHeading><Line />
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Cancer Treatment" RHead="Services"> 
    <Title>Cancer Treatment Services. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Senator Paddy Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Brendan Smith, to the House.  He looked very relaxed as he waited.  I wish him well for this afternoon.</P>
        <P>I thank the Chair for allowing me raise the issue of services at Mayo General Hospital on the Adjournment.  Last week the Minister for Health and Children was in Castlebar to open the BreastCheck unit there.  She gave some figures on the number of breast cancer operations that have taken place at Mayo General Hospital to the media, to the public and to seven ladies who are involved in a campaign to save the cancer services at the hospital.  The figures have greatly embarrassed the hospital&rsquo;s senior management, senior consultants and staff.  I heard the Minister say on the radio that there were 37 operations annually at Mayo General Hospital and that, as this was less than one a week, they could easily be catered for at the proposed centre for excellence in Galway, notwithstanding the huge problems there are in Galway, not only in hospital capacity but in traffic and parking.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">2 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>Yesterday, my party leader Enda Kenny, our health spokesperson Deputy James Reilly, our MEP, Jim Higgins, Deputies Michael Ring and John O&rsquo;Mahony and I met the senior management and staff at Mayo General Hospital.  The figures they gave us show that 97 breast cancer operations took place in 2007 at the hospital.  That differs greatly from the figures given by the Minister for Health and Children, and great concern has been expressed by Mr. Barry, the senior consultant surgeon at the hospital.  He has been taken aback by the interpretation and the figures that the Minister has put forward.  There is no doubt that she has done that to downgrade Mayo General Hospital and take cancer services away from it.  Mr. Barry told us clearly yesterday that, in 2000, the then Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children, Tom Moffat &mdash; a Mayoman &mdash; and Mary Hinds opened a satellite centre in Castlebar, which was linked to Galway in every way.  We want to hold that centre in Castlebar at the Mayo General Hospital.  The consultants at Galway and Castlebar work in conjunction with each other.</P>
        <P>Mr. Barry said that the criteria laid out at the opening of the centre was that more than 50 operations would take place annually and that the hospital would stand up to scrutiny.  There is no doubt that 97 operations took place last year.  Mr. Barry has said that if the figure drops below 50 and if the centre does not stand up to scrutiny or the centre of excellence strategy, it should be closed.  However, he guarantees that it is above board and will stand up to any scrutiny for any centre of excellence throughout the world.</P><Col N="561"/>
        <P>I must put it on the record that the Minister for Health and Children did a huge disservice to the morale of the staff in the hospital.  She should apologise to the staff and management of Mayo General Hospital.  The national cancer strategy includes eight centres of excellence, with which we have no problem.  However, if the strategy is based on the figures that the Minister for Health and Children gave to the media and put out into the public domain &mdash; 37 operations, instead of the 97 that took place &mdash; we have got the strategy completely wrong.  I want to know where Professor Keane stands on the issue.  What are his views on the figures indicated by the Minister for Health and Children?</P>
        <P>I want also to know what is the Minister&rsquo;s definition of a centre of excellence.  Is Castlebar a centre of excellence in its own right as a satellite of Galway?  What is the position with Sligo?  The Minister of State is in a hurry but I want to put on the record those issues and the deep dissatisfaction felt in Mayo General Hospital with how the Minister has put figures into the public domain.  Will the Minister of State clarify the discrepancy between the figures?  What year and what figures was the Minister for Children and Health talking about?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanSmith"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Brendan Smith</NameTxt>
	<P>I will take this Adjournment matter on behalf of my colleague the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Mary Harney.  At the outset, I thank Senator Paddy Burke for raising this important issue regarding the restructuring of cancer services, with particular reference to Mayo General Hospital.</P>
        <P>Data on surgical cancer procedures is collated by the hospital inpatient inquiry system, commonly referred to as HIPE, based on information supplied by hospitals.  The information is supplied by all public hospitals to the Economic and Social Research Institute, which validates the data.  The HIPE system collects information on all discharges and deaths.  The data provided by Mayo General Hospital show that in 2006, 43 surgical procedures were carried out on women with a principal diagnosis of breast cancer.  The HIPE data for 2007 are almost 90% complete and show 35 cases.  Data for 2008 have yet to be collated.</P>
        <P>The HIPE analysis counts every occurrence of these procedures in which the patient has a principal diagnosis of breast cancer and so may include more than one procedure per person.  Therefore, the data presented refer to the number of breast cancer related procedures and not the number of women.</P>
        <P>The Department of Health and Children is unclear as to the basis for recently issued figures from Mayo General Hospital that differ from the HIPE figures.  The hospital inpatient inquiry system provides validated figures that have been used to inform the decision-making process with regard to the establishment of the managed cancer control networks and designated centres.  The National Quality Assurance Standards for Symptomatic Breast Disease Services provide that each specialist unit should manage a minimum number of 150 new breast cancer cases per annum.  Mayo General Hospital falls well short of this figure.</P>
        <P Just="Left">We must be clear about the need for the change to higher case volumes.  People in the west and south have a poorer survival rate for common cancers, including breast cancer, than the remainder of the country.  The designation of cancer centres aims to ensure that patients receive the highest quality care while allowing local access to services where appropriate.</P>
        <P>As Seanad &Eacute;ireann is aware, Professor Tom Keane has been appointed to lead and manage the establishment of the Health Service Executive national cancer control programme.  Professor Keane has ambitious plans and has already made significant progress in implementation of the programme.  The key objective of the national cancer control programme is to ensure equity of access to services and equality of outcome irrespective of geography.  This will involve <Col N="562"/>significant realignment of cancer services to move from the present fragmented system of care to one that is consistent with international best practice in cancer control.</P>
        <P>The decisions of the HSE in regard to four managed cancer control networks and eight cancer centres will be implemented on a managed and phased basis.  The HSE plans to have completed 50% of the transition of services to the cancer centres by the end of this year and 80% to 90% by the end of 2009.</P>
        <P>The HSE has designated University College Hospital Galway and Limerick Regional Hospital as the two cancer centres in the managed cancer control network for the HSE western region, which includes County Mayo.  The designation of cancer centres aims to ensure that patients receive the highest quality care while allowing local access to services, where appropriate.  Where diagnosis and treatment planning is directed and managed by multidisciplinary teams based at the cancer centres, much of the treatment, other than surgery, can be delivered in local hospitals, such as Castlebar.  In this context, chemotherapy and support services will continue to be delivered locally.</P>
        <P>The Government is committed to making the full range of cancer services available and accessible to cancer patients throughout Ireland in accordance with best international practices and standards.  The developments I have outlined will ensure that a comprehensive service is available to all patients with cancer in the western region including in County Mayo.  I assure Deputy Burke that in view of the fact that his figures do not run parallel to those I have given in reply, I will ensure that his contribution is brought to the attention of the Minister for Health and Children and to the attention of the senior management of the HSE.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Senator Paddy Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State.  I hope he passes on the figures, because otherwise the Government is making a liar out of one of the finest surgeons in the country.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Schools Building" RHead="Projects"> 
    <Title>Schools Building Projects. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>As the Minister of State is aware, Ballygarvan national school is in a growing area of County Cork.  Its present school is grossly inadequate, and it is unfair on the students, parents and teachers who have to endure a legacy and litany of broken promises, false dawns and new beginnings.  We have heard the usual story a number of times.  I am disappointed that the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Mary Hanafin, is not present, as she should be here to answer to the people of Ballygarvan.</P>
        <P>People are at the core of this discussion.  The learning community of students, parents and teachers deserves to be educated, to have their children attend and to work in a campus in conditions that are acceptable in modern Ireland.  The fundamental question is where we are in the process.  Meetings have taken place, students are in prefabs and portakabins.  I could list a litany of e-mails and letters I have received from parents.  I have been at meetings in Ballygarvan where we have seen rat-infested prefabs, school books have been burned and students have had to go home to wash and put on clean clothes.  The space and facilities are inadequate and this has been going on for almost ten years.  The chronology has continued.  When will building begin, when will it be completed and when will the students and staff move in?  It is important we get the answers.  Where are we on the purchase of land?  The pupils, parents and teachers of Ballygarvan deserve a real answer and not just tokenism.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanSmith"><NameTxt>Deputy Brendan Smith</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator for raising this matter, which I am taking on behalf of the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Hanafin.  Senator Buttimer&rsquo;s raising this issue gives me the opportunity to outline to this House the Government&rsquo;s strategy for <Col N="563"/>capital investment in education projects and the position on the building project for Ballygarvan national school.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Modernising facilities in approximately 3,200 primary and 730 post-primary schools is not an easy task given the legacy of decades of under-investment in this area as well as the need to respond to emerging needs in areas of rapid population growth.  Nonetheless, the Government has shown a consistent determination to improve the condition of our school buildings and to ensure the appropriate facilities are in place to enable the implementation of a broad and balanced curriculum.  The Government has dramatically increased investment in the school building programme from just over &euro;90 million in 1997 to almost &euro;600 million this year.  Under the lifetime of the national development plan almost &euro;4.5 billion will be invested in schools.  This is an unprecedented level of capital investment which reflects the Government&rsquo;s commitment to continue its programme of sustained investment in primary and post primary schools.</P>
        <P>As Senator Buttimer may be aware, a developing areas unit was set up recently in the Department to focus on the school accommodation needs of rapidly developing areas.  The main emphasis in 2008 is on providing sufficient school places in these developing areas, as well as delivering improvements in the quality of existing primary and post-primary school accommodation throughout the country.</P>
        <P>On Ballygarvan national school specifically and Carrigaline generally, the developing areas unit of the Department has identified Carrigaline as an area of rapid development.  A decision has been already taken to replace and expand the school.  The new building, when complete, will be a 16 classroom school with appropriate ancillary accommodation.  A suitable site has been identified for the school in question.  Senator Buttimer raised this issue.  The site comprises three plots of land with three separate vendors.  A number of issues have arisen during the acquisition process and the Department is continuing to progress these outstanding issues in consultation with the Office of the Chief State Solicitor.  When the site acquisition is complete, a building project for the school will be considered in the context of the Department&rsquo;s multi-annual school building and modernisation programme.  While I am not in a position to give a timetable for the commencement of this project, the need for a new school building for the school in question is acknowledged by the Department.  In the meantime temporary accommodation for the school has been approved by the Department as an interim measure to facilitate increased enrolments next September.</P>
        <P>I again thank Senator Buttimer for affording me the opportunity to outline to this House the position on Ballygarvan national school.  I will bring Senator Buttimer&rsquo;s comments on the need for new accommodation to the attention of the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Hanafin, without further delay.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank the Minister of State for his reply and I am conscious that it is not his Department.  The site was identified a long time ago.  We need information on when the site can be acquired and the process can begin.  I appeal to the Minister of State, Deputy Smith to bring it back to the Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Hanafin, that we need to put deadlines and times in place.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanSmith"><NameTxt>Deputy Brendan Smith</NameTxt>
	<P>I understand that outstanding issues are being progressed through the Office of the Chief State Solicitor.  All of us who deal with constituency work know how frustratingly slow some of these processes are.  I will also bring that point to the attention of the Minister, Deputy Hanafin.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish Deputy Smith well today.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <Col N="564"/><MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Road" RHead="Network"> 
    <Title>Road Network. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>I was about to issue the usual complaint that we do not have a Cabinet Minister in the House but perhaps we do.  We will find out very shortly.  I hope so and I wish the Minister of State, Deputy Smith well in the hours to come. </P>
        <P Just="Left">I raise the issue of the M50 and the degree of ministerial responsibility on the setting of the tolls when and if they are implemented in August.  The Minister will be well aware that there was a campaign to open the old toll bridge on the M50 to remove the tolls and barriers.  A politically driven decision was taken approximately 18 months ago that this should happen in August this year and that the tolls should be taken electronically.  It worries me that one monopoly has been replaced by another tyranny.  A private monopoly has been replaced by a public monopoly.  I want to elicit from the Minister what role he will play after August when electronic tolling is introduced.  This is an opportunity for the Government to play the kind of detached role it likes to play by saying a semi-State agency, the NRA, is in charge and that it is nothing to do with the Government.  When it is convenient the Government can claim credit for things State agencies do well but when it is not the Government can step back and say the NRA is an agency with a certain degree of independence.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I would like the Minister to say whether he considers the toll too high and what the NRA has already done monopolistic.  We have had the imposition of a &euro;2 toll at a certain point on the M50 and it was believed that would be the toll for the current year.  However I gather that in August, due to a spontaneous decision by the NRA, those tolls will rise again.  The rises are outrageous.  Some regular drivers who get the right tag will still pay &euro;2; other categories of drivers, including those who pre-register and travel casually, will have their tolls raised by 50 cent in one case and &euro;1 in another.  This is for an individual, ordinary motorist travelling through there.  Those are 25% and 50% rises, which are unforgivable and impossible to justify, particularly as they crucify the same motorists who have been crucified for many years and who get no return on it.</P>
        <P>I appeal to the Minister to tell us what he intends to do about this.  The procedure in place for an appeal against these types of imposed tolls was triggered last December.  When the increases were announced the National Consumer Agency, NCA, another Government agency without much clout, appealed against them.  The NCA appealed to a person appointed by the NRA.  Therefore, a Government agency appealed against price rises by another Government agency, but the appeals arbitrator was appointed by one of the parties involved.  That is in the legislation and that is the NRA&rsquo;s defence.  It is completely unjust that one of the parties involved should appoint the adjudicator.  I would like to hear the Minister&rsquo;s views on that and whether he can move in and do something to reduce these tolls, restrict the activities of the NRA and cut it down to size and ensure there is an appeals procedure that has credibility.  The result of that appeal, as the Minister knows, was that the NRA won game, set and match.  I suggest that this was not unpredictable in the circumstances.</P>
        <P>If tolls are to be imposed on the M50 and other roads, will the Minister ensure they are imposed fairly?  The toll point for electronic tolling on the M50 is exactly the same, give or take 100 yards or so, as was used &mdash; and is still being used today &mdash; for manual West Link tolling.  Why should those who go through that point subsidise the trips of others who do not go through it but use large stretches of the motorway?  One can go from Bray to the turn-off to Naas and further without paying anything, but if one goes through that point one will have to pay &euro;2, &euro;2.50 or &euro;3, which will be the new tolls from August.  I ask the Minister of State to explain the role the Minister will have in this, what he will do about these outrageous tolls and what powers he will have in the future.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="565"/>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanSmith"><NameTxt>Deputy Brendan Smith</NameTxt>
	<P>I am giving this reply to the House on behalf of the Minister for Transport, Deputy Noel Dempsey, who is unavoidably absent.  I note that this issue has for many years been close to the heart of Senator Ross.  I have had the opportunity to listen to the Senator speaking in the broadcast media and read his comments in the print media, and I know he has highlighted such issues over many years in various forums.</P>
        <P>As Senator Ross knows, the Minister for Transport is responsible for national roads policy and funding.  However, the detailed planning, design and implementation of all aspects of individual road improvement schemes, including such matters as the removal of the toll barriers at the West Link on the M50, is the responsibility of the National Roads Authority under section 17 of the Roads Act 1993.  Furthermore, the statutory power to levy tolls on national roads, to make toll by-laws, and to enter into toll agreements with private investors in respect of national roads is vested in the NRA under Part V of the Roads Act 1993, as amended.</P>
        <P>The Senator will be aware that it is Government policy under Transport 21 to address the issue of congestion on the M50 as a matter of priority.  The M50 has experienced massive traffic growth in line with economic and employment growth and increased car ownership rates.  Average annual daily traffic flows on a number of sections of the M50 are greater than 85,000 vehicles and major congestion occurs at peak times.  The solution to this is the upgrade of the M50 along with the move to barrier-free tolling.  A key part of the M50 improvement strategy is the transition to barrier-free tolling, which I understand from the NRA is on schedule to become operational in August 2008, as mentioned by Senator Ross in his contribution.  This will entail the removal of the current West Link toll plaza and its replacement with a fully electronic barrier-free tolling system that will allow drivers to travel unencumbered along the M50.</P>
        <P>I emphasise that in outlining the barrier-free tolling arrangements to the Government in 2007 the NRA indicated that the changeover would not entail any special increase, other than periodic inflation-related increases, in the basic toll level for users with electronic toll tags.  The expected electronic toll of &euro;2 from August 2008 is in line with these indications.  However, it is clearly important for the efficient operation of the electronic system that the fullest possible level of participation is encouraged.  To that end, an incentive for participation is provided by the application of higher toll charges for those who elect not to use electronic tags.  This is normal practice in toll systems around the world.</P>
        <P>I am pleased to have the opportunity to update the House on the progress being made on the M50 upgrade project.  The project, which involves widening of the M50 to three lanes, with a fourth auxiliary lane in places, and upgrading of the interchanges, will have significant benefits, as it will expand the capacity of the M50 to deal with at least 50% more traffic than at present; improve average peak-hour speeds; reduce traffic congestion on the radial routes, particularly the N3, the N4 and the N7; and improve traffic flow on the whole Dublin road network.</P>
        <P>The upgrade of the M50 is being carried out in three phases.  Work on phases 1 and 3 are either complete or close to completion.  Phase 2 will be fully completed in 2010.  Work on phase 1 of the upgrade is now well advanced and on schedule for completion in the autumn of this year.  The upgraded N4 and Ballymount junctions are now fully open to traffic and the mainline section of the phase 1 project, at almost 8 km, is now open with four lanes &mdash; three plus one auxiliary lane &mdash; in each direction.  Road users are already experiencing the benefits this improvement has brought to their everyday commutes.  Work is continuing on the N7 junction, commonly referred to as the Red Cow junction, sections of which have already been completed.  The junction is due for completion in the autumn of this year.</P><Col N="566"/>
        <P>Phase 2 of the upgrade is well under way, with a target completion date of 2010, while phase 3 is now complete, with four lanes now open to traffic.  The total cost of the upgrade is approximately &euro;1 billion and, as has often been the case with national road schemes over the past few years, it is on target for completion on time and within budget.</P>
        <P>I will conclude by pointing out that road users will continue to see significant benefits being delivered on the M50 during 2008 when the first phase of the motorway upgrade is fully completed and barrier-free tolling is in place.  Further improvement of the M50 will take place on completion of the final stage of the upgrade in 2010.</P>
        <P>I assure Senator Ross that I will bring the specific issues he raised in his contribution to the attention of the Minister for Transport, Deputy Dempsey.  As I mentioned, I have listened on many occasions to Senator Ross speaking on this issue in various broadcast media and read his comments in the print media.  He has, to say the least, been a tenacious campaigner on tolling and the M50.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>May I follow that up with a question?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Very briefly, as the Minister of State must be in the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>Is there a good reason?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes, hopefully.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanSmith"><NameTxt>Deputy Brendan Smith</NameTxt>
	<P>No.  It is just to vote.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>I find an anomaly in this area.  The road we are talking about is under Government control.  The Minister of State said in his reply that the day-to-day running of the roads is under the remit of the NRA.  That is technically true.  However, the buy-out, which is the important thing for the M50, was decided and paid for by the Government.  The former Minister, Deputy Cullen, regularly answered detailed questions &mdash; perhaps not adequately &mdash; about the M50 and how it would operate.  Could the Minister of State assure me that the Minister for Transport, whoever he is &mdash; it could be anybody in this room at this moment &mdash; will keep us informed of the day-to-day running of the M50, as it is of such public importance, and will keep a vigilant eye on the NRA to prevent its putting up tolling prices to indefensible levels?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanSmith"><NameTxt>Deputy Brendan Smith</NameTxt>
	<P>I assure the Senator that the issues he has raised will be brought to the attention of the Minister for Transport.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 2.25 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 8 May 2008.</adjournment>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
