<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Tue" Date="30" Month="Jan" Year="1923" Vol="2" No="22" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 30 Eanáir 1923" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 30 January 1923" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1071">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1071" /> Do cromadh ar obair an lae ar 3.15 p.m.  Bhí an Ceann Comhairle Micheál O h-Aodha sa Chathaoir.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- PORT OF DERRY">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - PORT OF DERRY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="DARGHAL FIGES DARGHAL FIGES">
      <NameTxt>DARGHAL FIGES</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the President, in view of the fact that the Port of Derry has been closed for the shipment of live stock, and the grave injury thus done to those parts of the Free State of which Derry is the only available port, whether he has made, or will make, firm representations to the British Government on the matter, with a view to getting the closure removed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government has all along been in touch with the position in Derry, and the steps to be taken are under consideration.  If the Deputy would kindly place at the disposal of the Government any firm representations made to him it is possible that further advantage might be derived from the information.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- MOTOR TAX">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - MOTOR TAX.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir SEAMUS CRAIG Sir SEAMUS CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir SEAMUS CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance whether, pending its being found practicable to introduce a measure placing the tax on Motor Vehicles on the amount of Petrol consumed, <i>i.e.</i>, on the Petrol imported into the country, he is prepared to consider the advisability of giving some relief to Motor Users, by reducing the Tax of £1 per horse power to 10s. per horse power, under the existing method of taxation, when introducing the Budget and Finance Act for 1923-1924.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (The President) William T. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (The President)</NameTxt>
      <P>The suggestion in the question will be considered, but it is not possible to give any indication at this stage as <Col N="1072" /> to what proposals will or will not be included by the Executive Council in the Budget for next financial year.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="MILITARY AND GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - MILITARY AND GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="TOMAS O CONAILL TOMAS O CONAILL">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS O CONAILL</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance whether it has been the practice of the Military Authorities to notify the heads of Government Departments to the effect that payment of salary to Government servants against whom certain reports are made or received must be suspended; whether a Government Department is bound to suspend payment on receipt of such notification; in that case with whom does the duty lie of investigating the truth or otherwise of such charges as may be made, and whether it is not a fact that some public servants have had their salaries held up for several months as a result of such reports, while the Military Authorities took no action towards establishing the truth or otherwise of the charges on which suspension of payment was founded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government has ordered the suspension of any official who is believed to be in complicity with the irregular forces, and such suspensions as have been made were carried out because of good reason to believe that the official did not give that faithful service which the Government must expect from its servants.  These suspensions have, happily, been very few in number.  In every case enquiry is made by the Military Authorities.</P>
      <P>If the Deputy has any particular case in mind and will communicate with me I will enquire into the circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="WESTMEATH COUNTY COUNCIL GRANTS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - WESTMEATH COUNTY COUNCIL GRANTS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance whether the Government intends to pay the withheld grants, to the amount of £21,000, due to the Westmeath County Council; and whether, in view of the acute unemployment obtaining in Westmeath, and in order to provide work for and to relieve the sufferings of those people, he will act on the resolution of the Council, urging that payment of the grants be expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1073" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The amount available for allocation to Westmeath County Council in respect of grants formerly withheld by the British Government in the Local Taxation Account was paid to the Council in September last.  The issue of the normal grants for the current year, so far as still unpaid, depends upon the adjustments at present being made in the Guarantee Fund by reason especially of default in the payment of tenant purchasers' annuities.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- RATES OF INTEREST">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - RATES OF INTEREST.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="DARGHAL FIGES DARGHAL FIGES">
      <NameTxt>DARGHAL FIGES</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance if he is aware that many people owing money in Ireland, especially in the remoter parts of the country, are suffering from usurious rates of interest, amounting in very many cases to well over 100 per cent. per annum.  And if, having regard both to the immorality of such proceedings, and to the injurious effects on the trade and prosperity of the country, he will consider the advisability of bringing in a short Bill at an early date, giving relief to such cases, putting private debts on a more equitable foundation, and limiting for the future the rate of interest for which private debtors may be liable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot give any undertaking in this matter at the present time.  The Deputy is, no doubt, aware that the existing law makes provision in regard to harsh and unconscionable transactions in certain cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- IRISH CLASSES FOR ADULTS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - IRISH CLASSES FOR ADULTS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance whether he is aware that, without adequate financial support, it is most difficult and practically impossible to organise and conduct on a satisfactory basis Irish classes for adults in the Counties of Westmeath and Longford, that in every parish of these counties there are many people who left school without a knowledge of Irish, and who now wish to acquire it, that funds are needed to place a sufficient number of competent teachers of Irish at the service of these people; and whether in view of these facts, any monetary help would be forthcoming to enable people to acquire a thorough knowledge of the Irish language.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1074" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>A question on this matter is being answered by the Minister of Local Government to-day.</P>
      <P>The Government are anxious to facilitate as fully as possible the teaching of Irish, and to that object the introduction of early legislative measures to regularise the levying and application of the necessary funds by way of rates is under consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="REPARATIONS COMMISSION CHAIRMANSHIP">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - REPARATIONS COMMISSION CHAIRMANSHIP.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephHenness" hpid="MICHEAL O hAONGHUSA MICHEAL O hAONGHUSA">
      <NameTxt>MICHEAL O hAONGHUSA</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance whether he is aware that, owing to the recent resignation of Lord Shaw from the Chairmanship of the Criminal Injuries Compensation (Ireland) Commission, cases in which legal points arise cannot be heard and ruled on; and if the Minister can state when he expects the vacancy in the Chairmanship to be filled, and the Commission fully competent to deal with all cases awaiting adjudication.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The appointment of a successor to Lord Shaw as Chairman of the Commission referred to is under consideration, and it is expected that the appointment will be made shortly.  It is understood that no general inconvenience has been occasioned by Lord Shaw's resignation in the manner described in the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- ENFIELD (CO. MEATH) MAILS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - ENFIELD (CO. MEATH) MAILS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O SEANAIN CATHAL O SEANAIN">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O SEANAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Postmaster-General whether the night mails for Enfield (Co. Meath) sub-district are now sent from Dublin by the 6.15 p.m. train to Mullingar and thence back to Enfield next morning, arriving at 9.50 a.m.; whether the mails from Dublin, dropped from the limited mail about 7.45 a.m., are held up in Enfield till the mail bag returns from Mullingar, involving a delay of over two hours in delivery; whether the night despatch from Enfield is sent first to Mullingar by train leaving Enfield at 7.15 p.m., and thence to Dublin by next morning's train, arriving in Dublin about 10.45 a.m., the letters not being delivered till next day, thus making a delay of two days in the delivery of a letter at a distance of some 20 miles; and whether he would consider making an arrangement by which the night mail <Col N="1075" /> might be sent direct from Enfield to Dublin, instead of Mullingar; and what other arrangements he is making to remedy this state of affairs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="The POSTMASTER-GENERAL (Mr. J.J. Walsh) The POSTMASTER-GENERAL (Mr. J.J. Walsh)">
      <NameTxt>The POSTMASTER-GENERAL (Mr. J.J. Walsh)</NameTxt>
      <P>It has now been arranged to have direct despatches made from both Dublin and Mullingar to Enfield by evening trains, and to restore the earlier hour of the morning delivery.  The delay to correspondence from Enfield for Dublin, referred to in the second part of the Deputy's question, has already come under notice, and a direct despatch to Dublin by the last evening train was instituted on the 22nd instant.  This enables the correspondence to be included in the first morning delivery.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="CAHIRCIVEEN POSTAL OFFICIALS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - CAHIRCIVEEN POSTAL OFFICIALS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O SEANAIN CATHAL O SEANAIN">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O SEANAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Postmaster-General whether there has been any cause of complaint as to official Post Office duties against the three members of the Post Office staff at Cahirciveen who were summarily dismissed from their position on December 22nd by Commandant Griffin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesJosephWalsh" hpid="Mr. J.J. WALSH Mr. J.J. WALSH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J.J. WALSH</NameTxt>
      <P>The three officials referred to, who are female sorting clerks and telegraphists at Cahirciveen, have not been dismissed, but were suspended from duty on the 22nd December, 1922, by order of the military.  Their cases are at present under enquiry.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="ARREST OF NATIONAL TEACHERS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - ARREST OF NATIONAL TEACHERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="TOMAS O CONAILL TOMAS O CONAILL">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS O CONAILL</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Education what action is taken by his Department with regard to national teachers arrested by the military authorities and detained without trial; and whether it is the intention to adopt the same procedure as was followed by the Commissioners of National Education during the British regime.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfEoinMacNeill" hpid="MINISTER for EDUCATION (Professor Eoin MacNeill) Eoin MacNeill">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for EDUCATION (Professor Eoin MacNeill)</NameTxt>
      <P>When a teacher is arrested, payment of his salary is suspended as from the date of his arrest, and the manager of the school concerned is advised that a qualified teacher should be appointed in his place, and that payment of salary will be made to such a <Col N="1076" /> teacher as a &ldquo;locum tenens&rdquo; or temporary teacher pending the decision of the military authorities on the case of the teacher under arrest.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="DISTRICT JUSTICE'S STATEMENT">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - DISTRICT JUSTICE'S STATEMENT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="RISTEARD MAC LIAM RISTEARD MAC LIAM">
      <NameTxt>RISTEARD MAC LIAM</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Home Affairs whether his attention has been drawn to the following statement, alleged to have been made by District Justice Little, at Bray, and reported in the <i>Wicklow News-Letter</i> of the 13th inst., as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;This was owing to the damnable ignorance of the farming class, who tolerated dirt in every shape and form, and was opposed to the law until it was brought home to them.  They had no instinct for cleanliness.  We want people, he added, to have Christian appreciation of their duties to their fellowman.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Whether he considers the Courts of Justice a suitable theatre for the propagation of insults to any particular class of citizens; whether the words attributed to this District Justice do not clearly indicate unfitness for the position he occupies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. K. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. K. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>The remarks quoted in the Deputy's question are certainly improper and objectionable.  If I considered that they represented a settled mental attitude on the part of this Justice towards a large and important element in the country and in the area of his own administration, I would agree with the Deputy that an outlook of that kind would constitute a disqualification for the equal and impartial administration of justice.  After conversation with Mr. Little on the subject, however, I am convinced that it was far from his intention to stigmatise the entire farming class. Stung by a particularly shocking case, he failed to qualify verbally a thought which he did in fact qualify very definitely in his mind, with the result that, instead of being a rebuke to particular members of a class who are guilty of certain forms of neglect, his words read as a general indictment of that entire class.  Such an indictment would, of course, be absurd and untrue.  Mr. Little has written to me expressing his sincere regret that he should have caused pain and given <Col N="1077" /> offence by his momentary indiscretion. In these circumstances I trust that the Deputy will agree with me that no further action is called for.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- COST OF RATE COLLECTION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - COST OF RATE COLLECTION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesNicholasDolan" hpid="SEAMUS O DOLAIN SEAMUS O DOLAIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAMUS O DOLAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Local Government what is the present cost of collecting local rates throughout the Saorstát, and whether he has considered the question of substituting some cheaper and more effective method of collection than that at the present prevailing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>The cost of collection of the rates for last year will amount to approximately £200,000.  The collection of County Council rates by means of receivable orders through the agency of the Post Office has been recommended, and, so far as this has been considered, it appears to promise substantial advantages over the present system both as regards economy and efficiency.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="GRANTS FOR TEACHING OF IRISH">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - GRANTS FOR TEACHING OF IRISH.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Local Government whether he is aware that the Westmeath County Council granted a sum of £1,300 in 1921 to the Gaelic League for the revival of the native language; and, further, on what grounds did the Local Government Department refuse to sanction the above sum; further, is he aware that the same County Council granted, on November 2nd, 1922, the Westmeath Technical Instruction Committee the sum of £400, for the teaching of Irish in Westmeath; and further, whether it is the intention of the Minister to sanction this grant, as the scheme is held up for approval.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am unable to find that sanction to the proposal made in 1921, was refused.</P>
      <P>The Temporary Provision Bill includes specific proposals to regularise the levying and application of a rate for the teaching of Irish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. J. LYONS Mr. J. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>As I stated in the question the Westmeath County Council granted a sum of £1,300 in 1921, and because that was not sanctioned by the Local Government Board the teaching of Irish in Westmeath was crippled. Can I now have a definite answer?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1078" />
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given a definite answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Local Government whether sanction will be given for the striking of a special rate for the teaching of Irish by the County Councils of Westmeath and Longford, as was done by the Roscommon County Council, and, if the rate be sanctioned, whether the local County Committees of the Gaelic League will be allowed to administer the Fund.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>In March, 1922, Longford County Council increased their rate for Agricultural and Technical Instruction for the current financial year to 2d. in £, so as to provide for the teaching of Irish.  This proposal was sanctioned in April last.</P>
      <P>I do not know of any more recent proposal from Longford, but my reply to the last question concerning Westmeath County Council applies equally as regards any additional schemes which may be adopted by other Councils.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - INTERNED" RHead="PRISONERS. (PAYMENT OF SALARIES)">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - INTERNED PRISONERS.  (PAYMENT OF SALARIES).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="DARGHAL FIGES DARGHAL FIGES">
      <NameTxt>DARGHAL FIGES</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Local Government whether, having regard to the fact that his intimation that any salaries paid by the Dublin Corporation to interned prisoners will be surcharged, is of itself sufficient to check such payment, he will withdraw his statement that further housing grants to the Corporation will be withdrawn; and if he will state why, when legal remedies are available, he should attach merely punitive measures to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is based on a mistake as to the facts, inasmuch as an intimation to the effect stated has not been given by me, and, in fact, could not be given because in the making of surcharges auditors act judiciously and independently and their decisions are open to review on appeal.  The decision of the Corporation to give half-pay to the dependents of men interned for irregular activities involves even more serious issues than the misapplication of ratepayers' monies for which individual members would be held personally responsible at a future date.  The Government could not, by failing to take immediate <Col N="1079" /> steps, countenance action which would in effect subsidise and promote sabotage and disorder.  The Government has decided to withhold housing grants as a first step, so that the serious attention of the ratepayers of Dublin, and of the majority of the Corporation may be drawn to the grave situation which has arisen.  That decision will not be altered unless the Corporation's resolution is rescinded.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - IRISH" RHead="CONSULATES (MADRID AND ROME)">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - IRISH CONSULATES (MADRID AND ROME).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="DARGHAL FIGES DARGHAL FIGES">
      <NameTxt>DARGHAL FIGES</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for External Affairs if it is true that the offices of the Free State in Madrid and Rome have now been closed. Further, if he will indicate, of the total amount of work being done by his staff, what proportion of the staff, or of the work of the staff, is taken up by the external relations of the Free State, and what proportion by publicity in Ireland, and if it is proposed to make the necessary distinction between these in all future estimates for his Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="MINISTER for EXTERNAL AFFAIRS (Mr. Desmond Fitzgerald) Desmond FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for EXTERNAL AFFAIRS (Mr. Desmond Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>The office in Madrid has been closed.  The office in Rome has not been closed.  The distribution of the work is of such a nature that, for the present, it is impossible to say what proportion is external affairs and what proportion is publicity It has yet to be decided if the two branches will be estimated for separately.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- CONSULATE IN PARIS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - CONSULATE IN PARIS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="DARGHAL FIGES DARGHAL FIGES">
      <NameTxt>DARGHAL FIGES</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for External Affairs if it is true that the Irish Consulate at Paris has now passed into the care of the Irregulars; and, if this be so, if it is due to any neglect of the business intended to be done by him, when appointed to his office by this Dáil; and further, if it is true that any decision has been taken by the Executive Council on his advice, not communicated to this Dáil, that the external relations of the Saorstát with other countries, whether diplomatic or trade. be curtailed or ended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. FITZGERALD Mr. FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>The former Irish Trade Agent in Paris has now passed into the care of the Irregulars.  This is <Col N="1080" /> due solely to treachery on the part of the late Trade Agent.</P>
      <P>I have given no such advice, and the Executive Council has taken no such decision as that suggested in the last part of the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="JUDICIARY" RHead="COMMISSION">
    <Title>JUDICIARY COMMISSION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think an undertaking was given last week that I should announce the terms of reference to the Judicial Commission that has been set up.  The terms of reference are:&mdash;&ldquo;To advise the Executive Council of Saorstát Eireann in relation to the establishment in accordance with the Constitution of Courts for the exercise of judicial powers <Col N="1088" /> and the administration of justice in Saorstát Eireann, and the setting up of offices and other machinery necessary or expedient for the official conduct of legal business.&rdquo;  I will undertake to have that circulated to the members of the Dáil, but, I think we have undertaken to read it here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>If the President could also announce, as I believe a pledge was given to do so, the personnel of the Commission, perhaps this might be a fitting time to make a similar statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know whether it is in accordance with facts that we undertook to give the names.  I have not got them here at any rate.  This is a Committee set up to advise the Government on matters judicial.  I will see if I can get the names, and have them circulated also.  There was a matter I would like to ask permission to raise and that is with regard to the sittings of the Dáil.  I suggest for the consideration of the Dáil that we sit until 6 o'clock each evening instead of until 8.30 o'clock. It is a long sitting and it is rather difficult just now to arrange business.  It absorbs a good deal of the time, and if it meets with the convenience of members we propose to recommend that arrangement. It is only by agreement I expect that we could adopt that plan.  If we allow private members' business to be taken at 5 o'clock on Wednesdays and Fridays instead of 7.30, it would give one hour, and in that case, if agreeable to members, I propose to adjourn this evening at 6 o'clock, and take up whatever business is left over to-morrow at 3 o'clock.  I take it that the ordinary business before us this week will be the Enforcement of Law Bill, the District Justices Bill, and, possibly, we hope to be able by the end of the week to have the Malicious Injuries Bill circulated. It is also possible that a Temporary Provision Bill, as well as an Order in connection with the Revenue Board, will be laid for presentation on the table.  If there was general agreement I would propose that we adopt the plan recommended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not proposed to amend Standing Orders?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1089" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It could be arranged from week to week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>May I take it that in the event of the President's proposal being agreed to should there be a debate on the adjournment it would go on until 6.30?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that this is a matter that should be raised before the Committee on Procedure.  We are to meet to-morrow, and I would suggest that the advisable course would be for the Minister to give the Dáil some idea of the business he desires to be brought forward.  Private Deputies may have other business that they wish to bring forward, and they should also give notice, so that the Committee on Procedure could discuss the wisdom of having short meetings each day, and meet according to the Standing Orders. I do not think it is desirable to accept motions of this kind without some consideration beforehand of the whole of the business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is desired to adjourn any particular evening at any particular time, that can be done by motion.  It would be better if the Committee on Procedure considered the question of a change in the hour of meeting, and make a recommendation to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.  I take it there will not be any objection to moving the adjournment this evening at 6 o'clock.  Will that be agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That cannot be decided until the adjournment is moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a rather important matter.  When the Dáil sits, we come here at 3 o'clock. There are some who are not frequent in their attendance, but for those of us who are here it means that the day is broken. It would be more satisfactory and much better if we had not that amount of business that would employ us for the whole week, sitting from, say, 3 until 8.30 p.m.; that we should sit fewer days and longer hours in order to have the remaining days free for business that Deputies might be engaged in.  I do think it is a serious decision to take, that because you <Col N="1090" /> have not got the amount of work ready to keep us occupied the whole time, we should sit continually for a greater number of days, and pretend to be occupied, when we could sit fewer days and for a longer time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>No decision has been taken, except that the Committee on Procedure will consider the matter.  They can take the initiative. Meantime, the Orders of the Day can be taken now.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="INDEMNITY (BRITISH" RHead="MILITARY) BILL">
    <Title>INDEMNITY (BRITISH MILITARY) BILL.</Title>
    <P>(FROM THE SEANAD.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I have circulated a Resolution dealing with the following Resolution passed by the Seanad, 24th January, 1923:&mdash;&ldquo;That the consideration of this Bill be adjourned till every Irish prisoner under control of the British Government for a political offence connected with Ireland, in whatever country the offence may have been committed, has been released.  The status, political or otherwise, of each prisoner to be decided by a certificate of the Irish Government.&rdquo;  My Resolution reads:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That the Bill be recommended to Seanad Eireann, with the following message:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;&lsquo;Dáil Eireann again desires the agreement of Seanad Eireann to the Indemnity (British Military) Bill, 1923, and while appreciating the reasons stated by Seanad Eireann for adjourning consideration of the Bill, urges upon the Seanad that the object which both Houses have in view would be best attained by the speedy passage of the Bill into law.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have already dealt, I think, with most of the matters of importance that were raised as far as I could learn from the debate in the Seanad, and having put the case to the Dáil when the Bill was passed and sent to the Seanad, we know the circumstances of practically all those in whom the Senators have interested themselves in connection with this Bill. As I explained to the Dáil when putting the Bill before it on the last occasion, we believe the best interests of the parson <Col N="1091" /> ties will be served by the passing of the Bill.  As I was unable to attend the Seanad meeting the day the Bill was introduced, I propose that it be again sent to the Seanad, and I will attend there and recommend its passage into law.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, I should like to ask you if we have any authority whatever for considering a Resolution such as this, and the ground on which I base my point of order is this, that this Bill has been sent up from us to the Seanad.  It is now in the possession of the Seanad; it has not been sent back again to us and, being in the possession of the Seanad, I suggest to you that it is not in order for us, under any procedure that has been adopted, to give any attention to business that is not now before us but before the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to support this point of order.  It seems to me that this Dáil is disseized of this Bill altogether under the Constitution.  I should like to ask the Chairman to let the Dáil know exactly what communication, if any, has been received from the Seanad.  If a communication has been received asking this Dáil to deal with the matter that might alter the position, but if the Resolution passed by the Seanad has merely been communicated as a matter of courtesy to this Dáil, then I think we must go by the Constitution, which clearly provides that when this Dáil has done with the Bill it hands it on to the Seanad itself to consider it. The Seanad can hold the Bill up, if it thinks proper, for 270 days.  In the present case the Seanad has not yet rejected the Bill; it has declined to proceed with the consideration of the Bill until a certain event happened, and, dealing only for the moment with the Bill, on the point of order I submit that it would be a monstrous infringement of the privileges of the Seanad if this Dáil broke in upon them at this juncture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The communication from the Seanad will be read.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CLERK of the DAIL CLERK of the DAIL">
      <NameTxt>CLERK of the DAIL</NameTxt>
      <P>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;A Chara, &mdash;Reference the attached Indemnity (British Military) Bill, I have to inform you that Seanad Eireann has adjourned consideration <Col N="1092" /> of it, in accordance with a motion made by Senator Colonel M. Moore, seconded by Senator Butler Yeats, and passed by the Seanad on the 24th January, 1923.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I attach a copy of the motion which was passed by Seanad Eireann.</P>
    <P Just="Right">&ldquo;Is mise, le meas,</P>
    <P Just="Right">&ldquo;EMMET DALTON,</P>
    <P Just="Right">&ldquo;Cleireach an tSeanaid.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. T. JOHNSON Mr. T. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I assume that the copy of the motion which is alleged to have been passed is correctly printed in the Order Paper, but it contradicts&mdash;at least, it is different from&mdash;the report of the Resolution which was passed as printed in the Official Report of the debate. I do not know how the mistake has arisen, but it is rather a distinct change.  The report as printed in the Order Paper&mdash;presumably the report that was sent down to you from the Clerk of the Seanad&mdash;was the proposal that was first moved and then withdrawn. The motion which was passed was a different one.  I think that we are being asked to consider a certain proposal moved by the President on the basis of information which has been wrongly sent to us.  On the question of order, it seems to me that we have every right to pass any resolution that we wish, desiring the Seanad to do anything that we wish the Seanad to do, and that there is nothing out of order in our considering the motion that is down in the name of the President desiring that the Seanad will do certain things that they have not yet thought well to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Resolution as on the Order Paper is wrong.  It is not the Resolution passed by the Seanad finally; it is not the Resolution sent down by the Clerk of the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the question made by Deputy Figgis and Deputy Gavan Duffy is pressed, I would suggest for their consideration the object that, I am sure, both those had who objected to the passage of the Bill in the Seanad and those who passed the Bill here.  The object they have in mind is forgiveness to any person on the British side&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not this a point of order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1093" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but if I can prevail upon them to withdraw, I take it that your course would be easier, sir.</P>
      <P>There are people who are vitally concerned. One name was mentioned both here and in the Seanad&mdash;the name of Mr. Dowling.  There are others who, properly speaking, are not within the purview of pre-Truce prisoners, but for whom we hope to be able to get liberty. Now, we believe that the liberty of those people is best effected by the passage of this Bill, and as ours is the responsibility, I would ask, having regard to the circumstances of the case, that those objections should not be urged, and that the Resolution should be passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>In answer to the appeal made by the President, I only desire to say this, that the point of order having been brought to your attention, it would sooner or later have to be resolved.  When the Bill was before this Dáil I voted for it, and if the Bill were before the Dáil again I would vote for it; only I do remember an earlier incident which had arisen, in which certain matters happened between this House and the other House that led to a passage that was at least regrettable, and it would be still more regrettable if that passage were to recur.  I do think it might fairly be argued by the Chairman of the Seanad, seeing that the matter has been adjourned by them and not rejected, that it is still in their possession, and that it would be a grave questioning at least of their privileges if we were to trample upon them while they are still on the consideration of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I am concerned, I am prepared to say that what the President has said raises two quite distinct issues&mdash;one, the constitutional question, which is the main question which interested me in this matter&mdash; and I would urge the President not to persist with his Resolution on that ground.  But from a non-constitutional aspect he raises a question in which some of us have taken a very deep interest, and he asks us to believe that the release of Dowling and others will follow the course of action he proposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly not, I have said no such thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1094" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>He asked us to hope for the release of Dowling and others from the passing of the Amnesty Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask you not to lock them up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>But he has given us no facts whatever which would justify us, in my view, in assuming that any such result would happen.  Had I been here when this Bill was before the consideration of the Dáil I should have strongly opposed it, and I am extremely glad the Seanad has taken the action it has.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>We know where you are now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>On the point of order, the Resolution of the President as worded recommends this Bill to the Seanad and urges its speedy passage.  It is certainly a different thing from an indefinite adjournment.  I think the Dáil, if it chooses could send such a message to the Seanad.  The motion can, therefore, be seconded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. DESMOND FITZGERALD Mr. DESMOND FITZGERALD">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DESMOND FITZGERALD</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The correct terms of the motion passed by the Seanad are:&mdash;&ldquo;That the consideration of this Bill be adjourned to give the British Government the opportunity by a similar gracious act to release or transfer every Irish prisoner under its control for a political offence connected with Ireland in whatever country the offence may have been committed.  The status, political or otherwise, of each prisoner to be decided by a certificate of the Irish Government.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The message that was sent to Seanad Eireann with the Bill was &ldquo;Dáil Eireann has passed the Indemnity (British Military) Bill to which the agreement of Seanad Eireann is desired.&rdquo;  I regret the error on the Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>On this question I am speaking entirely for myself. As I understand the position, the Dáil on the initiative of the Ministry said that &ldquo;we are prepared to make a clean slate.&rdquo;  We are not doing anything in the nature of bargaining, and it is no use trying to bargain for the release of these prisoners, on the one <Col N="1095" /> hand and wiping out the offences on the other, but we think it is good for the State sometimes to adopt a Christian attitude.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That such an action on the part of the State may often evoke reciprocal Christian action on the part of another State.  That doctrine might be applied in other Departments as well as in International relations. There has been no bargaining, and it is undesirable that there should be any bargaining.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the view of the Ministry, and the Ministry knows the position much better than we do.  As the President has said, they have with all their knowledge given this advice that the Bill should be passed, and the Dáil has agreed to pass it.  The action of the Seanad is an indication of the mind of the Seanad.  Bearing in mind the Constitution of the Seanad, and whom it was established to represent, and especially the fact that this holding up was by unanimous vote, it has probably accomplished all that any other act could accomplish.  It has indicated to the British authorities that that body that might be considered to be a conservative loyalist body has definite views upon the release of prisoners.  Now, I think that all that could be done in the matter has been done by the Seanad, and if the attempt is made to hold this matter in abeyance, and refuse to pass this Bill until 270 days, or whatever the number may be, has expired, and if then it is forced through, any grace would have been lost, and even then you will not accomplish your object.  In all these circumstances I think the wise thing would be for the Dáil to agree with the resolution of the President.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>One point I wish to mention in connection with this to show that there are more things that we want to influence outside of what can be influenced in a purely formal way by doing a straight act and a generous act and saying we propose to pass the Indemnity Bill, and we will pass it like men.  Then, if the people on the other side of the question are not going to act <Col N="1096" /> like men, well, the disability is on their side, and this disability affects themselves, and does not affect us.  I had this morning a letter from a mother of a prisoner, who was apparently an English soldier two years ago.  He was an Irishman in the English army, and he is doing something like ten years penal servitude because of some offence committed during that time.  Now, we here may have some idea of what the general circumstances of Irish soldiers serving in the English army during the last three, four or five years were; we can easily imagine that there were circumstances in connection with the situation, the thought from the man's own mind, the mind of a man who is an Irishman in the British army, that might very easily be a strong influence in getting him into trouble from a purely disciplinary point of view, and that on the face of it could not be said before his immediate superior officers to be anything but a definite breach of discipline without any extenuating circumstances, such as the man's mentality, and because of the man's own thoughts on certain things that were happening at that time.  Some of us had hoped at any rate in passing this Indemnity Bill freely, frankly and fully that the people on the other side would be induced to do the same, and that we may come to a point at which they will, perhaps, look back over the list of the Irish prisoners that they have in their military prisons, or the military prisoners they may have in their jails who are Irish, and consider whether there are not among them men who, if the ordinary rules of procedure have to be adopted with regard to them, might have to spend 8 or 10 or 15 years in prison because of the trouble they got into on account of the fact that they had in the backs of their mind that they were Irish.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to this Resolution I feel myself in somewhat of a difficulty.  With regard to the original Bill and the substance of the original Bill, what Deputy Johnson has said I think very fairly and very adequately expresses the attitude that should be taken by this country towards England with regard to that matter.  What is right or wrong for us to do cannot be decreed by what the other man purposes to do.  If it is his intention to act in a churlish way, whether designed or not I <Col N="1097" /> do not know, that is his concern.  We cannot, because he desires to be churlish, let him enforce his churlishness upon us.  And for that reason I think the Bill should have passed, and might possibly have been passed by the Seanad too.  But far more important than any relations that exist between this and any other country are the relations that should exist between the two Houses of the Oireachtas.  For that reason I feel some diffidence in the matter of this Resolution, and I feel that the Seanad, having by a unanimous vote, representing whom they do, decided to defer this matter, I think it is correct, from rumours that one hears, that certain members of that body are representing to the British Government the liberation of the prisoners concerned pending their postponement.  Seeing that that is the case, I do feel it is a little over hasty to bring this Resolution forward quite so quickly as has been done.  You have ruled, and your ruling binds us all, that if we desire to bring a matter like this, and desire to propose such a Resolution, although the Seanad actually has at the moment the matter under consideration, it is within our right to do so.  That at once brings it within our rights, and although it may not be right for us to bring it in&mdash;it may not be quite tactful for us to have brought it in just at the moment&mdash;I do wish that this Resolution should be withdrawn, though I do think that the Seanad would have done more wisely had they passed this Bill as it was passed by this Dáil.  For the reason that I have stated, if the thing be right and generous for us to do, then it remains right and generous, and we cannot permit ourselves to be deflected from anything that we conceive to be our duty because the other man thinks that he may be able to get more advantage out of a churlish action of his own.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the purpose of the President being served by this discussion?  There is ample evidence that the Seanad reads the Official report of the debates in the Dáil.  Consequently it will have been brought under their notice that it is the desire of the President and the Government and their supporters to have those cases of prisoners dealt with as they ought to be dealt with.  If the motion is pressed, I shall <Col N="1098" /> feel myself in this predicament&mdash;we are creating an evil constitutional precedent. Repeatedly I have in my own small measure protested against the creation of precedents which our successors would not find it well to follow.  No doubt the creation of this Parliament has in it an element of originality.  And we are not bound to follow the procedure that is followed in other similar Assemblies. Still, let us remember this, that the Amnesty Bill is like any other Bill.  It is an Act of Parliament in process of becoming. When it has passed this Dáil it is sent to the Seanad for consideration. Now, let us bear in mind the peculiar relations of the Seanad to this Dáil.  By the Constitution the Seanad is authorised; in fact, the very essence of its existence is to be as I described it originally&mdash;a cooling chamber; a House in which legislation may be hindered and delayed for a period, a House in which, if I may change my metaphor, legislation is to be incubated for a longer time than it has undergone here.  If we now, when the Seanad in the exercise of its constitutional powers proceeds to delay, to hold up, this measure&mdash;if we now pass a Resolution calling upon it to speed up its operations because of reasons that appeal to us, no doubt, as you have ruled, we are within our powers in doing that.  But is it a good thing to do?  The question of policy is important.  Now, there is a second consideration which weighs with me.  The Senator who was the protagonist in this performance in the Seanad put forward an argument which I find for myself irresistible.  These prisoners were not English prisoners; they were British prisoners, and at the time in which they became prisoners Ireland was part of the United Kingdom.  It should follow in reason that they should be transferred to our custody after the Treaty.  We should be permitted to deal with them.  They should not be in English prisons.  I need not stop to say what an Irish Government would do with these men if the custody of them was so transferred.  I would suggest to the President that his purpose has been served by this discussion, and I would suggest, with all deference to his better wisdom, that we need not press this Resolution to the decision of a vote.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. FITZGIBBON Mr. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would very <Col N="1099" /> much regret if it was supposed to be the duty of the Members of the Dáil to read everything that occurs in the official reports of the Seanad in order to find out what the views of the Senators are.  I think it would be equally unfair to expect that the Seanad should toil through the reports of the debates here in order to find out what the views of this Dáil were about Bills that were being sent up to them.  There are, as I think everybody here knows, Standing Orders or Regulations of some kind in preparation for regulating the intercourse between the two Houses.  These have not yet been adopted.  I believe that they are under consideration in conjunction with some Committee from the Seanad&mdash;so that we may take it that they will be submitted to them at any rate&mdash;so that we may by mutual agreement devise some means of getting official information from one House to the other of circumstances which it is deemed advisable the second House, whichever it may be, should be fully informed about.  Those Regulations have not been completed yet, and now what has happened is this: We have sent up a Bill to the Seanad which is regarded by the Government, I suppose with justice, as a Bill that is rather urgent. The Seanad, not knowing what the views of this Dáil are, what the views of the Ministry are upon the subject, have adjourned it for a period, which may be 270 days.  As far as their Resolution goes, they have adjourned it <i>sine die</i>, until a certain event happens which may never happen.  At any rate, they have adjourned it.  In the absence of any Standing Orders of either House surely it is not unreasonable that we should give them information in the only way in which information can officially be conveyed, that is by a Resolution of this Dáil, conveyed by the Officer of this Dáil to the Officer of the Seanad, of what our views are upon this subject. I have no doubt that means will be devised, and that before very long, by which these things will be done without such a cumbrous method as we are adopting now.  At any rate until they are, the only way in which they can be informed of anything that happens here is by a Resolution passed here and properly conveyed to them.  It seems to me that <Col N="1100" /> the only ground upon which this Resolution could fairly be challenged would be that it amounted in form to a dictation to the Seanad of what they were to do. Looking at this Resolution I cannot see that it can be tortured by anybody into an attempt to dictate to them upon a matter that everybody must admit is entirely within their own power.  They can pass this Bill at once; they can reject it at once; they can postpone consideration for 270 days or whatever period it may be.  We are not asking them to do anything.  We are merely conveying to them the view of this Dáil that the object that both Houses have in view would be best attained by the speedy passage of this Bill.  That is only an expression of our opinion.  The only other question remaining is this&mdash; whether that is our honest opinion or not.  Upon that we have the assurance of the President.  We did not want that to-day, because we had the same assurance before we passed the Bill, when the same objection that has been raised in the Seanad was raised in this Dáil by some body.  I do not know who it was, but I have a distinct recollection that somebody suggested that we should postpone the passage of this Bill until the English Government had released, or had given a definite promise to release, these prisoners.  That objection was overruled because we accepted the assurance which the President gave us then, that the object of this Dáil would be best attained by passing this Bill, and showing to the English Government the attitude that we were prepared to adopt towards those people who were charged with offences against this country.  We have had that assurance repeated by the President here, and that being so, can we have any doubt that it is our opinion that this object would best be attained by the speedy passage of this Bill?  That being so, why should we not inform the Seanad courteously and officially that that is the opinion of this Dáil?  If they do not choose to act upon that opinion the responsibility, as far as the prisoners are concerned, rests with them.  But is it not our duty, if we believe that to be the fact, to let them know that that is our opinion?  They can reject our opinion if they please but I cannot myself see&mdash; you having ruled the question of order&mdash; any objection on the ground of form or policy to the passage of this Resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1101" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. W. DAVIN Mr. W. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think if all the members of the Dáil read in the Official Reports of the Seanad all the discussions that have taken place up to the present, they will find that we can blame ourselves for a discussion that took place here some time ago over the action of the Seanad in sending back this Bill.  I refer to the criticisms that were made in the Dáil when a discussion took place regarding two appointments made by the Seanad, their power to appoint certain officers, and the salaries they thought fit to offer.  In the discussion that took place in the Dáil on that particular occasion, some of us on these benches took the view that the Seanad had not been doing very much work, and, perhaps, they in their wisdom on this occasion, have sent back this Bill to the Dáil in order that we in turn might send it back to them, and give them another opportunity to do work that, up to the present. they have not got.  That is my view.  Perhaps for that reason alone it might be a very wise thing if we sent back the Bill to the Seanad, so that they might have a long drawn out discussion and prove to the people of this country that they are, if we give them the opportunity, willing to earn the salaries that we are prepared to give them. When generally looking over the Official Report of the Seanad this morning I noticed that the Chairman paid particular attention to remarks made by Deputy Professor Magennis and Deputy Johnson in regard to that particular thing.  How ever, I think none of us need be afraid of the precedent that is likely to be created by doing a certain thing in a certain way now.  Personally, I believe and hope that many of the things said in the Dáil and done outside of it in the country, will never be taken as a precedent by future generations as to what is right and what is wrong.  I hope, however, in passing this Resolution and sending it back to the Seanad to give them another day's work, that when it is passed the Seanad and the Dáil, as a result of its passage, will take into consideration the cases of the men who are prisoners in the hands of the Northern Government at the present time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. D.J. GOREY Mr. D.J. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I also support the Resolution put forward by the President. I have listened to Deputy Magennis describing the Seanad as a cooling chamber. <Col N="1102" /> I think he used that description when we were going through the Constitution; he repeated it to-day, and it is a description that I am in thorough agreement with.  It is an exact description of the other House.  I take it the holding up of this measure is more or less an assertion by the Seanad that it was something else than a cooling chamber. I think it is an attempt by the members of the other House to clothe themselves with an authority that they do not possess, and should not attempt to possess.  I think we are taking the other House too seriously, and the Dáil should now proceed to take a vote on the Resolution without further discussion.</P>
      <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DISTRICT JUSTICES (TEMPORARY" RHead="PROVISIONS) BILL">
    <Title>DISTRICT JUSTICES (TEMPORARY PROVISIONS) BILL.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the leave of the Dáil be granted to have printed and circulated a Bill, the long title of which is: &ldquo;A Bill to provide for the appointment of District Justices to hold Courts of Summary Jurisdiction and to make consequential alterations in the law relating to Courts of Summary Jurisdiction and for other purposes connected therewith.&rdquo; The short title of the Bill is: &ldquo;The District Justices Temporary Provisions Bill, 1923.&rdquo;  The Act may be cited as the District Justices (Temporary Provisions) Act, 1923.  There is nothing of a very startling nature in the Bill.  It regularises the position of existing District Justices.  Up to the present orders and decisions of theirs might have been quashed by a legal pedant on the grounds that they were given at other places and at other times than the statutory places and times.  In the past a Petty Sessions Court had a definite territoral jurisdiction, and an offence committed, however small a distance outside that territorial limit. could not be tried at that particular Petty Sessions Court.  It will be necessary to re-arrange the districts.  Further, the Bill provides for the appointment of people called Parish Commissioners.  I will simply state briefly the duties we propose to assign to those functionaries: <Col N="1103" />&mdash;Signing Petty Sessions summonses, signing warrants, administering oaths and taking declarations and affirmations, committing dangerous lunatics and idiots to lunatic asylums under Section 10 of the Lunacy Act, 1867, and signing certificates for the admission of pauper lunatics and idiots to lunatic asylums, These Parish Commissioners will also have certain remand powers.  They can remand a prisoner brought before them, charged with an indictable offence, on bail or in custody.  As it is not proposed to give them a judicial character, they will not have the power to refuse informations or power to discharge.  The Bill goes on to deal with the appointment of clerks to these District Courts, and provides that the Civic Guard shall hold the same relations with regard to District Courts which the old R.I.C. had, in the past, with the Petty Sessions Courts.  It also provides for an increase of the Petty Sessions fees which were arrived at a very long time ago, and are absurdly low, having regard to the present value of money.  With the exception of the dog tax, it is proposed to double all these fees.  A clause in the Bill confirms the appointment, and the acts since appointment, of all the present District Justices.  That is the Amnesty clause, which was considered unsuitable to be embodied in the Adaptation of Enactments Bill.  Then, there are definitions of some schedules.  I formally move for leave to introduce the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan) Patrick J. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I second that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>The wording of the Bill, as described in the Order paper I hold in my hand.  reads:&mdash;&ldquo;A Bill to provide for the appointment of District Justices to hold Courts of Petty Sessions, and to make consequential alterations in the law relating to Petty Sessions, and for other purposes connected therewith.&rdquo; That is somewhat different to the wording of the Bill as read out by the Minister. What I want to know is, if the appointments of the District Justices, whose names have been announced in the Press, are only of a temporary nature? If that is so, I would suggest to the Minister that, for reasons fairly well known to himself, the subordinate appointments should also be held up until the Second Reading of the Bill.  When will it be possible to take the Second Reading?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1104" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not quite sure that I understand the Deputy.  This is called &ldquo;The District Justices (Temporary Provisions) Bill.&rdquo;  The entire system of the administration of law in the country will pass under the review of the Judiciary Committee.  This is, merely, a carrying on provision, pending the report of the Judiciary Committee, and the legislation that must follow on that report.  The Justices that have been appointed are well aware that their positions are of a temporary nature, and carry no pension rights and no security of tenure.  The clerks appointed to their Courts are being appointed&mdash;all of them &mdash;for a probationary period of three months.  They are purely temporary appointments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Do I understand that the Minister for Home Affairs will accept direct responsibility for the appointment of the Clerks, or is it the District Justices, pending the passing of this Bill, who will have the making of the appointments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to that, I accept as much responsibility, as any Minister can possibly accept, for the thousand details of his Department. Taking it that there are a dozen or so clerks in each of the twenty-seven areas it gives a rather big total number.  I could not possibly weigh personally the rival claims and qualifications of the very numerous candidates, but I can say, in a general way, that such claims and such qualifications received very real and very earnest attention in my department, and, to that extent, I take political responsibility for these appointments. I could not undertake in the future&mdash;I do not say that I have done it in the past&mdash;to give close personal attention to matters of that kind which, after all, viewed in perspective, are trifling and unworthy of the personal attention of a Minister with so much work on his hands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate what the Minister has said with regard to the heavy task that he himself has in other more important matters, but, pending the passing of this Bill in its final form, is it to be understood that the District Justices have no share or responsibility in connection with the appointment of <Col N="1105" /> the clerks who will be called upon to do work of a temporary nature which may lead to something permanent in the end?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter which, in the ordinary course, should be put as a Question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The District Justices do no more than recommend to the Department, and it is the Department that has the responsibility.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That leave be granted to introduce the &lsquo;District Justices (Temporary Provisions) Bill.&rsquo;&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MONEY" RHead="RESOLUTION">
    <Title>MONEY RESOLUTION.</Title>
    <P>The following Resolution was submitted by the President:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;That it is expedient to authorise the payment out of moneys to be provided by the Oireachtas of the expenses incurred in relation to the employment under any Act of the present session of deputies for Under-Sheriffs and of persons to act as Bailiffs.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no provision, I think, at present in the Standing Orders for dealing with financial resolutions.  Bills which require the expenditure of public money must, as is indicated in the Constitution, be provided for by a Message from the Governor-General for such a purpose, and a Resolution must be passed.  In this case the Message has come.  I have handed it to the Ceann Comhairle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Has this Money Resolution been circulated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it proposed to take it now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, properly speaking, the Bill should not be introduced until a Money Resolution would be passed.  Really, a matter of this sort &mdash;a Bill which is a mixed Bill&mdash;will, I expect, have to be dealt with under the Standing Orders.  No such provision is made, but before a Bill of that sort, which entails the expenditure of public money, is passed an authorisation for that expenditure must be made by the <Col N="1106" /> Dáil, and the customary procedure will have to be adopted in the form of a Resolution like this in the first instance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a resolution asking us to incur expenses&mdash; at least, to authorise payment of expenses&mdash;in the case of a certain Bill before the Dáil passes it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>We have no knowledge at all that it will pass.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>But we are asked, even before the Dáil has gone into Committee stage, to authorise the payment of such expenses as will then be provided for.  I submit, a Chinn Chomhairle, that we ought to know something about the Bill before we authorise any payment of expenses.  We do not know yet whether any amendments will be made to it; we do not know whether we are going to add immeasurably to the expenses that will be incurred in this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputy is under a slight misapprehension with regard to it.  No such monies can be paid until the Bill itself is passed.  The Bill itself cannot be considered until an authorisation such as this has been passed.  One must get a Money Resolution passed first with regard to those Bills which entail an expenditure of public money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us be clear on this.  I think the President is under a misapprehension.  I think the clause of the Constitution to which he refers is the clause which provides that money shall not be appropriated for certain purposes without a Message before the passing of a Bill.  I submit that the passing of the Bill is one thing; the subsequent request to this Dáil for money to be appropriated is another.  I suggest to the President that the mere passing of the Bill is not in any way prohibited by the Constitution without reception of the Message first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot pass a Bill which entails the spending of money until you have provided that money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1107" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit that the President is under a misapprehension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a fact that you cannot undertake to spend money until you have provided the money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>We have practically incurred the expenditure of money on the Electoral Bill.  We have gone through Committee on the Electoral Bill, and we have not yet, so far as I know, passed a Resolution authorising the payment out of monies to be provided in respect of the Electoral Bill.  If the argument that the President uses now in one case is true, it is true in the case of the Electoral Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would direct your attention to the fact that you will find an entry in the Estimates we have already passed for the Electoral Bill or for the expenses that will be incurred in connection with the Electoral Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not undertaking anything of the kind.  I suggest that the resolution can come later on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>This resolution has only been placed in my hands now.  It is unfair that I should be asked to deal with these matters without any notice whatsoever.  I have not had any opportunity of consulting any lawyer as to what the Constitutional position is about this resolution.  The President presumably has had such an opportunity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is in order to keep you right I brought it forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to be kept right by being kept right in time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been advised by the Law Officer that this is the proper course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It would have been more courteous to pass on that advice&mdash;the advice of the Law Adviser&mdash;before the matter was brought up in the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the matter can be settled in this way. The Bill that we are going through to-day <Col N="1108" /> has to go through several readings. The President's point can be met if he brings the matter forward before the Final Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I have made that suggestion to the President already.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been advised that this must be passed before the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We had better take this as a notice of motion for to-morrow and postpone the Committee stage of the Bill.  Is the Minister going on now with the Enforcement of Law (Occasional Powers Bill)?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is inadvisable to postpone the Committee stage.  The Bill is urgent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the final stages be taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>As soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not proposed to finish the Committee stage to-day.  It is proposed to adjourn at 6 o'clock.  That has been suggested already. The Committee Stage could not be finished until to-morrow.  Could not this resolution be taken then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>It is impossible to say how long the Committee Stage will take.  Simply, the position is that it is rather desirable that the Bill should go through in as short as possible space of time.  I say that, without any wish to limit the discussion on it here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The resolution as it stands is:&mdash;&ldquo;That it is expedient to authorise the payment out of monies to be provided by the Oireachtas of the expenses to be incurred in relation to the employment under any Act of the present session of deputies for Under-Sheriffs and of persons who act as bailiffs.&rdquo;  It seems that unless an Act is passed providing for deputies for Under-Sheriffs or persons who act as bailiffs, you cannot spend any money. It would not seem, therefore, very wrong to provide the money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>If this matter is going to be pressed, I am going to ask <Col N="1109" /> you to rule whether this is in order or not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>No resolution is in order unless four days' notice has been given of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, you are aware that there is no provision in the Standing Orders for financial resolutions or financial business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that a financial resolution is a resolution that is provided for in the Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I would suggest that as there is a difficulty in proceeding to pass a law for certain things that would involve the expenditure of moneys that are not available, that seems to be the case for the resolution preceding the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not possible, I should say, having regard to the circumstances of the Dáil, and to the fact that we are not experienced in those matters, to produce to the Dáil in apple-pie order every resolution that comes up.  I learned of this matter to-day.  I got advice at the earliest possible moment.  You are not committed to the Bill by passing this resolution, but I was advised by the Finance Ministry that it is not right to go on with the Bill until this resolution is passed.  You may reject the Bill&mdash; absolutely reject it&mdash;but, in order to make the way clear for consideration of the Bill, this resolution should be passed. If there is any fault in the matter, I accept it.  The fault is mine, but I wish to put the Dáil right, and to keep the Ceann Comhairle right with regard to this matter.  I would very much regret if we induced the Ceann Comhairle to commit himself to a ruling on this point without notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Ceann Comhairle has been asked precisely to do this, and asked by the President.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>Either this Resolution should have been introduced before the Bill was introduced at all, or before the second reading, or it can come up before it is finally passed.  We <Col N="1110" /> have already got through the second reading; therefore the Resolution did not matter.  What provision is there in the Constitution that it should come up before the Committee stage?  I have asked the President to say what section of the Constitution he is relying on. When he raises an important constitutional point&mdash;a matter of finance&mdash; surely the Dáil is entitled to know where his doctrine comes from.  I suggest that if we go on with the Bill no harm can be done, and the President can introduce his Resolution before the Final Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that the Ministry and the Dáil and yourself, sir, ought to be better judges, better exponents, of what is right constitutionally in respect of the Dáil than the advisers of the Ministry.  If we go wrong, the responsibility then will be the responsibility of the Dáil.  Article 37 of the Constitution, which I presume is the one in question, has no bearing on this case at all.  It says: &ldquo;Money shall not be appropriated by vote, resolution, or law, unless the purpose of the appropriation has in the same session been recommended by Message from the representative of the Crown, acting on the advice of the Executive Council.&rdquo;  In passing this Bill we are not appropriating monies; therefore there is no harm in going ahead with the Bill and discussing this Financial Resolution entirely independently.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee stage of the Bill can be proceeded with and the Resolution taken afterwards, or the Resolution can be taken to-morrow before the Committee stage by leave of the Dáil.  Will that meet the case?  Either that, or take the Committee stage now and take this Resolution afterwards.  There will be no objection, I take it, by special leave, to our taking this as notice of motion now, and taking it up to-morrow or at such time as we shall have finished the Committee stage.  Does the President propose to continue the Committee stage now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I to take it, that the Dáil or yourself will not agree to this Resolution being proposed now?&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Motion withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - ENFORCEMENT" RHead="OF LAW (OCCASIONAL POWERS) BILL">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - ENFORCEMENT OF LAW (OCCASIONAL POWERS) BILL.</Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1111" /> SECTION 1.</P>
    <P>(1)  For the purpose of the application of Section 11 of the Adaptation of Enactments Act, 1922 (No. 2 of 1922) to Section 1 of the Sheriffs (Ireland) Act, 1920 (10 &amp; 11 Geo. V., ch. 26), the member of the Executive Council for the time being Minister of Home Affairs shall be deemed to be the Minister or authority exercising in Saorstát Eireann functions the same as or corresponding to the functions which prior to the 6th day of December, 1921, were in the area now comprised in Saorstát Eireann exercised by the Lord Lieutenant under the said Section 1 of the Sheriffs (Ireland) Act, 1920, and accordingly all the powers conferred by the said Section 1 shall be vested and exercisable by such member of the Executive Council and the expression &ldquo;the Minister&rdquo; wherever the same occurs in this Act means such member of the Executive Council.</P>
    <P>(2)  No oath of office or other oath shall be administered to or required to be taken by any person appointed after the passing of this Act to be Under-Sheriff but in lieu thereof every person so appointed shall before entering on his office subscribe and make a solemn declaration in a form to be prescribed by an order of the Minister that he will duly perform the duties of his office, and Section 14 of the Statute 12 George I., c. 4 (Irish), shall be read as if the making by every Under-Sheriff of the Declaration so to be prescribed were substituted for the taking of the Oath prescribed by that Section and for the making of the Declaration prescribed by the Sheriffs (Ireland) Adaptation of Enactments Order, 1922.</P>
    <P>(3) If the Minister shall be at any time satisfied that any Under-Sheriff is by reason of illness, unavoidable absence, or for any cause whatever unable, or is unwilling, to perform the functions or properly to discharge the duties of his office for the time being, then and in that case the Minister may appoint any person (whether a person possessing the qualifications prescribed by Sub-section (3) of Section 1 of the Sheriffs (Ireland) Act, 1920, or not) to act as deputy for such Under-Sheriff during such time and upon <Col N="1112" /> such terms as the Minister may by Order specify, and the person so appointed shall for the purposes of any and every power authority immunity and protection given by law to the Under-Sheriff be deemed to be the Under-Sheriff for the same bailiwick, and all writs decrees and other documents in the hands of the Under-Sheriff for execution shall be forthwith handed over to such deputy, who shall deal with the same in all respects as if he were a lawfully appointed Under-Sheriff.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move Section 1.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To substitute for the words, lines 44, 45, 46, &ldquo;(whether a person possessing the qualifications prescribed by Sub-section (3) of Section 1 of the Sheriffs (Ireland) Act, 1920, or not),&rdquo; the words &ldquo;having the qualifications for the time being prescribed by law for an Under-Sheriff.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The position is this.  At present the Under-Sheriffs, who have very much less power than the substitutes appointed under this Bill to do their work, who will be autocrats, must be either people who have been Under-Sheriffs before, or solicitors or barristers of five years' standing, or people who have been managing. clerks to Under-Sheriffs for five years.  In other words, it has been thought necessary before you make men Under-Sheriffs that you make certain that they have a clear idea of what their duty in that office is.  When you are setting up what I take it is a new office and a new officer with very much more extensive and arbitrary powers than anything which the Under-Sheriff ever had, it is doubly necessary that this Dáil should be quite certain that the gentleman to be appointed shall be a properly qualified person.  I do not mind much what the qualifications are.  If we do not like one class of person, we may put in some other, but the Bill as drafted enables a Minister to appoint any person, and we all know that it is not the Minister for the time being who does this thing, but some particular clerk in the Home Office who has charge of these appointments, and this gentleman is to be allowed to appoint anyone he wishes. <Col N="1113" /> But before this it was expressly laid down that the Under-Sheriff should have certain qualifications.  Now, I am not saying that it may not be necessary to appoint people outside the ordinary Under-Sheriff.  We may have to do that, but we ought to know what type of man the Minister proposes to appoint, and it has been said that considerable criticism has been aroused by the suspicion that military men were to be appointed as Under-Sheriffs, and the Minister was invited to disclaim any such ideas, and I hope he does not entertain them. Although in extreme cases I appreciate the necessity of meeting force on the part of a judgment debtor by force on the part of a judgment creditor, yet I do not see any reason why the Under-Sheriff himself, or the person whom the Minister appoints in his place should be military men, and I see very strong reasons why the Army should be kept out of that kind of office.  Therefore I hope the Minister will have no difficulty in accepting the principle that the man who takes the place of a Sheriff must be a person with definite qualifications, and as I say, if the Government does not like the qualifications I mention, let them put down others, but let them put down something definite, and not let this Bill provide that any person may be appointed as a Sheriff.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot meet Deputy Gavan Duffy on that amendment. I cannot agree that the position is not one which demands considerable freedom of choice in the selection of a deputy for the Under-Sheriff, should it become necessary to select a deputy at all.  The present qualifications for an Under-Sheriff are, that one must be a solicitor of 5 years' standing.  In any given county there may not be an embarrassing number of solicitors of 5 years' standing, and solicitors and barristers are as a class a nervous body, unsuited to the robust times in which we live.  If it became necessary in your hunt for a solicitor of 5 years' standing to take a man from some other county which would involve the giving up of his business, the expense to the State would be very considerable.  It is not now merely a question of finding a solicitor of five years' standing, but it may be a question of finding a solicitor of 5 years' <Col N="1114" /> standing and having a high degree of personal courage and civic virtue. Deputy Figgis invited me to disclaim a certain very preposterous suggestion, which he said he had heard outside.  I have no doubt Deputy Figgis hears many things and many preposterous things outside, but I consider it no part of his duty to come in here and demand a disclaimer of these things, and no part of my duty to concede to such demands.  I must ask that in this matter the freedom which that provision leaves, be left to the responsible Minister.  The position is, and the Deputy who has down this amendment knows it, that that provision is in that Bill to meet the condition of personal terrorism which I will not say prevails, but which does exist to a certain extent in the country: terrorism by murder, terrorism by arson, terrorism in a thousand mean and cowardly forms.  I could not guarantee to be able to find a sufficient number of solicitors of 5 years' standing to stand up to circumstances of that kind, but I can guarantee that if that provision is left as it is, the appointment of deputies will be a matter that will receive my personal attention.  With regard to the contention of Deputy Gavan Duffy that some clerk in an office will have charge of those matters, I have only to say that I hope, in the headship of my department, I have a sense of proportion, and realise the things that are important and call for personal attention and supervision, and that I give that personal attention and supervision.  This is a matter that will receive my personal attention and supervision, and if it becomes necessary to select deputies for Under-Sheriffs I shall exercise the discretion which the matter deserves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor WILLIAM MAGENNIS Professor WILLIAM MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor WILLIAM MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am disposed to support the amendment were it not for the fact that after the speech of the Minister it would seem to be a reflection upon what he has just now given in the nature of a personal undertaking: that is, that he would consider it to be a cardinal duty of his office to select the Deputy, or to see that a proper person is selected as deputy Under-Sheriff.  Supporters of the measure described it as drastic.  The Minister who introduced it claimed that it would be a measure of rigorous compulsion upon defaulting debtors.  That was <Col N="1115" /> the sense of his recommendation, although I do not recall that he used those words.  Now, I should like to mitigate the rigour of this very drastic measure in certain respects, which shall arise for our specific consideration later on.  There is a middle course between that proposed by the Minister and that recommended in the amendment. The Minister proposes to do away with the qualifications hitherto exacted, and he has made a very excellent and, to me, a very convincing case for that, because, in the original, it is set out that among the various cases that would occur for appointing a deputy for the Under-Sheriff are cases in which the Under-Sheriff is unwilling&mdash;not that he is unwell&mdash;but unwilling to discharge his functions.  So that the Minister is undoubtedly correct in saying that what he would have to look for was not so much a solicitor of so many years' standing, as a man possessed of moral and civic courage.  But he did not suggest the necessity for qualifications, and for demanding certain qualifications to be possessed by those who would be appointed Deputy Under-Sheriffs. I have no doubt he would reply that, before selecting any such persons, he would satisfy himself as to their fitness, but I felt on the occasion of the second reading of this Bill that we were upon a slope, and sliding down a very slippery slope, in this particular measure.  We were told that, no doubt, a great many things which might happen, and conceivably could happen, under this legislation would not happen, because such and such a Minister would not permit it to happen.  I am afraid if that became the practice, as regards the passing of laws in this Dáil that, while we recognise the potentiality in our legislation of injustice, or, to put it more mildly, elements of infirmity in our legislation, yet we may proceed onwards in the passing of it with a light heart, because we rely upon the integrity and vigilance and sense of justice of our Ministers in control of the executive functions. That is substituting arbitrary government of Ministers for democratic rule, and I think in the name of democracy it is necessary to warn my colleagues against too much reliance upon the pledges of Ministers, notwithstanding the obvious character of the Minister <Col N="1116" /> as one in whom the most implicit faith might be put.  It is not a question of personality here; it is a question of principle. I am perfectly satisfied that the Minister for Home Affairs would never appoint anyone as deputy to the Sheriff who would not be a proper man for the discharge of the extraordinary powers that are to be given to him under this Act.  But I do not like the principle; I do not like assenting to the doctrine&mdash; for it may be applied later in regard to other measures.  No doubt this is only to hold good for six months, but the thing will be on historical record that in an emergency we were so carried away by the desire to overcome the inherent difficulties of the position that we were willing to subscribe to this doctrine&mdash; that we were prepared to give unqualified discretionary powers to a Minister to eke out the insufficiencies or defects of a particular measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy, I presume, is very nearly three score years of age (Mr. Darrell Figgis&mdash;No.) and for all but three years of that time while occupying the position of a citizen of Dublin, he has grown under the very thing that he is now objecting to, by having a person appointed as Sheriff to the City of Dublin who, at his own sweet will, always appointed the Under-Sheriff for the City of Dublin. And he never knew he was under any such grievance until this morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. P. HOGAN Mr. P. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not going to make this a measure of democracy or of anti-democracy.  This is merely proposed as a mere emergency measure, and all we propose to do is to give the Minister discretion to appoint Under-Sheriffs if the necessity arises.  Any person who occupies the position of Minister for Home Affairs has to make a great many appointments, in the ordinary course, which are much more responsible and difficult than appointments of the sort contemplated by a Bill of this kind.  The question of such appointments is not likely to arise on more than two or three occasions.  We all admit that this is a matter where you should choose the man that suits the circumstances of the occasion. I agree with Deputy Magennis that, in normal times, it would be essential to have the qualifications of any appointment, big or small, set out definitely <Col N="1117" /> in an Act of Parliament.  We are not living in normal times, but we are living in times that are rather abnormal, and it is necessary, if I may say so, to strengthen the Executive Government, and it is a democratic thing to do.  And it is simply an abuse of language to pretend that the vesting of one or two appointments of this kind in a Minister of Home Affairs is doing something that is undemocratic.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and negatived.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret being compelled to have to ask permission of the Committee to make an insertion in Sub-Section 3 of Section 1, that is, after the word &ldquo;time&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;at such remuneration (to be paid out of moneys provided by Oireachtas&rdquo;), so that the lines would read:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Then and in that case the Minister may appoint any person (whether a person possessing the qualifications prescribed by Sub-Section 3 of Section 1 of the Sheriffs (Ireland) Act, 1920, or not), to act as deputy for such Under-Sheriff during such time, at such remuneration (to be paid out of moneys provided by Oireachtas), and upon such terms as the Minister may by order specify, and the persons so appointed shall for the purposes of, etc., etc.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That will be covered by the money resolution subsequently.  I thought that the money resolution would be passed first.  If it becomes necessary to appoint a deputy to the Under-Sheriff there would be no fund available at the moment to pay him, and it will be necessary to pay him from a central fund from the Treasury.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is the Under-Sheriff paid by now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the County Borough Councils and the County Councils pay him under the Act of 1920.  The Under-Sheriff for Co. Dublin is paid £350 a year, those for other Boroughs £250, and those for the Counties £200.  &ldquo;The following sums shall be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament to the Under-Sheriffs appointed under this Act.&rdquo;  Portion is paid by the Co. Council and portion by the Government. In this case I do not expect that the <Col N="1118" /> County Councils will put up the extra proportion, and it is proposed to provide it by the Oireachtas.  That is the need for the insertion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that the Under-Sheriff at present as contemplated under this Bill is to continue to draw his money whether he acts or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It depends on circumstances I should say.  If he does not act I do not see how he will be drawing his money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Then, why do you appoint a deputy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Unable,&rdquo; or &ldquo;rendered unable.&rdquo;  It is quite a different matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Or &ldquo;unwilling.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that permission is given to have this amendment moved.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I now put the amendment.  &ldquo;Section 1, Sub-Section 3, Line 47, after the word &lsquo;time&rsquo; to insert the words &lsquo;at such remuneration (to be paid out of the moneys provided by the Oireachtas).&rsquo;&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>As that amendment is passed would Ministers not see their way consequentially to delete the words &ldquo;is unwilling&rdquo; higher up?  It seems to me scarcely reasonable that a Sub-Sheriff might simply decline, as the section says, properly to discharge the duties of his office, and saddle the State with the remuneration of his deputy.  I can quite understand where he is ill, unavoidably absent, or from reasonable cause unable to perform his duties that he should not be dismissed, but some temporary substitute should be appointed, and, of course, paid.  The insertion of the word &ldquo;entitled&rdquo; by the mere expression of his unwillingness properly to discharge his duties and to saddle the State with a substitute, so that two stipends would be paid to two men for the same work, one who is doing the duty, and the other, who refuses to do it, would be unreasonable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1119" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The force of &ldquo;unwilling&rdquo; there is simply this.  It might not be possible physically for the Under-Sheriff to perform his duties, and in that sense it could not be said that he was unable, yet the conditions might be such that he was terrorised, and consequently unwilling to take the risk of performing his duties.  In such circumstances where one man a civil officer, whose duty it is to perform certain work, refuses, it might be a matter of great difficulty, it might be a matter of impossibility to secure precisely that same class of man with the same qualifications to undertake the work.  While it would be a matter for consideration whether an officer who is unwilling to perform his work ought not to be summarily removed from office the question of filling that office with a man of just the same kind of stereotyped qualifications might be one of great difficulty at the time.  I do not know whether the Deputy quite understands what I mean, but it might be physically impossible for a man to perform the duties of his office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>It would meet my view if the Minister instead of saying that an unwilling man be dismissed, provided that during his unwillingness a substitute should be paid out of his salary.  It is only to provide against two men being paid for the one office.  I do not want the Sub-Sheriff dismissed.  This is only a temporary Bill, and if he says &ldquo;through terror or other reasonable cause I would rather be relieved of the duties for the present&rdquo; why should he draw his pay? He should transfer his stipend to a man willing to do the duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We have added something on line 47, and it is difficult to go back, but if Ministers would give consideration to the points raised before the next reading, or if the Deputy would put in an amendment it would meet the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest to the Ministers that where unwillingness is the cause the unwilling man should be liable to pay his substitute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>It puts the answer, &ldquo;can't&rdquo; and the answer &ldquo;shan't&rdquo; on precisely the same level, <Col N="1120" /> and in doing so it puts a premium on fear.  Why should any Under-Sheriff run any risk whatever if by declining on the ground of unwillingness he is no worse off?  I do not think that that is a very good method of administration.  I quite see the point which the Minister has made of distinguishing between two kinds of incapacity.  It is not necessary a man should be physically unable, but he may from the circumstances be morally unable.  The word &ldquo;unwilling&rdquo; means of his volition he declines, not from pressure of exterior circumstances, but as an inward decision of his own.  Undoubtedly it would be a wrong thing to leave him precisely as he stands if he were to shirk the discharge of an unpleasant or difficult duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>A man unwilling to perform the duties of any particular office should not be allowed to remain in that office, but if circumstances arose, where the individual expressed himself unwilling to perform the duties attaching to his office&mdash;circumstances that might be such as would render it difficult to get a successor in the real sense of the word&mdash;that is, with exactly the same qualifications, to be appointed to the office under the same tenure, it would be wise to have the power that this Clause gives to appoint a person to carry on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I suspect that there might be an added reason for the amendment as it stands, and for refusing to accept the suggestion that was made, that the Sheriffs have been appointed under certain statutory powers which define their duties.  You are entitled to pay them, or they are entitled to draw from the public purse certain moneys under that authority.  You are going to enlarge the duties of that office, and give the holders more formidable, more unpleasant, work to do, and put upon them the duties of a bully, rather than the duties of semi-gentlemen; and consequently they may be unwilling to accept these added responsibilities, but you will be bound to pay their salaries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the amendment standing in my name:&mdash;<Col N="1121" />&ldquo;At the end of Sub-Section (3) to add &mdash;Provided that every such order shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas forthwith, and unless and until a resolution is passed by either House of the Oireachtas within the next subsequent seven days on which that House has sat after such order is laid before it annulling such order, such order shall have effect.&rdquo;  I do not stand over the wording, which is curious.  It is the official wording taken from the official draftsman, as adopted by him in certain early Acts passed by this Dáil.  I am certainly inclined and delighted to find that the President agrees with me that the official draftsman is not a very good one.  The substance of the amendment, apart from the awkwardness of the wording, is practically to meet the point we had brought out by several Deputies, but to put it in a milder form.  There is a considerable power exercised under this Clause, as it stands, by the Minister, and if this Bill be a right Bill&mdash; the substantial Bill that it should be&mdash;and if it is passed by this Oireachtas, and be of a temporary nature, it is inevitable that the Minister should exercise certain powers, as it were, out of hand; but it is also necessary, and it meets the point raised by Professor Magennis, that the Dáil should have some knowledge of what was happening in that matter.  I think I agree with the Minister in the argument he has brought forward that it might be difficult to find a solicitor with the requisite amount of experience required by the statutes for the fulfilment of the Under-Sheriff's duties.  I think, when he said it might be difficult to find a solicitor of 5 years' training, with the necessary civic duty, that was a little hard on his own profession, but, perhaps, that was a little slip of words on his part.  I do urge that there are powers conferred which require to be watched, and which the Minister should desire the Dáil to watch.  I mentioned here, when this Bill was before us for Second Reading, that it had been stated, and in quarters not ordinarily subject to rumour, that it was the intention to appoint military officers, and the Minister suggests that a rumour such as that should not be repeated in the Dáil.  I hold a very contrary view of the Dáil from the Minister, apparently.  I believe this is the place <Col N="1122" /> where the nation should hear authoritative statements, and I did put forward a rumour on the Second Reading, expecting confidently that at the end of the discussion the Minister would have taken the opportunity of knocking it on the head.  He did not, and it spread since then.  His disclaimer to-day will, I hope, be accorded the same currency that the rumour originally got.  In any case, whatever kind of person, or whoever should be appointed, it would be a good thing for the Dáil if it was kept informed of the persons being appointed.  I can realise that it would be difficult to expect extended notice to be given, and therefore I have kept the amendment as short as I could under the circumstances&mdash; 7 days instead of 21 days that we have put into similar clauses in other Acts.  I hope the Minister will consider this amendment, because I believe it is a sound democratic principle in the first place, and in the second place I believe it will lead to public confidence, and I hold that the two reasons are not wholly unconnected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I must still differ with Deputy Figgis on the question as to whether the Dáil is the proper place or not to retail gossip.  I understand that a restaurant is being started in connection with the Oireachtas, and whenever such a restaurant is started, I would be glad, over a glass of soda water and milk, to answer such questions as Deputy Figgis has raised.  This amendment I do not intend to say much about, as it is more or less in the nature of a vote of no confidence in myself.  I think, if I am fit or qualified for the position I hold, such a matter as the appointment of a deputy for an Under-Sheriff, under certain conditions which would incapacitate such an Under-Sheriff, from acting, is a matter which might very well be left to my notorious discretion.  If Deputy Figgis is inclined to press this amendment, and if there is any enthusiastic following behind it in the Dáil, well then, with the best grace I could muster, I would bow to that wave of emotion, provided that the order appointing a deputy to the Under-Sheriff&mdash; I expect that is what Deputy Figgis is aiming at&mdash;shall have effect unless and until repealed by law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going to vote for this amendment if it is pressed <Col N="1123" /> to a vote, as an alternative&mdash;a poor alternative&mdash;but still, an alternative to my own.  I say a poor alternative, because I think the other one was considerably clearer.  It is a pity that Ministers are apt to take these matters as personal.  Now, the Minister for Home Affairs must realise that when this Bill is an Act it will have quite a long life&mdash;six months, I think, it provides for. A number of things could happen in six months.  That is why, when he gives personal undertakings about what he will do, he is not really meeting the point of the objection.  It is not a question of any individual Minister.  It is a question of putting into the power of a Ministry that may be&mdash;not, of course, under the present dispensation, but under another one&mdash;a dangerous power, and, therefore, I am sorry that the Minister did not accept my amendment. I am going to vote for this one, unless he saves us the trouble of going to a vote by graciously agreeing to it himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Anyone who is qualified for the headship of the Home Affairs Department, or anyone that the Dáil or a President would put into that position, ought to be capable of exercising the amout of discretion which is necessary to the proper appointment of a deputy for an Under-Sheriff.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am rather surprised that this amendment should have been pressed.  What does it amount to? If the necessity should arise, I take it that the appointment should be made without delay, if you are to carry into effect the real purpose of this Bill.  It is said that this Bill is drastic.  Certain machinery has been found ineffective, by reason of the fact that the central authority was weakened and the circumstances arising from the weakness of the central authority are well known to everybody, and it requires strengthening.  What is required is that an order appointing each Sub-Sheriff should be laid on the Table, and each Sub-Sheriff so appointed, if at all, shall be a cockshot for everybody over the county.  Is not that really what it means, that you want an advertisement for the person appointed to take up a responsible position in each county to carry out the laws that are given in your Courts functioning under the name <Col N="1124" /> of this Dáil?  It is an unreasonable proposition, and I do not think that it ought to be pressed.  For many years the central authority in this country, not having the support of the people behind it, made appointments of Sheriffs all over the country every year.  No exception was taken to this method of appointment. A democratic assembly is set up, and certain people are entrusted with authority, and somebody must carry out certain regulations.  Those people, find it necessary to assert the authority that everybody here wishes to see asserted, an exception is taken to it, and certain people think that an advertisement&mdash;probably with a photograph of each Under-Sheriff, should any be so appointed&mdash;should appear in the Press. That would not tend towards the purpose that we have in view.  It would not be any improvement on the machinery, and it is more than possible that it would damage the usefulness of the person so appointed, because some debtor in the particular county in which he was appointed would probably write to every single representative of the constituency and say: &ldquo;You ought to object to So-and-so being appointed, and if you get him knocked out it will take them another week to appoint another, and we will see if we can get him knocked out in the same way.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The President has just used a word which has been used several times in regard to the position of this Dáil&mdash;that it was opposed because it is too drastic.  As far as I and the Deputies on this side are concerned, it is not opposed because it is too drastic.  It is opposed because it is too drastic in the wrong direction; it is putting a premium upon rough and tumble or &ldquo;rough and ready law,&rdquo; as the Minister for Agriculture described it, irregularism under the guise of the law.  It is because of that that the Bill is opposed from these Benches, and not because it is drastic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>But surely it is not put up by the Deputy who has just spoken that this particular feature is Irregularism?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I got in what I wanted to say on the Bill as a Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1125" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I know.  When a man gets a decree in the Courts&mdash;because the expenses of keeping up the Courts is paid out of his taxation&mdash;he gets a decree and finds that it is not possible for the Sheriff of his county or the Under-Sheriff of his county to present him with the amount so awarded in the Court.  We seek to set up certain machinery.  If there be a defect in it&mdash; if it be thought that out of a panel some suggestion could be made whereby you would have a list of more competent persons than it is possible for the Executive to appoint&mdash;there is some sense in criticising this proposal, or asking that such an order should be put on the Table. But no such suggestion has come forward, and everybody knows that at this moment the more criticism that there is of the manner in which administration is carried out by the central authority, the more Irregularism is bred.  The sense of suspicion that there is in the Dáil through certain persons&mdash;I do not mean to say all of the Deputies &mdash;is bred right through the country, and people say: &ldquo;Surely if their own friends suspect appointments such as these there must be something wrong.&rdquo; I cannot see any sense in the amendment; I cannot see how it improves the Bill; I cannot see how it renders it less drastic, as some Deputies have mentioned, and I do not see how it will effect the purpose that Deputy Figgis has in his mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. P. HOGAN Mr. P. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson describes this Bill generally as irregularism under the guise of law.  This Bill sets out exactly the powers of Sub-Sheriffs and defines them, and does no more than to take steps to give the Sub-Sheriff effective support in carrying out what he is asked to do, and that is described by Deputy Johnson as irregularism under the guise of law.  This is a Bill to make the law effective.  It is a Bill to ensure that when a County Court Judge comes down to any county and gives a decree to any man who is owed money for the goods he sold across the counter, that that decree shall be effective, and that is what is described as irregularism under the guise of law. That is a misuse of language.  Now with regard to rough-and-ready law&mdash;rough-and-ready law is better than no law at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1126" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Ku Klux Klan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>With much of what the President has said I might be in agreement.  This Bill has been described as a drastic one, and a Deputy described it as ferocious.  If it be drastic, if it be ferocious, these qualities in it will be exercised by certain persons who will act either as Under-Sheriffs, or who will act on behalf of these Under-Sheriffs. The provisions themselves as they are put into effect will, or will not, be tempered by the persons who put them into effect, and for that reason it is of the very first importance that this Dáil should see that the right persons are appointed for these positions.  When I urge that, the Minister for Home Affairs replies with a pleasing mixture of humour and asperity.  I object neither to humour nor asperity&mdash;I am always willing to retort with both when they are required. He says that this is a motion of no confidence. It was not so proposed, but seeing that he has evoked the taunt I think the thought is eminently justified, because appointments have been made in the country that have been defended in the Dáil&mdash;appointments of profit and suggestions for appointments&mdash;and the Ministry must know, and the Dáil must know, that these appointments and these suggestions have aroused no confidence whatever in the country, and for the reason that was stated by the Official Whip for the party, for whom the Minister speaks, and that is that they are proposing to find jobs for the fighting men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that this amendment shows no sense of proportion, and, moreover, I am inclined to think that it probably indicates that the Deputy who proposed it did not scrutinise very carefully the Clause he proposes to amend.  As far as I can see the Order will specify the time and terms of remuneration upon which a deputy to the Under-Sheriff may be appointed. Now the time must be less than 6 months, and as to the remuneration the Dáil will have an opportunity to review that when it is providing money, because the Dáil will have to pass some form of resolution providing the money.  The terms, I think, can only be something detailing and expounding matters already <Col N="1127" /> set out in the Act, so that Order, therefore, will be a very formal Order, an Order of a very temporary nature, and not such an Order as should be laid on the table of the Dáil.  Orders, when we view things with some idea of proportion, that ought to be laid on the table of the Dáil, and give the effect that is given to Orders by being on the table of the Dáil, should be Orders that do something in the way of legislation, and not mere executive Orders.  You do not lay on the <Col N="1128" /> table of the Dáil an Order or decision which decides how a charwoman shall be appointed, and the terms upon which she will hold her office.  To press an amendment like this is to be without any sort or sense of proportion, or any idea of the things that are to be brought before Parliament and the things that are not to be brought before Parliament.</P>
      <P>Amendment No. 2 put, and declared lost.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That Section 1 as amended stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided: Tá, 35; Níl, 9.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Liam T. Mac Cosgair.<br />Donchadh Ó Guaire.<br />Uáitéar Mac Cumhaill.<br />Seán Ó Maolruaidh.<br />Seán Ó Duinnín.<br />Mícheál Ó hAonghusa.<br />Séamus Breathnach.<br />Pádraig Mag Ualghairg.<br />Darghal Figes.<br />Deasmhumhain Mac Gearailt.<br />Seán Ó Ruanaidh.<br />Ailfrid Ó Broin.<br />Pilib Mac Cosgair.<br />Mícheál de Staineas.<br />Domhnall Mac Cártaigh.<br />Maolmhuire Mac Eochadha.<br />Gearóid Mac Giobúin.<br />Liam Thrift.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Eoin Mac Néill.<br />Liam Mag Aonghusa.<br />Pádraig Ó hÓgáin.<br />Seoirse Mac Niocaill.<br />Fionán Ó Loingsigh.<br />Criostóir Ó Broin.<br />Caoimhghin Ó hUigín.<br />Próinsias Bulfin.<br />Séamus Ó Dóláin.<br />Eamon Ó Dúgáin.<br />Peadar Ó hAodha.<br />Séamus Ó Murchadha.<br />Liam Mac Sioghaird.<br />Earnán de Blaghd.<br />Domhnall Ó Broin.<br />Séamus de Burca.<br />Mícheál Ó Dubhghaill.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Tomás de Nógla.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Seoirse Ghabháin Uí Dhubhthaigh.<br />Aodh Ó Cúlacháin.<br />Liam Ó Daimhín.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Seán Ó Laidhin.<br />Cathal Ó Seanáin.<br />Domhnall Ó Ceallacháin.<br />Domhnall Ó Muirgheasa.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Motion declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move Section 2 as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(1)  From and after the passing of this Act it shall not be obligatory upon any Under-Sheriff to employ any bailiff to assist him in the execution of a writ of <i>fieri facias</i> or writ of <i>habere</i> or to employ any bailiff appointed under Section 5 of the Civil Bill Courts Procedure Amendment Act (Ireland), 1864 (27 &amp; 28 Vict., ch. 99), to assist him in the execution of his duties under that Act, but in lieu of or in addition to such bailiffs it shall be lawful for any Under-Sheriff to employ such and so many persons as he shall think fit to assist him in the execution of any or every writ of <i>fieri facias</i> or writ of <i>habere</i> and of any or every decree (whether for debt, possession of lands or otherwise) of a Civil Bill Court.</P>
      <P>(2)  Any person employed by an Under-Sheriff as bailiff under this section may be employed at a weekly or other wage to assist him generally in the execution of such writs and decrees as aforesaid or may be employed specially to assist the Under-Sheriff in the execution of a particular writ or decree.</P>
      <P>(3)  Wherever persons are employed by an Under-Sheriff under this section to assist him generally in the execution of such writs and decrees as aforesaid the number and rate of remuneration of such persons shall be subject to the approval of the Minister, and the sanction of the Minister of Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(4)  Wherever any persons are employed specially by an Under-Sheriff under this section to assist him in the <Col N="1129" /> execution of a particular writ or decree the number and remuneration of such persons shall be in the discretion of the Under-Sheriff.</P>
    <P>(5)  Every person employed under this section by an Under-Sheriff to assist him in the execution of a writ of <i>fieri facias</i> or a writ of <i>habere</i> shall have all the powers which are by law vested in a bailiff employed by an Under-Sheriff for that purpose, and every person employed under this section by an Under-Sheriff to assist him in the execution of any decree of a Civil Bill Court shall have all the powers which are by law vested in a bailiff appointed under the Civil Bill Courts Procedure Amendment Act (Ireland), 1864 (27 &amp; 28 Vict., ch. 99).</P>
    <P>In moving the Section I have to ask indulgence for a similar insertion to that which I made in Sub-Section 3, Section 1, namely, to insert in Sub-Section 3 of Section 2, after the word &ldquo;persons&rdquo; on the fourth line:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;To be paid out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The alteration is necessary, because it may be necessary to offer a man an engagement over a period at a fixed remuneration. The present procedure is that they get special fees for particular work.  There is a scale of fees laid down. If men have to be engaged for a period they must be paid from the Central Fund that will be always available.  If that is to be done the fees that are recoverable in seizures from time to time will revert to the Treasury in recoupment of the weekly payment, or towards the recoupment of the weekly payment. I do not think there is anything special in the Sub-Section calling for comment by me.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister's amendment will come after the amendments which are on the paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:</P>
      <P>To insert before the word &ldquo;persons,&rdquo; line 9, the word &ldquo;suitable.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This particular Section is one of the most important in the Bill.  I do not know whether it is generally appreciated that the proposed Statute is by no means confined to small debts or County Court operations, and that executions for enforcing High Court Judgments and <Col N="1130" /> Orders also come under it, so that its scope will be a much wider one than was at first supposed.  The first amendment I have to this section is only the insertion of one word, the word &ldquo;suitable.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister will include a corresponding word in Sub-Section 3, line 20, and make it read:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The number, rate of remuneration and suitability of such persons shall be subject to the approval of the Minister.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendments on the paper are before that.  We shall take the Minister's amendment in Sub-Section 3, and we shall consider that point as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move: &mdash;To add to Sub-Section 1 the following words:&mdash;&ldquo;Provided that nothing in this Sub-section above contained shall be deemed to authorise an Under-Sheriff so to employ any person subject to military law, but if at any time the Minister shall be satisfied that a person against whom a judgment, order, or decree shall have been made is well able to satisfy the same, but is nevertheless persistently contriving to defeat the same by force, the Minister may, by warrant under his hand, grant to an Under-Sheriff exceptional authority to seek and employ military assistance for the purposes in this Section mentioned, and in any such case Sub-section 5 of this Section (but not Sub-sections 2, 3, and 4) shall apply.&rdquo;  This amendment is one of the most important, and I hope it will be agreed to.  Deputies will see that the first Section is designed to empower Sheriffs or Under-Sheriffs to employ anybody they like to help them in enforcing judgments and decrees by way of execution. I ask the Dáil to accept the principle that you are not justified in applying for that purpose military force, save only where a man is resisting by violence the payment of his just debts. I think that principle is one which must be universally accepted.  The army is not recruited to collect people's debts If you get an extreme case where a recalcitrant debtor, who could perfectly <Col N="1131" /> well pay up, barricades his house and uses other force against the Sheriff's Officer in order fraudulently to avoid payment of that debt, then, where it is worth while, where it is not a matter of the collection of a pound or two, I would be in favour of authorising the calling in of military aid, but only in extreme cases, and the amendment I have put down is drafted for that purpose. It says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Provided that nothing in this Sub-section above contained shall be deemed to authorise an Under-Sheriff so to employ any person subject to military law.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>So far as a Sheriff is concerned, he has got to employ civilians, but then the moment comes when the creditor finds that he cannot get his remedy in that way, on account of the violence of the debtor, and then I suggest the matter be dealt with in this way:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;But if at any time the Minister shall be satisfied that a person against whom a judgment order or decree shall have been made is well able to satisfy the same, but is, nevertheless, persistently contriving to defeat the same by force, the Minister may, by warrant under his hand, grant to an Under-Sheriff exceptional authority to seek and employ military assistance.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think that it ought to be a condition, precedent to the employment of military assistance, that you have violence on the side of the debtor.  There is another amendment proposed in another place dealing with the distinction that ought to be made between the dishonest and honest debtor, and I am assuming, after what fell from the Ministers the other day, that substantially we are in agreement upon that.  The honest debtor is not to be touched by this Bill.  We are, therefore, dealing with the case of the dishonest debtor, and I say that, even in the case of the dishonest debtor, it is bad for the army, as well as being bad from a civil point of view, to bring military interference in in order to collect debts, except in an extreme case where there really is violence, such as the Sheriff cannot deal with by ordinary police and civilian aid.  I ask the Dáil to accept that principle.  It is a most dangerous thing to bring the military <Col N="1132" /> into a performance of this kind except when you are driven to it.  You may be driven to it in extreme cases&mdash;the Ministers rather outlined their idea that it would be only in extreme cases such a thing would happen&mdash;and where a particularly obstinate and violent fellow would refuse to pay his just debts, as I say, give a discretion to the Minister, because, naturally, he would not allow the employment of soldiers to collect a few shillings.  It would not be worth while.  I also propose that so many of these Sub-sections as refer to the payment of the persons employed by the Sheriff shall have no application to military persons employed.  That is to say, that the military get their ordinary pay, and there should be no question of paying them any addition as bailiffs in the rare cases where they are called in, I take it in only one or two counties.  I suggest that you give them the powers that other non-military persons should have, but not any special remuneration, and that the matter be confined to extreme cases where the Minister is satisfied that there is no other way of meeting the situation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to oppose this amendment because of its implications.  It certainly, in its concluding stages, contains the implication that in certain circumstances the Under-Sheriff would be authorised to seek and employ military assistance for the purpose of a particular seizure.  There is no such proposal, and I do not contemplate that there will be any such proposal. But, glancing through that amendment, it occurred to me to wonder how often a man would have successfully to defeat the law by force before it would be correct to describe him as &ldquo;persistently contriving to defeat the same by force.&rdquo;  That is merely incidental. There is no question of military being employed in the capacity of bailiffs. There is a question of full and impressive military protection to the people who are so employed; protection rather of the kind to deter intervention&mdash;calculated to deter rather than to deal with intervention, when such would actually occur; protection so full and so impressive that intervention or interference would be most unlikely.  But no one contemplated that the military would be asked, as part of their duties, or even outside their duties, actually to seize <Col N="1133" /> goods&mdash;to carry out a physical seizure. That is not their function.  I have no feeling that it will be difficult or impossible to secure men to carry out that civil function as officers acting under the Sheriff, who is an officer of the Court, provided it be made clear that the resources of the State are there and will be there to protect them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>Then, is there any objection to the first three lines of the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>No; because from the very nature of the position that is excluded.  I would give the Deputy quite definitely that undertaking that the military will not act under the orders of the Under-Sheriff, and will not carry out seizures under the orders of the Under-Sheriff.  From the very nature of the position, I should have thought that the Deputy would have agreed with me that they are debarred from any such duty, but they are not debarred, when instructed to do so by their proper officers, from giving adequate protection to civil officers in the discharge of their duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister assures us that the emphatic words are in line six, that the Under-Sheriff may employ other persons besides the bailiff to <i>assist</i> him in the execution of his duties.  These words necessarily imply that the Under-Sheriff may not employ a member of the army in his capacity as a soldier in military service to take part in making a seizure.  The contrast is between &ldquo;assist&rdquo; and &ldquo;protect&rdquo; in the discharge of his duties.  The slight alteration that was introduced with regard to the source from which the payment would be made for these services makes that additionally clear, if any additional clarity were required, because, obviously, if the intention of the Section had been to empower the Under-Sheriff to call in military force to assist the members of it to effect seizures of property, to act, in fact, as bailiffs, they would be in receipt of their ordinary military pay.  But the provision of special sources for the remuneration for these especially employed people goes to show that it is not the intention of the Section to use the military in this extraordinary fashion.  I take it, therefore, <Col N="1134" /> that the military are employed only where such breach of the peace is foreseen as to make it necessary for the preservation of order to awe opponents of the execution into refraining from interference with it.  So, while I object to the ferocity of certain clauses, I detect no ferocity in this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>Who is going to pay for the military assistance when it is invoked?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know quite what the Deputy means when he asks who is going to pay for military assistance.  The Minister for Defence agrees with me that the present situation in the country constitutes in some ways more, and in some ways less, than a war, that it is a kind of organised sabotage, and that to meet and counter it, and to counter its various side issues and the mentality behind it, the army must be asked to perform many duties which do not attach to the regular army of an old-established Government in normal times.  They must be asked to perform many duties which under normal settled conditions would be police, rather than military duties.  The number of such manifestations and the extent of them in present circumstances, taken together with all the existing circumstances of the times, are sufficient to constitute a military rather than a police problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>The point of my question was rather different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>These men will not be paid specially.  They will do those things as part of their ordinary routine duties, and the Commander-in-Chief and the Minister for Defence have agreed that it is necessary for the attainment of the objective the entire fight is being waged for, that they should be available to uphold and strengthen the civil machinery.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>The point I wish cleared up is that in view of the fact that a great many new expenses are to be added under the Bill the employment of military to make a display of force will not in any way tend to add to the expenses which the debtor has to pay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1135" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>It will not.</P>
      <P>Amendment withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Mr. O'HIGGINS amendment to Sub-section 3:&mdash;&ldquo;To add to the word &lsquo;remuneration&rsquo; the words &lsquo;to be paid out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas,&rsquo;&rdquo; put, and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I would suggest putting in the word &ldquo;suitability&rdquo; in that Sub-Section, so that when we arrange that the Sub-Sheriff is authorised to employ suitable persons, the judge of the suitability should be the Minister, and not the Under-Sheriff; I do not mean as regards the individual, but as regards the class.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it would be possible for me to examine in detail the qualifications of the people who will be employed in this capacity throughout the country.  The Sub-Sheriffs will receive instructions that the men they are to employ are to be men of good character and integrity.  But to refer that back to me in Dublin to satisfy myself that such was the case would be cumbrous, and besides, I am not likely to be able to form a better opinion than the Sub-Sheriff.  One must delegate a certain discretion to civil officers, and if the Sub-Sheriffs simply got a reminder that these men, because of the nature of their duties, ought to be men of good character and decent men, it would meet the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with every syllable the Minister has said.  I do not at all propose to add to the arduous duties that he is already patiently bearing up with, by determining whether Michael O'Flaherty or Timothy Muldoon is a fit and proper person to assist such and such an Under-Sheriff. What I had in view is laying down general regulations legally determining what kind of person he would consider fit and proper.  Consider this possibility: I am an Under-Sheriff.  I am not a man of integrity. As an Under-Sheriff I employ men, otherwise engaged as touts for dealers in <i>objets d'art</i>, articles sometimes facetiously described as articles of &ldquo;bigotry and virtue.&rdquo;  It is quite easy to enter into a corrupt arrangement, and, for what is vulgarly known as a handover, <Col N="1136" /> to arrange for that type of sale, or non-sale rather, that is dealt with in a later section.  It is quite possible for me to appoint an auctioneer to assist me, who will later assist me in another sense than in his capacity as an auctioneer. Of course, the Minister will reply that we are to put perfect faith in our fellow-countrymen, and to believe that, notwithstanding all the disorder, riot, and commotion in the country that we have still so much of our Gaelic virtues that corrupt things could not happen.  We know that they do happen, and we ought to take measures to see that they will not become common in their happening. I ask for specific regulations that such and such a person shall not be enlisted to act.  It may be difficult to decide just the precise category, but, at any rate, there is a certain type of respectable rogue that should not be employed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The remarks of Deputy Magennis surprise me.  He seems to be supporting a view that the Minister holds, and which runs through this Bill &mdash;that the administration and the enforcement of the law is the function of the Ministry, or any department of the Ministry, and that the Ministry may make orders and may advise the officer of the court who should be employed or who should not be employed.  I am utterly at sea if that is the notion of how law should be enforced in the country. I imagine that the Sheriff, and those connected with the Sheriff, are officers of the Court, and are entirely outside the jurisdiction of the Ministry.  Once the issue of a decree or a judgment comes from the Court, then the procedure is automatic, and there should be, and must be, no interference by the Ministry with those processes of law.  That is not the conception behind this Bill.  It is not the conception of the Minister; it is not the conception of Deputy Magennis, judging by his last speech.  There is an assumption right through this Bill that the Ministry can come in and say &ldquo;this shall be&rdquo; and &ldquo;this shall not be&rdquo;; that the Ministry shall advise the officer of the Court what to do, and that they can put a veto on the officer of the Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, by legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1137" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an utterly false construction of what should be the process of law, and yet that idea is running right through this Bill.  In all the defences that the Ministers have made for separate provisions of this Bill they have said &ldquo;we do not want anything of the kind,&rdquo; and &ldquo;we do not propose that this or that shall take place.&rdquo; It has nothing to do with them if this interpretation of law is a correct one.  If the enforcement of law is at the discretion of any decree of the Ministry, then all criticism of this Bill is gone by the board.  If it is a ministerial function, then let us understand where we are. There is only one other step, and that is to make the enforcement of the law, the issuing of judgments, the starting of processes of law, a function of the military power.  That is what we are coming to. This is merely one other expression of the idea that the Executive authority for the time being, whichever it may be, is the body which has control of the legal process of the Courts.  That I protest against, and will protest against to the utmost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I already, this afternoon, spoke in language not quite so strong as that of Deputy Johnson. He was speaking to a colleague at the time when I used the sentence, and possibly he missed it.  &ldquo;That the substitution of the Ministerial exercise of discretion that ran through this Bill was practically the substitution of arbitrary power for democratic rule.&rdquo;  Now Deputy Johnson says, in a more effective, if fuller form of expression, precisely the same thing.  I am not proposing that the Executive should interfere after the decree of a Court has been issued against a certain debtor, and prescribe to the Under-Sheriff, then, and only then, what type of person is eligible for this appointment. I want the legislation that controls all these procedures to prescribe that such and such persons shall, or shall not, be eligible for these offices of deputy bailiff, substitute bailiff, or assistant to the Under-Sheriff in the making of seizures.  I am quite as strong&mdash;I am sure the Minister himself is quite as strong&mdash;as Deputy Johnson in not proposing a revolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>They do not propose it; they act it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1138" />
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>That, at times in certain sections of the Bill, it is detectable I quite agree.  But I voted for the Bill because I believe, and still believe, that it is not the doctrine; that it is not the express, conscious doctrine of the Minister that he intends to make such a revolution.  What I want to secure is that the Under-Sheriff may not, at his own sweet will, declare a certain type of man, because he chooses so to do, a suitable person within the meaning of the Act; just as before, the Sheriff himself was obliged to consider certain qualifications and restrictions in the selection of the Under-Sheriff.  The President forgot this evening&mdash;I did not think it worth while to waste the time of the Dáil in reply&mdash;when he twitted me with the fact that I had been living without complaint under a system in which the Sheriff exercised his unfettered discretion in the selection of the Under-Sheriff and that I did not groan because&mdash; there was no such unfettered discretion. The Sheriff was obliged to select men who had certain prescribed qualifications. Similarly, I want certain prescribed qualifications for the filling of the offices I have mentioned.  If the Under-Sheriff is at liberty to select men at his own sweet will, then the ferocity of these provisions becomes operative, and the innocent debtor, because of other debtors failing in their payments to him, may find himself utterly ruined under the operation of this new law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>There is really no need for the making of heated speeches which have got absolutely nothing to do with the merits of the case.  Deputy Johnson seems to be under the impression that the Ministry claim to interfere in the executive acts of the Sub-Sheriff, and he says the Minister takes up the position that he will not do this, or that, or the other thing.  Why not give examples of where the Ministry have taken up that attitude?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Read the last debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I challenge him to point out a single example in the text of the Bill where the Ministry have attempted to dictate to the Sheriff or Under-Sheriff as to what they shall or shall not do.  There is no use, dealing as we are now with the Committee <Col N="1139" /> Stage of the Bill, making general charges, and at the same time refraining from giving a single example.  We will never get business done that way.  I want examples.  The Bill is here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>From start to finish of this Bill, there is no mention whatever of the military.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>When defending the Bill against certain criticism, the President, the Minister for Home Affairs, and the Minister for Agriculture successively said &ldquo;they had no intention to do so and so; they would not allow the military to do so and so; they would not allow this thing to happen,&rdquo; but I say you cannot prevent the military from doing so, if the other authorities fail in carrying out the order of the Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I can only speak for myself.  When defending this Bill, on the first reading, I was referring to speeches made by Deputies here which seemed to be based on the assumption that the Sub-Sheriff would take extreme measures in every case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>How do you know he will not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I pointed out that they were not to assume, that because this Bill was passed, the Sub-Sheriff would change his nature and rush out immediately, requisition the military and employ them in impressive and tremendous force to execute every debt.  Whether he does so or not has nothing to do <Col N="1140" /> with Deputy Johnson's point, which was this: that the Ministers had said that they themselves would not allow the military to do this, that, or another thing.  My only point was, that the Sub-Sheriff would not ask for the assistance of the military in cases where he could execute without them, and I put that to the Dáil as a perfectly obvious and reasonable point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister forgets that all checks upon the actions of the Sub-Sheriff under the present law are removed.  When it was suggested that the result of the removal of checks would be to enable, at the will of this officer, a man to do certain things, we were told: &ldquo;we would not allow such things to happen.&rdquo;  I admit that this is a Second Reading point and not a Committee point, but I am of opinion that it should be restated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>And examples given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The only statement I made, which would indicate any limitation whatever was this, that while the Bill applied equally and bound the Sub-Sheriff equally, as the existing law does, that discretion would be exercised before the military arm, the military unit, would be availed of in the execution of decrees, and so it will.  It is not sound to say that we cannot exercise any discretion as to the duties the military will or will not perform.  We can, and we will.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That Sub-Section 2, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided: Tá, 34; Níl, 8.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Liam T. Mac Cosgair.<br />Donchadh Ó Guaire.<br />Uáitéar Mac Cumhaill.<br />Seán Ó Maolruaidh.<br />Seán Ó Duinnín.<br />Mícheál Ó hAonghusa.<br />Pádraig Mag Ualghairg.<br />Seoirse Ghabhain Uí Dhubhthaigh.<br />Deasmhumhain Mac Gearailt.<br />Seán Ó Ruanaidh.<br />Mícheál de Duram.<br />Ailfrid Ó Broin.<br />Pilib Mac Cosgair.<br />Micheál de Stáineas.<br />Domhnall Mac Cárthaigh.<br />Maolmhuire Mac Eochadha.<br />Gearóid Mac Giobúin.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Liam Thrift.<br />Eoin Mac Néill.<br />Pádraig Ó hÓgáin.<br />Seoirse Mac Niocail.<br />Fionán Ó Loingsigh.<br />Criostóir Ó Broin.<br />Caoimhghin Ó hUigín.<br />Próinsias Bulfin.<br />Séamus Ó Doláin.<br />Eamon Ó Dúgáin.<br />Peadar Ó hAodha.<br />Liam Mac Sioghaird.<br />Éarnán de Blaghd.<br />Domhnall Ó Broin.<br />Séamus de Burca.<br />Micheál Ó Dubhghaill.<br />Liam Mag Aonghusa.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl <Col N="1141" /><Col N="1142" /></P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Tomás de Nógla.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Aodh Ó Cúlacháin.<br />Liam Ó Daimhín.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Seán Ó Laidhin.<br />Cathal Ó Seanáin.<br />Domhnall Ó Muirgheasa.<br />Domhnall Ó Ceallacháin.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Motion declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I now move that the Committee report progress to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE." RHead="- ">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - [  DAIL RESUMES. ]</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Commitee reports to the Dáil that two sections of the Enforcement of Law (Occasional Powers) Bill, 1923, have been passed in Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE." RHead="- THE ADJOURNMENT">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - THE ADJOURNMENT.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I now move the adjournment of the Dáil until 3 o'clock to-morrow.  I think we will be able to take the Second Reading of the Justices' Bill on Friday, and the Report Stage of the Local Government Electoral Law Bill on to-morrow week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the District Justices' Bill be in the hands of the members?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>To-morrow afternoon, probably at 4 o'clock. Is it proposed to take the Second Reading on Thursday or Friday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>It will depend on whether we will finish the Committee Stage of this Bill on which we are engaged on to-morrow.  If we do finish to-morrow there will be, I think, no business except the Second Reading of the District Justices' Bill for Thursday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That would hardly give us time to consider it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is unlikely that we will finish the Committee Stage of this Enforcement of the Law Bill to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We will take the Report Stage of the Electoral Law Bill on to-morrow week.  Deputies should put in their amendments for this Electoral Law Bill as early as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask a question as to how we stand with regard to that matter.  There were several suggestions made with regard to this Bill, and they were accepted, subject to reservations by the Minister, and yet in the form in which it is now circulated it is described as &ldquo;Amended in Committee,&rdquo; while a great many of these amendments are missing.  Will it be necessary for us to repeat those amendments, or is it the intention of the Minister in charge of the Bill to bring them forward himself?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I am concerned, in sending out the Bill to Deputies we are obliged to send it out as actually amended; but the Minister, I understand, has that matter in hands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose to move a large number of amendments, in compliance with the undertakings I gave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will it be convenient for the Minister to circulate his amendments as early as possible?  It would save sending in a large number of amendments if they were circulated in time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I will circulate them as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister's amendments were circulated in time for Deputies to see them, if they were satisfied with them it would save our having amendments such as Deputy Magennis speaks of.</P>
      <P>Motion put: &ldquo;That the Dáil adjourn until to-morrow (Wednesday), at 3 o'clock.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 6.40 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="CIVIL SERVANTS' BONUS">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - CIVIL SERVANTS' BONUS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="AILFRID O BROIN AILFRID O BROIN">
      <NameTxt>AILFRID O BROIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance if he will say what percentage of bonus is being used for pensionable purposes and for calculating gratuity, in the cases of Civil Servants retiring under Article 10 of the Treaty, and what fractional part of such percentage is being given; whether the supplemental pension is a fluctuating one in the case of such Civil Servants; and whether he will agree to regard part of a year served as a year in calculating such pensions and gratuities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Civil Service Committee (Compensation) has advised the Government that in the case of awards of compensation under Article 10 of the Treaty cost of living bonus should be treated in the same way as it is treated for ordinary pension awards.  I am sending to the Deputy a memorandum showing the method of calculation adopted.</P>
      <P>The Superannuation Acts specifically provide that only complete years of service can be reckoned for purposes of pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="PRISON OFFICIALS">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - PRISON OFFICIALS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="AILFRID O BROIN AILFRID O BROIN">
      <NameTxt>AILFRID O BROIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance whether he is aware that the Prisons officers seeking permission to retire under Article 10 of the Treaty elected a representative to represent them on the Compensation Committee; that notice of the appointment of this representative was sent to the Committee in October; that the Committee decided upon the terms to be given to the Prisons officers without their representative being present; that the representatives appointed by the Civil Service Federation to the Committee do not, and cannot, represent consistently those officers by reason of the fact that they were refused membership of the Civil Service Federation a short time ago; that by filling up the application form for retirement those officers claim they are seeking permission to retire, and not retiring in the ordinary way; and, taking <Col N="1081" /> those facts into consideration, will he take the necessary steps to see that those officers receive added years, as provided in the 1920 Act for those who retire with the permission of the Civil Service Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Prison Officers did not ask the Civil Service Committee (Compensation) to give them representation on the Committee, and it has already been pointed out to their representatives that the notice referred to in the question contained no such request.  The Committee unanimously decided that the compensation terms due were those for ordinary retirement in consequence of the change of Government, and not the special terms referred to in the question, and I cannot consent to modify in any way the findings of this Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - SUPERANNUATED" RHead="OFFICIALS. (PAYMENT OF ALLOWANCES.)">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - SUPERANNUATED OFFICIALS.  (PAYMENT OF ALLOWANCES.)</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="AILFRID O BROIN AILFRID O BROIN">
      <NameTxt>AILFRID O BROIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Local Government if complaints have been received by him from various ex-officials of public bodies throughout Ireland (whose offices have been abolished, and who have not been awarded the superannuation or compensation to which they were entitled under Section 8 of the Local Government (Ireland) Act, 1919, and Section 66 of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, and what steps the Local Government Department are taking to ensure that local bodies will discharge their liabilities to such ex-officials.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>Complaints of the nature indicated have been received occasionally, and are investigated as they arise.  It is possible that in some instances local authorities may have postponed payments due to ex-officials owing to temporary financial embarrassment caused by delays in payment of rates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AlfredByrne" hpid="AILFRID O BROIN AILFRID O BROIN">
      <NameTxt>AILFRID O BROIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Local Government if many of the officials of the abolished Unions in the county of Donegal, and these the most needy, have not yet received one penny of their pensions or gratuities; and if his Department will urge the local body responsible for the payments to pay same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1082" />
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>There has been an unavoidable delay in the payment by the County Home Committee of pensions or gratuities to ex-officials of the abolished Unions in County Donegal, but it is expected that the matter will be settled almost immediately, as transfers of necessary funds are now about to be made to the Committee by the County Council.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - GRANT" RHead="FOR EX-SERVICEMEN">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - GRANT FOR EX-SERVICEMEN.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnRooney" hpid="SEAN O RUANAIDH SEAN O RUANAIDH">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O RUANAIDH</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Agriculture, <i>(a)</i> what arrangements have been made, if any, to secure that the eleven and half million pounds granted under the Soldiers and Sailors Act of 1919 will be available for the purpose of the Act, and whether there is to be formed an Irish Soldiers and Sailors Land Trust, financed by the English Treasury; <i>(b)</i> what amount will be available to develop and divide the Castle warders' estate purchased from Lord Cloncurry, through the influence of the local ex-Servicemen?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan) Patrick J. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards the first part of the question the British Government in 1919 agreed to advance money to enable soldiers and sailors to share in the advantages of the Land Purchase Acts. There was considerable opposition to the scheme in various localities, especially where land was bought exclusively to make provision for soldiers and sailors. Further operations under the Act were suspended by the Irish Government in February, 1922, and it is not possible to state at present if or when such operations will be resumed.</P>
      <P>The Irish Sailors and Soldiers Land Trust referred to in the question is a Trust proposed to be established under Sec. 3 of the Irish Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act, 1922, for the purpose of continuing and carrying into effect the provisions of Sec. 4 of the Irish Land (Provision for Sailors and Soldiers) Act, 1919, under which cottages and gardens as distinct from holdings could be provided for sailors and soldiers.  The terms and conditions of the proposed Trust are fully set out in Irish Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act, 1922, above referred to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards the second part of the question the Estates Commissioners acquired under Section I. of the Irish Land (Provisions <Col N="1083" /> for Sailors and Soldiers) Act, 1919, 885 acres of the Castlewarden and other lands on the Estate of Lord Cloncurry. The lands have not been divided, but are let for the present under temporary grazing lettings to small holders.  It is not possible to state at present what moneys will be available to develop and divide the lands in question.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - SOLDIERS'" RHead="DEPENDENTS' ALLOWANCES">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - SOLDIERS' DEPENDENTS' ALLOWANCES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether it is true that repeated applications for dependents 'allowance have been made on behalf of the wife and four children of Sergeant John O'Shea (No. 08530, 1st Western Division), O'Connell Street, Tullamore, and seeing that O'Shea has been serving since July 12th, 1922, if the Minister will state when he will be in a position to deal with this long outstanding claim, the non-payment of which is causing much misery and inconvenience to his penniless wife and children?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>Several applications were received, but difficulty was experienced in tracing evidence of O'Shea's enlistment. The claim was, however, passed on the 17th inst., and arrears of the allowance have been paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence if it is correct to state that several applications for dependents' allowance have been made on behalf of Private James Gilmartin, Cappaneale, Birr, Offaly, now attached to 1st Regular Garrison, Carlow Brigade (joined 25th August, 1922), and if and when he will be in a position to deal with this claim?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Two applications were received from Mrs. Gilmartin who, on three occasions, was asked to complete a Declaration Form.  The receipt of that Form cannot be traced, but the claim is, however, being investigated urgently.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="MOUNTMELLICK TENANT'S CLAIM">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - MOUNTMELLICK TENANT'S CLAIM.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that the licensed premises of Mr. E. O'Connor, Patrick-Street, Mountmellick, <Col N="1084" /> was taken over by R.I.C. forces on 12th January, 1921, and held by them at a rent of £10 per month up to March 25th, 1922, on which date the premises were evacuated by R.I.C. and occupied by National Troops; whether it is a fact that the National Troops left the town on June 28th, 1922, without giving over possession to the owner, and subsequently returned to another premises in the same town; and whether the Military Authorities are now in a position to hand over possession of the premises to Mr. O'Connor, if they intend to pay the rent up to the date of such handing over, and to compensate him for damage done to the premises by reason of their occupation, and also for loss of profits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mr. O'Connor's house was occupied by our troops from the 1st April to the 29th June.  Very little damage was done during their occupation and the house was locked up when they left.</P>
      <P>Mr. O'Connor was advised both verbally and in writing that he was at liberty to resume possession.  In the situation as it then was, it was not always possible to adhere to strict points of law in dealing with the occupation of and evacuation of premises required by our troops.  Claims for rent in respect of the occupation of the premises by the troops and of any damage caused during that occupation will be dealt with by the Office of Public Works.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - COMPENSATION" RHead="FOR EDENDERRY MEN">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - COMPENSATION FOR EDENDERRY MEN.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="LIAM O DAIMHIN LIAM O DAIMHIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O DAIMHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that a number of members of the I.R.A. from Edenderry and district left their employment at the request of the Commandant of the 6th Brigade in July last for the purposes of assisting the forces of the Provisional Government in protecting the lives and property of the people in the area; whether he has received any application for payment or compensation owing to loss of wages during their period of such temporary service, and when it is his intention to deal with this claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Applications have been received for payment of the men in question.  They are being dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DISMISSAL OF" RHead="CAHIRCIVEEN POSTAL OFFICIALS">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - DISMISSAL OF CAHIRCIVEEN POSTAL OFFICIALS.</Title>
    <Col N="1085" />
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O SEANAIN CATHAL O SEANAIN">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O SEANAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether three members of the permanent Post Office staff at Cahirciveen were served with notices of immediate dismissal on December 22nd, 1922, by Comdt. W. Griffin, O.C., Cahirciveen, without complaint made; by what authority was this action taken; what were the reasons for these dismissals; whether the ladies concerned had signed a declaration of allegiance to the Government; and whether it is not a fact that testimony as to the loyalty of these ladies can be obtained from reliable local citizens.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Enquiries are being made into the matter, but they have not yet been completed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - A" RHead="REQUISITIONED BICYCLE">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - A REQUISITIONED BICYCLE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="TOMAS O CONAILL TOMAS O CONAILL">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS O CONAILL</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence if he can state when a bicycle, requisitioned from Mr. J.P. O'Neill, of Mainguard Street, Galway, on 14th October, 1922, by the Military Authorities, will be handed back to the owner, who requires this machine in the pursuit of his business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The matter is being enquired into.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. - SALARIES AND" RHead="DEPENDENTS' ALLOWANCES IN ATHLONE">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - SALARIES AND DEPENDENTS' ALLOWANCES IN ATHLONE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence if he is aware that a large number of officers and non-commissioned officers in the National Army stationed in Athlone are not receiving officer's pay, and whose commissions have been sanctioned by the Army Authorities; further, if he is aware that the above ranks were all appointments by the late Commander-in-Chief, Michael Collins, and furthermore, will he state why the mothers of those officers are not in receipt of Dependents' Allowances, when those officers were the chief support of their mothers before joining up; and will he state when it is likely that the above officers shall receive their rank pay and also the allowance to their mothers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of those things.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1086" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely you must be aware that these men are acting as officers for over two years.  They acted as officers in the old I.R.A., and are now officers in the National Army.  As stated in the question, some of these appointments were made by the late Commander-in-Chief.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there a supplementary question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to know why these officers are not being paid, and why their mothers are not getting their allowances?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a supplementary question; that is the same question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of the matters referred to in the question, and I cannot undertake to take the initiative in inquiring into them.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="AN ATHLONE NOTICE">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - AN ATHLONE NOTICE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence if he is aware that the following notice was posted on the bridge in Athlone and on the walls of Fitzgerald's public-house in Connaught Street, Athlone:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Any person or persons found speaking to &lsquo;Bolshies&rsquo; shall be shot at sight.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Signed on behalf of</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The Military Headquarters, Athlone.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>And will the Minister see that this pseudo-military order is officially repudiated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that a notice as quoted was posted up, and I presume that it is thoroughly understood that it was not authorised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I take that answer as satisfactory.  It was on behalf of the people of Athlone.  I asked the question.  I was in Athlone, and saw the notice posted up, and as long as it is not authorised by this Government I am satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely no reasonable public person could consider that a notice worded in the way that notice was would come from any responsible officer or any responsible soldier of any rank.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>It ought not.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead="WRITTEN ANSWERS. -" RHead="ATHLONE EXECUTIONS">
    <Title>WRITTEN ANSWERS. - ATHLONE EXECUTIONS.</Title>
    <Col N="1087" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence if it is a fact that in connection with the five executions which took place in Athlone on Saturday, January 20th, the parents of the prisoners were not notified until after the executions had taken place; and, if so, what was the reason for this; also, why the remains of John Hughes, one of the executed men, were not given to his mother, at her request.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not the practice nor is it the intention to address communications to the relatives of men who are arrested, with the exception that, in the cases of men executed, formal notification is after execution at once sent to the next-of-kin or nearest relative, where any such are known. Also, it is not the intention to hand over to relations or friends the remains of men executed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask a supplementary question in regard to this man John Hughes, who was executed? His parents live one and a half miles from Athlone.  His mother was in town at the market, and was going home when she was overtaken by some person in authority, who told her about the execution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>As this was the first time in the history of Ireland that an execution took place in Athlone, and this man's people live within a mile of the town, surely it was the duty of the Government to notify them before executing him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not a question.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>