<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Tue" Date="29" Month="May" Year="1923" Vol="3" No="18" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 29 Bealtaine 1923" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 29 May 1923" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1181">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1181" /> Cromadh ar obair an lae ar a 3 p.m. Bhí an Ceann Comhairle, Micheál O hAodha, sa Chathaoir.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.  -" RHead="LETTERKENNY LABOURERS AND THEIR COTTAGE RENTS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - LETTERKENNY LABOURERS AND THEIR COTTAGE RENTS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="TOMAS MAC EOIN TOMAS MAC EOIN">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS MAC EOIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether he has received a request from the Letterkenny Farmer Labour Union for an officer of his Department to visit the district with authority to deal with the situation created by the labourers' inability, owing to the prevailing poverty and distress, to pay the rents of the District Council cottages, together with the farmers' inability to bear any heavier burden of rates, and whether the Minister will accede to the request in order to relieve a very strained situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER FOR LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>In compliance with a request of the Letterkenny Rural District Council, an Inspector of the Ministry will attend their next meeting on the 8th June.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM (SLIGO)">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - OLD AGE PENSION CLAIM (SLIGO).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="TOMAS MAC EOIN TOMAS MAC EOIN">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS MAC EOIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether he is aware that in the case of Margaret Egan, of Sligo (Pensions Officer's Register No. 1030A), the claimant's application for an old-age pension, originally made 2½ years ago, was recently vouched for by a well-known merchant, who is one of the oldest residents in Sligo, and also by the President of the St. Vincent de Paul Society in Sligo, it being impossible for the claimant to produce documentary evidence of birth on account of the destruction of the Cathedral records, and whether he is prepared <Col N="1182" /> to cause further enquiry to be made into the case with a view to the granting of the pension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>The first claim in this case was made not only 2½ years ago, but six years ago.  The memoranda of testimony referred to in the question were not sufficiently definite and detailed to be accepted as proof of age.  If the applicant will make a fresh application to the local Pensions Sub-Committee, and submit to them further and more detailed evidence of age in affidavit form, giving reasons for statements and opinions made therein, the case will be reconsidered.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. " RHead="- KILKENNY OFFICER AND WORKERS' STRIKE">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - KILKENNY OFFICER AND WORKERS' STRIKE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamOBrien1922" hpid="LIAM O BRIAIN LIAM O BRIAIN">
      <NameTxt>LIAM O BRIAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that a strike of farm and creamery workers has existed at Kilmanagh and Ballyline, Co. Kilkenny, and that one of the employers whose men are on strike is Lieutenant William Ryan, of Kilmanagh, a shopkeeper and farmer of that district, who is now stationed in Kilkenny Barracks; and further, whether he is aware that on Thursday, May 17th, four half-barrels of porter were conveyed from the brewery in Kilkenny to the barracks, and from the barracks to Lieutenant Ryan's shop in Kilmanagh in a lorry occupied by a number of soldiers, who were employed in assisting to unload the porter at the business establishment of Lieutenant Ryan; and, if so, will he state whether this was done under his authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware that Lieut.  William Ryan, of Kilkenny Military Barracks, is one of the employers concerned in the strike, and I am assured that soldiers did not handle the consignment of porter referred to.  The facts are that on the 17th instant a lorry, the property of the Kilmanagh Co-operative Society, delivered a load of butter at Kilkenny Railway Station, and on its return journey, as usual, carried goods for Kilmanagh traders.  Some bedding was also loaded on the lorry at Kilkenny Military Barracks for Kilmanagh military post, and Messrs.  Smithwicks were asked by Lieut. Ryan, in his capacity as trader at Kilmanagh, to have four half-barrels of ale ready for the lorry when it would call <Col N="1183" /> at the brewery.  As it appeared that the brewery would be closed by the time the lorry would reach it, the company sent the ale to the lorry in the barracks.  Two civilians who were on the lorry did the loading and unloading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamOBrien1922" hpid="Mr. W. O'BRIEN Mr. W. O'BRIEN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. O'BRIEN</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister consider that it is proper that a military officer should carry on his duty as a shopkeeper at the same time side by side, and is he aware that this officer is to be seen frequently milking his cows, in full uniform?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had to take into the Army the service of many people, and it would be unreasonable to ask a man who joined the Army and has business interests to relinquish these interests.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - CHARGE AGAINST SLIGO PRISONER">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - CHARGE AGAINST SLIGO PRISONER.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="TOMAS MAC EOIN TOMAS MAC EOIN">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS MAC EOIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether it is proposed to bring any charge against John Fallon, now in Sligo Jail, and, if not, whether he is prepared, in view of the fact that this lad is only 17 years of age and has already been in prison for over six months, to order his release.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>James Fallon, who gave his age as 18 years, has already been tried on a charge of aiding Irregulars, and as a result was recommended for internment.  It is not the intention at present to release him.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] - FIRING AT RABBITS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS.   [ORAL ANSWERS.] - FIRING AT RABBITS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="AODH O CULACHAIN AODH O CULACHAIN">
      <NameTxt>AODH O CULACHAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that troops travelling between Mullingar and Edenderry in motor lorries are in the habit of firing at rabbits in a warren near Rahan, and further, whether he is aware that on the night of the 17th instant, about 8.15 old time, a man living in the neighbourhood had a narrow escape from death by a bullet grazing his right ear, and to ask whether he will take steps to prevent a repetition of this practice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware that habitual firing of the kind mentioned takes place.  On the date in question a Crossley tender conveying a party of <Col N="1184" /> troops broke down near Rahan.  While the car was being repaired two soldiers fired at rabbits.  The necessary disciplinary action has been taken.  General assurance is given that all necessary steps are being taken to prevent such occurrences.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="INCREASE OF RENT AND MORTGAGE INTEREST" RHead="(RESTRICTIONS) BILL, 1923.&mdash;FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>INCREASE OF RENT AND MORTGAGE INTEREST (RESTRICTIONS) BILL, 1923.&mdash;FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. K. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. K. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chinn Chomhairle, the Increase of Rent and Mortgage Restrictions Act, 1920, which was emergency legislation to control increases in rent and mortgage interest in respect of certain dwellings and business premises, is due to expire on the 24th June next. In the circumstances, a Departmental Committee was set up in January of this year to inquire into and report on the operations of the Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act, 1920, and to advise whether or not the said Act should be continued, and, if continued, in what respect amendments, if any, were necessary or desirable.  The Committee reported in due course, and Deputies have had a copy of their report for some weeks. As the Committee have recommended that control is still necessary, I now move for leave to introduce a Bill, entitled &ldquo;Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Bill, 1923,&rdquo; this being a Bill &ldquo;to amend and continue certain restrictions with respect to the increase of rent and recovery of possession of premises in certain cases, and the increase of the rate of interest on and the calling in of securities on such premises, and for purposes in connection therewith.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. E. BLYTHE Mr. E. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second the motion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for Second Reading on Tuesday, 5th June.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="FINANCIAL MOTION. -" RHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE">
    <Title>FINANCIAL MOTION. - DAIL IN COMMITTEE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move: &ldquo;That there shall be added to Paragraph (a) of Clause 1 of Schedule D of the Income <Col N="1185" /> Tax Act, 1918, the following sub-paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(iv.) to any person, whether a citizen of Saorstát Eireann or not, although not resident in Saorstát Eireann, from the sale of any goods, wares or merchandise manufactured or partly manufactured by such person in Saorstát Eireann.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I do not think that there will be any objection to this paragraph, which secures to the State revenues that, I think, it will be admitted it is entitled to in equity, and therefore I beg formally to move the resolution.</P>
      <P>Resolution agreed to, to be reported to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="FINANCIAL MOTION." RHead="- DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>FINANCIAL MOTION. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>Resolution reported.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Dáil agrees with the Committee in this resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FionanLynch" hpid="MINISTER for FISHERIES (Mr. Fionan Lynch) Fionán Lynch">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FISHERIES (Mr. Fionan Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second the motion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>This will necessitate recommitting certain sections of the Finance Bill instead of taking the Bill on Report now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I think it would.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Shall we recommit the Bill for all sections proposed to be amended, and for the insertion of this resolution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - FINANCE" RHead="BILL, 1923.&mdash;RE-COMMITTED">
    <Title>THE DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - FINANCE BILL, 1923.&mdash;RE-COMMITTED.</Title>
    <P>SECTION 7.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move an amendment to have a new sub-section added to this section as follows:&mdash;&ldquo;This section shall cease to have effect on and after the 1st day of January, 1925; provided, nevertheless, that no action shall be brought after that date in respect of anything done or omitted to be done before that date which could not have been brought if this section were still in force.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In accordance with an intimation that <Col N="1186" /> I gave when this Bill was last in Committee, I desire to move my amendment, the effect of which is to restrict, by a limitation of time, the very drastic powers that are given by Section 7 of the Finance Act for the recovery of debts due to the State.  It will be within the recollection of the Dáil that every provision in this section was passed some time ago under an Emergency Statute for the enforcement of powers during a present temporary emergency.  That statute was fought, I might almost say, clause by clause, through the Dáil, and divisions were taken against many sections in it, but I do not think there was any section in it that was fought more fiercely than the one which is now being put into the Finance Bill.  Now, that Enforcement of Powers Act was justified by every Minister who supported it as a purely temporary and emergency measure.  I did not vote against this section; on the other hand, I supported it, because I was convinced by the arguments of Ministers that the times required drastic powers to enable decrees to be levied and debts to be collected.  The Ministry themselves recognised that the statute was one for emergency only, because they limited its duration for the very short period of six months from the date at which it was passed.  As I say, everyone who supported it did so on the ground that it was for all practical purposes a war measure, that the country had got out of hand, that illegality of every kind was rife throughout the country, and that it was impossible to levy decrees in the ordinary way or for the Sheriff to hold auctions in the ordinary way for the purpose of collecting debts according to the mode of law by which they have been collected since times that none of us can remember.</P>
    <P>It seems to me a very excessive arrogation of powers to the State when we find that these drastic powers, which were taken for six months only, in con consequence of emergency in the case of ordinary civil debts, were made permanent for the purpose of collecting debts due to the State for Income Tax and the other Customs and Duties that are dealt with in this Statute.  No one will, I think, charge me with having any sympathy with law-breakers, or with desiring in any way to shield people who <Col N="1187" /> are trying to evade the payment of the debts which are honestly due by them to the State.</P>
    <P>For that reason, when this Bill was before the Dáil, I supported, in a division which was taken on this Section, the enactments of this Section, because I was convinced by arguments of Ministers&mdash;I did not require much conviction&mdash;that the State was entitled to collect these debts by any means that any individual citizen was entitled to use, and that it was only fair that the State should have a longer period than the short six months that were given by the Enforcement of Powers Act, because these debts would not become due, in many cases, until after the expiration of that period, as they are in respect of the past financial year, and people have rights of appeal and rights to enable them to challenge the accuracy of the accounts furnished them, which will exhaust this six months.  Therefore, unless some longer period than six months were given to the State, the powers would be practically useless to it. For that reason I cast about to form an opinion, having been given no assistance by anybody else, which would enable me to come to a satisfactory conclusion as to what would be a fair time to give the Government for the execution of debts due to them by means of these extraordinary powers.  It appeared to me that as this financial year will not end until April, 1924, and that the people who owe debts which have not been collected by April, 1924, may be able to stave off execution for some few months longer, that it would not be unreasonable to let the Government possess these powers until the conclusion of the year 1924.  That gives them eighteen or nineteen months as against the six that the ordinary citizen possesses for the exercise of these drastic powers of collecting debts.</P>
    <P>Now, it is a very easy thing to say, and it was said in the arguments on this Bill in Committee, that all these powers will be shelved, that there will be no need to exercise them, but that it is a very useful thing to have them.  That is a dangerous argument, and that argument would apply to every single one of the extraordinary powers which this Dáil has conferred on this Government and <Col N="1188" /> upon its predecessor, the Provisional Government, since they first came into office.  Yet, would any Minister stand up and say that because it is a very useful thing to possess powers for interning people, without trial, powers to try people before Military Courts, and that these will not be exercised unless there is a great emergency, that, therefore, they ought to be left on the Statute Book as part of the regular law of the land?  If it is unreasonable that war measures should be exercised in times of peace, there is no necessity for keeping war measures on the Statute Book in time of peace.  When a new war breaks out, then let the Government come to the Parliament of the people for such powers as they think they ought to get, and the Parliament of the people will not deny them.  We have not been niggardly.  I do not think that the Government will suggest that we have been niggardly in giving them every power which they asked for, which they satisfied us was reasonably required by them for carrying out their duties in any existing emergency. Now, when they have relied upon the existing emergency for justifying the conferring upon them of these powers I do think that these powers ought to cease when the existing emergency comes to an end.</P>
    <P>There is one point in it which seems to me to be actually unfair, and that is to allow the Government to retain these powers when other people are not allowed.  They can levy their debts by the use of these extraordinary means, but they deny to the poor man who owes a debt to them the powers for collecting from his debtors the money with which he is to pay.  Is it a fair thing that the landlord, say, who cannot collect his rents, the tradesman who cannot collect the shop debts due to him, in order that he may get the money to pay his debt to the State, is to have these extraordinary powers put in force against him which may result in ruining him, when he is unable to use similar powers to get in the money with which he is to pay his debt to the State?  For that reason alone, if there were no others, it seems to me unfair that the State should have a power against the individual debtor that the individual creditor has not against those who owe debts to him.  Again, it seems <Col N="1189" /> to me to argue a lack of confidence, not only in the people, but in themselves, that Ministers should ask for these extraordinary powers as part of the ordinary law of the land.  No debts were ever more completely discharged in the past when they were levied by what was known as an alien Government than the debts that were due to the State.  They were not paid out of love for the Government of the day, or from the enthusiasm that anybody has for discharging his public debts. I do not suppose that there is any tax that one pays with less avidity than a tax due to a public body, whatever it may be.  That may be due to a lack of civic responsibility or not.  I do not know; but I do not think anybody cheerfully paid his rates or Income Tax, or whatever it might have been.  But whether he paid it gladly or not that was the kind of debt that was almost always discharged in full, and the occasions on which the Crown in the past had to resort to the courts of law for the purpose of collecting debts were infinitesimal in comparison with the resort that the ordnary citizen had to make for the purpose of collecting ordinary civil debts.</P>
    <P>The mere fact that it was a debt due to the State, and that the State could and would, at the public expense, sue a debtor and make him pay, was quite enough to make people pay in ordinary times.  We know that in the past public debts, or debts due to the State, were discharged in that way, and it does seem to me to show a lack of confidence in the power of Ministers themselves to restore the country to a normal state of affairs, and in the prospects of a return to sanity on the part of the people, that Ministers should tell us that they want these extraordinary powers as a big stick to hold over the people.  I have more confidence, I think, in the people than the Ministers themselves, and I have more confidence in the Ministers.  I believe that at the end of another eighteen months or so, we shall have got so far on the road to ordinary civic sanity, that people will be paying their State debts as they did in the past.  Surely, it is not too much to hope that the people when they are running the country themselves, and when it is being run by a Government of their own election, their own choice, their own people will realise that it is their duty to pay unwillingly it may be, and with <Col N="1190" /> a grumble, but still to pay whatever taxes are levied on them by the State for the purpose of carrying on the affairs of the Nation.  I do not think the people, however mad they may have been for the past twelve months or more, will continue in that state of insanity.  I have no doubt that there will be a great unwillingness to discharge the big load of arrears that has accumulated during the last couple of years, and it is for that reason I have supported the Government in asking for these powers to enable them to collect these arrears.  People will try to get out of paying these by every kind of excuse.  Excuses ought not be listened to; they ought to be taken with a firm hand, and this Bill enables the Government to do that in respect of these arrears.  People have been getting up several times here, and we have lots of correspondence in the public Press in which people tell us these ought not to be collected, because of the old story we have heard so often, that the President in some other capacity, or some other Minister, said that these were not going to be collected.  These excuses are being made, and if people make these excuses without any foundation for them, then I think the Government are perfectly right in taking strong powers to overcome the refusal to pay based on excuses of that kind.  But when these arrears are wiped off, and we get back to the normal taxation and collect the year's revenue and the year's taxes within the year, I do not believe that these powers will be required, and if they are not required I do not believe that they ought to be on the Statute Book, as part of the ordinary law of the land.  It is not creditable to any country to have to keep war measures on the Statute Book.  It shows, as I say, a lack of confidence on the part of the Government themselves when they say &ldquo;we cannot trust ourselves to get in the debts unless we have the big stick, which was put into our hands in the time of war to shake it over the people to make them pay in times of peace.&rdquo;  It is for that reason, and not from any desire to help anybody who is trying to get off paying his taxes, that I think for the credit of the Statute Book we ought not to perpetuate a war measure by making this perpetual.  A Finance Act must be brought in every year.  If in twelve months' time it is found that no progress has been made, or that insufficient progress <Col N="1191" /> has not been made in getting in the £3,000,000 arrears that the President told us were outstanding for Income Tax, then I am quite sure that the Dáil will not be slow to extend these powers for another twelve months, as emergency powers, because the emergency still exists.  I do not think that anything that has passed up to the present would justify the Government in saying that they have not our full confidence.  We will give them any powers that they satisfy us are really necessary, but unless these extraordinary powers are necessary, I do not think the Government ought to have them.</P>
    <P>Remember, it is not necessary to say that the Government exists here by the will of the people, and if these measures are oppressive they can be turned down. There will be no general oppression against the people as a whole which would get up a general agitation against the continuance of these powers.  It is one man here and one man there who will suffer by the exercise of these powers.  I have no doubt they will be exercised often, and there will be cases here and there in which the exercise by the Sub-Sheriff of the powers to take away and sell cattle and things of that sort, to seize without notice, will do grave injustice to individuals here and there. These individuals will not have the power to influence this body.  One question by one man here, and one in another place will be raised, but there will be no concerted action over the whole country, and the past in every country shows that it is almost impossible to work up any satisfactory or successful agitation against the oppressive use of State powers unless it is an abuse that affects the community as a whole.  No people will stand up, and no agitation will be made by the community as a whole for an injustice which hits only an odd individual here and there.</P>
    <P>What brought about the revolution in England, the levying of ship money had gone on uninterruptedly for twenty-five or thirty years without complaint by anybody, until it was used as a means for preventing the calling together of Parliament. If an injustice so grave as that which overthrew the Stewart dynasty in the end had gone on through two entire reigns, and possibly for more, without <Col N="1192" /> complaint and without objection, surely it is not a very likely thing that a Government here will be overthrown because one or half a dozen individuals, even in every one of the counties under the Government's sway, happened to suffer some injustice through the negligence of a Sheriff or a Sheriff's officer?  It is for that reason that I fear these powers will cause injustice, an injustice for which there will be no remedy.  I do not think they ought to be continued after the cessation of the emergency to meet which they were conferred.  Therefore, I beg to move that the powers conferred by the amendment in my name, the effect of which is that the powers conferred by this Section shall cease with the end of the year 1924, be agreed to.  I do not know whether it is necessary to explain the proviso at the end.  The Bill gives indemnity to Sheriffs for things which they have done.  It would be clearly unjust that persons should wait until January, 1926, and then slap an action against the Sheriffs for something which they could not bring an action against them for before.  I think the Sheriffs ought to retain immunity for all time for anything they did while the Act was in force&mdash;the same immunity which they would have while the Act would be in force.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>After the able speech of Deputy Fitzgibbon very little remains to be said.  I opposed Section 7 on the last Reading, and having done so I intend to support Deputy FitzGibbon's amendment, so that these excessive powers may have a definite period in which they will operate.  I am not at all impressed by the arguments advanced that those powers are necessary.  I would point out to the Government that they are very anxious to collect debts due to them yet, at the same time, from all over my constituencies&mdash;there are two of them&mdash;I am pestered with letters dealing with accounts due by this Government. The Government refused to pay, or for some reason do not pay, those accounts, and I have not got the powers which they have under Section 7.  The Dáil takes that as a joke, no doubt, but it is no joke for a man when he is kept twelve months out of his money.  It is no joke for a man who has rendered service to a Government, and who wishes to support it, to <Col N="1193" /> be unable to obtain redress when he asks for payment, even after consulting with the Deputy for his constituency.  I put it to the Minister for Finance that that very point alone is sufficient to make any Deputy support Deputy Fitzgibbon.  He wants, merely, to limit the powers of the Government after a certain time, and I have yet to learn what argument can be brought forward by which this amendment should not be accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to support the amendment moved by Deputy FitzGibbon, and I do so all the more heartily because of the fact that I urged the Minister for Finance to consider this very point when the Bill was in Committee.  I have been unable to call to my recollection exactly what the Minister said then, whether he would leave the matter open for consideration or whether he would turn it down.  I do know that the matter was put before him by me, and I again support it now. I support it with all the greater heartiness because Deputy FitzGibbon, in placing the case before the Dáil, has based it on the argument used by the Minister for Finance.  The Minister, in defending Section 7 of the Finance Bill, stated that those powers were necessary for the collection of income tax arrears. The amendment proposed by Deputy FitzGibbon states that the Section shall have no effect after January 1st, 1925, by which time those arrears should have been collected; therefore, according to the arguments used by the Minister, Deputy FitzGibbon's case has been made and these powers should be powers limited in time, because they are, by the nature of the case as put before the Dáil, limited in their purpose, and when the purpose has expired the time also should be caused to expire under the provisions of this Act.  There is one other aspect of this matter that has not been touched upon by Deputy FitzGibbon, and it does raise a constitutional question of very great importance, I think, to the legislation to be passed through the Dáil and sent up to the Seanad.  This Bill, presumably, one would imagine, of all Bills to be passed by the Dáil, is essentially a Money Bill. If this is not a Money Bill, then there is no Money Bill.  In other words, the powers of the Seanad are limited in respect <Col N="1194" /> to this Bill because of certain provisions in the Constitution.  For that reason I urge that entirely new legislation, which is not strictly financial, but administrative, should not have been introduced into this Bill.  These provisions are not provisions that should be covered by a certificate from the Ceann Comhairle as being strictly of a Money Order.  They are dealing with powers of the Executive, which are of a different class of legislation altogether. Here is a matter where criticism by another body of the same legislature should be welcomed, and that body should have power and effect to amend a Bill, whereas those powers are limited by the certificate issued because it is a Money Bill.  I think it is an unwise use.  I would even go so far as to say, without charging any intention in the matter, that on reflection it must appear to be an unfair use of the powers of this Dáil to bring in under cover of a Money Bill something that is not strictly, and ought not strictly, to be covered by the certificate of the Ceann Comhairle.  I hope in any case that that aspect of it will be very largely mitigated by the adoption of this amendment; and I hope for that reason, in addition to the reason mentioned by Deputy FitzGibbon and put so clearly and cogently by him, that it will be accepted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope the Deputy is not under the impression that it is within the province of anybody except the Ceann Comhairle to certify a Bill as a Money Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I said it would naturally carry your certificate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is merely an expression of opinion from Deputy Figgis.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the existing law a Collector of Taxes is empowered by his warrant of appointment to proceed by distraint for the collection of taxes outstanding from defaulters.  Section 7 has two definite objects.  Sub-sections 1 and 2 deal with the utilisation of the Under Sheriff for the purpose of recovery, and the strengthening of the powers of distraint so as to ensure that distraints will be effective for securing to the revenue the duty to which it is entitled.  I <Col N="1195" /> cannot undertake to accept any amendment on sub-sections 1 and 2; but I take it that the criticisms that have been directed to this section deal with the sub-sections 3 to 13.  There are arrears, as I have already explained, amounting to over 2½ millions.  It is unnecessary to explain to the Dáil that it is absolutely necessary that we should get in that money.  Fixing a time limit upon the operations of these particular sub-sections would immediately give rise to schemes for escaping their operations during the period from now until the 1st January, 1925.  I am sure that that is not the intention.  We must have the powers to collect, and I take it that Deputy Fitzgibbon, in moving the amendment, quite realise that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now Income Tax is imposed every year and it is open to the Dáil each year to review the Income Tax Acts.  I take it then that when the Dáil, next year, is considering the imposition of Income Tax, it would be open to the consideration whether it was necessary to have those powers next year or not.  I should say that three particular cases of interference with the Collectors have come under my own notice.  It will be alleged by some that that was owing to certain Irregular activity.  I incline to the view that it is not; that it is another sort of activity altogether, simply that people will not pay Income Tax and will seek to avoid it.  In our first years of administration it is absolutely necessary that those people should be made to realise that they have responsibilities which cannot be shelved by any so-called political activity.  In three cases men were taken away, having gone to certain areas peacefully and according to law, to collect what was due to the State.  They were arrested, brought away into the country, deprived of their money and their books, and so on.  Directly that that sort of information gets spread out, the life of a Collector in any one of those places would be made intolerable.  We owe a duty to people who take up these responsible positions, of Collectorship, or who have those positions, and we owe it to them to say that it will not be open to people who have no sense of responsibility to make war on them.  If cases are put to us that we have moved against people who are unable to meet those debts, and that it <Col N="1196" /> interfered with them in the course of their business, then there is a case for objection to this, but no such case has been put to us.  It is a case of wilful obstruction of the officers of the State in the execution of their duty on behalf of the State.  If the Deputy would agree, I would suggest that he would withdraw the amendment, and add at the end of the Section a new sub-section 14, to read &ldquo;sub-sections 3 to 13, inclusive, of this section, shall only apply to any such certificate as aforesaid which relates to Income Tax for the year beginning on the 6th April, 1923, or any previous year.&rdquo;  That gives us an opportunity of collecting, not alone the arrears, but the taxes we are now imposing by this particular machinery, and does not give power, or anticipate power, for any future imposition that would be made. If next year it is thought necessary by the then Minister for Finance to ask for such power, he will have to ask for it, but in respect of arrears due up to date and Income Tax due for this year, that is all we are asking for.  We are not, in this case, asking for anything additional to what Deputy Fitzgibbon has in his amendment.  The last day for payment of income-tax for this year is, I think, the date he has down; that is for the second moiety.  Therefore it would meet that particular case, and it leaves open for consideration any provisions that may be required next year.</P>
    <P>As regards Deputy Figgis's suggestion about a Money Bill, I suggest that he ought not to allow prejudice to blind him in this matter.  A Money Bill is a Money Bill whether it has clauses in it, to which the Deputy objects, or not, and he ought to know, powerful and comprehensive constitutionalist that he is, what dangerous ground he is entering upon, when he is laying open to consideration the authority and sovereignty of this particular section of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. FITZGIBBON Mr. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that the amendment suggested by the Minister for Finance does all that I desire to effect by my amendment, and I think, if anything it ties the hands of the Government a little tighter.  Therefore, I have no particular objection to allow his words to be substituted for mine.  My main object was that the Government should come back again if <Col N="1197" /> they wanted fresh powers.  So far as I could gather from the amendment read by the Minister for Finance, and certainly from his statement, his amendment would have that effect.  It was to apply to arrears due to date and to Income Tax for the present year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>While undoubtedly the amendment that has now been suggested for acceptance by the mover of the amendment on the Paper is satisfactory in so far as it meets the points raised by Deputy Fitzgibbon, it is not satisfactory towards meeting the points raised by Deputy Wilson.  While we will all support the amendment as an improvement in the Bill as passed in Committee, it is not to be taken that we approve, in any degree, of Section 7 in the form that it has passed the Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Fitzgibbon desires leave to withdraw the amendment on the Paper, and to substitute for it the amendment read by the Minister for Finance.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. FITZGIBBON Mr. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>I move &ldquo;that the new Sub-section 14 stand at the end of Section 7.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. EAMON DUGGAN Mr. EAMON DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EAMON DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In Section 8, Sub-section (1), line 18, page 6, to insert immediately after the word &ldquo;assessed&rdquo; the words &ldquo;on and shall be payable by the person entitled to receive such interest, dividends, or other annual payments.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>It is merely a drafting amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move: In Section 10, Sub-section (1), line 51, page 6, to insert immediately before the words &ldquo;Rules applicable to Schedule C&rdquo; the word &ldquo;General.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>It is simply a correction of a clerical error.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: In Section 12, page 8, to insert immediately after Sub-section (3) a new Sub-section as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;(4) There shall be added to paragraph <Col N="1198" /> (a) of Clause 1 of Schedule of the Income Tax Act, 1918, the following sub-paragraph:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;(iv) to any person, whether a citizen of Saorstát Eireann or not although not resident in Saorstát Eireann, from the sale of any goods, wares, or merchandise, manufactured or partly manufactured by such person in Saorstát Eireann.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The words are identical with those of a Financial Resolution already proposed by the President.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: In Section 12, Sub-section (4), line 25, page 8, after the word and figure &ldquo;Rule 1&rdquo; to insert the word and figure &ldquo;and 2.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. DUGGAN Mr. DUGGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DUGGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: In Section 12, Sub-section (5), line 29, page 8, after the words &ldquo;Case IV.&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;and Rule 3 of the rules applicable to Case V.&rdquo;  It is merely a drafting amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE DAIL IN COMMITTEE." RHead="- THE DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>THE DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - THE DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill, as further amended in Committee, is reported.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Minister deals with the main question&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We have been in Committee on those amendments. The main question is not to be taken now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say a few words on Clause 4 at the Report Stage of the Finance Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the Report Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am in the hands of the Dáil with respect to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. FITZGIBBON Mr. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we still in Committee?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We have gone out of Committee because we have finished, with the amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. FITZGIBBON Mr. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>In Section 21 there is a provision that certain stocks <Col N="1199" /> and bonds issued by the British Treasury should be accepted in satisfaction of that duty, but that they shall not apply in the case of any claim for death duties arising in Saorstát Eireann on a death occurring on or after the 1st day of April, 1923.  We are now ended the financial year and the 1st April, 1923, is two months ago.  It seems to me a little hard that the executors of the late deceased should be deprived of the privilege I think they still possess at this moment, and will continue to possess until this Section passes.  I suggest the figure 3 should be made into 4.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That can be done in the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. FITZGIBBON Mr. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am throwing it out merely as a suggestion.  It seems to me that retrospective legislation is very objectionable, but when it is retrospective legislation against a corpse it is even worse.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is a reasonable suggestion, and I am prepared to accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. FITZGIBBON Mr. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>It can be treated as a printer's error.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Report Stage of the Bill has not yet been considered.  I think it would be better to take it to-morrow.  Deputy Johnson's point would then arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it would not be inadvisable to say that what I propose to do is to ask the Minister for Finance whether he will at this stage deal with the question which was put up to him on an earlier stage and which was passed by on the assumption that we were out of order in raising it on the clause under discussion.  It turned out that it was not out of order, but in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand we took the earliest opportunity of informing the Dáil at that time at the next clause that it was open to anyone to raise any question.  There was a discussion, the Deputy may remember, for a couple of hours on the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1200" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The question that were raised on the correct section were not raised in the following section, and therefore were not dealt with by the Minister.  Perhaps if he refers to the official report he will see the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>On the motion to-morrow &ldquo;that the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo; it will be possible to raise any matters dealt with in the Bill, and in that way the Minister will be almost compelled to deal with them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>It would not be possible to treat the whole of Section 7 as a clerical error?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Report Stage will be taken to-morrow.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES." RHead="- COMMITTEE ON FINANCE">
    <Title>ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES. - COMMITTEE ON FINANCE.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil went into Committee on Finance on the Estimates for the financial year ending March 31st, 1924.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES. -" RHead="SUPERANNUATION AND RETIRED ALLOWANCES">
    <Title>ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES. - SUPERANNUATION AND RETIRED ALLOWANCES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;&ldquo;That a sum not exceeding £1,220,055 be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the Charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1924, for expenditure in respect of Superannuation, Compensation, Compassionate and Additional Allowances and Gratuities under Sundry Statutes; Compensation under Article 10 of the Treaty of the 6th December, 1921; Compassionate Allowances, Gratuities and Supplementary Pensions awarded by the Minister for Finance; the salary of the Medical Referee; and Sundry Payments in respect of Pensions at present paid by the British Government.&rdquo; There has been £420 voted on account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. W. DAVIN Mr. W. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to ask the Minister if he has had any representation regarding the question of pensions to Prison Officers, or whether it is the intention of the Government as the result of any representations that may have <Col N="1201" /> been made to amend the Act of 1909? I would also like to ask the Minister if he is aware of any cases where people who have taken advantage of the conditions under Clause 10 of the Treaty and retired upon fairly reasonable conditions have got positions in any other Government Departments or section of the Free State Civil Service.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister assist us to understand what are likely to be the total commitments under Article 10 of the Treaty in respect to allowances?  I daresay that he has been able to sound the views of members of the various staffs, officials, and so on, as to whether they are likely to retire or whether they are to be asked to retire. If he could give some idea how far the retirements have proceeded and what are likely to be the total commitments under this head it would be of interest to the Dáil and the country.  I am not sure whether I understand this aright.  In regard to the retirement under the Treaty of officials of the Post Office, Customs and Excise and Inland Revenue Departments, are they charged in their respective estimates, and if so, why are they treated differently?  Why should they not be brought under this Estimate so that we will get to know more clearly what the total sum chargeable under this head may be?  Perhaps the figures are already in the hands of the Minister and he could enlighten us on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of the point raised by Deputy Johnson I would be glad if the Minister would give a little further explanation, than I for one am in possession of, or I believe anybody is, in regard to the operation of Article 10 of the Treaty.  Article 10 of the Treaty states that certain compensation will be paid to those who are discharged by the Free State Government or who retire in consequence of the change of Government effected in pursuance of the Treaty.  It appeals to my mind, at least, that if a person is likely to retire in consequence of a change of Government that there ought to be some date by which that person's decision should be limited.  It is incredible that a person should retire, say twelve months after that change has been effected, by reason of the change, because if twelve months, then <Col N="1202" /> why not two years, and so on?  I think there ought to be a limit of time within which such persons shall have made up their minds whether the change of Government is such as would cause their retirement.  That arises specially on the Vote immediately before the Committee, because it appears from the Estimates put before us that the Estimate under this particular head for the new financial year is to be £31,000 in excess of what it was the year that has just closed.  That figure surprised me very considerably because I had imagined that a great number of them, if not all the retirements, would have operated by the end of the last financial year, and that there would be very few to be incurred in this new financial year after the establishment of the State, and six months after the enforcement and prescription of the Constitution.  In any case there is a figure showing an increase of £31,000, £29,000 having increased to £60,000.  I think we ought to have some fuller information put before the Committee as to the cause of that increase.  When that is being furnished perhaps the Minister will also let us know if these compensations are to be continuously incurred in future, or whether a decision has been come to as to a time limit within which the possibility of retirement and compensation can be taken to be considered by the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>This Vote covers payments of the ordinary pensions under the Superannuation Act of Civil Servants who have retired on or after the 1st April 1922, from all Departments of the Civil Service, excepting the Post Office, the Revenue Department, and one or two small Departments whose pensions are charged on special funds&mdash;that is the Congested Districts Board and the Intermediate Education Board.  The number of pensioners who have retired in the ordinary course is as yet very small, and the ordinary charges under sub-heads (a) and (b) are consequently of small amounts.  The additional allowances paid to such officers are charged under sub-head (c), and certain gratuities to non-pensionable people under sub-head (d). Those who retired under Article 10 of the Treaty retired under conditions not less favourable than those given by the Act of 1920&mdash;the Government of Ireland Act &mdash;and under the terms of that Act, I <Col N="1203" /> think there was a period of seven years during which Civil Servants had the right of electing whether they would serve or not under the Government.  Of course they would be entitled during any of these seven years to retire.  Some retired immediately, and others retire occasionally, as time goes on.  The number recently has not been considerable.  Pensions of Civil Servants who had retired from the Departments I have mentioned before the 1st April are still being paid by the British Government, and the payments made by them are covered, partly from this Government and partly from the Government of Northern Ireland. They were, as it were, servants of the whole country.  A proportional amount is payable by the Government of the Saorstát and by the Northern Government. The proportion of the Saorstát will form the subject of discussion, and the sum inserted under sub-head &ldquo;H&rdquo;&mdash;£135,000&mdash;is, therefore a conjectural sum.  Sub-heads &ldquo;B.B.&rdquo; and &ldquo;C.C.&rdquo; cover allowances paid as compensation, under Article 10 of the Treaty, to Civil Servants and other public officers who have retired in consequence of the change of Government or who have been discharged by the Government.  The annual allowances are charged to sub-head &ldquo;B.B.&rdquo; and a lump sum, payable to persons under the Superannuation Act, 1909, is charged to &ldquo;C.C.&rdquo;  The number of allowances being paid at the time the Estimate was framed is shown in Part 3 of the Estimate.  The number has slightly increased between that date and the present time.  Sub-head I, which is the largest sub-head on the Vote, may give rise to some criticism.  It represents the repayment by Saorstát Eireann of seventy-five per cent. of the pensions awarded to the Royal Irish Constabulary on disbandment, excluding persons recruited in Great Britain during the two years preceding the Truce, and the ordinary Pensions payable to the R.I.C. This percentage has been agreed upon provisionally, without prejudice to the ultimate financial settlement.  I have not had any representations from the prison officials in connection with superannuation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the people who have taken advantage of their position <Col N="1204" /> under Clause 10 of the Treaty to get positions in other Departments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know of any such cases and I should say offhand that they would not be entitled to be re-employed; that would be to get pensions and also payment for services now.  I do not think they would be entitled to the two.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Does that apply to disbanded Royal Irish Constabulary men?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I should say that it does.  I do not think there is any case in which a disbanded Royal Irish Constabulary man drawing a pension is employed by us at present.  I do not think there could be such a case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That last point raises a question that would require a little explanation and the Dáil should be satisfied on it.  This amount £1,350,000, is to be paid to the British Exchequer pending a final settlement.  One might ask, I think, whether there is to be any other authority for paying this sum except this Vote?  The Treaty under which this money is paid says that the Government of the Irish Free State agrees to pay fair compensation, on terms not less favourable than those accorded by the Act of 1920, to judges, members of police forces, etc., but so far as I remember no authorisation has been given as to the terms on which these pension shall be given.  How much more favourable, for instance, than the Act of 1920 would allow or would make compulsory?  We do not know what rate these pensioners are being paid and we do not know what conditions are being imposed upon them. We do not know, for instance, whether it is a fact that men in receipt of these pensions can receive other Government pay; whether men who were in the Royal Irish Constabulary are able to join the police force&mdash;the Civic Guard. No authorisation has been given, so far as I know, for the payment of this sum of £1,350,000, and we are presumably only handing over a sum to the British Exchequer according to their demand without knowing what conditions are being imposed before these pensions are paid.  I think it would be necessary to have this matter brought before the <Col N="1205" /> Dáil formally so that we should know what the money is intended to cover, what pensions are to be paid, and the rates of these pensions and what conditions are attached to them.  Whether the Government of the Free State has agreed with the British Government to pay compensation on terms much more favourable than those accorded by the Act of 1920 we do not know, and I suggest that it might be to the advantage of the Exchequer to withhold this payment for a time until a little further enlightenment has been given to the Dáil and perhaps some formal authorisation given to the Ministry for the expenditure of this money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>If there was one clause more than another to which I took strong objection in the Treaty it was the clause which authorised a pension; committing the Irish Free State to the extent that we are now asked to vote away this large amount of money. There was a time, I understand, during the operations of the Anglo-Irish war when representations, official or otherwise, I do not know, were made to the Royal Irish Constabulary to the effect that it would be in the interests of the country that they should terminate their service to the British Government which was carrying on as we know at that period.  Certain numbers of men put loyalty to their country before their pockets and made sacrifices by resigning from the R.I.C.  Hundreds and thousands of young men in Ireland who were too lazy to thin turnips or do other useful work joined the R.I.C., and I think that their services, which were services to the British Government at that time, should be paid for out of the British Imperial taxation rather than having it placed upon the shoulders of the Irish taxpayers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy cannot argue that thesis now.  At this stage it is impossible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>It is stated that it is agreed provisionally that Saorstát Eireann will pay 75 per cent. of the above pensions without prejudice to the ultimate financial settlement.  Now, I contend that these Irishmen served England rather than Ireland during that period, and I <Col N="1206" /> object to the big pensions they are getting from this country.  Generally speaking, they had only two or three years' service, and now we find that able-bodied Irishmen who served in the R.I.C. for that short period are disbanded and getting pensions of £100 a year.  As well as that, many of them are getting positions and taking these positions below the ordinary trade union rates of pay in many business concerns, while at the same time we find twenty or thirty thousand men in this country unable to get any employment or consolation, except what they receive through the payment of the dole.</P>
      <P>I hope that when these things come to be settled, if there is ever a settlement of these financial matters between the Free State and the British Government, that whatever Executive Council is functioning on behalf of the Irish people at the time, will impress upon the British Government the necessity of undertaking this liability which is a British liability, and which never should have been placed upon the shoulders of the Irish people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has very successfully made a speech upon one of the Clauses of the Treaty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I was just going to point that out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>And it is as well that the Deputy should know that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The 75 per cent. is provisional, and is open to consideration. It is well known that in all these questions of an accountancy character which arise, some arrangement must be arrived at.  I think that, taking them all round, we have got favourable provisional rates. This one may not be too favourable to us, but one cannot have the best of all bargains. This particular one may be to our prejudice to the extent of 10 per cent., but in carrying out our part of the arrangement we are carrying out the strict letter of the Treaty under terms &ldquo;not less favourable.&rdquo;  This means exactly what they are receiving; it did not mean more favourable, and that they have got terms more than favourable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it it is the object of the Free State to make it more favourable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1207" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if they could afford it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to know whether you have done so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The people have got exactly what they were entitled to get. It does not mean that they got more. Some people's interpretation means a good deal more than what was given by the Act of 1920, but we are not liable for more than was asked under the Act of 1920.  It was not contemplated in the interpretation the British Government made.  There is nothing except £1,350,000 that represents anything for which we are liable, and the same applies to the Civil Service so far as the application of that Act is concerned, and they have been considered on terms not less favourable.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES." RHead="- RATES ON GOVERNMENT PROPERTY">
    <Title>ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES. - RATES ON GOVERNMENT PROPERTY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move: &ldquo;That a sum not exceeding £105,000 be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the Charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1924, for expenditure in respect of Rates and Contributions in lieu of Rates, etc., in respect of Government Property.&rdquo;  £15,000 has been voted on account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to know if this vote covers payment by the Government for rates due on private property commandeered for military purposes.  I know of some cases where private property was commandeered over twelve months ago and on which no payment for rates or anything else has been made up to the present time, and in which the individuals who own that property have been summoned for the payment of the rates due on their property.  I would like to know if the payment of these rates by the Government is included in the Vote as it stands?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>In paying the rates will the Government consider it a duty to pay the special six-penny rate which is levied under the Damage to Property Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1208" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Vote does not include any sum for cases such as Deputy Davin mentioned.  I should say that all claims, such as he refers to, would come in in a separate account in respect of property for whatever service commandeered the property.  Government property is exempt from statutory liability to assessment to local rates, but is by custom the subject of contributions in lieu of rates.  Contributions are given from this Vote for all property occupied by the Government for the Public Service and maintained directly out of Votes of the Oireachtas.  Premises become non-rateable immediately they come into Government occupation and it is the fact of occupation upon which the grant is based.  All the different contributions in respect of Government property, instead of being charged on the different Votes, are united in this principal Vote with the exception of rates assessed on telegraphs under the Telegraph Acts which are provided in Sub-head L 4 of the Post Office Vote so as to bring all the expenses of the Postal Service together as far as possible.  The valuations on which the contributions are given were formerly fixed after communication between the British Treasury Valuer, acting for the Government, and the Local Authorities.  They are based, so far as practicable, on the same principles as the valuations of rateable property with which they can fairly be compared.  By administrative arrangement, the valuation Department now performs for the Ministry of Finance the function of the former Treasury Valuer, and all claims by local rating authorities for contributions in lieu of rates are examined and certified by that Department before payment is made by the Ministry of Finance.  The details given in Part 3 of the Estimate suffice to explain the provision made for the current year.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES." RHead="- MINISTRY OF HOME AFFAIRS">
    <Title>ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES. - MINISTRY OF HOME AFFAIRS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Vote 32&mdash;Ministry of Home Affairs&mdash;is the next Estimate set down by the Committee on Procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the sum of £29,546 be granted as the amount required for the year ending 31st March, <Col N="1209" /> 1924, to pay the salaries and expenses of the Ministry of Home Affairs.  £10,000 had been voted on account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to discuss, under the terms of this Vote, any question regarding the policy of the Ministry of Home Affairs, but I desire to take this opportunity to draw the attention of the Minister to certain facts in connection with the cases of ex-R.I.C. men who resigned during the period of the Anglo-Irish War.  You have, in another Vote, already made provision for pensions for men who served England up to the time of their disbandment.  The Minister is well aware of the conditions under which many patriotic Irishmen resigned from that service during the period of the Anglo-Irish War.  Promises were made, as far as I understand, that men making such sacrifices would be provided for not less favourably than the men who carried on and served England up to the time of their disbandment.  A committee was set up a long time ago to go into individual cases, and I cannot understand why a report from that committee has not been submitted to the Minister, and some action taken to relieve the men I refer to, many of whom are in a very bad position, indeed.  I know personally of two cases, two married men, with wives and dependants, who resigned from the R.I.C. about three years ago.  I know that in these particular cases the men concerned have been unable to find employment, and ever since they resigned have been living on the charity and friendship of their relatives.  I think that men who made such sacrifices as they did should not be placed in that position.  I desire to ask the Minister whether there is any prospect, in the immediate future, of a report being submitted from the committee that was set up to deal with cases such as I mention, so that legislation may be introduced into the Dáil to make provision for these men and their families. In my opinion the committee that was set up has exhausted a good deal of time. Whether they have done all that could be done in the period since they were set up as a committee to deal with this matter, is not for me to say, but I think <Col N="1210" /> that in fairness to these men, to whom promises were made, that we should have some indication from the Minister as to when legislation is likely to be introduced to deal with cases of hardship such as I refer to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The committee in question submitted a report almost a month ago.  It is at present under the consideration of the Ministry of Finance. It will not be for me to introduce a Bill bearing on that matter.  It was within the scope of my Department to conduct an inquiry.  An inquiry has been conducted by a Departmental Committee, and the result of that inquiry is at present before the Ministry of Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we to understand from that that the decision of the Ministry of Finance is to be final, or are the facts to be brought before the Dáil before the matter is finally determined?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Ministry of Finance is considering the matter and a Bill will be introduced.  Otherwise it would be impossible for the Ministry of Finance to act and grant pensions; it would be against the law.  These are persons who are not properly pensionable under the existing law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that I misunderstood the Minister for Home Affairs.  I thought what he said was that it was not now a matter for the Dáil but for the Ministry of Finance.  On the Vote, I would like to ask the Minister for Home Affairs to explain one or two items in the estimate.  Though we have the sub-heads A, B, C, D and E, we have no explanation of E, which is given as &ldquo;Expenses of winding up affairs of late Dáil Eireann Courts, including remuneration of certain Judges of Dáil Eireann Supreme Court.&rdquo;  I think it would be desirable that we should know to what date the Dáil Judges have been paid, or will be paid, and how much they will be paid.  It is even of more importance to have information as to the relations between <Col N="1211" /> the old Courts and the new Courts, and as to when litigants, who got judgments in the old Courts, will have the right to claim that these judgments shall be enforced.  The position as I understand it at present, is that many of those who went through the courts and got judgments are not able to proceed any further, are not able to get their judgments enforced, and they are invited either to take new actions in the existing courts or to wait until the Ministry has made up its mind as to how to unify the two operations.  I have heard complaints from litigants on that score, and I think it is causing a great deal of heart-burning and a lot of expense.  People who were quite able to pay damages six months ago are not now able to pay, and, therefore, the complainant in the case will, probably, have to whistle for the damages that he was awarded in the courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>No information is given to us in these Estimates of the £6,000, &ldquo;Expenses of winding up the affairs of the late Dáil Eireann Courts.&rdquo;  Under Sub-head (a) we have an item, &ldquo;Adviser on Police Organisation, £567; salaries, £1,000, and presumably, the balance is pension.  In looking through the other Estimates we find that, altogether, £6,528 is provided for police headships:&mdash;Chief Commissioner, Civic Guard, £1,300, Deputy Commissioner, Civic Guard, £1,000, Assistant Commissioner, Civic Guard, £900, Director of the C.I.D., an unspecified salary, plus £250 on this Vote; Chief Superintendent, C.I.D., £400, Chief Commissioner, D.M.P., £1,700, Assistant Commissioner, D.M.P., £975&mdash;a total of £6,525.  One might almost imagine that that would be nearly enough for advice on police administration, but we are asked in this Vote to provide another £567 for an Adviser on Police Organisation, and £500 for a Civil Commissioner.  Perhaps the Minister will deign to give us some information on these two offices, and explain why it was not possible to get from the existing police officers of long experience, the advice that this £1,067 was intended to pay for.  There is also a question whether the provision for administration of the Alien Restrictions Act, £1,200, is really necessary, in addition to the ordinary <Col N="1212" /> police operations.  One would think that police organisation would be quite enough to deal with this trivial work of restricting the invasion of aliens, and some explanation might be given to us as to the reason for this expenditure of £1,200 over and above the ordinary police operations.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister would be able to give an indication to the Dáil as to when the ordinary law will again become operative in the country unaffected by the over-riding powers of the military, and when it will be possible to declare that a state of war no longer exists, a condition which prevents the ordinary law from operating and which is the reason given by the Government on many occasions for adopting what some of themselves described as &ldquo;rough and ready methods of carrying out the law.&rdquo;  We are advised, of course, and rightly so, to obey and respect the law, and the law is there to punish individuals and also to protect individuals.  But of late the measure of protection has not been very great, so far as individuals are concerned, and perhaps the Minister would be able to say how soon he hopes we will be back to ordinary conditions as they existed before the so-called state of war prevailed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>The £6,000 to cover the expenses of winding up the affairs of the late Dáil Courts is made up as follows:&mdash;Payment of outstanding debts due in respect of the said courts, estimated at £1,500, the said debts falling into five main classes: costs due to Solicitors who acted as prosecutors in the late Dáil Courts; arrears of remuneration to District Registrars and Clerks of Parish Courts; claims for escort and conveyance of prisoners and their maintenance in custody, including expenses incurred in effecting arrests; minor expenses of Courts remaining unpaid, such as rent, purchase of stationery, cost of lighting, and similar items; sums paid by way of deposit for hearing of cases which were, in fact, never heard.  There is a provision of £4,500 in respect of the salaries of judges of the Supreme Court.  There were four such judges at £750 per annum, two of which are at present suspended <Col N="1213" /> from office without salary, the other two being employed in other capacities.  A Bill will be introduced shortly dealing with this matter.  I am well aware that there has been hardships to litigants, and I am equally well aware that there has been consequent heart-burning. There has been heart burning of many kinds, and there are many causes within the last year or so.  I genuinely regret that it has not been possible to deal with this matter earlier.  It was very complicated, and the condition of things in the country did not help towards the speedy straightening out of the tangles. A Departmental Committee has been at work on this matter, and a Bill is in preparation.  That Bill will provide for the formal validation of the decrees of one kind or another given in these Courts, and after investigation and after formal validation the decrees will bind on an Under-Sheriff equally with the decrees given in the Courts at present functioning.  There is no absolutely royal road out of the kind of chaos in which things were in the country a year or more ago.  It was a revolutionary period.  There was debris of one kind or another and it was a question of hewing our way out of it, but substantially the tangles will be made straight, and people who brought cases before these courts and produced proper evidence and proved them and secured decrees, may feel assured that such decrees will obtain execution.  It may be very belated execution.  That is unavoidable, but the writ will run and we will take measures and bring a Bill before the Dáil to make sure that that will be so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As to the Adviser on Police Organisation&mdash;in the Estimates that item is starred, and it is pointed out that this post is held by an officer who is in receipt of a pension, and his actual pay as Adviser is the excess of £1,000 over such pension.  Last July and August when the Civic Guard were down at Kildare men were sent in to make trouble, and they had a certain measure of success.  That trouble centered largely around the personality of men who were admitted to that force, and who had served in the Royal Irish Constabulary.  It was a good peg to hang activities on, and the very most was made of it.  There was no advertance to the fact that these men were admitted to that force with the full approval <Col N="1214" /> and endorsement of the man who had acted as head of our Intelligence in the struggle with the British Administration, and the British Occupation here. That was waved aside, and these men were held up to odium as ex-R.I.C., as if they were ex-R.I.C. and nothing more than that.  This man who is Adviser of Police Organisation was a member of the Civic Guard at that time, and was one of those that the trouble and the policy that was fomented within the Force centered around.  When it came to dealing with that trouble, which amounted in effect to mutiny, some concession was necessary, and, at the same time, this officer was a man of great experience, a man with skill and knowledge of police matters.  I could not agree to leave the new Commissioner who took over at that period, without his services, his experience and advice.  The thing was met by technically removing this man from the Force, making him an official of my Ministry, and leaving him as a lay secretary to the new Commissioner. That is the position.  He has acted in the capacity of Secretary to the new Commissioner since then, and he acted in that capacity with very good results. It is, I think, an advantage that the Ministry should be represented at the Civic Guard Headquarters by such a person who is not himself a member of the Force, and who is available to advise and consult with the Ministry from time to time in matters affecting public peace and order.  There are not, I think, many items in these Estimates for which the taxpayers are getting better value than that particular item.  The Civic Guard has been brought out of a very disturbed and precarious condition into an efficient Force, and while much of that is due to the personality, the efficiency and sense of discipline of the Commissioner, much of it is also due to the fact that he had available at his elbow a man of ripe experience, and extremely level-headed in dealing with police matters.</P>
    <P>The Civil Commissioner is certainly an item that would call for attention.  It will be remembered that a particularly inflamed situation existed in the Pettigo area something more than a year ago, and that impetuously, as we thought, and without consultation with the Provisional Government, the British moved their forces beyond the strict line of the Border, and occupied the village of Pettigo, <Col N="1215" /> having used a certain amount of artillery to clear their way.  Pettigo was a little barrel of gun-powder on the Border line, with possibilities of trouble, one might say, out of all proportion to its own intrinsic importance.  When the situation improved here, and improved up, in, and around that area, representations were made to the British to withdraw these troops, and that was conceded.</P>
    <P>There was a tendency to represent the Orange or Protestant inhabitants of that area being in a state of terror, owing to the impending Free State occupation and administration, and it was considered wise and advisable, without ourselves agreeing that there was any particular ground for that suspicion or distrust to take all reasonable steps to meet those fears.  A military post was sent up there under the charge of a picked officer, considered eminently reliable and specially suitable for a difficult position of that kind, and a specially picked number of the Civic Guard were sent up there.  In addition to that there was sent a Civil Commissioner, generally to watch the situation and report direct to the Government through me, and readily available for any Protestant inhabitants of that area.  Incidentally, he himself is a Protestant.  It was felt that it was something of a gesture to send there a man of their own faith to listen to and transmit to us any complaints that had to be made.  Very few complaints were in fact received through that channel, but the presence of the Commissioner had a steadying effect, and Pettigo, which six or eight months ago was in an inflamed condition holding possibilities of trouble that might spread widely and intensively in that area is now a little short of a model village.</P>
    <P>The most cordial relations exist between all creeds and classes there, and between those Protestant inhabitants and the forces of the Government, of which they stood in dread before our administration.  It is perhaps more correct to say they were taught to stand in dread.  The need for the Commissioner there is rapidly passing away, and steps will be taken to place the person in question on some other employment. I do not think there were any other points raised except Deputy O'Connell's point as to when the situation <Col N="1216" /> in the country will be such as will admit of a recurrence to the ordinary law, as he says.  That, of course, is a matter of surmise; but we have to face it that owing to the events of the last ten months you have a very grave condition of affairs in the country and a great deal of explosive material, literally and figuratively, lying about.  It is rather for the Minister for Defence than for me to state when the situation would be so normal as to cease to require the military treatment of certain problems. There is a distinct improvement inside the last three or four months.  That improvement is likely to be maintained, in fact progressively maintained, but if the Deputy had the facts and reports from the various counties at his disposal &mdash;the facts and reports that I have at mine&mdash;he would probably agree that there are throughout the country many problems and many situations that are not capable of being dealt with by Civil Bill procedure.  Take one county alone. There is one county in which there are no less than twenty farms in the occupation of people who have neither legal nor moral nor equitable title to them. There are many counties where there is a considerable amount of real property also in the possession of people other than the owners.  There are stolen motor cars from one end of the country to the other, and generally it will have to be recognised that there must be something in the nature of a middle period as between the period of absolute revolt and the period of normal conditions.</P>
    <P>It is probable that within the next month I will introduce a Bill dealing with what we regard to be the requirements of that middle period.  In so far as the use of the military is concerned, we will endeavour to see that that is kept down to the minimum.  But it is also our duty to see that minimum will be the minimum which will ensure that the problems that exist as a result of the revolt and turbulence of the last ten months will be very adequately and very speedily dealt with.  The country wants security.  It wants the vindication of legal rights.  It wants to end all the disorder that has been undermining the national credit and destroying the commercial security of the country within the last year.  It will be best <Col N="1217" /> that we should all face that situation here, and agree, irrespective of mere catch-cries or mere electioneering, to do the best thing for the country, so that it can go ahead in stability, and go ahead with the very necessary work of reconstruction.  The unemployment figure in the country is probably high. That unemployment will not even begin to be drained off unless people feel that they can wisely and with a fair prospect of a return, put out their money in enterprises of one kind or another.  No one here wants to embark on any career of junkerdom or militarism, and similarly we must learn by the past, and we must realise that there are urgent problems existing in the country; that you have only an unarmed police force at half strength.  There are only three hundred and fifty stations established out of a total establishment providing for eight hundred and seven stations, and it will be necessary, and necessary for some considerable time to come, to use certain things, at any rate the armed servants of the State, for whose maintenance the people are paying, and paying dearly.  So it is that at present the problems of what may be called the middle period are being visualised, and a Bill is in course of preparation.  That Bill will come before the Dáil in due course.</P>
    <P>Question: &ldquo;That a sum not exceeding £19,546 be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the charge which would come in course of payment for the year ending 31st March, 1924, towards the salaries and expenses of the Ministry for Home Affairs,&rdquo; put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES." RHead="- MINISTRY OF AGRICULTURE">
    <Title>ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES. - MINISTRY OF AGRICULTURE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move that a sum not exceeding £275,982 be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the charge which will come in course of payment for the year ending 31st March, 1924, for the salaries and expenses of the Ministry of Agriculture; and of certain services administered by that Ministry including sundry Grants-in-Aid.</P>
      <P>£125,000 had been voted on account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Provision is included in this estimate not only for services in connection with Agriculture but also for services in regard <Col N="1218" /> to Technical Education.  Of the total estimate of £400,982 nearly half is in respect of the latter services.</P>
    <P>The estimate shows an increase of approximately 3 per cent. over that of the past year, but the increase is more than accounted for by one item in respect of technical education, to which further reference will be made later on. The most noteworthy change is the disappearance of the Fishery staff.  Those services have been transferred to a special vote.  When comparing the vote with 1922-1923, the necessary adjustments in respect of this transfer have been made.  The reduction of approximately £16,000 has been effected under the sub-heads covered by the expenses of the Headquarters staff.  The most serious increase is £28,000 in respect of certain grants-in-aid and other grants, and the bonus of teachers in technical subjects, including Irish, whose subsistence allowances and salaries are paid out of Dáil funds, apart from monies affected by this Vote or obtained by local authorities from the product of certain special rates.  As matters stand at present the payment of these bonuses from monies provided by the Dáil is unavoidable.  Steps are being taken with a view to considering whether new arrangements cannot be introduced for the future whereby the State's contribution in this respect can be kept within some definite limit.  In view of the increase it will be appreciated in order to keep the total estimate within the 50 per cent. increase over last year that it has been necessary to make reductions on all remaining items. An exception exists in the case of the sum available in the scheme for the improvement of dairy cattle.  That is increased by £1,500, consequent on a rapidly increasing desire to enable dairy farmers to secure registration of their herds.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON</NameTxt>
      <P>In connection with this estimate I would like to again press upon the Ministry the consideration of the question of tobacco-growing. We discussed it here before Whitsuntide and on that occasion the Minister made certain statements.  I would like to ask him to meet the people concerned in a rather better manner than has been promised.  Undoubtedly <Col N="1219" /> the whole thing is an experiment, perhaps a costly experiment, but in spite of the Minister's statement I do not know that it has yet been proved that the experiment has not been worth while.  From information I have received I understand the growers and workers of tobacco could be met in a reasonable spirit if the Ministry were willing to so meet them.  Even if the Ministry were willing to consider the whole thing as yet in the experimental stage it would be sufficient.</P>
      <P>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle at this stage took the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON</NameTxt>
      <P>It is claimed that this Government is not prepared to do what other Governments even within the Commonwealth are prepared to do for tobacco-growing.  Surely the Government should be able to meet the growers in a much better spirit than has existed up to the present.  As I said on the last occasion, the Ministry wants to restrict the acreage to 60 acres. Up to the present there have been 200 acres given over to the experiment. As Deputy Johnson pointed out there were fairly definite promises made to these people by the Ministry, and a great deal of encouragement was given them before the 6th December last.  On the strength of those promises certain of those people have gone to a great deal of trouble and a considerable amount of expense in equipping and installing machinery for the handling of tobacco.  I am not an expert, even in tobacco, but it may be that there is some difficulty in handling this material from the manufacturer's point of view.  It is claimed for the growers that the difficulty is largely due, not altogether to the quality of the home-grown tobacco, but to the conditions under which the growers have been labouring.  If there is one thing that is, perhaps, defective in Irish agriculture, it is that where there could be more crops, there are not more crops grown.  This particular crop does mark an advance in that respect towards a better system of agriculture.  For that reason, if for nothing else, it should get some encouragement.  I hope the Minister for Finance will be able to throw a <Col N="1220" /> little more light on the subject of the grant from the Development Commissioners for this experiment.  It was considered as an experiment, and was encouraged by grants as such.  It is claimed now that there is still about £40,000 from the Development Commissioners' grant under the control of the Saorstát, and that that should be devoted to the continuance of the experiment. I hope the Minister will say definitely what is the position with regard to that £40,000.  It is claimed by the growers that they are being put unfairly into competition with growers elsewhere, and that they are not getting as good a chance as those other growers.  They say, for instance, that Indian tobacco is grown and worked not only with very cheap coolie labour, but it is grown duty-free, and on account of that it has got considerable preference over certain American tobaccos.  It is not grown duty-free in Ireland.  The Minister says if it were the Revenue would lose.  He has not yet told us how much, exactly, it would lose, but he says it would be a good deal. Now, if there were a considerable reduction in the duty, I think that the growers would be prepared to consider continuing their work.  If they were met in that respect they could consider the position of the Government in the matter, but they say that the offer already made, which penalised in cash certain growers, is not and cannot be accepted.  They say that it will mean that the whole experiment is likely to go by the board and that this particular crop is&mdash;so far as this generation is concerned&mdash;likely to be lost to Irish agriculture.  That would be a very unfortunate thing, indeed&mdash;that any crop, even if only an experimental crop, should be lost to Irish agriculture.  I should like to ask the Ministers whether they would not reconsider the question of the duty on tobacco.  If there are not a great many, there are at least a considerable number of people engaged in this business.  It is not right or fair that because it is not a crop that has been attempted by the farming or agricultural community generally to say that only a handful of people are engaged in it.  They are a handful of people in comparison with the whole population, but they are a handful of people who have been trying to do something that has not been done for the furtherance of the national <Col N="1221" /> economy.  For that reason they should not be brushed aside, because some of them may have peculiar temperaments and numerically, perhaps, they are only a thousand all told.  I am sure that the Minister has seen a statement in the Press during the week.  A case has been made by one of the persons interested in the industry, and I think it is up to the Ministry to answer that case.  This gentleman says that if you take the average yield per acre at 1,000 lbs., the amount of tax remitted at 50 per cent., the amount paid in labour, directly and indirectly, on every acre of tobacco grown in the various processes from sowing to placing in bond at about £150 per annum, you will find that £145 is equivalent to the wages of one man and one woman for a year&mdash;a clear national gain of £145 per annum.  The Irish Exchequer save unemployment pay for one man at 15s. and one woman at 10s. a week or £65 per annum.  Tobacco growing would thus mean an annual gain to the nation of £210 per acre.  The Exchequer would probably lose something between 4s. and 5s. on every pound grown, and taking the yield at 1,000 per acre it would lose probably £208 6s. 8d. per acre.  It is claimed by this gentleman that when everything is gone into, there would be a gain to the nation of £1 13s. 4d. per annum per acre grown, plus increased wheat, grown without a subsidy, plus the establishment of the industry.  If the Minister can meet the case I hope he will with full facts and figures.  Incidentally, I may say that, if it is met in the sense in which I have indicated, the growers' claim&mdash;I do not know whether they will be justified or not&mdash;they will be in a position to dispose of part of the crop for the year 1921-22, which at present they are unable to dispose of.  I hope the Ministry will give the whole matter consideration, and that they will meet, even in a generous way, the claim for a considerable reduction in the original duty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnRooney" hpid="Mr. ROONEY Mr. ROONEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ROONEY</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not regard this as a question of considering the tobacco industry in its experimental stage, but rather as an attempt to revive an Irish industry.  In Co. Wexford there were 1,000 acres of tobacco grown formerly.  I suppose it was largely consumed in Ireland and outside of it.  I think that one of the reasons that Irish tobacco is not popular now in Ireland is because the <Col N="1222" /> English Government when it was here succeeded in cultivating a taste for English tobacco.  I think if the Irish Government allows Irish tobacco to go on the market a little bit cheaper than foreign grown tobacco it will be a very good remedy, and a number of people will cultivate a taste for it.  Another point of view I would like to put before the Dáil is this.  If a man with a small farm of 10 acres grows an acre of tobacco he will have a more handsome income out of it than he would get from any other crop.  Taking all these matters into consideration, I hope the Minister will see his way to give a rebate of 5 per cent to Irish-grown tobacco.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. DOYLE Mr. DOYLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOYLE</NameTxt>
      <P>As one who was engaged in tobacco-growing for some years, I can add a little to this discussion, and I say that I think that the Government would be entitled to allow at least 50 per cent. off the present duty imposed on the leaf.  In the other Colonies they are allowed to grow tobacco duty-free, as we are allowed to grow barley and oats.  If it were grown duty-free here it would prove a most profitable crop, so profitable that you would have every acre in Ireland planted under tobacco next year.  I was sorry to see the castigation which the Minister for Finance gave the quality of Irish tobacco on the last occasion.  I was not here then, but I may say that I have grown tobacco for 14 or 15 years, and I put it on the market and brought it to Belfast to Mr. Gallagher, and I heard him say that in this country we could grow plug tobacco fit to compare with any grown in the United States or South America.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not pretend that we can grow light tobacco, but as far as heavy pipe tobacco is concerned we have gone beyond the experimental stage, and in the acres of tobacco grown in my vicinity we produce more per acre than any in America.  The average yield would be one thousand pounds per acre, but in some of the highly manured districts in Wexford they went so high that they produced two thousand pounds per acre.  The experiment first was started under conditions like those which induced everyone to do his best. A rebate of one shilling per pound was given.  The duty at that time was four shillings per pound, and labour did not cost over a third of what it does now. <Col N="1223" /> At that time, I have known acres to net one hundred pounds profit with that shilling rebate.  The sale of the leaf paid the expenses of growing the crop, and the shilling per pound was put into the pocket of the grower.  I am talking now of a time when wages were one-third of what they are.  As far as promoting labour is concerned it is known that tobacco will require three times as much labour as any crop grown in Ireland, and it would be an incentive to relieve unemployment if grown on a large scale.  I think the growers are not asking much when they ask for 50 per cent. rebate, as other growers are growing it duty free in other colonies.  If you want to get the crop grown it will also be an incentive to breaking up land and tilling it.  A crop could never be grown on its own in this country.  There is no reason why there should not be some rebate taken off it, a rebate which would give an impetus to the grower to continue the growth of it.  Something should be done to release all the tobacco that cannot be sold at the present time.  If there were a rebate sufficient to induce people storing it to sell it, it would bring in a handsome sum to the Government at the present moment. I think the Ministry would be well advised to give some stimulus to the growth of tobacco.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not going to thresh the tobacco question any further, but merely to say that tobacco was first introduced into Europe by Sir Walter Raleigh.  It was in Ireland it was first grown by Sir Walter Raleigh, and it is very singular if it is going to be a failure in the country in which it was first introduced into Europe.  My remarks are in connection with the estimates for Agriculture as they were last year.  I pointed out last year that out of many thousand pounds, forty-six million pounds, less than half a million was used for developing the oldest industry in this country.  We were then told that the Department of Agriculture was marking time for carrying on.  I want to ask the Minister to say whether he is still marking time or carrying on.  I believe money spent in the developing of the dairy industry is well spent.  Money spent in any of the products in which we excel is well spent. But when you see four million pounds <Col N="1224" /> spent on primary education, and only half a million spent on this industry it seems to be a lob-sided arrangement and it seems that we, who are looking after the interests of agriculture, are not doing our duty.  I am not objecting to anyone interrupting me but I do not think the head of the Government should interrupt a man doing his best.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not interrupt the Deputy.  I said a word to Mr. Blythe, Minister for Local Government, and I suppose I am entitled to say a word.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course it is on agriculture. Anything is good enough for the farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not about agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>We were promised last year that the Department was going to be organised, and I want to ask the Minister, although he is engaged in the dangerous occupation of bringing in Land Bill, what steps has he taken to re-organise his department in order that we who live on the land may be enabled by expert advice to carry on; in order that this country may be a suitable place for our sons and daughters to live in, and in order that we need not be shipping them to America, our daughters to be the handmaids of Russian Jewesses who have got rich in New York. and our sons to be policemen.  Without education, badly equipped, we have to send them abroad, and all the money that can be spent on our children is less than half a million.  The Minister occupies an outside position in the Executive. I believe the Minister for Agriculture should be in the Executive. The question is too big in this country. The Minister in charge of our industry should be in the Executive, and if we farmers ever get into power we will be in the Executive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamOBrien1922" hpid="Mr. O'BRIEN Mr. O'BRIEN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'BRIEN</NameTxt>
      <P>Where will we be then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. WILSON Mr. WILSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to make a joke of this question.  I really would like to hear from the Minister what steps he would be able to take so that the veterinary department and all the other departments may be placed in a proper position so that they may give us <Col N="1225" /> efficient and proper instruction in the ways we ought to follow to meet the world's competition.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would suggest for the better ordering of this discussion that the Minister, or some member of the Government, should deal with the question that has been raised regarding the tobacco industry, and let us exhaust that, and that even if somebody has to follow him on the same subject he could deal with other matters, such as may be raised by Deputy Wilson and others.  This is a very big Vote, a very important Vote, indeed, and it cannot be dealt with simply by skipping from one subject to another, and asking the Minister to reply <i>en bloc.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="MINISTER for AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan) Patrick J. Hogan">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for AGRICULTURE (Mr. P. Hogan)</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the points that have been made with reference to encouraging tobacco growing, we agree that the experiments which Sir Nugent Everard has conducted have proved that tobacco can be grown in this country, and that a certain kind of tobacco can be grown as well in this country as in any other country.  There is no doubt that Sir Nugent Everard's experiments have proved that.  There is no doubt either that Sir Nugent Everard and the other experimenters have acted in a very public-spirited manner in regard to this particular question.  It is due to them to say that.  It is one thing to prove that tobacco can be grown&mdash;I think Deputy Wilson pointed out that Sir Walter Raleigh proved that&mdash;it is one thing to prove that tobacco could be grown fifty years ago at a profit; it is a totally different thing to prove that tobacco is a profitable crop at the present date.  That is the real question.  I do not think that even the most ardent admirer of the experiments that have been made will go so far as to say that it has been proved that tobacco is a profitable crop from any point of view.  I am not saying it is not, but I say that the experiments up to date are still experiments from the point of view of showing that tobacco can be grown as a profitable crop, and as compared with other crops in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When the experiments started the idea was to show that tobacco could be grown here as well as it was grown in the British Colonies, and for that purpose a grant was given.  The scheme intended that the <Col N="1226" /> grant would equalise the conditions here with the conditions in the English Colonies, where tobacco had been grown successfully.  It is a totally different matter to ask us to encourage tobacco-growing by a rebate of duty.  That raises totally different considerations.  It is a question for the Government, for the Minister for Finance and the Dáil to consider very seriously whether this is the right time to change the character of the experiments.  Sir Nugent Everard, the most important of the experimenters, has suggested that he should get a total rebate of Excise Duty, and claims that he could grow at least half of the tobacco that is being used in the country if he got that rebate.  I have not the exact figures available at the moment, but they are so big that I can use fairly round figures.  If he is right it would mean that we would lose in Excise Duty something over £400,000 per annum.  It is a very important question at present, and it would be a very important question in the best of times, as to whether we could afford to lose that amount of revenue. There is the prior question as to whether he is right, whether you could get people in this country to smoke nothing but Irish tobacco.  But, assuming his own figures are correct, that his own prophecies in the matter are correct, we would stand to lose something like £400,000 of Excise Duty.  The question is&mdash;can you put that £400,000 to better use?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnRooney" hpid="Mr. J. ROONEY Mr. J. ROONEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. ROONEY</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, they are only asking for half.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>We can adjust the figures.  Let us say £200,000&mdash;a quarter of a million.  Can you put that to better use?  You can hardly expect the Government to decide that question at this time when we are Budgeting for a deficit of £24,000,000.  Apart altogether from that this question of rebates is a question that affects not only tobacco but other industries, and in deciding a big fiscal question of that sort you cannot decide it with a view to tobacco-growing alone, or an experimental crop.  You cannot change your fiscal policy, in order to help experiments. You certainly should not change your fiscal policy merely with a view exclusively to what everybody in the Dáil has admitted is even at the present stage an experiment.  I think that would be generally agreed upon. <Col N="1227" /> On the other hand, we acknowledge obligations to the people who have made these experiments, and who are conducting these experiments, and we are trying to meet them.  We are willing to carry on, and the Minister for Finance has consented to give them the same grant as they got in normal times, plus the extra grant that they got during the war for war purposes, for this year.  I think I can say now without being accused of being a prophet that we are coming into happier times financially, and next year we certainly ought to be in a much better position to make up our minds as to what we will do in the way of giving a rebate. When we are making up our minds we must have in view not only tobacco, but fiscal policy generally.  That is the position with regard to tobacco.  Sir Nugent Everard has, as Deputy Rooney pointed out, asked for this 50 per cent. rebate. I think that would work out at £133 per acre.  If you compare that with the £25 per acre which he received while the British Government was running this country you will see that he is not making a very modest claim.  We suggest that he gets a grant of £25 per acre and his old grant of £8 per acre on the uncropped area.  The total acreage is 114, and the uncropped area would be 74 acres.  That is the grant that was provided for him to meet war conditions, and though we are entering into peaceful times we are willing to continue that grant for one year, and I think that the Dáil will admit that we are meeting him fairly so far.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister say what conditions apply?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>At the moment they are not settled.  We are still debating the question.  Sir Nugent Everard knows very well what his rights are, and knows pretty well the business side of his proposition, and we have not quite settled the conditions as yet.  With regard to Deputy Wilson's remarks, he wants to know am I still carrying on.  I feel inclined to say I still am, in one sense.  He has asked what are our plans for the Department of Agriculture.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A Ministries Bill will be introduced immediately which will have the benefit, from the point of view of the Department of Agriculture, of confining it strictly to agriculture.  That will be so much <Col N="1228" /> gained.  It will be a very big gain, as it will transfer Technical Education, Science and Art, and other services which have nothing to do with agriculture, to other Ministries.  When that Bill is through, and I hope it will be through within the next few months, the Department of Agriculture will be organised for the first time as a Department of Agriculture, and not as a sort of Department to deal with Arts and other services of that sort with which it has nothing to do.  He has asked what money we are spending on agriculture.  Well, in spite of the fact that we are spending money on the Army, money for compensation, and money for other purposes on which in normal times you need not spend money, and on which money has not been spent during the last decade, we are still maintaining the Estimate for the Department of Agriculture at practically the old figure.  We are still maintaining all the services, and, in view of the financial stringency, I think it is a very creditable, if not a very daring, programme.  With regard to the general policy of the Department, there is an Agricultural Commission sitting at the moment, which has already sent in two or three interim reports dealing with very important matters&mdash;marketing, grading, etc.  We cannot change the agricultural policy in these matters without considering these reports very carefully.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be better if the Minister did not now give a general reply, as other Deputies may wish to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that as this is the only other point raised, I should deal with it at the moment.  If you wish, however, I will wait.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be better to wait.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. DOYLE Mr. DOYLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOYLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister said the offer was £25 plus £8 on the uncropped area.  What about the cropped area?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>£25.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. DOYLE Mr. DOYLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOYLE</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no use offering that sum, as tobacco could not be grown with it at the present price of labour.  We had £25 an acre on the last growing, when labour was not so high as it is now, and <Col N="1229" /> we had to give up growing it.  It could not pay under any conditions whatsoever except the Government are prepared to give a substantial rebate of nearly half the duty at all events.  I do not see why the Government should not give a rebate in this country similar to that given in the other colonies, where all tobacco consumed is all grown duty free.  If we could grow it duty free you would have in Ireland one of the most profitable crops in the world.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel that this question of tobacco-growing ought to be considered from the point of view of agriculture, and not from the point of view of fiscal returns.  The trouble, I think, is&mdash; and it is just as well that the grower should face it&mdash;that it is a nuisance to the Revenue Department to have tobacco growing in Ireland, and that the Department would very much rather it were not grown in Ireland.  That is frankly and honestly the real trouble that the farmers in Navan district and in Wexford district are faced with&mdash;the fact that the Revenue people consider tobacco-growing in Ireland a great nuisance.  Their interest in agriculture is only in so far as it is a system of spending money.  They do not want revenue from tobacco grown in Ireland. They would rather get revenue from tobacco smoked in Ireland, and therefore they are going to put all kinds of obstacles, as they have done, against the encouragement of the growth of tobacco in this country.  I think it is as well we should understand that, and ask ourselves if it is worth while spending money on tobacco-growing when the chief Department&mdash;the Treasury&mdash;is definitely against such encouragement.  They put all kinds of obstacles in the way of the grower, and they make it very difficult for the crop to be grown profitably.  Consequently some kind of subsidy on the growing side has been found necessary. I am rather concerned with the position up to date.  The State has given encouragement to small farmers to grow tobacco.  It has also given encouragement to the manufacturing and the preparing end to invest money for the purpose. Now that they have got into a state when they are blocked up with stocks which they cannot realise without great loss of money, they are met with a new situation from the fiscal side.  Imperial <Col N="1230" /> preference was given to India, which has encouraged the unloading of stocks of tobacco in England and Ireland, produced at a very low price, and these stocks have brought down the price of Irish tobacco to almost nothing.  One Department of the State has encouraged and continued to encourage tobacco-growers, and the other Department of the State comes along and makes the effort of the Agricultural Department null and void, and penalises to a very great extent the men who followed the advice and almost direction of the Agricultural Department.  Now, if the Ministry of Agriculture and the Ministry of Finance have made up their minds that tobacco-growing&mdash;having gone through the experiments and proved itself quite satisfactory from the agricultural point of view&mdash;is bad for the revenue, and therefore bad for the country, let them say definitely to the farmers of the country, &ldquo;We are not going to encourage you any longer to grow tobacco, but, in view of what you have done in response to our advice, we are going to see you through the present tangle and the present losses.&rdquo;  It seems to me that is the only position the Minister for Agriculture and the Minister for Finance can take up on this matter consistent with the arguments they have used.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The growing of tobacco has, undoubtedly, proved very valuable from many points of view, speaking as a national economist.  It is good for the country.  It is a good crop and employs a great deal of labour and is demanded by the people, that is to say, it has met a want, and it can be improved in quality. But from the Revenue point of view, undoubtedly it has disadvantages. It is very much better for the Revenue that they should get tobacco from America, Turkey, or anywhere else, as it has to come through certain ports and come through in bond.  A man wanting to grow tobacco, say, in Kerry, Galway, or Cork has to apply for a licence to do so, and I suppose a Revenue Officer has to be kept lying under a ditch or hedge to be sure that nothing goes wrong with the tobacco, so that the Revenue Department may not suffer from tobacco growing.  There is no doubt whatever that a Department of the State has encouraged the people who were working at tobacco growing, <Col N="1231" /> and the people who have spent money for the curing, preparing and re-handling of the tobacco, and it is only fair to those people&mdash;those small farmers&mdash; who have assisted in this, and spent a lot of money, and bound themselves to certain commitments, that they should be assisted out of the money of the Development Grant voted for this purpose.</P>
    <P>Deputy O'Shannon raised a question, and indicated that there is a great deal of doubt as to the facts in regard to this grant of £70,000.  It is alleged that the £70,000 was earmarked out of the Development Grant for the purpose of encouraging tobacco growing in Ireland, and that £30,000, or thereabouts, has been spent.  I take it that the sum of £3,000, odd, referred to in this estimate, is portion of that £70,000, which may have been the capital sum&mdash;I do not know how it is arrived at&mdash;but I suggest, if Ministers have made up their minds that it is not a good proposition to encourage tobacco growing, and if this is a balance of this fund that has been earmarked for the tobacco growers, then the losses that have been sustained, or would have been sustained, by putting the present stocks upon the market at the moment, ought to be met, to a considerable extent, out of the balance of this fund that is available.  If it has been decided that there should be no more peddling with tobacco growing, and that is the indication given us from the Ministry, then there should be some recompense to those men who have at their direction persisted in this experiment. I realise the force of the argument of the Minister in regard to 50 per cent. of the duty, if 50 per cent. of the duty could be foregone.  Fifty per cent. of the duty at present rate could be expended upon the encouragement of some industry, and probably could be spent to better advantage than on tobacco growing.  I admit that frankly, and I do not think that there is very much to be got out of the claim that so large a proportion of the duty should be remitted unless there is going to be a very narrow limitation in the acreage grown; and that, I think, would be an impossible condition.  If you are going to remit the duty to the extent of 50 per cent. you cannot limit the acreage, and one could easily multiply <Col N="1232" /> the present tobacco production 20 or 30 times if you are going to remit 50 per cent. of the duty.  I do not think that there is very much advantage, considering the present state of the revenue, to be obtained by a claim for the remission of the duty for the purpose of continuing the growth of tobacco; but I contend that there is something due to those people who have invested money and time at the direction, and more or less for the convenience, of the State, and that they, at least, should be met in regard to their losses in the matter.</P>
    <P>There are one or two other small matters on this vote that I want to get out of the way in case the Farmers' Party desire to raise bigger questions.  I think Deputies on the Government benches, at least, will probably be glad to have some fuller information about item H.H. and as to the work of the National Stud.  I have no doubt it would be very interesting to the Dáil and the country to know what has been the result of these activities in regard to horse-breeding at the National Stud.  You may find that it is going to be a new Department, and perhaps Deputy Doctor White might have something to say in regard to the manning of that Department.</P>
    <P>There is an item of £457 for Statistics and Intelligence Branch.  The Minister for Finance told us a few days ago that in future the Statistical Branch of the Ministry of Industry and Commerce will compile statistics relating to agriculture also.  There are no provisions made in the Industry and Commerce Vote for the statistics of agriculture, and one would expect that the whole of this Vote would come under one head.  Whether that is a matter for adjustment after the Ministries Bill has been passed I do not know, but it at least seems there would be need for a good deal of revision of the Department's work in regard to statistics if it is to be brought under the Ministry of Industry and Commerce and under one chief statistician.  Then all these charges should be brought under that head, including the Vote for £457 for the Inspector of Statistics.</P>
    <P>I notice also an item, &ldquo;Officer in charge of Agricultural Labour Disputes,, which was not a charge in last year's account.  I take it that that is an officer who has been transferred from the Ministry of Industry and Commerce to the <Col N="1233" /> Ministry of Agriculture.  While one can understand the advantage, perhaps, of having such an officer under the Ministry of Agriculture, it does not seem to fit in with the general work of such an officer with regard to disputes.  I am inclined to think that unless there is very close collaboration between the two Departments in regard to this kind of work, there will eventually be a lot of overlapping. You cannot detach an officer and use him for this work alone without relating it to work of a similar kind on other Departments, and it seems to me that his value will be greatly minimised by detaching him from the general work of such a Department.  I would like also to hear from the Minister some explanation regarding the reduction in the amount for allotments, and as to whether there has been any great decrease in the demand for allotments, and, generally, to ask that he should make a statement as to this question of allotments, and explain why a reduction has been found necessary.  There is another matter, too, that I would like to ask the Minister to enlarge upon.  There were two reports submitted to the Minister's Department from the Commission of Enquiry relating to the encouragement of cow-testing through the country and the establishment of special stud farms. So far as one can gather, the money and time spent on that enquiry have been wasted.  No results are apparent, except the publication of reports, and inasmuch as these reports were sent in as definitely practical propositions&mdash;that is to say, were generally proved as practicable, economical and urgent&mdash;it is required, I think, of the Minister to explain whether anything is being done in regard to the putting into operation of these recommendations, or as to what decision has been come to in regard to them: whether they have been turned down as impracticable or as being too costly, and why nothing has been done in that respect. I note there is an increase in the Vote for the improvement of dairy cattle.  Perhaps we shall have some information as to what that is intended to cover, and as to what the proposal is.  Is it to increase the premiums, or to develop any special side of the industry?  I think the country, the agricultural community, and the Dáil is entitled to a very much fuller statement of policy, past, present, and <Col N="1234" /> future, from a Ministry when presenting a Vote asking for money of this kind, and it is not too late, even if we have to adjourn this discussion, for the Minister to make a full statement in regard to Ministerial policy on agricultural questions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with the Deputy that the Dáil is entitled to full information in regard to the Estimates, and I think I have heard that before.  The Dáil is always given full information in regard to the Estimates, and if there are any points that any Deputy wishes to get any light or leading on I will be personally, and every other member of the Government will be, willing to give it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Excuse me a moment.  My suggestion about further information is rather this, that the presentation of Estimates of this kind is an occasion when the Minister might well make his statement of policy, examine the work of his Department, and the proposals he has in mind for the future of the Department.  We might agree with every item in these Estimates, and unless we are fault-finding we have nothing to say except to try to extract information. We might make charges for the purpose of extracting information, but it seems to me that it would meet the desire of the Dáil and the country if, in presenting Estimates asking for money for the coming year's work, the Minister would generally review the work of his Department and give some indication as to what the intentions are in regard to that Department's work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I daresay there will always be differences of opinion.  I do not agree with the Deputy as to what would be the correct way to view, either the past work of the Department of Agriculture, or the intentions of the Ministry for the future.  Nothing would suit me better than to come in here and to deliver a long general statement as regards agriculture.  It is quite simple and quite easily done, but I do not think it is business.  Agriculture is a very big question, and the future of agriculture in this country is a very big question. &ldquo;The future policy in regard to agriculture&rdquo; is such a vague expression that I do not know what it means.  Land purchase is a very important item of agricultural policy, grading of products <Col N="1235" /> is a very important item of agricultural policy&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. DOYLE Mr. DOYLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOYLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Transit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Transit.  Deputies can suggest things.  I could go on for a long time, and I could mention various important items that go to make up general agricultural policy.  But I suggest to the Dáil that it is much better, and much more like business, to attend to these separately, and when you have anything worth saying on each of them, to say it.  When I am dealing with the question of grading, I hope to tell the Dáil very fully what our policy is, and to give our reasons, our plans, to show what has been done in the past and what will be done in the future.  But I wish to say, with all deference, that I do not agree with the Deputy's suggestion that in introducing Estimates of this sort you should make a general statement on agricultural policy.  I do not think it would get us anywhere.  I think it would take about two days to make a statement of that kind, and I do not think anybody would be very clear as to what our policy was at the end of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to tobacco, there is one thing perfectly clear, that we have not made up our minds&mdash;neither the Minister for Finance nor I have made up our minds.  But Deputy Johnson has made up his mind, and has stated frankly that there is no future for tobacco in this country, and that it would not be worth while spending a couple of hundred thousand pounds on it.  That is very frank. I have been wavering a very long time in my own mind, and I have often almost come to that conclusion, but I am not quite of that mind, and I do not think the Minister for Finance is quite of that mind.  We certainly will not dogmatise by saying that there is no future for tobacco in the country.  We will say, that if it is necessary to forego something like £600,000 in revenue, that it could be better spent than to spend it on tobacco, but we are not clear that there is a necessity for the foregoing of that.  If we examined the whole experiment which has been going on for many years, and it is extremely difficult to get information with regard to it, I am not clear that we might not find that tobacco-growing was not such an impossible <Col N="1236" /> proposition as the figures would lead one to believe.  We are quite frank when we say that we have not made up our minds that tobacco-growing is impossible. What we have made up our minds about is, that we cannot afford to spend, at this stage, anything between £200,000 and £600,000 on it.  I think that is a fairly evident proposition, and I need not labour it.  We are blamed because Deputy Doyle stated it is out of the question to ask Sir Nugent Everard to carry on for another year with the subsidy we are giving him.  Well, we are giving him £25 per acre, and he carried on for a great many years on that. We are also giving him £8 an acre on the uncropped area.  That brings the total up to something like £40 per acre on the cropped area.  If you transfer the poundage on the uncropped area to the cropped area, and if you add the poundage you are giving him on the cropped area, you get something like £40 an acre.  He carried on for £25 an acre for many years, and it is not too much to expect, in view of the circumstances and the financial stringency of the country, that he would carry on for £40 for another year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. DOYLE Mr. DOYLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOYLE</NameTxt>
      <P>And produce a crop that cannot be sold, with that subsidy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I will go no further than to state that he carried on his crops and produced them for a great many years with a subsidy of £25 an acre, and he got no greater subsidy, notwithstanding that he was dealing with a Government that could balance its Budget.  We are offering him £40 an acre.  I do not claim that we are infallible.  We have not made up our minds definitely, like Deputy Johnson, that there is no future for tobacco.  We will give ourselves another year.  The Department of Agriculture are engaged at present in trying to get&mdash; and it is extremely difficult to get the information from Sir Nugent Everard&mdash;all the data that would enable us to come to a definite conclusion on the subject.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>When he says the Minister has not made up his mind, does he mean to say the President has not made up his mind?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly, if the President had made up his mind that there was no future for tobacco-growing he would not give a subsidy of £40 an acre.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1237" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I was rather taking the evidence of his last statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I read his last statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I heard it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot usefully argue about that.  The President is able to speak for himself.  We are giving £40 an acre anyway, and we do not claim to be infallible.  By this time next year we hope to get sufficient information from Sir Nugent Everard.  It is extremely difficult to get information that would enable us to come to a conclusion.  I may say we are in exactly the same position as the Agricultural Commission found themselves.  They heard all the witnesses and experts&mdash;the Department of Agriculture, Goodbodys, growers, etc. &mdash;and yet they have not been able to make a recommendation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>We do not know what your fiscal policy will be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the difficulty. We have not yet decided what our fiscal policy is to be.  I do not know that there is any secret about that.  We have not decided yet as between Tariff Reform and Free Trade, and we never pretended that we had.  We would be extremely foolish to initiate our fiscal policy by dealing with a purely experimental crop like tobacco. That is all I intend to say with regard to tobacco.  With regard to statistics, that sum will be dealt with as a result of the Ministries Bill.  With reference to the National Stud, I hope the Dáil is not under the impression that the National Stud is not an extremely useful institution. It is.  I think the best recommendation it could get is to say that the only money we need provide for it out of Votes amounts to £5.  I do not know whether the Deputies know its history. It was a stud presented, I think the words are &ldquo;to the nation,&rdquo; some years ago by Lord Wavertree.  There is one farm in England and one in Ireland, and there are thoroughbred horses in each farm.  We have not yet settled our claim, which is that we are entitled to all the horses and assets in Ireland, and the English may have the horses and the rest of it in England.  There is some valuable blookstock down there, and Captain Greer is the man in charge.  It <Col N="1238" /> would be extremely difficult to get a more competent man, and the National Stud is run on most efficient lines.  I do not know what information Deputies require regarding the Stud.  All I want to impress on the Dáil is that the National Stud is a most useful and valuable acquisition, and we do not propose to allow it to be interfered with or its usefulness impaired in any way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Magennis makes the point that from the size of the Estimate it would suggest that it was rather like a collar stud.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am surprised that a financial expert like Deputy Figgis never heard of such a thing as a total Estimate.  I do not think I will waste the time of the Dáil in explaining the meaning of that technical term.  Now, with regard to the provision for dealing with wages made in the Estimates of the Department of Agriculture, I am surprised that Deputy Johnson disagrees with the principle, because I think the principle is sound.  Surely the Department that should deal with agriculture should deal with agricultural wages.  I had taken it for granted that I would not find any opposition from the Labour benches to the principle that a Labour Department as such&mdash;a purely Labour Department&mdash;is essentially fundamentally unsound; that we should not have a Department merely for settling strikes, and that wages should be dealt with as part of its particular industry.  I thought we had received the approval of the Labour Party to that principle when this question arose before in connection with the Ministry of Industry and Commerce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is quite true, and I raised this matter as a grievance. The Minister is now proving my contention as to the desirability of not having to extract information in the form of a grievance.  It is not a grievance. It is a point I wished to draw the Minister's attention to, the desirability of such an officer being in very close touch with the officer who has similar work in the Industrial Department generally.  I just raised the question with a view to finding out if such an officer is kept in that close touch, inasmuch as he would have to have some assistance.  Is that assistance provided out of this Department, or is it provided out of the other Department? <Col N="1239" /> I urge there should be at least very close contact between the two Departments that have to deal with questions in dispute between employers and employees, not necessarily wages questions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I am giving information to the Deputy that he knows better than myself.  There must, of course, in the nature of the case, be very close contact between the two departments, especially on questions which affect the wages side.  The Deputy mentioned the Interim Reports which the Agricultural Commission sent in, and he wanted to know what would happen and what we were doing about them, and more or less suggested that after the work of this Commission we had put the Reports in the waste paper basket.  I must say I consider that unfair.  I would not like to say that we have not got them a month, but we have not got the Reports for more than two months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is under a misapprehension.  I was speaking of the Commission of Enquiry into the Industrial Resources of Ireland, and not to the present Commission.  I meant the old Dáil Commission, the Figgis Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has put me in a quandary, for I never heard of that Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is exactly the grievance here.  The Dáil spent several thousands of pounds on this, and a dozen men spent a great deal of time on it. A considerable sum of money was spent in printing the Reports, which were approved by the country if the country spoke the truth and expressed its true opinions, by the Dáil if they expressed their true opinions, and by the Ministers if they expressed their true opinions, and yet the Minister for Agriculture knows nothing about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>What I did say is that I never heard of the Figgis Commission, and the Deputy is doing me an injustice. I read the Reports, but I did not know them by that name.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I read the reports Deputy Johnson refers to.  I did not know them by that name.  The Deputy wants to know what <Col N="1240" /> we are doing about those reports.  The Agricultural Commission now sitting is engaged on practically the same work, and personally I would prefer to take the evidence of the present Commission on the various questions raised.  I am quite serious when I say that I would not change policy in regard to any matter which the present Agricultural Commission may be dealing with without first receiving their report.  I have two or three of their reports already, and if there is time we propose to introduce legislation along the lines suggested there. The reports we have got from the Commission are at present with the Department of Agriculture, and certain points are being made up in connection with them that I require further light on.  I hope to deal with the most important of those reports if there is time during the session within the next few months.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the reports be printed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>They will be printed immediately.  With regard to dairying, we all know that that is specially for the South, the hope of agriculture in the South.  We have increased the Estimates to some extent and tried to provide efficient and fairly well paid officers for the various Cow-Testing Associations. That is the addition that the Deputy refers to in the Votes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards the question of tobacco-growing, I understand there are something like 800 lbs. of tobacco grown to the acre.  After half duty being allowed on that, it would amount to £130 an acre.  In examining a question of this character, Deputies interested in it ought at least to give us figures, and be in a position to explain how many people are employed and what proportion of wages or money spent in wages would have to be contributed out of Government funds in order to make the proposition an economic one.  I am sure the Deputies who so warmly supported this line would not do so were they not satisfied it was a business proposition.  If we spent £200,000 or £100,000, or indeed any sum of money, on a particular service such as that, Deputies will, I think, admit there ought to be a reasonable return for it, and the person engaged in <Col N="1241" /> that sphere of activity should have a fair recompense, and there should be an equally fair recompense for those he would employ.  That is an aspect Deputies have not dealt with.  I may not have exhausted the subject when I was examining it.  Speaking from recollection, I am satisfied that we would have to pay twenty to thirty per cent. of the wages. I do not think that is a reasonable request to put before the Executive Council. Even if our balance was on the right side, the business of the Government would be to see whatever money is spent, or raised by revenue to be spent, is spent on a sound economic basis.  It is very painful to people like myself to have to speak plainly on matters like this.  For something like twenty years I have been advocating Irish manufactures.  I never bought anything except what was raised in the country if it could be got at any price.  In the old days it was quite a proper thing to suggest that the British Government should forego a tax on homegrown tobacco.  It did not matter from what source support came for Irish industries at the time.  It is a matter of very serious import now, and we are not entitled to fling away money regardless of results.  If the results of tobacco-growing in Ireland can stand the test of examination, and if it is a reasonable proposition; we are prepared to support it. Facts and figures should be produced here.  It is not our business to produce them.  The gentlemen in that particular line ought to give us information, and up to this we have not got it.  In the circumstances we are not prepared to go further.  We did not make a bargain with Sir Nugent Everard.  We have carried out any undertakings that were the subject of arrangement between Sir Nugent Everard and the British Government. In fact, we have gone further. We are not satisfied that it is reasonable to ask us to go any further than we have gone.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. DOYLE Mr. DOYLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOYLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Things must be done very differently now in the tobacco-growing business when the Minister is not in a position to have facts and figures at his disposal.  When we were connected with the experiment we had to supply a weekly report embodying all details in regard to wages and other things, and that was sent to the Department.  I believe the <Col N="1242" /> Minister for Agriculture could supply the particulars the President requires.  I actually read them at the Commission the other day, and they are all set out. It is not exactly the fault of the growers that the returns are not to be had, except matters have altered in the last few years. They should continue the system of weekly reports as long as the experiment goes on.  If things were carried out as in the old days, the Minister would have all facts and figures at his finger ends.  I believe the Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture could bear me out in that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>If there were such returns so favourable to this industry&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. DOYLE Mr. DOYLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOYLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not say anything about favourable returns.  I told you they were set out in the weekly report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, it is not my business to produce them.  Deputies interested in this experiment ought to be in a position to say, &ldquo;Here is an economic proposition; it is the duty of the Government to support that.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Minister suggest he does not collaborate with the Minister for Agriculture on this matter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not suggest that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Has he been able to supply you with the figures?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>He has, and it is on those figures I have based the information I have given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Then why do you ask the Dáil for them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am satisfied at any rate that it is not a good proposition, and I give the invitation to somebody to prove that it is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Agriculture said you have not made up your mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>When?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Before you put this Vote there is an item here in these Estimates on which I would like to ask information. It is with regard to Transit Inspectors. I would like to know the nature of the duties performed by people under the head of Transit Inspectors here.  I have <Col N="1243" /> been reading through the official export list so far as non-dutiable goods are concerned, and I see that the railway companies are asked to supply information which originally, as far as I know, used be supplied by the Transit Inspectors. I would like to know if the Vote now asked for is one that will not be provided for in any future Estimate.  In connection with the export of cattle the railway companies are asked to supply information which the exporters should supply as to the class of cattle&mdash;information which will show whether the cattle shipped are either bulls, milch cows, breeding cattle, store cattle, fat heifers, and so on.  This is the first time this information has been asked for from them, as it was previously supplied by the people who are termed in this Estimate &ldquo;Transit Inspectors.&rdquo;  I would like to know what is the position with regard to these in the future, seeing now that this information is to be supplied by the railway companies.  I understand that within the Department there is a section for dealing with the question of traders' grievances, particularly in regard to the export of agricultural produce. That was usually a grievance-hearing department in the past.  I would like to know whether that Department still exists, what are the powers, and if it is possible to extend the powers of that Department?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>A very important question of policy has been enunciated here by the Minister for Finance. A certain policy is adopted by the Ministry with regard to a certain industry&mdash;the tobacco industry.  The only persons who have the entire statistics on that matter are the Executive Council or the members of the Executive Council, or the Minister for Agriculture on behalf of the Ministry at large.  It is decided by one Minister to discontinue a certain policy.  Surely the onus of proof lies on him in whose possession the entire statistics lie and not upon other people in whose possession those statistics are not to be had.  If the whole case were put up here clearly by the Minister for Finance, and the figures were put before us, and it was decided then by the Ministry that this help to the industry by the making of a certain grant is an uneconomic proposition for the State, <Col N="1244" /> then that statement being made, and the case being put, the Minister stands on firm ground.  But when he says we have come to the decision from an examination of the figures which are not in the possession of the Dáil, and says that the onus of proof lies upon other people who have not got the figures, he is taking up a position that is in the last degree unjust and unfair.  This is a matter that has aroused certain attention outside.</P>
      <P>From the statements that are made here in the Dáil I would be inclined to say that any industry that requires so large a backing, so large an en dowment, before it can find its economic subsistence in the State, was <i>ipso facto</i> an industry that it was not for the benefit of the country to continue.  But we have no figures.  The figures are not in our possession.  They are in the possession of the Minister, and before a question of policy of this kind is decided on and confirmed by the Legislature the whole information&mdash;that is, the information of the country&mdash;should be put before the Legislature, in order that it may be able to know where it stands in regard to this matter.  Deputy Johnson touched upon the question of Cow-testing Associations.  One of our largest industries in Ireland at the present moment, and certainly one of the basic industries, is the dairy industry, because it underlies the cattle industry.  Here we have the remarkable fact that Deputy Doyle referred to the Irish tobacco growers as being able to supply all the tobacco consumed in Ireland if half the tax were remitted, which practically means that if the tobacco-growers had a protective tariff in their favour they would be able to supply the tobacco consumers of Ireland.  I never heard of anybody advocating such a protective tariff in respect of butter, but we might hear that next.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnRooney" hpid="Mr. ROONEY Mr. ROONEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ROONEY</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a question of subsidy.  It is a question of the taxation of Irish-grown tobacco.  Irish-grown tobacco is not able to bear the taxation because imported tobacco is produced by Coolie labour at 3d. a day.  It is not so in Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I realise that; but the effect is exactly the same. If you put on a duty at a certain figure, <Col N="1245" /> and halve it to the Irish producer, it is exactly the same as if you put on the duty against goods coming into Ireland. The fact remains that foreign butter is being bought in Ireland to-day more cheaply than Irish butter, although sent from a considerable distance.  That is a state of affairs that I think should require a great deal more attention than the continuance of an industry which, so far as one hears, is economically doubtful.  In regard to all this, we do desire, in respect of agriculture, as an independent Department of its own, the collection and constant publication and circulation amongst the members of statistics dealing with every branch of this the greatest industry in the country.  That leads me to the one final point which I am anxious to put before the Ministry, and that is with regard to the compilation of statistics. Statistics are made available by the Statistical Branch of the Department, and are sent to the Press, while the same is true of the Ministry of Commerce, but Deputies are required to purchase them at very exorbitant charges.  I urge the Ministry to consider this matter of the publication of these particular statistics. They say that the figures with regard to the tobacco industry are in possession of the Ministry, and I urge that they should be circulated, showing the exact state of the industry and the causes that led the Minister for Finance to say, from his examination of the figures, that he came to a certain conviction, and that this industry was not worth continuing and not worth endowing as it was endowed in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not remember making any such statement.  The figures that are here will probably bear out that.  The sum put down this year for tobacco-growing is £3,313.  Deputies will see that on page 140.  Last year the amount was £3,030.  I expect that the Deputy will probably learn to know after a while that the particular business of the Minister for Finance is to justify an increase.  I do not think that I have justified it to any great extent, but I will make the Deputy a present of the fact if I have not.  If I have not justified any more, I do not think it is my business. If the Deputy thinks it is, I must dispute it with him.  This is not our policy, but the policy we got from those <Col N="1246" /> that were here.  We are carrying out an undertaking which the people before us made with the tobacco-growers.  We made an increase, and I can be criticised for giving more than I was satisfied should have been given.  But it is there, and if you are not satisfied with it, you can shout out &ldquo;<i>Níl.</i>&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not dealing with those figures.  The Minister for Finance challenged Deputies here who had brought forward a case for tobacco growing to bring forward certain costing figures.  He spoke about the cost of labour and the number of hands employed, and Deputy Doyle replied that those figures had been sent in to the Minister for Agriculture, and were available for the Minister for Finance.  The Minister for Finance replied at once that he had seen those figures, and had come to his conclusions.  I say, let us have the figures with the conclusions presumed to be based upon them, and which we have not had.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has had the figures on a few occasions, and I am not going to give them again.  I have stated our position with regard to tobacco; I have given the figures, and stated the conclusions with regard to those figures.  With regard to Deputy Davin's point, the officers he refers to are the officers who look after the watering, feeding of cattle, the disinfection of waggons, and other duties like that. They are really inspectors of the railway companies in the sense that they see how the cattle and live stock are being carried.  I do not know what section of the Department he refers to that deals with complaints from traders.  The Deputy may refer to the fact that traders used to send in complaints with regard to rates on carriage.  It is still open to traders to send in those complaints, and they are brought before the Railway and Canal Commission.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Which does not exist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJHogan" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, at the moment; the Deputy has caught me out there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Question put: &ldquo;That a sum not exceeding £275,982 be granted to complete the sum necessary to defray the charge which will come in course of payment during the year ending on the 31st day <Col N="1247" /> of March, 1924, for expenditure in respect of the salaries and expenses of the Ministry of Agriculture, and of certain Services administered by that Ministry, including sundry Grants in Aid.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Agreed.</P>
    <P>At this stage the Ceann Comhairle resumed the Chair.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret to say that the Minister for Education is ill, and the Minister for Defence has asked me to get his Estimates postponed.  I propose to take up from 19 to 29, inclusive to-morrow, as well as 34, 36, 37, 39, 40, 42, 43 and 54.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that, owing to the unfortunate illness of the Minister for Education, Estimates 51 and 52 will be postponed. When will the Army Estimate, 58, be taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Defence told me he had to go away, and <Col N="1248" /> that he did not expect it would be taken for a couple of days.  I will make an announcement with respect to it to-morrow. I will see if it can be taken to-morrow evening late.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say whether Education will be taken on Thursday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move to report progress and to ask leave to sit again.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC" RHead="SERVICES. - DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil went out of Committee and progress was reported.</P>
    <P>It was ordered: that the Committee sit again to-morrow.</P>
    <P>The Dáil adjourned at 7.5 p.m. until Wednesday, the 30th May, at 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>