<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Tue" Date="20" Month="Mar" Year="1923" Vol="2" No="41" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 20 Márta 1923" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 20 March 1923" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="2285">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2285" /> Cromadh ar obair an lae ar 3.10 p.m. Bhí an Ceann Comhairle, Micheál O hAodha, sa Chathaoir.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - [ORAL" RHead="ANSWERS.] IRISH FREE STATE LAWS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - [ORAL ANSWERS.]  IRISH FREE STATE LAWS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="GEAROID MAC GIOBUIN GEAROID MAC GIOBUIN">
      <NameTxt>GEAROID MAC GIOBUIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the President whether he has taken, and if not, whether he will take, the opinion of the Legal Advisers of the State upon the questions whether the expression in Article 73 of the Constitution &ldquo;laws in force in the Irish Free State at the date of the coming into operation of this Constitution,&rdquo; and the expression in the preamble of the Adaptation of Enactments Act, 1923, &ldquo;Acts passed by the British Parliament which were in force on the 6th day of December, 1922,&rdquo; do not mean and include all Statutes of the British Parliament duly enacted by that Parliament, and purporting to affect the area now comprised in Saorstát Eireann which were unrepealed at that date, and also whether the repeal of certain sections of a nonexistent Act which &ldquo;was never in force in Ireland&rdquo; can have the legal operation of enacting by implication the remainder of the same Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy will mention any concrete matter as to which he suggests that the Government appear to him to have omitted to be advised, the suggestion will receive every consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. FITZGIBBON Mr. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>A concrete case is the Criminal and Malicious Injuries Act, 1920.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="INTERNMENTS IN SAORSTÁTEIREANN">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - INTERNMENTS IN SAORSTÁTEIREANN.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="TOMAS MAC EOIN TOMAS MAC EOIN">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS MAC EOIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the President to state the number of persons who have been interned in Ireland <Col N="2286" /> within the past fourteen days in pursuance of Orders issued by British Secretaries of State; how many, if any, of these prisoners are citizens of Saorstát Eireann; whether the President's attention has been called to the terms of the Internment Orders in which the British Minister &ldquo;orders&rdquo; that certain persons &ldquo;shall be interned in the Irish Free State,&rdquo; and &ldquo;shall be subject to all the rules and conditions applicable to persons there interned, and shall remain there until further orders&rdquo;&mdash;such orders to be made by him; whether the Executive Council of Saorstát Eireann was cognisant of the terms of these Orders of Internment before they were issued; if not, whether it is intended to protest against the implied assumption contained in these Orders that British Ministers have authority in the affairs of Saorstát Eireann, and that Regulations made under the Restoration of Order in Ireland Act (1920) are still enforcible inside Free State territory at the will of British Ministers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>As to the first part of the question, the answer is 110.</P>
      <P>As to the second part of the question&mdash; this is a question of fact which has yet to be inquired into; all are presumed to be such citizens.</P>
      <P>As to the third part of the question, the Restoration of Order in Ireland Act, 1920, and the Regulations made thereunder are, so far as the territory of Saorstát Eireann is concerned, spent and of no legal force or effect.  Legal opinion in Britain is to the effect that they are still in force in Great Britain, though it has not been suggested that they are so in force in Saorstát Eireann.  Whatever be the authority under which certain persons have been arrested in and deported from Great Britain to this country, no one is being held here under the authority of that Act or the Regulations under it.  The Executive Council was not cognisant of the terms of the Orders referred to before they were issued.  No such implication of assumed authority on the part of British Ministers in the affairs of Saorstát Eireann, as suggested in the question, has been found or is apparent.  The suggested protest is, therefore, not called for.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- GRANTS FOR HOUSING">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - GRANTS FOR HOUSING.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance if the Government will <Col N="2287" /> give a grant to individual workers to build their own houses at a cost of not exceeding £750, the worker to raise £350, and the Government to advance £400 as a free grant, as given to Urban Councils for housing schemes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (The President) William T. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (The President)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am unable to contemplate the making of grants to private builders in respect of houses costing as much as £750 or on the scale suggested by the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - CRIMINAL" RHead="INJURIES (IRELAND) ACT, 1920">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - CRIMINAL INJURIES (IRELAND) ACT, 1920.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="GEAROID MAC GIOBUIN GEAROID MAC GIOBUIN">
      <NameTxt>GEAROID MAC GIOBUIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Home Affairs whether the Criminal Injuries (Ireland) Act, 1920, which he has stated &ldquo;was not in force on the 6th December, 1922, and was never in force in Ireland,&rdquo; has not been repeatedly acted upon and enforced in the Courts of Law in Ireland, and when and by whom has it ever been repealed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="GEAROID MAC GIOBUIN GEAROID MAC GIOBUIN">
      <NameTxt>GEAROID MAC GIOBUIN</NameTxt>
      <P>also asked the Minister for Home Affairs whether, as he has stated that notwithstanding Article 73 of the Constitution, and the Adaptation of Enactments Act, 1923, a Statute of the British Parliament, though duly enacted before the 6th of December, 1922, and unrepealed on that date, which purported to affect the area now comprised in Saorstát Eireann, &ldquo;was not in force on that date and was never in force in Ireland,&rdquo; he will publish for the information of those citizens who are bound to obey the law and of the Judges whose duty it is to administer it, a list of those Statutes and portions of Statutes, passed by the British Parliament before the 6th day of December, 1922, and purporting on that date to affect the area now comprised in Saorstát Eireann, which were not in force in that area on or since that date, especially as those who assumed that the Constitution means what it says have been described by the President as plunderers and robbers, and have been exposed to pecuniary loss for observing the laws thereby declared to be in force.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. Kevin O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. Kevin O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall answer these two questions together.  I may, perhaps, say first, as a formal answer to the question, that the Criminal Injuries <Col N="2288" /> (Ireland) Act, 1920, was undoubtedly an unrepealed British Statute in Ireland on 6th December, 1922.</P>
      <P>As regards the suggested list mentioned in the second question, I do not intend to publish any such list.</P>
      <P>Having thus answered the questions formally, I may, perhaps, venture to say that the questions seem to be founded upon an erroneous idea of a previous remark of mine in the House.  I did say that this Act was never in force in Ireland, but I explained in the following sentences as clearly and as fully as I could that I did not mean what the Deputy's question suggests I meant.  I explained that when I said the Act was not in force I did not mean that it has been repealed, but that it had broken down in practice because the people of this country and the elected Government of this country had resisted it strenously and successfully.  I think that the Deputy or any other person who does me the honour of reading my remarks on the occasion in question&mdash;it was on the 7th of this month&mdash;will admit that I made my meaning perfectly explicit.  I need only add now that the Deputy's knowledge of law is too well known to me to permit me to suppose that he does not appreciate the distinction I drew or understand that laws can become ineffective by disuse and incurable unpopularity as well as by formal repeal.  I need go no further for an example than the well-known instance of the non-enforcement against Catholics in these countries in recent years of unrepealed penal legislation directed against them and their religion.</P>
      <P>In negotiations which took place with the British Government the dead letter status of these Criminal Injuries Statutes was well recognised, as evidenced by the fact that arrangements were made for payment of compensation otherwise than as these Statutes provide.  Their formal repeal is merely the official acceptance and regularisation of that position.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- &ldquo;SUMMER TIME.&rdquo;">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - &ldquo;SUMMER TIME.&rdquo;</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJamesCraig" hpid="Sir SEAMUS CRAIG Sir SEAMUS CRAIG">
      <NameTxt>Sir SEAMUS CRAIG</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Home Affairs whether the Government have considered the introduction of &ldquo;Summer Time&rdquo; for the present year, and, if so, when their decision on the matter will be communicated to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2289" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>This matter has been considered, and I am introducing a Summer Time Bill this week.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="POWERS FOR NORTHERN RAILWAY">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - POWERS FOR NORTHERN RAILWAY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="SEAN O MAOLRUAIDH SEAN O MAOLRUAIDH">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O MAOLRUAIDH</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether his attention has been called to the fact that the Derry and Lough Swilly Railway Company are introducing a Bill in the English Parliament authorising them to borrow money, and having regard to the fact that the line of railway worked by this company is only three miles in area described as Northern Ireland and over one hundred miles in the territory of the Free State, he will consider whether an explanation should not be asked from this company as to why they should go to London for powers which they would obtain at home.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EdmundJDuggan" hpid="Mr. EAMON DUGGAN (for the Minister of Industry and Commerce) Mr. EAMON DUGGAN (for the Minister of Industry and Commerce)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. EAMON DUGGAN (for the Minister of Industry and Commerce)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no knowledge of the fact stated in the first part of the question, but if the Deputy will furnish a copy of the Bill I will have it examined.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- ATHY PENSION">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - ATHY PENSION.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="AODH O CULACHAIN AODH O CULACHAIN">
      <NameTxt>AODH O CULACHAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Local Government on what grounds the Old Age Pension of 10s. per week, awarded on two occasions to James May, Reg. No. 1972, of West-End, Monasterevan, Co. Kildare, by the Athy No. 1 Sub-Committee has been rejected, and if he will have this claim investigated again, with a view to carrying out the findings of the Sub-Committee who must have had special local knowledge of the claimant and his means of living before they issued their award.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Athy No. 1 Pension Sub-Committee voted a pension of 10s. a week to James May.</P>
      <P>The farm consists of 10 Irish acres of good land; rent £8 10s. 0d., valuation £7 10s. Od; the crops were 1½ acres of potatoes, 1½ acres of roots, and 2½ acres of barley.  The live stock were 3 cows, 6 yearlings, a horse, an ass, and the usual fowl.</P>
      <P>As the yearly means of the claimant exceeded £49 17s. 6d. his claim to a pension was accordingly disallowed on the 21st October last.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- A MAYO ARREST">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - A MAYO ARREST.</Title>
    <Col N="2290" />
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="SEOIRSE GHABHAIN UI DHUBHTHAIGH SEOIRSE GHABHAIN UI DHUBHTHAIGH">
      <NameTxt>SEOIRSE GHABHAIN UI DHUBHTHAIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence for what reason Michael J. Hanley, of Knockmore, Ballina, Co. Mayo, was recently re-arrested, and whether sufficient reason exists for keeping him in prison.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for DEFENCE (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am making enquiries, but am not yet in a position to give a full reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- MARRIED QUARTERS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - MARRIED QUARTERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="AODH O CULACHAIN AODH O CULACHAIN">
      <NameTxt>AODH O CULACHAIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether the four houses (Married Quarters) recently built by the British War Department at the rere of Kildare Military Barracks, on the road leading from the Railway Hotel to the Standhouse, could be transferred to the Local Authority, and on what terms, so that they may be able to ease, even in a small way, the housing problem which exists in an acute form in the town of Kildare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The houses referred to may be required in the near future for occupation by troops.  A decision cannot, therefore, be taken at present on the question of making them available for civilian tenants.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- HEALTH OF A PRISONER">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - HEALTH OF A PRISONER.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="SEOIRSE GHABHAIN UI DHUBHTHAIGH SEOIRSE GHABHAIN UI DHUBHTHAIGH">
      <NameTxt>SEOIRSE GHABHAIN UI DHUBHTHAIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether his attention has been directed to the very grave state of health of Robert Barton, T.D., now a prisoner in Mountjoy, whether Mr. Barton has been examined by the Medical Officer or Officers of the prison, and, if so, what reports upon his health have been made by any such officers; and whether he will personally look into the matter with a view to ascertaining whether these are not the most urgent reasons for Mr. Barton's release.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mr. Barton has recently been examined by a Medical Officer who did not find any signs of physical unfitness.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="BILLETING OF NATIONAL ARMY">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - BILLETING OF NATIONAL ARMY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="TOMAS de NOGLA TOMAS de NOGLA">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS de NOGLA</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether the National Army has been billeted and maintained <Col N="2291" /> in the houses of the townspeople of Skibbereen since the 9th August, 1922, at the expense of the householders. Whether there is upwards of £10,000 due to the townspeople for goods and food supplied to the billeted troops, and whether it is true that no payment has been made to the majority of these people up to the present, and whether some of them had to borrow money in the banks at interest to pay for the food for the soldiers; whether an undertaking given by the military authorities in Portobello on 10th January to the representative of the people to pay these accounts will be carried out forthwith.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Troops have been billeted in Skibbereen since about the date mentioned.  Amounts incurred in the town do not amount to more than about £4,500.  More than 75 per cent. of them were cleared during the past month, and the balance are receiving due attention.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. -" RHead="COMMANDEERED PREMISES (SKIBBEREEN)">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - COMMANDEERED PREMISES (SKIBBEREEN)</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="TOMAS de NOGLA TOMAS de NOGLA">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS de NOGLA</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether the Government troops commandeered from Mr. Cornelius O'Shea, Skibbereen, his large business establishment, known as The Emporium, Main Street, Skibbereen, and occupied same for over twelve months, without making any payment. Whether the responsible military authorities (local) allowed their Adjutant to open a shop and carry on business there, keeping Mr. O'Shea out of possession of his property.  Whether the Adjutant-General, Portobello, received a letter dated 4th January, 1923, from Mr. O'Shea's solicitors, applying for possession, as the troops were no longer in occupation, and for compensation.  What steps does the Minister propose to take to give Mr. O'Shea clear possession of his premises, and what compensation he proposes to pay Mr. O'Shea for his heavy losses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am advised that the premises were occupied by troops in February, 1922, as successors to the British Army, and that possession was given to Mr. O'Shea's accredited agent on the 12th December, 1922.  The Office of Public Works has been asked to have rent paid for the premises for the <Col N="2292" /> period during which they were occupied by our troops.  Mr. O'Shea's solicitors have been so informed.  They, however, deny that clear possession has been given to a properly accredited agent, and the point is being therefore investigated.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- CO. KERRY SCHOOL">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - CO. KERRY SCHOOL.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAMUS O CRUADHLAOICH SEAMUS O CRUADHLAOICH">
      <NameTxt>SEAMUS O CRUADHLAOICH</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether the Intermediate School, Killorglin, Co. Kerry, was taken over by the military authorities in August last and has been occupied by them since, whether four teachers employed there have been deprived of their salaries and are unable to find other employment; what steps it is proposed to take to compensate these teachers for the loss they have suffered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The facts are correct as regards the occupation of the school.  It is not possible to entertain any claim from the teachers.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DISTRICT JUSTICES BILL&mdash;FROM" RHead="THE SEANAD. - DAIL IN COMMITTEE">
    <Title>DISTRICT JUSTICES BILL&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD. - DAIL IN COMMITTEE.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil went into Committee on the Amendments from Seanad Eireann to the District Justices (Temporary Provisions) Bill, 1923.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. Kevin O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. Kevin O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to these Amendments from the Seanad, what exactly is the position?  Is it necessary for someone to move them here?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The new Standing Orders say that the Dáil will go into Committee on amendments or recommendations coming from the Seanad.  They can be taken one by one on a motion that they be agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>It occurs sometimes&mdash;it has in fact occurred in this case&mdash;that amendments are inserted which if it were left to my judgment would not be inserted, but which at the same time are not so important that I would favour the sending back of the Bill to the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order, is it not necessary for someone to father each particular amendment which comes forward?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>In the absence of such percentage can there be any discussion upon it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we could have no discussion except someone move that we agree or that we do not agree.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>Suppose it were to happen that an Amendment was moved by the Seanad and tabled here and nobody wished to father it, does it mean that it would not be proposed at all, even though it is allowed under the <Col N="2297" /> Constitution to make such an amendment? Are the provisions of the Constitution made dependent upon the agreement of some one or other Deputy with Senators across the way?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that that Constitutional question will worry lawyers very much.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 1.</P>
      <P>(1)  It shall be lawful for the Governor-General of the Irish Free State on the advice of the Executive Council from time to time to appoint fit and proper persons being Barristers-at-Law in Saorstát Eireann or Solicitors of the Supreme Court in Saorstát Eireann to be Magistrates with the title of &ldquo;District Justices&rdquo; and to perform the duties and have the powers prescribed by this Act.</P>
      <P>(2)  Every person appointed to be a District Justice may be dismissed or removed at the pleasure of the Governor-General of the Irish Free State on the advice of the Executive Council.</P>
      <P>(3)  Every person so appointed to be a District Justice shall while he holds that office be paid out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas a salary and allowances in accordances with a scale to be prescribed by the Minister with the concurrence of the Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(4)  No person shall while holding the office of District Justice be capable of <Col N="2298" /> holding any other office or position of emolument or of being elected to or of being a member of either House of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(5)  Every person so appointed to be a District Justice shall before entering on his office subscribe and make a solemn declaration in the form contained in the First Schedule to this Act.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>With qualified enthusiasm I move that we agree to Amendment 1, which sets out &ldquo;In Sec tion 1, in line 20, to insert after the word `Eireann' the words `of at least two years' standing.&rdquo;'  The effect of this amendment is that a barrister of less than two years' standing may not be appointed District Justice.  What exactly two years' standing means in that connection might need to be cleared up.  A man could be called to the Bar and have never practised his profession.  He might have taken up literature or some other calling, and I would be glad if some lawyer in the Assembly would enlighten me as to whether two years' standing means that he must have been qualified not less than two years before his appointment, or whether it means that he must have been, in fact, practising his profession.</P>
      <P>Question put: &ldquo;That Dáil Eireann agrees with Amendment 1 sent from Seanad Eireann.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Dáil divided:-Tá, 37; Níl, 11.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Liam T. Mac Cosgair.<br />Donchadh O Guaire.<br />Seán O Maolruaidh.<br />Seán O Duinnín.<br />Darghal Figes.<br />Seoirse Ghabháin Uí Dhubhthaigh.<br />Deasmhumhain Mac Gearailt.<br />Ailfrid Ó Broin.<br />Risteárd Ó Maolchatha.<br />Domhnall Mac Cárt aigh.<br />Sir Séamus Craig.<br />Gearóid Mac Giobúin.<br />Eoin Mac Neill.<br />Liam Mag Aonghusa.<br />Pádraig Ó hOgáin.<br />Padhraic Ó Máille.<br />Seosamh Ó Faoileacháin.<br />Seoirse Mac Niocaill.<br />Fionán Ó Loingsigh.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Séamus Ó Cruadhlaoich.<br />Criostóir Ó Broin.<br />Rist árd Mac Liam.<br />Caoimghin O hUigín.<br />Próinsias Bulfin.<br />Tomás Mac Artúir.<br />Aindriú Ó Láimhin.<br />Liam Ó hAodha.<br />Seán Mac Eoin.<br />Próinsias Mag Aonghusa.<br />Eamon Ó Dúgáin.<br />Peadar Ó hAodha.<br />Séamus Ó Murchadha.<br />Seosamh Mac Giolla Bhrighde.<br />Liam Mac Sioghaird.<br />Tomás Ó Domhnaill.<br />Earnán de Blaghd.<br />Séamus de Burca.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="2299" />Tomás de Nógla.<br />Riobárd Ó Deaghaidh.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Liam Ó Briain.<br />Tomás Ó Conaill.<br />Aodh Ó Cúlacháin.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">
              <Col N="2300" />Liam Ó Daimhín.<br />Seán Ó Laidhin.<br />Cathal Ó Seanáin.<br />Domhnall Ó Muirgheasa.<br />Domhnall Ó Ceallacháin.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Motion declared carried.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
    <P>(1)  The Minister may from time to time by warrant under his hand appoint and remove such and so many fit and proper persons as he shall think expedient in each county to be called &ldquo;Parish Commissioners,&rdquo; and to perform and exercise within such County the duties and powers prescribed by this Act.</P>
    <P>(2)  A Parish Commissioner shall have all the powers and authorities which immediately before the passing of this Act were vested in a Justice of the Peace in respect of the several matters following, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(<i>a</i>)  signing Summonses;</P>
    <P>(<i>b</i>)  signing Warrants;</P>
    <P>(<i>c</i>)  Administering oaths and taking declarations, affirmations and informations;</P>
    <P>(<i>d</i>)  committing dangerous lunatics and idiots to Lunatic Asylums under Section 10 of the Lunacy (Ireland) Act, 1867 (30 &amp; 31 Vict., ch. 118);</P>
    <P>(<i>e</i>)  signing certificates for the admission of lunatics and idiots to Lunatic Asylums;</P>
    <P>Provided always that any summons against any member of the Civic Guard shall be signed by a District Judge.</P>
    <P>(3)  Whenever any person charged with having committed an indicatable offence shall be arrested by a member of the Civic Guard such person shall forthwith be brought before a Parish Commissioner, who after hearing such evidence as may be offered shall remand such person either in custody or in such bail as the Parish Commissioner shall think fit and remit the case for hearing before a District Justice on a date not later than the next District Court to be held in the Court District where such person was arrested.</P>
    <P>(4)  Whenever any person charged with having committed an indicatable offence is brought before a District Justice it shall be lawful for such District Justice to remand such person to a date not later than the next District Court to be held by him in the Court District where such person was arrested.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I move an Amendment: &ldquo;In Sub-section (1) to delete the word `Parish,' and to insert in lieu thereof the word 'Peace,' and to make all consequential alterations.&rdquo;  So Parish Commissioners become Peace Commissioners under this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask the Minister to say if any, and what, arrangements are being made for the appointment of Peace Commissioners under the terms of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  This is a motion to change the name, and nothing else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems rather strange that though the Minister appears to have been present when these amendments were carried in the Seanad that he is not prepared to father them in the Dáil, or to give any explanation arising out of the amendments carried in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a different thing altogether.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;After Sub-section (2) <i>(e)</i>, to insert the following:&mdash;`<i>(f)</i> signing the certificate required by Section 2 of the Statute entitled the Registration of Clubs (Ireland) Act, 1904.' &rdquo;  This amendment was moved in the Seanad at my request.  It rectifies a slight omission in the matter of the powers of these Peace Commissioners.  There is a certificate which has to be signed under the Registration of Clubs (Ireland) Act, 1904, and before the applicant is heard in Court it has to be signed by a magistrate.  It is proposed to add this signing to the powers of the Peace Commissioner.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash; In Sub-section 3, Section 4, after the word &ldquo;shall&rdquo; to insert the <Col N="2301" /> words &ldquo;unless a District Justice is immediately available.&rdquo;  The force of the amendment merely is that it ought not to be made absolutely cast-iron that a person arrested on an indictable offence shall, in all circumstances, be brought before a Peace Commissioner. If a District Justice is available, for instance, if it happens to be on the day that the District Justice is holding his Court in that locality, it saves time, and it is a better procedure to bring him immediately before the District Justice. That is simply the effect of the amendment.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 9.</P>
      <P>(1)  Each of the persons named in the Third Schedule to this Act having been appointed under the Constabulary (Ireland) Act, 1836 (6 &amp; 7 Will. IV., ch. 13), by the Governor-General of the Irish Free State to be a Magistrate under that Act shall be deemed to have been appointed and to be a District Justice under this Act.</P>
      <P>(2)  Every act, matter and thing done after the 28th day of October, 1922, by any of the said persons named in the Third Schedule to this Act in exercise or purported exercise of any authority purported to have been at the time of his doing such act, matter or thing vested in him by reason of his having been appointed or purported to have been appointed by the late Provisional Government of Ireland or any Minister thereof to be a District Justice shall notwithstanding any failure (whether by way of commission or omission) to comply with any statute, rule or order or any other irregularity be as valid and effective as if the same had been regularly done by a Magistrate duly appointed under the Constabulary (Ireland) Act, 1836 (6 &amp; 7 Will. IV., ch. 13), or (in the case of acts, matters and things which are by law required to be done by two Magistrates appointed under the Act aforesaid sitting together) by two such Magistrates sitting together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(3)  No action shall lie against and no penalty shall be incurred by any of the said persons named in the Third Schedule to this Act for or on account or in respect of any act, matter or thing done by any such person after the 22nd day of <Col N="2302" /> October, 1922, in exercise or purported exercise of any such authority as is mentioned in the preceding sub-section or any failure (whether by way of commission or omission) to comply with the terms of any statute, rule or order or any other irregularity in the doing of such act, matter or thing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash; In Section 9, Sub-section 2, to delete the words &ldquo;appointed under the Act aforesaid&rdquo; in lines 37 and 38, and to delete the words &ldquo;sitting together&rdquo; in line 39.  The amendment improves the sub-section without in any way altering the sense or the effect of it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DISTRICT JUSTICES BILL&mdash;FROM" RHead="THE SEANAD. - DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>DISTRICT JUSTICES BILL&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments reported.  Perhaps the Minister will move that the Dáil agrees with the amendments made by the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;&ldquo;That Dáil Eireann agrees with the amendments inserted in Seanad Eireann.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DISTRICT JUSTICES BILL&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD. - LOCAL" RHead="AUTHORITIES (EXTENSION OF TIME) BILL, 1923.&mdash;FIRST STAGE">
    <Title>DISTRICT JUSTICES BILL&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD. - LOCAL AUTHORITIES (EXTENSION OF TIME) BILL, 1923.&mdash;FIRST STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move for leave to introduce the Local Authorities (Extension of Time) Bill.  The purpose of this Bill is to extend the time limited by special Acts of Parliament which have been obtained by Local Authorities enabling them to do such public works as the provision of water supplies or the carrying out of sewage works.  There are several such cases through the country.  A typical one is that of the Dingle Rural District Council, which in 1915 was given powers to acquire certain lands and water rights compulsorily for the purpose of supplying water for the town of Dingle and neighbourhood.  The time for exercising the powers was limited to three years from the passing of the enabling Act. The old Local Government Board, on the application of the Council, extended this limit several times by Orders made under the Special Acts and the Extension of Time Act, 1915.  The last extension <Col N="2303" /> expired on the 29th July, 1921. The Council did not then apply for any further extension as it had broken off relations with the old Local Government Board.  The Council is now anxious to carry out the work, and it is not desirable that it should be put to the expense and delay which would be involved in obtaining a new Provisional Order, and having an Act passed confirming that Order.  It was impossible in the circumstances of the time for the Council to carry out the work.  There are other Councils in a somewhat similar position, and it is felt to be desirable that power should be taken to extend for a period the time during which Councils which have got special powers under Acts confirming Provisional Orders, or other Special Acts, should be enabled to carry out the necessary works for which these Acts were obtained.</P>
      <P>Question: &ldquo;That leave be given to introduce the Bill,&rdquo; put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Ordered for Second Reading on Friday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DISTRICT JUSTICES BILL&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD. - DOUBLE" RHead="TAXATION (RELIEF) BILL, 1923.&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>DISTRICT JUSTICES BILL&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD. - DOUBLE TAXATION (RELIEF) BILL, 1923.&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move the Second Reading of the Double Taxation (Relief) Bill.  As already explained it is an enabling Bill, which will permit the Free State Government to arrange with the British Government for relief from double taxation, and empower the Governor-General to make Orders giving statutory effect to such arrangements. The British Government has taken a similar power in the Irish Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act of 1922. The Bill now before the Dáil will put the Free State Government in the same position as the British Act places the British Government in.  Under Article 74 of the Constitution the taxation code at present in force in the Free State is the same in practically all respects as before the change of Government, and this state of affairs continues until the end of the current financial year.  On the 6th of next month for Income Tax, and on the first of next month for all other taxes, a clean cut will take place; and where we have, as at present, one taxation code as between ourselves and Great Britain we will have, after those dates, two taxation codes similar in regard to law but independent in jurisdiction.  The effect of this will be liability to double <Col N="2304" /> taxation.  A person drawing a dividend from an English Company would be taxed at the source there, and at present would not be liable to any further tax here in Ireland; but unless some such arrangement as this Bill will enable us to make be made, that person would, in the first instance, be liable to deduction at the source in England, and, secondly, on payment of the dividend here would also be liable to Income Tax taxation. Conversely the same thing happens with regard to investments and dividends paid from here and their reception in England and taxation there.  Our aim in this matter of double taxation is to ensure that no person will pay more than the higher rate of tax prevailing in either one country or the other.  Now, in the case of the Corporation Tax, which is chargeable on the profits of all companies registered in the area of jurisdiction and on the profits earned in the area of jurisdiction of companies registered outside, the same profits would be liable to taxation in both countries in respect of companies trading in both countries, and a provision must also be made here to avoid double taxation.  In the case of Death Duties, personalty, such as stocks, shares, etc., passing on the death of a person, might be liable to pay Death Duties twice over, and provision must be made to correct that.  Lastly, in the case of Stamp Duties, documents such as cheques, transfers, which are stamped in the Free State now, do not require to be stamped in Great Britain, but after the 1st April, if no provision were made such as this Act entitles us to make, a cheque issued from here upon which a stamp duty of 2d. has been paid, will also be liable to stamp duty either in Belfast, if it went to Belfast, or in London, if it went to London. It is only in the case of Inland Revenue that the question of double taxation arises.  It does not arise in the case of Customs.  The British Government has already, as I have explained, taken power to provide against double taxation, consequent on the establishment of the Free State.  Under Section 5 of the British Act entitled the Irish Free State (Consequential Provisions) Act, 1922, it is provided that where any tax is payable in the Free State in respect of a subject of charge, in respect of which a corresponding tax is payable in Great Britain and arrangements have been <Col N="2305" /> made between the British Government and the Free State Government to give a relief from double taxation, in such cases, Orders in Council may be issued giving statutory effect to the arrangements agreed upon between the two countries.  Provision is also made in that Section for the extension of relief to those taxes which are within the jurisdiction of the Government of Northern Ireland.  As regards Northern Ireland it has to be borne in mind that death duties and stamp duties are taxes under the control of that Government and its consent will be necessary to the inclusion of its taxes within the general arrangements for relief.  The provisions of the Bill introduced now are reciprocal provisions.  The most urgent aspect of the problem is in respect of stamp duty because unless arrangements are made before the 1st April, there is a liability in respect of any such duties to a double tax.  A transfer stamped in Dublin would require again to be stamped before registration in Great Britain, and <i>vice versa.</i>  A marketable security stamped in London would require to be stamped again on coming into Dublin, and so on, with regard to the various documents and instruments coming within the scope of the Stamp Acts.  It is fairly obvious I think that unless suitable provision is made to avoid incidence of double taxation in connection with stamp duties there would be serious interference with trading operations, and it is for the purpose of permitting the Government to make such necessary arrangements that this Bill was introduced. I formally move the Second Reading.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the justification the Minister has attempted to make for this Bill is insufficient to warrant us in allowing it to pass.  The Bill proposes to empower the Ministry to make arrangements with the British Government and with the Government of North-east Ireland in regard to double taxation, but to leave it to them to make any reciprocal exemptions that between them they may agree upon, and having made these arrangements to lay upon the Table an Order which then is to be revoked by a specific vote of the Dáil.  Well, this particular method of legislation by Order is <Col N="2306" /> undesirable, particularly when the onus of examining the Provisional Orders is not imposed upon any particular person, or group of persons, and that the Dáil refused to appoint a committee a week ago to have the duty thrust upon it of examining Provisional Orders.  Now, it remains for the individual member to go through these particular Orders, find out whether they are objectionable or not in any of their details, and only when he has found that out, and persuaded the majority of the Dáil of their objectionable character can they be annulled.  I think we ought to object to the particular method by which this kind of relief from taxation is to be attained.  It seems to me if it is essential that there should be exemptions made from taxation that these exemptions should be contained in a Finance Bill or the Finance Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>They ought not to be the subject of agreement between two Governments, each of which is supposed to have fiscal independence of the other.  I find that in respect of the Australian Parliament they have an arrangement whereby the double taxation in regard to income tax shall not be imposed except under certain conditions. It is by an Act of the Parliament of Australia, and the rate of exemption is specifically laid down beforehand. It is made quite clear to people, citizens of Australia, investing their money abroad, what liability they are to be under.  The proposition here is to leave it entirely in the hands of the Ministry of Finance to arrange with the Parliament or Treasury in England, or in the North-east of Ireland, to make such exemptions as they wish.  I think that method is a bad one, and ought not to be adopted by the Dáil.  The general principle, too, ought to be examined more closely than the Minister has suggested it is worthy of.  Take the matter of income tax as an instance, especially when the Minister says that there shall not be imposed upon any holder a greater amount of tax than the highest tax in force as between the respective countries.  You are hereby inviting Irish investors to invest in British stocks.  I think the pressure should be the other way, and I do not think it is desirable that we should invite Irish investors either to retain their money in British investments or to increase the amount so invested.  I rather think there should be somewhat of a penalty imposed upon the export of capital in this way.  I <Col N="2307" /> believe it would be very much more conducive to the prosperity of the Saorstát if, before we allowed any exemptions, they were thoroughly examined in the Dáil, and we should as a matter of fact impose an extra tax upon incomes through investments outside the Saorstát.</P>
    <P>The Minister speaks of the necessity of doing certain things before the first of April.  I suggest it would be easy to bring in a Bill making exemptions in respect of stamp duty if it is necessary, and I am very doubtful of the necessity It would have been just as easy to bring in a Bill setting forth the exemptions which he proposes to make, as to bring in a vague proposition of this kind, in which he asks us to hand over the powers of taxation, and, worse still, exemptions from taxation, and leave out control, because that is what it means in practice.  He asks us to hand over control&mdash;renounce the real control the Dáil should have over taxation and exemptions from taxation.  My feeling in respect of this Bill is that it is, perhaps, not so designed, but its effect will be to place the Saorstát in greater subjection than ever to British economical and financial interests.  We are, I fear, going to encourage Irish investors who may be somewhat timid, and who may be encouraged by promises from across the water of higher rates of interest and profit, to invest their moneys over there. Then where their treasure is there will their hearts be also.  Investors will look abroad and think always of their financial connections.  The financial bond will be encouraged, will be strengthened, and I submit our efforts ought to be directed towards loosening that financial bond and using pressure upon Irish investors to compel them&mdash;or, shall I say, induce them&mdash;to put their money into Irish investments.  We do not know what the intention of the Ministry is in regard to this reciprocal arrangement.  I have no doubt they will assure us nothing of the kind is intended such as agreeing to an arrangement which would give any inducement to Irish investors to take their money abroad; but we do not know.</P>
    <P>This is a reciprocal arrangement.  The British side of it was passed some months ago, presumably with reference to the transition period.  We are now invited to extend that period, and I have <Col N="2308" /> a shrewd suspicion from what has passed in the Press recently, confirmed by this Bill, that we are going to be told that there will be no change in the incidence of taxation for the next year at any rate; that the fiscal system that was obtained in the Treaty is not going to be of any effect for another year.  I suppose we shall have to wait a little while before we are confirmed in that suspicion or disillusion, but the signs seem to point to the fact that we are going to give away the advantage that fiscal freedom has given to us.</P>
    <P>The third objection that I have to the Bill is that the authorisation to make arrangements for granting relief from double taxation is confined to the Governments of Great Britain and the Government of the North-East corner. If it is desirable to make such arrangements in the interests of citizens of the Saorstát, why not extend to the Government here power to make similar arrangements of a reciprocal kind with any other Government that is willing to do so?  Conceivably there are men in Ireland who have moneys invested in Canada, Australia, or South Africa.  Is this Bill depriving the Government here of the power to make arrangements with the Governments of those other countries? Conceivably also Irishmen may have investments in France, or Germany, or Mexican Rails.  Are we willing to make any arrangements with the Governments of those countries?  If not, why not?  It may be a very good thing to facilitate intercourse between England and Ireland, and even to facilitate the investment of British money in Irish concerns, so as to give the British investor the real control that President Wilson and many others have talked about&mdash;the real control that overrides political control and determines the lines that political affairs will take.  It may be a very good thing to facilitate that kind of investment, but I submit to the Dáil that it is not good for us to hand over the power to make arrangements of this kind to the Ministry, leaving us only the provisional order to annual or accept as a whole.  I submit that this ought to go into the Finance Bill and that we should examine each particular item clause by clause.  Then we shall know whether it is likely to be to the advantage of Saorstát or to the disadvantage, <Col N="2309" /> and the Dáil will be responsible.  I would ask you to vote against the Second Reading of this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GERALD FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not wish to say anything against this Bill for I think it is a good one, but there is one matter that I would like to direct the attention of the Minister for Finance to.  In the course of his introduction of the Bill, he referred to Income Tax, and then he went on to several other matters which he described as Duties, Death Duties, and so on.  I confess that I have not looked into the matter very deeply.  I took a glimpse through some of the Taxation Acts before I came down here, and I suggest the Minister should consider whether it would not be well to introduce a Clause defining tax or stating what it includes. We all know Income Tax is called a tax but the Minister himself refers to Death Duties and Stamp Duties.  I am by no means certain that the word tax, which is the only word used in the Bill, would be regarded as sufficiently extensive to cover Death and Stamp Duties.  I suggest that it might be well to be quite certain about that before we part with the Committee stage of this Bill, and that it might be desirable, possibly, to introduce a definition clause defining taxes as including all subject matters of duties, imposition or charge, or some extended term of that kind so as to make it quite clear that these duties to which the Minister referred in introducing the Bill would be covered by the word &ldquo;taxes&rdquo; which is used here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. D.J. GOREY Mr. D.J. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that it is the country where the industry is carried on that would have the right to income tax and not the country of residence. For instance, an Irishman with money invested in England would be liable for the English Income Tax and the Englishman with money in Irish Industries, which is scarcely a likely thing, would be liable for the Irish rate of Income Tax, and would not be liable to English Income Tax afterwards.  The attitude of Deputy Johnson would be bad enough on investments made as from this date, but his attitude to previous investments to my mind is absolutely malignant, and the present time is not an opportune one for introducing legislation to make them invest in Irish Industries. <Col N="2310" /> We have people at the moment going around the country under the red flag, seizing any industries we have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>This does not arise under this Double Taxation Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not arise, I quite agree, but it is unfortunate that the Deputy mentioned it at the present time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="A Labour Deputy A Labour Deputy">
      <NameTxt>A Labour Deputy</NameTxt>
      <P>What is your flag&mdash; the black flag?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, it is not the white one anyway.  And the red has no terror for me, and any time the red people want it they can have it in any form they like.  That is all I have to say.  I am anxious that the President would give us some idea as to whether it is the country of residence or the country where the tax is earned which would be liable for income tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The case made by Deputy Johnson does not appear to me to be very convincing.  The question arises first of all as to whether this ought to be done.  That is a vital question, I suppose, for us here.  I do not know to what extent it may be a vital question for the British Government, but it is a vital question for persons who have considerable investments and who are citizens of either one country or the other, and as such it ought to be a vital question for citizens of Great Britain as well as for citizens of Saorstát Eireann.  I think there is no doubt whatever that this is a matter which should be settled, and settled as quickly as possible, and that there should be an arrangement that no person by reason of the new position created by the setting up of the Saorstát should be committed to double taxation.  In some cases people are at present liable to the extent of 12/- in the £; if liable to, say, 12/- in one country they are held liable for 12/- in the other country.  It is obvious that someone will have to make up the difference. The next question arises as to whether or not this is the best machinery to adopt in order to deal with it.  We believe it is.  No real case has been made against it.  The Bill which I think has <Col N="2311" /> been circulated provides that Orders made by the Governor-General shall be laid before Dáil Eireann so that it shall have an opportunity of considering any such Order.  We can circulate, if necessary, a White Paper with the Order explaining in detail its operation and effect. I think it is fairly clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the President if he is aware that an Order of that kind can only be annulled <i>en bloc</i>&mdash;it cannot be amended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware of that.  Stamps, I think, I have already explained, must be provided for before 1st April.  Now if it be put forward by the Deputy that we could get through an arrangement of this sort in a Finance Act he is very much more optimistic than I am.  I do not know how it can be done.  A Finance Act, as he is well aware, without any elaborate explanation of it, ought to be an instrument of very considerable importance to this Dáil.  It is obvious that one cannot rush that through in the time between now and the 1st April.  If the case be that we ought to have done it before this I admit at once that he has scored a point there, but he might have reserved a small quantity of ammunition when he engaged in that offensive.  There are many other things we ought to have done as well.  There is a large list of necessary legislative Acts that ought to have been introduced and dealt with, but it has not been possible and it will not be possible to do these things as quickly as the necessities of the time perhaps demand. Now, for the first year we must have Orders, but it might be provided that in subsequent years legislation could be introduced which would deal with them in a manner which might give greater satisfaction, although it is possible that it would be only a satisfaction to members of the Dáil.  As long as the instruments that we put up effect the purpose that we have in mind and satisfy the equities of the case, which are really what should be satisfied, I do not know that there are reasonable grounds for complaint.  As regards the necessity for relief, we have interviewed the authorities of the Stock Exchange and they are all clear as to the necessity. We have reason to believe that the Banking world also demands relief. <Col N="2312" /> I do not know whether the Deputy is aware of the extent to which monies in vested in either one country or the other are involved.  Very large sums of money are invested.  I think the Deputy appreciates the necessity of not further complicating the money markets by neglecting to discharge our obligations as a Government in a matter of this kind.  People who invested in English firms or in English securities, whether gilt-edged or otherwise, were entitled to understand that whoever would be the responsible persons in either this country or Great Britain would look after their interests should such political changes occur as would prejudice their investments.  That is a reasonable assumption for any person to make in any country.  I do not think that there is any objection to considering the point made by Deputy Fitzgibbon; it is a reasonable suggestion, and I will undertake to consider it and see if we can introduce some clause defining what is meant by a &ldquo;duty.&rdquo;  The matter mentioned by Deputy Gorey is a matter for arrangement.  We start away with the fundamental idea I suppose, that there should be a division as regards the income tax.  I do not think it would be fair to expect me to enter into a laboured explanation of the merits of either a person who owns property in the one case or the country which provides the money in the other.  If you take into consideration the question of Consols, monies provided for carrying on the war, and so on, the sums of money invested by this country&mdash;that is by the whole of Ireland&mdash;amount to something like one hundred and six million pounds&mdash;that is, that we hold about that much of English securities.  On the other hand, sums of money advanced for services in this country by the British Government, or, at least, by the citizens of Great Britain, amount to something like one hundred and thirty millions, in respect of Land Stock.  One of these would practically balance the other.  If income tax were deducted, or liable to deduction, in both cases it would be rather an expensive subject to go into.  Deputies will appreciate the fact that in respect of War Loans income tax is not deducted in the case of some of these Stocks.  I do not think that the Dáil would be justified on the case made by Deputy Johnson in refusing to pass this Bill.  I think it is a <Col N="2313" /> duty that we owe to our own citizens; it is a duty that we owe to those of our own citizens who are investors, and it is a duty that, in equity, is due to people that they will not be mulcted, and that the ordinary business people in Ireland would not be subjected to double Stamp Duties or other such impositions which, under the circumstances, would be very unjust and very immoral, and that we would certainly fail in our duty if we did not seek to relieve them of such impositions.</P>
      <P>Question put:&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second time.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>When will the next Stage be taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to take it as early as possible.  I will have to ask the indulgence of the Dáil with regard to that.  I do not think that it is very contentious.  If the Dáil would agree to have it taken tomorrow&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Then there will not be time for amendment.  Some amendments will have to be put forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Four days notice of amendments is supposed to be given.  If the President waives that it means that he will be taking amendments when the Bill is in Committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>As long as they give me ten minutes, or quarter of an hour, to consider them I will be satisfied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Committee Stage of this Bill will be taken on Thursday then, which means that amendments will not be printed unless they are received to-morrow morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not satisfactory and it is not fair.  I think that, as far as the proposers of amendments are concerned, we should have at least until Thursday.  As to what the Dáil does, of course it can do what it pleases; but I think that those who wish to propose amendments should have some little time to think about them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>No amendments will appear in print on the Paper unless received to-morrow.  Since the Bill is to be taken in this way, we must receive amendments up to the last moment, but they will not be upon the Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2314" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Dáil is agreeable to that, I am quite willing.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - CRIMINAL AND MALICIOUS" RHead="INJURIES BILL&mdash;MONEY RESOLUTION">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - CRIMINAL AND MALICIOUS INJURIES BILL&mdash;MONEY RESOLUTION.</Title>
    <P>The Dáil went into Committee on the Money resolution of the Criminal and Malicious Injuries Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That for carrying out the provisions of any Act of the present Session to amend the law relating to Criminal and Malicious Injuries, it is expedient that the authority mentioned in the resolution on this subject adopted by the Committee on Finance on the 22nd February last be extended so as to cover&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(1)  The substitution in the said resolution of a reference to the 20th day of March, 1923, for the reference to the 6th day of February, 1923, and&rdquo;&mdash;that is, the time that has already generally been extended&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(2)  The payment out of moneys to be provided by the Oireachtas of such amounts as may be required to be paid for the purpose of any agreements made pursuant to such Act between the Minister for Finance and any Railway Company or Companies.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I take it, it is unnecessary for me to mention that there will be no further extension than what is indicated here&mdash; namely, the 20th day of March, 1923 That is the final day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to move as an amendment the deletion of Clause (2) of the resolution which has been moved by the President.  We are asked under the terms of this clause of the resolution to vote away, perhaps, or hundreds of thousands of pounds, or perhaps even millions of money, from State funds for the purpose of carrying out the terms of an agreement which has neither been explained to the Dáil nor to the people. However much we may regret the necessity for having to make provision for the destruction of the lines of communication in this country, and being forced at the same time to make such provision, I think there is one purpose that will be <Col N="2315" /> served, and that is perhaps to make quite clear to the people of the State who are called upon to pay such huge amounts of money out of their pockets for stupid and senseless destruction done in this country that it is calculated to injure more than anybody else the non-combatant section of the community.  I am always careful, personally, when any agreement is being made with the railway companies or railway magnates&mdash; especially where money is concerned and where people are called upon to pay&mdash; that it should be made quite clear what are the conditions governing such agreement.</P>
      <P>(At this stage An Leas Cheann Comhairle took the Chair.)</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>This clause does call for the payment out of State funds for specific purposes, namely, for the making of provision for the rebuilding of the lines and the restoration of wagons or engines that may have been destroyed as a result of the destructive policy engaged upon and that has been going on since last June or July.  I want, in any agreement made, where Irish funds are being paid over to any railway magnates, that the purpose for which the money is paid out will be made quite clear before any of that money is paid; that it will be spent in this country and not in English workshops.  We also want to have it made quite clear that any bridges that may be rebuilt will be rebuilt so as to cope with enlarged and increased traffic, particularly over the main roads, that may arise in this country in the future.  I thought it necessary to personally bring under the notice of the Minister for Industry and Commerce the failure of the Great Southern and Western Railway to rebuild any of the bridges that had been destroyed in their area since the destruction commenced last June or July.  They have persistently taken up the attitude of point blank refusing to meet any request made to them by the present Government. The result of one particular instance that I have in my mind is that of a certain county boundary bridge&mdash;the company refused to reconstruct or rebuild that bridge in an area where for some time past there has been no Irregular activity; and the failure of the company to rebuild this <Col N="2316" /> particular bridge means that the communication between two very important towns in two different counties are cut off since June or July last.  I do not know whether any of these things have been mentioned to the railway companies or their officers by the President, or any member of the Government, in discussing the terms of agreement under which these huge sums of money are to be paid to the companies.  I would like, on the question of rebuilding, to know whether the question of increased traffic has been taken into consideration.  I am personally aware that in many instances where destruction has been done to railway property it has been welcomed for many reasons by the railway companies themselves.  We have had it in the case of railway stations where originally there existed two signal cabins. The Great Southern and Western Railway Company in restoring the damage only built one signal cabin where two originally existed.  And in the case of the saving of labour, that means doing away with the position of three signalmen alone.  I wonder if any saving effected in such a case as that is taken into consideration by the Government when discussing the terms of settlement.</P>
      <P>I also particularly wish to draw the attention of the Government to the position of the future of the Irish railways arising out of a statement made in this Dáil in a Debate which occurred here on the 3rd January last.  The Minister for Industry and Commerce, speaking, as he said, for the Government on that occasion, stated:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;The future of the Irish railways has been uncertain ever since August, 1921. In the view that the country cannot afford to allow the question to drift any longer, the companies have been informed that if they do not produce an agreed scheme of grouping such as the Government can approve within three months from the 1st January, 1923, legislation will be introduced with the object of bringing about unification within a period of six months from that date.  Such legislation would require to include provision for dealing with rates, fares and charges, with machinery for avoiding disputes and for consultation with the employees on matters concerning them, and with many other matters on which existing legislation is not <Col N="2317" /> adequate or satisfactory.&rdquo;  [<i>Official Report&mdash;January</i> 3<i>rd</i>, 1923&mdash;<i>Col.</i> 433].</P>
    <P>Now that undertaking expires at the end of the present month, and probably before the passing of this Bill or any other Bill as makes provision for the payment of monies out of State funds, will become operative.  I want to make sure that any money voted to Irish railway companies will not be utilised on or after the 1st of April for legalising an agreement which would make the port of Dublin a third rate port, in place of what it should be&mdash;the principal port in the country.  I warn the Government that agreements have been made, and some have been signed, which if approved of would make Dublin a third rate port.</P>
    <P>We have, from previous knowledge and experience, seen what occurred in the case of the British Government when a sum of three million pounds was voted away under the Claims and Settlement Bill for the specific purpose of deferred maintenance.  If you read the reports of the recent annual meetings of the Irish railway companies, you will see that this money was set aside for the purpose of maintaining pre-war dividends, instead of using it for the purpose for which it was voted&mdash;namely, to make provision for deferred maintainance.  I warn you to see that any money you are going to vote away for a certain specific purpose under this Bill will not be used for a different purpose altogether, as happened in the case I have just referred to.  I also wish to bring under the notice of the Government the question of having an understanding with the railway companies, when agreement is arrived at, as regards making reasonable and suitable provision for the dependants of those who have been killed or injured in carrying on essential railway services since June or July last.  It has been stated to me that railway companies are responsible to the dependants of those who have been killed or injured under the provisions of the Workmen's Compensation Act, but, I put it to the Dáil that men who have been doing this particular class of work under extraordinary difficulties should be provided for under the terms that are more satisfactory than the provision made for them under the Workmen's Compensation Act.  I also wish to draw the attention of the President and the Government to the fact that the railway companies <Col N="2318" /> have very reluctantly agreed, and in most cases have refused altogether, to open up any works that have been closed down since this war started in June or July last.  They are going around the country with an economy stunt which, under very abnormal conditions, means, as you know, the cutting down of labour, and the cutting down of all classes of expenses, and you have this at a time when conditions are not normal, and when such things should not be going on.  I have been told, but I cannot say it is exactly true, that they have received such instructions from the Government.  I hope the statement is not correct.  I move the deletion of the clause, because, as I have stated, there has been no reasonable explanation given to the Dáil, or to the people, as to the terms of the agreement under which we are asked to vote away huge sums of money.  I hope, before this clause is passed by the Dáil, that a reasonable explanation will be given to the Dáil and the people who will be called upon to pay the huge sums of money voted out of the public funds.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The rejection of this money resolution, in effect, will mean, first, that the railway companies will get no compensation, and, secondly, that no repairs and no reconstruction of bridges and no ordinary maintenance of that particular service, can be undertaken by any of the railway companies in question.  They are excluded so far from the terms of this Bill.  There is an amendment before the Dáil for consideration to-day, or at least it will come on when the succeeding stages of the Bill are taken, which indicates what the proposals are that the Government had in contemplation for remedying the damage done to the railway companies. Now, as far as I am aware, they are placed in the position in which claims for compensation made by them are subjected to close investigation by the Government. That matter will come on before the Dáil when we reach that particular amendment or clause dealing with compensation to railways.  It will be observed that the resolution here is to provide for the payment of moneys for the purpose of any agreement made pursuant to such Act; that is, the particular Act, so that, in essence, it comes to this that even if this resolution were passed and that the Dáil rejects the amendment there would not be any arrangements <Col N="2319" /> come to between the Government, on the one hand, and the railway companies, on the other; and consequently there would not be any authority as far as I know&mdash;I am speaking now within the law&mdash;to discharge such liability. It is right to say this, that we have already paid on account to at least one railway company some money; otherwise it might have been impossible for that particular concern to have gone on with the work.  That is a case in which repairs had been effected and money spent.  Now they are not in any worse position than anybody else whose property has been damaged.  The mere fact that we have disputes, or that there are disputes of one sort or another with railway companies, either on the part of the people whom the Deputy speaks for or represents, or, in so far as any Government policy with regard to the railways themselves are concerned, does not alter the fact that we have got to deal justly and fairly with these important organisations.  Their property has been damaged to a very considerable extent, and their co-operation must be sought and must be got, in order to repair the damage done, and to enable them to carry on the necessary services for the public.  For that purpose they are entitled just the same as any other person whose property has been damaged, to compensation.  The terms under which such compensation will be paid to them are, in my opinion, sufficiently restricted and sufficiently protected, as far as we are concerned, regarding the public funds, to entitle the Dáil to consider on its merits the proposal we are making.  To wipe out the resolution now simply means that you will not give any compensation whatever of any kind or sort to the railway companies.  It means that they get nothing if this resolution be not adopted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>That was not exactly what I said.  What I moved was the deletion of Clause 2 until such time as the terms of the agreement come to between the Government and the Railway Companies had been explained to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>That raises a constitutional question which the Deputy, I am sure, will not expect me to explain. The usual procedure with regard to any service that we administer or <Col N="2320" /> intend to provide is, first of all, to get a money resolution authorising its execution. If a Bill be introduced which contemplates the spending of public money a resolution authorising such expenditure has to be introduced and passed, and within the ambit of that particular resolution you are entitled to consider&mdash;to amend, but not to extend&mdash;the authority that you get by reason of such resolution. In other words, if a sum of money were mentioned here, it would not be within the competence of Deputies to move that that sum should be extended, say, to one and a half millions.  According to the Constitution, only the Minister for Finance can bring in a resolution and get it proposed.  I would point out to the Deputy that unless that resolution be passed the Dáil cannot consider and pass any clause in this Bill dealing with compensation to the Railway Companies. It is open, of course, to him to amend and otherwise alter the clauses which we put down, but it is not open to us to consider that until the resolution put down here is passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The proposal of Deputy Davin is to delete Clause 2 of this resolution, not for the purpose of preventing the authorisation of money to be spent, but to enable the Ministry to bring forward a separate resolution in a separate Bill which would give us information such as is not contained in the present Bill.  This resolution is preliminary, as the Minister himself has said to a proposed amendment of the Bill which is to come forward at a later stage, and which authorises the Ministry to make terms with the Railway Companies&mdash;to make an agreement with the Railway Companies&mdash;without giving any information to the Dáil as to the terms of that agreement until after it is signed, sealed, and delivered. What we desire to do is to make it possible for the Ministry to bring forward to the Dáil a Bill which would enable them to pay such compensation as is necessary on such terms and conditions as the Dáil thinks desirable and to precede that by a similar Money Resolution. On the question of procedure the advice of Ceann Comhairle has been followed in this matter, and that was that questions under discussion ought to be raised on the Money Resolution in the first instance. The proposal in the Bill is, of <Col N="2321" /> course, to empower the Government to make agreements with the railway companies in regard to the terms in which compensation will be paid, but it will be noted that in the case of any other person or company that has suffered damage there are express conditions set out in the Criminal and Malicious Injuries Bill, but exceptions are being made in the case of railway companies.  We think it desirable that the Dáil should be informed of the terms, or, at least, the line of thought of the Ministry in considering agreements with railway companies in respect of compensation.  Deputy Davin has spoken of the necessity of insuring that the sufferers from rifle shot, broken bridges, amongst railway servants should be specifically provided for in any agreement, and I would press upon the Dáil to insist if they desire to keep the railway services going that the railway companies should be in a position to ensure that their servants will be protected against poverty as well as personal injury as the result of that poverty.  We want to ensure that the men engaged in this particular work should be assured of some compensation because of the risks they are running.</P>
      <P>At this stage Ceann Comhairle resumed the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>And quite apart from the other question that Deputy Davin raised as to the conditions under which the money shall be spent, we want to insist that provision shall be made in any agreement of this kind that the companies will be bound, if nobody else is bound, to recompense sufferers from malicious damage committed on the railways.  I think the Dáil is entitled to know what kind of agreements are being demanded by the companies, and what kind of agreements are being offered by the Ministry to the companies before we vote either for this Money Authorisation, or, at a later stage, for the amendment that is being put down.  Surely, it is not too much to ask at the end of March for some information as to the policy that the Government is proposing in regard to these railways; first, in regard to their reconstruction as to damage and generally in regard to railway policy.  The amendment, if carried, to delete Sub-section 2, does not prevent money being paid to the railway companies for compensation, but will enable the Minister to come forward and explain the scheme, <Col N="2322" /> and to tell us some of the terms of the agreements that are being entered into, and to get authorisation specifically for work that has to be done on the railways and the compensation that has to be paid to the railway companies.  That would be the effect of the carrying of the amendment, and it does not destroy the plan of the Bill to any extent whatever.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="Mr. COLOHAN Mr. COLOHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. COLOHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>In Clause 1 of the motion I wish to say that the President extended the date from the 6th February to the 20th March, and I would now ask him to extend it to the 31st March.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We are on a motion to delete Sub-section 2 of the motion, and I think we had better get that disposed of before we go into any other question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no desire whatever to have it understood by the President or by the Government that I am moving the deletion of this clause for the purpose of denying the railway company the right to compensation.  The President has informed the Dáil, and I understand it for the first time that he or the Government have already paid a sum of money in advance to one railway company for a particular purpose.  I submit to him that the deletion of this clause will not prevent him or the Government from paying any similar amount to any other company for the purpose of carrying out reconstruction work.  I submit that the Dáil and the country are entitled to understand quite clearly every condition of any agreement entered into between the Government and the company in regard to the question of compensation, and the conditions under which money is going to be voted out of public funds.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and negatived.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to move a further amendment to Clause 2; that is to add at the end the words, &ldquo;approved by resolution of both Houses of the Oireachtas.&rdquo; The effect of that would be that the agreement which is to be made pursuant to the Act which is now to be considered between the Minister for Finance and any railway companies shall be approved by a resolution of both Houses of the Oireachtas before it becomes oprative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Would not this amendment be more properly moved in the discussion on the Bill when <Col N="2323" /> the amendment to insert the agreement Section is being taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am satisfied, if that meets the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. FITZGIBBON Mr. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. FITZGIBBON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make a suggestion in support of that. The resolution says, &ldquo;any agreements made pursuant to such Act.&rdquo;  Therefore, if we introduce into the Act, by way of amendment to the motion that has been proposed by the Minister for Finance that such motion be approved by resolution that would meet the view of Deputy Johnson, and this resolution would not prevent the necessity of obtaining such resolution.  I submit to Deputy Johnson and to you that it would come in better in the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>On the other hand if it were defeated in the Bill I doubt if it would be operative here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would rather see it defeated now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, Deputy Johnson has withdrawn the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HughColohan" hpid="Mr. COLOHAN Mr. COLOHAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. COLOHAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to ask the President to extend the time further from the 20th March to the 31st March. As he is aware a considerable number of claims for malicious injuries have come in from the country and it would relieve the County Councils very much if it were extended, and I have no doubt he would give that request a sympathetic hearing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would point out to the Deputy that my office is limited. I am merely President, and it is not from the President that you would get authorisation but from the Executive Council.  I am asked to extend this from the 20th March to the 31st March. If my recollection is right it is stated in the Gospel &ldquo;sufficient for the day is the evil thereof.&rdquo;  No damage has been done beyond the 20th March and I am invited to pay for damage that has not yet been done.  As a business man I do not think that I could undertake such liability as that.  This is a generous concession that up to date we are prepared to pay for damage, but if we are asked to take on liability that has not materialised it is too much.  I do not think that any Minister I ever heard of would make such a recommendation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2324" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest to the President that in this motion the words &ldquo;Committee on Finance&rdquo; be changed to &ldquo;Dáil Eireann.&rdquo;  We only created the Committee on Finance by our Standing Orders coming into force to-day.  There was no such thing known before the 22nd February as a Committee on Finance.  I suggest that leave of the Dáil be asked to make that change operative.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>All right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it leave is given to the President to amend the motion accordingly.</P>
      <P>Motion as amended put and agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE." RHead="- DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion is reported to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Dáil doth agree in the said resolution.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - STATUS" RHead="OF THE IRISH LANGUAGE">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - STATUS OF THE IRISH LANGUAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adjournment of the Dáil until 3 o'clock to-morrow to enable Deputy Gavan Duffy to raise his question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="SEOIRSE GHABHAIN UI DUBHTHAIGH SEOIRSE GHABHAIN UI DUBHTHAIGH">
      <NameTxt>SEOIRSE GHABHAIN UI DUBHTHAIGH</NameTxt>
      <P>Eist, a Chinn Chomhairle, le droch sgéal a fuair mé san pháipéar coichthís ó soin.  Do leigheas ins an bpáipéar go raibh cúis mhoir os chomhair na h-Árd-Cúirte.  D'iarradh ar an offigeach páipéar i nGaedhilg a ghlacadh. Acht éist leis seo: &ldquo;Mr. Maguire said he would not accept it without direction. He took the directions in his Chambers. The Lord Chief Justice is Head of the Judicature, and he said it could be filed if it was accompanied by an exactly similar affidavit in English, bearing the filing stamp also.&rdquo;  Fuaireamar sgéal ba mheasa ó shoin.  Bhí sé le léigheamh againn sa pháipéar Lá Fhéile Pádraig gur eirigh an cúis leis an Árd-Bhreitheamh. Dubhairt an Árd-Chúirt fhéin sin&mdash;an t-Árd-Bhreitheamh céanda agus beirt eile&mdash;go raibh an ceart ag an Árd-Bhreitheamh. Anois, féach ar an mBun-Reacht.  'Sé seo an dligh atá ceapaithe 'san Bhun Reacht:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Sí an Ghaedhilg teanga Náisiúnta Shaorstáit Eireann, ach có-aithneofar an Béarla mar theanga oifigiúil.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>'Sí an Ghaedhilg an teanga náisiúnta, ach mar sin féin, séantar an teanga orrainn <Col N="2325" /> agus ní tugtar Cothrom na Féinne dí ins an Árd-Chúirt fhéin.  &ldquo;<i>Quis custodiet ipsos custodes?&rdquo;</i>  An lá a ghlacamar leis an mBun-Reacht do chuireamar i n-iúil do'n tsaoghal Fodhlach i d-tosach báire gur ab í teanga na nGaedheal an teanga náisiúnta.  Shaoil na Breitheamhain sin nach rabhamar i n-dáiríribh. Bhí sé i g-ceist aca nach rabhamar ach dul chun dalladh mullóg a chur ar na daoini simplí a though mar Teachtaí sinne.</P>
    <P>An raibh an ceart aca?  Le linn an chogaidh do bhí ar siubhal do chuir na buic mhóra sin a ngeall ar an taoibh a shaoil siad a ghnothóchadh; do chailleadar an báire, ach, má chailleadar féin, tá siad níos udarásaighe indiú ná ariamh &mdash;níos udarásaighe ná bhíodar faoi shean-Reacht an Ghaill Féin.  Tá an tír uilig faoi smacht aca go fóill, agus feicthear dobhtha gur féidir leo&mdash;cosantóirí an Bun-Reachta, mar dheadh!&mdash;an Bun-Reacht féin a chur ar leathaoibh mara bhfeileann sé dobhtha.</P>
    <P>Cé a thóigfeadh sin ortha?  Cad a dhéanas mac a chuit ach luch a mharbhadh? Is orrainn fhéin atá an locht toisg go dtugamar an cead sin dobhtha. D'fhágamar an tír faoi n-a g-ceannas, daoine nach bhfuil aon mheas ná aon taobhadh ag Gaedheal ar bith leo.  Agus táimid ag ioch go géar as margheall ar sin.</P>
    <P>Ní féidir leo a bheith dílis do chúis na Gaedhilge; bíonn siad ar nós na g-cnoc árd sin a mbíonn na néalta go siorruidhe ar a mbarr.  Bíonn, agus beidh go deo, ceo dhubh dhorca ar a g-cuid súil, ceo na n-árd-smaointe a bhíos ag eirghe in a g-cinn aca i measg na réalta.  Má tugtar cead a g-ceann do na sean-Bhreitheamhain béidh sé fánach againn rialtas a ghabháil chugainn fhéin; agus tá an Bun-Reacht féin bréagach san méid a fhógríonn sé gur ab í an Ghaedhilg an teanga náisiúnta. Má leantar do'n chúis seo déanfaidh fóbhreitheamhain agus Iúistisí aithris ar an droch-bhreith sin.  Agus ní h-é sin amháin, ach cuirfear ar leath-taoibh Reacht na n-Gaedheal chun Reacht na nGall a bhuanú go doimhin in a h-áit. Agus is sinne&mdash;Teachtaí muinntir na h-Eireann&mdash;atá cionntach ann.</P>
    <P>Níl ach fíor-bheagán Gaedhilgeoirí annso idir Airí agus Teachtaí, a thuigfeas an Ghaedhilig agus go bhfuil grádh acu don Teangain ach is iad sin an chraobh chosanta aonraic atá ag cúis na Gaedhilge san Dáil.  Ná tréigimis an chúis; caithfimíd a bheith aontuighthe <Col N="2326" /> le céile ar son na teangan, agus má sheasamuid uilig ar an g-ceart, mar ba choir duinn, beidh linn.  Ná geillimís doibh seo atá ag maslughadh na teangan, ach abramaois amach, díreach' d'aon guth, go g-caithfidh gach aon breitheamh geilleadh do'n mBun-Reacht nó eirigh as a phost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>We have listened to a remarkably able speech from the Deputy.  I regret that I cannot find myself in complete agreement with the sentiments he has expressed.  A cynic who is himself a fluent speaker of Irish said to me once that humour shrieked and died in Ireland when the Gaelic League was founded.  I did not believe him; I do not believe him now.  I hope that we have sufficient humour left to appreciate the position that has arisen in regard to this matter.  It came before the notice of Deputies first in a letter from the Secretary of the Gaelic League. The letter was in Irish, and was accompanied by an English translation.  The official Gael, the salaried official Gael, writes here to Deputies his Irish letter, but accompanies it with an English translation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON</NameTxt>
      <P>Why wouldn't he?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Why wouldn't he, exactly!  But it comes ill from that official Gael to blame people whom he would describe as ex-British Judges for the same practice.  Yet that is what it is all about.  The ruling of Lord Chief Justice Molony required that an affidavit in Irish be accompanied by a duplicate in English, and the Secretary of the Gaelic League has written to T. D. 's drawing their attention to the fact. Article 4 of the Constitution states that the National Language of Saorstát Eireann is the Irish language, but it goes on to provide that for official purposes English shall be equally recognised. This means that for all official purposes both languages stand on precisely the same footing, and that it is unquestioned that every citizen of the Irish Free State is entitled to use either language equally at his own option&mdash;a constitutional right which cannot be taken from him while that provision of the Constitution stands. Any person having recourse to the Courts and having to prove the facts by affidavit is entitled as of constitutional right to <Col N="2327" /> make his affidavit in the Irish language. That is not questioned, and has not been questioned by anyone.  At the same time, while a man's official affidavit may be in the Irish language, there is nothing in the Constitution to prevent the Courts making rules, for convenience and to prevent the defeat of the ends of justice, requiring an authentic translation in English, and <i>vice versa</i>, to be lodged with the original in the other language.  This is not merely a matter of insisting that Judges and Court officials shall know the national language.  It is a question of the right of the other party to the litigation to be put in possession of the facts alleged and relied upon, the object of the affidavit being to prove and put on record the fact relied upon.  The Constitution does not give any right to one litigant to choose that one of the two official languages of which his opponent is ignorant and exclude him from defending his position by refusing him the official language he does know.  Provision will have to be made on the reconstruction of the Judiciary for equal recognition of the two languages, but rules of Court will be required to protect litigants against being deprived of their rights by playing on the national language to the defeat of justice. When fair rules come to be drawn up, it will be found that the provisions in this respect will not differ substantially from the ruling of the Lord Chief Justice.  That is the position.  There is no occasion for people to work themselves into a rage or to suggest that we have brought balm and wine to Judges who received the death-stroke from the Deputy's pen on the 6th December, 1921, and who would have expired long since but for our attentions.  We were much too occupied for that particular kind of first aid.  There is one matter that, perhaps, does require to be cleared up, and that is the matter of stamping both documents. The matter of stamping is not one for the Judges at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is one for the Ministry of Finance, and if application is made to the Minister for Finance for a ruling on that particular matter I have little doubt the ruling will be satisfactory to all concerned, including the Secretary of the Gaelic League.  But you have to remember the functions of the courts of law. They are places for the transaction of <Col N="2328" /> public business, for the settlement of conflicting claims, and for the administration of justice between citizen and citizen.  They are not primarily linguistic schools or anything of that kind.  A non-Irish speaking plaintiff or a non-Irish speaking defendant, as the case may be, in a particular piece of litigation, and his non-Irish speaking solicitor and counsel are entitled to know what is the case put up by the other party to the dispute, and are entitled to have that case put up in a language which they understood and which is open to them.  Anything else would not be recognising the equality which is laid down in the Constitution, the equality for official purposes of the two languages. The only scrap of grievance in this matter and the only peg there has been to hang all this controversy on has been the one matter of what was stated with regard to both documents being stamped. As I said that is not a matter for the Judges to rule on at all.  It is purely a Finance matter, a matter for the Department of Finance, and the Minister for Finance is not likely to give a ruling in accordance with what was stated in the course of that matter.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that the Dáil ought to be satisfied with the answer of the Minister at all.  I think from the ordinary reading of the reports in the newspapers of this case in the Courts before the Master of the Rolls and before the Appeal Court that there has been a certain slight and slur cast on the position of Irish as the National language, and as one of the two official languages of the Saorstát&mdash;a slight and a slur just as sharp and as uncalled for as the slight and the slur in the Minister's reference to the payment of the Secretary of the Gaelic League.  The Minister was so ignorant that he did not know that one of the Generals in the Army was at one time a paid Secretary of the Gaelic League.  That is the kind of thing&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy pardon me, I was referring rather to his official position.  As the salary puts the stamp rather on that official position I mentioned the matter.  I was contrasting this official Gael who ought to have known better, that is if his own contention were right, with what he would call ex-British Judges, who never hung <Col N="2329" /> themselves out as having any particular ardour or enthusiasm in that direction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON</NameTxt>
      <P>No; the ex-British Judges might not be expected to have any particular ardour or enthusiasm for the carrying out of the spirit of the Constitution, but the most you would expect was that Ministers would have some ardour and enthusiasm for carrying out the spirit of the Constitution. It may be all right, as the Minister said if a special application were made to the Ministry of Finance that the Ministry would see that whoever had to pay for the stamps on the affidavit in Irish would not have to pay on the affidavit in English.  That is not the question.  The question is that these Judges&mdash;Lord Justices O'Connor and Ronan, and the other&mdash;have said that the Irish language was the National language, but that English was the official language of the Courts.  One of them&mdash;and, I think, perhaps, from common report he is one of the most learned in the law&mdash;has stated that by an old statute English has been made the official language of the Courts, and he doubted if an affidavit in Irish could be accepted by the Courts Now, the contention, I think, of those who stand for the acceptance of the affidavit in Irish is that according to Article 4 of the Constitution the National language of the Irish Free State&mdash; Saorstát Eireann&mdash;is not only Irish, but that it is co-equal as the official language of the Courts and of everything else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>According to another Article of the Constitution, Article 73, it is stated that, &ldquo;subject to this Constitution, and to the extent to which they are not inconsistent therewith, the laws in force in the Irish Free State, Saorstát Eireann, at the date of the coming into operation of this Constitution shall continue to be of full force and effect until the same or any of them shall have been repealed or amended by enactment of the Oireachtas.&rdquo;  They shall be of full force to the extent to which they are not inconsistent.  I maintain that this Statute to which the Judge refers is to this extent inconsistent with the Constitution, and that, therefore, the Constitution is a superior document and a superior instrument to the old Statute, and that for that reason there should be no requirement at all of a second affidavit because that is what the Judges have asked for&mdash;a second affidavit.  They will have an affidavit in Irish provided there is another affidavit to the same effect in <Col N="2330" /> English.  The cases are not analogous at all to that of the Secretary of the Gaelio League sending letters to T. D.'s in Irish with an English translation.  It is not an English translation that the Judges ask for.  It is affidavits in English they have asked for.  They are not willing to put Irish in its proper place according to the Constitution. I am one of those who are a bit cynical about the future of Irish as a spoken language.  Things have been happening that have shaken my faith in the likelihood of Irish becoming a dominating language in Ireland within my time, but so long as the Constitution puts it not only as the national language, but one of the two official languages, I submit that the Courts, although they are the old Courts and not the new ones of the Oireachtas, have got the duty to recognise the Irish language as the official language of the Courts, and that affidavits, apart altogether from translation, should be quite acceptable to their clerks and everybody else.  Now, what would be the position of an Italian speaker who did not know English or Irish, or of a French speaker who had to make an affidavit?  Incidentally I might ask a question in conclusion, just to see how the thing is being done at the fountain head.  There is an Article of the Constitution which provides that two copies of every law passed by the Oireachtas shall be made, and one of them shall be signed by the representative of the Crown, to be enrolled for record in the office of such officer of the Supreme Court as Dáil Eireann may determine, and in case of conflict one of them is to fix the question as to which of the two documents is to rule.  The one to rule is the one presented and signed by the representative of the Crown.  I should like to ask whether, in the case of laws already passed by the Dáil, the Acts presented and signed by the representatives of the Crown and enrolled for record in the office of such officer, have been the copies in Irish or the copies in English?</P>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="EARNAN DE BLAGHD EARNAN DE BLAGHD">
      <NameTxt>EARNAN DE BLAGHD</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl a fhios agam an raibh an ceart ag an Árd-Chúirt nó nach raibh?  Agus is cuma do na Teachtaí annseo cad é an tuairim a bhí aca.  Do réir Airtiogail 66 san mBun-Reacht níl aon dul thar na cúirteanna ar cheist mar seo.  Tá an Árd-Chúirt tar éis breitheamhnas a thabhairt ar cheist.  B'fhéidir nár léigh siad agus <Col N="2331" /> nár thuig siad an Bun-Reacht mar a bhí ceapaithe againne.  Ach is ortha san gach dlighe a mhíniú, agus is ar an Rialtas gach dlighe a chur i bhféidhm mar a thuigeann na cúirteanna í.  Munab ionnan é agus an dlighe a bhí ceapaithe againn, níl aon rud againn ach athrú a dhéanamh air.  Nuair a bhímíd ag pleidhe Bille annseo ní bhíonn gach Teachta ar aon inntinn i d-taobh ciall na n-alt a bhíonn ann.  Is ar na cúirteanna atá an dualgas an chiall a mhíniú, agus caithfimíd géilleadh do thuairim na g-cúirt.  Ní raibh mé fhéin sásta le tuairim na mBreitheamhain sa chúis seo, ach ní abraim go ndearna siad rud ar bith nach rabh cead aca a dhéanamh.  Níl aon mhaith a bheith a cur síos ar cheist mar seo. Muna bhfuil an dlighe soiléir, nó muna bhfuil sé mar do shíleamar go mbéadh sé níl againn le déanamh ach amháin an dlighe a athrú.  An fiú an dlighe a athrú anois nuair a bheidh na cúirteanna nuadh ar bun laistigh de ráite? Tá coisde in a suidhe anois; tá Bille dá ullamhú, agus ní fada go mbeidh na cúirteanna nuadh ag obair.  Tig linn an Bille seo do chumadh i dtreó go mbeidh an Ghaedhilg ar aon dul agus ar aon chéim leis an Bhéarla ins na cúirteanna. Do réir mo thuairime níl 'sa cheist seo ach ceist an-shúrach.  Ni féidir le duine gach rud a dhéanamh i lá amháin.  Tá a lán rudaí go mí-shlachtmhar agus nílimíd ach a chur deis ortha anois.  Is mar sin le ceist na Gaedhilge ins na cúirteanna.  Socróchar an cheist sin sar i bhfad, agus níl aon mhaith a bheith ag déanamh clampair anois.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="PADHRAIC O MAILLE PADHRAIC O MAILLE">
      <NameTxt>PADHRAIC O MAILLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Sílim féin gur cóir dúinn níos mó suime a chur ins na rudaí a déantar ins na cúirteanna seo. Bhí lucht na gcúirt i gcoinne na Gaedhilge go dtí anois, agus ba chóir go gcuirfimís i niúil dóibh sin go mbeidh ortha Cothrom na Féinne a thabhairt do'n Ghaedhilig feasta.  Ba chóir go dtabharfaidhe cothrom do na Gaedhilgeóiri agus do na Béarlóirí comh maith ins na cúirteanna.  Ar feadh i bhfad bí an Ghaedhilg fé chois agus is mithid dúinn anois á rádh go mbeidh Cothrom na Féinne le fághail ag an Gaedhilgeoir in a thír féin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>To the superficial view of the ordinary man in the street, the Clerk of the Court who was <Col N="2332" /> quoted by Deputy Gavan Duffy appears to be right, and the Judges appear to have common sense on their side.  If they are to adjudicate on evidence submitted to them, and if the evidence is submitted in a language which they cannot understand, it would seem only reasonable that they should demand&mdash;in fact, claim&mdash;to be entitled to have the evidence put before them in a language which they do understand, above all when they are able to appeal to the Statute law and to show that, according to it, the official language of the Court is English, and there has been no Statute passed in this Parliament repealing that declaration.  But the superficial view and the first-sight view are not always the sound views of a difficult and complex matter especially.  To read together the 4th Article of the Constitution and the 73rd Article of the Constitution will show that there is a great deal to be said on the other side.  True, Article 73 of the Constitution declares that the Statute laws hitherto prevailing as the law of the land shall continue to be so until specifically repealed.  But the clause was quoted which was very apt and very relevant, &ldquo;unless in so far as they are inconsistent with the Constitution.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Article 4 of the Constitution is the Article bearing upon the matter.  It says that the Irish language shall be the national language of the Saorstát.  I would direct the special attention of Deputies to the formula which follows: &ldquo;And the English language shall be equally recognised as an official language.&rdquo; If there is any meaning in the words &ldquo;English is an official language equally with the Irish language,&rdquo; it makes the Irish language the standard. That Irish is the national language, as contemplated in that article of the Constitution, does not mean, therefore, that it is to be the speech of the market-place and the speech of the ordinary populace, while English is to be the language of the cultured section, the upper classes. That is not a legitimate interpretation, in view of the further statement that English is equally the official language with Irish.  Now, it seems to me&mdash;in fact, I should not use such guarded language at all as &ldquo;it seems to me,&rdquo; because I am thoroughly convinced&mdash;that all the efforts of the Gaelic League and <Col N="2333" /> of our Irish colleges and our compulsory Irish policies in the Universities, will be rendered futile, absolutely futile, and be shorn of all results in future generations, if we are dispassionate and unconcerned in the question as it now shapes itself. Everyone here knows that there was a period after the Norman conquest of England when the language of law courts, the language of the Bishops and the language of the higher schools was Norman-French, and the Anglo-Saxon was left for the swineherd and the agricultural labourer.  It was because of the patriotic efforts of the Anglo-Saxon monk who wrote the history of his people in the Anglo-Saxon tongue in verse, and had it committed to memory by the children, that the Anglo-Saxon language at all survived.  Had it not been for a very important happening on the Continent of Europe, by which the Norman Dukes that reigned in England as Kings were deprived of their territories in France, there is not a question but that the Norman-French language would have utterly suppressed in time the native speech.  It took from about 1066 to 1399 or thereabouts&mdash;that is, three and a quarter centuries&mdash;for the vital forces of the Anglo-Saxon speech to reconquer its earlier position; but it was a new speech, it was a new language.  The impress of the other had left a permanent mark upon it.  Now, anyone who brought his case before the courts was allowed to put his legal document in the two languages. As you know&mdash;it is rather pedantic, perhaps, to enlarge upon it&mdash;that is the origin of the double phrase such as &ldquo;hue and cry,&rdquo; and statements were made in the courts of law in such wise that the judge could understand, and the man indicted and the witnesses could understand. The Anglo-Saxon was to be for the people, and the Norman-French for the higher classes.  Something of the same thing will happen here, and we cannot count upon the intervention of Divine Providence in the form of some Continental upheaval to come to the rescue.  There might be some such things brought to bear, but that is purely conjectural. During the transition stage, when there are so many of us like myself who find it easier when he has anything to say to express himself in English, and who finds it easier to understand another when he speaks English, it is during the lifetime of those people, only reasonable <Col N="2334" /> that they should have the evidence, with which they are to deal, submitted to them in English.  The method of the procedure by which thy get this convenience provided for them is all-important.</P>
    <P>If they are to be allowed to declare, as in the case of the court, that in addition to the affidavit sworn in the national language of the people the litigants must be at the expense and trouble of swearing a second affidavit in the English language, whether that is to bear the additional stamp or not does not greatly matter, but if that is to be a decision which every litigant who chooses to use the national language must be bound by, then unquestionably the necessary result of it will be that the national language will not be employed in the law courts of the people, and if it will not be employed in the law courts of the people there is no reason why it should be employed in the higher walks of life at all, and accordingly it will come back to the position it was in some generations ago.  It will have the brand upon it of belonging only to the poor, and to those who have no social status, and only to those who are of no account in the eyes of those who speak English. We have before us a striking illustration in the case of Belgium.  Until the war broke out in 1914 you had a conflict there between French, with its social status, and Flemish without it. You had the one with the cachet of society and wealth and culture, and the other merely the language of the ploughman.  A movement in favour of Flemish as the national language had been gathering strength, and the matter was coming to an issue but for the intervention of the war.  Now that there is peace the question is being debated again.  A young University had just been founded before the war in which Flemish was all in all.  Now I suggest to you that what is happening in other countries provides us with an illuminative experience here.  If we are going, I say, to allow insistence upon the use of English in certain departments of public life, then undoubtedly you have got the thin end of the wedge.  You have begun a movement, a fissiparous movement, by which gradually step by step the Irish language will be back again as the language of the helot and the slave.  It seems to me that this is the <Col N="2335" /> moment, and that the battleground has been provided unless the proper interpretation is given to Article 4, which makes Irish the language in all the fulness and significance of the words &ldquo;National language,&rdquo; and permits only English as an official language equally with Irish; unless the proper interpretation of the spirit of the Irish nation is given to these words the Irish language is a lost cause.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. -" RHead="DEPORTATIONS FROM ENGLAND">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - DEPORTATIONS FROM ENGLAND.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The discussion that has just taken place, and the discussion earlier in the afternoon on another question&mdash;a question which I want to deal with&mdash;strike me as being part of a desire existing among members of the Dáil to re-assert the position won by the men who made the Treaty, and to prevent as far as possible by, perhaps, a little inadvertence or slackness that position being given away.  It is with that in my mind that I want to raise the question of which I gave notice earlier in the day respecting the 110 persons who appear to have been taken in charge by the Government here from the hands of the British authorities.  In reply to a question that I submitted to the President he told us that there were 110 persons interned from the hands of the British Government, and all of whom are presumed to be citizens of the Saorstát, and he also told us that the Restoration of Order (Ireland) Act, 1920, and the Regulations made thereunder are, so far as the territory of Saorstát Eireann is concerned, spent and of no legal force and effect.  That is important, and I would suggest directing the attention of the President to the First Schedule of the Criminal Malicious Injuries Bill, which says we are proposing to repeal Clause 1, sub-section 3 of Section 1 of the Restoration of Order (Ireland) Act, 1920. Deputy Fitzgibbon will be interested in the proposal to repeal portion of an Act which is spent and is of no legal force or effect.  It is important to know that the men and women who have been deported from England and have been taken in charge by Free State officers are not held under any regulations made under the Restoration of Order in Ireland Act, so that what we have to presume is that not only are these men and women citizens <Col N="2336" /> of the Saorstát, and not citizens of Great Britain, but that they were handed over by the British Government to the charge of the Saorstát for offences against the Saorstát presumably committed in Great Britain.  My primary concern is not with the question of the liberty of the subject in England; it is not with the question of the right of the British authorities to deport any person by any manner or means from that country.  That is not my intention in raising this matter at the moment, whatever my thoughts on that subject may be, but I want to draw special attention to the manner in which this action has been conducted.  The British Minister has told his people that our Government asked him to put in motion the regulations of the Restoration of Order in Ireland Act, in order that these men might be interned.  In response to that request from our Government to put into force these particular regulations to deport citizens of Saorstát Eireann from England and Scotland to Ireland, the British Minister issued orders for the deportation of these people.  There was no question of extradition; there was no question of obtaining the consent of the Courts.  The proposal was from our Government, in the language of the Minister for Home Affairs of Britain, that these citizens of Saorstát Eireann&mdash;presumably citizens of Saorstát Eireann, according to the President's reply to my question&mdash;should be deported and placed in internment camps or in prison at the charge of the Free State Government.  Now so far as that goes we can understand the position. They were citizens of the Saorstát, and at the request of the Government of the Saorstát these men were deported upon an order under an Act which is no longer in existence in Ireland, but which, they were advised, was still operative in England.  But the order that was issued under this Act gives, or presumes that the power over the person of those citizens of the Saorstát while interned in an Irish prison remains under the control of a British Minister: &ldquo;I hereby order that the said... shall be interned in the Irish Free State in such place as the Irish Free State Government may determine, and shall be subject to all the rules and conditions applicable to persons there interned, and <Col N="2337" /> shall remain there until further orders. If I am satisfied by the report of the Advisory Committee that this Order may be revoked or varied I will revoke or vary this Order by a further Order.  Failing such revocation or variation this Order shall remain in force.&rdquo;  Now, these are citizens of the Saorstát; they are arrested in England and Scotland; they are, shall I say, dumped into Ireland, and taken prisoners by our Government, presumably on the authorisation which has been granted by the Resolutions of the Dáil. But, having these citizens under our charge, the British Secretary of State says:&mdash;&ldquo;I will control them; I can order their release; I can insist that they shall be brought over to England to appear before an Advisory Committee, and can order their release.&rdquo;  But, he says more than that.  He says that in his opinion the Government had control over the interned men.  He further says that he was endeavouring to show that they had followed the strictly legal and regular course and kept control of those men in every essential point.  Further, he maintains that these undertakings, undertakings as between the Free State Government and the British Government, showed that they, the British Government, had complete control over the possession of the internees.  The terms upon which these men were handed over included an express pledge by the Free State Government that they would hold these men harmless, keep them safe, and return them if the Advisory Committee so directed.  Now, I maintain that that is an assumption of authority over the affairs of the Saorstát which is not justified by the position that the Saorstát occupies in relation to England.  It is an assumption of authority by British Ministers over the citizens of the Saorstát, while in the charge of the Saorstát, and in the territory of the Saorstát.  If, perchance, the Minister was not well advised in saying that these were citizens of the Saorstát, but were British citizens handed over at the instigation of the Government of the Saorstát by the British Government, then we are in the position of being jailers of British citizens for the British Government. We are going to keep control of these persons while in the territory of the Saorstát, but still under the direction of the British Government.  I submit that this particular process is only explainable and understandable on the <Col N="2338" /> assumption that no greater change in the relations between the two countries has taken place than a devolution of authority, subject to the suzerainty of the British Government.  All the arguments submitted in defence of the British Government's action have running through them the thought that &ldquo;we have given the Free State authority, but we still retain supreme control; we still retain the power, the right to do things in relation to persons in the territory of the Free State, British citizens or Irish citizens.&rdquo; The order, of course, under which these people were interned is one which says that the Secretary of State shall have power to intern in any part of the British isles.  They have acted under that authority, and having interned in Ireland, they still assert before their own constituents that they have control over them; they still assert, when they set up an Advisory Committee consisting of three Judges, that the Free State must hand over these prisoners to that Advisory Committee for inquiry, and on the advise of that Committee must release them.  Now, that is quite justifiable on the assumption that Britain does hold the suzerainty, that the British Government is the overriding authority over the proceedings of this Government, but only on that assumption.  We know that in Ireland as well as in England there are two views held in respect of the Treaty.  We have the one side in England maintaining that everything was given away to Irish demands by England and that Ireland was guaranteed virtual independence.  The apologists for the Treaty in England, who were trying to convince their supporters that it was something they could ratify and approve of, rather belittled the amount of the freedom and independence that was involved in the Free State by the Treaty. We have their counterpart in Ireland, but we must bear in mind in this connection that the British Government at present is composed of those people who would like to belittle the amount of the authority that has been won by the aid of the Treaty.  We know, too, that it is not what people say so much as acts and proceedings that form the basis upon which jurists will at a later day expound the meaning of certain Acts and Constitutions. Now, if the Treaty is, as is obvious from what I have said respecting the two views in relation to the <Col N="2339" /> powers conferred by the Treaty&mdash;if that Treaty is susceptible of different interpretation, then we must be more and more careful to insist upon every possible occasion that the widest interpretation of these powers shall be maintained by our Government, by Oireachtas and by the people here; but in this Act and this procedure it seems to me that we have allowed the interpretation&mdash;the mildest possible interpretation&mdash;to be supported in the act of the British Minister in deporting these men under these conditions and these orders, and maintaining the right to control these men while in the charge of the Irish Government.</P>
      <P>My purpose in raising this matter in this way, is not to discuss the question of the rights or the wrongs of the arrests, it is not to discuss the question of the freedom or the liberty of British subjects or Irish citizens in England, it is to give the Minister here an opportunity to re-assert the strength of the Irish position in relation to England, and to deny what I maintain is implied in the conduct of the British Ministers in regard to these proceedings.  Every act of theirs in respect to these internments&mdash;the Order that was presented to the prisoners, the offer that they may appear before an Advisory Court which is an offer made to prisoners in charge of Saorstát Eireann, in prisons and camps associated with other prisoners who have not the same rights, the power to appear in England before an Advisory Committee at the request of these prisoners&mdash;is an assurance that the British Ministers have given to the British House of Commons that they still have control of the bodies of those prisoners, and that I say is only consistent with the interpretation of the Treaty that leaves Britain in supreme authority over the Government of Ireland. It is not consistent with the interpretation of the Treaty which involves virtual independence.  It is not consonant with the interpretation of the Treaty, which gives to Ireland the same right and power over its internal affairs as Canada has, and, I believe, it is the duty of the Dáil, and of the Ministry, to courteously but firmly insist that the language of this Order, the language of the defence they are making for their own conduct, cannot be supported by the Irish Minister, and conflicts with the conception of Ireland's status that we will and must maintain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2340" />
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the basis upon which Deputy Johnson has put his case, as far as I can judge, is the right issue, and the gravest issue raised in these detentions.  I do not propose, any more than he did, to deal with the question of the arrests themselves at all. People who have been in England conspiring against the peace and good conduct of this State are not necessarily deserving of a great deal of sympathy from us although we would still agree that they were entitled to at least a fair trial and to justice.  I imagine one is not entirely ignorant of the state of affairs upon the other side.  We had an organisation that did exist before the Treaty was signed, and we do know the plans that were made, and would have been carried out, if the Treaty had not been signed, and we know that a great part of the organisation still exists upon the other side, and that it can be exceedingly mischievous not only to the people upon the other side, but also to us here and to the State.  Therefore, I assume it is perfectly reasonable that a large number of those persons who have been arrested should have been arrested.  On the other hand, I put it, there was a procedure that should have been adopted in these cases that was not adopted.  The procedure that has been undertaken by the Executive Council has, in my judgement, and I put it very simply and sincerely and fairly to the Ministry, impeached the very meaning of our Constitution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the first place, I think we are entitled to learn at whose instance these arrests were made.  It was stated by the English Home Secretary, in definite terms, that they were made at the request of this Government.  That was in the first debate yesterday week, but in his language yesterday the contrary would seem to be implied.  Surely it is only fair that one should know exactly and precisely&mdash;these arrests having taken place&mdash;at whose instance they did take place; whether the Government on this side desired that they should take place and desired that the English Government should arrest these people, or whether it was proposed from the other side to us that these arrests should be made, and that these persons should be kept in detention here under the Restoration of Order (Ireland) Act.  If the instance were ours, it means perfectly clearly that, not only do we recognise <Col N="2341" /> the Restoration of Order (Ireland) Act as of statutory effect&mdash;which is recognised, as Deputy Johnson has pointed out, in the Schedule of the Criminal and Malicious Injuries Bill now before the Dáil&mdash;but we go further, we avail of this Act.  We originate a prosecution under an Act originally devised against the interests of this country.  I think that is a very grave decision to have taken, if that was the procedure.  But if, on the other hand, the instance lay with the English Government and that the Free State Government acted as their agents in the matter, then I think we have a right to know that too; because then it would appear that they arrested certain persons for wrongful acts done in English territory, and, having so arrested these persons, turned to this Government and made Ireland a jail for their detention. But, in any case, I think it is right that we should know what is exactly the upshot of the act that has taken place. We have three different objections, under each of which heads the Constitution has, in my judgement, been impeached. They are quite clearly in the words of the English Home Secretary.  He said, &ldquo;The Irish Free State had undertaken that if any other proceedings were desired by them against the deportees they were only to be taken after consultation with, and with the consent of, the British Government.&rdquo;  In other words, it means that the people who are held in this country in detention by the Irish Government, which is a co-equal Government with any other Government in the British Commonwealth, that the Irish Government cannot proceed against any of these prisoners without first having to seek the consent of some other Government.  That is a recognition of the superiority of that Government, at least in that specific matter&mdash; a superiority in jurisdiction, in any case. The English Home Secretary also stated that he undertook that the internees should have every facility for a personal hearing before the Advisory Committee, and that if that Committee decided that any person should not have been deported he should be released.  That is the second objection, which allows an English Home Secretary to appoint some kind of Tribunal, under his own hand, to sit in England to try prisoners held by this Government, and if that Tribunal, sitting in England, is appealed to over the <Col N="2342" /> heads of the Irish Government, acting as a jailer in this case, such prisoner shall have freedom to proceed to England to have his or her case heard, and if the Tribunal there decides that such prisoner shall be liberated such prisoner shall be liberated, the Irish Government acting as jailers notwithstanding.  An incidental trouble that arose out of this is that one of the benefits of the Treaty &mdash;not one of the main considerations of the Treaty, but one of the substantial set of benefits obtained under it&mdash;has been that Irish affairs have, by this action, been taken away from discussion in the English House of Commons. We have now seen that Irish affairs in the most acute form&mdash;a lively domestic Irish issue&mdash;has been made the subject of debate in the English House of Commons, and I think a great deal of harm has been done by the action that has led to such debate.  In all this the case I am putting forward is not that these persons should not have been arrested. Of that I know nothing.  I think it extremely likely that the majority of them should have been arrested.  But in seeing that they were arrested a procedure has been adopted that has put this country in an unfortunate position as regards a country with which it has made an international Treaty, the foundation of that Treaty being that the two countries are in all matters on absolute terms of equality.  Those terms announced by the English Home Secretary are not the terms of equality.  I suggest that it is not difficult to discover what might have been done in the circumstances if we were to turn to the like case of Canada. If certain persons in England of Canadian birth or otherwise were conspiring against the safety and peace of Canada, and if either of the two Governments, the Canadian Government or the English Government, decided to proceed against such persons, what would be the procedure adopted?  I think there is no doubt what the procedure would be. The procedure in that case would be that the English Government, at its own instance, no matter where it got its information, would arrest such persons, and having arrested such person under its own laws would be under the necessity of trying them for having been guilty of acts against specific laws in that country against a friendly and associate Power.  It would have laid upon itself <Col N="2343" /> the responsibility of such imprisonment or other penalty that the Courts may award.  I do not imagine that Canada would for one moment permit a situation such as has arisen within these past ten days.  I do not imagine that Canada would for one moment permit Canadians to be arrested in England and sent to Canada, with a right of appeal from Canada to an Advisory Committee in England.  By a curious irony of chance, in one of the papers this morning&mdash;the &ldquo;Daily Independent&rdquo;&mdash;almost in adjacent columns we had two specific items of news.  In one case there was a report of a debate in the House of Commons yesterday upon the constitutional position as between Ireland and England in respect of these deportations, and in an adjoining column there was the constitutional position of Canada's independent signing of a Treaty.  Canada in one column had made a declaration of increased separation, of stronger independence, and in the adjoining column an other sister nation of the Commonwealth had receded from the position which had been won for it under the Treaty, and which had been laid upon the foundation of the Constitution.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>There were two statements made by the last speaker&mdash; one that we had given away our sovreignty by saying that we would not prosecute any of the persons that we had arrested at Dun Laoghaire; the other was that we had given permission for these persons to go before the Advisory Committee. In his excitement the Deputy forgot to mention a third one, but if it has anything like the punch of the other two I am sure we have not lost much in not hearing it.  We have been told that we have lost our sovereignty, that we have given away everything, I suppose, the Deputy has won for us either in the Constitution or the &ldquo;London Times,&rdquo; and that as a matter of fact we have bartered away our whole position as a nation.  The facts of the case are, there were certain citizens of ours&mdash;certain people about whose citizenship I am in some doubt, although I am presuming that they are citizens of the Saorstát&mdash; certain citizens who, I believe, in their own minds are in some doubt as to their citizenship or as to the country to which they belong, and those people got busy in England in a conspiracy to bring down <Col N="2344" /> this State.  We asked for those prisoners. We got those prisoners, and we had to give certain undertakings in respect of getting them which the people who gave them to us were entitled to ask for.  One was that we would not prosecute them without an agreement.  An agreement usually takes place between parties to an agreement.  The parties to an agreement in this case are equal.  An agreement in order to be an agreement must be subscribed to by both parties. We have got to come to an agreement if we are going to prosecute them.  They were not our prisoners.  We had to ask other people to get them for us.  They got them for us.  We have them; we have given an undertaking, and we are going to keep our agreement with regard to them.  We undertook also to allow them to go before this Advisory Committee. It does not require very much exercise of the imagination to know, why they ask for such a condition as that.  It is possible that some of these people may be English citizens; they may claim British citizenship.  They are certainly not a credit to Irish citizenship if they are Irish citizens, and they may possibly have another nationality either by marriage or assent or by anything else of that sort.  If they be such they are entitled to say that they are not citizens of the Saorstát and the British Government is entitled to claim for them privileges which we could deny them if they were citizens of ours.  That undertaking we have given&mdash;that they will go before the Advisory Committee.  As far as any liability the British Government has to any person resident within its shores to protect them and to give them all the facilities of their courts and of their Constitution, they have retained that.  They were entitled to do it, and we admitted their right to claim such and we gave it to them.  These people have been arrested in England and sent here at the request of the Irish Government. It is our duty to protect this State. We are merely instruments of the people of this country and instruments of this Dáil.  We would have failed in our duty if, knowing the work these people were engaged in, knowing the conspiracy of which they are alleged to be component parts and of which we are fairly satisfied from the evidence we have that they are conspirators, we would have failed in our duty if we did not get them.  In <Col N="2345" /> getting them we had to give undertakings which I am perfectly satisfied are just, fair, and equitable, and which the British Government would have been in duty bound to ask for.  If we have given more than we were entitled to give then our judgement is exceedingly bad and we will have to call in some of the elders of the nation in the future to advise us whenever we have matters of importance like this to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think that the President has disposed of the weight of the case that has been made against the Executive Council with reference to these arrests in England and internments in Ireland.  The President says that it is presumed that these people are citizens of the Saorstát and he states quite definitely and specifically that the Regulations for the Restoration of Order in Ireland are spent and have no effect in Ireland.  Now against the President are all the declarations not only of the British or the English Home Secretary but of the English Attorney-General.  The President says that it is quite right and proper and just and decent to treat an Irish citizen who happens to have been over in England and happens to have been arrested there differently from an Irish citizen who happens to be arrested in Ireland.  He does it on the ground that the British Government and the Irish Government are Governments of equal authority and equal jurisdiction. Of course he knows perfectly well that that is not the position and that it has not been the position that has been taken up by the English authorities. He knows perfectly well that the only shadow of legality the English Government had for deporting, not for arresting, these persons out of England is the regulations for the Restoration of Order in Ireland.  He says it is quite right and just and proper that an Irish Government or the Government of Saorstát Eireann should make an agreement with the Government of England that Irish citizens in England should go, if they so desire, before an Advisory Committee appointed by the English Home Secretary and there show reason why they should not be interned in Ireland within the Saorstát.  I claim that these Irish citizens, if they are Irish citizens, have no more right or duty to recognise the <Col N="2346" /> English Home Secretary's Advisory Committee than the late President Arthur Griffith had when he refused to recognise or to answer any questions put to him by a similar Committee&mdash;none at all.  I will admit that this whole thing circulates round the question of citizenship.  The President says they may claim British citizenship.  He knows there is no such thing as British citizenship, but that there is British subjectory.  There is such a thing as citizenship of the Saorstát, but the citizenship of the Saorstát carries with it what is technically known as British subjectory, and he and I and the rest of us are all British subjects, but if we are our Saorstát citizenship, I claim, does not entitle any British Secretary of State, Home Secretary, or anybody else to claim or to exercise control over the custody of our persons in the Saorstát. That is the position that has been put up by the British Home Secretary and Attorney-General.  The Executive Council is putting these people, if they are citizens of the Saorstát, in a superior position to other citizens of the Saorstát. As the Dáil knows the general run of citizens in the Saorstát, if they have taken any part, or are suspected of having taken any part in activities against the Government and the Saorstát, come within certain Regulations which have been approved by this Dáil.  Apart altogether from one's opinion of these Regulations we know that the Regulations expose such citizens to certain penalties, to certain procedure before certain Courts or Military Committees or Courtsmartial. But the Executive Council has gone and assured the English Attorney-General that in the case of these presumed citizens, who happen to be three or six or twelve months, or maybe only a week or two, resident in England, there was no possibility of the internees being tried by Courtmartial in Ireland.  If I am suspected of taking part in activities against the Saorstát, and am arrested in Dublin I may be subject to the death penalty, but if I cross over to Liverpool or London, and Scotland Yard remembers that I was on its black list twelve months or two or three years ago, and it hands me over to the military forces of the Saorstát, then I am not to be subject to the Regulations which have been approved by this Dáil.  The English <Col N="2347" /> Attorney-General says that no proceedings will be instituted against any of the deportees without the consent of the Home Secretary, and that when the consent is given a prisoner will be placed in exactly the same position, and dealt with in exactly the same way as if he had not been deported.  In other words he will be dealt with by the ordinary common law of England, in open court, where he will be able to bring witnesses and challenge the evidence of those who prosecute him.  If the offence is one triable in England, but not in Ireland, merely because he happens to have been asked for, in England, he is going to get treatment which is not being given, and which it has been decided definitely by this Dáil, at the request of the Executive Council, is not to be given to an Irish citizen.  The President says that that is just and fair, and reasonable.  Several speakers in the English House of Commons last night took it as settled, and not only took it as settled, but accepted the full assurance of the British Ministers that in every particular these British Ministers had full and complete control, as one of them said, over the internees.  There cannot be such a thing as complete control by the Saorstát and complete control by the British Government.  One or other of the two Governments has complete control. If the British Government, as it claims, has complete control over the persons of these people while they are interned here then the Saorstát Government has not complete control over them.  But a remarkable thing comes out in the course of the debate in England. The English Attorney-General said that the Free State Government asked not only for the arrest and detention of these people, but asked that their internment should be in Ireland, and it was in accordance with that request that the English authorities put into force 14B of the Restoration of Order in Ireland Regulations.  They were asked by the Free State Government to hand over these people because the only place where they would be safe would be in a prison in Ireland.  I turn to the Act under which these Regulations were made in England and I find that it is the Restoration and Maintenance of Order (Ireland) Act, 1920.  I <Col N="2348" /> find that the only legal authority that the English have for handing over these people to the Free State, on the request of the Free State, was a Sub-section which authorised the conveyance and detention in any of His Majesty's prisons, in any part of the United Kingdom, of any person and so on.  &ldquo;In any part of the United Kingdom,&rdquo; and the Saorstát is not part of the United Kingdom!  The English Minister ran away from the question when it was put to him last night, but Irish Ministers are prepared to take anything. They can waive aside the Restoration of Order in Ireland Regulations and that Act and everything else. They can go to England and ask the British Government to hand them over certain people whom they presume to be citizens.  They do not give twopence whether they are citizens or not, and they did not even enquire whether they were citizens or not.  As a matter of fact if they had made enquiries they would have found that many of them&mdash;at least some of them&mdash;are not citizens of the Saorstát at all, and can make no claim to citizenship of the Saorstát.  None whatever. Now, the position to me seems to have been fairly well summed up by one of the speakers in the British House of Commons when he said that one of three things had happened&mdash;either these people had been taken up in England and interned in Ireland under servants of the English Government, or one of two other things.  The first, he said, was unlikely. It is most unlikely.  The second thing, he said, that might have happened would have been that the English Government might have an arrangement that servants of the Free State should be temporarily servants of the English Government.  It was on that, I think, the big blunder in policy has been made by the Executive Council of the Saorstát, that they have put themselves in the position that they seem to be, whether they will it or not, the servants of the English Government, acting within Ireland for that English Government. He said that that might be unlikely. The third was that they had been interned in Ireland under the custody and control of the Free State, and that they were under the control of the Free State.  But he was assured by the British Ministers that they were not under the control of the Free State, that they were <Col N="2349" /> under the control of the English Home Secretary and his Advisory Committee. To back up that the English Home Secretary turned round blandly and informed the gentleman that &ldquo;the power I have is to send people for internment in the British Isles.&rdquo;  And he sent them to Ireland.  Now, there used to be a fiction in the Black and Tan days that when an Irishman in England was arrested by English police he was not arrested at all. He was simply detained for examination and investigation until such time as a squad of Royal Irish Constabulary men came over and took him into custody. That fiction is being maintained and perpetuated by the Free State Government because its position is, that it has taken these citizens, or presumed citizens of the Free State into custody, has arrested them as soon as they were dumpted into Dun Laoghaire by a British warship It did not arrest them in England.  It arrested them inside Ireland, and although it arrested them inside Ireland, inside the Saorstát, it is going to give them advantages over other citizens of the Saorstát whom it arrests inside Ireland. The British Home Secretary said the British Government had control of the interned men.  He became aware of what was going on, and the Free State asked him to put in motion the Regulations for the Restoration of Order in Ireland, in order that these men might be interned and have their activities curtailed.  Now somebody is lying.  It may be that it is the British Home Secretary is lying, but there is a conflict there, and I am prepared to take the word of the President in his answer that the Free State did not ask that these people should be arrested and deported under the Restoration of Order in Ireland Act.  But the British Home Secretary said that he was asked in such terms.  The main charge, I think, has not been really met by the President, and it is this, that in certain of the acts, including this one of the Executive Council of the Saorstát, it is presumed that Ireland or the Saorstat is not a co-equal with Great Britain, and the evidence is in the action of Great Britain in this instance, that Great Britain, or the Government of Great Britain, which officially to us must be Great Britain, takes up that under one of its Acts it can dump into Ireland anyone whom it likes because <Col N="2350" /> that Act specifies that certain things can be done within the United Kingdom, and it regards these two islands as the United Kingdom.  That is not a position which this Dáil can take up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>This debate has gone on for a considerably longer time than half an hour.  I take it, it is meant to conclude now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>There were times in the course of this debate when I was inclined to wonder where exactly we were.  The geography was mixed and my bump of location disturbed.  While it is a fair and reasonable thing that we should carry our own burdens and our own responsibilities and answer for our own sins&mdash;if we should so far forget ourselves as to sin&mdash;it is just a little overmuch in times like these that we should be called to book here for the deeds, or the misdeeds, of British Ministers. What are we discussing?  Is it the grievances, real or imaginary, of those men against this Government, or their grievances, real or imaginary, against the British Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. O'CONNELL Mr. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>Neither one nor the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had quibbling about &ldquo;I wonder have we lost our sovereignty?&rdquo;  People do not seem to realise that there is a difference between things done as of right and things done by agreement.  None of us, and we know the position, lay awake at night wondering if we had lost our sovereignty, because we knew that we had not.  What is the position?  You had a country within a stone's throw of our shores&mdash;or at least a stone's throw for such a man as Finn MacCumhaill&mdash;used as a base, an arsenal, and an effective headquarters for a campaign against this State; not so much against the armed forces of this State as a brutal, cowardly campaign against the defenceless civilians who are citizens of this State.  And we were to take no action!  Afraid that we would lose our sovereignty, we were to take no action!  People spin webs.  Supposing it were France that was being used as a base, an arsenal and an effective headquarters for a campaign against the people of this country, and our relations with France were friendly, and if we approached the French Government and said:&mdash;&ldquo;You might see your way to <Col N="2351" /> arrest the people who are taking action of this kind against our State and our citizens,&rdquo; can you not conceive the French Government saying:&mdash;&ldquo;Yes, on terms?&rdquo;  The terms would be &ldquo;if we make a mistake, if it is put up to us that we have made a mistake, or have done wrong, we should be in a position to bring back any one of those persons for investigation.&rdquo; But, because the British say the same thing, because the British say, &ldquo;Yes, we are prepared to round up those men who are conducting this cowardly campaign against your people; we are prepared to send them across to you; but if the question is raised that a particular case needs investigation, you must agree, you should agree, and it is a reasonable thing to ask you to agree, that that person is sent back to have his case investigated here by the people who arrested him,&rdquo; it is different. We were told what would have been done if it were Canada, or under a Figgis administration here.  This exact position could not arise with regard to Canada, and, therefore, there is no use talking about it.  England, from its geographical position in relation to this country was an effective base and arsenal, and effective headquarters for a campaign against this country.  It was the nerve centre of the world-organisation these people are trying to bring into play against this State and against democracy in this State.  I am not going into the abstract question of the citizenship of these men or women, or any one of them.  It is a rather abstract and complicated question, because citizenship would depend a great deal upon whether a particular individual had what I might refer to as the <i>animus revertendi</i>, the intention of returning.  I do not know how many hail from here, and how many had the intention of returning. I know, however, of one man who had not the intention of returning, inasmuch as he sailed away with £7,000 out of public funds in his pocket.  Deputy Gavan Duffy, no doubt, knows him, too. It comes to this: Their offence was an offence against this State.  What fools we would be, conducting a fight for the very life and honour of this nation, not to accept the custody of those men and women.  It is as true to say in that matter that we were acting as servants of the British Government, as <Col N="2352" /> it is to say that in the rounding up and arresting of them the British Government were acting as servants of ours. Certain men got up here to-night, and I thought for a moment they were solicitors for the internees, and that this was the Board of Inquiry, or whatever it is, that is to be set up in England. They made an eloquent plea for them and an indictment of those who had arrested them.  What is that to us?  I never heard British Ministers or British members of Parliament as frequently quoted in this Dáil as to-night, and I hope I may never hear it again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope you never give occasion for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Now the man in opposition is irresponsible; he likes to get his wipe in.  People who have to answer for this fight&mdash;to answer to the Irish people for every day it goes on, and the cost of it in money&mdash;are not going into quibbling metaphysics as to citizenship or anything else.  Those men were planning war and were making war from a distance against our people here. We put it up to the British Government as to whether it would be possible for them to arrest those people and to send them over in custody.  They are over in custody here, and our watchword is&mdash;as I heard it before in another part of this country&mdash;&ldquo;What we have we hold.&rdquo; We will keep to the agreement we entered into as a condition of getting these men, and that is that if individuals amongst them want to go into the question with the British Government of the propriety or impropriety of their arrest, they can be brought over there, and that question can be thrashed out in the country where they were arrested.  My own candid opinion on this matter is that the Dáil has been kept long enough and over-long on this matter.  To us it is a very straight and simple matter.  Every person who levies war against this country, wherever he is living, wherever the scene of his offence, if we can get him into our custody we will hold him.  To get those people into our custody we made certain agreements, and we mean to stand by them.  None of us lost a wink of sleep as to whether it was or was not a derogation of sovereignty.  It was a thing that was not done of right, but as by agreement.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 7.5 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead=" -" RHead="DEPENDANTS' ALLOWANCES">
    <Title>[WRITTEN ANSWERS.] - DEPENDANTS' ALLOWANCES.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="TOMAS O CONAILL TOMAS O CONAILL">
      <NameTxt>TOMAS O CONAILL</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that no dependant's allowance has yet been paid to Mrs. P. Tighe, of Arm. Castlerea, in respect of her son, John Tighe, 24256, B. Company, 2nd Western Division, who joined the National Army on the 23rd July, 1922; that this soldier was the sole support of his invalid father, his mother and five children, and in consequence of the delay in this payment the family are in a very bad way; Mrs. Tighe herself has had to take up work in order to try and support the children, and would the Minister cause payment to be expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mrs. Tighe's claim is under local investigation, which is being expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence if he is aware that Mrs. Rattigan, Patrick Street, Athlone, has not received dependant's allowance in respect of her three sons, Captains Séan and Patrick Rattigan, stationed in Custume Barracks, Athlone, and Volunteer James Rattigan, who is attached to Moate Barracks.  Further to ask if payment will be speedily made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2293" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mrs. Rattigan was paid sums on the 6th January, 17th February, and 3rd and 15th March amounting to £29 in connection with a dependant's allowance in respect of her son Captain Séan Rattigan.</P>
      <P>No applications were received in respect of Patrick and James, but on the information contained in the question claims are being investigated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that no dependant's allowance has been paid to Mrs. M.J. Keyes in respect of her son, Volunteer Frank Keyes, who is stationed in Moate.  Further, will the Minister see that payment of the allowance is expedited, as this man was his mother's chief support.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mrs. Keyes was partially dependent on her son prior to his enlistment, but the extent of dependency established as a result of investigation did not amount to the minimum extent required by regulations, namely, 12/- per week before an allowance can be issued.  A soldier is expected to contribute at least 8/- per week to the support of his dependants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence whether he is aware that no dependant's allowance has been paid to Mrs. Reid, Bridge Street, Athlone, in respect of her son, Volunteer Hugh Reid, Custume Barracks, Athlone, who is serving in the National Army as a motor mechanic.  Further, if the Minister is aware that he is Mrs. Reid's chief support, and in view of this will he see that payment of allowance is expedited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mrs. Reid was partially dependent on her son prior to his enlistment, but the extent of the dependency established as a result of investigation did not amount to the minimum extent required by regulations, namely, 12/- per week before an allowance can be issued.  A soldier is expected to contribute at least 8/- per week to the support of his dependants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence if he is aware that Mrs. Ellen Bracken has not received dependant's allowance in respect of her son, Volunteer Matthew Bracken, who joined the army in May, 1922, and is <Col N="2294" /> now stationed in Fianna Camp, Ballyshannon, and who, previously to his joining the army, allowed his mother £3 per week, and also in respect of her son, Volunteer Peter Bracken, at present stationed in Mullingar, and to ask if the claim be expedited, as Mrs. Bracken is destitute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>No applications appear to have been received for the payment of dependant's allowance to Mrs. Bracken.  On the information conveyed in the question, her claim will be investigated as quickly as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="SEAN O LAIDHIN SEAN O LAIDHIN">
      <NameTxt>SEAN O LAIDHIN</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Defence if he is aware that Mrs. Mary Galvin, Brideswell Street, Athlone, was refused dependant's allowance in respect of her son, Volunteer Thomas Galvin, who is at present stationed in Longford Town, and who allowed his mother £1 per week prior to joining the Army, and further, if he is aware that Galvin would now be earning £3 10s. per week as a motor mechanic if he had not enlisted, and if the Minister will have the claim further investigated, with a view to favourable consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Mrs. Galvin was partially dependent on her son prior to his enlistment, but the extent of the dependency established, about 10s. per week, as a result of investigation did not amount to the minimum extent required by regulations, namely, 12s. per week, before an allowance can be issued. A soldier is expected to contribute at least 8s. per week from his pay to the support of his dependants.  There appears to be no ground for investigating the case again.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead=" - SIX" RHead="COUNTIES CUSTOMS FRONTIER">
    <Title>[WRITTEN ANSWERS.] - SIX COUNTIES CUSTOMS FRONTIER.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="AlexMcCabe" hpid="ALASDAIR MAC CABA ALASDAIR MAC CABA">
      <NameTxt>ALASDAIR MAC CABA</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance whether on the establishment of the Six Counties Custom Frontier it is the intention of the Government to change duties on goods of foreign manufacture; whether the rate will be similar to those collected under the British Fiscal system; whether discrimination will be made in favour of goods of British manufacture, and if so, what reciprocal arrangements, if any, <Col N="2295" /> are made on the British side as regards goods of Irish origin.</P>
      <P>Whether any accurate idea of the volume or fiscal possibilities of the foreign trade of the Free State can be had by allowing free dumping from a neighbouring country or territory.</P>
      <P>Whether he is aware of the fact that in return for a few small concessions in taxation certain Irish manufacturers are prepared to guarantee the employment of 100,000 additional hands within the coming twelve months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="MINISTER for FINANCE (The President) William T. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FINANCE (The President)</NameTxt>
      <P>In reply to the first part of the question, I would suggest that the Deputy should await the Budget proposals which will be submitted to the Dáil before the end of the present month.</P>
      <P>I am not quite clear as to the meaning of the second part of the question, but if the Deputy will let me have precise particulars of the information that he desires I will endeavour to meet his wishes.</P>
      <P>I am not aware of the concessions to which the Deputy refers in the third part of his question, but he will have an opportunity of putting them before the Dáil in the course of the debates on the Finance Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead=" - STATUS" RHead="OF THE IRISH LANGUAGE">
    <Title>[WRITTEN ANSWERS.] - STATUS OF THE IRISH LANGUAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to ask that the Agenda may be suspended in order to enable the Dáil to discuss the extraordinary action of the Court of Appeal in repudiating the status expressly given to the Irish language in the Constitution of Saorstát Eireann, by virtue of which that Court exists.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Will twelve Deputies support that request?</P>
      <P>Twelve Deputies having risen in their places.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The question will be discussed at seven o'clock if we are sitting until 8.30.  If it is proposed to adjourn earlier, some other arrangements will have to be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>In order to suit the convenience of Deputies, I am satisfied if the discussion is taken at 5 o'clock, on the understanding that we adjourn at 6 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2296" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Will that be satisfactory to the Deputy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, that will suit me.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="WA" LHead=" -" RHead="DEPORTATIONS FROM ENGLAND">
    <Title>[WRITTEN ANSWERS.] - DEPORTATIONS FROM ENGLAND.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOMAS JOHNSON Mr. THOMAS JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOMAS JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to raise a question, on the adjournment, as to the position of the Free State Government in regard to deportations from England.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>