<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Fri" Date="3" Month="Jul" Year="1925" Vol="12" No="19" DateIrish="Dé hAoine, 3 Iúil 1925" DateEnglish="Friday, 3 July 1925" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="2041">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="2041" /> Do chuaidh An Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar a 12 a clog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT" RHead="No. 1) BILL, 1925&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - CONSTITUTION (AMENDMENT No. 1) BILL, 1925&mdash;FROM THE SEANAD.</Title>
    <P>Amendment 1. &mdash; The following words inserted at the end of the title:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;and making an alteration in the vacancies which the sixteenth and subsequently elected members shall be deemed to have filled at each triennial election.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Amendment 2.&mdash;Before Section 3 a new section inserted as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The Constitution shall be and is hereby amended by the deletion at the end of Article 34 of the words &lsquo;Provided that the sixteenth member shall be deemed to have filled the vacancy first created in order of time and so on&rsquo; and the substitution therefor of the words, &lsquo;Provided that the sixteenth member shall be deemed to have filled the vacancy created by the death or withdrawal of the Senator, or one of the Senators, the unexpired period of whose term of office was greatest at the time of the election and so on.&rsquo;&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins) Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for JUSTICE (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>The effect of these amendments, inserted in the Seanad, is to remove the anomaly which lies in the fact that, at present, under the Constitution, the person elected sixteenth may secure the place of a Senator whose term of office is, say, three years and the person elected seventeenth may secure the place of a Senator having a term of six years or possibly <Col N="2042" /> nine years.  I asked the Seanad to disagree with this amendment, not because it is in itself unsound&mdash;it is, as a matter of fact, quite a sound and desirable amendment&mdash;but because I thought it was outside the scope of the main purpose of the Bill, which, after all, was introduced to deal with the question of the pending elections to the Seanad and purposes directly connected with that.  This matter is not so directly connected with that purpose. It is kindred matter, no doubt, and it aims at removing an undoubted anomaly&mdash;that of a person elected number sixteenth, possibly getting a short term of office&mdash;say, a term of three years&mdash;whereas persons elected lower down might secure a term of office of six years or nine years.  It will be noticed that the amendment involved a change in the Long Title of the Bill, as a consequential amendment, because it lay somewhat outside the scope of the Bill as drafted and as sent to the Seanad.  Although I feel that if this amendment had been proposed when the Bill was before the Dáil, I would possibly have objected to it on the ground that it was undesirable in a Bill brought in to deal with a specific point and embodying a specific amendment to the Constitution to introduce other matter, I think that the point is, perhaps, not worth differing with the other House about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>We will take Amendment 2 first and Amendment 1, which is the consequential amendment, afterwards.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose that the Dáil agree with Seanad in Amendment No. 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has given the reasons why he asked the Seanad not to agree with this amendment. I think those reasons were sound and conclusive.  When the Bill was brought forward, expression was given to the view that a Constitutional amendment over a small matter was undesirable and unnecessary and that, without question, there would, within the next two or three years, require to be brought forward for consideration. several other amendments to the Constitution. <Col N="2043" /> It was urged that this matter ought to be treated as part of a general amendment of the Constitution. I think the Minister's views as to the undesirability of making a second amendment of a minor kind in the Constitution, which amendment is not necessary, should be adhered to. If such an amendment as is now proposed is required, and is not urgent&mdash; as it obviously is not&mdash;it ought not to be introduced into this Constitutional Amendment Bill, which is only to deal with an emergency created through the necessity for electing members to the Seanad.  I think that the House would be well advised to hold by the position which the Minister himself stated.  I do not think the Seanad could regard this action as manifesting a desire for conflict.  I think that we should stand by the expression of opinion that amendments to the Constitution should be very carefully considered before they are entered upon. This amendment has not been carefully considered.  It has come down to us from the Seanad and is being treated, obviously and necessarily in the circumstances, as a minor amendment. Whether it is a minor amendment or not, I cannot say.  I doubt whether many members of the Dáil have given the matter that amount of consideration which any amendment of the Constitution, however trifling, requires.  I would urge the Minister to stand by his decision and I suggest that we should notify the Seanad that, in the circumstances, we think that such an amendment, however desirable it may be, should not be passed without the fullest consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nothing obscure about the amendment, and it is scarcely right to say that it has not been carefully considered.  I have no doubt it was very carefully considered by those who urged its acceptance in the Seanad and, once it appeared as an amendment, it was carefully considered by me, with the assistance of the Law Advisers of the Government. As I say, the amendment in itself is sound and desirable.  The only objection <Col N="2044" /> I made to it in the Seanad was that while cognate and kindred to the subject-matter of the Bill, it lay just outside the scope and purpose of the Bill, as is shown by the fact that its acceptance involved an amendment in the Long Title.</P>
      <P>It is undoubtedly an anomaly, probably not contemplated by those who drafted and endorsed the Constitution, that a Senator elected sixteenth in order would possibly fill a casual vacancy created by the death or resignation of a man who had only a three-years' period, whereas someone coming next to him, seventeenth or eighteenth on the list, might get the casual vacancy of a man who had a much longer tenure in the Seanad, a tenure running possibly to nine years.  That is, of course&mdash;there is nothing obscure about it&mdash;wrong and unsound, and this amendment aims at changing that. Therefore, it is quite desirable in itself. The only objection that could be urged to it is that it is a little beside the main objects of the Bill.  I asked the Seanad to take that view, and by a very substantial majority they took the other view.  I have the feeling now, seeing that nothing can be urged against the amendment itself and seeing that a great deal can be urged in its favour&mdash; in its favour as far as its intrinsic soundness and wisdom goes&mdash;that it would be perhaps straining things for the Dáil to send a Message back to the Seanad disagreeing with the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not discussing the merits of the Bill, but we are liable to get into the position that amendments to the Constitution can be treated as ordinary legislation and in a rather casual fashion, without having the very careful united consideration, perhaps of the two Houses, even preliminary to introduction.  The casual passing of amendments to the Constitution, even though their desirability may be obvious, is a very undesirable procedure.  Either the Constitution is the most important document that we have which guides and determines the limits of our legislative activity or it is a matter of trifling importance.  If it is, as we all admit, the supreme document, <Col N="2045" /> governing our legislative activities, it should only be altered after microscopic examination and after all sections of the House had, perhaps, considered it over a table.  I do not know what the idea of the people who drew up this particular form may have been, but we have a right to assume that during a sitting of several months they examined very closely and carefully all the phrases and their consequences. There are, I think, other anomalies which would be generally admitted equally with this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but scarcely equally cognate to the Bill as this is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>But it is not essential. The Minister has said, and the House has agreed with him, that the original Bill was designed and was necessary to meet a particular emergency. It is not contended that this amendment is designed to meet a particular emergency and is actually necessary.  Therefore, I say we ought not introduce it into a Bill which only deals with an absolutely necessary thing.  I say it is leading to a cheapening, in the minds of Deputies, of the Constitution, and will lead to our thinking that any constitutional amendment might be treated in a similarly light and casual fashion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>The Constitution is fundamental law.  Any tampering with it or alteration of it must, therefore, be looked upon with considerable suspicion, or, to put it positively, any amendment must be the result of a great deal of careful consideration. It is declared as one of the Articles of the Constitution that alterations in it are to be made after the fashion of ordinary law; that is to say, that a Bill for the express purpose of altering the Constitution must be introduced in one of the Houses, get its First Reading, its Second Reading, and go through its different stages.  I think that is the regular procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do share the view of Deputy Johnson that whether an amendment which arises casually is a valuable amendment or is not is comparatively irrelevant <Col N="2046" /> where the consideration is the paramount importance of keeping the Constitution a sacred instrument.  I quite agree with the Minister for Justice that that is a desirable and valuable amendment, but let us consider in what way it has come before us.  It has come before us as an amendment to a Bill that was properly initiated in one of the Houses, had its First and Second Reading, went through all the courses of an ordinary Bill and then was submitted to the consideration of the Seanad.  In the course of the consideration of that Bill by the Seanad this amendment was introduced. I think that is derogatory to the dignity of the Constitution.  To me it is a valuable alteration.  It amends a flaw. It comes to the assistance of those who enacted the Constitution and removes an objectionable feature; but I hold very strongly where there is a question of making an amendment of that type that would preserve a proper veneration for the Constitution and impress on the public mind its character as fundamental law, that even&mdash;I may be open to the charge of pedantry in this&mdash;for the alteration of a comma, we should go through all these Stages, at whatever cost of time and trouble.  I say that all the more when I remember that it was contended that the Article of the Constitution with regard to an amendment of the Constitution could be given another construction than that which we uphold.  It was contended that after the fashion of ordinary law, it meant that if a Bill included a section which ran counter to the Constitution, and in the course of time the Bill became an Act, this <i>qua</i> Act in so far as it conflicted with the Constitution was thereby amended and we had the <i>obiter dictum</i> of a Judge in one of our Courts to that effect.  It is, therefore, to my mind most essential that, at the very earliest opportunity that presents itself, a proper interpretation and an interpretation supported by the Irish translation of the Article in question should be maintained here.  If it had no other value than this I would oppose the amendment, namely, that it provides us with a striking opportunity for declaring our view on the nature of the Constitution and the procedure by which alone it can be modified.</P>
    <Col N="2047" />
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we will have ourselves to adopt the same method that has been adopted in practically every country, and that is of devising some special method of undertaking constitutional amendments, even during the eight year period when they may be taken, as Deputy Magennis has correctly stated, according to the form of ordinary legislation.  In most countries very great difficulties are raised over the introduction of any legislation that means the slightest alteration of the fundamental law of the country. We have done so in the Constitution after the eight-year period.  Within that eight-year period we have not prescribed any special forms except the form that the Government has now rightly and very wisely adopted of describing this particular Bill as a Constitution (Amendment) Bill.  I do not go further into that at the present moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>All I do say is that I think we ought to consider some procedure.  The French have a procedure whereby the two Houses sit as one to debate a Second Reading, and there has to be a special summons.  Various countries adopt different procedures, and I think we ought to adopt some procedure that would specify a Constitutional amendment as distinct of its kind and character from all other kinds of legislation. But we have not done that.  All that we have done is, we have adopted a description of the Bill as being a Constitutional Amendment.  Having got the words in that, this is a Constitution (Amendment No. 1) Bill, I think, seeing that we have not prescribed any special form, and seeing that this amendment is by agreement, as Deputy Johnson and Deputy Magennis have said, a sound change, and a change to which we would be pressed at a later stage, if we were not to do it now, I think we might let the matter pass and I would vote for the Seanad amendment on the soundness of the amendment on its own merits, because we have got this phrase that it is an Amendment No. 1 Bill, and it is cognate to the original purposes of the Bill, as the Minister has said.  It would be carrying the matter too far, I think, to press the objection further.  I think <Col N="2048" /> the Minister might give some assurance to the House that some kind of procedure will be adopted in future by which any and every amendment of the Constitution will be compelled to go through a specially difficult prescribed course.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister would note the very change that we made here in the Short Title, making it Amendment No. 1 Bill&mdash;not Constitution (Amendment) Bill, No. 1, but Constitution (Amendment No. 1) Bill.  Now we are proposing to introduce No. 1 and No. 2.  The second amendment has not had the detailed consideration, with the possible implications, that such a Bill should have; even the Short Title is changed in the proposed amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I have some sympathy with the point of view as represented by Deputy Johnson and Deputy Magennis.  I feel that if this amendment had been put up in the Dáil when the Bill was here, I probably would have said much the same thing myself about it.  I did, in fact, in the Seanad urge a substantially similar objection. The Seanad, however, have inserted the amendment, have sent it here, and I have endeavoured to give the Dáil a clear and accurate presentation of my state of mind.  I think, to justify or warrant the sending back of the Bill to the Seanad, there ought to be some objection to the amendment <i>in se.</i> There is no such objection.  On the contrary, it seems admitted, and I certainly consider, that the amendment in itself is sound and desirable.  If not strictly related to the main substance of the Bill, it is kindred matter, and is not out of harmony with the Bill. It deals with, or aims at, removing that peculiarity, that anomaly, with which I have dealt.  I have no very decided view about the thing.  I think, on the whole, the Dáil ought not to take the course of sending the Bill back to the Seanad.  If the majority hold another view, I would not be very perturbed about that.</P>
      <P>Question &mdash;&ldquo;That the Committee agree with the Seanad in amendment No. 2&rdquo;&mdash;put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="2049" />
      <Col N="2050" /> The Committee divided: Tá, 36; Níl, 31.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Séamus Breathnach.<br />Seoirse de Bhulbh.<br />Próinsias Bulfin.<br />Séamus de Búrca.<br />Sir James Craig.<br />Máighréad Ní Choileain Bean Ui Dhrisceóil.<br />Osmond Grattan Esmonde.<br />Darrell Figgis.<br />Desmond Fitzgerald.<br />Thomas Hennessy.<br />William Hewat.<br />Patrick Leonard.<br />Liam Mac Cosgair.<br />Séamus Mac Cosgair.<br />Pádraig Mac Fadáin.<br />Patrick McGilligan.<br />Seoirse Mac Niocaill.<br />James Sproule Myles.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Martin M. Nally.<br />Michael K. Noonan.<br />Peadar O hAodha.<br />Ailfrid O Broin.<br />Seán O Bruadair.<br />Parthalán O Conchubhair.<br />Máirtín O Connalláin.<br />Eoghan O Dochartaigh.<br />Séamus O Dóláin.<br />Peadar O Dubhghaill.<br />Eamon O Dúgáin.<br />Seán O Laidhin.<br />Fionán O Loingsigh.<br />Risteárd O Maolchatha.<br />Máirtín O Rodaigh.<br />Seán O Súilleabháin.<br />Caoimhghín O hUigín.<br />Seán Príomhdhail.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Pádraig Baxter.<br />Thomas Bolger.<br />Seán Buitléir.<br />Louis J. D'Alton.<br />Séamus Eabhróid.<br />Patrick J. Egan.<br />David Hall.<br />John Hennigan.<br />Connor Hogan.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Risteárd Mac Fheorais.<br />Pádraig Mac Fhlannchadha.<br />Liam Mag Aonghusa.<br />Tomás de Nogla.<br />Risteárd O Conaill.<br />Tomás O Conaill.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aodh O Cúlacháin.<br />Liam O Daimhín.<br />Eamon O Dubhghaill.<br />Pádraig O Dubhthaigh.<br />Mícheál O hIfearnáin.<br />Aindriú O Láimhín.<br />Séamus O Leadáin.<br />Domhnall O Mocháin.<br />Domhnall O Muirgheasa.<br />Tadhg O Murchadha.<br />Pádraig O hOgáin (An Clár).<br />Pádraig O hOgáin (Luimneach).<br />Seán O Raghallaigh.<br />Andrew O'Shaughnessy.<br />Liam Thrift.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Séamus O Dólan, Seán O Suilleabháin.  Níl, Risteard Mac Fheorais, Liam Mac Aonghusa.</P>
    <P>Motion declared carried.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Constitutions for sale, cheap!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment 1 is a necessary consequential amendment.  I move that the Committee agree with the Seanad in that amendment.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>There are now two amendments in the Bill and, as a consequence, it will be necessary, I submit, to alter the Short Title.  I think that a consequential change in the Short Title is necessary, and I move an amendment accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill as it left the Dáil seems to me to have contained two amendments to the Constitution. There was the insertion of two Articles, one, Article 31 A., and the other, Article 32 A., dealing with kindred but different things, so that the amendment proposed by Deputy Johnson, if we agree with his assumptions, might not completely meet the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I assumed, and I think the House assumed, that though the amendment that was in the Bill originally contained two clauses, it was one Constitutional amendment.  This is another Constitutional amendment and should be designated as such.  Otherwise, there may be consequences that we do not at present foresee.  If the Bill, while containing two amendments of a distinct character to the Constitution, continues to be described as Amendment No. 1 Bill, it is liable to the interpretation that it is simply the first of a series of amending Bills, whereas the intention of the Dáil was <Col N="2051" /> to deem this to be the first amendment to the Constitution.  Now we have made a second amendment in addition to the first amendment, and I submit that the Short Title should necessarily be altered accordingly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree with Deputy Johnson in the opinions that he expressed before as to the need for giving the greatest care to any amendment to the Constitution that is proposed, and as to the need for examining in the most careful way even the very words that are used.  I think, however, that he is now putting forward something which it would be rather dangerous to adopt.  The amendment is an amendment in principle, and I do not think that we ought to take Amendment No. 1 in any sense but in a collective sense, referring to one kind of principle which has been touched in the Constitution. Amendment No. 1 may still be regarded as the proper title, and as the amendment first proposed in the order of time. The second Bill would then come on as Amendment No. 2 Bill, proposed at a different time.  I think it might be even dangerous to adopt the idea which Deputy Johnson suggests, because his amendment might really, though called one amendment, touch two or three different things, and perhaps, to a certain extent, separate things in the Constitution. I would prefer to keep Amendment No. 1 as simply meaning the first amendment that was introduced in the order of time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I think Deputy Johnson's amendment would imply that every time a change was made in the Constitution, every time a word or an alteration was made in it, that you would need to have a separate Bill. That would mean, I take it, that one Bill could not cover more than one alteration made in the Constitution, however slight that alteration was, or however far-reaching it might be.  There might be consequential alterations to the Constitution caused by one amendment, and therefore what Deputy Johnson seems to imply is that to provide for these consequential alterations three <Col N="2052" /> or four Bills, or perhaps more, should be introduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to prevent discussion on this matter, but I was wondering whether it was in order for the Dáil, at this stage, to do anything more than agree or disagree with the Seanad amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Dáil can deal with the Seanad amendments, but an amendment may be proposed at this stage in the Dáil if it is shown that the amendment proposed is relevant to the amendments made in the Seanad, or rather relevant to the action which the Dáil is taking upon the amendments made in the Seanad.  There appear to be two interpretations of the words in the brackets in the Short Title to Amendment No. 1.  On one of these interpretations Deputy Johnson's proposed amendment would be in order, and if the Deputy persists with the amendment, which would give a remarkable Short Title, I would accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to persist, but I am putting it forward as a possible view to indicate how very important and how very necessary it is that every possible effect of a change in the Constitution should have the most careful examination.  I am putting the point to you, sir, to find out whether there is unanimity or any understanding of the meaning of the amendment that we have made, or even of the Bill that we have passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamMagennis" hpid="Professor MAGENNIS Professor MAGENNIS">
      <NameTxt>Professor MAGENNIS</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is, whether No. 1 refers to the Bill so that in our list of statutes it would be Amendment of the Constitution No. 1 Bill, or whether it refers to the actual emendations.  It seems to me that what is of importance is that it should be on record unmistakably that an interference, by way of change with the Constitution, has been effected by such and such a measure, and that that is No. 1, and that any subsequent Act should be No. 2 even though it may contain one, two, three, or four, or more alterations.  I think Deputy Johnson's purpose would be effected by retaining No. 1, as I have put it just now, namely, that this is the first <Col N="2053" /> amending Act in reference to the Constitution, irrespective of its content, whether it contains an alteration in respect of one Article, or two Articles, or three Articles.  Otherwise, we may have refinements and subtleties later as to whether a certain change, for example, the one effected just now by the amendment from the Seanad, was to be numbered separately from the first, and though it might be clear in one particular case that they were not cognate, it might be very difficult to determine, in another case, whether or not they were sufficiently akin as to rank as one.  It seems to me that convenience and clearness would be well served merely by numbering the Acts, and as this is the first amending Act, let it go as No. 1.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is Deputy Johnson moving his amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment not moved.</P>
      <P>Amendment to the Long Title agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE." RHead="- DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Dáil agrees with the report of the Committee on the amendments made in the Seanad&rdquo;&mdash;put, and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - FISHERIES BILL," RHead="1925&mdash;(MESSAGE FROM THE SEANAD)">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - FISHERIES BILL, 1925&mdash;(MESSAGE FROM THE SEANAD).</Title>
    <Col N="2054" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Two messages have been received from the Seanad.  The first is that the Seanad at its meeting on the 1st July, 1925, decided not to insist upon amendments Nos. 2 and 14 made by it in the Fisheries Bill, 1925.  That puts the two Houses in agreement upon that measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - FINANCE BILL," RHead="1925&mdash;(MESSAGE FROM THE SEANAD)">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - FINANCE BILL, 1925&mdash;(MESSAGE FROM THE SEANAD).</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The second message from the Seanad is that the Seanad at its meeting on the 2nd of July passed the Finance Bill, 1925, and made one recommendation. That recommendation will be placed on the Order Paper for Tuesday, 7th instant.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - BEET SUGAR" RHead="(SUBSIDY) BILL, 1925&mdash;FIFTH STAGE">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - BEET SUGAR (SUBSIDY) BILL, 1925&mdash;FIFTH STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that this Bill do now pass.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - LOCAL GOVERNMENT (RATES ON" RHead="AGRICULTURAL LAND) BILL, 1925&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - LOCAL GOVERNMENT (RATES ON AGRICULTURAL LAND) BILL, 1925&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Ordered: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration&rdquo; (The President).</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Go gcuirtar ar fionnraoi forálacha Buan-Ordú 88 i dtaobh fógra do thabhairt chun Cúigiú Céim Bhille do thógaint, chun go gceadófar Cúigiú Céim an Bhille Rialtais Aitiúla (Rátaí ar Thalamh Thalmhaíochta), 1925, do thógaint iniu.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">That the provisions of Standing Order 88 as to the giving of notice for the taking of the Fifth Stage of a Bill be suspended to permit of the Fifth Stage of the Local Government (Rates on Agricultural Land) Bill, 1925, being taken to-day.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;&ldquo;That this Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Ordered: &ldquo;That the Bill be sent to the Seanad.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - OIREACHTAS (PAYMENT OF MEMBERS)" RHead="(AMENDMENT) BILL, 1925&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - OIREACHTAS (PAYMENT OF MEMBERS) (AMENDMENT) BILL, 1925&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill be received for final consideration. There are two amendments&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In page 2, Section 2 (2), line 53, <Col N="2055" /> after the word &ldquo;apply&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;or be deemed ever to have applied,&rdquo; and in line 59 after the word &ldquo;be&rdquo; to insert the words &ldquo;or be deemed ever to have been.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The first of these amendments is necessary in order that advantage should be reaped in the future and extended back over the last twelve or eighteen months.  In order to effect that purpose the amendments are necessary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Have these amendments been circulated?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The reasons for the amendments are that in some cases of military service pensions it has transpired that while the pensions would be relieved from any deduction in respect of allowances paid to members of the Oireachtas unless these words were inserted referring to the passing of the Act, that penal restriction which, I think, was not intended either in the Payment of Members Act or in the Military Service Pensions Act would apply and income tax would be collected or deducted as the case may be, and no reimbursement to the persons affected would take place.  In order to remedy that these words are being inserted.  They ought to have been inserted in the first instance, and it is only in the last day or two that we discovered that, in respect of some persons, this particular charge would be made and these moneys collected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Leave is asked to take these amendments without notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Are these amendments matters of substance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think they are matters of substance. The rate of payment is the same, except provision is made retrospective for a certain period, but, of course, it is an amendment moved without notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an amendment moved without notice, and it may have consequences which on the mere verbal statement of the President we cannot <Col N="2056" /> foresee.  I suggest that we ought to have the proposed amendments circulated, even though we deal with them later this afternoon.  I am not prepared to vote for amendments of that kind without knowing what I am committing myself to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well.  We can do that.  The amount involved is £252 7s. 11d.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the President say that only two persons would be affected?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Only two persons.</P>
      <P>Consideration postponed.</P>
      <P>On resumption,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>The effect of the first amendment would be that sub-section (2) of Section 2 would read: &ldquo;No such provision as is mentioned in the foreging sub-section shall apply, or be deemed ever to have applied, to so much of the salary,&rdquo; and so on, and lines 58 and 59 would read, &ldquo;if he did not hold such office nor shall any pension payable out of public moneys be, or be deemed ever to have been suspended or abated in respect of or on account of so much as aforesaid of any such salary.&rdquo;  It was the original intention, and the intention running through the entire measure, that whatever were those particular allowances they were to be regarded as running over the whole of the period as from the day on which they were first paid, and these amendments now, although late notice was given of their introduction, are really only verbal amendments in so far as they are really carrying out the original and subsequent intention in regard to this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I recognise that the amendments are verbal and do give effect to what was declared to be the intention.  I content myself with saying that whatever may have been the intention of the Bill, the Bill itself is far beyond the intention of the original proposals regarding the payment of the members, and I think it is unfortunate that we should be asked to pass this Bill at this time.</P>
      <P>Amendments agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2057" /> Question &mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill, as amended, be received for final consideration&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.  (The President.)</P>
    <P>Ordered: &ldquo;That Standing Order 88 be suspended to enable the Fifth Stage to be taken.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill do now pass&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.  (The President.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I certify this is a Money Bill under Article 35 of the Constitution.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - ESTIMATES FOR" RHead="PUBLIC SERVICES&mdash;REPORT STAGE">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - ESTIMATES FOR PUBLIC SERVICES&mdash;REPORT STAGE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>It was ordered that the Votes passed in Committee on Finance be reported to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;&ldquo;That the Dáil agrees with the Committee on Finance in the Resolutions of Supply reported in respect of the several Estimates.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a matter raised here, I think, on Wednesday last when the President made some references to suggestions that were thrown out by Deputy Corish and Deputy Good dealing with the question of unemployment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I happen to be the responsible Secretary of the Irish Trade Union Congress, and the suggestion that was made regarding a conference, or conferences, between employers and employees to consider a means of dealing with the problem of unemployment will, no doubt, be considered by the body of which I am Secretary.  I want, however, to say here that when Deputy Good made a statement in regard to the conclusions that such conference would, in his opinion, inevitably arrive at, and a statement appeared in a newspaper which might be said to be more obviously and avowedly the mouthpiece of the larger employers, more frankly, though not less certainly than the other morning paper, the mouthpiece of employers as against the workers, and whenever there is a dispute, or the possibility of a dispute, this and the other morning paper in <Col N="2058" /> Dublin are always to be counted on as being against the workmen.  When Deputy Good makes his statement, and the &ldquo;Irish Times&rdquo; makes its statement, prejudicing any possible outcome of any conference, it is rather difficult to plead for a conference of the kind suggested being held.  When we are told beforehand, by the parties speaking on behalf of one side to the proposed conference, that the inevitable necessity, before entering into a conference, is that they shall agree upon a reduction in wages, it makes it difficult to advocate the acceptance of such a proposal.  I want to make that point quite clear.</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Johnson is a very sensible member of this House, and I think if he himself were questioned what order of the community the particular journal to which he has referred speaks for, or what deliberative assembly has suggested to its editor to write that particular article, or how the person who wrote it could be said, by any stretch of the imagination, to represent anybody in the community but the writer, he would not know.  There is a good deal too much consideration given to and expressed about the Press.  One speaks of the Press as if it were an institution. What is it?  A man sitting in his office at a late hour at night, or during the evening, and giving out what he considers to be words of wisdom to the world, directing the Government, directing the people, directing chambers of commerce and trade unions, as the case may be, as to how they should discharge their duties.  During the two or three years which we have been sitting here, discharging the business of the nation, is there any man who ever got light or leading from either of the two journals circulating in this city?  I think that Deputy Johnson has stressed the matter too much.  If I might point out one particular infirmity in regard to these journals, it is their reference to this House as the Lower House.  Who makes it the Lower House?  They do. They pass Acts of Parliament, pass their decrees, and give forth their words of wisdom whenever they please, <Col N="2059" /> and who accepts them?&mdash;Nobody but themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>This matter of conference, irrespective of what is said on the subject by Deputy Johnson's very impressive statement, arose on the question of the responsibility of the community for the unemployed.  When Deputy Johnson says that the first question that must arise in connection with that conference is the question of wages, I say that, of course, if that is so there is no use in going into a conference, and there is no good purpose to be served by it.  I should think that any conference that would take place should not regard the question of wages as a primary, or preliminary, matter in the solution of the problem. I say, and I said before, that the employers or the monied class, were handicapped by certain considerations, such as security and the return that money invested is going to produce. I also say that at the present time, even if the conference led to nothing, even if it became abortive, the very effort in itself would be useful, as representing a community of interests, if I may put it that way, as between the employers, or if you like to call them the capitalists, on one side, and labour on the other.  Essentially, of course, one of the factors that must come into consideration in expending capital is the return that capital is going to get and the security that capital is going to enjoy.  I say that in the past the question of security of capital has not been so very apparent, and that no great encouragement has been given to take more risks than people with capital are prepared to take in connection with undertakings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I would like to take away from this whole question any atmosphere of the sort which Deputy Johnson thinks would be imported in connection with arranging any conference that might be arranged.  If it is going to be of any use, it must be from a decided effort and an acknowledgment of the need of an effort on the part of both sides to give the maximum amount of employment that can be absorbed by industry or in any other direction. <Col N="2060" /> That I think is all that a preliminary conference can have anything to say to.  So far as sitting down to consider whether wages in this industry or in that industry are too big or too small, we would get nowhere and, in fact, I would not give such a conference five minutes existence.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate very much the attitude of Deputy Hewat, but I thought it necessary to make it quite clear that when the statement of Deputy Good, containing, as it did, his final judgment on the cause of unemployment and the suggestion of a conference, which was then followed by a statement of the President, that the sequence was not helpful to the possible fruition of that proposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it was rather desirable that Deputy Johnson should have raised this matter in the way he did because, no matter what the President may say as to what he thinks about the Press, I think he will have to admit that a great many people outside look upon what the Press says as orthodox.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>That may be so in Wexford but not anywhere else.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardCorish" hpid="Mr. CORISH Mr. CORISH">
      <NameTxt>Mr. CORISH</NameTxt>
      <P>They do in Dublin and probably in Kilkenny also.  I think it is desirable to see agreement, in a tentative way at any rate, between Deputy Hewat and Deputy Johnson. So far as I am concerned, when I suggested a conference, I did so because I think it is absolutely necessary, if this country is going to be put on its feet, that this conference should be brought about.  At the same time I think it was desirable, as I have said, that Deputy Johnson should have raised this matter, as there would be a feeling abroad, unless Deputy Johnson did so, that the one desire on the capitalists' side, was to get a reduction in wages.  I hope that is not their desire.  So far as I am concerned, I am prepared to go into the conference with an open mind and to do everything possible for the interests of the country as a whole.  Personally, I think that that is the only way in which the matter can be approached, <Col N="2061" /> and I hope that both sides will approach it from that point of view, with an earnest desire to do something that will get the country out of the position in which it is at present.</P>
      <P>Resolutions put, and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE." RHead="- DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>Resolutions reported and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. -" RHead="ISSUE OUT OF CENTRAL FUND">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - ISSUE OUT OF CENTRAL FUND.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That towards making good the supply granted for the services of the year ending on the 31st day of March, 1926, the sum of £17,881,333 be granted out of the Central Fund.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE." RHead="- DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>Resolution reported and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - APPROPRIATION" RHead="BILL&mdash;SUSPENSION OF STANDING ORDERS">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - APPROPRIATION BILL&mdash;SUSPENSION OF STANDING ORDERS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That the provisions of Standing Orders 79, 86 and 88 as to the giving of notice for the taking of the Second, Fourth and Fifth Stages of a Bill be suspended to permit of the Second, Fourth and Fifth Stages of the Appropriation Bill, 1925, being taken to-day.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any objection to that course?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I object.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>May I point out that the motion on the Order is not correctly worded?  It runs from the Second to the Fourth Stage.  I think there should be another word introduced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy say what is the defect in the motion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS</NameTxt>
      <P>It says the Second, Fourth and Fifth Stages.  What about the Third Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Have you not had 90 hours' discussion on it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The suspension of Standing Orders is only <Col N="2062" /> necessary for the Fourth and Fifth Stages.  It is not necessary to suspend Standing Orders for the Committee Stage, which could be taken immediately. To what extent does Deputy Johnson object?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>My first objection is that the only notice that was given of this suspension was given before the Bill had received First Reading, and that the notice required according to Standing Orders was not given.  I would suggest to the President that he should postpone this motion until the next item on the Order Paper has been disposed of.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would agree to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The Appropriation Bill is in a category by itself.  It is founded on the Estimates passed in Committee and discussed at a certain length.  It is really a formal Bill of which Deputies have full knowledge beforehand.  The discussion on the Appropriation Bill takes place, not so much on the Appropriation Bill as in Committee on Finance in discussing the Estimates. The practice in another place is that the Second Stage of the Appropriation Bill is used as an opportunity for raising any general question of which notice has been given to the Government. I was only anxious to find out from Deputy Johnson whether he objected to all the Stages being taken to-day, or only to some of them.  The proposal now is to go to items 10 and 11 on the Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I would agree to take the Second Stage, and to leave the Fourth and Fifth Stages until we have disposed of item 10.  I presume Deputy Johnson will not persist in his objection?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not object to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Then we will take the Second Stage now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me understand the position.  There will be a new motion, I take it, to deal with the Fourth and Fifth Stages?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2063" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, by leave of An Ceann Comhairle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The motion is to suspend the Standing Orders to take the Second Stage.  Then we can also take the Committee Stage, and later on we can come to the Fourth and Fifth Stages.</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - APPROPRIATION" RHead="BILL&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>COMMITTEE ON FINANCE. - APPROPRIATION BILL&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <P>Motion made&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it this is the proper place to raise any question which, though discussed on a particular Estimate, has not been satisfactorily cleared up?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry if I have given Deputy Davin that impression.  The practice of which I spoke of is rather this: a general, not a particular, question dealing with an Estimate could be raised, or even more than one general question, by an arrangement between the Government and the parties who wish to raise it. But, strictly speaking, on the point of view of order, on the Second Reading of the Appropriation Bill you could raise almost any question one could imagine, but I would not like it to become the practice.  I do not think it would be advisable it should become the practice that when we are discussing the Estimates&mdash;to push it to its logical conclusion&mdash;that Deputies would take notes of points on which they were not satisfied, and on the Second Reading of the Appropriation Bill that every dissatisfied Deputy could raise these points and have them discussed.  If that had to be done we should have an official gallery of enormous dimensions, for every Minister would require to have his officials to furnish details. What is the point Deputy Davin wants to raise?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>I only wish a certain point to be made clear.  A certain statement was made last night by the Minister for Industry and Commerce. He stated, and it was the first time it was stated in the House, though I know the statement was made outside <Col N="2064" /> the House, that the failure of the Government to proceed with the drainage of the Barrow and give employment thereby was due to the fact that the people who made the offer of finding pound for pound for financing this scheme had been repudiated.  I have given notice to Deputy Professor O'Sullivan about this, and I would ask him to tell the House when the offer was repudiated by any local authority, or by any individual speaking on behalf of any organised body of ratepayers, farmers or others in the area, This must be cleared up in the House. If the offer has been repudiated by anybody outside the House, speaking on behalf of any section in a particular area, then it would be for them to settle it between themselves.  The Minister said he has more information in the matter than I have.  That is quite true. Undoubtedly he has more information on every matter than any Deputy.  All I am asking is that Deputy Professor O'Sullivan, who is directly responsible for this work, should state who has repudiated the offer, when it was repudiated, who are the parties who have repudiated it, whether they are members of the Farmers' Union, or members of any organised body of ratepayers, or are they only speaking for themselves?  I am authorised by the Senator who made the offer in the first place to ask for that information.  It will be very valuable to the people in that particular area who are pressing for this scheme to be carried out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJohnMarcusOSulli" hpid="Professor O'SULLIVAN Professor O'SULLIVAN">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'SULLIVAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Davin, about five minutes ago, gave me notice that he was going to raise this question, and now he wants to know when, why and by whom the offer was repudiated?  First of all, it is not true that it was suggested that the failure to carry out this work was due solely to the failure of the people concerned to put down pound for pound.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>That was said in the House yesterday by the Minister for Industry and Commerce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJohnMarcusOSulli" hpid="Professor O'SULLIVAN Professor O'SULLIVAN">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'SULLIVAN</NameTxt>
      <P>No; he said that that was one of the reasons. It is quite clear from my statement that the reason why we could not go <Col N="2065" /> on with the carrying out of the scheme was that there was no scheme in existence. I hoped that I had made that clear to the Deputy.  We cannot plunge into the river, even in this particular weather, and spend £1,000,000 without knowing what we are doing.  That would be absolutely indefensible.  What we have to do is to carry through the preliminary work of measuring, and we are doing that; we are taking steps since I spoke the other evening to see that that will be done as soon as possible. Deputy Davin has raised the question as to whether there was repudiation. There was practical repudiation from Deputy Conlan.  I do not know what repudiation is if his statement was not, when he told me not to take seriously the offer made by the deputation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not repudiation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJohnMarcusOSulli" hpid="Professor O'SULLIVAN Professor O'SULLIVAN">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'SULLIVAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish the Deputy would not interrupt, because I can only deal with one repudiation at a time.  That is one.  One of the counties affected is Carlow, and the Carlow County Council has passed a resolution on the subject, the exact wording of which I have not with me. The moment I got Deputy Davin's note I sent for a copy of it.  That, to my mind, amounted to a practical repudiation; at all events, it stated that the work should be carried out by means of Government funds.  That is what it amounted to.  As far as I can gather, they had only one meeting. There were resolutions from other bodies, but they took good care never to approach the definiteness of a pound for pound offer.  As the Deputy has raised the point, I wish again to state that the scheme stands on that particular offer, and on the counties being ready to bear their share sufficiently to bring the local contribution up to the pound for pound basis.  If the Deputy wishes, I can show him the actual resolution passed by the Carlow County Council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Has the Deputy not previously stated, both privately and in the House, that the counties likely to be most affected were Leix, Offaly and Kildare, not Carlow?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2066" />
    <Speaker pid="ProfJohnMarcusOSulli" hpid="Professor O'SULLIVAN Professor O'SULLIVAN">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'SULLIVAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I say that it has been clearly before them for over twelve months, and although the Deputy could have put the Government view before them, not a single resolution has come from these counties.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamDavin" hpid="Mr. DAVIN Mr. DAVIN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DAVIN</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy let me have a copy of the Carlow resolution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfJohnMarcusOSulli" hpid="Professor O'SULLIVAN Professor O'SULLIVAN">
      <NameTxt>Professor O'SULLIVAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamHewat" hpid="Mr. HEWAT Mr. HEWAT">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEWAT</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not on the Barrow. The Appropriation Bill marks the close of the important work which has been done on the Estimates.  As a farewell to the whole question of finance for the year under review I would like to repeat that the amount required for the administration of the affairs of the country is out of proportion to what the people can bear. I do not say that the Government are not alive to that fact or that they have not made efforts to cope with the situation, but much remains to be done. We, of course, have very little knowledge of the administrative work of the various Departments, and to expect us to say that the amounts looked for are the minimum amounts with which these Departments could carry on would be to expect us to form an opinion which would be impossible without the aid of some expert commission.</P>
      <P>There are two ways of reducing the burden of taxation&mdash;by economies or by increased production and wealth, which would reduce the burden on the individual.  But one must remember that the development of industry cannot be reached by a jump.  When discussing the matter on broad lines people are apt to form a mistaken idea of the lines along which business is to be developed.  Increased business and general prosperity is, and must be, a creature of slow growth.  The idea that you have only to go to bed and will prosperity and development of industry to obtain it is a mistaken one.  The growth of industry and of commerce can only be achieved by each individual attending to his own business and doing his share to the best of his ability.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2067" /> The other way to relieve the taxpayer is by means of economy, the cutting down of expenditure.  I am not an advocate of cutting down.  I am rather an advocate of the expansion of the responsibilities and the activities of business. When a business requires the pruning knife, the operation is very delicate and the cutting-down process is not a very healthy one.  We have over sixty departments.  I cannot believe that it is necessary for the discharge of the functions of government that all these departments are necessary. I may be asked what I suggest. I cannot suggest anything; in going through the various accounts, I could not find anything that was culpably negligent or on which to base any drastic proposal for reform.</P>
    <P>I say it is a matter that ought to get the consideration of the Government. I am satisfied that if they consider the matter and come to a decision that it will be a wise one.  The problem is there.  The amount of money involved in these accounts is very large.  The country is not as strong financially as one would wish; we hope a different state of affairs will be achieved in time, and we will be better able to achieve that by looking into small as well as large objects.  Anyone can talk in big figures and of large projects, but, personally, from my experience of business I say there is such a thing as going too fast in connection with expenditure.</P>
    <P>Motion put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister say whether Section 5 is normal?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a stock section included in the Appropriation Account each year.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - APPROPRIATION" RHead="BILL, 1925&mdash;(COMMITTEE STAGE)">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - APPROPRIATION BILL, 1925&mdash;(COMMITTEE STAGE).</Title>
    <P>Bill passed through Committee, without amendment.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE." RHead="- DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>Bill reported.</P>
    <P>Ordered&mdash;&ldquo;That Standing Orders 79, 86 and 88 be suspended.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="2068" /> Bill received for final consideration and passed.  (The President.)</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is a Money Bill under Article 35 of the Constitution.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PRIVATE TEACHTAS' BUSINESS. -" RHead="RETURN OF RATES FOR CURRENT YEAR">
    <Title>PRIVATE TEACHTAS' BUSINESS. - RETURN OF RATES FOR CURRENT YEAR.</Title>
    <P>Motion by Deputy Mícheál O hIfearnáin:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That a return be laid before the Dáil showing the&mdash;</P>
    <P>(1)  total amount of rates struck in each administrative county for 1925-26;</P>
    <P>(2)  total amount of rates on agricultural land for each county;</P>
    <P>(3)  rate per pound (P.L.V.) in each county for&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  county charges,</P>
    <P>(b)  Board of Health charges,</P>
    <P>(c)  highest rate struck in each county for district charges,</P>
    <P>(d)  lowest rate struck in each county for district charges.</P>
    <P>(e)  highest rate in each county for separate charges,</P>
    <P>(f)  lowest rate in each county for separate charges,</P>
    <P>(g)  highest rate struck in each county for all purposes,</P>
    <P>(h)  lowest rate in each county for all charges;</P>
    <P>(4)  total assessed rate for the whole of the Saorstát.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Before we proceed to the next business, perhaps we could dispose of the motion for a return by Deputy Heffernan.  If there is an agreement between the Minister and Deputy Heffernan, the matter can be disposed of at once.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. Burke) MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. Burke)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I have discussed the matter with Deputy Heffernan, and the information will be given to him privately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That means that the motion is not to be moved?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelRichardHeffer" hpid="Mr. HEFFERNAN Mr. HEFFERNAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HEFFERNAN</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2069" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>That disposes of the Private Business and allows us to go on without interruption.</P>
      <P>Motion not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - SHOP HOURS (DRAPERY TRADES, DUBLIN" RHead="AND DISTRICTS) BILL, 1925&mdash;(SENATE)&mdash;COMMITTEE">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - SHOP HOURS (DRAPERY TRADES, DUBLIN AND DISTRICTS) BILL, 1925&mdash;(SENATE)&mdash;COMMITTEE.</Title>
    <P>SECTION 1.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;&ldquo;That Section 1 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;  It is arranged that this Bill will be construed with reference to the Shop Hours Act, 1912.  I am informed legally that it simply covers the question of definition and it ensures that this Bill, from the point of view of definition, will be read in connection with the Shop Hours Act.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;&ldquo;That Section 2 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;  It simply specifies certain areas around Dublin to which the Act will be applied.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
      <P>Save as hereinafter provided no shop in the area to which this Act applies in which the trade of draper, tailor, outfitter, hatter, hosier, glover, boot and shoe dealer or house-furnisher and upholsterer, or any of them, is carried on shall remain open on any Saturday after the hour of half-past seven in the evening.  Provided that this section shall not apply to the Saturday before Easter Sunday, the Saturday before Whit Sunday, and the Saturday before Christmas Day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;In line 36 to delete the word &lsquo;seven&rsquo; and substitute the word &lsquo;eight.&rsquo;&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="2070" /> In moving my amendment I may say at the outset that it is by way of compromise. It only asks that the hour in the Bill be extended from seven until eight o'clock.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>It is from seven-thirty to eight-thirty you mean.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, we will say from seven-thirty to eight-thirty.  This amendment is not only in the interests of a large body of small shopkeepers, but it is also in the interests and for the convenience of a large section of the public.  These small shopkeepers do the main part of their week's business on Saturday, and of Saturday's business, I believe, they do almost fifty per cent. in the evening.  Their half-holiday is on a Wednesday.  In supporting this amendment I may say I should not have associated myself with it if I believed in any way it had for its object the sweating of assistants.  Its main object is to find the means of paying assistants. If their hours are changed it will mean simply that shopkeepers will have to get rid of many of their assistants, for the simple reason that they will not have the means of paying them.  The hour as in the Bill, seven-thirty, will be of very little advantage to those small shopkeepers when we remember that the tea-hour is taken out of that.  The tea hour, under the Shop Act, is supposed to be over at seven o'clock.  It will occupy half an hour or forty minutes, so in reality they will have little or no time after six o'clock for supplying their customers.  This Bill is, of course, altogether in the interests of the larger merchant shopkeepers, and they are very small in numbers as compared with the class of people in whose interests I am moving this amendment. I am informed that four hundred small shopkeepers are affected by this Bill, and that they employ thirty-three and a half per cent. of the number employed by the merchants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think it is unfair that this legislation should be rushed on the House because it is a local Bill and only affects the area of Dublin and the townships.  I think if the question is to be dealt with at all it should be on a national basis. It has also been said that the Bill is an <Col N="2071" /> agreed Bill.  I think the fact that I hold a memorial signed by some 250 shopkeepers will dispose of that argument. Again, a good deal of literature has been circulated&mdash;I believe it is a travesty of the case; it may be applicable, say, to one small shopkeeper, but it has no general application&mdash;about the ill-treatment of those people, that they are being sweated.  From the shopkeepers' point of view I think I have said almost all that has to be said, but there is another point.  While the Bill prevents shopkeepers with assistants from keeping open their shops after seven-thirty, it allows shopkeepers with no assistants to keep open as long as they like.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PadraicOMaille" hpid="AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE Padraic Ó Máille">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS-CHEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>took the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>The result will be the people who at present have two or three assistants will find it necessary to get rid of these assistants and run the business with their own family. That will mean disemployment.  We have heard a great deal about disemployment from all parts of this House and the appalling conditions that follow it. I think we should not add to the unemployed list.  Now, coming to the question of public convenience, many people, in fact, nearly all the working people, get paid on Saturday.  This is, then, the half-day.  The husband goes to some form of amusement, generally to sports, for that half day, and when he comes back he relieves his wife, thus enabling her to go out to do her weekly shopping.  If she cannot get clothes for external application to her body, it will allow her husband a little more money to go to some other shop and have an internal application, when he cannot have an external one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is another class that, numerically, is very large&mdash;domestic servants. They cannot get out early enough to shop if the shops close at 7.30.  I do not know anybody, either on the Labour or Capitalist Benches, who will allow his servant out in time to do shopping before that.  I could understand this Bill coming from the Labour Deputies, but when people's interests are affected <Col N="2072" /> things quite as revolutionary come from other Deputies.  The amendment is so moderate that I think it should be accepted.  I have every reason to believe that if these people are interfered with in the arbitrary way this Bill proposes it will put them out of business.  They pay shop assistants for the whole week.  These assistants are practically idle for four days, but are kept on simply to do one and a half day's business at the end of the week. If these shopkeepers are deprived of the means of paying these assistants, it will lead to their disemployment.  I ask Deputies to give the amendment careful consideration and be satisfied at any rate to begin with a moderate remedy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Hennessy will convey a wrong impression if it is thought this is making a start with something.  This is proposing to put into the form of legislation an agreement which has worked satisfactorily for this trade in the city for the last four years and which is now being broken by some of the smaller houses looking for trade that they can snatch from the houses that close.  That is creating a very undesirable state of affairs in the drapery trade.  I shall leave the question of the convenience of the public to be dealt with by Deputies who can put up good arguments against the shutting of, say, barbers' shops at one o'clock on Monday.  Whatever time I may have at my disposal, I never felt my feet travelling in the direction of a barber's shop that I did not realise that it was after one o'clock and a Monday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>Do your own shaving.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I go for haircutting. It does happen, and it will happen, that people think of going to a drapery shop at 9.30 p.m. on a Saturday, but the whole tendency has been, in the interest of public order and in the interest of different classes of the community, both employers and workers, to systematise the hours during which shops can be kept open.  Deputy Hennessy says that there are 400 shops in the city which will be affected by this.  He speaks of having a list of 250 <Col N="2073" /> or so.  I got a list on which there are the names of 204 people who suggest that this is going to make matters very difficult for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Deputy tell us how many are in favour of the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>Only 128 of the names on this list have been examined, and of these, 94 do not come within the terms of the Bill, because they do not employ assistants.  The Bill affects 1,033 shops, employing 3,810 assistants. There are 190 assistants employed by the people who figure on the first half of this list&mdash;that is the 128.  I do not know how many are employed by the rest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>How many are on the Deputy's list calling for the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no list calling for the Bill.  As I have said, the organised drapers and the organised workers have come together, as they did four years ago, owing to the difficulty of working the Shops Act of 1912, and have come to an agreement. They ask that the agreement which secured the satisfactory running of the trade during the last four years should be put into legislative form.  The question of the tea hour is, no doubt, important, but the fact is that for the last four years the question has not arisen as a matter of difficulty in houses closing at 7.30, or at 6.30.  I take it people who close at 6.30&mdash;and a large number of shops close at that hour to give the smaller shops a chance&mdash;do not give a tea hour.  As to the possibility of assistants being got rid of, I shall leave that question to be dealt with by people who know more of labour conditions than I do.  But it has been very definitely stated to me by people who have experience and information that many of these assistants are paid only 2/6 or 5/- a week.  If the amendment were accepted, the position would be that instead of closing at 7.30, as has been the case up to the present with the smaller houses, or at 6.30 in the case of the larger houses, you are going to have a tendency to remain open until 8.30, and the further tendency that <Col N="2074" /> the Saturday half-holiday, which obtains in many houses, will be shifted to the middle of the week, bringing about a state of affairs that will not be as convenient for the workers, as far as I know, as, with the half-holiday on Saturday, they have a fairly substantial break from work over the Sunday. If the amendment is accepted, it will really defeat the purpose of the Bill, and there will be a very serious risk of friction in the drapery trade during the summer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAlexanderNagle" hpid="Mr. NAGLE Mr. NAGLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. NAGLE</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to suggest to Deputy Hennessy that there is an easy way out of his dilemma.  That would be, if the Dáil gave me permission to move my amendment to delete Section 6.  If Deputy Hennessy supports that amendment he will have got rid of one of the biggest arguments used in favour of an extension of the hour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret that I cannot accept Deputy Nagle's suggestion because it does not get over the difficulty of the public inconvenience.  What I say is that these people have no other time to shop except during these hours. When an opportunity is provided for them to shop at an earlier hour I think that will be the proper time to legislate on this question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCollinsODris" hpid="Mrs. COLLINS O'DRISCOLL Mrs. COLLINS O'DRISCOLL">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. COLLINS O'DRISCOLL</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot agree with Deputy Hennessy in what he said about the public convenience. The public will very soon get to know that the closing hours are 7.30 p.m. and will arrange their business so as to shop before that hour.  Not one person will suffer any inconvenience by closing the shops at 7.30, and the same amount of trade will be done.  A certain amount of drapery is bought in the city and it will be bought before 7.30 just as well as if it were made 8.30.  I oppose the amendment, as I think it defeats the purpose of the Bill.  The sooner the public is trained and disciplined to shop earlier the better.  It is well known that the publichouses are closed at 9.30 and people do not go looking for drink after that hour&mdash;at least, those who obey the law.  During the discussion on the Intoxicating Liquor Bill I remember <Col N="2075" /> hearing references to allowing the publichouses to remain open until 9.30. I assert that drapery houses being open so late is one of the causes why publichouses are patronised so much at late hours.  While the wives are going about from one shop to another the men turn into the publichouses.  If shopping were done early it would conduce to happier homes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeadarSeanDoyle" hpid="Mr. P.S. DOYLE Mr. P.S. DOYLE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.S. DOYLE</NameTxt>
      <P>The opposition to the amendment seems to be based on the argument that it would defeat the objects of the Bill.  I do not wish to discuss the merits of the Bill from the point of view of its effects on the assistants.  I think the facts are quite contrary to the arguments put forward, that the amendment takes from the Bill.  It is said that the houses affected and that oppose earlier closing open at 8.30 a.m. and do not close until 11 o'clock at night.  I do not know of any drapery shops that open at 8.30 a.m. The usual hours are from 9 to 10 a.m. I think there is general unanimity of opinion that something should be done to bring about general early closing if for no other purpose than to alleviate the hardships the assistants endure by late hours.  I do not wish to say anything against the Bill.  On the contrary, I wish to support it, but on behalf of the minority of the trade affected I think the amendment would be some compromise, at any rate, until general closing arrangements would be made for all shops.  I do not think the extra hour asked for in the amendment will in any way affect the Bill.  For that reason and that reason alone I am inclined to support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Doyle knows the effect as well as anyone of a little latitude here and a little latitude there as between competitors.  The effect of this amendment, if carried, would be to defeat Deputy Hennessy's professed intention.  What is going to happen if this amendment is passed, or if the Bill is not passed?  The larger shopkeepers, who have been loyal to the agreement entered into, have found themselves bitten here, bitten there, a <Col N="2076" /> little nibbling at this and a little nibbling at that.  Those members of the trade who were not parties to the original agreement have been using their influence as competitors to take away the trade of those who were loyal.  The smaller shopkeepers then ask for a little more and there is steady encroachment on the hours which were hoped to be the closing hours.</P>
      <P>Supposing this amendment is passed, and supposing the effect is to nullify the agreement entered into, and that the larger shops open until 8.30, as they are entitled to do, what benefit will be then secured by these shopkeepers who are now pleading for 8.30. They say that 50% of their Saturday trade is done between the hours of six and nine o'clock.  If, by their resistance to this very reasonable agreement, they force the larger shopkeepers to remain open until 8.30, if this Bill is thrown overboard and the compromise broken, then the larger shopkeepers are going to get the advantage and the smaller shops will be crushed out utterly. That would be the effect of passing the amendment or losing the Bill.  The passing of the amendment may well mean the losing of the Bill. If that is the intention then the small shopkeepers are not going to be even able to continue in their present advantageous position, because they will be eaten up by the larger shopkeepers.  In addition to that you will have all kinds of difficulties raised within the trade by imposing undesirable conditions or attempting to impose undesirable conditions on the assistants engaged in the larger shops as well as in the smaller shops and you will probably bring chaos again to reign in the trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think Deputy Hennessy has been tempted to rely on the figures that have been submitted and I think it might be well if he were to examine them a little more closely and see how unreliable they are.  We are told that there are four hundred small shops employing 33?% of the total number of assistants engaged in the trade, represented by the opposition to the Bill. That is palpably false.  Out of 4,000 assistants, it is probably not correct to say that any more than 200 or 250 are employed in these small shops affected <Col N="2077" /> by the Bill&mdash;if so many.  They then tell us that they will be badly hit.  They say that 50 per cent. of their trade is done on Saturdays, and that 50 per cent. of that trade is done between the hours of 6 o'clock and 9 o'clock.  It would not be extravagant to estimate the takings at £25 per assistant per week.  Leaving out the service rendered by the small shopkeepers on their own account, let us take 4,000 assistants and let us assume that £25 is a reasonable figure for a week's takings by an assistant, on the average.  We have these shopkeepers, representing 33? per cent., as they say, doing 50 per cent. of their trade on Saturdays.  For five days of the week that 33? per cent. of the assistants&mdash; 1,200 or 1,300&mdash;are doing comparatively nothing.  On five days they are doing half the trade of the week.  They are taking £12 10s. 0d. per assistant. On Saturday, up to the hour of 6 o'clock, they are taking £6.  For the other three hours, they are doing the balance of the 50 per cent. of their trade.  I think the figures given here are not at all reliable.  Deputy Hennessy should not pay too great heed to them.</P>
    <P>It is not correct to say that workers generally are paid on Saturdays.  That day is past in a great many cases.  It is not correct to say that if these particular shopkeepers were obliged to close at 7.30 it would have a detrimental effect on the buying public. The habit of early shopping is one that can easily be acquired.  The greater proportion of the working-class trade of the city is not done after 7.30 at night.  The only reliable case that can be made for these small shops is that there should be encouraged this multiplication of small traders.  I ask the Dáil whether it considers that it should go out of its way to encourage the development in the community of small trading establishments doing nothing, or nearly nothing?  Should the House go out of its way to encourage the retired policeman and the retired postman and other retired persons to open up a little shop here, there and everywhere, to employ a little apprentice&mdash; a maid of all work&mdash;to help behind the <Col N="2078" /> counter.  That is a sort of trade I say we should not encourage.</P>
    <P>The Minister for Justice has stated some views, which, I think, are generally held throughout the country, as to the undesirability of encouraging little public houses doing half a week's trade in six days or seven days and nights. To meet the overhead and other charges this publican has to keep up the prices. That is the sort of trade that is sought to be extended and continued and developed. There is nothing in this Bill to deter this trade from carrying on. There is an attempt to deprive them of a privilege.  We ought not to take a retrograde step and undo the work that has been done by the kind of conference that has been so much talked about&mdash;a conference between organised employers and organised employees. Any agreement entered into in that way can be broken by any disloyal member, or person outside membership, if it has not some kind of legislative sanction.  There are two or three ways of meeting those difficulties.  There are the methods, which some Deputies think better than legislative action, of the strike and boycott and exposure, refusal to supply goods, and generally using the weapon of individual or collective extra-legal action.  It might be possible to interfere in that way with the disruptive activities of the kind of shopkeeper who seeks to get privilege by this amendment and other amendments that have been spoken of, but&mdash; I am glad to say&mdash;not suggested here. The disruption of agreements between organised bodies can easily be brought about.  The only way to prevent that is either to break the disruptionists by extra-legal action, or, formally and by legislative action, to sanction the agreement and make it generally applicable.</P>
    <P>This Bill is an attempt to prevent disruption and to make generally applicable the terms of an agreement, which, in my view, are very generous indeed to the shopkeepers outside the Association. While I am supporting the Bill, I want to say that it is not by any means the Bill that would have been put forward on behalf of the assistants or, perhaps, even on behalf of the <Col N="2079" /> trade, except with the object of having the Bill passed without much difficulty and without much trouble.  The amendment will go a considerable distance towards preventing the possibility of this agreement continuing.  I fear that, if passed, it would mean that the Bill would not become law, and the consequences that would be entailed would be largely upon those Deputies who support the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not have risen to take part in this debate were it not for the misapplication of terms by Deputy Johnson.  He says that this amendment will encourage the small trader to set up in this business.  It is not a question of encouraging him; it is a question of suppressing him.  What is meant by this Bill is suppression of the small trader.  The Bill has its foundations in an agreement made between representatives of the larger drapery houses and their employees.  It was found that they were not able to enforce this agreement implicity in respect of those who took no part in the arrangement.  It is pretty well understood that the employees of the large drapery houses are able to enforce their own agreements, because these houses are absolutely dependent on their employees.  In the case of the smaller houses, the agreement was not found so effective, because they can carry on independent of the agreement and independent of the assistance of their employees.  It is in order to give effect to an agreement between a certain number of people engaged in the drapery trade that the Bill has been introduced.  To my mind that is a deliberate interference with the liberty of the subject.  I have no more wish than other Deputies to see a large section of the population living by what is known as &ldquo;distributive trades,&rdquo; but I think it is not fair to provide for the suppression of these traders.  The amendment of Deputy Hennessy goes a long way to give a chance to the small trader.  The amendment is not designed to encourage him, but it goes some way towards preventing his absolute suppression.  As I understand the meaning of plain words, the word <Col N="2080" />&ldquo;encouragement&rdquo; has been misapplied by Deputy Johnson.  &ldquo;Suppression&rdquo; would have been the right word to employ.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>There was a deliberate interference with the liberty of the subject when the Shop Hours Act of 1912 was passed, giving powers to local bodies to close down certain trades at certain hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>And in the Licensing Bill, which Deputy Gorey supported.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no comparison.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>This is particularly for Deputy Gorey's benefit. Employers and employees desiring to close drapery houses at 10 o'clock on Saturday night had to work six years to get it done by means of the machinery provided in that Act.  They got it done after six years and it fell so far short of what was desirable from the point of view of the employer and the point of view of the assistant&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>The big employer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>That two years, after that six years' struggle, they came together again and decided that the larger of them would close at 6.30 on Saturday evening and the less large at 7.30.  They have carried on the work of the drapery trade harmoniously since then.  They are asking you to assist them in keeping these harmonious conditions in the trade by giving effect by means of legislation to an agreement which has done so well for the last four years.  They are asking you to give effect to it only over the area in which the agreement holds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not have interfered in this debate at all were it not for the extraordinary attitude taken up by Deputy Gorey.  Deputy Gorey talks about this Bill being an interference with the liberty of the subject.  I take it that all our laws and regulations made to regulate the life of the community are capable of being interpreted in effect as an interference with the liberty of the subject. I would like to refer incidentally to the very enthusiastic support which <Col N="2081" /> Deputy Gorey gave to the Licensing Bill when it was before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no contrast. You do not get drunk on an extra pair of boots or trousers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>If Deputy Gorey will allow me to say so, I am quite in agreement with him in that, but he will find many people who own publichouses to hold that the Act was a deliberate interference with the liberty of the subject.  Perhaps if I mentioned another matter, which Deputy Gorey is specially keen about, the analogy will be clearer.  There is no greater enemy, in this House, at any rate, of the poacher than Deputy Gorey is, whether in fishing, hunting, or any other form of sport.  I take it that instead of the description which Deputy Gorey has applied to this Bill, the suppression of the small shopkeeper, it is really in effect the suppression of the poacher, the person who wants to take advantage of an agreement come to by the vast majority of the traders and their assistants.  This person comes in to take advantage of that agreement by poaching, as it were, on the trade, which is voluntarily given up, in so far as it is given up by the arrangements which have been come to by the general body of shopkeepers and their assistants.  Deputy Gorey has not, I think, read Section 6, or adverted to Section 6 of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not read the Bill at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has never read the Bill, and he does not know what is in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I have never seen it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy says he has never seen it.  There is one thing that we can give Deputy Gorey credit for, and that is his honesty.  Let me inform Deputy Gorey that the effect of Section 6 is that this Bill will not apply to any house in which assistants are not employed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>He can poach away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>He can poach away, as Deputy Gorey says.  I <Col N="2082" /> agree with Deputy Johnson and other Deputies who have spoken, that the amendment moved by Deputy Hennessy will spoil the effect of the Bill because the agreement embodied in the Bill was come to only after very considerable trouble.  If this amendment were adopted, it would mean that the whole tendency would be to keep open until after 8.30 p.m., not only in the case of the smaller houses.  Nearly all the houses will find it necessary to extend their hours if they are to meet this unfair competition.  That will give rise to very serious trouble and it will mean the smashing up of the agreement which has been come to and which has worked so harmoniously for the past two or three years.  Deputy Doyle urged that something should be done to bring about a general early closing and I think he told us that he was in favour of such a step.  I maintain that this is a step in that direction, a very substantial step in that direction.</P>
      <P>I quite agree with Deputy Mrs. Collins O'Driscoll in her statement that it is advisable from many points of view that shopping should be done earlier than it is.  I agree with her that late hours provide an excuse&mdash;an excuse that is given often&mdash;for people remaining out late and possibly doing other business than the ostensible business for which the people had remained out. There is no reason why we should not adapt ourselves to the new conditions. As a matter of fact people are doing it.  That is my experience, in any case, of the city: that the majority of the people do their drapery shopping very much in the earlier hours and not at these late hours of the night.  I suggest to Deputy Dr. Hennessy that his amendment would not meet the situation as it had been put to us by Deputy Mulcahy and I appeal to the House not to accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I regret I was not present on Tuesday when Deputy General Mulcahy moved the Second Reading of this Bill.  Had I been present I should certainly have voted against it.  That is not owing to the point of view that I do not want to see the drapers' premises closed at an earlier hour on Saturdays in order to facilitate the <Col N="2083" /> assistants.  But I hold that in any Assembly such as this the legislators should not introduce legislation like this to facilitate 3,810 of the population of the Sáorstat.  I think the Bill should have been general.  If the Bill had been general I certainly would have supported it.  Yesterday and the day before we heard a lot about unemployment. I put it to Deputy Mulcahy: how many drapers' assistants who are engaged in large drapery premises in the city have drapery shops of their own?  How many of them when they quit at night at 7.30 will be able to go home and work behind their own counters?  We have heard a lot about unemployment.  But in every trade that is carried on in the Saorstát there are, to my mind, large numbers of people employed who have other ample means of livelihood, and yet in the same occupations there are hundreds of people who have to go to the Labour Exchanges for the dole.  I know some drapers' assistants in the towns who have&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill has only to do with Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I can cite cases in Dublin where drapers' assistants have premises and shops of their own.  I fail to see why legislation should be introduced for the benefit of a section of the community.  I think that an assembly like the Seanad, when they put forward legislation of this kind, and an assembly like the Dáil, which is about to give its consent to this Bill becoming law, should first have looked to every town and every village in the country where drapery shops are established. In every town at present, or in practically every town where big drapery shops are situated, they do close their premises at six and 6.30 o'clock.  The smaller traders must get an opportunity of getting some means of livelihood, and they get this when the big premises are finished their work for the day.  If Deputy Dr. Hennessy's amendment is accepted it does not mean that the big drapery establishments will keep open until 8.30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When the Licensing Bill that Deputy <Col N="2084" /> Mrs. Collins O'Driscoll spoke of here went through the Dáil the hours were changed from 10 o'clock to 9 o'clock on Saturdays, and under the late Act the hours are changed back again to 9.30 o'clock.  That did not mean that the assistants had to work half an hour longer. Surely the assistants have their Labour movement and their organisation, and it is up to the organisation to look after the interests of their members. I fail to see why those who have introduced the Bill are not satisfied to leave it to the Labour organisation. To compel any trader to close an hour or two before the time he wishes to close is to my mind coercion.  I would agree with the Bill, however, if it were made general and if it were made to apply to the whole Saorstát.  Why not make it general?</P>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a General who is making it anyhow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>A General is putting forward the Bill, but that General in that matter is not voicing the general opinions of the citizens.  Deputy Johnson agreed that the small traders must get some opportunity of doing business, but does Deputy Johnson agree that there are hundreds of drapers' assistants at the present moment walking the streets of Dublin unemployed when other members of the Drapers' Assistants' Organisation who work all day in big drapery establishments have shops of their own in which they work in the evenings?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>resumed the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>I will vote with Deputy Lyons if he will move that the small shopkeepers shall all close at 7.30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>All the small shopkeepers who have been engaged in other premises and earning a wage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>If Deputy Lyons will support that proposition the drapers' assistants he complains about will not have any opportunity of working in their own shops, because all the shops will be closed.  I would deprive them of an opportunity of carrying on <Col N="2085" /> business in the same trade after they had closed the establishments where they were working for wages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  Deputy Johnson now agrees with us that there is a large number of drapers' assistants who work in the evenings in their own shops.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I do not.  I quite agree that there are some.  It is not a large number but a very small number, perhaps three or four.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I know that there are six in one firm in this city alone. That is, people who have shops of their own and who work in one large firm for wages.  Because the Bill is not general I will support the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MargaretCollinsODris" hpid="Mrs. COLLINS O'DRISCOLL Mrs. COLLINS O'DRISCOLL">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. COLLINS O'DRISCOLL</NameTxt>
      <P>Just one question I would like to ask&mdash;does Deputy Lyons agree that it is fair competition for a shop assistant to leave a big establishment at one o'clock and then enter into competition with his employers?  I rather think Deputy Lyons would not limit the hours of closing at all, but would let them remain open all night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>If this is a Free State let people have their own freedom.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'CONNELL Mr. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>And close all the publichouses.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I would not close the publichouses either.  I have already explained my intentions with regard to this Bill.  Because it is not general, I would have opposed this Bill when it was moved if I were here.  I want the same legislation to apply to all parts of an Saorstát.  I want the same legislation for Longford and Westmeath, and I want to see the small traders acting in accordance with the law.  I hold that the Labour movement is sufficiently strong to compel the large traders to close at any hour they choose.  I think it would be unjust to the trade in the city if this Bill is allowed to become law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS</NameTxt>
      <P>Why?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been informed to-day by one particular trader in the City that one hour on a Saturday <Col N="2086" /> night would mean in returns to him something like £15.  People have to pay very large rents and rates in the City of Dublin, and if it is possible to prevent the chain of unemployment being stretched further than it is at the present time I think the best thing we could do would be to agree to Deputy Hennessy's amendment.  What would happen in the City would be that instead of having 3,810 drapers' assistants you may have only 3,000 employed in 1,033 shops as a result of this Bill, and have 810 drapers' assistants more than we have at present in Dublin on the dole.  I, at least, am convinced that it is the intention of the Government to do everything possible to relieve unemployment and to prevent any further number of workers from being unemployed in any particular trade or occupation.  If this Bill is passed it would be instrumental, in my opinion, in placing on the books of the Labour Exchange in Dublin another 800 unemployed men and women from the ranks of the drapers' assistants. The Government, I am sure, do not want that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>I am delighted to hear the President say &ldquo;No.&rdquo;  I ask the Government to agree with Deputy Dr. Hennessy's amendment, because if these traders are given an hour extra they will be able to continue in their services the assistants they now have in their employment.  The Labour movement is sufficiently strong to prevent any employer in the drapery trade in the City remaining open longer than the drapers' assistants wish them to remain open.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>A good deal has been said about an agreement.  The existence of that agreement has been denied.  Though I have not first-hand information on the matter, I could never imagine an agreement between such two divergent interests as the merchant drapers and the small drapers.  We have heard a lot about encouraging early shopping.  How can you encourage early shopping amongst the poor people?  A man is half a Saturday at work, then he comes home <Col N="2087" /> and he tries to have a few hours' enjoyment. He will return about 6 o'clock.  The wife then arranges that he will take care of the children while she goes out to do the shopping.  I think there is scarcely a Deputy here who does not realise that the position is as I have described.  It is frequently necessary for the breadwinner to take care of the children and look after the house while the wife does some hasty shopping.  We have also heard some talk about freedom.  Deputy Gorey's version of freedom has been criticised. In criticising it I think it was licence that was advocated, and freedom went into the background.  After all, the poacher should not get freedom or licence to do what is morally wrong. There are no questions of public morals in this matter.  If Deputy Mulcahy would meet me in a sporting way and give a further compromise, because my amendment has been a compromise from the first, I would agree to having 8 o'clock fixed as the closing hour. There is only half an hour between us. I think he is sport enough, and I am sure his hands are free enough to accept my offer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to put Deputy O'Connell right on a few little points.  He made an analogy between the licensing and the drapery trades.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I think he did.  I think even the Minister for Justice will admit that it is not at all likely that you will have a man going into a draper's establishment and asking for pants, and when he has had a pair given to him, saying: &ldquo;I want another pair.&rdquo; Take it that he wants a pair of boots. It is not at all likely that the getting of one pair of boots will go to his head and that he will want another pair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>He might visit the publichouse first.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not go into a publichouse; I never did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an awful pity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to poaching, Deputy O'Connell has said in effect <Col N="2088" /> that the man who has an assistant cannot poach, but the man who has not can poach away.  The man who runs a drapery trade assisted by his own family can poach away even under this amendment.  Is that right?  The next step that we may anticipate from the Labour Benches is that even that type of trader is to be suppressed.  They have already gone a bit of the way and the next step will be to follow up the private individual.  They will get on to him after a short time.  The next thing we will have is some regulation as to the hours at which cows will be milked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>And possibly the way they will be milked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite so.  We will have some direction, possibly, as to the way in which they will be milked, and also some instructions as to the time potatoes should be sowed and harvested.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON</NameTxt>
      <P>And perhaps some regulation dealing with dirty milk and the selling of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I will leave all those matters to Deputies Johnson, O'Connell and Hennessy; let them deal with the dirty milk and dirty water.  We know nothing about those things.  Only those Deputies who are talking about those matters know about them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TomasOConnell" hpid="Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T.J. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>But you send us the dirty milk from the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the arguments in favour of the amendment are very weak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'CONNELL Mr. O'CONNELL">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'CONNELL</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY</NameTxt>
      <P>I should have said against the amendment.  Deputy O'Connell stood up to make a strong case, but he sat down, having made a very weak and incomplete case.  He made a case that dams this section of the Bill and in favour of the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry that there should be disagreement between myself and Deputy Hennessy, but I cannot accept his suggestion of 8 o'clock.  I think if the Deputy looks <Col N="2089" /> into the matter he will see that the acceptance of the hour of 8 o'clock would mean upsetting an agreement which has worked very well in trade.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>The agreement has been denied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>The agreement has been denied by people who turn round in a list like this.  If Deputy Hennessy would turn to 20 in the B list and to 2 in the H list, he will find the names are the same.  If he turns to 21 in the B list there is a statement there to the effect: &ldquo;had learned with surprise that our names have been appended to a memorial opposing the Bill and forwarded to Deputies of Dáil <Col N="2090" /> Eireann.  We did not sign the memorial to this or any of like effect and did not authorise anybody to sign it on our behalf.  Further, we entirely agree that the closing hour for shops should be settled by legislation and approve of the proposal to this effect in the above-named Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DrThomasHennessy" hpid="Dr. HENNESSY Dr. HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Dr. HENNESSY</NameTxt>
      <P>Those peoples' names appear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>They are in your list of 204, that you call 250.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnLyons" hpid="Mr. LYONS Mr. LYONS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. LYONS</NameTxt>
      <P>Read the names out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given the numbers there.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Committee divided: Tá, 20; Níl, 22.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Thomas Bolger.<br />Séamus de Burca.<br />Michael Egan.<br />Thomas Hennessy.<br />John Hennigan.<br />Connor Hogan.<br />John T. Nolan.<br />Michael K. Noonan.<br />Seán O Bruadair.<br />Parthalán O Conchubhair.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Eoghan O Dochartaigh.<br />Peadar O Dubhghaill.<br />Pádraig O Dubhthaigh.<br />Donnchadh O Guaire.<br />Mícheál O hIfearnáin.<br />Seán O Laidhin.<br />Fionán O Loingsigh.<br />Domhnall O Mocháin.<br />Andrew O'Shaughnessy.<br />Seán Príomhdhail.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Earnán Altún.<br />Seán Buitléir.<br />Seoirse de Bhulbh.<br />Máighréad Ní Choileáin Bean<br />Uí Dhrisceóil.<br />Séamus Eabhróid.<br />David Hall.<br />Patrick Leonard.<br />Liam Mac Cosgair.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Risteárd Mac Fheorais.<br />Pádraig Mac Fhlannchadha.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Tomás de Nógla.<br />Risteárd O Conaill.<br />Tomás O Conaill.<br />Aodh O Cúlacháin.<br />Liam O Daimhín.<br />Séamus O Dóláin.<br />Eamon O Dubhghaill.<br />Risteárd O Maolchatha.<br />Domhnall O Muirgheasa.<br />Tadhg O Murchadha.<br />Liam Thrift.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers.&mdash;Tá: Donnchadh O Guaire and Seán O Laidhin.  Níl: Tomás O Conaill and Liam Thrift.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That Section 3 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 4, 5, 6, 7 and 8 were agreed to, and added to the Bill.</P>
    <P>Title put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE." RHead="- DAIL RESUMES">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - DAIL RESUMES.</Title>
    <P>Bill reported without amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General MULCAHY General MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General MULCAHY</NameTxt>
      <P>I handed in a motion dealing with the suspension of the Standing Order to enable the Fourth and Fifth Stages to be taken on Tuesday.  But if we do not meet for the transaction of business on Tuesday I would ask to have the Fourth Stage taken to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any objection to the Report Stage being taken to-day?</P>
      <P>Agreed.</P>
      <P>Bill received for final consideration and ordered for Fifth Stage on Tuesday, July 7th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - DUBLIN RECONSTRUCTION (EMERGENCY" RHead="PROVISIONS) (AMENDMENT) BILL, 1925.&mdash;SECOND STAGE">
    <Title>DAIL IN COMMITTEE. - DUBLIN RECONSTRUCTION (EMERGENCY PROVISIONS) (AMENDMENT) BILL, 1925.&mdash;SECOND STAGE.</Title>
    <Col N="2091" />
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT and PUBLIC HEALTH (Mr. Burke) Seamus Aloysius Bourke">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT and PUBLIC HEALTH (Mr. Burke)</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move the Second Reading of this Bill.  It is only a short Bill which proposes to make some slight modifications in a similar Bill introduced last year.  The principal change is in Section 7 (1) of the Principal Act.  That section gave the Minister for Local Government power, after the duration of two years from the passing of the Principal Act on the 10th July last year, on the application of the Dublin Corporation, in the case of the owners of buildings that had been destroyed in previous disturbance not having started to rebuild on these sites, or if the site happened to have been one of those where the owner was obliged to remove the building under another section of the Act, and if he did not begin either to start building or remove the obstruction, or if, having started the building it was for any reason discontinued, to issue an order enabling the Corporation to put the property up for public auction. That Act, as I say, has been in operation for practically a year, but I am sorry to say that as a result of it there has been very little work done.  Reconstruction in Dublin has not advanced very far, and accordingly it has been considered desirable that we should take somewhat stronger measures to oblige the owners of destroyed property in the city to start reconstruction.  Accordingly, this Bill provides that the Minister shall have legal authority to exercise these powers within three months from the passing of this Bill.  That is the main object of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is necessary in the Bill to exempt the sites of buildings that were destroyed in 1916, because in the case of these particular sites the Corporation and the Minister for Local Government have the powers given in the Principal Act.  These powers actually date from the passing of the 1916 Act, so that I am in a position to exercise them with <Col N="2092" /> regard to buildings at the present moment, but if these buildings were brought in under the present Bill I would not be able to exercise these powers for three months.  In that particular case it is not necessary to have these powers, because I think there is only one building in the City of Dublin which was destroyed at that time that has not been reconstructed, and that particular building is in Abbey Street. There is another provision in the Bill which is an amendment to the Act of 1924.  That provision enables awards that were granted by the Minister for Finance to be put up for public auction. It is clear that if the purchaser of one of these sites put up for public auction is required to pay the full amount of the grant accorded, it would be very difficult to get purchasers, and accordingly we are deciding that the grant is also to be put up for public auction.  There is another minor matter which it is proposed to remedy in the Bill.  In the previous Acts there was a remission of rates granted in the case of buildings destroyed up to March, 1926.  In one case, at all events, the tenant of a destroyed building pays an inclusive rate, and the landlord in this particular case, although he is not required to pay any rates on the property, charges the same rent to the tenant as if he actually was paying the same rate as previously.  There is a section in this Bill intended to rectify that anomaly.</P>
    <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second time&rdquo;&mdash;put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusAloysiusBourke" hpid="Mr. BURKE Mr. BURKE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BURKE</NameTxt>
      <P>I ask that the Committee Stage of the Bill be taken on Tuesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ConorHogan" hpid="Mr. C. HOGAN Mr. C. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. C. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to oppose the proposal that the Committee Stage of this Bill should be taken on Tuesday, but I think the time has come when legislation should no longer be rushed.  I quite appreciate that, in the case of a young State, a lot of preliminary legislative work is necessarily entailed, but I think we have arrived at a stage when our future legislation should be based on other considerations than considerations of urgency and expedition.  I think that hasty legislation is bad and undesirable. <Col N="2093" /> This is the last measure, I understand, that is to be brought forward this session, but in the opening of the new session I, for one, will oppose any suspension of Standing Orders for the purpose of taking Bills.  I think in a matter of this kind that the regular procedure should be followed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy would so command circumstances that no occasion would ever arise in which speedy legislation may not be absolutely essential, then I could give such an undertaking, but otherwise I could not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="2094" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. HOGAN Mr. HOGAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. HOGAN</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not asking for it in cases of special emergency.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 7th July.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it proposed to take the remaining Stages as well on Tuesday?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>We hope so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course, that cannot be done without consent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>I know that.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 3 p.m. until Tuesday, July 7th, at 3 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>