<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="19" Month="Mar" Year="1964" Vol="57" No="10" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 19 Márta 1964" DateEnglish="Thursday, 19 March 1964" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="797">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="797" /> Do chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take No. 1 and if the House is agreeable, to finish the debate in time to allow the Minister to reply not later, I should suggest, than 9 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>Speaking for most of this side of the House, we shall do everything possible to facilitate that arrangement.  I cannot speak for everybody.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the House agreed on that?  Seeing that there is agreement, I shall call on the Minister for Finance at 9 o'clock to conclude this debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>I think 9.15 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>9 p.m. or 9.15 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Not later than 9.15 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Central Fund Bill, 1964 (Certified Money Bill)" RHead="&mdash; Second Stage (Resumed) and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Central Fund Bill, 1964    (Certified Money Bill) &mdash;  Second Stage (Resumed) and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Last night I was about to deal with the agricultural side of the <i>Second Programme for Economic Expansion.</i>  This has gravely perturbed many of us who are closely connected with agricultural organisations and agricultural developments. We firmly believe that this programme is going to fall between two stools in regard to its target for agricultural production. It has aimed too high for the apparent continuation policy that is advocated; in other words, jog along as we have been and assume that we can merely set down a figure for increased productivity from our agricultural workers of 4.6 per cent per <Col N="798" /> annum and that with a few minor adjustments&mdash;a few heifer and other schemes thrown in&mdash;the result will be attained.</P>
      <P>I believe that is not so.  I believe the figure called for, 2.7 per cent per annum, requires a far greater shake or change in our approach to agriculture than appears to be envisaged anywhere either in the Second Programme or in the pronouncements that have been made on that.  I believe if we face up to creating this changed approach, we should aim not at 2.7 per cent but at a more realistic figure, a figure that would be well within our capabilities&mdash;at least four per cent or five per cent, or even better.  Let us say a minimum of four per cent.  I hope to substantiate that by quoting from some real authorities on this subject.</P>
      <P>The Second Programme is based on the assumption that Ireland will be in the Common Market by 1970.  At the moment that appears to be a very dubious proposition.  England's entry does not appear imminent and certainly if there is a Labour victory at the polls in England in the summer, there will be then very little likelihood of England being in the Common Market by 1970.  Yet, taking that as an assumption from which to proceed, it does seem rather strange that all the burden is being put on industry. Industry is to take the shocks of entry into the Common Market with the disappearance of very many large-scale industries at present, such as the motorcar assembly industry, and so on.  It is to absorb these shocks and at the same time provide some 86,000 new jobs in the period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is suggested that agriculture, which is at last supposed to be about to get some fair treatment by entry into the Common Market, with some hope of getting near to European price levels, will lose 66,000 workers. The burden will be placed on industry of finding new jobs for those workers. In the general target, agriculture is to increase by 2.7 per cent while industry is to increase by 7 per cent.  There is an imbalance there, quite definitely, which is seen in great relief when contrasted with the programme in <Col N="799" /> England.  The English programme aims at an increase of 4.4 per cent per annum.  Industry is asked to exceed that target, at 4.6 per cent, and agriculture is to be slightly under, at 3.5 per cent.  That is an expansion target in an agricultural industry that has already had a very spectacular expansion. So I fail to see how these figures can be reconciled.</P>
    <P>Before proceeding to some of the authorities, I want to point out a fundamental difficulty here and a fundamental fault.  It lies in having a different approach in the planning of the programmes in relation to agriculture and industry.  That difference was first brought into relief when it was known that agriculture was not to be included in the Economic Development Council that was set up, called the NIEC, over one and a half years ago.  That was a fundamental mistake because the two sectors must be developed in harmony and must also have the same pattern of development. The fundamental aim of NIEC was to secure harmony between industry and labour on the one hand and Government planning on the other, to ensure that there was free exchange across the conference table and that all efforts were pooled to produce the best result.</P>
    <P>This segregation has been commented on in a very forthright article by Mr. Garret Fitzgerald on &ldquo;The Second Programme and Agriculture&rdquo; in the <i>Irish Farmers' Journal</i> of Saturday, 14th March, where he said:</P>
    <P>A feature of the industrial consultations has been the give-and-take between the programmers and the industrialists, whose views on likely trend in home demand, exports, imports and output are given considerable weight by those responsible for the Programme, and will undoubtedly determine the final shape of the industrial targets.  This whole process of consultation is moreover being supervised by the National Industrial Economic Council to ensure that it is carried through effectively, comprehensively and speedily.</P>
    <P>There is the Kernel, Mr. Fitzgerald <Col N="800" /> goes on to comment on the grave mistake made in not giving similar treatment to agriculture.  This is highlighted by the conflict at present between the ideas of the producers, the National Farmers Association and what they believe is possible, and what the Government plan believes is possible.</P>
    <P>The only information we have on the steps taken is that given by Professor Louden Ryan at the Statistical and Social Inquiry Society, where he spoke on &ldquo;The Methodology of the Second Programme&rdquo;.  The only apparent consultations were with the Department of Agriculture.</P>
    <P>In regard to the industrial plan, there was close consultation with the Economics Research Institute and, naturally, they produced a cross-checking plan by Dr. Geary, which was modelled on the Irish economy.  I should like the Minister, if possible, to allay our fears in regard to the agricultural plan.  There is no reference that the corresponding organisation, the Agricultural Research Institute, was consulted as to the targets for agriculture.  My faith in the Agricultural Research Institute would be shaken considerably if I thought that their expansion target was a mere 2.7 per cent.  I do not believe for one moment that any one of their scientists would subscribe to such a paltry target for agriculture in this decade.  If I did, I would advise the Minister for Finance straight away to curtail the rather generous grant he is giving to that body.</P>
    <P>Likewise, we know definitely that the National Farmers Association had not been consulted.  It is fundamental in modern development that it must be a team affair between the producers and the Government planners. Nowhere is that more important than in agriculture.  If there is one lesson we can learn from our competitors in the various countries, Denmark or Holland, New Zealand or elsewhere, it is the central position that is occupied in each of those by the farmers' organisations.  We lacked that here until quite recently but now at last we have reached that stage and we have the National Farmers Association who are doing a very good job, <Col N="801" /> comparing more than favourably with what is being done by similar organisations elsewhere.  It did seem that we were in for a period of very close co-operation but there has been disharmony in recent weeks.  I hope the Minister for Finance, who is the soul of tact, will use his good influence to see that any rift does not develop or widen and that the same speedy process of planning is applied to agriculture as is applied to industry.</P>
    <P>The NFA have produced this first-rate document which we might call the Green Book.  It is worthy to rank with the Grey Book and the Blue Book as a major contribution to our economic thinking and our development policies.  I hope members of the Seanad will get copies of this, if they have not already done so, because it is a most interesting and detailed assessment of our capabilities itemised down through the various sectors of agriculture, dairying; livestock, horticulture <i>et cetera.</i>  The figures are set out in minute detail so that it forms a very clear basis for planning.  Right through runs the optimism and the feeling that agriculture must play its proper role. The target set is 4 per cent, or slightly better.  On page 147, the figures add up to a total of 3.9 without including the contribution from horticulture and some of the crops, potatoes, sugar beet and poultry.  So it probably adds up to somewhere around 4.2 or 4.3 per cent. It is based on at least retaining the present numbers on the land.  That is the kernel of it.  In other words, it is a recognition by practical farmers of the central fact in agriculture that the greatest obstacle to increased production is lack of a skilled labour force.</P>
    <P>They give the expenditure that will be called for and that expenditure, by any measure, is modest and well within the capabilities of the State because in this document we can take it that the total increase they say can be attained in gross output in the period 1964 to 1970 is some £89 million.  When that £89 million gross output in agriculture circulates through the economy, paying for some of the seeds and fertilisers being used in agriculture or spent by the farmers in buying necessaries of life or on certain pleasures such as <Col N="802" /> motoring, as it passes through different hands, it expands by about a further 6 per cent so that it would give a figure of somewhere around £140 million to £150 million of an increase in the national income.  Then the ordinary tax laws, whether applied to petrol or cigarettes or other things, operate on this money and, on the average, the Exchequer gets back something between 25 per cent and 28 per cent of national income.  If we take an average figure, it might be a little above or a little below that, but you would expect it would recoup something around £48 million to the Exchequer each year or, over a seven-year expansion period&mdash;which is taken &mdash;begin from nought and go up to £48 million.  It means that the Exchequer would be better off to the extent of £168 million.</P>
    <P>The cost as set out here calls for an expenditure of £300 million, of which it proposes that £100 million should be contributed by the Government, £100 million by the farmers directly from their own resources and another £100 million by them from borrowing.  The Government contribution should allow for some deductions due to the drop in the TB scheme and would call for additional investment by the Government of £10 million per year for seven years or £70 million.  I put it to the House: is it reasonable that out of increased tax, the product of £168 million due to this expansion, £70 million might be asked from the Government as a hand-back to aid the process?</P>
    <P>That seems reasonable by any standard.  To put it another way: it is merely suggesting that the increased produce should be exempt from all taxes and make no contribution to general taxation for some few years. That again seems a business-like proposition. The whole difference between the £168 million and the £70 million would not remain in the Exchequer, that is, the balance of £100 million, because some of it might be needed to subsidise some of the exports.  Even allowing for a fairly high level of subsidy, there would still be a substantial balance remaining in the Exchequer.</P>
    <P>Consequently I suggest to the House, <Col N="803" /> the Minister and the Government that the target of four per cent as proposed is a feasible target well within our capabilities.  It provides for an additional 66,000 new jobs or, at least, it offsets the loss of those proposed in the Blue Book and from that point of view, I think it is something that is eminently practicable.  This view, as contained in the booklet of the National Farmers Association, has been the result of a great deal of study and research on their behalf by various committees and economists and others they consulted in drawing up the document.</P>
    <P>It is further corroborated by a publication which came out two months ago and which probably has not been noted as much as it merits. That is the ICMSA publication by Mr. Raymond Crotty, M.Sc., entitled &ldquo;Agriculture in an Expanding Irish Economy&rdquo;.  This is a first-rate publication written by a man who is among the leading five agricultural economists in these islands.  Mr. Crotty is unique in that he farmed in Kilkenny for a few years before continuing his studies. His brilliance has been commented on by all.  In this he has produced a study that is as fine as ever I read.  It gives facts and figures right down the line. In it he comes to the inescapable conclusion that agriculture must expand by at least 50 per cent in the decade 1960 to 1970 if our aims for that decade are to be realised.</P>
    <P>Briefly, the central thesis in this is that to increase the gross national product by 50 per cent requires roughly a doubling of imports.  That will require, in return, that we will have to send out double our exports.  At present 75 per cent of our exports are either agricultural produce or derived from agricultural produce.  Therefore, 75 per cent is agricultural in origin.  If you double exports and make the reasonable assumption that agriculture should maintain its contribution to that, percentagewise, it means you have to double the amount of agricultural produce being exported from here.</P>
    <P>At present, roughly two-thirds of our agricultural produce is consumed at home and one-third exported.  If <Col N="804" /> you have to double exports, you have to add another one-third to what we are producing&mdash;a 33 per cent increase. Likewise, if the gross national product and standard of living go up by 50 per cent, as we hope in this plan, then part of that money will be spent in buying increased quantities of agricultural produce.  The best estimate of the experts on that is that there will be an increase of about 30 per cent in the consumption of agricultural produce. That requires 30 per cent of 66? per cent, which is roughly a further 20 per cent, all adding up to an increase of 50 per cent.  To attain that, you have to do slightly better than 4 per cent per annum.</P>
    <P>There you have again full agreement with the figures as given by the NFA.  I certainly should like to see a study and some figures produced by the Agricultural Institute.  I cannot understand why in the present case they were not asked for a study similar to that done by Dr. Geary for the industrial side.  We should try to get that without delay.  The doubling of exports involves just a seven per cent per annum increase in our sales abroad.  That is certainly not outside the bounds of possibility, especially in view of the great strides being made at present in our marketing organisations.</P>
    <P>The spectacular successes of Bord Bainne and also of the Pigs and Bacon Marketing Board are great auguries for the future.  They are doing an excellent job.  Their chiefs are quite satisfied and confident that they can cope with any marketing problems that may arise.  In fact, it seems a tragedy that in the current year, which is exactly one and a half years after the foundation of Bord Bainne, the chief of Bord Bainne has stated that we will be short 20 million gallons of milk this year to fulfil the markets we got since last year.  That seems an extraordinary position.  It shows we are reverting in some measure to the fly-by-night type of marketing we indulged in, unfortunately, in the past. In other words, when we got a group used to buying our products, then next year came and our products were not on sale to them, so their taste for those <Col N="805" /> products was lost.  I should like to ask the Minister if the statement by Mr. O'Reilly concerning the 20 million gallons was brought to his notice and if anything can be done about it.</P>
    <P>Then there is also this fatalistic acceptance of the fact that there must be a flight from the land which is permeating all thinking on this programme, such as the calm acceptance of a loss of 66,000 from the land in a period of ten years.  It is just accepted that such things are happening internationally. Of course, these matters should be examined critically.  I should like to quote a few paragraphs from page 18 of Mr. Crotty's booklet, which I think summarises all this:</P>
    <P>The dependence of the Irish economy on agriculture is greater than some commentators have, of late, been inclined to suggest.  Overconfidence, engendered by an uncritical assessment of the nature of the economic growth achieved in recent years, may be largely accountable for this.  Public concern for agriculture has of late tended to be based on social welfare rather than on economic grounds.  The attitude has been that, if all is not as it might be, an additional vote for this or for that out of an expanding revenue will set grievances right...</P>
    <P>A further factor which no doubt has contributed to the current pejorative attitude towards agriculture is the widespread existence of agricultural surpluses in Western Europe and the United States.  These surpluses clearly indicate that there has been, in a real economic sense, an over-expansion of agriculture.  In those countries where this has taken place, notably Britain, the United States, West Germany, Italy, Belgium and France, it is economically desirable that agricultural output should be stabilised, if not decreased.  But the error is frequently made of arguing from the general to the particular. Because in many neighbouring countries agriculture is already over-developed, and ought not to be further expanded, it is wrong to assume, as tends to be the case, that <Col N="806" /> Irish agriculture ought not to be further expanded either.  There are special factors applying to Ireland which make it the exception that proves the rule.  If, in Western Europe and North America generally, economic progress is likely to be furthered by a curtailment of agricultural output it does not follow that this is the case in Ireland also.</P>
    <P>Economically an industry is overexpanded when, given a free market, resources can be moved from it to other industries in which they will achieve an output of greater total value.</P>
    <P>He goes on to prove that, of course, this does not apply here.  If we move those resources out of agriculture&mdash;that is the 66,000 who are to be moved out &mdash;we move them into England, and so they are outside the Irish economy. That is a totally different situation from the one that prevails in the country that will help them to get full employment.</P>
    <P>Mr. Crotty makes the case that if the European economy were run by a central planning agency it is more than certain that they would not advise the movement of labour out of Irish agriculture, unless they were concerned with the effects in Central Europe and were trying to restrict more intensive production to the small farmers there. I have given a rather brief outline to show that quite a lot of thinking must be done on agriculture, and that there must be quite a lot of real consultation before we get a finalised target.</P>
    <P>I suggest that the present target falls between two stools.  The target should be at least at the four per cent level. There is need also for the creation of conditions which will attract and hold the necessary skilled labour force on the land.  The idea of equality of opportunity will have to apply as it applies in other walks of life.  A young man who is prepared to work on the land must have as an inalienable right the opportunity of one day owning some land, if he is good enough.  A young man in any of our towns or cities can aspire to become an engineer or a doctor, and if he is good enough he can attain his ambition.  Something <Col N="807" /> similar is required in the case of agriculture.</P>
    <P>On the question of policy, we see that the third arm of our economy is emerging as tourism.  A great deal of notice is focussed on this by the many statements from those concerned.  I am a little perturbed about this industry as a whole, because, as it is at the moment, it is far from being an ideal type of industry.  It has a short season, and it gives employment to young boys and girls who have nothing better to do at the end of the season than go to England.  I suggest that if there is to be increased investment of public money in tourism, a good deal of it should be channelled into efforts to create steady employment in the tourist industry. That involves making a very decided effort to lengthen the tourist season considerably, and to give full employment to staffs of hotels and other people.  The slack in the tourist season should be taken up.  There should be training courses in the various adaptations that are required.  If that were done, October and part of November, and probably the early part of the season would be brought into the tourist season.  I suggest that the tourist industry for four or five months of the year is a type of industry we would be almost better without.</P>
    <P>We are not satisfied that any Government have tackled the problem of our emigrants in a realistic way.  In fact, we have tended to wash our hands of our emigrants immediately they left on the ship, except to hope that they would send back what are called emigrants' remittances, which help to get us out of our balance of payments difficulties.  We should provide liberal aid to centres overseas, and ensure that they are first-class centres for keeping our emigrants together, for advising them and giving them some of the assistance they should get.  We are just extracting the last pound of flesh and giving nothing in return.  The remittances they send home at present run to £12 million a year.  We use that money in our economy.  It figures in our national income. It is subject to our tax laws and it produces £5 million a year, but we <Col N="808" /> do not spend £1 of that £5 million on our emigrants.  It is all used within our own State.</P>
    <P>I suggest that our emigrants have a strong claim on the tax that is raised on the pounds and shillings they send home to help those they left behind.  I should like to see an Irish centre established in London.  I know the work that is done by the Irish Club and others, but I think a centre should be established with ten or 20 times their resources.  Welfare officers should be attached to it who would do everything possible to help our emigrants to get adjusted to their new life, and who would run training courses.  Perhaps that might be done on this side, but it could be followed up over there.  It is no excuse to say there are many organisations to cater for them.  We must not start thinking in pounds, shillings and pence.  In this case we really should think in millions.  We should be prepared to spend as Denmark spent on marketing organisations and centres in London, for our people as well as for our markets.</P>
    <P>Finally, we read quite a lot in the papers about the agitation over take-over bids, and the vast fortunes which are being made.  I wonder what is Government policy in this regard?  Are they looking calmly at this question, or can they be encouraged to ensure that there would be at least one representative of the Minister for Finance present at each take-over bid to claim his share of the easy money that is going?</P>
    <P>Finally&mdash;and I mean it: I am still within my time &mdash; I should like to appeal to the Minister to use his great influence, as he has used it many times in the past, to try to bring the various groups together to ensure that there will be united action on the <i>Second Programme for Economic Expansion.</i> My memory of the Minister goes back quite a long way.  When I was a student at University College, Cork, I once heard the Minister introduced as &ldquo;An Fear is grámhaire chroí i nÉirinn&rdquo;.  I hope he will spread that measure of goodwill over to the problem of getting the organisations to work together. Apparently consultations with the industrial groups have reached a sound <Col N="809" /> and reasonable footing here at present and are satisfactory to all.  In other words, the groups concerned feel that if they go into consultation they are really being consulted, that their point of view gets across and that it has a full chance of being considered and probably of being a big influence on the plan.  But other groups do not feel this way.</P>
    <P>The educational groups in the country are still smarting under this type of second-class treatment.  They feel they are just expected to carry out what the Department concerned dictate rather than be consulted as they should be consulted in a modern democratic State.  We should get away from that.  We should credit the groups who go to the trouble of making representations with having something to offer and we should look on this as team work.</P>
    <P>Then there is the glaring example of the way the agricultural organisations feel they are being treated on this.  I appeal to the Minister to do his utmost to ensure that all are harmonised together in our common effort to ensure the success of this plan.</P>
    <P>While at this stage we have to be highly critical of anything we think should be criticised in the hope of improving those features of it, once the plan gets the final <i>imprimatur</i> I know we will all combine together to ensure that the targets are exceeded. I suggest that in the present debate the Minister has heard the contributions and noted the great research work put in by Senator Dooge and Senator O'Brien and there are many others here who are equally anxious and who have put in considerable research work.</P>
    <P>I ask the Minister to give us a means of communicating that research work and our efforts to those who are concerned with making the plans.  It is not just sufficient that we should simply talk here for an hour or an hour and a half, as in the case of Senator Dooge's valiant effort.  We want something more than that.  We want to hear our figures thrashed out across the conference table.  If there are errors in them, we want those <Col N="810" /> errors pointed out.  If there are not errors in our figures, we want them to carry the weight they should carry in the planning quarters.  Officially or unofficially, the Minister should make some arrangements to see that this is done.</P>
    <P>A wonderful step forward would be to ask Seanad Éireann to set up a Committee on Economic Development.  If he does that, I think it would give the Seanad an opportunity of making a real contribution to this problem.  If we had those opportunities, I think we would be far less critical in our public utterances on this matter.  If we have no other means of communication but what we can do in public then we have got to take that means and we have to give the figures as we see them.  We have to try to focus public opinion on it.  Surely it would be far more in keeping with the modern planning spirit if we could do a great deal of that across the conference table?  I appeal to the Minister to use his influence to try to see that that is brought about.  If he does, I assure him that we in Seanad Éireann will not be found wanting either in energy or in the giving of our time to this great national effort.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I believe the Government are very lucky because in Dáil Éireann today we have an enlightened and constructive Opposition who are prepared to assist the Government and to support them in any dangerous or important international situation that may arise.  The Opposition in the Dáil, led by the Fine Gael Party, backed the Government in the Congo dispute and did not try at any time to make political capital out of it even before the general election of 1961 when perhaps they could have done so. Our Leader there, Deputy James Dillon, has proved himself to be a first-class statesman.  We on this side of the House are prepared also, as Deputy Dillon has pointed out, to support the Government in the Cyprus dispute. Deputy Dillon has already informed the Government of that decision.  However, we do believe that our troops should be properly equipped and should not be used to partition that unhappy island.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="811" /> The Government at the present time are getting the full help and support of the Opposition but I am sorry to have to say that the Government are not co-operating fully with Dáil Éireann. Indeed, as the leading article in a national newspaper pointed out yesterday, &ldquo;lack of information has been a feature of this operation: the Dáil has not been well treated by the Government in the Cyprus matter.&rdquo;  It is unfortunate that with the co-operation the Government are getting from the Opposition such a statement could be made and such a statement is true.  The Dáil adjourned on Thursday 12th March.  It is a pity that more information was not given by the Government before the Dáil adjourned because, on the very next day, an announcement was made in the Press, over the radio and on television that the Government were sending 500 Irish troops to Cyprus.  I believe that this tendency by the present Government to by-pass Dáil Éireann and the elected representatives of our people and to make important statements outside the Dáil, and very often at Party and political functions, is completely wrong.  I believe it is not good for democracy in this country. We wish our troops well and we hope they do, as they have done in the Congo, valiant work there.</P>
    <P>When we look at the front page of the <i>Irish Press</i> today we see the Taoiseach shaking hands with Sir Alec.  We are glad to note that the fresh winds of co-operation are affecting our politicians in that direction today.  I remember well when we on this side of the House were dubbed pro-British when we advocated co-operation in the past, when we pointed out the importance of the British market and said that that market should be fostered.  We are glad that, at long last, bitterness is abating.</P>
    <P>We all know that the founders and architects of this State&mdash;Collins, Griffith and Cosgrave&mdash;preached co-operation and an end to hatred and bitterness.  We are glad to see that, even now, an end is being put to it.</P>
    <P>I want to refer briefly, since I am dealing with External Affairs, to a statement made on 27th February last by Mr. G.M.L. Wheeler, Irish Exporters, <Col N="812" /> criticising our embassy staffs. He complained of a lack of co-operation and he stated that, with the exception of some Notes on the Swiss Market, he could not recall a single communication sent to his association in the past few years on trade possibilities from, embassies or legations. The Department of External Affairs, he said, lacked appreciation of the urgency attaching to the promotion of the export trade.  We have often claimed that it is a pity our embassies and ambassadors seem to ape some of the big nations; it is all right to talk about international prestige, throw big parties, or attend them, but it would be better if we had in our embassies, I think, salesmen, agricultural attachés, and others who would know something about selling our agricultural and industrial produce and something about finding markets for them abroad.</P>
    <P>The Government and the Minister for Local Government, Deputy Blaney, are to be complimented on the campaign they have initiated in order to keep death off the roads.  We have all received a copy of the letter dated 13th March appealing for the co-operation of Deputies and Senators in this regard.  The Minister has asked public representatives to play their part; he hopes he can rely on them to further the campaign by mentioning the matter at meetings.  In the course of his letter he states that recent figures indicate that the accident position, which showed an improvement in December, has again begun to worsen, and he goes on: &ldquo;I have accordingly decided to initiate a further campaign the coming Easter when what might be called summer driving commences and peak traffic on our roads begins to develop.&rdquo;  The campaign will be initiated tomorrow.  We should all join with the Government in appealing to the public to show courtesy and consideration and to obey the rules of the road, remembering especially the slogan: &ldquo;If you drink don't drive.&rdquo; We must face the fact that, if the present trend continues, almost 500 Irish citizens, alive and in their health today, will be mown down and sent to <Col N="813" /> their eternal reward inside the next twelve months, and another 5,000 or 6,000 will be injured.</P>
    <P>We seem to be becoming somewhat complacent about the whole situation. We seem to regard it as something inevitable, something that must happen. It is the duty of the Government to put their foot down once and for all on the drunken driver who, in my opinion, is a menace to society, but who seems today to be accepted by and in society.  I know we cannot advocate legislation on this Bill, and I have no intention of doing so, but I believe the existing law should be enforced without fear or favour.  In Ireland today&mdash;I can say this from my own knowledge and experience&mdash;the law is not being enforced without fear or favour.  It all depends on who you are and what you are; if you have influential friends and enough political pull you will get away scot-free.  That should not be the position.  It behoves each and every one of us to play our part and appeal, with the Government and the Minister, to the people not to be the cause of bringing death, sorrow and anguish to any family, not just for Easter but for the whole year.</P>
    <P>In the Book of Estimates the Government, through the Minister for Finance, are seeking to extract from the taxpayer&mdash;let me use the famous expression&mdash;the largest sum ever asked by any Minister for Finance.  It is £185,922,680, an increase of £18 million over last year's figure of £167 million odd.  The increase last year over the previous year was £19 million.  The present figure, therefore, is £37 million more than two years ago and £76 million more than in 1957.  There is no doubt people were shocked when they were informed of the cruel imposition. People ask: When will it stop?</P>
    <P>I know Senators on the other side will say we are always making the same speech, but I look back over the year 1956 and I see where the late Senator Fred Hawkins, speaking here as Leader of the Opposition, referred to the demand then before the Seanad as a cruel and callous burden on the people.  At that time it was £109 million. Senator Ó Ciosáin, who spoke after Senator Hawkins, also referred to <Col N="814" /> the huge imposition on the people.  The imposition then was only £109 million. It is something like £78 million more today; it is 60 per cent higher than it was in 1957.</P>
    <P>When Fianna Fáil are in office they tell us the money is needed to give employment.  There are today 64,567 fewer in employment than there were in 1951.  Again, Fianna Fáil always tell us the money is there to put their plans into operation.  If plans, promises and after-dinner speeches could make the people wealthy there is no doubt we should be the richest country in the world.</P>
    <P>The arguments produced against the upward surge in Government expenditure fail to reflect the real gravity of the position; we are accustomed to hearing that the burden is very close to the endurable limit.  The present Taoiseach stated that in 1956 and the present Tánaiste made a similar statement in 1957.  Fianna Fáil speakers always make these statements when they are in opposition.  When they are in Government they play a different tune.</P>
    <P>Public expenditure is careering upwards. The rate of growth in current public spending and on non-productive capital items has far outpaced the real growth of the economy as a whole.  The proper way to get increased revenue is by a growth in national production, a growth which will provide larger taxable incomes.  It is possible to make the national cake larger and larger so that, from a bigger national cake, even at the level of existing taxation, we can get an ever-increasing amount of revenue.  The inescapable fact is that if public expenditure, both Government and local, maintains its upward course at its present rate the only result will be a disturbance in the real growth of the economy.  That is the danger that faces us now and the only alternative will be increased demands on the taxpayers, demands which will have, as they are having at the present time, their own adverse effects on the economy of the country as a whole.</P>
    <P>Fianna Fáil in opposition and Fianna Fáil in Government speak two different languages.  In opposition they preach a policy of reduced taxation, reduced <Col N="815" /> expenditure, higher wages for the poorer sections of the community. Bask in 1956 and 1957 they made those promises.  Earlier, when they first got into power, they promised they would reduce expenditure by £2 million.  They said that Ireland was living like a mighty empire, aping the British, and all we had to do was throw out the Cumann na nGaedheal Government, put in Fianna Fáil, and expenditure would be reduced immediately by £2 million.</P>
    <P>The people believed them at that time.  They threw out the Cumann na nGaedheal Government and put in Fianna Fáil, and expenditure has gone up every year they have been in power since that time.  The Fianna Fáil policy in office, and especially at the present time, has contributed to the development of inflation, with all its evil results.  Everybody knows today that the pound is swiftly losing value.  What the people need today is value for money, not money fast losing value as they are getting.</P>
    <P>We hear from platforms and in the Dáil and Seanad what Fianna Fáil are supposed to have done and what they intend to do.  There is no denying they can paint a beautiful picture but we are entitled to point out the truth to the people.  Fianna Fáil have been in power for almost 30 years now since we got our freedom.  They say they have set up many records.  Indeed they have set up many records of which the people cannot feel proud.</P>
    <P>Before us today there is a sum of £185,922,680 which is a record.  From those figures and from other information, we can believe that next year's Budget will be a record of more than £220 million.  There is record taxation of almost £85 per head in respect of every man, woman and child in the country, and that despite what the Taoiseach and the Minister for Health said away back in 1956 and 1957.  A record amount in rates was collected from the people last year, roughly in the region of £25 million.  For the coming year the increases to be imposed by every county council in Ireland range from 4/- to 15/-, so that a record amount of almost £30 million <Col N="816" /> will be collected, three times the amount it cost to run this State away back in the past.</P>
    <P>There is a record national debt of over £530 million and, as was pointed out yesterday, it is costing £20 million to service that debt.  I remember that in 1951 when the then Government borrowed money for their capital programme in order to build houses and hospitals, the leaders of Fianna Fáil and their henchmen went round the country telling the people the then Government had put the country in pawn.  Fianna Fáil put up the pawn-broker's sign on some of their posters stating that the country was in pawn. If it were in pawn then, I should like the Minister to tell us how it is now.</P>
    <P>There is a record cost of living figure at present of at least 165 points.  Perhaps the Minister has the exact figure; it may be a little more.  Last year there was a record adverse trade balance of more than £110 million.  We all know the political propaganda the Fianna Fáil Party made out of the fact that at one time when a different Government were in power, there was an adverse trade balance of £97 million.  They went from chapel gate to chapel gate throughout the country telling the people that the country was ruined. Now it seems to be all right when there is a large adverse trade balance under Fianna Fáil.  Another record is the fact that the pound is worth only 5/9d. now as compared with pre-War.</P>
    <P>On the other side we have a record low population of 2.8 million.  There is also the record number of almost 300,000 of our people, young boys and girls, having emigrated over the past seven years.  There is the further record that Ireland's total population today per square mile of agricultural land is the lowest in Europe.  Our rural population per square mile of agricultural land is also the lowest in Europe.</P>
    <P>Surely that is not what the architects and the founders of this State, Pearse, James Connolly, James Larkin, Michael Collins, Arthur Griffith, Kevin O'Higgins and others gave their lives for.  They dreamt that after shaking off the shackles of British government and securing native Government the population would grow to 8,000,000 or <Col N="817" /> 10,000,000.  Others who were around at that time who will never perhaps be mentioned in history prophesied that Ireland would support and could support a population of 17,000,000 people. Others are enjoying the fruits of those people's labours today.</P>
    <P>It might be no harm to inquire what has happened in the past 100 years in regard to our population as compared with that of Britain.  One hundred years ago the population of the Twenty-Six Counties was roughly 5,000,000 while Britain's was 20,000,000.  The ratio was 1:4.  Today our population is 2.8 million while Britain's is 52 million. The ratio has fallen to 1 : 18.  I do not think any politician should be proud of that.  Unfortunately those are the facts about Ireland, not the biased propaganda that is in this little Fianna Fáil handbook which has been printed with the people's money to glorify a particular Party.</P>
    <P>This bill before us today is only part of the burden the people must bear.  I have already pointed out that £25 million was collected in rates during 1963. This means, apart from Government grants and other receipts to local authorities, a further burden of £8 for every man, woman and child in the country.  No matter where one goes in Ireland today, there are complaints about this.  It comes from all sides&mdash;not merely from Fine Gael or Labour but from Fianna Fáil as well&mdash;at the different county council meetings.  Farmers, business people, even people in labourers' cottages complain about the ever-increasing rates.  It is estimated that in the current year between £28 million and £30 million will be extracted from the people in rates, another Fianna Fáil blister on their backs of £3 to £5 million.  I well remember the by-election of Laois-Offaly in 1956.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator does not remember the Cork and Kildare by-elections at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The people of Ireland, unfortunately, may remember them for a long time.  They were bought with the people's money.  Fianna Fáil have never hesitated to use the people's money in their own interest.  However, time alone will tell whether their <Col N="818" /> actions were justified or not.  They bribed the electorate who fell for it, hook, line and sinker.  The people themselves may pay dearly for it in the years ahead but, of course, the people on the other benches may not fret about that.  In any event I remember 1956.  I remember the Fianna Fáil posters about the high rates and the crippling effects they were having on the people of Laois and Offaly at that time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator remember the ones in Cork and Kildare?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I do.  I remember that some of them were damn lies in any case.  If you want to know something about the ones in Cork&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>They are coming home to roost now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange was proceeding very nicely, though close enough to the wind.  I think he should get back from the windy side now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We were told that the Health Act would put an extra 2/on the rates.  We all know now from experience, throughout the length and breadth of the country, that it means anything from 12/- to 14/- on the rates.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is not correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister give us the correct figures?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall give them to the Senator afterwards and I hope he will accept them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister tells me he has got them from the official report, I shall check on them.  I shall give the Minister figures today which are taken from his own publications and I hope the Minister will accept them.  I know when the Minister comes to reply, it will be the one answer&mdash; that he has been listening to these lies and half truths from Fine Gael for the past 40 years; they never had anything constructive to say; they never will; their figures are all wrong; and mine are right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="819" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not fair to drag up the Health Act; the Minister can stand anything but that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I can stand anything, even that.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>You cannot.  It is a long way from the few shillings you promised.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Could we get back to the Central Fund Bill, please?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no denying that much of the recent increase in the rates is due to the Health Act.  It is bitter medicine for the ratepayers in the provinces that any increase in the rates of 3/- to 15/- should be due to the Health Act, but the bigger increase is due to the 2½ per cent turnover tax and the ninth round increase of wages, which the people are undoubtedly entitled to.  The increase in the cost of living has been forced on them.  Anyone who reads the paper can see that it is not by 12 per cent it is going up now but from 12 per cent to 25 per cent.  The price of some of the national newspapers went up 33? per cent.  Sales are going down.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>They took the caption &ldquo;Republican Party&rdquo; off the outside page of the <i>Irish Press</i> and put it on the inside.  They did that so that people might buy it for the <i>Irish Times.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Will Senator L'Estrange cease to take notice of interruptions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The <i>Irish Times</i> is a great paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been for the Minister's Party in recent years.  There is no denying that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is an intelligent newspaper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is has no place in the discussion on the Central Fund Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="820" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>And should not have any place in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister was warned about these dangers last year, about the 2½ per cent turnover tax and the increase it would bring about in the cost of living.  All that was brushed aside and it was stated there would be only a small increase.  They have been proved wrong.  This ever-increasing spiral in rates will have to stop.  The Taoiseach and the Minister for Local Government spoke with one voice about a week ago when they talked about changes in the financing of the local authorities.  The sooner it comes the better.  Action would be better than all this talk.  I think it was the Minister for Finance&mdash;he spoke in a similar tone last year, when the rates were being struck&mdash;who said that something would have to be done.  The time has arrived when something will have to be done and a little action is better than all the talk we have heard for a long number of years.  I think I am correct in stating&mdash;the Minister can correct me if I am wrong&mdash;that the percentage of gross national product taken last year was the highest ever reached in our history.  Last year £1 in every £5 of gross national product was taken by the Government and, if figures mean anything, the percentage extracted from the people this year will be even higher.</P>
      <P>What exactly is the policy of the Government?  Is it their policy to create jobs and opportunities for more people at home or is it their policy&mdash;at least this is what is happening at the present time anyway&mdash;to make the wealthy and the rich wealthier still, and make the people who are poor considerably poorer still?  Do they not believe that the aim of any Government is to provide good jobs in Ireland for our boys and girls?  They should remember that the safety valve of emigration to England may not always be there.  It would be interesting to know what would happen if Britain closed the door to the Irish emigrants, or if they were sent home.  It should be the aim of any good Government to provide jobs for all the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="821" /> As I stated earlier, there are Ministers in the Government who stated&mdash; and our present President said it at one time&mdash;that this country could support 17,000,000 people.  They further stated that if they got back into power, they would bring back all those who had emigrated to America and other countries.  Since they made those statements, almost 1,200,000 people left the country.  This is how they ensured that the population of the country would reach 17,000,000.</P>
    <P>The Central Fund Bill always affords us an opportunity of reviewing Government policy and of looking back over the year to find out what has been achieved.  If I were to attempt to summarise the activities of the Government during the year, I should do so very briefly.  It has been one great gamble after another.  They failed in their gamble for admission to the Common Market.  We must admit the Government had built all their hopes on that but those hopes were dashed by de Gaulle.  Then there was the publication of the booklet <i>Closing the Gap.</i>  They intended to have a wages standstill order.  But it is to the credit of the Opposition in Dáil Éireann, the Fine Gael and Labour Parties, that Fianna Fáil did not succeed in that gamble.  The Opposition in the Dáil secured for the workers their right to a larger share of the national cake, if it were there. In any case, Fianna Fáil failed to get away with that gamble.</P>
    <P>The next gamble was the turnover tax, which imposed a tax on food, clothes, fuel and the necessaries of life.  Fianna Fáil told the people at that time that there would be a very small increase in the cost of living. They even said that the manufacturers, the traders and the shopkeepers could absorb it all.  The cost of living has increased and if you look at the papers, you will see that the price of bread, butter, tea, clothes, boots, shoes, everything that any man or woman can buy, is increasing daily. Bus fares and telephone charges are being increased and we know from the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs that during the year there will be an <Col N="822" /> increase in postage, etc.  The third gamble was made last October in relation to the vote of no confidence, the gamble of getting the Independents in the Dáil.  They won that but we all know how they won it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the fourth gamble&mdash;Kildare and Cork?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The fourth gamble was the timing of the Cork by-election, when it should have been held.  Fianna Fáil succeeded in pulling another rabbit out of the hat.  They injected £40 million into the economy to win the two by-elections.  It was an awful change of heart for Fianna Fáil to have to agree to the 12 per cent increase because we know what they did to those people in the past.  Remember the teachers were out on the streets for six or eight weeks.  We remember not two years ago when the civic guards were going on strike.  We remember when the civil servants could not get their increases, when they were refused them and only got them by a change of Government.  All those things are fresh in the people's minds.  Fianna Fáil were prepared to gamble with the people's money in order to keep themselves in power.  The country may pay for it in the years to come and at what a price to our economy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Six to four.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>In any case I suffered.  I know what you are at.  You may have won for the time being but the people may suffer in the years ahead.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>God is good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>You fooled the people at the dead of night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamAlexanderShel" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Sheldon) Acting Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Sheldon)</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not.  If the Senator will address the Chair, it would save trouble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well, Sir. This 12 per cent increase was introduced on the basis that if there were a change of Government, the people would not get it.  Unfortunately the people believed that.  In any case, we have to admit that no matter what way the elections went, the taxes were put <Col N="823" /> on the essentials of life and the cost of living has already started to go up. This is bound to involve severe hardship for every householder and will also increase the cost of production in all our export industries.  There is no denying that.  This is at a time when we should be vigilant in our efforts to keep the cost of production at the lowest possible level in order to compete effectively in our export markets.  I believe that what was wanted was a reasonable period of stability if we could get it in order to let our industrialists and others obtain a proper foothold in those markets. The Government, however, set the ball rolling with their turnover tax and their taxes on the necessaries of life.</P>
      <P>Fianna Fáil say that they must tax essential foods, fuel and clothing in order to get the money to pay for the social services.  The Fianna Fáil turnover tax has already produced an increase of a penny a bottle on beer, 2d on the packet of cigarettes, 2d on a glass of whiskey and 1½d on the gallon of petrol.  If these were put on as ordinary excise taxes, they would yield more than £6 million, but the Government&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I hate to interrupt the Senator when he is being orderly, but taxation is not a suitable subject on the Central Fund Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not advocating it.  Those increases resulted from the turnover tax, but I shall move away from it.  Increases in the cost of living brought about by Fianna Fáil have reduced the purchasing power of the social service payments, and now the 35/- old age pension only buys about 10/- worth compared with the period before the war.  The £ was worth 20/before the war and in 1947 it was worth 11/9d.; at mid-February, 1963 it was worth 6/9d.; and today it is worth between 5/6d. and 5/9d.  We on this side of the House believe that the welfare of the old people comes before Party advantage and that the people are entitled to a decent standard of living in their own country.  We believe in equal opportunity for all our people to use their talents to the betterment <Col N="824" /> of themselves and of the country as a whole.  To this end, our objective has always been to provide our people with the opportunity of earning a secure living in their own land, whether they live in town, city or country.  We all have to admit that the Government are neglecting the farmers.  The greatest national resource with which our people are endowed are 12 million acres of arable land which are neglected by the Fianna Fáil Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>£40 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Where is the money going?  Where is the subsidy for the calves going?  Read the report of the Fianna Fáil convention in County Longford at which it was pointed out that the subsidy was going to the rancher and to the grazier whom Fianna Fáil condemned in the past. One delegate after another got up and said that the small farmer was the backbone of the country, the man who had kept cows&mdash;and who was always said by Fianna Fáil to be the backbone of the country&mdash;could not keep an extra cow but the man who never kept a cow could now go out and buy 40, 50, 80 or 100 heifers and draw the £15 bonus on each.  The man who always did his best for the country will get nothing out of this.  The Minister for Lands had a difficult task keeping those delegates in order at that convention. The report is there in the <i>Longford Leader</i> for anybody to read.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Freedom of speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>£40 million is still twice as much as Fine Gael gave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>What did Major Chance say about it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what he said.  Take the small farmer with ten or 12 cows and 50 acres.  He has been keeping his maximum number of cows and he is not in a position to keep any more.  He will not get the grant.  The man who bought his milk locally and now buys 100 cows and thereby gets 100 heifers is entitled to £1,500 of the people's money.  Those <Col N="825" /> are the people who were condemned throughout the length and breadth of the country in the past by this Government. They referred to them as the ranchers and the graziers.  There is definitely a big change now in Fianna Fáil policy.  It has very often been pointed out that the real yardstick by which to judge the prosperity of the country is the number of families and the number of people living in happiness and prosperity, earning their livelihood on their own farms or from their own businesses, the number of fathers and mothers who have peace of mind, knowing that when their children are educated and are ready to work, they will be able to get work in their own country and not have to emigrate to Birmingham or other cities in England or to any other country.</P>
      <P>It has been pointed out by eminent churchmen in this country and it was preached away back in the past by people who were members of the Fianna Fáil Cabinet&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>In the bad old days.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>They are bad days for a lot of people at present. Speaking at column 1144, volume 161 of the Dáil Debates for 14th May, 1957, the Taoiseach, then Minister for Industry and Commerce, said:</P>
      <P>I and my colleagues have no doubt in our minds that we became the Government because the people expected us to work determinedly and intelligently to bring about a situation in which employment would expand, in which the twin problems of unemployment and emigration would be vigorously tackled.</P>
      <P>Let us get away from all the highfalutin talk one hears on Telefís Éireann and Radio Éireann about the prosperity of the country at the present time, about the number of jobs, about the new opportunities for students leaving the universities, and let us get down to hard facts and the truth, not the sort of facts contained in the publication &ldquo;Facts about Ireland&rdquo;, but the facts as regards employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Details of the working population of <Col N="826" /> the Republic are contained in Volume IV of the Census of Population, 1961, published on Wednesday, 11th March. The figures in respect of industries are alarming.  They show that, despite all the talk about increased production, a bigger national cake, more factories, increased employment, reduced unemployment, there are 64,567 fewer persons in employment in Ireland today as compared with 1951, ten years ago.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>How can you say &ldquo;today&rdquo; when that relates to four years ago?  Why do you not get the Central Statistics Office statement?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ó Maoláin must stop interrupting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>If you want them, they are worse today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Get them and read them out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>If you want them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>All I want is a discussion on the Central Fund Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We are entitled to ask if that is Government policy?  In 1951, the total number of workers in the Republic of Ireland was 1,217,106; for 1961, only three years ago, the figure is 1,152,529.  That is a reduction of 64,567.  If you want to come to 1956&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a bad year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall give you 1956 and you can talk about the bad or disastrous year, if you like.  There were 1,163,000 in productive employment in this country, according to those figures and, remember, you would change them if you could but you cannot.  The figure is 1,163,000, in 1956.  In 1961, the figure was 1,052,539.  That is a drop since 1956 of 110,461 in the number of persons employed in Ireland, despite all the hullabaloo and the figures that will be produced.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Last year the Minister for Finance told me that I gave some wrong figures.  I have looked them up and I find that I did in that regard.  I said there were only 70,000 fewer people in <Col N="827" /> employment whereas I should have said 110,461.  Between 1951 and 1956, the number of persons in productive employment fell by 54,000 but from 1956 to 1961, the number fell by 110,461.  Those figures were also quoted by Deputy Corish, the Leader of the Labour Party in the Dáil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>He is not infallible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>If he is not infallible, the Minister for Finance should have contradicted him.  The figures are published in Volume IV, Details of the Working Population of the Republic, published on Wednesday, 11th March and the Senator can get them if he wishes.  Some of these figures were published in the <i>Irish Times</i>, the <i>Irish Press</i> and the <i>Irish Independent.</i>  I shall quote from the <i>Irish Independent</i> of 12th March.</P>
      <P>The industry employing the most people was agriculture&mdash;376,272&mdash;but this was 117,020 fewer than the 1951 total of 493,202.  Other reduced figures were: clothing manufacture, 28,796, a drop of 7,070; transport equipment manufacture: 9,482, a drop of 1,304; building construction: 59,587, a drop of 26,312; commerce: 143,495, a drop of 5,970.  There were 5,577 fewer workers in transport, communications and storage; 22,773 fewer in personal services including a drop of 22,031 in private domestic services. There were also fewer employed in fishing, coal-mining, turf production and wood and cork work excluding furniture.</P>
      <P>We all remember the promises that were made in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>What year was that?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>That was 1961.  No miracles have been worked since then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Give us 1962.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>There are no reliable figures except the figures that I shall give and I shall give the figures for June 1963.  I shall be more up to date, if you want the figures, if you will be <Col N="828" /> patient.  Do not get blood pressure. They are not figures that anybody likes to hear but, unfortunately for the people, they are the truth and the people are entitled to know the truth, not the fancy bedtime stories such as are contained in the publication &ldquo;Facts about Ireland&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>The people of Cork and Kildare know the truth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not mind what happened anywhere else.  Deny these figures if you can, published by a Government Department, by civil servants. Surely the Senator has faith in our civil servants and believes what they publish?  I shall make a bet with the Senator.  I shall bet him an even fiver.  Get the figures and contradict me.  They do not want to lose more money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Give the figures for the year 1962.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We remember the promises made in the past.  I have said that there were no miracles performed since 1961.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I want 1962.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We remember the posters, &ldquo;Wives, Put Your Husbands to Work&rdquo;.  Unfortunately, the wives did not think that they were to put them to work in Birmingham, Coventry and other places abroad.  That is where they have put them to work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator mentioned that before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>He did, and last year and the year before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators will tell us that there is a reduction in unemployment but the fact is that if almost 300,000 people had not left this country in the past seven years, there would be almost 360,000 people unemployed here today.  Why not tell the people the truth?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Give the figures for 1962.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ó Maoláin must stop interrupting.  Senator <Col N="829" /> L'Estrange must be heard without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>He will be heard anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maolain Tomás Ó Maolain">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maolain</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no doubt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Whether Senator L'Estrange welcomes interruptions or not is beside the point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry.  Farms are being denuded.  Let there be no doubt about that.  The figures are remarkable and should shock us all. I shall give the Senator some 1962 figures before I conclude.  In 1926, 650,000 persons found occupation on the farms of Ireland.  In 1936, ten years later, there were 613,000 people on the land.  In 1946, the figure had gone down to 567,000.  In 1956&mdash;the disastrous year we are told about&mdash;the figure was 445,000.  I had better give the 1961 figure because the Senator is trying to compare 1961 with 1963.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>No.  I am talking of 1962.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall give you 1963, which is even later.  In 1963, there were 376,272 persons earning their livelihood on the land of this country. In June, 1963, the figure was 354,900. Last June the answer was given to Deputy Corish in the Dáil by the Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach.  Between 1956 and 1963, 90,000 people left the land or were driven from it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>In case it might be alleged that I am interrupting for the sake of interrupting, I am trying to get Senator L'Estrange to give me figures for 1962, not alone in relation to the drift from the land&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that is not a point of order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I am entitled to make my own speech.  I am making it and shall continue to do so.  If we look at the <i>Second Programme for Economic Expansion</i>, we find that the Government envisage that by 1970 there will be 70,000 fewer people on <Col N="830" /> the land, bringing the figure down to 284,000 people which will be 366,000 fewer than when we got native Government.  Is that something for the Government to be proud of? St. Patrick banished the snakes; Brian Boru banished the Danes; but it took the Fianna Fáil Government to banish the farmers and the people from the land of Ireland.  Due to Fianna Fáil mismanagement of our market system, the Danes have been allowed to capture the British market which is on our doorstep and of which, if the Government were doing their duty, we would have a much larger slice.  That market is worth hundreds of millions and if Fianna Fáil had the same regard for it in the past as they now have, there would be no need for 300,000 of our people to have left Ireland in the past seven or eight years.</P>
      <P>Nobody likes to leave the land where they were born and reared and emigrate, but that is happening.  It might be no harm to quote what the Tánaiste said when he spoke on excessive emigration continuing.  He spoke at the annual banquet of the Irish Club in London and his speech was reported on yesterday, 18th March. He said that the 1961 census disclosed that in spite of our relatively rapid economic growth, our population had fallen by some 142,252 over the decade beginning in 1951.  If the Senators do not believe my figures, can they deny the speech made by the Tánaiste to the exiles in Britain?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator did not give the figures I asked for in 1962.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not enough to quote 1963 figures?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Why is the Senator running away from 1962?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>No miracle happened in 1962.  Does the Senator suggest there were more employed in 1962 than in 1963?  If so, it is backwards we are going when we should be progressing under what the Senator would describe as progressive Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="831" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I have great respect for Senator L'Estrange's filing system&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish the Senator would have as much respect for order.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg your pardon, Sir.  I was trying to help him out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Tánaiste said the decline was entirely due to emigration, mainly to Britain.  Emigration, he said, had been a dominant feature of our economy for well over a century. The Tánaiste went on to give the exact figures I have given, that there were 42 per cent fewer people on the land now than in 1926-27.  He said:</P>
      <P>Between 1926-27 and 1962 the volume of gross agricultural output increased by 26 per cent.  On the other hand over the same period the number of people at work on the land fell from 646,000 to 376,000 a reduction of 42 per cent.</P>
      <P>Surely the Minister, when replying, will not say, as he usually does, that my figures are all wrong.  If so the figures given by the Tánaiste are wrong and somebody should tell him to speak the truth when he goes abroad.  One of the greatest failures of the Government has been, and is, their inability to realise that the fall in the population means a reduced home market for the products of agriculture and industry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Tánaiste mention 1962?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>He did, yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Let us have the Senator's figures now for 1962.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I am giving my figures for 1963, making the deductions I am entitled to make.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>But I want 1962.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Ó Maoláin will have an opportunity, I understand, of speaking later in this debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>But I shall have forgotten what he said then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="832" />
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the use in Senator Ó Maoláin, the Taoiseach and his Ministers thundering about the necessity for increased production when the most important market for this production is shrinking daily?  We must all admit that the complacency of the Government in the face of the rapidly dwindling population is alarming. It shows how completely out of touch they are&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator not know that the population is increasing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange should not invite Senator Yeats to be disorderly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The only figures we can give are the official figures taken from the census.  In the past when Fianna Fáil were questioned in the Dáil between 1956 and 1961 about emigration, they said there were no reliable figures on which to base any estimate and that we should wait until the census of population is published after 1961.  That report has been published and all they can say now is that things have improved in the past two years.  If so, why was the answer given to Deputy Corish in the Dáil that in June 1963 it was estimated there were 354,900 only on the land of Ireland? Let us have no &ldquo;codology.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>You may call it hot air, but if so, it is hot air the Tánaiste was spouting last week to the Irish emigrants because he gave exactly the figures I gave today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>But the Senator did not give 1962 figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The census of population revealed that the population has fallen more in the five years between 1956 and 1961 than in the whole of the previous 30 years, from 1926 to 1956.  If Senator Yeats wants those figures, he can look up the official statistics.  A total of 215,000 emigrated in those five years alone and the average annual rate of net emigration was higher than in any <Col N="833" /> other inter-censal period and double what it was from 1946 to 1951.  If one remembers that the total population of Longford, Westmeath, Kildare and Wicklow is 218,000, one gets a picture of the enormous loss in emigration there was in these five years between 1956 and 1961.  We have lost the equivalent of the entire population of those four counties.</P>
      <P>I remember on numerous occasions in the past the man who is now our President speaking about emigration. He said at that time that every man or boy who left this country was a loss to the country of £1,000&mdash;what it cost to rear and educate that boy.  If we accept his figure, the loss to this country from 1956 to the present is over £300 million.  Assuming that his figure was correct 25 years ago, today it would take twice that amount to rear and educate a boy. Therefore, the loss to the Irish economy from 1956 to 1961 would be in the region of £600 million.</P>
      <P>That is a colossal sum.  Sentaor Ó Maoláin is anxious to find out about 1962.  I know that in 1962 we had increased production, more cars, more factories, more washing machines&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>And more employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We certainly had not.  Unfortunately, we had 281,000 fewer people than we had since this State was established.  I do not propose to go back over what a curate in Killarney said in June, 1961, but I want to quote what he said about his parish in Killarney.  What applies to that parish applies to every parish in rural Ireland today.  It is not such a long time since I was going to the national school in Lismacaffrey.  When I was there, there were over 120 on the roll.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator must have been a precocious youngster.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what sort of devil I was.  Today the number <Col N="834" /> is down to 40, that is, one-third the number attending in my time.  This curate in Killarney was not a politician. He had no axe to grind.  He made a survey of his own parish and he said that some Kerry parishes had little more than one-tenth of their pre-famine population.  A parish that had 343 baptisms in 1842 had less than ten per year in 1962.</P>
      <P>If that is where Fianna Fáil policy has brought us, I do not think there is anything in it they can be justly proud of.  Alone among the nations of the world we have had a decrease in population.  If there is a more depressing thing in Irish life today than emigration, it is our acceptance of it, the acceptance by the Government that it is normal and that it is a safety valve for them.  Indeed, the architects of this State&mdash;Connolly, O'Higgins, Collins and Griffith&mdash;never dreamed that anybody could get up in this House and tell the people that alone among the nations of the world we had a fall in population.  Were it not for the safety valve of Britain, condemned so much in the past by the people now in Government, I do not know what state of affairs we would have here.</P>
      <P>When you see tens of thousands of our youth leaving the country every year, you do not have to be an expert to know there is something wrong somewhere.  When you see abandoned farms all over the country, you do not have to be an expert to grieve for the many who have gone.  It is well known that we have those abandoned homesteads today, especially in the west. There are many in Ireland today who cannot benefit from the ninth round increase in wages.  There are the farmers, especially the small farmers, small shopkeepers, small business people and all those on fixed incomes; and unless there is a very big increase given to the social welfare recipients in the next Budget, they will be in a very bad state also.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The farmers have to pay the 2½ per cent and they have also to pay their share of the 12 per cent increase. There is no denying that for the vast majority of the commodities they produce, <Col N="835" /> the farmers are getting only 1953 prices.  At present we are becoming more and more like some of the American States.  On the one hand, you have untold wealth and, on the other, poverty.  The Proclamation of 1916, to which the Fianna Fáil Party pay so much lip service, states that we should cherish all our children equally. I do not think they are being cherished equally at present.  The recent ninth round increase means that a man with £1,600 will get an increase of roughly £200, while a man with £2,400 will get an increase of £300.  The recent investigation into small farms revealed that there were small farmers trying to exist on £4 per week.  If prices are at the 1953 level and if the cost of production goes up, it follows that the farmer's income is being reduced every year.  The farmer lives by his profit, the same as anybody else.  His profit is the difference between what he sells at, on the one hand, and his cost of production and overheads, on the other.  If the price he sells at remains static, as it has since 1953, and his costs of production and overheads go up, as they have done, his profit is dwindling.  That is what has happened over the past ten to 12 years.  That is why the farmers are leaving the land at present.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach, Fianna Fáil Ministers and others seemed to be tripping themselves up recently declaring that our national prosperity depended on our exports of livestock.  Indeed, they have emerged as enthusiastic advocates of the improvement of our grasslands in order to secure increased exports. While I heartily congratulate the Taoiseach on his conversion to our way of thinking, might I suggest an apology from him and his colleagues for the way they have maligned others for advocating the self-same policy in the long years before the Taoiseach's conversion?  We welcome the fact that they are going to employ 30 additional agricultural instructors in the west.</P>
    <P>The Fianna Fáil campaign of vilification against Deputy Dillon is fresh in the public memory But let us not forget that the description &ldquo;Minister for Grass&rdquo; was applied to Mr. Paddy Hogan, the first Minister for Agriculture, <Col N="836" /> as a term of abuse.  Let us not forget also&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The back lane factories.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;the prediction of various Fianna Fáil Ministers that the cattle trade was a dying one.  I shall tell Senator Ó Maoláin all he wants to know about back lane and front lane factories in a few minutes. It has taken Fianna Fáil a long time to wake up to the fundamental facts of our economic life.  In the meantime, let there be no doubt that the country has paid dearly for their ignorance and mismanagement of our affairs in the past.</P>
      <P>Fianna Fáil have now been seven years in office.  I should like to know what they have done to honour the promises they made to the farmers.  I remember the promises made about wheat and about milk.  I remember when the Minister spoke on the radio in 1957 before the general election about the cruel and unjust cut in the price of wheat.  The farmers were told that if Fianna Fáil were returned to office, they would get an increase, but they got no increase since except an increase in their costs of production and overhead expenses.  We remember that the Government in office were taxed about the price of milk.  We remember the promises that were made to the milk farmers.  We know the Minister for Agriculture has said he will make a statement before Budget Day, and we all hope Fianna Fáil will honour the promises they made to these people years ago.  The farmers who were then the victims of that campaign now know the truth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Ó Maoláin asked me about industries.  Our record on this side of the House so far as industries are concerned is all right.  We can stand over it at all times.  We have nothing to be ashamed of now or in the past.  As followers of Arthur Griffith we believe that not only must our industries be expanded to provide employment for our people but agriculture must be developed with it.  That is the important thing as a means of increasing our national income.  Fianna Fáil have <Col N="837" /> neglected agriculture, while we have always believed the two arms should be built up together, because our hopes. for improved conditions for all our people inevitably depend on a rise in the national income.</P>
    <P>We initiated the Industrial Grants Act, 1956, and the tax concessions in the Finance Act, 1956.  It has always &mdash;I repeat always&mdash;been our policy to encourage industrial development.  It might be no harm to state that as reported in the Dáil Debates of 11th March, 1964, in volume 208, column 810, the Minister said:</P>
    <P>After all, if the Government had not pursued the policy they did pursue and had not built up the industries and built up the incomes all over, built up exports, and so on, as I have already enumerated, that 12 per cent would not have been possible.</P>
    <P>Reading through that, one would not have thought Fianna Fáil objected to the setting up of industries in this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Even with the Senator there should be a limit.  We hear fairy tales, but&mdash;!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I can give plenty of quotations.  I quote now from the <i>Sunday Independent</i> of 15th March, 1964.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The project is State Socialism in one of its crudest forms ... no Socialist government could go further than Mr. McGilligan has gone.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;If, on the other hand, Mr. McGilligan persists in his present attitude of trying to cover up one blunder by another he will be guilty of grave folly.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;This scheme is audaciously speculative ... the Government has yet to justify the preposterous policy of organising power on a great scale in the hope that the supply will create demand.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;The Shannon Scheme is premature and ought to be suspended by acknowledging that fact now.  In doing so the Government would do <Col N="838" /> the greatest service to the nation and to itself.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;In view of the amount of capital involved it will be a national disaster of the greatest magnitude if the Shannon Scheme is a failure.  They should take the opportunity at the General Election to sweep out of office the men whose incompetence had produced such an impasse.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The success of the Government's policy is expressed in the Shannon Scheme, the Dairy Disposals Board and the beet sugar factory&mdash;as precious a collection of white elephants as ever drove their unfortunate owners to the verge of insolvency.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>There is no need to tell the House who made that speech.  It was made by the Tánaiste, Deputy MacEntee.  If it were not for the Shannon Scheme and our beet factories, where would the country be today?  If we had not got the Shannon Scheme, there would be no power for development and for the industrial revolution that took place. He said:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The scheme is audaciously speculative ... the Government has yet to justify the preposterous policy of organising power on a great scale in the hope that the supply will create demand.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The supply was there and the demand was there.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>After Fianna Fáil came into power, the demand was created.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>It was there, and it did not matter a jot what Government were in power.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>There was nothing there except Guinness's Brewery and Beamish's.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Shannon Scheme was there; the Dairy Disposals Board was there; and the beet factories were there.  They were called &ldquo;as precious a collection of white elephants as ever drove their unfortunate owners to the verge of insolvency&rdquo;. <Col N="839" /> The Tánaiste also said: &ldquo;The project is State Socialism in one of its crudest forms.&rdquo;  The Party who organised and started those industries was told they were a socialist Government and that the demand would not be there.  That Party have been proved right and as followers of Arthur Griffith, we still believe we were right. Why are there industries in this country? They are there because of the incentives given in the 1956 Finance Act to bring foreign industries and foreign industrialists to this country. That scheme was condemned by the Fianna Fáil Government.  At that time the Control of Manufactures Act, 1932, was on the Statute Book, and it prevented foreign money from coming into the country.  Yet Senator Ó Maoláin and the Minister claim they have always been in favour of those grants.  They extended that scheme and they are working it.  Let me now quote what the Taoiseach said on 5th December, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Tell us about the rabbits in Rineanna.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall tell the Senator about some he pulled out of the hat recently.  If words have any meaning&mdash;unless the Government can get the Oxford Dictionary again and find some different meaning&mdash;the House will see that they were totally opposed to help being given to foreign industrialists who had the know-how and could give employment to our people.  As reported in the Dáil Debates of 5th December, 1956, at column 1948, volume 160, the Taoiseach said:</P>
      <P>If it could be shown that any single industrial proposition that would not otherwise proceed was likely to go ahead quickly because of the provisions of this Bill, I would say that that is an argument in its favour.  We have not been told that.  Indeed, no reason has been advanced for the Bill at all.  There is an implied assumption that industrial development has been held up by the absence of free grants.  That is not true.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="840" /> He went on:</P>
    <P>You do not have to meet it by going into the pockets of the taxpayers to hand out grants of this kind when, by doing so, you are creating a situation in which concerns that might otherwise develop will not develop unless this grant is given to them and where the policy of western development is negative at the same time.</P>
    <P>He went on:</P>
    <P>It is not easy for a party in Opposition to vote against a measure introduced by a Government in office to give money for nothing to anybody...</P>
    <P>Grants given were &ldquo;money for nothing to anybody&rdquo; when the Bill was introduced in the Dáil by Deputy Norton and Deputy Sweetman.  The Taoiseach said they were not in favour of giving &ldquo;money for nothing to anybody.&rdquo;  If the money were not given at that time and if that money were not provided where would our people be today?  It is because of the wisdom of the late Deputy Norton and of Deputy Gerard Sweetman and of the Government of that time that those grants were given and those people were invited in and that we have the industrial revolution we have experienced in this country in the past few months.  The Fianna Fáil Senators may smile but that is what the man who is our present Taoiseach had to say.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is conceded then that there is an industrial revolution?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We stood for it. We started the Shannon Scheme, the beet factories, the Dairy Disposal Company&mdash;and they were called white elephants by the leaders of your Party. On the occasion in question, while in opposition, the present Taoiseach continued:</P>
      <P>I believe that this Bill introduces an undesirable principle in the operation of industrial policy, that it is unnecesary, that the aid which industry requires is not this type of aid ....</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>He was against giving the grants to <Col N="841" /> those industries at that time and he opposed it bitterly.  He went on:</P>
    <P>The Minister can have his Bill, as far as I am concerned, but I want to make it clear that, in my view&mdash;and I may at some time in the future be empowered to influence Government policy&mdash;I think it has no importance whatever in relation to our industrial development and it represents a completely wrong approach to the problems of Irish industry as they exist today.</P>
    <P>How wrong he was then.  He got his opportunity since and instead of doing away with that Act, as some of his people said they would, they have continued it.  Industrialists have come in from abroad because of what the late Deputy Norton and Deputy Sweetman did at that time.  The step was opposed bitterly by the then Deputy S. Lemass, our present Taoiseach, and by the whole of the Fianna Fáil Party who were then in Opposition.</P>
    <P>The man who is now Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach, Deputy J. Brennan, had this to say on 5th December, 1956, as reported at column 1950 of volume 160 of the Official Report, speaking directly after the Leader of his Party:</P>
    <P>I think every Deputy on the western seaboard must deprecate and deplore the introduction of this Bill tonight.  For the first time in the history of the undeveloped areas, the congested areas in the country, we saw hope for revival in the introduction here of the Undeveloped Areas Act.</P>
    <P>However, because grants were being given to encourage those people with the know-how to come in here, the step was condemned at that time by Fianna Fáil.  They have since adopted it and if there is any improvement in industrial employment in this country today it is due to the fact that the Industrial Grants Bill, 1956, was introduced and nobody can deny it&mdash;and Fianna Fáil opposed it at that time.</P>
    <P>Here is further proof of Fianna Fáil opposition to the principle enshrined in the Industrial Grants Act, 1956. When the measure was going through <Col N="842" /> this House the then Leader of the Fianna Fáil Party in this House, the late Senator Fred Hawkins, opposed it.  He ridiculed it and laughed at it. As reported at column 1548 of the Official Report of 21st March, 1956, vol. 43, the late Senator Hawkins said:</P>
    <P>..., we then set sail not to one continent but to two continents to hold out inducements to people to come here and give us, first, the &ldquo;know-how&rdquo;, to come with their knowledge and their finance and to build up industries here.  Many of the statements that have been made suggested thay should come and go into competition with many industries that are now in existence.</P>
    <P>It was opposed at that time by those people but they afterwards realised that it was a good Act.  They are working it now and as I said it is responsible for whatever increase we may have in industrial employment in certain sectors of our economy.</P>
    <P>I do not intend to speak much longer except to refer to the cost of living.  As everybody knows, despite what has been said by Fianna Fáil in the past, despite the way the people were fooled before the Cork and Kildare by-elections that they would get the 12 per cent and that there would be no increase for two and a half years, huge increases have taken place. The day before the by-elections, Deputy Sweetman said the price of bread would go up by one penny and Fianna Fáil said it was untrue.</P>
    <P>There was a time when Fianna Fáil said they were concerned to keep the price of essential foodstuffs as low as possible and when they considered bread an important item on the diet. What has happened since that time that they are now taxing the essentials of life?  I want to quote the report of a statement by the man who is now our President, Mr. Éamon de Valera, when speaking at Belmullet on 1st March, 1957.  At that time, Fine Gael speakers informed the people that if Fine Gael were returned to office they would abolish the subsidies.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It was ready for us when we came in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="843" />
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures were there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>You were elected to put into operation your own financial policy.  What was done before you took office had nothing to do with you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures were ready.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>They were not foolish enough to leave anything like that for you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzpatrick) Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzpatrick)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzpatrick)</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange must be allowed to speak without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>They floated the prize bonds and left £6½ million to Fianna Fáil the day they came in.  In any case, Mr. Éamon de Valera, speaking at Belmullet on 1st March, 1957, said:</P>
      <P>You know the record of Fianna Fáil in the past.  You know that we have never done the things they said we would do.  They have told you that you would be paying more for your bread.  We did not cut them&mdash;</P>
      <P>the food subsidies&mdash;</P>
      <P>&mdash;all out before because we did not want the price of bread&mdash;so important an article of diet for the poor&mdash;to be increased.</P>
      <P>At that time, he seemed to have some sympathy for the poor.  At that time, the price of the loaf was 9d. and a stone of flour cost 4/5d.  The Fianna Fáil Government increased the price of the loaf to the 1/8d. or 1/9d. that it is today and the price of the stone of flour to the 8/6d. or 8/10d. that it is today.  These are the facts and I think they cannot be denied even by Fianna Fáil.</P>
      <P>Always around St. Patrick's day we have parades of one description or another.  I think some Ministers have spoken on it recently and it is something that should be taken up by all Parties, namely, a Buy Irish campaign in this country not for one week of the year but for the 52 weeks of the year. Our people should be encouraged to buy Irish.  I do not know what is wrong with our people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="844" /> When we become reasonably well off, and this applies also to the wealthier people in our society, we are more inclined to buy something produced in some other country.  When we are poor and struggling, the Irish article is good enough but when we get up in the world we want Italian shoes, French dresses, and so on.  It is unfortunate that that trend exists among our people.</P>
    <P>An all-out effort should be made by all Parties to get our people to buy Irish.  Those in the NAIDA claim that from £70 million or £80 million worth of goods are imported into this country and bought by our people every year &mdash;goods which could be produced in our own country.  An all-out effort should be made in the years ahead in this connection.  When tariffs are being reduced and with the prospect of membership of the EEC in a few years, it will be more important than ever to buy Irish produce and we should have a Buy Irish Produce campaign not for one week of the year but for the 52 weeks of the year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>B'fhéidir nár mhiste cúpla focal Gaeilge a labhairt anois chun sólás a thabhairt do Sheanadóirí mar gheall ar an méid pionóis d'fulaingeadar le h-óráideacha leadránacha a tugadh ar an mBille Príomh-Chiste seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Léigh é seo agus beidh sólás agat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Dar ndó, is féidir labhairt ar mhórán rudaí a bhaineann le saol na tíre ach ní mian liomsa tagairt a dhéanamh do na pointí go léir dár thagair an Seanadóir L'Estrange agus dár thagair Seanadóirí eile.  Tá aon rud amháin le rá thar aon ní eile agus sé sin go bhfuil cúrsaí na tíre ag dul ar aghaidh go han-mhaith agus tá a lá dá bhuíochas san ag dul don Rialtas.  Tá i bhfad níos mó saibhris sa tír seo anois ná mar a bhí riamh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Sé atá i gceist sa Bhille PríomhChiste seo ná údarás a thabhairt don Aire Airgeadais an méid airgid a cuireadh fé mheas na Dála sa Bhóta-igCúntas agus ins na Meastacháin <Col N="845" /> bhreise d'úsáid ar mhaithe le muintir na tíre.  Anois ó cuireadh Leabhar na Meastachán ar fáil dúinn tá pictiúir iomlán le feiscint againn ar conas a ceaptar a caithfear an t-airgead ar fad sa bhliain airgeadais atá rómhainn. Chímid go gceaptar go mbeidh breis airgid le caitheamh ar sheibhíse áirithe agus go gceaptar go mbeidh níos lú airgid le caitheamh ar sheirbhíse áirithe eile.  Maidir leis sin, tá ár mbuíochas ag dul don Aire Airgeadais mar gheall ar an liosta san d'eisigh sé le Leabhar na Meastachán á léiriú dhúinn a héasca cad iad na seirbhís ar a mbeidh méadú caiteachais agus cad iad na seirbhísí ar a mbeidh laghdú.  Dar ndó is ionmholta an beartas é sin agus is mór an chabhair dúinn é an liosta san a bheith ós ár gcomhair ag gabháil don mBille Príomh-Chiste seo.</P>
    <P>Ach ní le ceisteanna airgeadais amháin is féidir linn a bheith ag plé sa Bhille seo: tá sé de chaoi againn léirmheas a dhéanamh ar chúrsaí na tíre, go mór mhór na gnéithe a bhaineann leis an gcuspóir eacnamaíoch agus leis an gcuspóir sóisialach agus, dar ndó, leis an gcuspóir cultúrtha, más mian linn é.</P>
    <P>Táthar ag gearán anseo sa tSeanad fé mar a gearánadh sa Dáil i dtaobh na breise atá le caitheamh sa bhliain nua airgeadais atá rómhainn ar sheirbhísí na tíre ach aoinne a dheineann machnamh beag ar chúrsaí na tíre fé mar atáid beidh fios fáth an scéil aige. Beidh a fhios aige nach féidir géilleagar agus tionnscalaíocht na tíre do cur chun cinn gan a thuille caiteachais. Beidh a fhios aige nach féidir na seirbhísí sóisialacha d'fheabhsú gan a thuille caiteachais.  Is amhlaidh a bhíonn daoine áirithe ag síor-éileamh breiseanna ar na seirbhísí sóisialacha san, ach nuair a thagann lá an chúntais, fé mar atá sé tagtha orainn-ne inniu, ní mó ná leath-shásta atáimíd nuair a cuirtear an bille ós ar gcomhair.</P>
    <P>Go deimhin, is ceart súil a choimeád ar an méid airgid atá le caitheamh ar na seirbhísí náisiúnta agus súil ghéar ach is géire fós an tsúil is ceart dúinn a choimeád ar an módh imeachta, nó ar an <i>modus operandi</i> atá againn.  Má táimíd ag dul sa treo ceart; más chun <Col N="846" /> a thuille saibhris a bhaint as talamh na hÉireann; más chun a thuille saibhris a bhaint as ár monarchain agus as ár n-aonaid gnótha atá an bhreis airgid le caitheamh againn, tiocfaidh dea-thoradh as.  Dála an gnó príobháideach, ní féidir gnó na tíre do leathnú gan a thuille airgid a chur isteach sa ghnó san.  Tuigeann na cnámhseálaithe atá sa Dáil é sin agus tuigeann na cnámhseálaithe anso sa tSeanad é sin chomh mhaith céanna. Tuigeann siad chomh maith san é is nárbh áil leo méar do leagadh ar aon cheann de na breiseanna atá i Leabhair na Meastachán agus a rá nach ceart é bheith ann.  Dar ndó, caithfimid a bheith dáiríre mar gheall ar an ngnó so ar fad agus rud eile d'oirfeadh dúinn a chur in iúil do mhuintir na tíre go bhfuilimid dáiríre agus nach féidir dúinn beith fuar agus te san am gcéanna.</P>
    <P>This debate on the Central Fund has taken many turns.  I have listened to some very lengthy speeches and I do not propose to deal with all the points raised by the speakers who came before me.  There are, however, a few things to which I should like to advert. What amazes me here, in this House, is the way in which certain Senators refer to the questions of unemployment&mdash;although we did not hear much about that today&mdash;emigration, and so on, when one would imagine that these are the very things they should avoid mentioning.  The Central Fund Bill gives an opportunity here of dealing with all these matters, unemployment, emigration, the cost of living, and so forth, but I should like to point out to Senator L'Estrange and to other Senators that as regards this question of emigration the record will show, as far as it can be ascertained, that emigration is on the decline.  In 1957 the figure for emigration was given as 40,000 and now it is down to 20,000.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>16,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Or maybe 16,000, which is more than a 50 per cent reduction over those years.  The unemployment figure is also down very substantially from what it was in the last year of the Coalition Government, 1957, when the figure was almost 100,000.  Now it is down to roughly <Col N="847" /> 60,000, a reduction of 40 per cent.  I cannot understand why some of the Senators over there, notably Senator L'Estrange, are so concerned about these questions today when their own people a few short years ago failed so miserably to cope with these problems at all.  They are trying to impress upon us also that the country's economy is not making progress but I say it is making good progress.  In 1957, the national income was £469½ million; in 1962 it was £640 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>What was the £ worth in 1957?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am taking the figures as I find them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>Deal with them in terms of real money.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an increase in the national income of nearly 40 per cent.  In 1957, exports from this country had gone down but in 1963, they were up by 80 per cent.  These are sure indications that the economy is making progress, that it is healthy and that there is no cause for complaint but cause for gratification.  All the trends show we are making progress, despite some of the pessimistic speeches to which we listened here today and yesterday.</P>
      <P>Senator Dooge seemed to be sceptical about the possibility of the fulfilment of the <i>Second Programme for Economic Expansion.</i>  I cannot understand why he should be.  There are certain targets set forth in that Second Programme and if all sections of the people pull their weight and co-operate with the Government, there is no reason why these targets cannot be reached.</P>
      <P>When the <i>First Programme for Economic Expansion</i> was introduced, certain people were also sceptical as to whether the targets laid down would be reached but they were, and they were exceeded, and we have to be thankful for the success that attended our efforts in that regard.  If, as I said, the <i>First Programme for Economic Expansion</i> was fulfilled, there is no reason whatsoever why the Second Programme should not also be fulfilled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="848" /> There was a great deal of talk about agriculture.  One would think by the way some of the speakers over there dealt with the subject that this Government were remiss in their handling of agriculture.  That is far from being the case.  As anybody can see by a perusal of the Book of Estimates, the amount of the Estimate for the Department of Agriculture this year is nearly £24 million.  Side by side with that, there is £9,400,000 for agricultural grants and £8.94 million for the relief of rates on agricultural land, giving a total of £42 million.  Somebody here mentioned the figure £40 million and a look of surprise came over the faces of some of the people on the other side, but the figure, as I have explained, is £42 million.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Against £15 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Against £15 million in the last year of the Coalition Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>And there were 90,100 more people on the land then. Why did 90,000 farming people leave the land since 1956?  That is the number who left, even according to the Tánaiste's figure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Senator name any country where they are not leaving the land?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>They are not leaving it as they are leaving it here.  In every civilised country, the population is increasing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is increasing here, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Since when?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Since 1961.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has no reliable figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator mentioned emigration but I have already stated that emigration is down by 50 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Tánaiste did not say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>We have now reached the position that the natural <Col N="849" /> growth in our population exceeds the emigration from this country today. The Senator should bear that in mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall wait until we see the figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>That has been the position for the past couple of years and we all hope that trend will continue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We should love to see it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I seem to detect a difference of outlook between Senator Dooge and Senator Quinlan as regards the financing of agriculture. Senator Dooge complained, so far as I could understand his point of view, that we are spending more on agriculture than we are getting out of it in return.  That would imply that we are spending money uselessly on agriculture. But Senator Quinlan pointed out today that we are not spending half enough on agriculture.  That illustrates the divergence of view as between the two learned professors. The point all of us should remember is that all a Government can do for the farmers is to provide the necessary aids and incentives and give the necessary directives.  It is up to the farmers then to make the best use of these aids.  A great deal depends on their own efforts. I think the farmers are very much alive to their own requirements and are taking more and more advantage of the aids and incentives given them by the Government.</P>
      <P>Consider the increases that have taken place.  Look at the Book of Estimates.  Indeed, it is not necessary to look at the Book of Estimates at all because the Minister has been good enough to supply us with a list of all the increases for the coming year. Casting an eye over that list one sees that a good many of these increases are directed towards the promotion of agriculture&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>You have £1.6 million less.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>For the civil servants you spoke against in 1946.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;Fóras Talúntais, the farm building scheme, the <Col N="850" /> water supply scheme, lime and fertiliser subsidy, and so on.  There is an item this year of almost £500,000 to finance the heifer purchase scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>You were cutting their throats not so long ago.  This is a welcome change.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>That will prove a very beneficial scheme to the farmers, and the farmers appreciate it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Longford Fianna Fáil convention did not say so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I meet the farmers up and down the country and I know very well they have a céad míle fáilte for this new heifer scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Ask Mr. Moran what they said to him in Longford.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a sum of £500,000 to finance that scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The ranchers are supporting you now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>So are the people of Cork and Kildare.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the people opposite have the temerity to say we should cut that out?  Would they have the temerity to suggest we should cut out the increase given for the lime and fertiliser scheme?  Would they have the temerity to assert we should cut out the increase for An Fóras Talúntais?  Would they have the temerity to say we should cut out the increased grants for agriculture?  They are all here.  There is a figure of about £9,400,000 for agricultural grants. Would the Senators who complain about this increased expenditure say we should cut that figure down?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>You give with one hand and you take back with the other. Why are they not staying on the land? Why did 90,000 leave the land since 1956?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Are they not leaving the land in every country in the world?  They are leaving it even faster in England than they are here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator <Col N="851" /> L'Estrange complained that employment on the land was going down.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Senator not realise that farming at the present time is being highly mechanised?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been mechanised these ten years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>The more farming in this country, or in any country is mechanised, the less employment there will be on the land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>That is nonsense. It has been mechanised these ten years, and there is only half the amount of tillage now.  The farmers are giving up growing wheat.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator say they should give up mechanisation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Would he tell the farmers in his part of the country that they should not buy combine harvesters and all this modern agricultural machinery?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>These were bought years ago and there was tillage then. There is no tillage now.  It has dropped to hell.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Cathaoirleach An Leas-Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The standard of this debate is dropping, too. Senator Ó Ciosaín now, without interruption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange also said he was shocked at the size of the bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, and the Senator himself said the very same thing in 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>If by any chance or misfortune, the Fine Gael people came into office with that programme of theirs&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>God forbid!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that programme they published before the <Col N="852" /> by-elections, how much increased expenditure would that involve?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>All speaking different tongues.  Some think Fine Gael were not going far enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>The programme would cost something like another £100 millions.  The programme is a fantastic one and, of course, the voters of Cork and Kildare realised it is fantastic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>They did not know the cost of living was going up.  That was a fantasy.  They recognise the fantasy when they see it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not so much of fantasy as the speech that said the cost of living would not go up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a programme Fine Gael would be well advised to drop if they want to have any chance at all of success, which is very unlikely, in the foreseeable future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The foreseeable future?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>James Dillon's words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Tell us why 90,000 left the land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Keep quiet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange complained about the lack of information from the Government in relation to the projected sending of a contingent of Irish troops to Cyprus. He said the facts were being concealed from Dáil Éireann.  Dáil Éireann adjourned on a Thursday and there was no demand from any Fine Gael Deputies that the Dáil should sit on Friday so that they might get some more information.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>They were looking for information the week before and they got none.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>The information was not available the week before.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>But it was available the next morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Why was there <Col N="853" /> not a demand then that the Dáil should meet?  This is just another red herring.  The Senator must realise anyhow that nothing can be done about sending a contingent to Cyprus until such time as the matter is brought before Dáil Éireann and Seanad Éireann.  It will certainly be brought before the Dáil.  I remember on the last occasion, when a contingent was sent to the Congo, the matter was brought before the Seanad as well.  The Senator need have no fears.  The Dáil will get an opportunity of discussing fully all the details in relation to this projected contingent.</P>
      <P>As I have said, many things have been mentioned in this debate.  I should like to have an opportunity of dealing with most of them but it would be quite impossible in the time at our disposal.  Senator L'Estrange said that the growth in the economy was not in keeping with the increase in expenditure. I have pointed out that the national income has increased by almost 50 per cent.  I have pointed out that our exports since 1957 have increased by 80 per cent.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at 6 p.m. and resumed at 7 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the House adjourned, I was dealing with the aids and incentives being given to agriculture today by the Government. I pointed out that the financial assistance which the farmers are getting from this Government today is about three and a half times what it was in 1957.  In fact, the farmers themselves are availing of the financial assistance so well&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>That 90,000 of them ran away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;that the value of land has gone up by leaps and bounds within recent years.  I would say that a farm of land that could be purchased for £1,000, say, 30 years ago, would now fetch about £7,000.  In other words, land has gone up about seven times in value as a result of the encouragement the farmers are getting to produce more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="854" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Senator say 30 years ago?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  You cannot get away from that.  There is no doubt about it.  The Senator knows that as well as I do.  In fact, the man with an ordinary amount of capital today finds it very difficult to go into the market and purchase land at all.</P>
      <P>Adverting to the criticism that came from the opposite benches about the increase in the overall expenditure envisaged for the coming year, I invited them to point out where they would effect the economies, whether that would interfere with the financial aid that is being given to the farmers.  I got no reply, of course, to that.  There are also other increases here of a substantial nature.  There are substantial increases for the Department of Local Government for increased expenditure on housing and water and sewerage schemes.  These are very necessary amenities and I do not think anybody on the other side would offer the advice that these items should be taken out of the overall expenditure.</P>
      <P>Now, as I said before, it is not enough to come in here and say that the amount of money required for the coming year is excessive or, as Senator L'Estrange put it, that it was a shocking size of a bill.  If there is to be any sincerity behind that statement, the person who made it should show us exactly where the economies can be effected.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I was quoting what you said in 1956 and 1957, when it was £75 million.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I invite the Senator, and any other Senator over there, to put his finger on any item of expenditure which should be removed from the Bill.  We have an increase in expenditure for the various Departments. I have mentioned the Department of Local Government.  There is a very substantial increase for the Department of Posts and Telegraphs, and included in that amount is £1,545,000 for engineering, stores and equipment.  I hope, as a result of this increase, this extra money that is being made available for stores and engineering services, that it will be possible <Col N="855" /> for the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs to deal with the many applications that there are for the installation of telephones all over the country.  I am given to understand that the demand for telephones, at the present time, is entirely beyond the resources of the Department.  I would go further and say that this demand for installation of telephones all over the country is a sure sign of the growing prosperity of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The 2.8 million who are left in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>There is also an increased provision for tourism.  That is a step in the right direction.  We all know that tourism is a great source of revenue to the country and last year, according to the figures supplied by Bord Fáilte, the amount of money secured from tourism was £57 million. That is a huge sum and it goes to show that tourism contains great potentialities for the economy of the country still.  Any financial aid we can give towards the further development of tourism will be money well spent.  I was intrigued to hear Senator L'Estrange speaking about the encouragement they were giving to the industrial development.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>We gave it in any case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I know what their record has been for the past 30 years in connection with the industrial drive initiated by Fianna Fáil.  Because of the fact that these projects were initiated by Fianna Fáil, there was hostility from Fine Gael.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Never.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>We all remember a few years ago when the then Minister for Industry and Commerce was laying plans for the airport at Shannon, the present Leader of Fine Gael scoffed at the idea and said that in a few years Rineanna would be a barren place with rabbits cavorting around it, playing leapfrog with one another.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Give us the reference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="856" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>That was the encouragement Fine Gael gave to our industrial drive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Senator is going to quote, he should give the reference.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>You are a great man for references.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is only paraphrasing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what Deputy Dillon said about the prospects for Shannon Airport and now it is one of the leading airports in the world. Nobody can deny that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>And it is not overrun by rabbits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>And more luck to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to delay the House any further.  I have pointed out what increases there are to be in the various Departments and I invited Senators who criticise the size of the bill for this year, to show us where economies could be effected. They have not done so and that proves that in their minds they acquiesce in this expenditure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the third Central Fund Bill which I have heard debated in this House since I was elected to it and I must admit to the very greatest difficulty in understanding what is relevant to the debate on this Bill and what is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is not the only one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JRoss" hpid="Mr. Ross Mr. Ross">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Ross</NameTxt>
      <P>I find it extremely difficult because in some years certain matters may be mentioned and in other years the same matters may not be mentioned.  It seems to me that it is really irrelevant to this Bill to debate who was responsible for the initiation of the industrial development of this country.  This Bill, as I see it, provides the opportunity purely to debate the policy that lies behind the issue of moneys out on the Central Fund and the powers of the Minister for Finance to borrow.  Therefore, it seems to me <Col N="857" /> that basically what we should be debating is the present and the future, and not the past.  I cannot see that on this Bill any good is being achieved by anybody debating what happened in 1956 or 1957.  That is a personal non-Party view, but I do not feel that it is getting us anywhere.</P>
      <P>The present signs of the economy, as quoted by Senator O'Brien yesterday from the Central Bank Quarterly Report, are all of a productive&mdash;one might almost say a buoyant&mdash;economy. Industrial exports are up; production is up; savings are up.  Yet I must admit that frankly I am worried about the Government's policy with regard to wages.  I suppose Senator Ó Ciosáin would say that I am one of those who will make a pessimistic speech.  I do not want to make a pessimistic speech but at the same time I do see some reasons for disquiet in the present economic situation.</P>
      <P>When we debated the turnover tax here some months ago, I supported it, although I was in favour of certain modifications.  At that time, and immediately after the tax was introduced, the Government were open to a great deal of criticism which for the most part was ill-informed and ill-conceived. In addition, shortly after the introduction of the tax, the Government were faced with two vital by-elections. I am afraid that faced with those two vital by-elections, they may have been tempted to take a somewhat easy way out of their responsibilities by giving their blessing to the negotiations for the 12 per cent wages increase.</P>
      <P>A couple of days ago the Taoiseach, in London, spoke of the turnover tax and said, rightly, I think, that it had had no appreciable effect upon price rises but he admitted quite openly that the 12 per cent increase in wages would have an effect on prices although he said he hoped that manufacturers would be able to cushion the cost of that increase by spreading it over the next 2½ years of sales.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think this is going to be extremely difficult because there are many industries and commercial enterprises which find themselves faced with an <Col N="858" /> immediate demand for a 12 per cent increase in wages and unless they have been fairly long-standing, unless they have got fairly substantial reserves of profits, they will not find it at all easy to cushion the cost of those increases in wages over their operating profits during the next 2½ years.</P>
    <P>This blow to our manufacturers has come at the same time as another blow, which is, the overall cut in tariff rates of 10 per cent which came into effect on 1st January.  I know of a number of firms which now find themselves quite heavily hit by this double blow.  On the one hand, the wage increase has made it a good deal harder for them to compete in export markets and, on the other hand, the 10 per cent cut in tariffs has made it that much more difficult to compete in the home market.</P>
    <P>I do not for one moment, of course, advocate the reimposition of tariffs and I would certainly encourage the Government in everything that they are doing to make Irish industry stand on its feet in what will eventually be, we hope, free trade conditions.  I entirely support the Government in that but I do want to make the point here that Irish industries as a whole are being asked to bear a burden which they may find difficult in the long run and certainly will find it difficult temporarily to bear and may even find in some cases that it is too heavy for them.</P>
    <P>Again, as the Taoiseach said in London, manufacturing industry here cannot depend solely on the home market and if we are to survive as a manufacturing country we have got to depend on and live by exports.  But these new burdens, of 12 per cent on the one hand in the wages increase and the tariff cut on the other, came at a time when we are facing further difficulties in any exports which we try to put into EEC countries because those countries are themselves raising their own tariffs against us and some Irish companies which I know of and which were exporting to Italy and Western Germany two years ago now find that those markets are closed to them because the increased tariffs abroad have made these markets quite impossible for them to enter.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="859" /> These are serious threats to our manufacturing position and serious threats to the Second Programme.  I believe that they have arisen to some extent because the Government moved a little too fast and a little too optimistically in encouraging what seem to me to be excessive wage claims and, as a result of this, we may in a very short time find ourselves in a serious balance of payments position or, as Senator O'Brien put it yesterday, we face the risk of inflation caused by rising incomes and rising prices.</P>
    <P>The answer to the problem is pretty easy, perhaps, on paper, although basically there is only one answer, that is, that Irish industry must achieve greater efficiency and greater productivity. But that is very easy to say and not quite so easy to achieve in practice and, with the undoubted cold draught that is now about to sweep, if it is not already sweeping, across some of our manufacturing industries, many of them will be in difficulties&mdash;I will not go so far as to say serious difficulties &mdash;but difficulties, in the fairly near future.  These do not show now.  They will only show in the statistical returns in the next three or four months and after that and, in three or four months' time, we may find a somewhat frightening position and it may not be such an optimistic picture as we see at the moment.</P>
    <P>Of course, it is true that if the 12 per cent increase can be restricted, as was negotiated, to a two-and-a-half year period&mdash;in other words, if there is no further increase over two-and-half years&mdash;we may, and we all hope we will, of course, get over these difficulties and towards the end of that period, where we can remain static as regards wages, we are obviously bound to get some relief from the fact that wages in European countries are undoubtedly rising at the same time. These are countries which are competing with us and we may, therefore, be in a less unfavourable competitive position in another year or two years' time.</P>
    <P>The real problem, of course, is increased productivity and increased <Col N="860" /> efficiency and, as Senator Ó Ciosáin said, if all the people co-operate with the Government, all will be well.  It is easy to make appeals to people; it is easy to say to the employers: &ldquo;You must do your part&rdquo; and to the employees: &ldquo;you must do your part&rdquo; and to the unions: &ldquo;you must do your part&rdquo;; but it is another thing when the spiral of the increased wages begins to affect the supply of goods and, in turn, once again, affect wage claims.  If we are to succeed in capturing overseas markets it will need a lot more than platitudinous appeals to employers, employees and unions and all of us will have to work extremely hard to arrive at a fair and reasonable understanding of the national problem.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Brien said yesterday that not all the credit for the present national prosperity should go to the Government.  Well, that is fair enough but, equally, it is only fair to say that many of those enlightened industrialists who have done such sterling work in setting industries on their feet and in getting exports from this country would not have been able to achieve very much if it had not been for the very considerable financial help and very considerable encouragement they have got from the Government and from the semi-Government organisations. In my view, credit should be given to the Government for the vigour and enthusiasm with which they have pursued the first Economic Programme.  Whoever may have instigated it, they produced it and carried it through and they have produced the draft of the Second Programme.  Here, again, my fears frankly arise because if the present wage agreement for 12 per cent is to last for two-and-a-half years, it will require a great deal of real courage on the part of the Government to see that the country, employers and employees' unions, stick to that agreement.</P>
    <P>The Government must do everything in their power to keep the country at the 12 per cent level for the next two and a half years.  Before that expires, we shall probably find ourselves in the middle of general election.  I think it is inevitable that the Government <Col N="861" /> will have to face increased wage demands between now and the general election or between now and the end of the two and a half years.  As the effects of the 12 per cent appear in the cost of living, the demands will start to come and that will be the time for the Government to show their courage and integrity and to be firm because if they do not, we shall inevitably be in a period of inflation and our manufacturers will face difficulties possibly too great for many of them to overcome. If that situation arises, I fear the Second Programme may be in danger.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>It is regrettable that the Minister finds it necessary to effect an economy in the Estimates for the Department of Agriculture at a time when farm produce prices have remained almost static over the past ten years.  During that period every other section of the community have enjoyed and benefited from round after round wage increases.  At a time when the Government have permitted a 12 per cent increase to every other section of the community except the farmers, last week the Taoiseach attacked a reputable farming organisation, the NFA, for asserting the right to secure a living wage for their members.</P>
      <P>The NFA have obviously put a lot of thought and energy into their programme and it is extraordinary to find that the professed policy of the Government seems to be to increase the standard of living of every section of the community and at the same time to force a lower standard on the farmers.  The Government and Government Senators are always seeking constructive criticism and suggestions and yet when the NFA, after exhaustive thought, submit their Green Book, the Taoiseach sees fit to convene a city convention of Fianna Fáil to make a skit of their achievement and castigate their efforts.  He had no qualms of conscience in seeking and providing more than £40 million for an injection into our economy in order to win the 12 per cent by-elections of Cork and Kildare.  It is significant that he made his speech in a Dublin constituency, not a rural one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="862" /> The Minister, in his introductory speech, told us the total expenditure on agriculture in 1964-65 will amount to £33 million, or 18 per cent of the total Estimate.  Most people, especially urban populations, have the mistaken idea that farmers are actually living on grants and subsidies and have little to do but draw them.  Looking over the Book of Estimates, I find that, contrary to the public belief, a very high proportion of this 18 per cent is accounted for by wages and expenses and salaries.  To take one item, in Vote 40, M.3, we find the total estimate for expenditure under that subhead is £73,642.  Of that, there is a total for salaries and employers' contributions under the Social Welfare Acts amounting to £48,387.  Travelling expenses of officials amount to £23,000 which leaves only £2,000 for the scheme itself.  The same trend is continued right through a considerable number of the subheads in this Estimate.</P>
    <P>In M.4 we find that of a total provided for expenditure under the subhead of £260,828, salaries and travelling expenses amount to £260,000.  There are many more instances I could quote and yet people are led to believe, and some would like them to believe, that all the £33 million in this Estimate goes directly into the farmers' pockets.  I do not deny that the services provided by this Estimate benefit the community but it is also true that they are more of a national than of a sectional benefit to the farmers alone.</P>
    <P>There are many items in this Estimate which do not really belong to the agricultural section and I cannot understand why they are included.  We see quite considerable sums for university colleges, grants to county committees of agriculture of over £500,000, of which I venture to say at least threequarters goes on administration. We have a contribution of £9,000 to the Irish Countrywomen's Association; to An Foras Talúntais of almost £1 million, to the Botanic Gardens, Glasnevin of £53,085.  Right through we find a number of headings which most people would not associate with agriculture.</P>
    <P>On page 173, we find a scheme of <Col N="863" /> grants for calved-heifers which Senator Ó Ciosáin found delight in praising but which I believe&mdash;when I see that there is only £405,000 provided to pay grants of £15 each for calf-heifers to an agricultural community of 360,000 farmers&mdash;cannot in the coming year provide even a single grant for one farmer out of every 15.  I believe this ridiculous scheme was designed solely as a vote-catching device and I can only classify it as fit to be included with the schemes for the Egyption bee, brown trout and chinchillas because, to my mind, they are all in the same category. I cannot understand why some sums are not put into the Votes for the appropriate Departments.  For instance, all the moneys expended on agricultural colleges, schools and university faculties should be included under Education.  Sizeable sums are spent on technical education of various kinds and we do not find them coming in under Industry and Commerce.</P>
    <P>Substantial grants are given to industrialists who set up new industries. They also have tax-free concessions as an inducement to production.  This is a good policy and I should like to see it being continued, but the same does not apply to the farmer.  He pays a levy on the production of wheat, milk, pigs and bacon.  That is most unfair when industrialists can get tax concessions for increased production.  More often than not, when the farmer looks for an increase, he is told: &ldquo;Increased production is all you need&rdquo;.  On that basis, when the industrial section of the community look for an increase they should be told: &ldquo;Work overtime, work harder, and then you can get more money&rdquo;.  It is unfair to tell the rural community, when they look for an increase, that they must work overtime.  The time has come when the Government must give this section of the community the last six rounds and bring them into line with the remainder of the community.  They are a sizeable proportion of our community. They are directly responsible for at least 75 per cent of our exports. Those exports are 100 per cent exports. They include no re-exports.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="864" /> Two years ago the Minister reduced the rate of taxation on agricultural tractors.  That was a welcome and a wise move.  I believe in the interests of the economy he could go a step further and encourage the use of dualpurpose vehicles on farms.  I am thinking of something like a saloon on a jeep chassis which could replace motor cars in some farms with great benefit. There are many jobs which could be done by a vehicle of this type, especially during the peak season in the spring and at harvest time.  I do not suggest farmers should not have motor cars, but if these vehicles were on the lower rate of taxation, they would be used more widely.</P>
    <P>I should like to draw the Minister's attention to the policy of the Government of grouping counties for the purpose of the Bovine TB Eradication Scheme.  In some of these groups, farmers have to travel up to 50 miles to these offices.  In the siting of these offices, the farmers' interests are completely ignored.  I know of one office in Naas, the property of the Board of Works, where farmers have to climb four flights of stairs and wait to be interviewed one at a time at a yard-long counter in a rickety old building. The farming community of two of the best tillage counties in Ireland should not be treated in this fashion.  It is no credit to the Board of Works to have a building such as that.</P>
    <P>I often wonder what plans the Department of Agriculture have for horticulture, having regard to the increasing urbanisation of the country and the ever-increasing demand for fresh vegetables.  I know Comhlucht Siuicre Éireann have established a vegetable and fruit processing industry, but I feel that industry does not meet the ever-increasing demand for fresh vegetables.  This branch of agriculture has not been referred to very much and I should like to see more thought given to it.  I should like the Minister to intimate if the Department have any section dealing with this activity.</P>
    <P>I believe that when creditworthy semi-State companies come to make demands on the State, the time is ripe for the Government to realise that <Col N="865" /> those demands should be met by public subscription.  It was desirable that the State should have taken the initiative in establishing these enterprises; but now that they are firmly established and employ a large number of people, it is only right that they should be handed back to the people, that the people should take a more active interest in them and reap some benefit from them.  If the workers in these enterprises had an opportunity of investing some of their savings in them, I believe they would have a personal interest in the well-being of those companies.</P>
    <P>I should like to refer to the Government's campaign to keep the roads safe.  I believe the Government can do much more in this matter.  It is regrettable that so many people are being killed on the roads.  The Minister for Justice in his law reform activities should take a more active interest in this daily slaughter on the roads and should direct the attention of the Garda to the problem of the drunken driver.  Any Senator who leaves this city from 10.45 p.m. to 11.30 p.m. knows the large number of queer drivers he will meet.  I travel out the Naas road and am always glad to get past the city because the standard of driving at night is deplorable. The Government could increase the number of Garda motor cycle patrols, which are the most effective way of apprehending these drivers. There also could be more equality in the sentences meted out to the few convicted.  It was extraordinary to read in the paper three weeks ago of a student being fined&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot allow the Senator to criticise court decisions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support the Minister for Local Government in his drive to keep the roads safe.  That is a very worthy policy.  I should also like to thank the Chair for its indulgence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>The Book of Estimates which we are, in effect, discussing here today discloses, on its face, an increased demand for £16 million.  For some reason or another, <Col N="866" /> that is not the whole story.  I understand there is a notable omission from the Book of Estimates, and that notable omission is provision for the ninth round of wage increases.  Perhaps the Minister, when replying, will tell us why that was not included in the Book of Estimates.</P>
      <P>I understand this ninth round was paid very promptly.  In fact, I had the unique experience of meeting a civil servant who had not received the eighth round increase which is still going on, but had got the ninth round. Maybe there is some significance in that.  It is difficult to see why it was not included in the Book of Estimates. If it were included, the total demand would show an increase of about £23 million or £24 million on last year. There is no use in saying that is a record.  Everyone knows it is a record, and everyone has come to expect records of that type from the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I want to dwell briefly on the increase in the cost of living brought about by direct Government action, and the effect of that increased cost of living on the country and on the people.  Some 12 months ago, by direct action, the Government increased the cost of living.  At that time they were warned that the proposals which they had initiated would have the effect of increasing the cost of living, but it was said that that was not so.  At any rate the cost of living did increase, as everyone who faced the position honestly knew it would increase.  When the cost of living increased, in order to compensate itself, organised labour demanded an increase in wages.  It was entitled to demand it.  The Taoiseach anticipated that demand by organised labour, and sought to take credit for the inevitable.  The ninth round, or the 12 per cent, whichever you like to call it, came, and came rapidly.  The Taoiseach, being a slick politician whatever else we may say about him, rushed into the traffic and gave the green light.  It was forecast again by anyone who gave the matter any thought, that this further increase in wages would again set off an increase in the cost of living.  Again we were told that would not happen, but it did happen as we all know, and the fact of the matter now is that we are in the <Col N="867" /> mídst of a contest between organised labour and organised industry.</P>
    <P>On the one hand, organised labour is trying to protect itself from the increased cost of living, by justifiably demanding increased wages, and on the other hand industry and the providers of essential services are seeking to recoup themselves for the increased wages by increasing the cost to the consumer of essential goods and services. That has all been brought about by the action of the Government, and there is no use in denying it.  It is a fairly strenuous contest; it is a contest that will go on; and it is a contest in which I fear a number of interests and a number of people will be injured, as happens in all conflicts.</P>
    <P>In the first place, I think the export drive will be irreparably damaged in this conflict.  I think we are about to price ourselves out of the world markets which we are supposed to be trying to capture.  There is no use in saying wages are going up all over Europe, and going up in England.  It is all right to have wages going up in highly-industrialised countries with a long tradition of industry, technique, know-how, and equipment behind them.  If we are to compete with those countries in world markets, we can do so only by keeping down our costs of production, because we are not yet able to compete with them in technique, know-how or equipment.</P>
    <P>Direct Government action, and direct Government policy, are forcing up costs of production, and there is not very much use in the Minister for Industry and Commerce going to a chamber of commerce dinner in Galway, or anywhere else, and saying the ninth round need not, and should not, increase costs of production, and telling those people that the increase in wages should be provided for out of increased production and more efficiency. If that were so you would expect State concerns and semi-State bodies to give a lead, show how that could be done, and demonstrate to private enterprise that it is not necesary to increase the cost of goods or essential services to make up for the increase in wages.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="868" /> I turn first to the Verolme dockyard in Cork.  I know it is not a State-owned enterprise, but there is certainly a lot of public money in it.  We know that concern has paid the 12 per cent, and that it fears it will be less able now than ever to compete in world markets.  It fears it will be put out of business.  That is, perhaps, a bad example, but we have CIE.  On payment of the 12 per cent, CIE promptly increased passenger fares and freight costs all over the country by 10 per cent, admitting thereby that it is able to absorb only 2 per cent. I venture to suggest that, before the end of the year, there will be a demand from CIE to the Exchequer for the remaining two per cent.  Again, maybe CIE is not the best example one could take. We may be told that it is only getting over its growing pains.</P>
    <P>Take another example: take the Sugar Company, one of the oldest industrial concerns in the country.  This is a concern whose raw material is produced at home, a concern with 40 years' experience behind it, a concern managed by an individual who is accepted, I think, as one of the best industrial brains in this country.  That man tells us that he cannot absorb in the Irish Sugar Company the 12 per cent which he has to pay and he gives facts and figures to support his statement that it is necessary for him to pass on the 12 per cent to the consuming public.  I merely give these examples.  I know the Government do not agree that this is necessary and have taken the unprecedented step of clamping down.  I wonder, however, when the inquiry is held, and when the Sugar Company has made its case, will the 12 per cent be passed on, or will it not.  I venture to suggest it will. Therefore I say that Government policy will damage the export effort.</P>
    <P>We are told that this 12 per cent is a payment in advance.  The Taoiseach has stated on a few occasions that the economy of the country could not afford the 12 per cent and the payment of this 12 per cent now is really in anticipation of a growth that it is hoped will take place over the next two and a half years.  As I understand <Col N="869" /> it, however, organised labour have accepted this 12 per cent as sufficient for 2½ years, provided things remain as they are and provided there is no increase in the cost of living.  Does anybody seriously think, remembering the trend of events, that this 12 per cent will last for 2½ years?  Senator Ross&mdash;he made a most temperate speech&mdash;has his doubts.  I think we all have our doubts.  I think we know what will happen before the end of the year.</P>
    <P>The export drive will be injured by Government policy and by this contest created as a result of Government policy.  There are many people who are unable to protect themselves from the increasing cost of living.  They will be injured.  The small farmer will suffer because the gap between his standard of living and the industrial standard of living will be widened. The middle classes, some of whom are living on modest incomes, will suffer in this contest.  People who are living on pensions, pensions which will not and cannot be adjusted, will be severely hit in this struggle.  I wonder what will happen to people who invested some years ago against old age or death by insuring their lives for what then appeared to them to be an adequate sum.  How will they be hit in this struggle?</P>
    <P>The value of money is being drastically reduced.  My own opinion is that, if this trend continues, if money continues to lose its value as a result of Government policy, people will think twice before investing in insurance. They will regard it as not very safe. Government policy has also forced up the rates paid by every ratepayer.  The Taoiseach, with a finger on the political pulse, says rates have reached the stage when something will have to be done about them, but it will be a longterm policy: Live horse and you will get grass.  The rates are a crippling burden.  It may be argued that agricultural holdings up to a certain valuation get generous relief.  That is so. What about the small towns already sorely hit by the drift from the land, the drift the Minister says is inevitable? Whether or not it is inevitable&mdash;I do not think it is&mdash;it is a fact.  The drift <Col N="870" /> from the land is crippling the small shopkeepers in the small towns of rural Ireland.  While their customer clientele is being depleted, the rates are being piled on.  I should like to know what will be done to remedy the position and when will it be done.</P>
    <P>Senator Ó Ciosáin quoted a great many figures to prove various things.  He asked us to compare the value of land now with the value of land 30 years ago.  I wonder did he realise the significance of that comparison?  Imagine asking a person to compare the value of land in 1934 with the value of land in 1964.  Suppose we compare the price of cattle in 1934 with the price of cattle in 1964.  You would get a decent bullock in 1934 for 50/-.  That is the sort of comparison we are asked to accept by Senator Ó Ciosáin.  It is not very sensible.</P>
    <P>He asks us to compare the national income of 1957 with the national income at the present time but he does not compare the value of money then with the value of money now.  Jibes have been thrown across the floor here in the past two days about Cork and Kildare.  The Government won the by-elections in Cork and Kildare and I wish them luck in their victory.  I hope they are as pleased and as proud about it at the end of this year or at the beginning of next year as they are now.  I should like to ask them what they think the result of that election would be if it were fought even now. It was fought on the basis that prices would not go up.  It was fought on the assurance of the Tánaiste given only a couple of days before the election that the price of bread would not go up.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It was fought on the Fine Gael policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder can the Tánaiste be so far removed from reality as to believe that the price of bread would not go up two days before, in fact, it went up.  As I have said, Government policy has increased the cost of living and has increased it with effects which will be injurious to the country as a whole and will inflict <Col N="871" /> agriculture.  I am sure Senator severe hardship on the average person in the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Like Senator Ross, I was rather surprised to hear a repetition of statements I have heard since I came into the House two and a half years ago.  I was hoping that even at this stage Senator L'Estrange would have grown up and would have begun to look to the future.  I was also hoping he would have read the statement of the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance in the Dáil last week in which he urged us to forget the past and to look to the future.  If he has not read the statement, I would refer him to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>When you are ashamed of the past, you like to forget it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We are very proud of the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not ashamed of the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We are good Christians.  We have a lot to forgive but we forgive.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We forgive even the Blueshirts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I have listened for the past two and a half years to the prophecies of the Fine Gael speakers on the other side of the House and none of the prophecies has come true.  I feel their prognostications this evening will not come true either, because the indications are that the country is in a sound economic position.  Some famous man once said&mdash;and I shall concede the Shannon Scheme and the sugar industry: &ldquo;If you are looking for a monument to me, look around you.&rdquo; That applies to the Government today. Look around: the evidence is there. It is there in regard to emigration. Figures have been quoted and somebody has said that statistics can prove many things.  However, the Catholic Social Welfare Bureau, Emigration Section, have noted the fall in emigration and said that as a result they are able to contact a greater percentage <Col N="872" /> of the total.  The total, as we have heard during interjections here this evening, is now 16,000 people.</P>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange stated that we had the lowest rural population of any of the European countries.  He is not quite correct.  I refer him to a book issued by the ICMSA in which it is stated that France has a lower proportionate rural population than Ireland. It also states that it is incorrect to equate the decline in the Irish rural population with the current decline in rural populations in many European countries.</P>
      <P>It is time we got away from the catch-cries about emigration and unemployment because they no longer apply.  I know from personal experience the people have now confidence in themselves and faith in the future and in the economic development of this country.  While it may have been popular politically to decry the progress made over the years, in the future that will not apply.  The man who does not give credit where credit is due will find that he will have very few followers.</P>
      <P>Senator O'Brien stated yesterday that it was now fashionable to have a deficit in the Budget.  If ever that happens here, we shall be in very good company since that policy was advocated by no less a man than the late President Kennedy who was received so well in this Parliament on the occasion of his visit prior to his lamented death, and I am sure we shall all be very happy to follow the very good example of that great man.</P>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange recalled to my mind something said in a letter by an Irish archbishop not in this twentieth century but over three hundred years ago, and it would be an apt quotation for Senator L'Estrange to make.  The letter deplored the lack of commodities, the evil quality of the beer, the prevalence of spotted fever, smallpox and catarrh, the lack of money in trade by reason of the war, the laziness of farmers and the fact that one-third of the population was living on its wits.  Senator L'Estrange and those other pessimists among us should ponder on that quotation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator McDonald was critical of the amount of money available for <Col N="873" /> McDonald is as intelligent as any member of this House and he must have read in the Estimates that the reduction was due to the completion almost of the bovine TB eradication programme.  He must concede that the Department have provided an advisory service for the western counties and that most of the counties have already implemented that service. The Senator cannot have it both ways, on the one hand decrying the amount of money being spent, and, on the other, telling us that not enough money is being spent.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator was quoting America.  Why not quote England where £20 million more is being spent on agriculture?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I read this morning's paper and I have heard no reference here to the fact that there will be increased prices for fat cattle and no reference here to the current prices for cattle.  I heard a lot this time last year about the terrible conditions the farmers were facing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CharlesBMcDonald" hpid="Mr. McDonald Mr. McDonald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McDonald</NameTxt>
      <P>The farmers in the midlands were almost bankrupt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Anyhow, Britain is more of an industrial country than an agricultural country and I presume their percentage could not be as high as ours.  As I said at the outset, it is not the past to which we should be looking but the future.  A Government can only spend the amount of money they collect from the people. We are living in an age when people are demanding services.  The rates have increased this year as a result of the demands of the people.  If the people require services, they must pay for them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I pointed out on a previous occasion, no Government have a hole in the ground out of which they can dig money every time they want it. They must depend on the people through taxation and there will be criticism if money is not provided for those particular services.  Senator L'Estrange said it was a question of making the rich richer and the poor poorer but he forgot to mention the fact that the people in the Social <Col N="874" /> Welfare class were cushioned against the impact of the 2½ per cent tax. Credit has been taken from the Taoiseach for his very fine achievement, to my mind, in bringing the trade union movement and the employers of this country together and getting them to agree, on a national basis, on a wage agreement.  I think that is one of the finest achievements, apart from our political achievements in the past, that this country has to its credit.  I think he has brought credit to both trade unions and employers and I think we should not decry his efforts in this respect.  It is to the benefit of the community as a whole that such a thing has happened and that we have become mature in this country, that we can sit down and discuss our problems and iron them out for the benefit of the general body of the people.</P>
    <P>If I have any criticism to offer it would be on two points.  One is in relation to Telefís Éireann.  I see the Chair looking askance at me, but when I raised this matter on a previous Vote in relation to the Department of Posts and Telegraphs I was told I would get an opportunity to raise it on the Vote on Account.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not the Vote on Account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Somebody told me today that it was the Vote on Account. I should like the matter clarified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Mr. Fitzpatrick Mr. Fitzpatrick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzpatrick</NameTxt>
      <P>It shows the Senator does not know what he is talking about.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>This matter is not appropriate on the Central Fund Bill. The Vote on Account does not come before the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephMooney" hpid="Mr. Mooney Mr. Mooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Mooney</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as the condition of the country is concerned, as I have pointed out, the evidence is there that economically we are developing.  We have had our political past.  We are now looking to the future with confidence and hope, and no greater indication of that confidence and hope has been given than the result of the by-elections in Cork and Kildare.  I have heard no reference at all today <Col N="875" /> in the House to a general election. There was a reference made by Senator Ross that the present lifetime of the Oireachtas will be completed in 2½ years' time.</P>
      <P>There is the question of money. Money is circulating more freely than ever in this country.  That is admitted by people whether they support the Government or not.  As someone said to me, there is no house or home in the country into which money is not going in some shape or form.  As George Bernard Shaw said, on one occasion, a civilised country depends on the circulation of its money as much as a living animal depends on the circulation of its blood.  That is in evidence today in this country.  We now use the term &ldquo;affluent society&rdquo;. Actually, Senator L'Estrange, although he may not have known it, gave us credit for that fact when he made an appeal to buy Irish.  He said we were so well off now that we were inclined to forget that Irish goods were on the market and that we were buying Italian goods.  That was a fair indication of Government progress in that particular instance.</P>
      <P>I should like to join with other Senators in making an appeal for road safety.  I disagree with Senator McDonald in the case of night driving. There is a terrible lack of courtesy, which all the laws in the world will not prevent unless the person behind the wheel exercises the courtesy that he should exercise.  Anybody travelling at night will see there is no response to dimming, and if there is a response it is by a minimum of people travelling on the road.  Some people go out of their way to put on extra lights in order to blind the oncoming traveller. I agree with Senator McDonald's suggestion that if the gardaí became more active in their cars and motor cycles and made a few surprise exits from the by-roads on to some of our main roads they would help to cut down the carnage that is taking place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonallOConallain" hpid="Dónal Ó Conalláin Dónal Ó Conalláin">
      <NameTxt>Dónal Ó Conalláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to detain the House very long.  I am becoming more and more bemused at what is relevant and what is not, but <Col N="876" /> I hope I shall not transgress so far anyhow from the straight and narrow as to incur the disfavour of the Chair. I share with most people, I suppose, the shock of the increased bill with which we are presented this year and I share with them also&mdash;or with most people I suppose&mdash;their apprehension as to how long this can go on.  This year our bill is some £16 million more than it was last year.  Last year it was more than it was the year before and the question which occurs to people is how long can this go on.  I do not think that these increasing costs from year to year are necessarily bad.  It all depends on whether the economy can absorb them or not.  It is difficult for a person in my position with no affiliations to come to a conclusion.  I am depending really on the interpretation of statistics made by a number of people on both sides of the House who profess to be able to interpret them accurately.  Personally, I have sufficient confidence in the Government and in their advisers, to believe that they will not let the situation get out of hand, that they will keep control to the extent of making the country safe.  Of course, I do share with Senator Ross the fears that perhaps their motives may in some instances be open to suspicion.</P>
      <P>As I have said, it is difficult for me to come to any definite conclusion because, on the one hand, we have people here telling us we are heading for disaster and, on the other hand, another group telling us we are heading for the millennium.  Whatever prognostication is correct, it appears to me that one aspect of our economy will have to be looked after.  One aspect of our life will have to be looked after and that is the educational aspect, whether education is going to be necessary, whether it is disaster or the millennium, either to cope with the disaster or to enjoy the millennium.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>During this current period of comparative prosperity I believe that a comparably high proportion of our resources should be devoted to raising our educational standards.  The Book of Estimates which we have all been examining recently would not give any substance to the view that the Government think on the same lines.  After <Col N="877" /> all, only a small proportion of the increase is devoted to education and of that increase only a minimum proportion&mdash;I think 15 per cent&mdash;is devoted to secondary or post-primary education, and it is in relation to post-primary education that we hear all the grandiose schemes for raising the standards among our people and giving them new skills and a new and higher interest in the things of life.</P>
    <P>I should like at this stage to welcome specifically two provisions that have been made in the line of secondary education.  One is the building grants to secondary schools which have been announced, and which I take it are to some extent provided for in the Estimates, and the second is the increase in capitation that is noted in the Estimates.</P>
    <P>Since the total increase in the Estimate for secondary education is only in the region of £500,000, I begin to have fears that the percentage to be devoted to building grants is not to be very large.  This is a measure which has been awaited for a great number of years.  Everybody has been clamouring for it and it is long overdue.  I hope that now it will be done in a generous way but I do not think that within the compass of the amount being granted this year for secondary education there is any prospect of a very generous grant.  I suppose it might not be more than 40 per cent, whereas in Northern Ireland and England the minimum grant for building purposes is about 65 per cent.  Anyhow I want to welcome these two provisions.</P>
    <P>There is no need to reiterate what everybody professes to believe, namely, that the best form of investment in modern times in a developing country is investment in education.  All Parties have agreed that is so, but a remarkable feature of this apparent consensus of opinion is that none of them seems to think that the most fundamental form of investment in education is to pay teachers adequately.  They do not seem to believe that a happy, contented teaching body is one of the first requirements in any system of education. As a teacher, I can assure them that that is so.  I speak now for all grades of teachers.  Peculiarly enough, <Col N="878" /> too, most people say that in every country teachers are underpaid.  Well, surely it is time some country took the initiative and we with our buoyant economy should not be the last to do so.</P>
    <P>As a representative of the graduates of National University, I took particular interest in what the Taoiseach had to say the other night in London to a meeting of emigrant graduates of National University.  He is recorded as saying this country had now become the land of opportunity for graduates of National University.  Now, we may make due allowance for the fact that at this function everything was being viewed through green-tinted glasses and that he was selling the country as it were, but if we examine that statement, particularly in the light that it was to a graduate audience, I think the element of hyperbole was a little too much.  We all know that a great proportion of our graduates go abroad each year and that a great number of them are discouraged from coming back and that the opportunities, if they do come back, are still very few.  They may be increasing slowly but still the opportunities are very limited for them here.  To describe Ireland as the land of opportunity for graduates is really going too far.  However, the phrase must have been selected because I note that on the very same evening in Portland, Maine, Deputy Noel Lemass used the very same expression when referring to Ireland.  That is significant. However, as I say, we will have to take it with a grain of salt.</P>
    <P>The Taoiseach did not tell the teaching members of the graduates whom he met that if they did come back to teach in corresponding schools here, they would have to begin at the bottom of the salary scale, irrespective of the number of years service they had in England.  Neither did he tell them that if they did come back as secondary teachers, graduates with a higher diploma, they would reach a salary, on a scale, of £1,215 per annum. That compares with other occupations not requiring graduate status, such as a bank clerk or some such person, who reaches a maximum salary of <Col N="879" /> £1,440 without any promotion.  The teacher in order to reach £1,215 must be a married teacher.  There is a differentiated scale for him but there is no such scale for the bank clerk.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry, but the Senator is becoming a little detailed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonallOConallain" hpid="Dónal Ó Conalláin Dónal Ó Conalláin">
      <NameTxt>Dónal Ó Conalláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to submit as a matter of policy that it is very little encouragement to our graduates to come home to work here while this sort of thing prevails. Secondly, which is worse, it is very little encouragement to people of ability in the country to look for higher education, to go to university and to make the sacrifices entailed in doing four or five years at the university, if there is this tendency to depress their salaries and their status in the community. This is the most grievous aspect of the whole thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Would Senator Ó Conalláin tell us who fixes the salaries for university appointments and posts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>No, he may not at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>I had not intended to speak in this debate and I am sure the House will have noted that the members on this bench have kept very quiet for the past 24 hours.  We have been more or less obliged to, but I am prompted to rise before the debate concludes because of the number of references from both sides of the House to what has been described in some cases as a blessing and in others as a curse, that is, this very much talked about 12 per cent wages increase. It is well for us to put the record straight on this matter.  Too much said about it at this stage would do more harm than good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has been a feature of the debate that almost every speaker seemed to give the full credit for giving that money to the Government.  With all due respect, even with full respect, to the Government, I should like to bring the House back to reality on this point. The Government have handed out nothing in this 12 per cent.  Let us face <Col N="880" /> the fact.  They have not been responsible. They are not entitled to credit for the 12 per cent any more than any individual in this House.  Let us put it straight.  The fact is that an adjustment in salaries and wages was necessary because of the rise in the cost of living and the trade union movement simply did its job in the matter by putting that fact squarely before the country as a whole, including the Government.</P>
    <P>In dealing with the situation that arose from that position, I give the Government full credit for having taken the initiative of bringing the unions and employers together.  That had been attempted previously and it had failed and, indeed, there were quite a number of people, even people in this House, who were pessimistic enough on this occasion to say that the attempt would fail again; but it did not deter the Government from making an attempt.  The attempt was made and this time it did not fail.  I give the Government full credit for that.</P>
    <P>But, when we come to this question of 12 per cent, we ought to be honest enough to recognise that the 12 per cent is a cold formula worked out in long and laborious negotiations, which took quite a long time, quite a number of weeks, in fact, before even a semblance of formula was arrived at. It was worked out in that cold, calculated way and based entirely on a factual appraisal of all the factors and considerations that have to be taken into account in arriving at any such formula.</P>
    <P>The 12 per cent compensates for a certain rise that has already taken place in the cost of living since the last adjustment of wages was worked out two years ago.  It also takes into account the further increase in the cost of living occasioned by the turnover tax and it does provide a small margin, not more than somewhere between three and four per cent, of a look into the future, in the real sense, in fact, a certain compensatory factor for the people for whom the trade unions speak, by reason of what is claimed to be the growth in the national product.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="881" /> The formula is that and nothing more.  But let us be clear.  Any spokesman we heard prior to the signing of the agreement between the employers and the unions&mdash;everybody, in fact, from the Taoiseach down&mdash;if they were on record at all went on record as saying that the country could not afford more than seven or eight or nine per cent.  Is that not so?</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>Having said all that, I think it will not serve either the country or the workers to any great extent, at this juncture, to hold an inquest as to who was or who was not responsible for the 12 per cent.  My only function here is to put these facts on record because they are available.</P>
      <P>I want to close by urging the Minister also to put that record straight and to make it clear to everybody concerned, to both sides of this House and through the House to the public at large, that, in fact, the Government had to agree to a 12 per cent adjustment in wages and salaries, that they had no option but to do so.  The Minister will be serving the country, serving the people and certainly serving the trade unions and everybody else, by making that fact quite clear to all concerned and let us finish the humbug about the 12 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Minister for Finance (Dr. Ryan) James Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Dr. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I want, first of all, to say that I listened with great interest to Senator Dooge's speech on the Second Programme and I should like, certainly, to congratulate him on the close study he made of this programme.  Otherwise, he could not have spoken in such detail as he did.</P>
      <P>I want to say also that this book that was published was an outline of the Second Programme and a detailed book will be published within a month or two.  Many of the questions dealt with by Senator Dooge will be dealt with in detail in the Second Book when it comes out, and for that reason I shall deal only with a few of the points raised by him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>First of all, he spoke about the 2 per cent target in the First Programme where we actually got four per cent <Col N="882" /> and&mdash;I am not sure if he said so plainly&mdash;he suggested that we had the same kind of procedure in mind in the Second Programme and when we put down four per cent or 4.3 per cent, we actually expected to get more.  I can assure Senator Dooge that we did not expect to get more in the First Programme when we were drawing it up and we do not expect to get more under the Second Programme.  We are glad, of course, that we got more than we expected in the First Programme and I suppose every Senator is glad also.  We have never claimed to be infallible and, of course, I need hardly tell the Seanad that the Government are entirely dependent on various opinions put to them in a case like this by economists, financiers, and so on, and they have got the best result they can out of all these opinions that were put up to them.</P>
    <P>Some public commentators have suggested that the present target for the Second Programme is too high. The Government do not share that view because we can generally assume that we should do as well between now and 1970 as we did for the past three or four years and, therefore, I think we are not too ambitious in the Second Programme.</P>
    <P>The National Industrial Economic Council, which is composed, as Senators are aware, of the leaders of industry, leaders of the trade union movement and certain Government nominees, have approved of the programme. They say that it is a realistic programme as far as they can examine it but they say that existing firms and industry will have to prepare effectively for the changes which lie ahead if expansion is to be given priority in the formation of this economic policy.  I think we all agree on that, that everybody must plan to the very utmost to achieve this Second Programme and I think we are getting that co-operation among, as I said, everybody concerned&mdash; industrialists, trade unionists and everybody else.</P>
    <P>Senator Dooge then referred to the Control of Manufactures Act.  I think we made very clear what our policy is there in paragraph 57.  I quote it:</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="883" /> The Government will, in due course, submit proposals to the Oireachtas for the repeal of the Control of Manufactures legislation; no obstacle must be placed in the way of the external investment which will complement our own efforts to achieve the growth targets.</P>
    <P>I think Senator L'Estrange mentioned that the Government had on a previous occasion, back in 1933, brought in the Control of Manufactures Act.  We are certainly not apologising for doing that because when we brought in a protectionist programme at that time, we were naturally very anxious to let our own nationals have the advantage of what we expected would be a growing economy and our own nationals took advantage of it.  They established the necessary industries to supply the home market.  It was a great help to us in building up our exports during the past seven or eight years that our own people had built up these native industries under protection, where, of course, they had a great chance of expanding.  They were very useful in building up our export industry in which they are taking part now.  Now that we have built our own native industries to that extent, we feel that we should not have the same restriction on capital coming in from outside and, therefore, it is decided that we will get rid of the Control of Manufactures Act in the course of the next few years.</P>
    <P>Senator Dooge is correct in inferring that the employment targets in the programme presuppose a reduction in the unemployment rate by 1970 of about 3½ per cent.  I think that is mentioned.  Senator Dooge asked how we calculate that.  If you calculate what progress various industries will make in the next five or six years, it is possible to calculate what the employment will be and also possible to plot the population, and we get the figures from that of both employment and emigration.  That is how these figures have been drawn up.  Of course, there are many imponderables but, on the other hand, economists are fairly reliable in forecasts of that kind and <Col N="884" /> we may take their forecasts as being as honest and as reliable as figures of this kind can be in all the circumstances.</P>
    <P>It is hoped to bring unemployment down by 1970 to 3½ per cent of the population which is about half what it is at present.  It is hoped to bring emigration down to 10,000.  It was 16,000 in the past 12 months and it has been coming down fairly rapidly in the past few years.  I do not think it optimistic to expect it to drop to about 10,000 in 1970.</P>
    <P>I was particularly interested in what Senator Dooge had to say about balance of payments deficits.  When you come to finance our programme, these deficits are necessary to bridge the gap between the investment and domestic savings targets of the programme. We plotted&mdash;and again, it is to be assumed, on the advice of the economists&mdash;on what they expect home investment will be over the next six or seven years, and what the investment will necessitate, and there is a gap. We find we shall not have enough of our own money to put into it and that gap has to be filled by bringing money in from outside.  That means a deficit in our balance of payments.</P>
    <P>Investment is expected to increase by 90 per cent in the decade from 1960 to 1970.  Most of the funds required are expected to come from increased savings at home but we do not believe there will be enough to cover our programme properly. Senator Dooge did at least go into the realm of surmise on what we could do without bringing in foreign capital at all but if we did that, we should probably, if we depended entirely on savings to create the capital necessary, have to bring down our target and would have not been able to achieve 4.3 per cent but probably something like 3.5 per cent.  Employment also would have to come down probably by 6,000 or 7,000 over the period and I do not think Senator Dooge or any other Senator would agree that we should do that in order to confine ourselves entirely to our own capital and not bring in any from outside.</P>
    <P>On the whole, we think we should use capital from outside also.  If we were to consider our external accounts <Col N="885" /> entirely, we should have to restrict our programme in that way.  There has been a substantial inflow of foreign capital for some years past and there is no reason to believe it will suddenly come to an end.  I think I can leave the balance of payments with these few observations.  I do not think that we shall upset the country very much by the forecast of what these balances of payments will amount to because our external assets will remain in quite healthy condition.  A later paragraph in the Blue Book makes it clear that external deficits of the order contemplated in the Programme should be regarded as an interim measure to assist the economy in reaching the level of investment necessary and to assist in achieving a satisfactory increase in output, employment and living standards.</P>
    <P>As Senator Dooge paid a great deal of attention to this, I should like to quote this paragraph:</P>
    <P>It would, moreover, be indefensible to incur the projected deficits in external payments except in association with the projected upward trend in real national product and in expectation of a continued advance, in incomes and employment, beyond 1970 which would be less dependent on external resources.</P>
    <P>In other words, we think that by 1970 we should be becoming a fairly healthy economy and we could either cut out this external deficit or perhaps bring the accounts into proper balance.  I might add that none of the international organisations which commented on the programme singled out for adverse comment the external deficits on which the programme is based. As Senators realise, these organisations would have a particular eye on that part of the programme.  We submitted this, for instance, to the International Monetary Fund which was set up after the last war to deal specifically with external deficits, and also to the World Bank and OECD.</P>
    <P>I agree fully with Senator Dooge when he calls for co-operation by the community in the preparation and implementation of the programme.  We have expressed that hope, I think more <Col N="886" /> than once.  The main functional organisations have viewed the programme. In fact, it is still being examined by some of them and we expect to have their views and correlate them and be able to publish the detailed programme to which I have referred, in a month or two.</P>
    <P>Senator Dooge, towards the end of his speech, spoke a good deal about the type of planning being adopted in various countries, whether centralistic or more of the liberal type.  I do not know enough about Senator Dooge's classification to say how we stand in this matter but the Government are determined that the programme will be based on consent rather than compulsion and that the community will be given a full sense of participation in the programme and its implementation. Every single industry has got an opportunity of looking at the programme and making comments and the same applies to farming organisations on the agricultural side.</P>
    <P>I want to thank Senator O'Brien for his admirably balanced and useful exposition of the economic background of the Bill.  I fully agree with him that we must be on our guard to ensure that the extra purchasing power released as a result of the ninth round of salary and wage increases does not lead to inflation and balance of payments difficulties.  One might ask: how is that to be avoided since we all know the simple fact is that when money in circulation exceeds production, there is danger of inflation and danger of some of the money going for extra exports and therefore causing trouble in our balance of payments?</P>
    <P>One thing I personally and others have advocated is that we should try to save a little more.  That would prevent some of the spending and we would have the saving for our capital programme which is very necessary. We could, perhaps, kill two birds with one stone if people would save a bit more and devote less money to current expenditure.</P>
    <P>Senator O'Brien inquired whether figures of capital expenditure below the line, as he put it, might be made available at the same time as those in respect of voted capital services so <Col N="887" /> that the Seanad might be in a position to consider the whole bill or the full range of capital expenditure.  As Senators are aware, in this Book of Estimates, there are some pages of voted capital expenditure which are referred to as capital expenditure above the line.  At Budget time we will be bringing in another sheet of capital items which will refer to extra capital items below the line.  The Senator asked why we could not have all these at the same time and debate them. There is one difficulty.  We do not have the necessary statistics and notes on the various items of capital expenditure until just about Budget time. For some years we have been trying to move in the direction Senator O'Brien recommends.  Last year we reached the stage of issuing a sheet with the capital expenditure and with notes relating to it.  We will do the same this year.</P>
    <P>With regard to discussing those in separate debates, the same question arose in the Dáil.  I pointed out that it was very difficult to debate the capital expenditure and not go any further.  I think a chairman would have a very difficult task in keeping Senators or Deputies in order.  It is better to have them all debated together.  That is why we issue the capital expenditure at Budget time.  In the Dáil there is a debate on the Budget itself and reference can be made there to capital expenditure as well as to ordinary expenditure.  In the Seanad, when the Appropriation Bill comes along, Senators have the same opportunity. That is all I can say at present. As Senators realise, it is difficult to get Parliamentary time for these debates and it is impossible to have the Estimates ready sooner than around Budget time.</P>
    <P>Senator Desmond referred to the borrowing powers in this Bill.  Somebody asked me in the Dáil why the Minister for Finance always asked for power to borrow the whole lot and whether he was afraid he would not get half in taxation.  No, but it is an old custom that has been handed down.  Nobody likes to say he hopes <Col N="888" /> to get half and that he will borrow the other half, or nobody likes to say he hopes to get 90 per cent and will borrow the other 10 per cent.  Nobody likes to draw the line.  I think it is better to let things stay as they are. There is a lot to be said for it.</P>
    <P>The Senator went on to refer to the Post Office Savings Bank and the rate of interest paid.  As far as I am concerned as Minister for Finance, I want money.  We are getting a fair return from the Post Office Savings Bank on 2½ per cent.  It runs up to £6 million a year, which is a fine amount of money.  I am not sure if we would get any more by raising the rate of interest.  However, consideration is given to these things from time to time.  You have the ordinary savings banks and you have the Post Office Savings Bank.  We must remember they are in the position of lending money practically on call.  A person can put money into the Post Office and can go the next day and draw it out.  He can go up to Sligo or Galway, go into a post office and draw it out. A great service is provided by the Post Office Savings Bank.  Therefore, there is no reason why the rate of interest should be higher than the joint stock banks give on a deposit. They do not give any more than 2½ per cent.  In fact, I think they give only 2 per cent on very big amounts. If the deposits are less than £20,000 they give only 1½ per cent.  We do a bit better than that.  Of course, it is said the small person cannot get the beneficial interest rates the bigger person can get.  However, there are Savings Certificates, which do not cost an awful lot, and, in addition, we have National Loans, Exchequer Bills and so on.  The higher you go on these things, the longer the money is invested. In a National Loan it is put in for 20 years.  A person cannot draw it out. He may sell it, but the Government have the money all the time.  They can afford to give a bigger rate of interest than they could in a case where the money may be taken out tomorrow.  In that event a certain amount of money must be kept for liquidity.  That is drawing no interest and they cannot give the same amount of interest on the rest.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="889" /> Senator Desmond raised a point concerning local authorities.  We lend money to them at what it costs.  About a quarter per cent is added for the mechanism of looking after it and so on.  We cannot, unless we want to subsidise local authorities, do it for less. We subsidise them in other ways.  On the housing side, for instance, there is a generous subsidy of up to two-thirds of the interest and sinking fund in respect of all borrowing for housing and sanitary services.  The Senator went on to refer to the banks.  I have no responsibility for the commercial banks and I cannot answer for them.  On the other hand, I think they are not doing worse than banks in other countries.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan drew a contrast between the methods adopted for selecting agricultural and industrial targets in the Second Programme.  That may be apparent, but it is not right. Of course, there is a difference in the conditions of agriculture and industry which must be kept in mind.  I should like again to fall back on my promise of a more detailed book on the Second Programme, which will be issued in a month or two and which will go into the matter in more detail.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan in particular was disappointed with the target of 2.7 per cent in respect of agriculture.  We would all like to see it higher, but we have to be realistic.  We have to say what we think it can be in all the circumstances, postulating that the Government will give whatever help they can in achieving this target.  The 2.7 per cent is higher than has been achieved in the last decade.  It will, as we said, require a considerable effort by farmers, and State support will be necessary if it is to be achieved.</P>
    <P>The limiting factor in agriculture is not so much the productive capacity of the farmers as the market outlets. For instance, it will be found in the programme that we aim at a very big increase in the number of cattle.  We feel the marketing of cattle and beef will not present the same difficulty as some of the other items might.  We are all aware of the fact that the land of this country, if properly looked after, would produce&mdash;some people say&mdash;twice as much as it does at the <Col N="890" /> moment.  Perhaps that is true.  There could be a very big percentage increase in the output of the land if a market could be found for the produce at remunerative prices for the farmer. The fundamental problem confronting Irish agriculture at present is marketing. Senators are aware of the various regulations which have been made by other countries to which we are sending our agricultural products.  These regulations are not always in our favour.  Sometimes it is even difficult to get them modified slightly in our favour, and they are never modified to the extent we would like in order to give us full advantage of the foreign market.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan mentioned that the NFA had formulated proposals which would enable an annual growth rate of 3.9 per cent to be achieved.  That figure is not comparable with our 2.7 per cent.  I want to point out that the 3.9 relates to gross agricultural output, and ours is net.  If you convert gross to net, there would be very little difference between them.  Probably the NFA figure would be down to 3 per cent, as against our figure of 2.7 per cent, which does not show a very big gap.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan also referred to a speech by the Deputy Secretary General of OEEC in 1959.  Senator Quinlan quoted him as saying there could be an increase in agricultural output of up to 4, 5 or 6 per cent.  I was rather surprised to hear that, and I asked for a report on it.  I think it is very clear that he was referring to the rate of increase in national production generally, and not to agriculture alone.  As I said, OEEC think we are putting the target as high as we possibly can.  In fact they say that their opinion is that 2 per cent would have been a more realistic figure.  They take into account what the various countries are prepared to try to export, and they have come to the conclusion that our target is, perhaps, a bit too ambitious.</P>
    <P>I want to quote what the Deputy Secretary General said.  I do not say I agree with it.  Senator L'Estrange might like to take a note of it.  He said that what we should have is fewer <Col N="891" /> but economically more sound family farms.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what the Minister preached in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the cold economic view and it is an objective view.  There are no social considerations in it. Senator L'Estrange has drawn me but I will not be drawn for long.  I think Senators will agree&mdash;I do not expect Senator L'Estrange to agree but I think other Senators will agree in all fairness&mdash;that we have been doing our utmost for the small farmers in the west of Ireland.  We have asked everyone to send along their proposals and suggestions to us.  We have set up a committee in every county, consisting of technical people, technical officials of various kinds, representatives of public bodies and others, to make suggestions to the Government on what we could do to keep the small farmers going.  We have spent a good deal of money on drainage, forestry, and in other directions where we thought it would help the small farmers.  Of course it does not help us in any way that Senator L'Estrange should be reading the reports of Fianna Fáil conventions like the one in Longford.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Minister read it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad he believes now that sometimes they make sense at those conventions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>They disagreed with the Minister's £15 for cattle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have never yet held a convention in secret.  They are always open to the Press.  Even the Fianna Fáil Árd Fheis is open to the Press while Fine Gael hold theirs behind closed doors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>That is definitely wrong, completely wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course it is not wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>It has always been open to the Press.  We have nothing to hide.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="892" />
    <Speaker pid="EamonKissane" hpid="Éamon Ó Ciosáin Éamon Ó Ciosáin">
      <NameTxt>Éamon Ó Ciosáin</NameTxt>
      <P>What suits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Every single thing. Only some Fianna Fáil conventions are open.  The one where Lawless was ejected was not open.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall come to Senator L'Estrange in a, few minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is quite welcome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am still dealing with Senator Quinlan.  Senator Quinlan had some mild criticism, if you like&mdash;I do not say he was in any way offensive&mdash; of our treatment of the universities. When I have given these figures, I think Senators will agree that we have dealt in a just way with the three colleges, University College, Dublin, University College, Cork, and University College, Galway.  Dublin has 6,600 students; Cork has 1,900 students; and Galway has 1,500 students.  One of the considerations which are taken into account when we come to help the universities is the number of students.  It is only one of the many considerations which are taken into account but, taking into consideration the number of students, Dublin gets £85 per student by way of subsidy; Cork gets £126 per student; and Galway gets £129 per student.  On the basis of the numbers, I think Senators will agree that is a fairly just proportion for each.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Apart from that, we have to give capital money.  That is current and is regarded as helping the colleges to run their current affairs such as paying professors, keeping the place going, and so on.  We have capital costs as well. In the case of Cork, this year a third storey was added to the electrical engineering building at a cost of £60,000. There is also provision for a new building for chemistry, physics and mathematics at a cost of £900,000.  Admittedly, we are not spending the same amount of money as they are spending in Great Britain and Northern Ireland on our universities, but we are a small country, and we have not the same amount of money to spend.  Certainly it can be said that the increase in expenditure is fairly steep each year, and <Col N="893" /> is likely to be just as steep for the next four or five years.  On that basis we are doing fairly well.</P>
    <P>It is true, as Senator Quinlan said, that academic salaries are lower in Cork and Galway than in Dublin.  That has been the case for some time.  I was rather surprised to learn that Trinity College salaries are not as high as the salaries in UCD.  As Senators are aware, a Commission is examining university education and we expect a report before the end of the year.  It will probably advise on the treatment of professors, and on the organisation of the colleges.  We shall be very interested to get that report.</P>
    <P>Senators may also feel on looking at the Estimates that Trinity College was not well treated compared with other colleges.  We all know that Trinity College has a fairly substantial endowment fund.  Naturally that is taken into account, and when everything is taken into account, it will be found that we treated Trinity College on a par with the others.  At least, if it is put to the Government that we did not, we will be interested to examine that matter.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan also complained that Maynooth was not getting proper treatment.  I pointed out to Senator Quinlan more than once that I have not the cheek, if you like, to go to the Bishops and say they are not asking for enough.  They are satisfied with what they have been getting so far as I know.  I have heard no complaints from any Bishop&mdash;I usually get complaints from people who think they are not getting enough&mdash;and I presume, therefore, that they are getting as much as they are entitled to in all the circumstances.  That is all I can say about that.</P>
    <P>I shall come to Senator L'Estrange now.  I will make a bargain with the Senator.  He did say a few things that he had not said before&mdash;but not very many.  I promise Senator L'Estrange faithfully to read his speech&mdash;one of his speeches because they are all the same&mdash;the night before the next Finance Bill comes on, if he promises to take it as read.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister <Col N="894" /> reply to the figures now and say what is wrong with them?  The Minister could not quote the figures last year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall quote a few figures, just a few.  Senator L'Estrange talked for a few hours; I am getting only half an hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not; I was one and a half hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Two hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Exaggeration again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They all agree it is two hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJFitzpatrick" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzpatrick) Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzpatrick)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Fitzpatrick)</NameTxt>
      <P>Order.  Senator L'Estrange must stop interrupting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>From 4 p.m. to 5.30 p.m. equals one and a half hours.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>All right; we shall accept that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange should not interrupt the Minister and the Minister should not provoke Senator L'Estrange.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange starts off with his usual gibe at Ministers' after-dinner speeches.  Why are you so jealous of Ministers having such a good dinner?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>That was your gibe for years when you were talking about the tall hats, and so on, in the past.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange said that if after-dinner speeches could make this country prosperous, we would be the best off country in the world.  In answer to that, I might say that if speeches by hungry Fine Gaelers could make this country poor, we should be paupers long ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>You tried to make it poor yourself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange says taxation has gone up very much.  It has remained a constant percentage of the gross national product.  It is practically the same from 1956-57 up to the present time.  Therefore, if, as Senator <Col N="895" /> L'Estrange I think truthfully points out, taxation has gone up between 50 and 80 per cent, then the income of every person has gone up the same.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Not necessarily. What about the farmers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>It has.  The money is divided between all the individuals and they are paying the same percentage of taxation.  Therefore, everybody in this country must be 50 per cent better off, on Senator L'Estrange's figures.</P>
      <P>I want to deal with the question of the Health Act.  Fine Gael Deputies and Senators quote me as saying that the Health Act would cost the local authorities about 2/- in the £.  First of all, that was 11 years ago.  I suppose I did not try to speak for more than four or five years to come but I can speak for those 11 years now.</P>
      <P>One would imagine, listening to those speakers misrepresent me and the facts, that there was no health provision at all in this country until I introduced the 1953 Act because with every increase that comes they point to the Health Act.  If there were no Health Act, we should still have mental hospitals, dispensary doctors, county hospitals, and so on, because all of these were there before the 1953 Health Act and they are the things that are going up in cost.</P>
      <P>In the county where I pay my rates, the mental hospital is costing as much as all the others: the Health Act had nothing to do with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The turnover tax.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are going over to the turnover tax: we are on the Health Act first.  The dispensary doctors were there.  There is no change as far as they are concerned.  Not a single one was added.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The ninth round.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>After making the case, Senator L'Estrange runs away.  The same number of dispensary doctors are there.  They got the ninth round increase and Senator L'Estrange points to the Health Act.  The same can be <Col N="896" /> said about the nurses: they got their increase.  I suppose the ambulance men and all the other people got their increase.  Then some opposition people mention the Health Act and remind me that I promised it would not cost more than 2/- in the £.</P>
      <P>Through Senator Browne I got the figures for Wexford last year.  They are analysed under the various headings I am talking about now.  As far as the Health Act was concerned, Wexford County Council were paying less than 2/- more than in 1953.  I will lay a wager with Senator L'Estrange, if he likes.  We will get an independent auditor to examine the figures and the Senator will have to admit I am right.  If you want to attack me, then try to get things right. Try to base the argument on fact&mdash; not on the type of argument you might make at a cross-roads in Westmeath where you think everybody will believe what you say.</P>
      <P>According to the opposition, there is a big increase in the cost of living. When the turnover tax was going through the Dáil and Seanad I said several times that the cost of living would go up 2½ per cent.  I provided for the social welfare people and everybody else on that basis.  I said that the cost of living will go up 2½ per cent and I will compensate for that.  I mentioned it several times during the debates when providing the money for social welfare and when the Fine Gael people said the cost of living would go up 12 or 15 per cent I said it would not but that it would go up 2½ per cent.  Who is right and who is wrong?  I said 2½ per cent; they said 15 per cent.</P>
      <P>When November came, the cost of living increase was between 2½ and 3 per cent and for food and clothes&mdash;the two things mentioned all the time, the necessaries of life&mdash;it was exactly 2½ per cent.  That was in November.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Now we come to February when prices have perhaps settled a bit better. We find there is an increase of less than 1 per cent.  In fact, taken with the November figure, it would amount to 4 per cent altogether.  If I said I expected an increase of 2½ per cent I was nearer to the truth than the Fine <Col N="897" /> Gael and Labour people who in this case said it would be 15 per cent.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I will have a wager with the Minister that it will be 10 per cent before June.  Take it on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This country is always getting into bankruptcy next June or next September.  Senator L'Estrange is looking forward to that all the time but he never gets it.</P>
      <P>Then he comes on to <i>Closing the Gap</i>.  We issued a paper called <i>Closing the Gap</i> last February.  We advised everybody concerned not to seek an increase in income.  We said we would resist any suggestion of an increase in income because money spending had got ahead of production and there was a great danger, if that went on much longer, of a big inflation and a big rise in the cost of living.  I do not say that that had full effect.  I do not know if it had much influence but there was no increase in incomes until the next February, 12 months later&mdash;and during those 12 months things had righted themselves to a great extent.  Production increased by practically five per cent during that period from February to February.  It went a long way to make things right as far as production and the cost of living were concerned. They were in balance by this February.</P>
      <P>I agree with Senator Crowley: I do not think we ever claimed we were responsible for the 12 per cent.  Senator L'Estrange says we did so in order to win the election but before that he said we should not get credit for it at all as Labour did it.  What leg will he come down on?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>When did I say it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>What leg will he come down on?  First of all, he said we were not responsible, that it was Fine Gael and Labour who did it for the people and then, later, he said we did it in order to win the by-elections. Frankly, I do not know what he believes himself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>If there had been a by-election February 12 months you would have had an increase instead of <i>Closing the Gap.</i>  You gave it when it suited you.  You timed it well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="898" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange must cease interrupting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>And, if there were an election next February, we would do it as well.  It is like the lady showing you around the garden&mdash;the flowers were lovely last week.  Another thing we have been told by some Senators is that 7 or 8 per cent would have been enough.  I was of that opinion myself.  There is a level to which wages can go.  It is the optimum and ideal level and, if we could find it, then there would be no increase in the cost of living, and everybody will be just as well off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>Better off.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Better off.  Perhaps 7 or 8 per cent would have been enough. Perhaps 12 per cent is too much.  I hope not.  I hope we shall be able to meet it.  Nobody is to be blamed for saying 7 or 8 per cent would be the proper figure.  As far as the Taoiseach was concerned and, indeed, as far as the Government were concerned, we were afraid of what one might describe as a disorganised demand for more wages, with some getting a lot more than others, in which event we would have had the same pattern for the next two years as we had in the case of the eighth round, with new categories coming in all the time to get themselves put right.  We were anxious to have a level increase all round and the Taoiseach asked employers and employees to discuss the matter.  He brought them together on the second occasion on which they made their decision.  I hope it is the right decision. I think we will be able to face it.  I think it was a great thing that we got the same increase all round and that that will continue for the next 2½ years. Let the credit go to the employers and to labour for that.  The only credit we need give the Taoiseach is that he brought them together and tried to get them to come to an agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the Dáil and here a figure is being constantly fired at us, a figure of 130,000 more in employment ten years ago.  That is the greatest nonsense.  In the statistics&mdash;I remember remarking on this some years ago&mdash;one notices <Col N="899" /> that those in industry and the various services are described as &ldquo;employed&rdquo; while those in agriculture are said to be &ldquo;engaged&rdquo;.  It was not called employment and they were right in not describing it as employment.  I can remember 30 years back&mdash;I am not asking Senator L'Estrange to remember as far back as that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, I remember it, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and I am sure a great many had the same experience as I had&mdash;when threshing came round, there would be at least 35 to 40 men looking for a job.  They were underemployed. They got a casual day here, there, and elsewhere.  The pattern was the same all over the country. The complaint now is that we cannot get a man to do a day's work when we want him.  How could anyone expect a man to live on a casual day, or two?  All these people have disappeared.  It is not a bad thing that they have disappeared.  They have got good jobs elsewhere.  The result is that employment, or engagement, in agriculture has gone down and the rural population has gone down, too.  But how can we do anything about that? If we make those engaged in agriculture a bit better off than they are, that is the most we can do at the moment.</P>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange talked about employment in 1961.  Take the industrial side.  The nearest quarter to that census was the quarter showing 155,300 engaged in industry.  In the last September quarter, the figure is 168.6 thousand, an increase of 13,000. That is genuine employment at a good wage on which people are well able to live and rear their families.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have heard a good deal about emigration.  The figures available for the past 12 months show the number at 16,700.  Senator L'Estrange said that, whenever we are asked about emigration, we say we have no reliable figures.  That is quite true.  The Statistics Office always used the same formula: &ldquo;We have no reliable figures but the movement of persons in and out is such and such&rdquo;, and they give <Col N="900" /> the movement in and out, but they do not guarantee the figures are correct. As a matter of fact, when it comes to the actual census, they are always proved to be fairly right.  In the last census they were proved to be a little too high, about one per cent.  They show the trend at least and the figure is, as I say, 16,700.  That means that for the past three years&mdash;1961, 1962 and 1963&mdash;our population has increased by 20,000.  If we take Senator L'Estrange's value, which he took from our President, of £1,000 per person, we are £20 millions better off now than we were in 1961.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>According to the Minister's figures, there were 40,000 fewer on the land last year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>But they are not my figures.  They are probably more reliable than my figures.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Where does the Minister get the figures if 90,100 left the land since 1957?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>A great many people left the land because they could not make a living on it.  They never did make a living on it.  They lived by catching rabbits, or something.  They are all gone to better employment now and I think it is a good thing they are.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>The Tánaiste admitted there were 42 per cent fewer on the land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange should cease interrupting the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Whether we have so many fewer or not, the fact is that there is a great deal more money now divided amongst our people.  Pay increases this year will amount to £140 millions and that will play a significant part in adding to our national income.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator L'Estrange said that we are now advocating the rearing of livestock and that we were against it in the past.  We were never against it. If Senator L'Estrange goes back and reads any speech I made when I was Minister for Agriculture&mdash;I do not care what speech&mdash;he will find I was <Col N="901" /> always advocating more tillage and no reduction in livestock.  Fine Gael did not agree with that.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>Fianna Fáil said the British market was gone, and gone forever, and thanks be to God.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>All the time I advocated tillage as well as livestock.  Fine Gael advocated livestock and no tillage. The leader of Fine Gael&mdash;he was not the leader then&mdash;made a famous statement on one occasion; he would not like to be found dead in a field of beet or wheat.</P>
      <P>(<i>Interruptions.</i>)</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Acting Chairman Acting Chairman">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator L'Estrange must refrain from interrupting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Another statement by Senator L'Estrange&mdash;another chapter from the gospel of Fine Gael, without any sound reasoning or facts to support it&mdash;is that farming costs have gone up.  That is not true.  Last year rates were a bit higher than in 1956-57. The year before they were lower. Fertilisers, feeding stuffs and seeds were 80 per cent of what they were in 1956-57, 20 per cent down in price. But that does not matter.  Statistics do not matter.  Senator L'Estrange will not have any truck with statistics.  He will go on saying costs have gone up and the cost of living has gone up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The question is, what do the farmers themselves think about these things? The fact is the farmer is paid about twice as much for land as he was paid when the Coalition were in office, maybe three times as much.  Certainly he is paid two to three times as much for cauliflower.  Then the banks, who are the best judges of all of what is going to do well, have more than doubled their loans to the farmers in the past six or seven years because they think farming is a good prospect. Senator L'Estrange says that everything that is good came from the Coalition, grants for industries, the ESB, the Sugar Company; everything that can be mentioned came from the Coalition in office.  Despite that I am sure Senator L'Estrange would not have the courage to go to any cross-roads <Col N="902" /> in Westmeath and say: &ldquo;We are going to have another Coalition.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I do not want any controversy on the next point but I wish to correct what was said.  Senator L'Estrange said we should have given the other Parties more information about Cyprus.  We could not.  I am sure Senators realise that we were in touch, back and forward, with the United Nations about the conditions under which these troops would go to Cyprus and various other matters like that.  We got the information that would enable us to make up our minds only on Friday afternoon, and the Dáil had adjourned on Thursday evening.  We were called together and we issued a statement telling exactly what we intended to do. The letter we had sent to the United Nations told them we would send the troops on certain conditions.  We gave all these conditions, so that if Senator L'Estrange read the paper on Saturday morning he knows as much about it as I do because that was all that was in it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldLEstrange" hpid="Mr. L'Estrange Mr. L'Estrange">
      <NameTxt>Mr. L'Estrange</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the Minister's word for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesRyan" hpid="Dr. Ryan Dr. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to take up one point mentioned by Senator Ross because I am very interested in it, that is, in regard to saving on this round of wages.  As I said already, we expect there will be about £40 million handed out this coming year in increased incomes.  That is my opinion and, of course, as I said already, I form my opinion on advice from the economists.  It does appear to me this increase is in advance of an increase in production and, therefore, we must be particularly careful that we do not start an inflationary movement and a big increase in the cost of living.  If we get over this first year, I think we shall be fairly safe.  That is why I would be very anxious that all of us in the community would save all we can in 1964 and spend as little as possible during that year.  If that can be done we shall probably be over the hump, as it were, and get over the difficulties of the 12 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some other Senator mentioned State bodies.  I do not know that State bodies will come into this matter <Col N="903" /> very much.  The ESB has not spoken yet.  I do not know if they will speak; I hope they will not.  The Sugar Company's case is being investigated but they made it very plain they had other things in mind besides the 12 per cent and I do not know what the result of the investigation may be.  However, I cannot see how an organisation like CIE could avoid trying to get the increased wages back by way of fares. We shall always have that difficulty. You cannot very well say to people working in CIE: &ldquo;You cannot increase your efficiency and therefore you cannot get an increase in salary or an increase in wages.&rdquo;  The manufacturers can improve their methods and can from time to time pay increased wages without putting up the price of the article.  We must face the fact that when organisations like CIE give increased wages the services they provide will cost a bit more.  If there are only a few cases like that I suppose we can face it.  I cannot see any way out of it.</P>
    <P>Senator McDonald complained about the Estimate for Agriculture showing a decrease at a time like this. That is unfair criticism because there are two columns there and in one there is an increase of £2 million and in the other a decrease of £5.6 million.  The decrease of £5.6 million is due to the fact that the amount for bovine tuberculosis eradication has gone down by £4.1 million.  Naturally we are not going to create bovine tuberculosis in order to spend money eradicating it. We are coming to the end of it and we should be thankful for that.</P>
    <P>As regards the disposal of wheat, there is no wheat to dispose of because the last harvest was all good wheat; hence there is no money being spent under that heading.  As regards grain storage, the Minister for Agriculture thinks there is enough storage and there is no more money being spent on that.  The Pigs and Bacon Commission say they do not need the same amount of money this year as they did last year.  I do not see how anybody could find fault with the Minister for Agriculture under any of those headings.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="904" /> Senator Fitzpatrick asked why the amount for the ninth round was not included in the Book of Estimates. I mentioned in my Second Reading speech that the figures were not ready when the Book of Estimates was going to print.  It was two or three days after 1st February when we made our first agreement; the second and third agreements were made some time afterwards; in fact the last agreement has not been made yet.  Therefore we could not possibly include the total amount in the Book of Estimates. However, in page xi of the Book of Estimates attention is drawn to the fact that the 12 per cent increase is not provided for and will have to be added afterwards.  I did give an estimate in the Dáil that the cost of the ninth round will be about £7 million.  I ask the Senator to accept that there is nothing sinister or secret about this matter.</P>
    <P>Senator Fitzpatrick points out that small farmers and pensioners will have their position still worsened by comparison with those who got the 12 per cent.  Local authorities must also increase their rates considerably on account of the 12 per cent increase in wages to their employees.  These are, of course, the ill effects of the 12 per cent increase but we cannot welcome the 12 per cent in some ways and then find fault with it because it brings difficulties in its wake.</P>
    <P>Senator Crowley wound up this debate by mentioning the agreement that was made on the 12 per cent. I want to refer to what he said because I did not follow it: that the agreement on the 12 per cent was made up of three components, one, an increase in the cost of living due to the turnover tax, which I have already pointed out was between 2½ and three per cent; another, an increase in the cost of living apart from that; and the third two or three per cent left for future growth.  While we may not altogether agree with that, it does not matter very much&mdash;we can have our own views on that&mdash;but I do not think there would be more than two or three per cent left for future growth.  As I say, it is not a matter of any great importance at this time.</P>
    <Col N="905" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>Actually, I think the figure is between three and four per cent.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="906" /> Bill put through Committee, reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 9.50 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>