<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Wed" Date="31" Month="Oct" Year="1956" Vol="160" No="4" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 31 Deireadh Fómhair 1956" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 31 October 1956" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="513" /> Do chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take business in the following order: Nos. 1, 5, 6 and 7.  Questions will be taken at 12 noon.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Married Women's Status Bill, 1954&mdash;Order" RHead="for Second Reading Discharged">
    <Title>Married Women's Status Bill, 1954&mdash;Order for Second Reading Discharged.</Title>
    <P>Order for Second Stage of Married Women's Status Bill, 1954, discharged and Bill withdrawn.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Married Women's Status Bill," RHead="1956&mdash;First Stage">
    <Title>Married Women's Status Bill, 1956&mdash;First Stage.</Title>
    <P>Leave granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to consolidate with amendments the law relating to the status of married women and the liabilities of husbands.&mdash;(Minister for Justice.)</P>
    <P>Second Stage ordered for Wednesday, 7th November, 1956.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Bill be available next week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be circulated to-day.  The Deputy is very anxious to have work for next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not fancy the prospect of the Dáil meeting next week with nothing to do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is more anxious to prevent Deputies on this side of the House going down to Carlow-Kilkenny.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach is proposing to take a Bill which he pretends is a Bill of some importance. We have not yet got a print of it.  We <Col N="514" /> have only got a typed copy.  We will not get the print until next Tuesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order! Will the Minister say when he proposes to take the next stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>This day week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Shake the lead out of your pants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Would someone go in and make peace in the Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Cosgrave) Liam Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Cosgrave)</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Deputy make peace in the wangle in Kilkenny and Carlow?  The Deputy did not tell us what happened there.  (<i>Interruptions</i>).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon) James M. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon)</NameTxt>
      <P>They did a little meddling in Carlow-Kilkenny.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Dublin was a face saver.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Animal Remedies Bill," RHead="1956&mdash;Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Animal Remedies Bill, 1956&mdash;Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be received for final consideration.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon) James M. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon)</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to say a word on this. I am gratified by the reception accorded to this Bill and, now that it is about to pass, I feel myself justified in sharing with the Dáil the realisation of a hope that I had occasion to express in regard to animal remedies on some previous occasions.  I avail of this occasion again to refer to it in order further to emphasise how important it is that our farmers should forbear from the use of quack remedies, which are often very expensive and wholly ineffective, when, by patience and research, it is usually possible to find a satisfactory remedy, even for our most intractable veterinary problems.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Minister will allow me?  His statement would be more appropriate on the Fifth Stage.  This is the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="515" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnWMoher" hpid="Mr. Moher Mr. Moher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moher</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say something on this stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister rose and we thought he was addressing himself to the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWMoher" hpid="Mr. Moher Mr. Moher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moher</NameTxt>
      <P>Under Section 3, the types of animals are classified and the most extraordinary thing is that pets and greyhounds are excluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The reason for that is that it was considered whether dogs should be included in the original draft and that consideration was discussed with the Veterinary Medical Council.  The Veterinary Medical Council expressed the view that we might, with advantage, name them in the Bill.  I took the view that it might be better at this stage to omit specific reference to dogs and, if necessary, under powers I have under the Bill, to bring dogs in if it were thought necessary after further deliberations with the Veterinary Medical Council and other interested parties.  We decided it was better to leave dogs out and, if necessary, by Order under the Bill, bring them in later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnWMoher" hpid="Mr. Moher Mr. Moher">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moher</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill deals mainly with the fraudulent sale of certain remedies and I think its scope is limited by classifying the animals. That, I think, is an impediment because there can be a considerable amount of fraud in connection with remedies for dogs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy's views will weigh powerfully with me.  I should like to say that the Deputy reinforces the representations made by the Veterinary Medical Council.  I am grateful to the Deputy for expressing his views, which I shall bear in mind. I was trying to give this Bill a special agricultural slant and therefore I gave in the Bill every animal ordinarily associated with the agricultural industry. I think we could say dogs are associated with agriculture in so far as they are sheep dogs and dogs used by a man about a farm.  I shall take careful note of the fact.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take Final Stage now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="516" /> Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to emphasise how urgent it is to carry conviction to the minds of farmers generally that they should forbear from the payment of ridiculous prices for quack remedies, because even the most intractable veterinary problems are susceptible of solution, given time, patience and industry. Deputies will have learned that on divers occasions the question of the warble fly and its impact on the cattle industry has been raised in this House. We were conscious of the fact that the action of the warble fly was highly detrimental to milch cattle by disturbing them, and, over and above that, greatly reduced the value of the hides.</P>
      <P>We were all concerned to do everything we could to evolve a method whereby the warble fly could be extinguished in this country, but the great trouble was to find a method which could be applied in practice, because, though one farmer might carry out the dressings which were recommended, unless all his neighbours did the same, his zeal and industry went for virtually nothing.  I have studied this problem continually and felt that no real progress could be made of an effective kind until a systemic remedy was discovered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>By a systemic remedy, I mean this: Long ago&mdash;and it is something of which we have reason to be proud&mdash;the life cycle of the warble fly was discovered and described by an Irish scientist working here in Dublin.  It was a matter of some satisfaction to me that when I first visited Beltsville near Washington, and when I spoke to the director, he said to me: &ldquo;I am surprised, Minister, that you should come to me because after all the whole parasitology of the warble fly was discovered by an Irish scientist in Dublin.&rdquo;  But having discovered that did not mean that a remedy was found. However, it was established that the warble fly laid its eggs on the legs of an animal.  It long remained a mysstery as to why the warble fly appeared on the back of the animal the following year.  It was then discovered that the egg of the warble fly found its way into the lymphatic system of the <Col N="517" /> animal and that, during its period of incubation, it was carried through the lymphatic system where it matured, eventually piercing a hole and emerging as a pupa to resume its life cycle on another animal.</P>
    <P>This, as we all know, had the disastrous effect of leaving a hole in the hide which greatly reduced the value of that hide.  I always believed that until we found a drug that could be administered to the animal which would operate to destroy the warble fly in the lymphatic system between the time the animal was bitten by the fly and the time it emerged on the animal's back, we would never be able to make an effective attack on this problem.  I think I am justified in telling the House of the exciting development in America as a result of which it is now believed that such a systemic remedy has been found.  I do not think any of us will be much the wiser when I say that the name of the drug is E. T. 57 (0-dimethyl-02, 4, 5 -trichlorophenyl-phosphorothricate).</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>That sounds worse than the warble fly itself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is holding forth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. A. Barry Mr. A. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy MacEntee is anxious to get on this morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought I heard a warble on the wing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The warble is coming from the other side to-day.  I do not know whether it is on his leg that the Minister has been bitten.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I have accordingly directed that this drug be intensively investigated under our conditions here in Ireland, and if it should transpire that the results claimed in America are confirmed here, I am not without hope that so intractable a problem as the deterioration of Irish hides from the attack of the warble fly may be mastered in the early future.  I do not think there is any more dramatic evidence of the fact that if people will trust to the progress of veterinary research there is no problem which cannot ultimately be solved without recourse to expensive quack remedies <Col N="518" /> which do little but enrich the quack and deceive the farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>On that point the Minister delivered a dissertation on the life cycle of the warble fly.  Does the Minister not acknowledge that the existing derris powder if properly used, and if the treatment is properly carried out, is sufficient to do away with the life cycle of the warble fly?  Some years ago in the Seanad, Senator Seán O'Donovan, I think, delivered a very instructive discourse on the warble problem.  We are all well aware of the depredations of the warble fly.  It has been calculated&mdash;I think rightly&mdash; that, through its depredations in this country every summer, we suffer a loss in hides to the value of probably between £8,000,000 and £9,000,000.  Any systemic remedy or treatment would be very welcome indeed.  The Minister has told us about a discovery in America, but he has not told us much more.  He told us that an effective treatment has been discovered, but will the Minister say that it is effective and if used by the individual farmer or whoever else produces live stock that it will succeed in eradicating this pest?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want Deputy Carter to be under any misunderstanding. Certainly, derris as a dressing is effective and we are at present carrying out an eradication operation with derris on Whiddy Island and Loop Head, but the trouble with the derris procedure is that, unless everybody adopts it at the same time, you do not get rid of the warble and, therefore, repeated efforts to eliminate the warble fly with derris have broken down because, although you might get a considerable number of farmers to co-operate, even if 5 per cent. of them in an area do not co-operate their animals can reinfest the cattle of all who are co-operating.  Where you get an island and persuade everybody on the island to co-operate, you have a reasonable hope of eradicating warbles with derris.  I am going a stage further in the hope that even on a peninsula you may be able to do the same.  But the process is laborious and the trouble is that you do not get the benefit of it <Col N="519" /> in the year of the dressing because by the time you can dress the warbles the damage is already done.</P>
      <P>If this drug fulfils what it is believed to be capable of doing, the beauty of it is that an animal infested and dosed will never have its hide pierced at all so that the farmer who is willing to co-operate is, in fact, getting some direct benefit from the treatment. Deputy Carter asks me if I have any guarantee.  The answer is that I have not, but the report we have from the research station in the U.S.A. sets out that, in one test at Kerrville, this drug was fed to grub-infested cattle at the rate of 100 milligrammes per kilogramme live weight, the treatment being applied some two or three months before the grubs would normally have appeared on the backs of the cattle.  In four out of five treated cattle, only a single grub appeared while in the five untreated controls 98 grubs appeared.  Other tests carried out at Corvallis showed that this drug was 88 per cent. effective in preventing grub development.</P>
      <P>In another experiment, 35 of 60 grub-infested calves in South Dakota were treated with the drug and shipped with 25 untreated calves to Kerrville for observation.  At the time of treatment grubs were already beginning to appear on the backs of the animals.  During the observation period an average of 30 new grubs appeared on the backs of each untreated calf while none appeared on the treated animals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On those facts I have recommended the Veterinary Research Station here to carry out experiments under our conditions because, in addition to determining the effectiveness of the drug, it is necessary to determine its toxicity, its possible residual effect on the flesh and milk of the cattle and any other untoward development that cannot be fully investigated without a careful scientific investigation carried out at a research station such as we have at Abbotstown. Although I do not want to discourage the Deputy for the time being from using derris, I entertain a high hope that <Col N="520" /> veterinary research is about to provide us with a more effective and convenient therapeutic instrument for this condition.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Pigs and Bacon (Amendment) Bill," RHead="1956&mdash;Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Pigs and Bacon (Amendment) Bill, 1956&mdash;Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Bill received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Greyhound Industry Bill," RHead="1955&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Greyhound Industry Bill, 1955&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following amendment to Section 48:&mdash;</P>
    <P Just="Center">PART VI.</P>
    <P>Before sub-section (2), to insert the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(2) Where regulations under sub-section (1) of this section fix, in relation to a greyhound race track or part thereof, maximum charges in respect of bookmakers carrying on their business which are more than five times the maximum charges fixed, in relation to the track or part, by the regulations (or by other regulations for the time being in force) in respect of persons who are not such bookmakers, the regulations shall require the consent of the Minister.&mdash; (An tAire Talmhaíochta).</P>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing with amendments Nos. 25 (a), 28 (a), and the Minister's amendment No. 24 which are now being taken together.  Are those not the amendments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to draw the Minister's attention to what I think is an error on my part in regard to amendment No. 28 (a).  Amendment No. 28 (a) deals with sub-section (5) of Section 48 on page 23 of the Bill.  Does the Minister see sub-section (5)?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>He does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>That sub-section deals with coursing grounds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It does not matter.  We can discuss the general question raised by the three amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="521" />
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the Second Stage of the Bill, the Minister has gone a certain distance by introducing a ministerial amendment which goes so far as to ensure that, in regard to the maximum charges in relation to the tracks in respect of persons who are not bookmakers, these regulations shall require the Minister's consent. That has gone very far to meet us.  In view of previous speeches made by the Minister himself, in view of the Racing Board and Racecourses Act of 1945, in which he showed great solicitude for the bookmakers and in view of the Advisory Committee's recommendation that the charges should be limited to five times the amount, I would press the Minister to introduce the same provisions here as exist in the Racing Board and Racecourses Act of 1945. The Advisory Committee, at paragraph 166 on page 70 of their report, stated:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;We assume that if our recommendations in regard to the installation of the totalisators are approved, a licence to operate them will be granted only to the control board and in accordance with the terms of the Totalisator Act, 1929, of which sub-sections (5) and (6) of Section 3 are as follows.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Then they quote sub-section (6) which says specifically that, where a totalisator is in use, the charge to a bookmaker shall be limited to five times the amount of the charge to the public, but the Advisory Committee were never informed that the Racing Board and Racecourses Act of 1945 repealed sub-section (6).  It is rather extraordinary that a Government commission, having the assistance of civil servants, were allowed to be under the misapprehension that a certain section which was subsequently repealed was still in operation.  Sub-section (4) of Section 26 of the Racing Board and Racecourses Act, 1945, says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Sub-section (6) of Section 3 of the Totalisator Act, 1929 (No. 22 of 1929), is hereby amended by the deletion of all words from the words &lsquo;and the charge to any such licensed bookmaker&rsquo; to the end of the said sub-section.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It has actually cut out a safeguard <Col N="522" /> which the members of the commission thought existed.  In other words, the bookmakers were under the impression, I was under the impression and most Deputies in this House were under the impression that, where a totalisator was in operation, automatically it followed that the charge to bookmakers was limited to five times the admission charge to the public.  I now find that that is not so.  There is no question of doubt about it.  Therefore, the position at present is that even though the totalisator is introduced to, say, Shelbourne Park or Harold's Cross, for a start off that concession, which the Advisory Committee evidently thought was in operation of giving some sop to the bookmakers, is not there now.  I refer to paragraph 166 of the Advisory Committee's report.  They took that into consideration.</P>
    <P>The Minister, when speaking on the Second Stage of the Bill, at columns 1435 and 1436, Volume 153 of the Official Report, said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Part V of the Bill, dealing with course-betting permits for bookmakers and levies in respect of course bets, follows the lines of Part III of the 1954 Act concerning horse racing except that its operation is subject to ministerial Order from time to time, as the possibility is allowed for that, instead of a levy on course bets, there may be substituted a special admission charge on bookmakers payable to the board under sub-sections (4) and (7) of Section 48 in Part VI of the Bill.  Such special admission charges would of course be in addition to the admission charges payable to the tracks or clubs holding the meetings and under sub-section (1) of Section 48 the board would have power to control the over-all charges.</P>
    <P>Under the 1945 Act concerning horse racing, the maximum admission charge to bookmakers is fixed at five times the charge to members of the public and it has been represented on behalf of the greyhound bookmakers, especially the smaller ones, that the same limitation should apply in their case.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="523" /> The Minister goes on to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The present charges&rdquo;</P>
    <P>&mdash;I am not sure where he got his figures&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;to greyhound bookmakers are substantially in excess of five times the charges to spectators and the greyhound tracks appear to think that the same limitation as for the horse racing would involve them in losses .... It may be said in particular that the board will be expected to protect at all times the legitimate interests of the small bookmakers who will be subject to a betting levy or to a special admission charge in lieu thereof.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The matter was very capably dealt with by Deputy Finlay at column 1495 in the same volume of the Official Report.  He said:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I should also like the Minister to consider the question of the maximum and minimum charges for admission to racetracks.  This is a matter which has been the subject of very hard bargaining between greyhound racing track managers and promoters and bookmakers, both collectively and individually.  I think there is considerable force in the argument that, where the board are getting power to fix a maximum admission charge and where the effect of this Bill will be to provide for the installation of totalisators on greyhound racing tracks, that must take away from bookmakers as a group, some of their bargaining power with racetrack managers.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The point he is making is perfectly correct.  Hitherto, like workers in industry, the bookmakers at tracks, where there is no totalisator, could say to the track executive: &ldquo;If you do such and such a thing, then we will stop betting.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Deputy Finlay rightly points out that, with the introduction of the totalisator, that bargaining power will be taken from them.  He goes on to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;... I would ask the Minister to consider the possibility of tying down the maximum charges for admission <Col N="524" /> to bookmakers to the maximum charges for the admission of the public.  The exact ratio is a matter which could be discussed.  It is not a matter on which I have any information which would be sound enough to be of assistance to the Minister.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>At the bottom of that same column, 1496, Deputy Finlay goes on to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;If it is possible to assess now what would be a reasonable ratio between the charges which could be made for the admission of the public and the charges which could be made for the admission of the bookmakers, it would allay the fears of those who are being affected by this Act.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>He is 100 per cent. correct in that&mdash; that this is the place, now, to tie down this ratio.  The Minister said that it was all right for Dublin to limit the possible charges to five times the admission charges, but that there were certain tracks down the country where the charge might be as low as 1/-.  At column 1657 of Volume 153, the following appears:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;... but when it comes to asking me to fix a maximum of five times the admission price for a bookmaker entering a greyhound track because that is the maximum fixed on the racehorse tracks, I want to remind the House that when we talk of greyhound tracks we should not think only of Harold's Cross and Shelbourne Park.  There may be tracks down the country where, in order to draw a crowd, the proprietors may charge only 1/- or 2/-.</P>
    <P>Mr. T. Walsh: There is not one in Ireland that I know where the entrance fee is 1/-.</P>
    <P>Mr. Dillon: I do not know.  I do not suppose the Deputy is a frequenter of these tracks much more than I am myself and I do not know what the practice is, but my advice from a variety of sources is that it may be that some of these country tracks have to charge very low entrance fees....&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is not so.  There is no track in Ireland to-day charging anything as <Col N="525" /> low as 1/- for admission.  The lowest I know of is 2/6.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. A. Barry Mr. A. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>In the outside rings?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The idea of outside and inside rings only exists in Dublin.  There is no class distinction in the rural areas.  When the Minister suggested that some bookmakers were at present paying as much as ten times the admission charges, Deputy Briscoe reminded him that he should know that the present high level of prices to bookmakers was of recent occurrence and was based on expectancy of the Bill. Therefore, as all these amendments are co-related, and as this appears to be the most contentious section in the whole Bill, would the Minister, in order that we might progress to the less important remaining sections, consider this point?  His point is that some racetracks charge, say, 1/-, and that, if the admission charges of the bookmakers were five times that amount, then they would be paying only 5/- and their assistant 1/-.  Would the Minister be agreeable to an addition to my amendment No. 25 (a) (2) (a) before the Report Stage, or on the Report Stage, to the effect that the minimum charge in no case shall be less than 17/6 for the bookmaker and 3/6 for his assistant?  I understand from friends of mine on the opposite side of the House who are interested in this Bill that this should cover everything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister's fear is that, down the country, the admission charges are so low that tracks might be losing.  I was satisfied, personally, that the track executives would lose so little on the transaction that, if they did need a grant, the board could favourably consider it, because they have the powers. In a nutshell, all these amendments would go, including the Minister's amendment, if, as in the Racing Board Act of 1945, the idea therein, word for word, were introduced here, but the safeguard then to keep in mind on the point made by the Minister could be that in no case the admission charges shall be less than say 17/6 for the bookmaker and, say, 3/6 to be paid by his assistant.  It would get us a considerable <Col N="526" /> distance.  In his White Paper, the Minister stated:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Under the 1945 Act the Racing Board may regulate the charges for admission of licensed bookmakers and their assistants to horse racecourses generally, but may not fix the charges for bookmakers at more than five times the charges for members of the public nor the charges for bookmakers' assistants at more than the charges for members of the public.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>He continued:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The Advisory Committee's report (paragraph 166) recommended the limits of charges for the admission of bookmakers and their assistants should apply in the same way to greyhound tracks on which totalisators may be installed.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That, as I have pointed out, even in the White Paper is wrong.  We now find that, even when the totalisator starts off in Shelbourne Park and Harold's Cross, this safeguard is not there of five times the admission charge.</P>
    <P>To hark back to the Minister's point, that some of them are possibly at present paying six, eight or ten times the admission charge, as Deputy Briscoe said, that was put on by farseeing directors of the Dublin tracks in anticipation of the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. A. Barry Mr. A. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>When was it first put on, exactly?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as I know, the increased charges are in operation about 20 months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. A. Barry Mr. A. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputy is completely wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I should be sorry if all my information were as unsound as the information of the Advisory Committee on which Deputy Barry sat. They are talking here about Acts of 1929 which were repealed in 1945.  I am not completely wrong.  The charges were bounced up 20 months ago and they were increased again before that. My point is that the reasons the Advisory Committee recommended that the charges be limited to five times the admission <Col N="527" /> charge were purely and simply to compensate the bookmakers in some small measure for the loss they would sustain, due to the introduction of the tote.  It is agreed by everyone in the Advisory Committee's report that the bookmakers' turnover will be reduced by about 20 per cent. taking into consideration increased attendances.</P>
      <P>I therefore ask the Minister to introduce, verbatim, Section 26 of the Racing Board and Racecourses Act, 1945, and everybody will be happy.  I would go further and suggest that this minimum charge should also be introduced before the Report Stage, which will cater for the point the Minister had in mind; in other words, that the minimum charge shall be 17/6 for bookmakers and 3/6 for their assistants.  I would go even further, but I do not know if I am going too far, and make the minimum charge in any case £1 and let the charge for bookmakers' assistants be 5/-.  That is going a long way.</P>
      <P>Take the track in Limerick.  It is 2/6 for the public to go in.  Five times that is 12/6 and the charge for the bookmakers' assistants under the Racing Board's idea is 2/6.  What I say is: limit it to five times the admission charge.  I do not know if the charges at Limerick can go up, but make the minimum charges £1 for the bookmaker and 5/- for his assistant which will not, I agree, be of any immediate benefit to the bookmaker, but it will allay his anxieties and his fears for the future.  The Advisory Committee report on page 70, paragraph 166, having satisfied themselves that, where the totalisator was installed, everything in the garden was rosy, that this five times charge was already there and not being aware that sub-section (6) of Section 3 of the Act of 1945 had been repealed in the main part, they went on to say, at paragraph 167:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;We are aware that when it was previously proposed to install totalisators on the Dublin tracks, difficulties arose between the track managements and the bookmakers in regard to the pitches allotted to the latter.  We are of opinion that the position of the bookmakers <Col N="528" /> should be safeguarded in accordance with the spirit of the above quoted paragraph (6) of the Totalisator Act, 1929, and that where totalisators are to be installed by the control board, a licence to operate a greyhound racing track should not be granted by the board to the management concerned, or an existing licence renewed, except on a condition on the following lines:&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is, that the bookmakers and the management where they fail to agree on the location of pitches should have the right of appeal to the board.  I draw Deputy Finlay's attention to this matter because he was very helpful on the Committee Stage of the Bill.  I draw his attention to paragraphs 166 and 167, on going on the false assumption that protective legislation existed and that, if it were repeated in the Greyhound Bill, there would be no need for anxiety.  I think it is a very important point.  It should also be borne in mind that the bookmakers will be, as has been pointed out, the unpaid collectors of the levy.</P>
    <P>In this connection, I hope that the Minister will bear in mind on the Report Stage the point which caused quite a great deal of consternation in racing and sporting circles, and the Minister agreed with me on the point raised.  I am not getting away from the amendments nor departing from the five times the admission charge point. I want to point out one thing in case the Minister, or the board, might be under any misapprehension about the source of revenue.</P>
    <P>At present, under the Finance Act, 1953, and written into this Bill here, if I have £1 on a dog to-morrow morning, the levy payable to the State on that bet, if I lose, is the appropriate rate levied by the board.  Supposing it is 10 per cent. and I have £1 on this dog and I lose, the bookmaker pays the State 2/-.  If my dog wins at 10 to 1, I get £11 less 22/-, but the bookmaker still pays the State on the £1. How many thousands of pounds have been taken out of the people's pockets in this way I do not know.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this relevant to the amendments?  I suppose it is as relevant as reading the Official Report <Col N="529" /> and the Deputy has been doing that for an hour, so I suppose I should not object.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not come in until 11 o'clock.  I am only trying to point out that the Minister cannot take this section and these amendments purely out of their context.  The commission made certain recommendations&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Read it all again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not reading it again, I know it all by heart.  They made certain recommendations and assumed a certain turnover and certain revenue and I am pointing out one thing which should be cleared up once and for all, because evidently when we go into further details on this amendment, it will be seen that the point I am trying to bring home to the Minister is that a coursing bet&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>This has nothing to do with the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already told the Deputy that he is not being relevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to point out a very important point.  A coursing bet is one entered into by a licensed bookmaker&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no question of bets in the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no question of bets, but nevertheless, when the commission prepared their report, they prepared it on certain assumptions: that a levy would yield so much at 2½ per cent. and so much at 1¼ per cent., that the licensee of the tracks would pay so much and that the contribution from the bookmakers in certain cases of fixed charges, in certain cases of this very section, would yield so much. I respectfully suggest that I am quite relevant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It has nothing whatever to do with the entrance fee charged.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The other matter I would like to stress is that the recommendations of the Advisory Committee limiting the charge to five times the admission charge were made after the <Col N="530" /> Advisory Committee had taken evidence from all the tracks in Ireland and examined their accounts.  That point was stressed by the bookmakers. As I say, the Minister has gone very far and there is very little between us. My suggestion of the minimum might meet him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I have carefully considered all the relevant matters in relation to this, including the protracted debate on the Second Stage.  I received several deputations from the Bookmakers' Association and other interested parties.  I have considered the amendments submitted by the late Deputy Walsh and the substituted amendments now tendered by Deputy O'Malley, and I have to inform the House that the solution I propose for this matter is contained in amendment No. 24, the acceptance of which I cordially recommend to the House as an equitable solution of the various problems ventilated on the Second Stage discussion of this Bill and in the text of the amendment submitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there no possibility that the Minister would meet the suggestion made by Deputy O'Malley in relation to the small tracks where the totalisator is not likely to be in existence?  While it is recognised that there should be a minimum charge greater than the charge to the ordinary person, at least it should be a specified charge and should be a reasonable sum.  If the Minister were to say that, in cases where the totalisator was not installed, the maximum charge would be, say, 17/6, as Deputy O'Malley has suggested, or £1, that would cover the whole ground, because we on this side are only concerned at seeing that the dice is not unduly loaded against the bookmakers where the totalisator is not installed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy not accept that the proviso in amendment No. 24, which says that it must not be more than five times the charge made to the general public without the special authority of the Minister, contains in it the clear implication that a strong case would have to be made for anything in excess of five times, so that <Col N="531" /> it is hardly credible that authorisation would be given for a charge in excess of eight times, which £1, I think, would represent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We do recognise that the Minister has gone quite a considerable distance but there is this difficulty. Notwithstanding the amendment which the Minister has put down, it would still be possible in certain circumstances to fix the charge for bookmakers at an exorbitant rate&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Not unless the Minister for Agriculture consents to the exorbitant rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>One does not want to be playing one member of the Government against the other, but suppose the present Minister for Justice, or a person of the same outlook or attitude towards betting as the present Minister for Justice has indicated here in the House, were to become Minister for Agriculture.  I concede that that is not likely, but after all we are here to try to safeguard the people who are earning a livelihood in a way which is now recognised as perfectly lawful and is, in fact, acceptable to the general mass of the people.  We are here to ensure that they will be protected against the idiosyncrasies and prejudices of whoever may be responsible to Dáil Eireann for administering this Bill. That is all we are concerned about.  If the Minister could come some distance to meet us in that regard I think we could get ahead with fair rapidity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Deputy and Deputy O'Malley fairly said, I have come a very long way indeed to meet appeals made by them and their colleagues in the course of this discussion. I do not think it would be right or even expedient to go further than I have tried to go in amendment No. 24 and I believe that, on reflection, Deputies will realise that, in substance, amendment No. 24 provides every safeguard that they really require.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I assume amendment No. 24 is coupled with amendment No. 27, but would the Minister <Col N="532" /> between now and the Report Stage consider the situation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I will consider anything.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I know, but we do not want that sort of blanket consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to deceive the Deputy.  I think amendments Nos. 24 and 27 are as far as I can go.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is rather regrettable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister not aware that the first thing the new board will have to do when it comes in is to deal with these matters because at the present time many of the tracks are robbing the bookmakers with the charges put on.  Last Christmas 12 months, in the 1954-55 winter, at Shelbourne Park and Harold's Cross, the charges were raised from £1 to 32/6, and the charges were raised at Dundalk and Navan in March, 1956, while this Bill was being discussed. Deputy Barry tells me I have all my facts wrong.  I think the bookmakers who have gone to the Minister and who have gone to people on every side of this House have said that this is the one thing that has been worrying them.  On a previous occasion when the 1945 Racing Board Act was being debated, the Minister showed great solicitude for the small man.  Would the Minister not think again and we could get the Committee Stage of this Bill over?  Could he not say there should be a minimum charge, that in no case shall it be less than £1 for the bookmaker and 5/- for his assistant and in no case shall it be more than five times the admission charge?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the arguments put up here this morning on behalf of the bookmakers, I would press the Minister very strongly to make a definite charge because four or five times the amount of the admission charge is still rather indefinite.  We are here to try and help the industry and there is no use trying to squeeze out a very important part of that industry. We would have very poor coursing if we had not bookmakers.  As Deputy O'Malley says, the Minister should <Col N="533" /> make a definite charge at a reasonable figure and not leave the bookmakers to the mercy of any particular board.  I am not saying that the board will not have a difficult task in carrying out their work.</P>
      <P>As I said last night, we want to be impartial, fair and just in this matter. There is no use trying to injure one section.  The tracks may decide they are going to put up their charges to £5.  They may try and make a case for doing that and they may have confidence enough to succeed in doing that.  Legislation by good will and good wishes is very little use to us and we should make it very definite and prescribe a figure.  If we succeed in doing that, we will be contributing something worthwhile to stability and eliminating misunderstandings that have occurred from time to time as a result of hasty legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we not induce the Minister to go a little bit further? I am just refreshing my recollection of the words of wisdom which the Minister himself used when he was in opposition and was pleading the case of the bookmakers when the Racing Board and Racecourses Bill, 1945, was before the House.  The reference is to Volume 96 and the column is 1878.  I shall not go so far as the Minister went in his allegations against the Government of that day.  I shall not say, as he said on that occasion:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I believe that the purpose of those promoting this Bill is to drive the bookmakers off the racecourses. I would issue this warning&mdash;the gentlemen who are concerned to do that are failing to see the wood for the trees....  In the last analysis, the horse-breeding industry&rdquo;&mdash;</P>
      <P>I suppose one could substitute &ldquo;the greyhound breeding industry&rdquo;&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;depends on the mug,&rdquo;&mdash;</P>
      <P>I do not agree with that, the Minister's then judgment&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;the person who attends the race meeting for the fun of it.  The hub of that fun is the bookmaker's umbrella. I am convinced that this Bill is designed to wipe out the umbrella. These gentlemen think that it is <Col N="534" /> better policy to run racing on the <i>pari-mutuel</i> system, as it is easier to collect the race board's revenue out of the totalisator than it is from the bookmaker.  I believe they have sold that idea to a great many people in this country who ought to know better, people who have been racing all their lives, who believe themselves to be deeply concerned with the horse-breeding industry and the success of the export trade.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The horse-breeding industry the Minister referred to there but the greyhound industry we are considering now.</P>
    <P>I shall not say that it is the purpose of the Minister to drive the bookmakers off the racecourses&mdash;the amendments, Nos. 24 and 27, which he has put to the House are evidence to the contrary&mdash;but we do not think that they do constitute a water-tight safeguard for the bookmaker, particularly for the bookmaker who attends the smaller meetings and in the smaller country towns.  I would ask the Minister, will he, between now and Report Stage, look into this matter and see if he can meet the views expressed by Deputy O'Malley and the purpose which lies behind amendments Nos. 25 (a) and 28 (a)?  If the Minister would undertake to see if he could meet us to that extent, we will withdraw our amendments and allow the Minister's amendment to go without a division on the assumption that he will consider the points which have been made and put down an amendment on Report Stage which perhaps might cover the point.</P>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is amendment No. 24 agreed to?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister, I notice, is not prepared to be very conciliatory this morning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has just said that I have come very far to meet him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.  I am asking him to go&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Further.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="535" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Just that little bit further which will meet with the general acceptance of the House.  That is all I am asking.  If the Minister could see his way to do that, then we certainly should be very pleased and I am sure he would not have any cause to regret it.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 25, 25 (a) and 26 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 27:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (4), before paragraph (b) to insert the following new paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(b) Regulations under this sub-section shall not be made in relation to a greyhound racetrack or part thereof unless regulations under sub-section (1) of this section are made at the same time (or have been made previously) in relation to the track or part.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That seems to be complementary to amendment No. 24.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 28, 28a and 29 not moved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 30:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before sub-section (6), to insert the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(6)  Where regulations under sub-section (5) of this section fix, in relation to an authorised coursing meeting, maximum charges in respect of bookmakers carrying on their business which are more than five times the maximum charges fixed, in relation to the meeting, by the regulations (or by other regulations for the time being in force) in respect of persons who are not such bookmakers the regulations shall require the consent of the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the same principle as amendment No. 24, which the House has already accepted.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="536" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 31:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (7), before paragraph (b) to insert the following new paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(b) Regulations under this sub-section shall not be made in relation to an authorised coursing meeting unless regulations under sub-section (5) of this section are made at the same time (or have been made previously) in relation to the meeting.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 48, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 49.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 49 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The section as drafted gives the board absolute power by regulation or notice to fix the stake money and prizes to be offered at greyhound racetracks and gives them absolute power to fix different stake money or prizes in respect of different events and in respect of different tracks.  I think that it would not weaken the section and might lead to more satisfactory working if the Minister were to make it obligatory on the board to consult the greyhound racetrack executives before they fix the prizes and stake money.  We concede the general principle, but I do think it would make for simpler working if the board were bound to consult.  I assume that in the normal way they would do it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I would assume, with the Deputy, that they normally would.  I have not thought it desirable to put any such obligation upon them in the terms of the Act.  I am not inclined to do so and if the Deputy feels it is urgently necessary and chooses to put down an amendment for the Report Stage, I will have it considered.  I agree with him that it is highly likely that they would consult but I am not quite clear in my own mind that it is desirable to make it a statutory duty upon them to do that, though indeed the statutory duty to consult is never very onerous.  However, I shall certainly <Col N="537" /> consider it if the Deputy puts down an amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would make for better relations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. A. Barry Mr. A. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the idea behind this was that there would be a subsidy to the prize fund.  Therefore, the obligation of consultation would be fulfilled by the track.  They are going to seek to increase their prize fund and you will have that consultation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>But there is nothing here about subsidy.  The Deputy has not read the section.  The section empowers the board by regulations or notice, one or the other, peremptory notice&mdash;if the Deputy will look at Section 51, he will see that notice might be served by registered post without any consultation.  As I say, the section empowers the board by regulations or notice to fix the stake money and prizes to be offered for events at greyhound tracks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy might read that in connection with Section 16 (1) (c).  However, I do assure the Deputy there is no need to worry.  I agree with the Deputy that consultation, in almost every circumstance, should take place.  The net point is: should we make it obligatory or not?  I see no great objection to making it obligatory, for consultation can never do anybody any harm.  I do not feel it is necessary to put it into the Bill, but if the Deputy feels it is necessary and indicates that by putting down an amendment between now and Report Stage, I shall certainly consider it most favourably.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>May I point out something to which Deputy O'Malley has drawn my attention and submit it for the consideration of the Minister? The statement which appears in the White Paper on page 11 relating to Section 49 is very pertinent.  It says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;As regards Section 49, the Advisory Committee's report (paragraph 148) recommended that the board should have power&rdquo;</P>
      <P>&mdash;there is no question of subsidy here&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;to require racetracks to increase <Col N="538" /> prize money if the tracks' financial position should warrant this.  In paragraph 81 (4) the report referred to the inadequacy of the prize money offered in the majority of cases.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>On the basis of the White Paper, I am sure the Minister will give this very careful consideration and I would be grateful if, in this case, he would relieve the Opposition&mdash;for there seems to be so little difference of opinion between us&mdash;of the onus of putting down the amendment.  He can draft it very much better than we can.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I will carefully consider that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 50</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 31 (a):&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before Section 50 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other section of this Act no regulation made by the board or rule made by the club, the contravention of which would constitute an offence under the Act and such offence on conviction would be punishable by a fine, shall have any force or effect unless the Minister shall have given his consent to such regulation and a statement to that effect appears on the face of the regulation in question.</P>
      <P>I think the Minister has indicated that he is prepared to table an amendment on Report Stage which will meet the principle we have endeavoured to make effective by this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this not covered by the general undertaking that any such regulations will have to lie upon the Table and be subject to revision within 21 days?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The point is we have not got the Minister's amendment before the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has no apprehensions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="539" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>None whatever, but, as I say, the Minister has already accepted this in principle.  I am not at all apprehensive that the Minister will not give full effect to his undertaking. I am not suggesting that for one moment.  I was merely putting the point and the Minister put the query to me to which I replied we had not the amendment before the House. Naturally, we would like to see the Minister's amendment not because we doubt that it will not go all the way to meet us, but because there might be some slight difficulty about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no objection if the Deputy wants to withdraw this amendment now and put it down again on Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, when we have seen the Minister's amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 31 (b):&mdash;</P>
      <P>Before Section 50 to insert a new section as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other section of this Act every regulation made under it by the board or rule made by the club as the case may be shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after it is made and if either House of the Oireachtas within 21 sitting days after any regulation as aforesaid is laid before it shall pass a resolution annulling such regulation then the regulation in question shall be annulled accordingly and be without any effect whatsoever.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the same thing and the same procedure will be appropriate.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 50 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a section which creates an extraordinary amount of difficulty in my mind because there <Col N="540" /> is a very peculiar principle of duality running all through it.  It is very difficult to debate it without reverting to some of the sections which are mentioned. Sub-section (1) says: &ldquo;An offence under this Act, other than an offence specified in sub-section (2) of this section may be prosecuted by the board.&rdquo;  If you turn to Section 25 you will see there is a degree of duality, that a sort of diarchy is going to be set up in relation to the control, not merely of greyhound coursing but of greyhound racing.</P>
      <P>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - House-Building Industry">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - House-Building Industry.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Taoiseach whether he has received representations from interested parties in the house-building industry in connection with the critical position of that industry and, if so, when; if he will state the nature of such representations, and what proposals have been decided upon by the Government with a view to alleviating the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Certain representations have been addressed to me by the Dublin and District House Builders' Association, and the Minister for Local Government, who is the member of the Government concerned in the first instance, is joining with me in receiving a deputation from that body to-day.  In view of the imprecise terms in which the Deputy's question is expressed, I have no means of knowing whether the representations to which I have referred are those which he has in mind.  They are, however, the only representations relating generally to the position of the house-building industry that are at present before me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Taoiseach not aware of the very serious unemployment which exists in the building trade?  Would he say if the Government has any proposals to relieve that position?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="541" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not the question the Deputy has asked me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Taoiseach say what type of representations are being made to him?  What is the nature of the representations?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>From the Dublin and District House Builders' Association?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am receiving that association this afternoon to hear what they have to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Have the representations been made in writing?  Has the Taoiseach not received representations in writing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I received a letter asking me to receive a deputation, which I am receiving this afternoon, together with the Minister for Local Government, to hear their case.  So far as the City of Dublin is concerned, the Government have put at the disposal of the Dublin Corporation a specified sum for this year and next year, a sum which we are advised will enable house building to be carried on in future as it has been heretofore.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>And if the Dublin Corporation were not making a &ldquo;hames&rdquo; of their job, they would do it properly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Taoiseach state whether it is not a fact that he received a memorandum in connection with these representations?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I did, of course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Has he not read the memorandum?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Does he not know the nature of the representations?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a separate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course I know the nature of the representations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Taoiseach to tell the House what the nature of the representations is?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="542" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall not answer that until I see the deputation.  Presumably the Deputy has seen the memorandum and, therefore, I need not tell him what the representations are.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Unemployment Position">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Unemployment Position.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Taoiseach whether the Government have decided on any permanent measures with a view to reducing substantially within the next three months the grave unemployment figures, and, if so, if he will state the nature of such proposals; further if, in view of the fact that the winter relief scheme grants to local authorities have been cut by over 60 per cent. as compared with last year, he will state whether proposals exist to deal with the unemployment emergency pending the fruition of permanent proposals.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the first part of the Deputy's question, I have already, in reply to questions addressed to me in this House on the 24th October, 1956, referred to the Government's aim and policy of promoting an expanding economy and increased employment, to the Government's practical, constructive programme directed towards those ends which I publicly announced on the 5th October, 1956, and to the steps that have been and are being taken to carry that programme into effect.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The measures included in the Government's programme are, in fact, permanent measures designed and calculated to bring about a lasting reduction in unemployment and a lasting and progressive increase in productive employment. We do not claim for them that they will effect a substantial reduction in unemployment within a short period, such as the period of three months referred to in the Deputy's question. It would, no doubt, be possible, if the necessary money were available, to put a considerably increased number of persons to work within a short period on unproductive schemes of a relief character.  This, however, could be done only at the expense of a grave threat to the solvency of the State; the employment so provided would be temporary and short-lived; and the <Col N="543" /> prospect of promoting an expanding economy would not, in consequence, be improved but, rather, would be seriously impaired.</P>
    <P>In reply to the second part of the Deputy's question, I would refer to the reply given to a question addressed to the Minister for Finance by the Deputy on the 25th October, 1956, in the course of which he was informed that the proposed State expenditure in the financial year ending the 31st March, 1957, on employment schemes of local authorities towards which money is provided out of the Employment and Emergency Schemes Vote amounts to £265,000, as compared with expenditure amounting to £317,071 in the year ended the 31st March, 1956.  This represents a reduction, due to the necessity, in present financial circumstances, of limiting public expenditure on non-productive works; but the reduction is not one of 60 per cent., as stated by the Deputy, but, rather, of 16 per cent.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Taoiseach telling the House that his remedy for the grave uneconomic distress which prevails throughout the country is to set up more commissions, with more sinecures and a larger corps of functionaries, battening on the economy of the State?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am saying nothing of the sort.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what the Taoiseach's answer amounts to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy knows perfectly well I am saying nothing of the sort&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the Taoiseach's remedy for our present ills.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and if the Deputy and those behind him would carry into effect the lip-service they say they are giving to help the Government in the serious financial conditions affecting the country rather than try to make small political points for political purposes, we would get along much better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="544" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>More jobs for the boys.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="Minister for Defence (General MacEoin) Seán (Major-General) Mac Eoin">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (General MacEoin)</NameTxt>
      <P>What boys?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Government (Mr. O'Donovan) John O'Donovan (Dublin South-East)">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Government (Mr. O'Donovan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Sixty per cent.!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Taoiseach aware that he has just informed the 55,000 unemployed and their families that, for the next two years, they have nothing to look forward to but hunger and unemployment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have just informed those who are unemployed that they have some hope of permanent productive employment in the future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the plans the Taoiseach has now be more effective from the point of view of reducing unemployment than the plans he was supposed to have two years ago?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order! Question No. 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions." RHead="Oral Answers. - Oil Refinery">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Oil Refinery.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if it is intended to place on the Table of Dáil Éireann details of the proposals to build and operate an oil refinery which have been submitted by certain oil companies and have been accepted by him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Norton) William Norton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Norton)</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not the practice to place the details of industrial proposals on the Table of this House and I see no reason for doing so in the case of the proposals in question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Do these proposals involve any commitment by the Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>A commitment to establish the industry, with which, I think, everybody agrees.  If the Deputy is concerned about the public interest, he may be satisfied that every necessary step has been taken to safeguard the public interest in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="545" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I am certain that the Minister has not misunderstood me. Will any undertaking be given by the Government which will bind future Governments?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. Morrissey Mr. Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Morrissey</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Deputy trying to sabotage the refinery?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Remember what you did.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy may be satisfied that, if this Government ever leaves office, it will leave the Deputy a first-class oil refinery.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any reason why the Minister should try to evade a reply to my question?  Are any commitments being entered into which will be of a binding character as between the Government here and the promoters of this undertaking?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a pity that the Deputy did not put that question to himself in connection with some other industries which he established here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Why can I not get a reply to my question?  Why is the Minister trying to evade?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Because he has given them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy confines his expansive mind to greyhounds, he will do a service to the oil refinery and employment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That is all the Government has to put before the House.  As I said yesterday, when the country is going to the dogs, all the Government can think about is greyhounds.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should play with a little dog.  Deputy Lemass should understand that the establishment of an industry, an industry in this case involving the investment of £12,000,000, necessarily involves discussion with the promoting authority, in which they ask certain questions: can they do certain things; will they be allowed to do certain things; and under what conditions can they do certain things?  These are inevitable questions with which, I am sure, <Col N="546" /> Deputy Lemass is familiar.  These questions had all to be answered in dealing with this company and, finally, an arrangement has been made satisfactory to the company and, I think, satisfactory to the Irish people.  The public interest has been adequately safeguarded in this matter.  Now, may I put it to Deputy Lemass, as a responsible Deputy, that it is clearly undesirable that a matter of this importance, holding out so much promise for the people of the whole country, and particularly the area concerned, should be made a plaything of politics and Party politics, at that, in this House?  I make this offer to Deputy Lemass and I make it to him as a responsible member of the Opposition: I will show him, in confidence, what has been discussed with this company.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to see it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite sure, if the Deputy sees it, he will feel a good job has been done; and let us all take joy in the fact that we are going to have an oil refinery at last.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Labour Party having sabotaged it in 1935.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked the Minister for information.  I had no reason to think the information would be refused until the Minister spoke.  May I put the question this way: is there any need, or intention, to promote legislation in relation to this undertaking on the lines of the Cement Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>No need whatever.  I will make this offer to the Deputy: I will show him in confidence, as a responsible Deputy, the agreement that has been arrived at, and I am sure that, like myself, he will take satisfaction in the fact that we will have a first-class oil refinery in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to hear anything in confidence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Dáil is entitled to know.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Wheat and Tea Imports">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Wheat and Tea Imports.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if it is <Col N="547" /> intended to make any departure in this year from the customary method of financing wheat imports and, if so, if he will give particulars.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if it is intended to make any departure in this year from the customary method of financing tea imports and, if so, he will give particulars.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>With the permission of the Ceann Comhairle, I propose to take Questions Nos. 4 and 5 together.</P>
      <P>No departure is contemplated from the customary method of financing wheat and tea imports by means of borrowings by Grain Importers, Limited and Tea Importers, Limited, respectively; the repayment of which is guaranteed by the Minister for Finance under the State Guarantees Act, 1954.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The procedure up to the present involved borrowing from Irish banks under Government guarantee. Is that procedure to be followed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that if these companies borrow elsewhere than from Irish banks the discount may be with Irish banks and the ultimate Government responsibility still remains.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it intended to borrow elsewhere?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if advantageous rates can be got.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that, in the case of wheat, the borrowing is done in a foreign country in hard currency?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of fact I think I should tell the Deputy that as far as the Department of Industry and Commerce is concerned, it comes in only in an accidental way.  These questions should properly be addressed to the Minister for Finance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of the Minister's reply, would it not be far sounder policy from the point of view of agriculture that the importation of wheat should be cut out altogether?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="548" />
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister prepared to say whether or not 80 per cent. of the borrowing for wheat is done in Canada in dollars and that this State must guarantee the repayments whether or not the currency situation remains as it is?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputy should put down a question in his own name.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the Tánaiste knows that is being done?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the purest blatherskite.  Deputy Briscoe is doing a dirty job.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order! Question No. 6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>We have got a statement that there is no departure from procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThaddeusLynch" hpid="Mr. T. Lynch Mr. T. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. T. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>You are doing your best to smear the oil refinery.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>I started it.  The Minister had only to sign his name and it took him a pretty long time to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers. - Tea" RHead="Importers, Limited&mdash;Profit and Loss Account">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Tea Importers, Limited&mdash;Profit and Loss Account.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will explain the entry in the trading and profit and loss account of Tea Importers, Limited, for the year ended 31st March, 1956, which indicates that a loss of £68,403 16s. 0d. resulted from a reduction in sales following the increase of 2/- per lb. in selling prices on 1st October, 1955.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Following the increase in the issue price of tea from the 1st October, 1955, sales of tea by Tea Importers, Limited for some months were substantially below normal level, presumably because traders, caterers, institutions and other consumers were drawing upon their reserve stocks of tea.  The reduced sales involved the company in the cost of financing and warehousing the resultant increase in their stocks in the period to March 1956.  This factor, in addition to higher rates of bank charges for overdraft <Col N="549" /> and bill accommodation, resulted in the trading loss of £68,403 16s. 0d. for the half-year to 31st March, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister make it clear to the House how it came about that a reduction in sales, accompanied by an increase in price, involved an actual loss?  The statement in the published report of Tea Importers, Limited, certainly does not make the position clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>As I explained in my reply, the loss occurred because of the fact that the company found a diminished demand for tea because caterers, wholesalers and other institutions have large stocks of tea.  Tea Importers, Limited therefore, did not clear the tea with sufficient acceleration. So long as Tea Importers, Limited had to carry the stocks, they had to finance them and pay warehouse charges on them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>They always had to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>Not so much and not for so long.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The charges for interest and warehousing appear as separate items in the accounts of Tea Importers, Limited.  Why is this part of their business taken out and shown separately?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy makes inquiries from Tea Importers, Limited, as I hope he will, he will see their explanation of the thing is that they had to pay warehouse charges.  They had to hold tea which was financed by overdraft for a longer period than contemplated.  That will be evident when I tell the Deputy that in October 1955, approximately 2,500,000 lb. of tea were purchased.  That fell progressively until March when the stocks were 948,000 lb. of tea.  In April it went up to 1,500,000 lb. of tea and in September tea was back to the normal consumption of 2.4 million lb.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not these figures suggest that some notification of Government intentions reached the trade?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="550" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a very civil kind of observation.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Doolin Phosphate Mines">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Doolin Phosphate Mines.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJohnHillery" hpid="Dr. Hillery Dr. Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will have the possibility of reopening the Doolin phosphate mines investigated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy will appreciate that the reopening of these mines is a matter for private enterprise.  I will be prepared to grant any necessary facilities, under the Minerals Development Act, 1940, in relation to the deposits, to an applicant who can satisfy the customary conditions as to financial and technical resources.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Rural Electrification">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Rural Electrification.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if he will state the number of miles of rural electrification network erected and completed during the first nine months of each of the years 1954, 1955 and 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed by the E.S.B. that the number of miles of rural electrification network erected and completed during the first nine months of each of the years in question is as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="25*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="25*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">1954</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">3,699 miles</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>1955</entry>
            <entry>4,485 miles</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>1956</entry>
            <entry>5,167 miles</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. O'Sullivan Mr. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>That shook them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but what will it be next year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>They will not be there next year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>No supplementary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, there is a supplementary. Is it not a fact that the decision which brought about the stepping up in the E.S.B.'s extension of the rural electrification network was taken by the Minister's predecessor?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an entirely separate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a complete fabrication.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="551" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Question No. 9.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether it is proposed to continue extending the rural electrification network in Inishowen until the entire peninsula is linked up, and, if not, if he will state the considerations which led to such decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed by the E.S.B. that it is the board's intention to extend rural electrification to all areas in the Inishowen Peninsula.  The time at which the remaining areas in the peninsula will be developed will, however, depend on their order of priority in relation to areas awaiting development in the remainder of the county.  The determination of this order of priority is a matter solely for the board and I have no function in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of the reply, can I have from the Minister any indication as to whether or not work will cease for some time in the Inishowen Peninsula in the near future?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a matter for the E.S.B.  The question I was asked was whether it is proposed to continue extending the rural electrification network in Inishowen until the entire peninsula is linked up.  My reply said that the rural network would be extended to all areas in County Donegal in accordance with the result of the canvass.  The Deputy's colleague, Deputy Cunningham, was told this by the E.S.B. on the 10th of this month and he could have saved the Deputy the trouble of putting down this question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course he wanted to cut the ground from under poor Deputy Cunningham.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Further arising from the Minister's reply, I have asked the Minister whether it is the intention to continue extending the network in Inish owen and when it is intended extending it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the Rosguill invasion of Inishowen.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="552" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>As far as the E.S.B. is concerned, Donegal is treated as a single county.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Will they continue extending it or will they not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Ask Deputy Cunningham. He called in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The position is that Inishowen will qualify for rural electrification development in accordance with its place in the priority list within other areas in County Donegal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>That is no answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Trentagh (Donegal) School">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Trentagh (Donegal) School.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Education what is the position with regard to the construction of a new national school at Trentagh, County Donegal, and if he will state the percentage grant which it is proposed to make towards the cost of construction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Minister for Education (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Education (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>A grant has been sanctioned by my Department towards the cost of the erection of a new school at Trentagh, County Donegal.</P>
      <P>It is a matter for the Commissioners of Public Works to take the necessary steps to have the school erected, and I understand that the commissioners are at present in touch with the reverend manager regarding the provision of an adequate and suitable supply of water for the school, which will be equipped with water-flushed sanitation.</P>
      <P>It is not the practice to make public the arrangements made with the school manager in respect of grant and local contribution for any particular school.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister not tell us the percentage grant made in this case?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it has not been the practice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that the Minister gave an answer in this House last July indicating that he did not know then what the percentage grant was going to be?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I probably did not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="553" />
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that the Minister in January of this past year had already indicated in writing what the percentage of the grant was going to be?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>Indicated to whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Indicated to the manager of the school?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not the practice to make public any information with regard to arrangements made between the Department and any manager regarding the local contribution and the grant in respect of any particular school.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister said he did not know what it was in July.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I probably did not know it until very recently.  The communication was made only on the 9th October this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Milford (Donegal) School">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Milford (Donegal) School.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Education what is the position with regard to the construction of a new national school at Milford, County Donegal, and whether in view of the grave necessity for a new school he will expedite the project.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed by the Commissioners of Public Works that the preparation of detailed working drawings and a specification for the proposed new school at Milford has been completed.  Bills of quantities have yet to be prepared before tenders can be invited.  Because of the fact, however, that the commissioners' existing contractual commitments in respect of expenditure of grants on school building and improvement in the current financial year will fully exhaust the amount provided in the Estimates under Vote 9, it is not possible to say at present when the commissioners may be in a position to invite tenders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we to take it from the Minister's reply that for this year at any rate this school is out?  Am I clear on that&mdash;that it will not be <Col N="554" /> commenced during the current financial year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no hope at all that it will.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Arising out of that, the Minister has stated that they were not getting to a position to invite tenders. Will the same thing happen in regard to this school in Donegal, that when the tenders have been invited, they will all be thrown out because of the financial situation and then the contractors will be put to the expense of retendering?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an entirely separate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not hear the opening words which probably were significant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Yesterday, the Minister told me in regard to a school in Louth that the tenders that had been invited had been examined but that the building of the school was being postponed and that some time in the future they would reinvite tenders.  That will involve double expense for the contractors. Will the contractors in respect of this school be told when they are being asked to tender that the tenders will be subject to being thrown out and other tenders invited from them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is rather complicated in what he is endeavouring to convey.  If the Deputy will read the answer that I gave him yesterday he will realise that there is no acceptable tender before the Office of Public Works at the present time, and that the reason it will be necessary to invite other tenders in respect of that school is that there is no tender there at the present moment that the commissioners could accept.  A tender was accepted, and the individual who tendered backed out of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>That was not stated in the answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General Mulcahy General Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>General Mulcahy</NameTxt>
      <P>I answered the question the Deputy put down and if the Deputy wants any information with regard to what happens in regard <Col N="555" /> to the acceptance or otherwise of tenders, I have no function in either the consideration or the acceptance of tenders.  I gave the information that the Deputy asked for and the position with regard to that school mentioned yesterday is that tenders will have to be invited again.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Scoil na Fairche (Contae na Gaillimhe)">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Scoil na Fairche (Contae na Gaillimhe).</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>den Aire Oideachais an abróidh sé cén staid ina bhfuil an tairscint chun scoil ghairm-oideachais a bhunú i bparóiste na Fairche, Contae na Gaillimhe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Risteárd Ua Maolchatha Risteárd Ua Maolchatha">
      <NameTxt>Risteárd Ua Maolchatha</NameTxt>
      <P>Níor deineadh aon tsocrú cinnte i dtaobh na scoile seo ó thugas freagra ar an dTeachta ar an 9-2-1956 a rá go raibh Corr na Móna ainmnithe mar ionad scoile i scéim forbairte Coiste Gairm-Oideachais Contae na Gaillimhe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Bhfuil an tAire sásta leis an socrú sin?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Risteárd Ua Maolchatha Risteárd Ua Maolchatha">
      <NameTxt>Risteárd Ua Maolchatha</NameTxt>
      <P>Is é an coiste a dhein an socrú sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Bhfuil an tAire sásta leis?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Risteárd Ua Maolchatha Risteárd Ua Maolchatha">
      <NameTxt>Risteárd Ua Maolchatha</NameTxt>
      <P>Táim, is dócha.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Má tá sé an féidir leis an Aire a rá cathain a tósófar ar an obair?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Risteárd Ua Maolchatha Risteárd Ua Maolchatha">
      <NameTxt>Risteárd Ua Maolchatha</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl aon eolas agam maidir leis sin.  Is é an coiste a rinne an scéim sin agus do cheap siad i Mí Dheireadh Fómhair anuraidh iarracht a dhéanamh chun a fháil amach an méid páistí a bheadh ag freastal ar an scoil dá dtógfaí í i gCorr na Mónadh.  Chomh maith agus is eol dom, níl an fhaisnéis sin acu fós, agus pé scéal é, níl aon eolas agam mar gheall air.  Is ar an gcoiste a bhraithean sé a rá cathain a tosnófar ar an obair.  Tá sé socraithe acu cheana go mbfearr leo gan tosnú leis an scoil sin go dtí go mbeadh an scoil tógtha i gCárna.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Scoil Gairm-Oideachais i gCarna">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Scoil Gairm-Oideachais i gCarna.</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>den Aire Oideachais an abróidh sé cén <Col N="556" /> staid ina bhfuil an tairiscint chun scoil ghairm-oideachais a bhunú i gceantar Charna, Contae na Gaillimhe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Risteárd Ua Maolchatha Risteárd Ua Maolchatha">
      <NameTxt>Risteárd Ua Maolchatha</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá moladh ós comhair mo Roinne ó Choiste Gairm-Oideachais Chontae na Gaillimhe, chun Scoil Gairm-Oideachais a bhunú i gCárna, ach ní féidir liom a rá faoí láthair cá fháid go mbéidh mé i ndon a cheadú don choiste dul ar aghaidh leis an mbeart sin.  Níl méid na scoile atá ag teastáil socair fós.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Is é méid na scoile an taon-cheist amháin atá le réiteach?  Sin í an t-aon-fhadhb atá le socrú, méid na scoile?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Risteárd Ua Maolchatha Risteárd Ua Maolchatha">
      <NameTxt>Risteárd Ua Maolchatha</NameTxt>
      <P>Nuair nach raibh fios ag aon duine cad é an méid ba cheart a bheith sa scoil&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Ach an í sin an taon-cheist amháin?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Risteárd Ua Maolchatha Risteárd Ua Maolchatha">
      <NameTxt>Risteárd Ua Maolchatha</NameTxt>
      <P>Nuair nach bhfuil fios ag aon duine cad é an méid ba cheart a bheith san scoil is deacair a rá cad iad na deacrachtaí eile a bheadh ag gabháil leis an gceist agus ba chóir go dtuigfeadh an Teachta é sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Migration of Tenants">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Migration of Tenants.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnGeoghegan" hpid="Mr. Geoghegan Mr. Geoghegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Geoghegan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Land is he will state the number of families migrated from West Galway to the Midlands last year, and the number which it is expected will be migrated in the coming year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Minister for Lands (Mr. Blowick) Joseph Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands (Mr. Blowick)</NameTxt>
      <P>Thirteen families, consisting of 107 persons in all, were migrated from West Galway to the Midlands last year.</P>
      <P>As regards next season's programme, the Deputy will realise that such arrangements for migration as are in train are still tentative.  Final decisions regarding migration each year are based on a number of factors, including the circumstances of the various applicants, the suitability of their lands for use in rearrangement schemes and the number of new holdings available for disposal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="557" /> In the circumstances, it is not possible to indicate at this stage to what extent migration from West Galway to the Midlands will be feasible in the coming spring.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PhelimAlfredCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands whether the Land Commission are now in a position to state whether it is proposed in the coming year to migrate any landowners from the Currane area, Achill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>I would refer the Deputy to my replies to his questions on 8th March and 15th December last, and also my reply to another question on the subject on 13th July last, in which I explained in some detail the unusual difficulties regarding migration and rearrangement which confront the Land Commission in relation to this particular district.  In the circumstances the Land Commission are endeavouring to secure the rearrangement of as many holdings as possible disregarding the question of enlargement.  A number of holdings in the townland of Tonragee East have recently been rearranged and further holdings will be dealt with as circumstances permit.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Louth Afforestation Scheme">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Louth Afforestation Scheme.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands when the proposed afforestation scheme at Ballymakalett, Ravensdale, County Louth, will commence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>There are a number of difficulties in the way of acquisition of suitable land for afforestation in the Ballymakalett area.  My Department's main interest is in a commonage area of 375 acres but not all of the owners are prepared to dispose of their interests in this commonage and further progress towards its acquisition is not possible until the case can be reviewed under the Forestry Act, 1956.  This will be done at the earliest possible date.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Price of Chicks in Clare Gaeltacht">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Price of Chicks in Clare Gaeltacht.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJohnHillery" hpid="Dr. Hillery Dr. Hillery">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Hillery</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture whether in the Gaeltacht areas of County Clare the price of day-old chicks has been increased by 2/- a dozen, and, if so, if he will state <Col N="558" /> the factors which justified this increase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon) James M. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware that day-old chicks are being offered for delivery in several parts of the country, including the areas mentioned by the Deputy, at prices somewhat higher than those which prevailed this time last year. As, however, the prices charged by hatcheries for day-old chicks are not officially controlled, I am not in a position to reply to the latter part of the Deputy's question.</P>
      <P>Under the special scheme for the distribution of day-old chicks in certain Gaeltacht districts, residents in parts of County Clare may obtain &ldquo;as hatched&rdquo; day-old chicks at a specially reduced price of 10/- per dozen, which is approximately 50 per cent. of the price charged by the suppliers of the chicks.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Importation of Landrace Pigs">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Importation of Landrace Pigs.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture whether he will make a full and comprehensive statement of his reasons for not allowing the importation of Landrace pigs, covering in detail the following points: (a) what is the percentage incidence of atrophic rhinitis in the breed in the countries where it is generally or fairly generally kept, (b) what is the average loss of weight, due to the disease, in the output of bacon from 100 Landrace pigs in a given time, (c) what is the loss in the reduction of weight in relation to the economic gain over the average Irish pig due to the reputed food conversion efficiency and the improvement in the quality of hams, and (d) what authorities he consulted in regard to the prohibition of the importation of the breed, and what exactly each of them said in relation to the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like first of all to refer the Deputy to the answer I gave to a question on this subject on the 20th April, 1955, and to the very full statement I made in this House last Thursday.</P>
      <P>As to the specific points raised in his question, my information is as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="559" /> (a) Precise percentage figures of this nature are not available for this or indeed for many other diseases.  However, in countries where the Landrace breed is established, the incidence of infectious atrophic rhinitis is undoubtedly heavy.  It is significant that such countries have in fact set up special organisations to investigate the disease and deal with the problems arising.  Imports from such countries into countries where this disease was not previously known were associated with subsequent outbreaks of the disease in the importing countries.  The prohibition on the import of pigs into Britain and the Six Counties, which had been relaxed to allow an importation of Landrace pigs, was reimposed in 1954 and has since been firmly maintained.</P>
    <P>(b) and (c).  It is not practicable to give detailed statistics on such points, but I may say that the economic losses associated with the disease would far outweigh the special advantages claimed for the breed.</P>
    <P>(d) Internationally recognised authorities were consulted, but I do not think that it would be right for me to name them without their prior consent, particularly as they are in the service of other Governments.  The definite advice of such authorities based on their own experience was not to permit the import of Landrace pigs into this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister try to put himself into a position in which he could mention the names or give extracts from the reports of these authorities, in view of the fact that it is important, if we are to concentrate on our own existing breeds and improve them, to ease the farmers' mind on this matter?  The farmers are reasonable beings and I want to know all the considerations the Minister had in mind when this prohibition was being made, so that we can get the farmers to concentrate upon improving their own breeds quickly.  I think as much information as the Minister has at his disposal should be made available to the ordinary farmer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I quite agree, but I <Col N="560" /> should direct the Deputy's attention to the significant fact to which I have referred in my answer that &ldquo;the prohibition on the import of pigs into Britain and the Six Counties which had been relaxed to allow an importation of Landrace pigs was reimposed in 1954 and has since been firmly maintained.&rdquo; I forbear from reading out to the House <i>in extenso</i> a full description of the disease, its historical aspects, its symptoms, its pathology. and its suspected inherited susceptibility, but I would refer the Deputy for fuller information on that to <i>The Veterinary Record</i> for June 12th, 1954, Volume 66.  I would further refer the Deputy to the <i>Bulletin de l'Office International Des Epizooties, Tome XLIV&mdash;Mai,</i> 1955.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>Merci beaucoup.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>At page 274 of this bulletin, there is a discussion on this problem, which concludes with these words: &ldquo;The only method of eradication is the stamping out of affected subjects, and even of the whole swine-stock in farms where the condition occurs.  It is to be desired that, in every country, a wide investigation should be done by veterinary services so as to determine if infection exists and of what importance it is.  Restrictive regulations of international traffic of breeding subjects should then be adopted.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>If it would be of convenience or of value to the Deputy I would be happy to send him for his perusal a copy of the bulletin to which I refer.  I should also like to refer to the resolution of O.I.E. reported on page 593 of the <i>Bulletin de l'Office International Des Epizooties, Vingt-Troisieme Session du Comité de l'Office.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>La même chose.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>
        <i>La meme source.</i>  It refers to contagious atrophic rhinitis and says in the concluding paragraph&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Quotations are not usually permitted during questions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="561" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been asked by way of question, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Quotations are irregular.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>It is all right.  The Minister is merely trying to emulate the French master in Killaloe.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I was asked the question and&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am endeavouring to keep the House right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>May I refer to this source, Sir?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to make it clear that quotations are not in order during Question Time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I refer the Deputy to page 593 of the bulletin to which I referred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for the information he has given me in regard to this matter, but might I further ask the Minister to make available to any farmer who is interested in this question copies of these articles?  It is important the farmers should be satisfied that the Department of Agriculture have a reasonable case in order that, having cleared their minds of the reputed efficiency of this breed, they should get on with improving the breeds that exist.  The Minister should make available&mdash;it will not cost a lot&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>This discussion is irregular.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;copies of these articles.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I should be very glad to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to ask the Minister one simple, short question. Can the Minister explain how it is that the Danes have been able to use this breed of pig with tremendously satisfactory results?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already referred to that.  I do not think we should seek the opportunity of introducing this <Col N="562" /> breed into our midst as we are free of the disease.  We are thus not required to take the precautions the Danes have to take.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions." RHead="Oral Answers. - Air Agreement">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Air Agreement.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for External Affairs when the text of the new Air Agreement with Britain will be submitted for ratification to Dáil Éireann.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Cosgrave) Liam Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Cosgrave)</NameTxt>
      <P>The agreement to which the Deputy refers is an exchange of notes amending the Air Services Agreement between the Irish and British Governments of the 5th April, 1946.  The notes were exchanged by the British Ambassador and myself on the 31st August, 1956.  This exchange was not subject to subsequent ratification by either Government.</P>
      <P>The requirement of Article 29.5.1º of the Constitution that every international agreement to which the State becomes a party shall be laid before Dáil Éireann, was complied with, in the case of this exchange of notes, on the 13th September, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that the original agreement was submitted to the Dáil for ratification, does the Minister not think that this important modification of it should also be submitted?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Deputy's mind is at fault there.  The original agreement was submitted for discussion, but it did not require to be ratified.  In this case, as the Deputy is no doubt aware, where an agreement does not involve a charge on public funds it has not to be approved of by the Dáil.  This agreement, in compliance with Article 29.5.1º of the Constitution, to which I have referred, was laid before the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it proposed to submit it to the Dáil for discussion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Mr. Cosgrave Mr. Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cosgrave</NameTxt>
      <P>Not by me, at any rate.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Import Levy on Motor Cars">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Import Levy on Motor Cars.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if the statement made by him, <Col N="563" /> and reported in the press on 4th October, that the special import levy on motor cars is to remain in operation for at least two years, still represents the intentions of the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Sweetman) Gerard Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Sweetman)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Press statement referred to by the Deputy was to the effect that following consideration of the matter by the Government the Minister for Finance had, with regret, intimated to the National Union of Vehicle Builders that he felt it would be necessary in the interests of the national economy as a whole and to avoid adding to our balance of payments difficulties that the special import levy on motor cars should remain in operation for at least two years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister had, I think, explained to him by the trade unions concerned the importance to them that there should be no doubt in anyone's mind that these special taxes &mdash;in this case involving motor cars&mdash; would last for at least two years.  In view of the importance of having any doubt in that regard removed, will the Minister take steps to ensure that none of his colleagues make statements which will cause any misunderstanding?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>None of my colleagues has made any such statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>They have indeed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>They have not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Industry and Commerce implied that these duties might go off.  The employment of a substantial number of workers depends upon its being understood that these are not likely to be removed.  Will the Minister see that ambiguous statements, which imply the contrary, are not made by his colleagues?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The ambiguity was in the Deputy's interpretation, and not by the Minister.  The Minister for Industry and Commerce is as aware as I am&mdash;perhaps even more so&mdash;that continuity <Col N="564" /> of employment depends on regularisation of supplies in the way the Deputy has himself indicated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>He should keep his tongue quiet, then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should not try to misinterpret or misquote.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Import Levy on Gifts">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Import Levy on Gifts.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether he is aware that gifts are affected by the special import levy and, if so, if in view of the hardship thus caused to people of moderate means and having regard to the fact that gifts do not affect the adverse trade balance, he will revoke the levy so far as gifts are concerned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The special import levies apply to gifts in the same way as they apply to other imports.  I appreciate that there is a case in principle for exempting gifts from levy, but I regret that for administrative reasons such an exemption would not be practicable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that to prevent somebody from receiving a gift will not affect the adverse trade balance?  We understand that these levies are primarily to stop imports for which we have to pay in order to correct the adverse trade balance.  By stopping gifts coming to our people&mdash;and there are many of them coming to people from abroad&mdash; and imposing these heavy levies on these people, the Minister is creating a hardship and is not helping the situation. Surely it is better to get something for nothing than not to get anything at all?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is as well aware as I am that certain things are sometimes described as gifts that are not gifts at all.  It would be administratively impossible to distinguish what are gifts in the true sense of the term and what are part of reciprocal arrangements under the heading of gifts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not so aware.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions." RHead="Oral Answers. - Relief Schemes">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Relief Schemes.</Title>
    <Col N="565" />
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state the amount allocated to each local authority for winter relief schemes in the current financial year and in the financial years 1953-54, 1954-55 and 1955-56; and if, in view of the present grave unemployment position, he will state the reasons for the substantial reductions in the allocations for the current financial year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Donnellan) Michael Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Donnellan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The information in the first part of the <Col N="566" /> question is in the form of tabular statements which, with the permission of the Ceann Comhairle, I propose to circulate in the Official Report.  The reasons for the reductions in the allocations for the current financial year are twofold: (a) the necessity in present financial circumstances of limiting public expenditure, and (b) the large carry-forward on the 1st April, 1956, of unexpended grants, amounting to £285,104, which are available for expenditure in the current year.</P>
      <P>The following is the statement:&mdash;</P>
      <P Just="Center">
        <i>(a)</i>  URBAN EMPLOYMENT SCHEMES.</P>
      <P Just="Center">GRANTS ALLOCATED TO VARIOUS URBAN DISTRICTS AND COUNTY BOROUGHS.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="4" colnum="4" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="5" colnum="5" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1956/57</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1955/56</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1954/55</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1953/54</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>URBAN DISTRICT:</entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Carlow</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
            <entry>1,150</entry>
            <entry>950</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cavan</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>600</entry>
            <entry>1,200</entry>
            <entry>1,300</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Ennis</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>1,400</entry>
            <entry>1,500</entry>
            <entry>1,950</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Kilrush</entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
            <entry>1,150</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
            <entry>1,200</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Clonakilty</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
            <entry>550</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cobh</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
            <entry>1,400</entry>
            <entry>1,950</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Fermoy</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
            <entry>750</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
            <entry>850</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Kinsale</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>650</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
            <entry>650</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Macroom</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Mallow</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
            <entry>600</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Midleton</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Skibbereen</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>600</entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Youghal</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
            <entry>1,150</entry>
            <entry>1,300</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Buncrana</entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
            <entry>1,300</entry>
            <entry>650</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Bundoran</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Letterkenny</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
            <entry>800</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Dun Laoire</entry>
            <entry>2,500</entry>
            <entry>7,000</entry>
            <entry>8,250</entry>
            <entry>8,750</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Ballinasloe</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
            <entry>600</entry>
            <entry>1,100</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Galway</entry>
            <entry>1,150</entry>
            <entry>3,700</entry>
            <entry>4,600</entry>
            <entry>4,550</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Killarney</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>800</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
            <entry>1,300</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Listowel</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
            <entry>1,300</entry>
            <entry>1,300</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Tralee</entry>
            <entry>2,650</entry>
            <entry>6,000</entry>
            <entry>6,300</entry>
            <entry>5,100</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Athy</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Naas</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Kilkenny</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
            <entry>2,200</entry>
            <entry>3,000</entry>
            <entry>2,900</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Longford</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
            <entry>1,250</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Drogheda</entry>
            <entry>1,500</entry>
            <entry>5,400</entry>
            <entry>5,600</entry>
            <entry>6,200</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Dundalk</entry>
            <entry>1,650</entry>
            <entry>5,500</entry>
            <entry>6,100</entry>
            <entry>7,550</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Ballina</entry>
            <entry>650</entry>
            <entry>1,650</entry>
            <entry>2,150</entry>
            <entry>2,250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Castlebar</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Westport</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
            <entry>750</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>An Uaimh</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>550</entry>
            <entry>800</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Ceannanus Mor</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>550</entry>
            <entry>650</entry>
            <entry>800</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Trim</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Carrickmacross</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Castleblayney</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>600</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Clones</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>600</entry>
            <entry>850</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Monaghan</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Birr</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>600</entry>
            <entry>750</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Tullamore</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>650</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Sligo</entry>
            <entry>1,600</entry>
            <entry>4,750</entry>
            <entry>5,300</entry>
            <entry>3,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <Col N="567" />
              <Col N="568" />Nenagh</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
            <entry>1,100</entry>
            <entry>1,400</entry>
            <entry>1,750</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Templemore</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Thurles</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>350</entry>
            <entry>600</entry>
            <entry>750</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Carrick-on-Suir</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
            <entry>1,150</entry>
            <entry>1,250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cashel</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>600</entry>
            <entry>850</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Clonmel</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
            <entry>1,900</entry>
            <entry>2,450</entry>
            <entry>2,650</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Tipperary</entry>
            <entry>550</entry>
            <entry>1,900</entry>
            <entry>1,750</entry>
            <entry>2,450</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Dungarvan</entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
            <entry>1,300</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
            <entry>1,250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Athlone</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
            <entry>1,600</entry>
            <entry>1,700</entry>
            <entry>1,850</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Enniscorthy</entry>
            <entry>550</entry>
            <entry>1,900</entry>
            <entry>2,150</entry>
            <entry>2,200</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>New Ross</entry>
            <entry>550</entry>
            <entry>1,100</entry>
            <entry>1,700</entry>
            <entry>1,500</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Wexford</entry>
            <entry>2,150</entry>
            <entry>4,800</entry>
            <entry>5,400</entry>
            <entry>4,700</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Arklow</entry>
            <entry>450</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
            <entry>1,400</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Bray</entry>
            <entry>800</entry>
            <entry>2,300</entry>
            <entry>2,750</entry>
            <entry>3,550</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Wicklow</entry>
            <entry>400</entry>
            <entry>800</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
            <entry>1,050</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>TOTALS (Urban Districts)</entry>
            <entry>32,500</entry>
            <entry>78,100</entry>
            <entry>89,500</entry>
            <entry>96,050</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>COUNTY BOROUGHS:</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cork</entry>
            <entry>7,500</entry>
            <entry>30,000</entry>
            <entry>33,000</entry>
            <entry>35,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Dublin</entry>
            <entry>Not Determined</entry>
            <entry>175,000</entry>
            <entry>200,000</entry>
            <entry>260,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Limerick</entry>
            <entry>6,500</entry>
            <entry>20,000</entry>
            <entry>24,500</entry>
            <entry>26,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Waterford</entry>
            <entry>3,500</entry>
            <entry>9,000</entry>
            <entry>13,000</entry>
            <entry>14,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>TOTALS (County Boroughs)</entry>
            <entry>17,500</entry>
            <entry>234,000</entry>
            <entry>270,500</entry>
            <entry>335,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>ALL AREAS: TOTALS</entry>
            <entry>50,000<br />(excluding Dublin)</entry>
            <entry>312,100</entry>
            <entry>360,000</entry>
            <entry>431,050</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>(b)</i>  RURAL EMPLOYMENT SCHEMES.</P>
    <P Just="Center">GRANTS ALLOCATED TO VARIOUS COUNTY COUNCILS.</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="5">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="40*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="4" colnum="4" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="5" colnum="5" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">County</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1956/57</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1955/56</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1954/55</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1953/54</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Carlow</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cavan</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>1,250</entry>
            <entry>1,750</entry>
            <entry>1,250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Clare</entry>
            <entry>420</entry>
            <entry>1,500</entry>
            <entry>1,500</entry>
            <entry>927</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cork, North</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>550</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cork, South</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Cork, West</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>1,750</entry>
            <entry>2,250</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Donegal</entry>
            <entry>700</entry>
            <entry>15,500</entry>
            <entry>15,000</entry>
            <entry>14,500</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Dublin</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Galway</entry>
            <entry>1,380</entry>
            <entry>7,500</entry>
            <entry>7,082</entry>
            <entry>8,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Kerry</entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
            <entry>7,000</entry>
            <entry>7,000</entry>
            <entry>6,250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Laoighis</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Leitrim</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>2,750</entry>
            <entry>2,850</entry>
            <entry>2,500</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Limerick</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>800</entry>
            <entry>1,250</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Longford</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>550</entry>
            <entry>900</entry>
            <entry>1,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Mayo</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>13,500</entry>
            <entry>12,000</entry>
            <entry>12,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Offaly</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Roscommon</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>1,250</entry>
            <entry>1,050</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Sligo</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>2,500</entry>
            <entry>2,500</entry>
            <entry>2,500</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Tipperary, N.R.</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Waterford</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Westmeath</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Wexford</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
            <entry>300</entry>
            <entry>500</entry>
            <entry>250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>TOTALS</entry>
            <entry>5,000</entry>
            <entry>58,850</entry>
            <entry>58,182</entry>
            <entry>51,727</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <Col N="569" />
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Parliamentary Secretary state if it is now the policy of the Government to limit expenditure at the cost of employment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what you are saying.  If the people believe you, they are fools.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Parliamentary Secretary indicate whether these cuts in relief scheme grants are uniform all over the counties or <i>pro rata</i> to the amount last year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>What cuts?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The cuts you have just admitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>He does not know what he said.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I get a reply, please?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Question No. 23.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Could I get a reply to my supplementary question?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not the duty of the Chair to get a reply for the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary should be made give a reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>He is dying to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>You are dying to tell me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state in respect of Roscommon County Council the amount allocated for winter relief schemes in the last and current financial years, respectively.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>The total allocation for winter employment schemes in County Roscommon in 1955-56 was £4,535 of which £1,250 was allocated to the county council.  The corresponding figures for the current financial year are £3,070 and £250 respectively.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the big reduction that has taken place in this grant, would the Parliamentary Secretary <Col N="570" /> explain what he means by stating that this reduction of the grant is for the necessity of limiting public expenditure when the Taoiseach has already stated that Government policy is to secure a lasting reduction in unemployment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Hear, hear!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is this lasting reduction in unemployment to be secured by a mounting rate of emigration forced by a reduction in Government grants to needy families all over Ireland?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Productive work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it Government policy now, during the Christmas period, to force the breadwinners in needy families to emigrate as a result of the reduction in the grants which has taken place, according to the Parliamentary Secretary?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>These unfortunate people can take a holiday, no doubt.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is a scandalous state of affairs.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Dublin Special Relief Works">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Dublin Special Relief Works.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance when he expects to be able to indicate to the Dublin Corporation the amount of grant which will be made available in this financial year for special relief works, and if he will state the amount of such grant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not in a position to determine the amount of the grant, if any, to be allocated to the Dublin Corporation for employment schemes until the position with regard to the progress of uncompleted schemes sanctioned in prior years has been clarified.  Work schemes, costing approximately £257,000, of which the appropriate State grant is £206,085, were outstanding on the 1st April, 1956.  The city manager has been asked for information on this subject and his reply is awaited.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Parliamentary Secretary aware that what he has <Col N="571" /> stated now is a terrible thing?  Is he not aware that, when grants are allocated, they are not necessarily immediately spent, because a scheme may take a year or 18 months to complete and that because the money has not been spent, no further grant will be made until it has been spent?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Some of these are not started even yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that the Parliamentary Secretary's excuse for not giving Dublin Corporation any notification of further grants for the relief of unemployment?  Is it because grants already allocated have not been spent, due to the fact that they cannot physically be spent until a certain period elapses?  Some of the schemes may take 18 months to complete and, consequently, the money cannot be availed of.  However, there are other schemes which, if grants are made available, can immediately be put into effect.  Is the Parliamentary Secretary now saying that, in Dublin City, the 300 odd men constantly employed on relief schemes can now be sacked?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>If they are, the Deputy can accept the main blame, because there is a sum of £257,000 there to be spent.  Some of the schemes have not yet even been started.  Does the Deputy expect us to allocate more money when that sum of £257,000 is still there?</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Swilly Burn Drainage">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Swilly Burn Drainage</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMcMenamin" hpid="Mr. McMenamin Mr. McMenamin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McMenamin</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he is now in a position to state when work will commence on the Swilly Burn catchment drainage scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Following the recent exhibition of the scheme in accorddance with the provisions of the Arterial Drainage Act, 1945, the further statutory requirements are now receiving attention.  I am not at present in a position to say when works under the scheme may start.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions." RHead="Oral Answers. - Housing Loans">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Housing Loans</Title>
    <Col N="572" />
    <Speaker pid="CeliaLynch" hpid="Mrs. Lynch Mrs. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether he is aware that as a result of the operation of Section 19 (b) of the Housing (Amendment) Act, 1956, great hardship is caused to applicants for loans because they have to pay deposits which are as much as two and a half times greater than heretofore, and if he will take steps to rectify the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Minister for Local Government (Mr. O'Donnell) Patrick O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Local Government (Mr. O'Donnell)</NameTxt>
      <P>In cases in which complaints of this nature have been made I have found that the difficulties complained of arise from the fact that the selling prices of some houses in the Dublin area exceed substantially the market values of the houses as determined by the local authorities concerned in accordance with statute.  I do not see any reason why selling prices should exceed market values as so determined.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Housing Guarantee Scheme">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Housing Guarantee Scheme.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="CeliaLynch" hpid="Mrs. Lynch Mrs. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he will state (a) the number of applications under the housing guarantee scheme received by the Dublin Corporation and the Dublin County Council, (b) the number approved by his Department and by the local authorities in question, and (c) the number finalised, and the amount of loans paid to applicants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>The information requested is not available in my Department. These are matters in which my approval is not required.  They are dealt with directly between the building societies and the local authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister say whether in the course of the last two or three weeks the various building societies have been refusing to entertain any application for grants?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of any refusal in the city or county of Dublin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the Minister is aware that some of the building societies have ceased to operate altogether?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="573" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not so aware.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware of the number of applications that have come for sanction for guarantee and that the number is indeed very small?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware of the fact that when the Deputy as Lord Mayor had done with the Small Dwellings Act and I exposed him in the <i>Irish Press</i> he undertook to call a special meeting of the Dublin Corporation which he has not done yet.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister need not be worrying about that.  A special meeting is being called and the facts are being prepared so that the Minister will not get out this time with bluff.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if, in respect of areas in which building societies are not prepared to operate the guarantee scheme provided for in the Housing (Amendment) Act, 1956, he will state whether persons, who in other areas would come within the scope of the guarantee scheme, will be regarded as eligible for loans under the Small Dwellings Acquisition Acts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Local authorities have been asked to confine advances under the Small Dwellings Acquisition Acts to applicants who could not reasonably be expected to finance the provision of their houses otherwise. The decision on each application rests with the local authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister give a straight answer once and for all and give over his bluff and say is he aware that in certain areas, where the guarantee scheme is not operative, the local authorities have confined their advances to certain categories and in view of the fact that the building societies do not operate in these areas how will building be carried on?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Local authorities have been asked to make loans available to applicants who are unable to finance the building of their own houses.  It is a matter entirely for each <Col N="574" /> local authority to adjudicate on each application submitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that the Minister intimated to each local authority that they should adopt such guarantee scheme?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>I recommended it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>You are the people bringing private building to an end.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Scéimeanna Oibreacha Poiblí">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Scéimeanna Oibreacha Poiblí.</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>den Aire Rialtais Aitiúil an abróidh sé cé mhéad scéimeanna i leith oibreacha poiblí faoi bhun dhá mhíle go leith punt costais an ceann a cheap an Coiste Idir-Rannach sna blianta 1954-55, 1955-56, agus atá ceaptha go dtí anois sa mbliain reatha; agus cé mhéad acu, faoi seach, a críochnaíodh agus atá ar siúl.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Pádraic Ó Domhnaill Pádraic Ó Domhnaill">
      <NameTxt>Pádraic Ó Domhnaill</NameTxt>
      <P>Cheadaigh an Coiste naoi scéimeanna sa bhliain 1954-55. Tá cúig cinn díobh siúd críochnaithe, dhá cheann ar siúl agus dhá cheann nár tosnaíodh fós orthu. Cheadaigh an Coiste ocht scéimeanna sa bhliain 1955-56.  Tá ceann amháin díobh siúd ar siúl.  Níor tosnaíodh ar na cinn eile fós.  Sa bhliain airgeadais reatha, cheadaigh an Coiste trí scéimeanna.  Níor tosnaíodh orthu fós.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Bóithre Cuartaíochta na Gaeltachta">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Bóithre Cuartaíochta na Gaeltachta.</Title>
    <P>D'fhaiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>den Aire Rialtais Aitiúil an bhfuil Coiste Idir-Rannach Oifig na Gaeltachta agus na gCeantar gCúng ann fós; má tá, an bhfuil dualgas orthu i leith bóithre cuartaíochta sa nGaeltacht d'fheabhsú; agus, más amhlaidh don scéal, an abróidh sé cé mhéad airgid atá ceaptha nó molta acu san mbliain reatha don chuspóir seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Pádraic Ó Domhnaill Pádraic Ó Domhnaill">
      <NameTxt>Pádraic Ó Domhnaill</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá an Coiste Eadar-Roinne a ghabhas le hOifig na Gaeltachta agus na gCeantar gCúng ar bun go fóill.  Níl aon dualgas ar an gCoiste sin i leith Scéim na mBóthar Cuartaíochta sa Ghaeltacht.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>An féidir leis an Aire a rá go gcuirfidh sé féin <Col N="575" /> airgead ar fáil le haghaidh na seirbhísí seo?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Pádraic Ó Domhnaill Pádraic Ó Domhnaill">
      <NameTxt>Pádraic Ó Domhnaill</NameTxt>
      <P>Sin ceist eile. Má chuireann tú an cheist síos, gheobhaidh tú freagra uaim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>An féidir leat &ldquo;is ea&rdquo; nó &ldquo;ní hea&rdquo; a rá anois?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Pádraic Ó Domhnaill Pádraic Ó Domhnaill">
      <NameTxt>Pádraic Ó Domhnaill</NameTxt>
      <P>Níshin í an cheist atá ann inniu.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá a fhios ag an Aire an bhfuil nó nach bhfuil airgead ceapaithe le haghaidh na seirbhísí seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Achill Water Supply">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Achill Water Supply.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PhelimAlfredCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether the revised plans for the Achill water supply scheme have yet been approved by his Department and, if so, if he will immediately notify the Mayo County Council of his decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielSpring" hpid="Parliamentarry Secretary to the Minister for Local Government (Mr. Spring) Parliamentarry Secretary to the Minister for Local Government (Mr. Spring)">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentarry Secretary to the Minister for Local Government (Mr. Spring)</NameTxt>
      <P>Detailed plans for a regional water supply scheme have recently been forwarded to my Department with reports containing estimates of the cost of various alternatives involved.  The extent of the work which the county council propose to undertake has not been indicated and they have been requested to furnish further information on this point.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Dundalk Housing Scheme">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Dundalk Housing Scheme.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeCoburn" hpid="Mr. Coburn Mr. Coburn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Coburn</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether he received recently from the Dundalk Urban District Council proposals in connection with the invitation of tenders for the Marian Park housing scheme and, if so, if he will expedite the issue of sanction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>The proposals referred to were dealt with in a letter dated 16th May last from my Department in which the council was informed that, subject to some minor amendments of their draft contract documents, no objection would be raised to the invitation of tenders for the scheme.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Mayo Medical Register">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Mayo Medical Register.</Title>
    <Col N="576" />
    <Speaker pid="PhelimAlfredCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Health if he will state in respect of County Mayo (a) the total number of applications for entry on the medical register under the Health Act, 1953, which have been received up to the latest available date, (b) the number approved, (c) the number rejected, and (d) the number under consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Minister for Health (Mr. O'Higgins) Thomas Francis (Jnr.) O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Health (Mr. O'Higgins)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed by the local authority that (a) the number of applications received for entry on the general medical services register up to the 30th September, 1956, was 9,629.  Of these, (b) 8,399 were approved, (c) 1,129 were rejected, and (d) 101 were under consideration.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Seirbhísí na Gaeltachta">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Seirbhísí na Gaeltachta.</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>d'Aire na Gaeltachta an bhfuil an fhreagracht sa Dáil i leith Seirbhísí na Gaeltachta aistrithe ón Aire Tailte chuige féin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Aire na Gaeltachta (Pádraig Mac Loingsigh) Aire na Gaeltachta (Pádraig Mac Loingsigh)">
      <NameTxt>Aire na Gaeltachta (Pádraig Mac Loingsigh)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá.  Le hOrdú na Gaeltachta (Riarachán Roinne agus Feidhmeanna Aire d'Aistriú), 1956, a rinne an Rialtas ar an 3ú Deireadh Fómhair, 1956, haistríodh Roinnteán Sheirbhísí na Gaeltachta den Roinn Tailte chuig mo Roinn-se amhail ón 15ú Deireadh Fómhair, 1956.  Tíolacadh cóipeanna den Ordú don Dáil ar an 3ú Deireadh Fómhair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>An abróidh an tAire linn go bhfuil athrú polasaí sa cheist seo?  An bhfuil fhios ag an Aire gur dhúirt céad Aire na Gaeltachta nach mbaineann a Aireacht le Contae an Chláir?  Tá a fhios ag an Aire go dtógann límistéir Acht na dTithe (Gaeltacht) Contae an Chláir isteach.  Anois tá Contae an Chláir tógtha isteach faoina sciatháin san Ordú sin.  An abróidh an tAire go bhfuil athrú polasaí ann?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní dóigh liom go mbaineann an cheist sin leis an gceist atá ar an bPáipéar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Parthaláin Gearóid Mac Parthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Parthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá ordú límistéirí Gaeltachta déanta ag an <Col N="577" /> Aire.  Tá na toghranna ceantair atá sa bhFíor-Ghaeltacht luaite ann agus, ar ndóigh, is ceantar thar a bheith beag é.  Tá Conndae Roscomáin, Conndae an Chláir, Conndae Luimnigh agus Conndae Phortlairge tógtha isteach anois faoina sciatháin ag an Aire i riaracháin Acht na dTithe (Gaeltacht).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní bhaineann sé sin leis an gceist atá ar an bPáipéir.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Seirbhís Tithíochta na Gaeltachta">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Seirbhís Tithíochta na Gaeltachta.</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>d'Aire na Gaeltachta an bhfuil freagracht sa Dáil air i leith seirbhís tithíochta na Roinne Rialtais Aitiúil chom fada is bhaineas an tseirbhís sin leis na ceantracha atá luaite in Ordú na Límistéirí Gaeltachta, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Pádraig Mac Loingsigh Pádraig Mac Loingsigh">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Mac Loingsigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá dualgas tógtha air féin ag an Aire ón Aire Tailte i dtaobh seirbhisí tithe i bPortláirge, Conndae Roscomáin, Conndae an Chláir, Conndae Luimnigh, Conndae Liathdroma, agus eile, agus níl aon dualgais air i leith tithíochta sa bhfíor-Ghaeltacht i ngeal ar go bhfuil siad faoin Aire Rialtais Aitiúla.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Oráid is ea é sin; ní ceist é sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>With your permission, a Cheann Comhairle, I propose to raise the subject matter of No. 2 on to-day's Order Paper, on the Adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I was about to ask you, Sir, for permission to raise the subject of my own question, No. 2, on the Adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has done so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Due to the unsatisfactory nature of the reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankAiken" hpid="Mr. Aiken Mr. Aiken">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Aiken</NameTxt>
      <P>The highly unsatisfactory nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the position in relation to Question No. 2 now?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not <Col N="578" /> ruled on any question so far, but I understand the Minister for External Affairs is prepared to answer the private notice question put down by Deputy MacBride.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="PN" LHead="Private Notice Question. - Irish" RHead="Citizens in Egypt and Israel">
    <Title>Private Notice Question. - Irish Citizens in Egypt and Israel.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>As a matter of urgency I ask for leave to ask a question from the Minister for External Affairs in regard to any arrangements we have been able to make to safeguard the interests and safety of Irish citizens in Egypt and Israel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCosgrave" hpid="Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Cosgrave) Liam Cosgrave">
      <NameTxt>Minister for External Affairs (Mr. Cosgrave)</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Egypt, arrangements have been made by us with the Egyptian authorities for the appointment of an honorary consul to look after the needs of our people in that country.  I have nominated for this post an Irish citizen resident in Cairo.</P>
      <P>With regard to Israel, I have made arrangements with the British authorities for making available to our citizens in that country any help or assistance they may require in the present emergency.  It has also been arranged that our citizens will be allowed to participate in any evacuation measures which the British authorities may decide to put into force.</P>
      <P>The number of Irish citizens in Egypt and Israel is, according to my information, about 50 in each country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister state whether the Government have made any protest at the action of the British and French in flouting the United Nations Organisation in its action&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an entirely separate matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Does it not amount to the fact that our membership of the United Nations Organisation would seem to be a farce?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>It has no relevance to the question asked by Deputy MacBride.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="579" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be no harm to answer the question.  It is an important one.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="PN" LHead="Private Notice Question. - Greyhound Industry" RHead="Bill, 1955&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Private Notice Question. - Greyhound Industry Bill, 1955&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed)</Title>
    <P>Debate resumed on the following question: &ldquo;That Section 50 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>On this section, I was directing attention to the fact that it is an exceedingly difficult section to understand because it refers back to a number of other sections, including Section 25 and Section 37.  I was saying there seemed to be a rather complicated system of dual control to be operated, on the one side by the board and, on the other side, by the club.  It will be scarcely appreciated what is at issue in this section unless Deputies turn back to Section 25.  I am not debating Section 25; I am merely calling attention to its nature.  Section 25 is rather confusing and peculiar.  It says that the board may by regulations make provision for certain things, and in particular it goes on to state in paragraph (a) of sub-section (2):&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;... prohibiting persons from performing specified functions, or specified classes of functions, on greyhound racetracks save under and in accordance with permits granted by the board at its discretion.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Again, in paragraph (f) of that sub-section its says:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;...prohibiting persons performing specified classes of functions on greyhound racetracks from having any beneficial interest in the income&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
      <P>and so on.  That is not so important. The important paragraph is paragraph (a) of sub-section (2) because we turn over to sub-section (5) of this section where we see what the club is empowered to do.  The club is empowered to make rules under the section and these are rules which require the provision of persons to perform specified functions on greyhound racetracks and prohibiting greyhound racing except when such persons and specified officers of the club are in attendance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We have the rather extraordinary <Col N="580" /> position that the board may prohibit persons from performing specified functions or specified classes of functions on greyhound racetracks save under and in accordance with permits granted by the board at its discretion. On the other hand, the club may require:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;... the provision of persons to perform specified functions on greyhound racetracks and prohibiting greyhound races except when such persons and specified officers of the club are in attendance.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Most people thought, and I was under the impression, that the whole of this business was to be under the undivided control of the greyhound industry board and that in fact there would be a simple division of functions, that the club would be a subsidiary body of the greyhound industry board with subsidiary functions&mdash;the subsidiary function of regulating and controlling the sport of greyhound coursing. I now find that, in fact, the club has functions in relation to greyhound racing and this brings me back to Section 50.  Let me state again, so far as I can clarify this highly confused situation, that the board would appear to have powers to prohibit certain persons from functioning and certain things from being done.  On the other hand, the club would appear to have power to require certain things to be done and certain persons to be appointed.  These persons are to be authorised officer.  The definition &ldquo;authorised officer&rdquo; is not necessarily an officer of the club or an officer of the board.  It is merely defined as:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;A person appointed by the board or club, as may be appropriate, to be an authorised officer for the purposes of this Act.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>One could see that in certain circumstances the club might appoint an authorised officer who could interfere with an authorised officer of the board in the performance of his functions. Bearing that in mind and appreciating &mdash;I do not want to detain the House unduly&mdash;that the same sort of diarchy is given effect to in Section 37 and I think also&mdash;I will have to refresh myself&mdash;in <Col N="581" /> relation to Section 43, we then come to Section 50 where we find this:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;An offence under this Act, other than an offence specified in sub-section (2) of this section may be prosecuted by the board.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That would appear to rule out all offences under Section 25 and Section 27 which consist of a contravention of a rule under the section.  It is very difficult for me to state the point I am trying to make but it does appear to me that, under certain circumstances and having regard to the overlapping powers conferred on the board and the club, respectively, the subsections (1) and (2) of this section might in fact operate to prevent the prosecution, particularly by the board, of certain offences.</P>
    <P>It is almost incomprehensible how this thing will work.  The one thing that would appear to emerge in the whole business is that we will have two sets of authorised officers doing almost identical things&mdash;one corps of officers appointed by the board, who will be charged to enforce prohibitions, and the other body of officers, appointed by the club, who will be empowered to see that specified requirements of the club are being carried out&mdash;and then, when these two sets of officers start to function in their respective spheres, there is a zone where their functions overlap and where, apparently, under Section 50, they will come into headlong collision with each other.</P>
    <P>It has been necessary for me to enlarge in that way in order to show how really absurd the scheme of this Bill is in many particulars.  It is only when one comes to Section 50 that the net point emerges, that the demarcation between the activities of the club and the powers of the club, on the one hand, and the functions and powers of the board, on the other hand, is so vague and indefinite that actually, while they have two separate corps of authorised officers, no one can say at the end who will be able to prosecute whom for an offence.</P>
    <P>I think it might be relevant on this section, having elucidated that fact, to refer to an incident which happened <Col N="582" /> some years ago and which is recorded in Volume 96, columns 1876 and 1877. If the House will bear with me, I will read it:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;With two friends, I went down to Connemara, to the Gaeltacht, a couple of days ago.  We went to visit an old lady friend of ours whose house stood about 100 yards up from the road.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="TonyBarry" hpid="Mr. A. Barry Mr. A. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>What is this about?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>This is about the plethora of inspectors, of authorised officers, who are going to fight each other under Section 50.  I continue the quotation:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;I went there with some people who were experts in the Irish language, to see how the language&mdash;&mdash;&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>This has nothing to do with Section 50 of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>
      </P>
      <P>&ldquo;&mdash;&mdash;was getting on in what was the Fíor-Ghaeltacht, if there was any such thing in Ireland.  We got out of the car on the road.  There were 100 yards of road up to the woman's house.  I could see her looking over the half-door when we got out of the car.  When she saw us climbing the fence to go up the road she clapped out the door and ran in.  My friend said to me: &lsquo;Is dóigh lei gur cigirí sinn&rsquo;&mdash;&lsquo;She thinks we are inspectors.&rsquo; Up we went to the house.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>This has no relevance to Section 50, which deals with the prosecution of offences by the board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Except to say this, that under this section we will have two corps of officers&mdash;one officer prosecuting a man, perhaps, because he is breaking a prohibition and another officer prosecuting a man, perhaps, because he is failing to fulfil a requirement. What I am pointing out is that here we are doing the very thing, under the Greyhound Industry Bill, <Col N="583" /> which the Minister complained was happening under the Racing Board and Racecourses Bill, because, Sir, the person who did make that pleasant journey into Connemara, the person who did affright the poor old woman so that she slammed the door in his face, was the present Minister for Agriculture, then Deputy Dillon.  But nothing in the Racing Board and Racecourses Bill equals the absurdity of the provisions of Section 50, which provides again for the two corps of prosecutors&mdash;the person who will prosecute under sub-section (1) of the section on behalf of the board and the person, or persons&mdash;let me put it in the plural because I am sure the number will be many&mdash;the persons who will prosecute under sub-section (2) on behalf of the club.  It seems to me that this section is very bad indeed and that it would be far better to reserve to the board the right to prosecute in all cases and to reserve the right to prosecute for all offences, whether they are offences arising out of the contravention of a regulation or the contravention of a rule, to the board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy had allowed me to interrupt him earlier on, I could have spared him the trouble of getting so cross about Section 50.  I explained, when I was introducing this Bill, in Volume 153, No. 10, columns 1433-4, on December 14th:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Part III of the Bill provides for the licensing of greyhound racetracks by the board and for regulations by the board to cover all matters in relation to tracks and greyhound racing.  Provision is also made for rules by the Irish Coursing Club in relation to the functioning of tracks and greyhound racing; here again the standing committee of the Irish Coursing Club appeared to make a reasonable case, subsequent to the Advisory Committee's report, for retaining purely disciplinary functions in regard to racing as well as breeding and coursing because of the close inter-connection of these in many respects, as well as the further important point made <Col N="584" /> by the club that its racing rules apply to the Six Counties.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The problem was, as I tried to explain in the House at the time, that the Irish Coursing Club is recognised as the authority for the 32 Counties and Partition has never been allowed to enter into it.</P>
    <P>That extremely happy state of affairs exists and I was particularly anxious to ensure that it should continue but if I, under this Bill, authorised the statutory body, the Greyhound Racing Board, to prosecute in respect of rules made by the club, which is recognised north and south of the Border, it was almost certain that by this Bill I would do the very thing I did not want to do&mdash;partition the greyhound racing industry of the country.  I think the Deputy agrees with me that where, in sport, business or in any other way, we maintain unity with our people of the North, it is a good thing to do.  If the Deputy would look calmly at Section 50 he would see that it provides that, in respect of the statutory conditions created by the greyhound industry in the Republic, the board is the prosecuting authority, but if he looks back at Section 25 (4) he will see:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The club may by rules make provision with respect to the use, management and control of greyhound racetracks and the conduct generally of greyhound races at such tracks.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>For the violation of such a rule, the club is the prosecuting authority because the club is making rules and regulations for tracks and the conduct generally of greyhound races not only in the Republic but in the whole of Ireland.  I wanted to leave that under this Act to be the authority for enforcing these rules so that there would be no disruption of the existing eminently desirable practice of the Irish Coursing Club being the recognised authority for the whole of Ireland.</P>
    <P>Similarly, if the Deputy looks at Section 37 he will find that regulations may be made by the board but under sub-section (4) the club may make rules.  Where there is a violation of rules, the club is the enforcing authority; <Col N="585" /> where there is a violation of regulations which are applicable only to the Republic under this statute the board is the prosecuting authority.  I suggest to the Deputy that in our special circumstances, where we are ardently anxious to ensure that nothing we did would disrupt the happy relationship that existed between coursing men and persons interested in greyhounds generally north and south of the Border, we were right to go to considerable lengths in order to avoid doing anything that would disrupt this happy relationship.</P>
    <P>We could have one body to be the sole body authorised to prosecute. Why did the Deputy think we went to the trouble of making provision for the possibility of two such bodies functioning? Surely if he sat down for a moment and asked himself: &ldquo;Why did they draft it so?&rdquo; he would have said to himself: &ldquo;They cannot have done it for fun&rdquo;, and it would have occurred to him there must be some good reason.  Does the Deputy not think it is a good reason?  The only method whereby I could achieve the simplicity, for which the Deputy appears to yearn, would be to disrupt the unity which at present exists, and it was to preserve that unity that I introduced the dual function set out.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly would not like to say, no matter how strongly I might feel, that there was a certain degree of absurdity in these provisions, which would in any way further divide Irishmen in their common effort to improve an industry or sport.  I would hate that anything put in this Bill would further consolidate Partition which the House and, I think, all sportsmen, deplore.  However, I cannot see that the Minister has justified fully the duality which runs through this Bill by the statement which he has made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not want to enlarge on this matter but if the Minister will turn back to sub-section (6) of Section 25 and the corresponding sub-section of Section 37 he will see that the rules take the force of law to the extent that, if they are broken in relation to greyhound racetracks, there is a contravention <Col N="586" /> of the rule and the licensee under the greyhound racetrack licence relating to the track shall be guilty of an offence and shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding £50.  I suggest there is not in that sub-section the clear-cut demarcation which he has described to the House. I will concede the Minister this.  I appreciate the difficulty with which he was confronted and I will go a very long way with him to overcome that difficulty even if it did lead to certain inconsistencies and, to some extent, perhaps, absurdities in the drafting of the Bill but I do not think that the provisions of sub-section (6) are fully consistent with the arguments which the Minister has put to the House.</P>
    <P>I cannot conceive that the Minister will say: &ldquo;After all, our jurisdiction in relation to prosecutions for the infringement of our laws does not run outside the Twenty-Six Counties and therefore nobody is going to try to enforce these provisions upon greyhound racing tracks in the north or outside the Twenty-Six Counties.&rdquo;  I presume that would apply also to the rules of the club in so far as they might cover local coursing.  Trying to make the point I am making in relation to Section 50 might have repercussions elsewhere and on that account I do not want to prolong the discussion and I shall let the Minister have the section.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 51 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SCHEDULE.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 32:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In article 1, page 25, lines 54 and 55, to delete &ldquo;duly recognised greyhound racetrack executives&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;persons owning or exercising control over greyhound racetracks (in this constitution referred to as greyhound racetrack executives).</P>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.  It has been introduced to meet a point raised by Deputy MacEntee in connection with the definition of a track executive. I hope it does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="587" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it was Deputy Burke who raised that matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>It was.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment has been introduced to meet the Deputy's point.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 33:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In article 3, page 27, before paragraph (ii), to insert a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(ii)  A representative member of the club appointed by a coursing club shall not be entitled to attend, act on or vote in the provincial committee unless such club has held a coursing meeting within two years of the date of such appointment.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 33 and 35 can be discussed together and separate decisions taken, if necessary, on them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister could easily accept this amendment.  Both amendment No. 33 and amendment No. 35 are quite reasonable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps I could help the Deputy.  The position is that the Bill, as it stands, is a good deal more stringent than the Deputy's amendment would make it.  The Deputy seeks to provide that &ldquo;a representative member of the club appointed by a coursing club shall not be entitled to attend, act on or vote in the provincial committee unless such club has held a coursing meeting within two years of the date of such appointment.&rdquo; Article 2 (3) of the Schedule provides, in effect, that he cannot attend, act or vote, unless the club has had a meeting within 15 months.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>We went through this Schedule carefully and that did not emerge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Deputy would look at article 2 (3) of the Schedule.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister is quite right.  I see it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="588" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>In effect, we are saying 15 months, which, I think, goes further than Deputy Burke's amendment and fully covers the point raised by him.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 34:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In article 4, page 28, paragraph (iv), line 26, before &ldquo;The&rdquo; to insert:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;, and from among the co-opted members of the club, provided always that the total number of co-opted members on the executive committee shall not at any time exceed, in the case of persons appointed:</P>
      <P>(i) from the Province of Leinster ... three co-opted members,</P>
      <P>(ii) from the Province of Munster ... two co-opted members,</P>
      <P>(iii) from the Province of Connaught ... one co-opted member,</P>
      <P>(iv) from the Province of Ulster ... one co-opted member.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister will accept this amendment, inasmuch as it provides for proportional representation. Perhaps the Minister would like to say whether he has considered the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not quite understand what Deputy Briscoe means by co-opted members because the whole theme of the Bill is to provide, over a term, that there will be no co-opted members on the executive and that the only person entitled to be on the executive will be a fully representative elected member.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>No; that is not the way to interpret it.  This amendment envisages the period after there have been co-opted members and it is for the purpose of restricting the number: &ldquo;from among the co-opted members of the club, provided always that the total number of co-opted members on the executive committee shall not at any time exceed, in the case of persons appointed...&rdquo;  It is designed for the purpose of giving proportional representation from the four areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="589" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>This proposal envisages a choice of co-opted members, but there will be no co-opted members on the executive 18 months after the Bill passes.  They have then to be elected members, fully representative of the clubs and tracks in their own provinces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the existing ones?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>They are passing out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree, but the late Deputy Tom Walsh&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order.  With your permission, a Leas-Cheann Comhairle, I would like to raise the subject matter of Question No. 22 as well as Question No. 23 on the Adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the purpose of this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I just want to widen the scope of the discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>This is scarcely the time to mention the matter.  We are trying to iron out the Schedule to the Greyhound Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I want permission from the Ceann Comhairle to raise this particular matter&mdash;Question No. 23.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand the Ceann Comhairle is considering this request.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>He is readily available in his room</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I suppose the Deputy had not formally mentioned the matter in the House and took this opportunity to do so.  I was saying that the late Deputy Tom Walsh and Deputy Briscoe were very keen on this for the reason that, while it is true that the co-opted members will in time disappear, in the transition period of the club, they should be allowed on the provincial committees and they should retain, during the transition period, their right to membership of the provincial committees.  There are a number of well-known sporting figures <Col N="590" /> who are co-opted members of coursing clubs and it was felt that, in recognition of their services to the sport, they might be allowed seats on the provincial committees and they might be allowed representation on these committees in accordance with the terms of this amendment.  Perhaps the Minister might see his way to conceding something like that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall be very happy to consider it for the transition period&mdash; not that I think that it is of any importance. I have my difficulties: how am I to determine whether a co-opted member is or is not from the Province of Munster, for instance.  Is it by residence?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Membership of the club in the area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not as easy as that. You may have a man who is prominently associated with Munster, but, if one comes to determine what club he belongs to, one will find he belongs to a club in North County Dublin.  Yet, he is esteemed to be a Munster man. There is a difficulty as to how one would define such people.  Remember, this is only for the interregnum.  In the permanent arrangement, they will be elected proportionately according to the number of coursing clubs and tracks in their respective provinces, subject to certain limitations.  I shall look into this, but I am bound to tell the Deputy that I see practical difficulties which, I think, would make the game scarcely worth the candle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>If the provincial clubs were permitted to keep their co-opted members, irrespective of where they resided, then in the case of an individual who belonged to a Dublin club but was esteemed to be a Munster sportsman, the Munster people might do him the honour of co-opting him to their provincial committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>This is for a very limited period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>Even for that limited period, I would like the Minister to concede this amendment because a number of men who have been <Col N="591" /> in the sport for a long time will be very hard hit, except during this transition period.  Would the Minister see his way to conceding this amendment tabled by Deputy Briscoe?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister says he is prepared to consider this amendment between now and Report Stage. I am prepared to withdraw the amendment now, in view of that undertaking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I will, but I do not want to mislead the Deputy.  I say I will consider the matter between now and Report Stage.  At the moment I feel the difficulties are such that I may not be able to meet the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I can withdraw the amendment now and reintroduce it on Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I would urge the Minister to introduce a similar amendment. It would give the sponsors of the sport a sporting chance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Before you leave amendment No. 34&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment has been withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has said he would consider it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>You may not debate it after it has been withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister not be a bit generous?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>The only point I wanted to make was about the proportional representation given to the different provinces.  Leinster is to have three co-opted members, Munster two, Connaught and Ulster one each. Munster at the present time has 88 affiliated coursing clubs and licensed tracks.  It heads the entire country, because Leinster has only 49 or approximately half as many, Connaught has 17 and Ulster only ten.  I would ask the Minister, since he knows very well that Munster is the headquarters of coursing&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="592" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Deputy explain to Deputy Briscoe the infinite and thorny difficulties that would arise in trying to implement the spirit of his suggestion?</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 35:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In article 4, page 28, before paragraph (v), to insert a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(v) A representative member of the club appointed by a coursing club shall not be entitled to attend, act on or vote in the executive committee unless such club has held a coursing meeting within two years of the date of such appointment.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment has been discussed with the previous one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I think my proposal goes even further than the Deputy's amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickJBurke" hpid="Mr. P.J. Burke Mr. P.J. Burke">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P.J. Burke</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the Minister's statement and will withdraw the amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 36:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In article 11, page 32, paragraph (ii), line 9, to delete &ldquo;the secretary&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;a committee consisting of the chairman, the secretary, and the honorary treasurer, provided always that all such appointments shall meet&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>I think this is a vital amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very pleased to meet the Deputy here, though I do not believe it is vital.  I have no hesitation in saying the appointment should be made by the secretary after consultation with the officers of the club.  The appointment by the secretary is merely a formality.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister accepting the amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>No, but if the Deputy withdraws that amendment, I will put <Col N="593" /> one down for Report Stage.  My amendment can then be compared with this one.  In the drafting of the Bill, I chose the secretary, my clear intention being that the secretary would make the appointments as the servant of the executive and not as the executive officer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>At the direction of the executive?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Wait a moment.  I do not believe that is the real purport of paragraph 2 of the article in which it is set out that the staff of the club shall be appointed by the secretary with the approval of the executive committee.  So it is not a mere formal appointment.  It is not merely signing on the dotted line on the committee's behalf by the secretary.  It would appear from the Schedule that the initiative would lie with the secretary and that all he has to do is to secure the approval of the committee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall bring in an amendment saying that the officials and servants of the club shall be appointed as the executive committee may determine.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 37:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In article 12, page 32, before paragraph (iii), to insert a new paragraph as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(iii) The report submitted by the secretary shall contain a statement setting out the names, duties, total remuneration derived from the club and its subsidiary undertakings and conditions of employment of any member of the staff whose total remuneration as aforesaid exceeds £300 per annum.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>My only reservation about this amendment is that I think it is rather supererogation to put it in this form.  The members can require the report to be submitted in any form they want it and can bespeak any information they may require.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="594" />
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has accepted in a sense the principle of the previous amendment and this obviously is consequential on it, from the point of view of operation.  There will be certain appointees whose salaries will exceed £300 a year.  There might be appointments at just under £300 a year which could be brought up to £600 a year after the appointment was made.  I want the carrying out of the board to be a proper carrying out and I want to ensure that the secretary should have certain privileges and rights, but that they should be restricted.  This is one of the points that I regard as being vital.  My purpose is to ensure that all appointments will be made by the proper authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>That has nothing whatever to do with this amendment.  The amendment states that the report by the secretary shall contain a statement setting out the names, duties, total remuneration derived from the club and its subsidiary undertakings and conditions of employment of any member of the staff whose total remuneration exceeds £300 per annum.  I do not give a fiddle-de-dee, but we are all familiar with the pious sections put in Acts of Parliament which result in extensive documentation being compiled for years and years and years, long after people have ceased to remember why.  It goes on and on, simply because somebody had a brainwave that this would be a good thing to do.  I would put a statutory obligation in so that all information would be available at the annual general meeting.  I would ask the Deputy to pause and consider.  He must have a great deal of administrative work to do himself now and probably has experience in the Dublin Corporation of returns being made which nobody ever reads. Does he want to create an obligation of this kind?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to make a comparison between this organisation and a local authority.  I do make a comparison between this organisation and similarly sized organisations. I do not believe any terrible amount of work should be put into the presentation of documents, but I think that a detailed document of expenses, <Col N="595" /> included in which would be a list of officials and their wages, should be presented at the annual general meeting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think it matters a hoot.  My only objection to this is that I am reluctant to put on this body the obligation of unnecessary documentation. I do not rate the issue of such importance as the Deputy attaches to it, but if the Deputy feels it is necessary, he might put down an amendment for Report Stage and I will accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>That puts us in a rather unfortunate strategic position. If we withdraw the amendment, we forfeit our right to debate it as in Committee. On the Report Stage, we will be spancelled by the rules of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I must resist the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very sorry the Minister has taken up this attitude.  We regard this as being of importance.  It is a simple amendment which does not impose any onerous duties upon the secretary.  It merely provides that the report submitted by the secretary shall contain a statement of the names and duties of officers getting over £300 per annum.  I will tell the Minister what really is the origin of this amendment.</P>
      <P>If the Minister will read from page 35 to, I think, page 52, he will see there that the procedure, the tactics and the efforts of the Standing Committee of the Irish Coursing Club appear to be devoted to concealing from its members the real position of the club.  The Minister has gone out to reform the club and the word &ldquo;reform&rdquo; carries with it the implication that there are abuses to be reformed.  One would not reform an organisation which was working in a sound, satisfactory way.  It is only an organisation which has been riddled with abuses that one strives to reform.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What we are really concerned about here is to ensure that one of the main conditions which allow these abuses to grow up and develop will be eliminated so far as the reformed club is concerned; that, in fact, a statutory obligation will be placed upon the <Col N="596" /> secretary or responsible officer of the executive committee to keep the members of the club fully informed in regard to the matters set out in the amendment&mdash;that is to say, who and what are the officials employed, what are their duties, what is their total remuneration derived from the club, what is their total remuneration derived from certain subsidiary undertakings carried on by the club and referred to in the Advisory Committe's report, and their conditions of employment.</P>
    <P>That does not involve any very elaborate documentation.  It merely means that there will be one table in which the names of the officials, their duties and the remuneration derived directly from the employment they hold under the club and the additional remuneration which they may draw from subsidiaries will be set out, so that every member of the club will be fully aware of what is being done by the secretary and the executive committee. I cannot see that there is any disadvantage likely to attend the publication of this information for the benefit of the members of the club. The Minister is anxious that all this business should be cleared up and one way of ensuring that the old situation will not redevelop is by the publication of information which the club members are entitled to get but which, unfortunately, was denied to them in the past.</P>
    <P>I am sure the Minister is not going to deny that, because here is the report of the committee which is very blunt and very informative.  We are merely trying to ensure that the same sort of intrigue and the same sort of connivance and collusion to keep the members of the club ignorant of what was being done in their name and allegedly on their behalf will not occur again.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot understand why the Minister does not accept this. I am a member of a number of small organisations but they are large enough to be compared with the organisation that has been conjured up in this present Bill.  From the point of view of the amount of money that this particular organisation will require, as envisaged in all the talk that we have had, the total number of employees <Col N="597" /> would be reasonably small and consequently the objection that the Minister has is not valid at all even if there is one-half&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no use in the Deputy wasting his breath upon the desert air.  I have told the Deputy already I think this is unnecessary; I think it is a waste of time but, if the Deputy feels strongly about it and put it down on the Report Stage, I will accept it.  I hope there is no need for me to say that 45 times.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I am accepting what the Minister now says but some minutes ago the Minister said he would resist it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>If&mdash;.  I told you ten minutes ago that I thought it unimportant but if it is important to the Deputy&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>It is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and the Deputy puts it down on the Report Stage I will accept it.  The Deputy was told that about a quarter of an hour ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>But there were conditions.</P>
      <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RobertBriscoe" hpid="Mr. Briscoe Mr. Briscoe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Briscoe</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 38:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In article 12, page 32, paragraph (iii), line 34, before &ldquo;A&rdquo; to insert the following:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;, together with detailed accounts and balance sheets in respect of each undertaking carried on by the club or on its behalf.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>This relates to article 12 of the Schedule, paragraph 3.  I want that to read:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;The secretary and honorary treasurer shall submit to every annual general meeting of the club a duly audited consolidated statement of revenue and expenditure and consolidated balance sheet of the club and its subsidiary interests for the year ended on the preceding 31st March, together with detailed <Col N="598" /> accounts and balance sheets in respect of each undertaking carried on by the club or on its behalf.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I do not think the Minister will need much explanation as to why that is necessary.  The Minister might say now if he will accept it and that will end the discussion but, if he is not prepared to indicate his views on it, I am prepared to argue my amendment and I hope my colleagues will further supplement my arguments so that if I leave out anything&mdash;as I probably shall &mdash;they will be able to bring it to his notice.</P>
    <P>What does this mean?  The supreme body will issue its accounts but there will be quite a few subsidiary undertakings acting as independent units and each of these as is usual in all undertakings commercial or otherwise should have their accounts submitted similarly in the same detail so that there would not be a bulk statement taken into the main balance sheet of the profits or losses of subsidiary organisations.  This is what I call consequential.  If the system of control by the members is to be accepted; if this is to be a democratic organisation, then every member should be entitled to this information.</P>
    <P>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Debate&mdash;Winter" RHead="Relief Schemes">
    <Title>Adjournment Debate&mdash;Winter Relief Schemes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy McQuillan gave notice that on the Adjournment he would raise the subject matter of certain questions on to-day's Order Paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Sir, you graciously gave me permission to raise two questions&mdash;Questions Nos. 22 and 23&mdash;on the motion for the Adjournment.  In order that the position will be quite clear to the Parliamentary Secretary and the Government, I want to inform him that I propose to deal solely with grants that have been allocated to local authorities. I have no great knowledge of the position in Dublin City and elsewhere. I am solely concerned with the position that is likely to arise in rural Ireland within the next six months, as a result <Col N="599" /> of the decisions made to reduce drastically the amount of money made available in former years for winter relief schemes and rural employment schemes.</P>
      <P>I regret that I have to raise these questions at all, in view of the fact that I had felt the welfare of the small farmer, the labourer and the worker in the towns of rural Ireland would be safeguarded, having regard to the fact that the Parliamentary Secretary is a man who knows rural Ireland and the problems that affect the folk who live there.</P>
      <P>The Taoiseach in many speeches in recent weeks emphasised the Government plans for the reduction of unemployment in Ireland generally and gave specific points of policy that are likely to affect the employment position in the rural areas.  I have only to mention the Government's alleged concern with rural matters when I refer the House to the fact that within recent weeks, a Ministry for the Gaeltacht has been set up.  In addition to that, we have in operation an undeveloped areas board charged with the setting up of industrial concerns, so that the employment figures in rural Ireland would mount and we would see an end in a reasonable space of time of the drain of emigration.</P>
      <P>The Taoiseach and the Government now proceed to put this long term programme into operation by taking steps this winter which will do untold harm to the people in rural Ireland. Having professed their interest in rural Ireland, they set about implementing their policy for the coming winter by throwing out of employment thousands of breadwinners, thus ensuring that this coming Christmas will be one of gloom and depression in many homes in towns and villages and in the countryside.</P>
      <P>What are the facts?  In the year 1955-56, the grants made available to various county councils in Ireland under the rural employment schemes amounted to £58,850.  The grants allocated this year, 1956-57, to the various county councils under the rural employment schemes amount to £5,000.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="600" />
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is some drop&mdash; 90 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Taoiseach, in a reply to a question tabled here to-day, admitted that a reduction in the allocation of money had taken place this year, but pointed out that the reduction was in the region of 15 per cent. and not the 60 per cent. suggested by a Deputy.  The figures I have disclosed here, namely, a reduction from £58,850 to £5,000, constitute a reduction of 90 per cent.  There can be no denial of that fact.</P>
      <P>One of the reasons given for that reduction, according to the Parliamentary Secretary in his reply to-day, is the necessity, in present financial circumstances, of limiting public expenditure. In order to cloud the issue, he goes further and states that the large carry-forward of unexpended grants on April 1st, 1956, amounted to £285,000 odd, which is available for expenditure in the current year.  In other words, he suggests that there was a large carry-forward from last year and that that would now be expended this year.</P>
      <P>I want to make it quite clear to the House that that large carry-forward has no bearing on or connection with the specific grants that I have mentioned, namely, the grants made available to various county councils.  The over-all figures given by the Parliamentary Secretary include Dublin Corporation and other large bodies and they have no bearing whatever on the grants made available to the county councils.</P>
      <P>If in his reply the Parliamentary Secretary makes reference to this carry-over, I want it to be clearly understood that it is a matter of clouding the issue involved, namely, the reduction that has taken place in the rural employment scheme grants to county councils&mdash;a reduction from £58,850 to £5,000 this year&mdash;and in case it is suggested that there is a carry-over, let me refer to Question No. 23, which affects my own constituency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I asked the Parliamentary Secretary if he would state in respect of Roscommon County Council the amounts allocated for winter relief schemes in the last and the current <Col N="601" /> financial year.  The Parliamentary Secretary pointed out that the reduction was from £1,250 last year to £250 this year.  Let us take the position as disclosed by the questions to-day in other counties in the congested areas &mdash;the areas in which this Government professes to have such a deep interest. Last year, Galway County Council were allocated £7,500 under the heading of rural employment schemes.  This year, the allocation to Galway County Council is £1,380.  Mayo County Council received an allocation last year of £13,500; this year the allocation is £250.  The allocation to Leitrim last year was £2,750; this year Leitrim gets nil.  Sligo got £2,500 last year and this year, the allocation is nil.  Last year, the allocation to Roscommon was £1,250; this year, the allocation is £250.  I will give one further instance of the position with regard to another county which includes a Gaeltacht area, that is, Donegal.  The grant allocated to the Donegal County Council last year under the rural employment scheme was £15,500; the allocation this year is £700.</P>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>That is right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>They should get out altogether.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would appreciate it if Deputies would allow me to finish my remarks.  I suggest that this reduction in grants that were normally meant to tide poor families over the most difficult portion of the year&mdash;the winter months&mdash;will mean that the breadwinners who were kept working last year will now join the ever-increasing throng who go on the emigrant ship.  This matter is of vital concern to these families.</P>
      <P>My main reason for raising this matter to-day&mdash;and I do not deny it&mdash; is to ensure that the utmost publicity will be given in plenty of time to these families in rural Ireland.  It would be far too late to have this position disclosed in the second week of December when it would be too late to do anything about it.  Now is the time for this fact to sink home in the minds of Deputies&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="602" />
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Particularly Labour Party Deputies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;whether in support of or in opposition to this Government. Now is the time when it must be brought home to the people in rural areas that the winter and Christmas which faces many of these families will be very poor indeed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>And in the cities as well.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>In reply to a question, to-day, which has a great bearing on this, the Taoiseach, who was asked if the Government had any policy that could be put into operation to reduce substantially within the next three months the grave unemployment figures, replied that the measures included in the Government's programme are in fact permanent measures designed and calculated to bring about a lasting reduction in unemployment.  I think I am quite justified in stating, from the figures and facts I have given to this House, that the Taoiseach's method of bringing about this lasting reduction in unemployment is to increase the rate of emigration.</P>
      <P>The net result of this reduction in expenditure on grants in rural Ireland means an increase in the emigration figures.  We all know that, once they go, they are very slow to return.  I think it cannot be denied, therefore, that the lasting results of this policy now being put into operation will be to reduce the man-power and family-power here in Ireland at a time when we can ill-afford to lose it.</P>
      <P>In many ways, the Parliamentary Secretary has manned the gap against opposition from the Dublin clique which tried at all times to put across their views in rural Ireland.  I would ask him to take a firm stand on this issue.  If he does, I can assure him that the people of rural Ireland will appreciate it and stand by him.  I want him to be quite clear now that, when he is replying, there is no use in trying to cloud the issue by saying that a large sum of money was brought forward last year which was not expended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>So far as the county councils to <Col N="603" /> which I have referred are concerned&mdash; and I have referred only to county councils&mdash;they expended the money allocated to them.  Roscommon County Council expended it and I am quite sure there are people here to talk for Donegal and other counties.  Roscommon expended the money made available to it.  There is no carry-over available for Roscommon, but, nevertheless, we have this substantial reduction.  If it is a question of urban areas, there are other Deputies here who can deal with that matter.  I feel that my responsibility is to the rural areas and to the people in the small towns in rural areas which come under the direction and authority of the county council.  As far as they are concerned, the reduction that has taken place in the amount of money available this year is in the region of 90 per cent. and no figures&mdash; no legal quibbles on the part of the Taoiseach or the other lawyer members of the Government&mdash;can hide that fact.</P>
    <P>If, in the meantime, between this and December, no action is taken by the Government to increase these grants, then my words will be clearly proved correct next winter when we will find that the St. Vincent de Paul Society and other charitable organisations will be working overtime doing the work that should be done by this Government in a practical sense.  This is not a question of just a sop for the unemployed.  Many of the works upon which the county council expended this money were of a practical and lasting nature.  It is a quibble to suggest that this Government is concerned only with productive programmes.  In the past fortnight, over £80,000 was expended by the Government in telling the people of rural Ireland to save more money.  At the same time, by this reduction in employment grants, the Government is ensuring that these people in rural Ireland will not have a bite this coming winter.  Nevertheless, they have the audacity to expend that large sum on advertising.  Before it is too late, I ask the Parliamentary Secretary to intervene with the Government in this matter.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Deputy Blaney rose.</i>
    </P>
    <Col N="604" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has only one minute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be brief.  I want to point out to the Parliamentary Secretary that, whereas to-day the Taoiseach stated in reply to another question that the over-all reduction in these grants was about 16 per cent., according to a circular letter received before our council meeting on Monday, the reduction in the grant to our county council for the coming year is in the nature of 95 per cent.  Furthermore, I would point out to the Parliamentary Secretary that, in addition to relieving unemployment, these grants have been used to help to supplement our roads programme in a most definite manner.  As a result of that system and tradition over the years, our five years' roads programme for the repair of county roads was designed to exclude roads in areas where these grants would apply.</P>
      <P>The net result this year is that not only have we not got these moneys to spend, but no other moneys will be spent in those areas, for the simple reason that this money, and the roads outside the five year programme, cannot be put on.  The money is not even sufficient to buy Christmas stockings for the children of the unemployed in our county.  I want further to ask the Parliamentary Secretary whether in his reply he will indicate why it is that the reduction in some counties is not <i>pro rata</i> with others.  In our case we have been reduced from £15,600 to £700.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sure what the Parliamentary Secretary has to say is of some importance and he has only a few minutes to reply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I doubt it, but I must give way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I heard about this matter only a few minutes ago, but Deputy McQuillan is generally in a hurry.  It was only at 5 o'clock yesterday that he gave notice of this question at all, and he is more than dishonest, I regret to say.  On Question No. 23 to-day, he asked me if I would state in respect of Roscommon County Council the amounts allocated for winter <Col N="605" /> relief schemes in the last and current financial years respectively.  My reply was that the total allocation for winter employment schemes in County Roscommon in 1955-56 was £4,535, of which £1,250 was allocated to the county council.  The corresponding figures for the current financial year are £3,070 and £250, respectively.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of order. In Question No. 23, I asked if he will state the amounts in respect of Roscommon County Council.  He is now giving the figures apart from the Roscommon County Council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not to be misrepresented.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary is replying.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures for 1955-56 are £4,535 and £3,070 for the current year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that for the county council?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the Deputy knows the question he asked.  There may be a little reduction.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>A little reduction?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>That is good.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>The policy of this Government is not built on relief schemes or on charity.  It is built on normal productive work.  Under the Fianna Fáil Government, the idea in those schemes was just something to keep on, until work of a productive nature could be obtained.  I believe that productive, normal work is much better than those relief schemes.  I believe that many of those relief schemes in parts of this country are just waste of time.  They are just money spent for the sake of keeping people in day-to-day employment, in the hope that something better will turn up.  I believe that such works as the Government have in hands at the moment&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="606" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Such as?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Arterial drainage and work of that description.  Even though the financial position is as it is, the Government have not cut down one halfpenny on any work of that nature.  There is more work of a productive nature in Galway at the moment than there ever was.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>Less people, too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry there is not a Galway Deputy present.  He would agree with me.  My point to Deputy McQuillan is that if, later on, he sees any great cases of hardship in Roscommon, or Deputy Blaney, or any other Deputy&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>I will give them to you to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have no arterial drainage in Roscommon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>You have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Even under the Fianna Fáil Government, those schemes were never regarded as perfect employment for people, but as just something to tide them over.  The Government in the present financial position, are doing their best.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not good enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>In that line perhaps, in the near future, things might be better, and our hope is that these relief schemes will be completely cut out in the near future and that there will be productive employment for all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>They have practically gone as it is.  The question I would like clarified is: since it is the Government's idea that these schemes are non-productive and only of a temporary nature, what is to replace them?  Where is the productive work to replace them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to ask the Parliamentary Secretary if he will tell us if any moneys are to be expected, as Deputy McQuillan mentioned, in the next few weeks before Christmas? <Col N="607" /> Is it the policy of the present Government to do nothing whatever for the 55,000 unemployed at the present time and is the Minister aware that within one week from now if this money is not put back, the Labour Party are getting out of the Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it a fact that £700 for Donegal County Council instead of the £15,000 for last year, is the final allocation?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary is being misled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBrennan" hpid="Mr. J. Brennan Mr. J. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am referring to <Col N="608" /> the E.S.V. grants notified to Donegal County Council last year.  I should like to know if we are getting a further allocation under that Vote this year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCarter" hpid="Mr. Carter Mr. Carter">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Carter</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Parliamentary Secretary seriously suggest that the work carried out by the Special Employment Schemes Office is not of a productive nature?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not time to abolish the men in the headquarters of that office?</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 2.30 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 7th November, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>