<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="15" Month="Nov" Year="1956" Vol="160" No="8" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 15 Samhain 1956" DateEnglish="Thursday, 15 November 1956" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="0">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1065" /> Do chuaigh an Ceann Comhairle i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Export of Timber">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Export of Timber.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="NeilTCBlaney" hpid="Mr. Blaney Mr. Blaney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blaney</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether a permit for the export of timber in the round has recently been issued and, if so, if he will state the circumstances in which it was issued.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Norton) William Norton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Industry and Commerce (Mr. Norton)</NameTxt>
      <P>Since 1st April, 1956, my Department has issued 35 licences for the export of softwood timber in the round and seven for the export of hardwood timber.</P>
      <P>The export licences for softwoods covered a quantity of about 26,000 tons of timber of the pitwood variety.</P>
      <P>The export licences for hardwood in the round comprised 678 logs from the Inishowen Peninsula which because of the remoteness of the area could not be economically disposed of in the home market; three walnut logs exported for conversion into veneers and return to this country and 220 logs of ash, oak and sycamore experimentally exported for the purpose of testing the suitability of these types of hardwoods for the production of veneers.</P>
      <P>This experiment was under the auspices of the Industrial Development Authority, which is examining the possibility of establishing a veneer mill in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. de Valera Mr. de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Mr. de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister say whether it would not have been possible to transport the wood by sea from Inishowen?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That seems to be a separate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1066" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The difficulty there is that those who have the timber in that area say it is too far away from the nearest sawmills and, therefore, they cannot sell the timber they have to the sawmills because of the uneconomic price at which it would land at the mill.  It is to facilitate them that they have been permitted to export the timber.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Emergency (Imposition of Duties) Order">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Emergency (Imposition of Duties) Order.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce in what circumstances and for what reasons the Emergency Imposition of Duties (No. 352) (Display Shapes or Stands) (Plaster of Paris or Papier Mâché) Order, 1955, was made, and if he will make a statement on the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Order mentioned by the Deputy was made because it was established in 1955 that the manufacturers of display shapes and stands, for whose protection the duty was imposed, were not in a position to supply the reasonable requirements of the market.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Is that the only reason why that Order was made?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Has it any relationship to a prosecution that was taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not come into a prosecution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware of a prosecution that was taken?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware of a prosecution but that prosecution was not taken by the Minister.  It would be instituted by the Attorney-General.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the initiative not come from the Minister's Department?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>That is an entirely separate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Oh, no.  It is not a separate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1067" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Are the two things connected or are they not?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>So far as the revocation of this duty is concerned, the sole purpose determining its revocation was that the individual who was operating under this protective duty was not in a position to supply the requirements of the Irish market.  His attempts to provide that market were simply grotesque.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>In those circumstances, was the prosecution to which I referred&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a separate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;completely unrelated to the making of the Order?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The prosecution was an entirely different matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Oil Refinery Agreement">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Oil Refinery Agreement.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if there is any objection by him to the publication by the oil companies concerned of the details of the agreement for the establishment of a refinery.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether the agreement for the establishment of an oil refinery provides for the subscription of all the capital required by the promoting companies, or if it is intended that capital will be obtained from any other source; and, particularly, whether any investment by the Government or any public issue of shares in the undertaking in this country or elsewhere is intended.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce if the agreement for the establishment of an oil refinery provides for the maintenance of protective import duties by the Government, and, if so, if he will give particulars.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>With the permission of the Ceann Comhairle, I propose to take Questions Nos. 3, 4 and 5 together.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The extent of the &ldquo;agreement&rdquo; referred to by the Deputy is that the <Col N="1068" /> oil companies concerned submitted proposals for the establishment of a refinery at Whitegate, County Cork, subject to certain conditions and undertakings, and I have accepted these proposals.  As the Deputy is, no doubt, aware, it is not customary for details of industrial projects to be published in their initial stages, and he will, of course, remember that during his own period as Minister for Industry and Commerce that practice was not departed from even in the case of some unusually large undertakings.  Promoters are, of course, free to publish details of their proposals and the position of the sponsoring companies of the oil refinery project is no different from that of any other promoters in this respect.</P>
    <P>In regard to the provision of capital for the project, the sponsoring companies, as I announced in my public statement on 5th July last, will assume responsibility for the provision of the total capital of £12,000,000 involved. No investment by the Government is intended.</P>
    <P>As to the Deputy's request for information (a) as to whether protective import duties will be maintained and (b) for particulars thereof, the answer to (a) is in the affirmative; while as regards (b) I am not prepared at this stage to make a statement on the matter.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - West Cork Minerals">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - West Cork Minerals.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether he has approved of the proposal to grant to a Canadian firm a prospecting licence for mineral development in the Skibbereen-Ballydehob-Crookhaven districts and, if so, whether he has received an assurance from the company that exploratory work will commence at an early date.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I have given a conditional undertaking to grant prospecting facilities under the Minerals Development Act, 1940, to a company which proposes to undertake minerals exploration in the area referred to.  I have asked the interests concerned to use their best endeavours to start exploratory work as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1069" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that is not a complete answer to my question. As the Minister is aware, I have impressed on him the desirability that whatever company got the option of mining in the district, the Minister should get a definite assurance that work would be commenced within a specified period.  We did get that assurance and it was adhered to in the case of the Can-Erin Company which is at present operating at Allihies, and I can see no reason why the Minister cannot get the same assurance from whatever company has got this option in the Ballydehob district.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I remind the Deputy that for the first time in his life I have now provided facilities for a mining company to operate in the area of Skibbereen and Allihies?  That is substantial progress.  I can understand the Deputy's desire that other projects in West Cork should be proceeded with as soon as possible.  I appreciate that desire, and as far as I am concerned I have urged the company to which this licence has been issued, to commence work in these areas as soon as possible.  I have no doubt that they themselves will be most anxious to do that.  I cannot at this stage give the date on which they will start.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that the company which has got an option in the Ballydehob district has got other options in this country, and that there is a likelihood that work may not commence, say, within the next 12 months&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a separate question.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and that is most undesirable, in view of the fact that there was such competition for the mining right in this district.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should not make the mistake of becoming avaricious over those mining projects.  This matter is being dealt with in a way that best serves the national interest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Seeing that we got very little in the line of industrial <Col N="1070" /> development from successive Governments&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputy Murphy is making three speeches.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the prospecting licence issued in this case&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I am in order in asking a further supplementary question on this most important matter&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy would be more effective if he voted as he talked.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy will ask a question, I will allow him to do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will ask this question: We have got little consideration from successive Governments in the line of industrial development in West Cork, and seeing that these minerals are now available for development, surely the least we can expect from the Minister is a specific date as to when the work is likely to commence, as we had in the case of Allihies.</P>
      <P>
        <i>(Interruptions.)</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>May I answer that question, first?  The work started in Allihies because of successful negotiations which I concluded with the company&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>And I appreciate very much the Minister's help in the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;and these matters will be equally successful and the Deputy will have an opportunity of looking at the mines with pride in due course.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Hedging!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the prospecting licence issued in this case contain a condition as to when the work will start?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1071" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>It must start within a particular period, as otherwise the licence is invalid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Tánaiste aware that copper mining was carried on at Allihies so recently as 1926, and does he suggest that Deputy Murphy is less than 36 years of age?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that while Deputy Lemass was in office, mining operations at Allihies were never heard of?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Rural Electrification in Kerry">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Rural Electrification in Kerry.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWPalmer" hpid="Mr. Palmer Mr. Palmer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Palmer</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Industry and Commerce whether he is aware that the scheme for the extension of rural electrification to the Cahirciveen area does not include the townlands of Kells, Reacastle, Mountfoley, Gortaforia, Gleesk and Rhoades; and if, in view of the fact that Kells is a tourist resort having 15 guest houses along the coast, a licensed hotel, two shops and a post-office as well as a county council quarry, a creamery stop and a potential sawmill, the E.S.B. will review the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamNorton" hpid="Mr. Norton Mr. Norton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Norton</NameTxt>
      <P>I am informed by the E.S.B. that the townlands mentioned are included in the Cahirciveen area which has recently been developed under the rural electrification scheme. The economics of extending supply to the householders of these townlands were examined by the board but it was found that because of their isolated location the normal fixed charges payable would be inadequate in relation to the capital cost of the high tension line and local network which would be required.</P>
      <P>The board have stated that if any of the residents wish to obtain supply they should communicate with the board's district engineer in Tralee who will quote them the terms on which supply will be made available.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Clonmel Technical School">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Clonmel Technical School.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJDavern" hpid="Mr. Davern Mr. Davern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davern</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Education if he will state the cause of the delay in giving sanction for the <Col N="1072" /> erection of a new technical school at Clonmel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Minister for Education (General Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Education (General Mulcahy)</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not be in a position to sanction the erection of a new technical school in Clonmel until the examination of the drawings and specification, which is at present on hands, has been completed, and it is seen that the money required for the work can be made available.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Iocíochta Faoi Vóta a 40">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Iocíochta Faoi Vóta a 40.</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>den Aire Oideachais an abróidh sé cé mhéad a híocadh anuraidh faoi mhírcheann C a seacht de Vóta a dachad de na Meastacháin i gcoir na Seirbhísí Poiblí.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="Risteárd Ua Maolchatha Risteárd Ua Maolchatha">
      <NameTxt>Risteárd Ua Maolchatha</NameTxt>
      <P>Sé an méad a híocadh faoi fhó-mhírcheann C a seacht de Vóta a dachad de na Meastacháin i gcoir na Seirbísí Poiblí don bhliain airgeadais 1955-1956 ná £65,545.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Land Commission Holdings in Mayo">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Land Commission Holdings in Mayo.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PhelimAlfredCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he will state in respect of County Mayo (a) the number of holdings in the possession of the Land Commission at the latest available date, (b) when they were acquired, (c) the area and poor law valuation thereof, and (d) when it is proposed to allot them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Minister for Lands (Mr. Blowick) Joseph Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Lands (Mr. Blowick)</NameTxt>
      <P>A comprehensive reply to this question would entail much investigation and labour and it is not feasible at present to divert staff for such a purpose. Broadly speaking, however, the position is as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In Mayo, the Land Commission have on hands, apart from about 2,800 acres of untenanted land on Congested Districts Board estates, some 120 estates or holdings comprising about 8,500 acres, the rateable valuation of which is in the region of £1,500. Though some of the properties came on hands prior to 1950 the bulk of the lands passed into the possession of the Land Commission only in recent years, being the vacated holdings of migrants who have transferred to the Midlands. <Col N="1073" /> It is not possible at present to indicate when the lands will be allotted but there will be no avoidable delay in their disposal.</P>
    <P>I must emphasise, however, that about one-third of the area mentioned represents poor quality land, always difficult to dispose of, while as much as 50 per cent. comprises land surrendered by migrants for the rearrangement and enlargement of intermixed and uneconomic holdings.  I have several times explained to the House the complexity of this work and the Deputy will realise that it is a lengthy and tedious process largely dependent on the co-operation of the tenants concerned. Moreover, it is a very delicate task which invariably calls for much resourcefulness, not to mention tact and endless patience, on the part of the Land Commission inspectorate, before satisfactory schemes can be put into operation.  Having regard to these factors and also to the fact that it is occasionally necessary to await the acquisition of some additional &ldquo;key&rdquo; lands before rearrangement proposals likely to produce worthwhile results can be formulated, it is inevitable that land acquired for rearrangement purposes must often remain on the hands of the Land Commission for longer than would appear necessary to the casual observer.</P>
    <P>The Deputy will appreciate of course that lettings of all lands on hands are made to the local tenants.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - West Cork Afforestation">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - West Cork Afforestation.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands if he will state the present position in relation to the proposal to acquire the Coolkelure estate, Dunmanway, for afforestation purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>My Department has agreed to purchase an area of 814 acres of the Coolkelure estate but the sale has not yet been completed.  High Court proceedings are involved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister tell me when these proceedings are to take place?  The money is supposed to be lodged in the Chief State Solicitor's Office for quite a long period.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1074" />
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>The High Court proceedings are pending and I am excluded from interfering.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it correct to say that the Department of Agriculture have agreed with the owner of the land on the price and that the money is lodged in the Chief State Solicitor's Office?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>Part of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>What then is the cause of the delay?  Surely when the money is available the High Court proceedings must be purely formal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>I assure the Deputy that I do not want to get stuck in the High Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister for Lands not give the Deputy some way out?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the Deputy who will be going out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Be very careful over there now.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Sales of Standing Timber">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Sales of Standing Timber.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PaugeBrennan" hpid="Mr. P. Brennan Mr. P. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands whether in relation to forest thinnings it is the intention of the Forestry Division of his Department to continue its present policy of selling standing timber by contract.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer is yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaugeBrennan" hpid="Mr. P. Brennan Mr. P. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that this new policy of selling timber by contract is responsible for a large number of men being laid off?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not responsible for a large number being laid off; it is responsible for some.  The thinnings must be cut down and got out, and the purchaser of the timber will presumably employ the men he finds are experienced in that work.  All it means is that the men will have a different employer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaugeBrennan" hpid="Mr. P. Brennan Mr. P. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it not be true to say that in the interests of the Forestry Division the work would be much better done by direct labour?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1075" />
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>If that were true the change would not have been made. The old system would have been retained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>This relates to thinnings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>To thinnings only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaugeBrennan" hpid="Mr. P. Brennan Mr. P. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that forests in the area may suffer from this system, that contractors who come in have no respect for the timber left standing?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy can rest assured that damage of that kind will not be permitted.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Mayo Forestry Lands">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Mayo Forestry Lands.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PhelimAlfredCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Lands whether the Forestry Division of his Department have inspected all lands in the electoral areas of Ballycroy which have been offered for forestry purposes and, if so, whether it has been decided to acquire any of those lands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephBlowick" hpid="Mr. Blowick Mr. Blowick">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Blowick</NameTxt>
      <P>In the area referred to by the Deputy my Department has on hands an offer of a one-seventh share of a commonage of about 3,500 acres in the townland of Ballycroy.  It is believed that the other co-owners may also be prepared to offer their shares. The commonage will be inspected as soon as possible.</P>
      <P>Five other offers, most of them commonages, with a total area of over 9,000 acres, were inspected in this district recently but were found unsuitable for forestry purposes because of soil quality and wind exposure.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Sale of Surplus Turkeys">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Sale of Surplus Turkeys.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DenisAllen" hpid="P. Brennan P. Brennan  Allen Allen">
      <NameTxt>Messrs. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>and <b>P. Brennan</b> asked the Minister for Agriculture what steps are being taken to ensure a market for surplus turkeys at a fair price, and if, for the information of producers, he will make a statement on the position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon) James M. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture (Mr. Dillon)</NameTxt>
      <P>The British market takes the bulk of our turkeys during the Christmas season, and the prices paid <Col N="1076" /> to our producers are, therefore, determined mainly by the prices obtainable for our turkeys in Britain.  These prices are decided by demand and supply. This year there has been a record increase in the number of British home-produced turkeys, as well as some increase in numbers here.  It is expected, in consequence, that turkey prices will be lower than last year.</P>
      <P>I might add, however, that, as a guide to turkey producers, a market bulletin will be issued to the Press and radio twice weekly, which will give the price and general market position in the principal centres in Britain and will give also the live-weight prices paid to our producers at our local markets.</P>
      <P>I would advise producers to follow that information as closely as possible to ensure that they obtain the proper market price for their turkeys.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisAllen" hpid="Mr. Allen Mr. Allen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Allen</NameTxt>
      <P>I feel sure the Minister is aware that last season the people were advised by the Department of Agriculture to hold over their turkeys and that consequently they found themselves, in Christmas week, with no market.  Will the Department advise turkey producers this year to market their birds early and not to hold them over?  It is very important that such advice should be given because producers will be influenced by such advice.  Can the Department give any help to producers to market their turkeys on the English market? Has anything been done by the marketing organisation to help producers find a market?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought I had explained that I had arranged to publish twice weekly reports upon this matter.  I want to correct the Deputy. I am not aware that the Department of Agriculture gave any such advice to turkey producers, as he alleges they gave, last year.  That is a figment of his own imagination.  I shall continue to provide for producers bi-weekly reports on the state of the market.  I do not think the Department is qualified to give the kind of advice the Deputy is seeking.  However, I believe it would be sound advice for producers who have large cock birds to dispose of <Col N="1077" /> them whenever they are offered the value of them, as the value of large birds is not calculated to increase, the closer we approach to Christmas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not a fact that last year the Minister was preening himself and strutting about like a turkey cock as the sultan of white turkeys?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that the 14,000 votes out of 60,000 that were recorded for the son of the Deputy's leader have somewhat intoxicated the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister arranging for the broadcasting of the market reports to farmers?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>Twice weekly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister sure he will not blame Radio Éireann for any depression in the prices of turkeys?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I thought the Deputy was asking a civil question or I would have given him an uncivil answer.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Potato Marketing Board">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Potato Marketing Board.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EugeneGilbride" hpid="Mr. Gilbride Mr. Gilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Gilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture whether he is aware that producers are dissatisfied with the operation of the Potato Marketing Board since it became a limited company and that they consider that there is insufficient producer representation on the board, and, if so, if he will take such steps as are necessary to ensure adequate producer representation on the board.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesMatthewDillon" hpid="Mr. Dillon Mr. Dillon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dillon</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not aware of any dissatisfaction on the part of growers generally with the operation of the Irish Potato Marketing Company.  The company is primarily a selling organisation, and, notwithstanding the very keen competition from other exporting countries, has succeeded each year in finding remunerative outlets for all of our surplus seed potatoes.  Representations have been received by me regarding producer representation on the board of the company.  I would, however, point out to the Deputy that under the articles of association of the company the power to increase the <Col N="1078" /> number of directors rests with the board, on which there are at present three growers' representatives.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Gaeltacht Fishing Stations">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Gaeltacht Fishing Stations.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Agriculture whether he has completed his consideration of the proposal to establish a fishing station in the Galway Gaeltacht, and, if so, with what result.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverJFlanagan" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture (Mr. O. Flanagan) Oliver J. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture (Mr. O. Flanagan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I assume the Deputy's question to refer to proposals for the establishment of a number of major fishing stations for which purpose the Galway Gaeltacht had among other regions been surveyed. These proposals generally have been under review but consideration of them has not yet been completed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Parliamentary Secretary say how any special difficulty has been experienced in relation to this matter?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverJFlanagan" hpid="Mr. O. Flanagan Mr. O. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure the Deputy that the proposals generally have been under review and that consideration of them has not yet been completed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I to take it that the plan for the establishment of these six stations is not yet decided upon?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverJFlanagan" hpid="Mr. O. Flanagan Mr. O. Flanagan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O. Flanagan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy may take it that the proposals generally are under review but that consideration of them has not been completed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>What I want to know from the Parliamentary Secretary is whether there has been a general decision that development of this kind will not be accepted by the Government? The Parliamentary Secretary will remember it was accepted in principle by the previous Government. Has that been confirmed or ratified by the present Government?</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Limerick Postal Deliveries">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Limerick Postal Deliveries.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs whether he has received complaints that last December six letters posted to a person in <Col N="1079" /> County Limerick [name and address supplied] within a period of three weeks never arrived at their destination; that letters posted at a County Limerick letter box between 3rd and 7th July, 26th July and 30th July were also lost or mislaid; that letters posted in England by the person in question and addressed to his wife in County Limerick were opened in the G.P.O., Limerick, last May; and if he will state the authority under which the letters were opened, and the reasons therefor, and why this person's letters have been consistently interfered with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Keyes) Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Keyes)">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Posts and Telegraphs (Mr. Keyes)</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no knowledge or record in the Department of complaints regarding (a) the non-delivery of six letters which are stated to have been posted in December, 1955, to the County Limerick address of the person concerned or (b) the alleged opening of letters sent by that person from England to his wife in County Limerick.  If the Deputy will let me know when and to whom the complaints are alleged to have been made I shall have these matters investigated.</P>
      <P>The only relevant complaint recorded concerns a report made to the British Post Office regarding the non-receipt of a letter posted in County Limerick between the 1st and 7th July, 1956, and addressed to London.  When this complaint was being investigated the sender of the item stated that a second one similarly addressed and posted in County Limerick on the 26th July, 1956, had also failed to reach the addressee.  The inquiries made by my Department and the British Post Office regarding these two letters yielded no clue as to why they failed to reach the addressee.  Both the sender and addressee were notified accordingly by letter dated 30th August, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that I furnished him with the original envelopes which were opened at the G.P.O. in Limerick?  Is the Minister further aware that in the case of correspondence addressed to this man in England and correspondence addressed to his wife passing through <Col N="1080" /> the G.P.O. in Limerick, the majority of that correspondence has been opened?  Is the Minister further aware that, according to this man's own statement which has already been submitted to the Minister, any letters addressed to him and posted elsewhere, from Wicklow, Dublin and Waterford, are not interfered with; but he says &ldquo;It is significant that all my letters passing through Limerick G.P.O. are opened or interfered with&rdquo;? Is the Minister further aware that marked across the envelopes are &ldquo;Posted in London; cleared by customs, 22nd May, 1956; G.P.O. Limerick&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Mr. Keyes Mr. Keyes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keyes</NameTxt>
      <P>It is implied in the Deputy's question that three complaints were lodged and three incidents occurred.  We have only got information in relation to one and we have traced that one.  I would ask the Deputy to give us the information upon which the other complaints were made and to whom they were made, and we will have them fully investigated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister state why these two envelopes were opened?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Mr. Keyes Mr. Keyes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keyes</NameTxt>
      <P>I could, if I got an opportunity of investigating it.  I have got no evidence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>When I put down my question, I attached these envelopes for the Minister's inspection.  Has the Minister seen them?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Mr. Keyes Mr. Keyes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keyes</NameTxt>
      <P>I have undertaken, if the Deputy helps me and gives me the necessary information, to trace the items, and then we will deal with them. The Post Office are very jealous of the protection afforded to letters, either registered or unregistered.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister state why these letters were opened? The Minister is aware they were opened and will he state why they were opened?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Mr. Keyes Mr. Keyes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keyes</NameTxt>
      <P>I have had no evidence until now that they were so opened.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Question No. 18.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1081" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJKeyes" hpid="Mr. Keyes Mr. Keyes">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keyes</NameTxt>
      <P>If the Deputy will give me that information, I will have the items traced immediately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>I gave it to the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Kerry Blind Pensions">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Kerry Blind Pensions.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWPalmer" hpid="Mr. Palmer Mr. Palmer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Palmer</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Social Welfare if he will state in respect of County Kerry (a) the number of persons in receipt of blind pensions, and (b) the number of blind persons who are not in receipt of any benefits; and if he will ask the local authority to evolve a scheme for the welfare of blind persons so that they may be cared for in reasonable comfort either in their own homes or elsewhere.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Corish) Brendan Corish">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Corish)</NameTxt>
      <P>At the 28th December, 1955, the latest date for which such statistics are available, there were 526 persons in County Kerry in receipt of pensions, as blind persons, under the Old Age Pensions Acts.  There are no data available as to the number of blind persons in the county who are not in receipt of any benefit.  As regards the latter part of the Deputy's question the local authority already operates a scheme for the welfare of the blind, which provides for the payment of weekly cash allowances to blind persons living in their own homes or in lodgings and also for the maintenance of blind persons in approved institutions.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Social Welfare Benefits">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Social Welfare Benefits.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DenisLarkin" hpid="Mr. J. Larkin Mr. J. Larkin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Larkin</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Social Welfare whether it is proposed to take steps to end the three-day waiting period in respect of benefit claims under the Social Welfare Act, 1952, particularly in cases where applicants are transferring from unemployment benefit to unemployment assistance; and, if so, when.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanCorish" hpid="Mr. Corish Mr. Corish">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Corish</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment of the Social Welfare Acts, 1952 and 1956, for the purpose mentioned in the first part of the Deputy's question, is not at present contemplated.  The matter referred to in the second part of the question has been examined and noted <Col N="1082" /> in connection with legislation, which I hope to introduce, to amend the Unemployment Assistance Acts.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- West Cork Special Employment Schemes">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - West Cork Special Employment Schemes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether he is aware that considerable dissatisfaction exists in many districts of West Cork as a result of the failure to implement an assurance that beneficiaries would receive preferential employment in schemes carried out by the Special Employment Schemes Office.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Donnellan) Michael Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Donnellan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Beneficiaries get only a limited preference in the recruitment of workers for schemes administered by the Special Employment Schemes Office in West Cork and elsewhere and any dissatisfaction that may exist is due to a misunderstanding of the position. I shall set out again for the information of the Deputy the recruitment procedure for the different types of schemes.  In the case of Minor Employment Schemes, recruitment of unskilled workers is confined to persons who are in receipt of unemployment assistance and who are fully capable and suitable for the work in hands, which is invariably heavy manual work.  Beneficiaries of the schemes who are not in receipt of unemployment assistance are not eligible for employment on these schemes unless they specially facilitate the carrying out of the work by giving concessions of real value disproportionate to the benefit which they otherwise gain from the carrying out of the work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In the case of Bog Development Schemes and Rural Improvements Schemes, recruitment of labourers is made in the following order of preference: &mdash;(a) Recipients of unemployment assistance.  (b) Recipients of unemployment benefit.  (c) Other persons registered at the local office of the Department of Social Welfare, including ex-members of the Defence Forces.  (d) Beneficiaries under the scheme who have contributed to the cost, or members of their families.  (e) Other workers in the area, preference <Col N="1083" /> being given, where possible, to necessitous cases.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it not implied in the application form for rural improvement schemes that applicants who are beneficiaries will get preferential treatment, so far as employment is concerned? As the Minister pointed out in his answer, most of these applicants are beneficiaries.  They give concessions to the Parliamentary Secretary's office to have these projects carried out. The fact that they do not get any return by way of employment gives rise to grave dissatisfaction, as the Parliamentary Secretary is only too well aware.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Parliamentary Secretary aware that the rural improvements scheme grants for West Cork have been cut from last year&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!  That is an entirely separate matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;because there is no money there?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>There is nobody from West Cork to talk about West Cork.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I am well aware&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is well aware.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Order!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have had occasion to bring to the notice of the Parliamentary Secretary's office several complaints regarding this question of the recruitment of labour on these schemes, and a number of these schemes had to be dropped because applicants did not get employment on them.  A number were closed down in West Cork for that reason.  Can the Parliamentary Secretary indicate whether any change will be made?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I made it quite plain that as far as those works are concerned people drawing unemployment assistance get first preference, and rightly so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1084" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Address the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not address Deputy MacEntee.  They get first preference, and rightly so.  If there are more required afterwards, the people who contribute or their families get second preference.  That was the case all along during my time and it will continue while I am there which will be a long time.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- West Cork Rural Improvement Schemes">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - West Cork Rural Improvement Schemes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether he is aware that an application for a rural improvement scheme grant for the carrying out of a most urgent and desirable work of general public utility was submitted some years ago by the residents of Corrydorrigan, Schull; and, if so, if, in view of the fact that the local contribution was paid a long time ago, he will, ensure that this work is implemented without delay.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Deputy has already been informed, the work referred to cannot be proceeded with, due to the refusal of some of the residents on the road to consent to blasting operations, which are an essential part of the work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Parliamentary Secretary's office not aware that this is a connecting road leading to a creamery serving many farmers in this district, and that as far as the consent is concerned, every one of these people who have land adjoining this road has consented, and that the money has been lodged in the Parliamentary Secretary's office with a view to having this work carried out?  The only objection to the scheme is from an old lady who has no land adjoining the road and who has complained to the Parliamentary Secretary's office that, if this work is carried out, it may cause an annoyance.  I want this situation made clear and I want a reply from the Parliamentary Secretary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Question No. 22.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Could not the Ceann Comhairle advise Deputy Murphy to <Col N="1085" /> borrow the Tánaiste's hammer to use on the Parliamentary Secretary?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Blasting operations have to be carried out.  Right beside it there is a house and, until these people give consent, we cannot carry out the work.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not the Parliamentary Secretary good at blasting?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I did not blast you out of it, anyhow.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if, in view of the general public utility of the proposed work and the fact that it involves the connection of two public roads, he will reconsider his decision disapproving of the rural improvement scheme submitted by Mr. Thomas O'Neill and others of Lissacalra, Schull.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am advised that the road referred to is not of use to the general public and is used only by the local landholders of whom only two would require to use the whole of the road.  I regret, therefore, that I cannot alter the decision already communicated to the Deputy that the cost of repairs would be excessive in relation to the utility of the work.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Mayo Minor Employment Schemes">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Mayo Minor Employment Schemes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PhelimAlfredCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for <Col N="1086" /> Finance if he will state in respect of each of the years 1952/53, 1953/54, 1954/55 and 1955/56 the expenditure on minor employment schemes for the rural districts of Ballina, Belmullet, Swinford and Westport, and the proposed expenditure for the year 1956/ 57 in each district.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PhelimAlfredCalleary" hpid="Mr. Calleary Mr. Calleary">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Calleary</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state in respect of each of the years 1952/53, 1953/54, 1954/55 and 1955/56 the number of works carried out under minor employment schemes in the rural districts of Ballina, Belmullet, Swinford and Westport, and the proposed number to be carried out in each district in the year 1956/57.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose, with the permission of the Ceann Comhairle, to take Questions Nos. 23 and 24 together, and as the information requested is in the form of a tabular statement, to circulate it with the Official Report.</P>
      <P>As the amounts actually expended are not readily available for subdivisions of a county, I have given instead figures based on the allocations for each year.</P>
      <P>The following is the statement:&mdash;</P>
      <P Just="Center">MINOR EMPLOYMENT SCHEMES</P>
      <P Just="Center">COUNTY MAYO</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="11">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="4" colnum="4" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="5" colnum="5" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="6" colnum="6" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="7" colnum="7" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="8" colnum="8" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="9" colnum="9" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="10" colnum="10" colwidth="8*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="11" colnum="11" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Rural District</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1" namest="2" nameend="3">1952/53</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1" namest="4" nameend="5">1953/54</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1" namest="6" nameend="7">1954/55</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1" namest="8" nameend="9">1955/56</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1" namest="10" nameend="11">1956/57</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>No. of Schemes</entry>
            <entry>Allocation</entry>
            <entry>No. of Schemes</entry>
            <entry>Allocation</entry>
            <entry>No. of Schemes</entry>
            <entry>Allocation</entry>
            <entry>No. of Schemes</entry>
            <entry>Allocation</entry>
            <entry>No. of Schemes</entry>
            <entry>Allocation</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Ballina</entry>
            <entry>39</entry>
            <entry>3,595</entry>
            <entry>48</entry>
            <entry>5,675</entry>
            <entry>34</entry>
            <entry>5,945</entry>
            <entry>45</entry>
            <entry>6,110</entry>
            <entry>19</entry>
            <entry>3,340</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Belmullet</entry>
            <entry>35</entry>
            <entry>3,975</entry>
            <entry>59</entry>
            <entry>6,600</entry>
            <entry>63</entry>
            <entry>7,390</entry>
            <entry>58</entry>
            <entry>6,970</entry>
            <entry>42</entry>
            <entry>5,425</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Swinford</entry>
            <entry>37</entry>
            <entry>5,955</entry>
            <entry>87</entry>
            <entry>9,450</entry>
            <entry>49</entry>
            <entry>7,460</entry>
            <entry>48</entry>
            <entry>8,130</entry>
            <entry>26</entry>
            <entry>4,405</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Westport</entry>
            <entry>64</entry>
            <entry>7,480</entry>
            <entry>74</entry>
            <entry>7,670</entry>
            <entry>66</entry>
            <entry>8,110</entry>
            <entry>58</entry>
            <entry>6,330</entry>
            <entry>30</entry>
            <entry>3,835</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Total (4 R.D.s).</entry>
            <entry>175</entry>
            <entry>21,005</entry>
            <entry>268</entry>
            <entry>29,395</entry>
            <entry>212</entry>
            <entry>28,905</entry>
            <entry>209</entry>
            <entry>27,540</entry>
            <entry>117</entry>
            <entry>17,005</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Emergency and Employment Schemes">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Emergency and Employment Schemes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJDavern" hpid="Mr. Davern Mr. Davern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davern</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance why the grant from the Emergency and Employment Schemes Vote in respect of the Tipperary urban district was reduced from last year's figure of £1,350 to £550 for the current year, and whether, in view of the high number of unemployed in the district, he will reconsider his decision.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Dáil has already been informed, the necessity <Col N="1087" /> in present financial circumstances for securing economies in public expenditure caused a reduction in the provision for special employment schemes, in common with other services.  The grant already allocated for Tipperary urban district represents the full amount at present available for the area.  As stated in the reply to a question addressed to me by Deputy O'Malley to-day, I cannot yet indicate whether any of the money which the Government have decided should be provided for works of a productive character during the remainder of the financial year will affect the present allocation from the Vote for Employment and Emergency Schemes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJDavern" hpid="Mr. Davern Mr. Davern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davern</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Parliamentary Secretary say if their latest policy is to exterminate the unemployed workers from Tipperary town?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>No such thing, but it was your policy for many years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Mr. Cunningham Mr. Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state (a) the amount allocated to the Donegal County Council under sub-head G of the Employment and Emergency Schemes Vote in each of the years 1955-56 and 1956-57, and (b) the estimated amount of the latter sum which will be spent on (i) administrative costs, (ii) materials and (iii) labourers' wages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>The available information is as follows:&mdash; (a) 1955-56, £15,500; 1956-57, £700.  (b) As the 1956-57 schemes have not yet been submitted by the Donegal County Council it is not possible to give the requested analysis of costs.  There will, however, be no administrative charge as these services will be provided by the normal county council staffs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Mr. Cunningham Mr. Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Parliamentary Secretary give some reason and, if possible, a fairly good reason, for the reduction in this grant from £15,000 last year to £700 this year and will be consider whether it is worth while seeking to relieve unemployment by issuing £700 to Donegal County Council?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1088" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Donegal cannot be an exception in relation to any other part of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Mr. Cunningham Mr. Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Why not give it all to some one county?</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - County Galway Grants">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - County Galway Grants.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Mr. Bartley Mr. Bartley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bartley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will state in respect of County Galway the total amount of grants spent last year and spent, or approved for expenditure, this year, respectively, under each of the headings: (a) urban employment schemes, (b) rural employment schemes, (c) minor employment schemes, (d) bog development schemes, and (e) rural improvement schemes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>As the information requested is in the form of a tabular statement I propose, with the permission of the Ceann Comhairle, to circulate it in the Official Report.</P>
      <P>The following is the statement:&mdash;</P>
      <P Just="Center">COUNTY GALWAY</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="20*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Expenditure 1955/56</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Allocations, 1956/57</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Urban Employment Schemes</entry>
            <entry>4,088</entry>
            <entry>1,450</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Rural Employment Schemes</entry>
            <entry>6,830</entry>
            <entry>1,380</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Minor Employment Schemes</entry>
            <entry>21,61</entry>
            <entry>11,835</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Bog Development Schemes</entry>
            <entry>33,574</entry>
            <entry>14,945</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Rural Improvements Scheme</entry>
            <entry>45,639</entry>
            <entry>20,047</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>(to 31st October, 1956).</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Totals</entry>
            <entry>111,802</entry>
            <entry>49,657</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>NOTE:&mdash;The Rural Improvements Scheme figures are gross,&mdash;i.e.&mdash;they include local contributions; the other figures are State Grant only.  Also, there is no fixed allocation for individual Counties under this Scheme.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Special Employment Schemes">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Special Employment Schemes.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he will correlate the sum of £265,000 stated by him on the 25th October last to be the proposed State expenditure in the current financial year for special employment schemes, and which shows a reduction of 16 per cent. on that for the previous year, with the reduction of 85 per cent. represented by figures supplied by him on the 31st ultimo in respect of winter relief schemes; further, if he will state <Col N="1089" /> the allocations of the sum of £265,000 as between the various local authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>As stated in my reply to the Deputy's question of 31st October, 1956, there was a large carry forward to 1st April, 1956, of unexpended grants, amounting to £285,104, in respect of schemes approved prior to that date.  This sum with the proposed allocation of £105,000 for new schemes makes at the present time a total of approved grants of £390,104, from which, as already stated, expenditure in the current year is estimated at £265,000.</P>
      <P>While it is not possible at this stage to make an accurate forecast, it is expected that the expenditure of £265,000 will be incurred as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="30*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="20*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Dublin County Borough</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">£155,000</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Cork County Borough</entry>
            <entry>20,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Limerick County Borough</entry>
            <entry>15,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Waterford County Borough</entry>
            <entry>8,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Other Urban Areas</entry>
            <entry>52,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Rural Areas</entry>
            <entry>15,000</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Winter Relief Scheme">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Winter Relief Scheme.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance whether, in view of the fact that there are 15,258 more unemployed now than at the same period last year, he intends to restore the cuts made in allocations from the winter relief scheme, and if not, if he will state why.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Sweetman) Gerard Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Sweetman)</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government have decided to restrict the savings which were being effected, under their directions, to deal with the adverse balance of external payments, so as to enable an additional sum to be allocated in the remainder of this year for expenditure on works of a productive character.  The effect of this decision will be to alleviate unemployment during the coming months.  The details of the financial and administrative arrangements to give effect to the Government decision have not yet been settled and, consequently, I am not in a position now to answer the specific point raised by the Deputy relative to the Vote for Employment and Emergency Schemes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1090" />
    <Speaker pid="DonoghOMalley" hpid="Mr. O'Malley Mr. O'Malley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Malley</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister state if he and the Government will have arrived at a decision about the allocation of this money before Christmas?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister and the Government will arrive at a decision very speedily in relation to this, as in other matters.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Minister aware that at the present time in many local authority areas road workers are now on alternate employment, that is, they are employed every second week, whereas this time last year workers in some other schemes were enabled to be kept in constant employment until at least the Christmas period was over?  Would the Minister do his utmost to ensure that employment will be given at least until the Christmas period has elapsed so that these breadwinners will be in a position to ensure that over the Christmas period their families will not be in want?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The allocations that have been made by the Government will be spent, so far as possible, on productive work and as speedily as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>According to this question&mdash;and it is quite true&mdash;there are 15,000 extra unemployed people and is not it a fact that, in order to meet that 15,000 extra unemployed, more money must be spent on nonproductive work to pay these men in idleness?  Is it not more important to put these men to work on schemes already submitted by local authorities rather than to have to pay them unemployment assistance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Is not it a fact that, so far as the present situation is concerned, the Taoiseach and the Tánaiste are much more responsible for it than the Minister for Finance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>Apart from the interjection by Deputy MacEntee, I do not think that question and answer here is the right way to discuss the full implications of an external imbalance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1091" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMacBride" hpid="Mr. MacBride Mr. MacBride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacBride</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister be in a position to make a statement to the House in the near future?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>You vote for them; you support them.  Bear your burden.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>In the near future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnODonovan" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Government (Mr. O'Donovan) John O'Donovan (Dublin South-East)">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Government (Mr. O'Donovan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Nobody supports Deputy MacEntee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>The public support us.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>The Parliamentary Secretary should not try to get out now.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Drainage of River Maine">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Drainage of River Maine.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWPalmer" hpid="Mr. Palmer Mr. Palmer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Palmer</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Finance if he is aware of the urgent need for the drainage of the River Maine, County Kerry, and if he will make a statement clarifying the present position in regard to this project.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>The preparation of a scheme under the Arterial Drainage Act, 1945, for the River Maine catchment area has been proceeding with all possible speed but, owing to shortage of technical staff and difficulties encountered in the design, progress has not been as rapid as was hoped. The preparatory work is now well advanced but, pending compliance with the statutory requirements in regard to exhibition and confirmation of the scheme and the availability of capital, it is not possible at this stage to say definitely when actual works on the ground can be begun.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWPalmer" hpid="Mr. Palmer Mr. Palmer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Palmer</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Parliamentary Secretary give an assurance that provision will be made for that project in the Estimate for the coming financial year and, if so, will he state the amount?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Deputy is aware, I cannot anticipate what might be in the Estimates for the coming financial year.  I would ask him to wait.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWPalmer" hpid="Mr. Palmer Mr. Palmer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Palmer</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Parliamentary Secretary now state at least that provision will be made for the scheme in the coming financial year?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1092" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Ask the Taoiseach.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will ask the Deputy to wait.  I hope he will not be disappointed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickWPalmer" hpid="Mr. Palmer Mr. Palmer">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Palmer</NameTxt>
      <P>How long shall I have to wait?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Ask Deputy James Larkin.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Deontaisi Bhóthair i nGaillimh">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Deontaisi Bhóthair i nGaillimh.</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>den Aire Rialtais Áitiúil an abróidh sé i leith Contae na Gaillimhe cé mhéad san iomlán de na deontais bhóthair a tugadh anuraidh agus a tugadh nó atá ceaptha i mbliana, faoi seach, faoi gach mírcheann nó teideal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="An tAire Rialtais Áitiúil (Pádraig Ó Domhnaill) An tAire Rialtais Áitiúil (Pádraig Ó Domhnaill)">
      <NameTxt>An tAire Rialtais Áitiúil (Pádraig Ó Domhnaill)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá an freagra don cheist seo i bhfuirm tábla agus led chead, a Cheann Comhairle, cuirfear ar fáil é leis an Tuarascáil Oifigiúil.</P>
      <P>Sé seo an tábla:&mdash;</P>
      <P Just="Center">COMHAIRLE CONTAE NA GAILLIMHE</P>
      <P Just="Center">Deontaisí Bóthar</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="24*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="13*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="13*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1955/56</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">1956/57</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
            <entry>£</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Deontas cothabháil príomhbhóthar</entry>
            <entry>61,000</entry>
            <entry>67,964</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Deontas feabhsú príomhbhóthar</entry>
            <entry>91,000</entry>
            <entry>75,800</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Deontas feabhsú bóthar contae</entry>
            <entry>128,800</entry>
            <entry>144,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Deontas na mBóthar Cuartaíochta</entry>
            <entry>55,000</entry>
            <entry>55,000</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Deontas breise ón Ród-Chiste</entry>
            <entry>25,000</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Deontas speisialta chun droichead nua a thógáil</entry>
            <entry>&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>5,250</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Deontas ó Vóta chun Scéimeanna Fostaíochta agus Eigeandála</entry>
            <entry>7,500</entry>
            <entry>1,380</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Iomlán</entry>
            <entry>368,300</entry>
            <entry>349,394</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Tipperary Cottages">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Tipperary Cottages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJDavern" hpid="Mr. Davern Mr. Davern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davern</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government when sanction will be given in respect of the remaining ten applications for cottages under the Tipperary, South Riding, County Council's No. 1 compulsory purchase order, and if, in view of the fact that the sites were provided voluntarily, he will expedite the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>Some points relating to the housing needs of prospective tenants of the cottages to be built on <Col N="1093" /> these ten sites are at present being examined.  A decision on the proposed acquisition of the sites will be conveyed to the county council as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJDavern" hpid="Mr. Davern Mr. Davern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davern</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he is prepared to approve Compulsory Purchase Order No. 2 in respect of 63 cottages, which was sent to him by the Tipperary, South Riding, County Council on 9th July, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Order is at present <i>sub judice</i>, I cannot give any indication as to whether it may be confirmed, in whole or in part.  I can, however, inform the Deputy that there will be no avoidable delay in bringing the matter to finality.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJDavern" hpid="Mr. Davern Mr. Davern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davern</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he is prepared to approve Compulsory Purchase Order No. 3 in respect of 42 cottages, which was sent to him by the Tipperary, South Riding, County Council on 11th September, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>My position in relation to this Question is as stated in reply to Question No. 33.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Clonmel Housing">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Clonmel Housing.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJDavern" hpid="Mr. Davern Mr. Davern">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Davern</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government if he is now in a position to state when sanction will be given in respect of the tenders received by the Clonmel Corporation for the erection of a 27 house scheme and a 32 house scheme in O'Donnell's Field, Clonmel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielSpring" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government (Mr. Spring) Daniel Spring">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Local Government (Mr. Spring)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not yet in a position to state when a decision will be given on these proposals.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Reduced Housing Grant">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Reduced Housing Grant.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Mr. Cunningham Mr. Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government whether he is aware that in the case of a new house [name and address supplied] built strictly in accordance with plans submitted to, and approved by, his Department a reduced grant has been paid and if, in view of the fact that such reduction appears to constitute an injustice, <Col N="1094" /> he will now take steps to have the balance paid.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>I am aware that the house referred to by the Deputy was erected in accordance with plans submitted to and approved by the appointed officer for the area, and that the grant payable was reduced owing to certain deficiencies in the plan which did not fully meet the statutory requirements.  In connection with this reduction I would refer the Deputy to Article 13 of the Housing (New Houses) Regulations, 1948, which provides that no grant shall be payable, notwithstanding the issue of a certificate of the appointed officer, until the Minister is satisfied as to the accuracy of the certificate.  I do not propose to vary the decision already given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Mr. Cunningham Mr. Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Parliamentary Secretary aware that his Department sanctioned certain plans in this case and the person constructing the house had the house constructed according to the plans sanctioned by the Minister?  Had those plans not been sanctioned, the applicant would have got plans which did comply with the regulations mentioned in the section to which the Parliamentary Secretary has referred.  In view of that, is it not most unfair to penalise an applicant because of a mistake made by an officer of the Minister's Department?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>It was not a mistake.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Mr. Cunningham Mr. Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>Then may I ask the Parliamentary Secretary if this applicant is being penalised because his house does not comply with the regulations, and is he aware that it does not comply with the regulations because these plans got the O.K. from the Minister?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>They got the O.K. subject to a fine and that fine was reduced from £15 to £10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Mr. Cunningham Mr. Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>There was no indication in the certificate of approval issued that there would be a fine and there was no indication that the plans were substandard.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1095" />
    <Speaker pid="DanielSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>Application for a certificate of approval in this case was made to the appointed officer on the 28th April, 1954, by the St. Eunan's Public Utility Society.  The certificate of approval was issued on the 30th April, 1954.  On 23rd December, 1954, a letter was received from the appointed officer stating that, on a recent inspection of the house for the purpose of authorising payment of an instalment of the grant, it was found that the glazed areas of the larger rooms were substandard. The papers were referred to the local housing inspector for investigation and he reported that the glazed area of one room was insufficient and, also, that the total floor area of bedroom accommodation provided was substandard. The public utility society was advised that a reduction of £15 would be made in the grant in respect of these deficiencies.  The members subsequently appealed against this decision and, on further consideration, the reduction was mitigated to £10.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Mr. Cunningham Mr. Cunningham">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cunningham</NameTxt>
      <P>All those ills arose because of the fact that the Department of Local Government had sanctioned a plan which was substandard. There is no use in saying now these things arose afterwards.  They arose when it was too late because&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>The appointed officer passed a plan and subsequently he would not approve of the house.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Construction of Dublin Flats">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Construction of Dublin Flats.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DenisLarkin" hpid="Mr. J. Larkin Mr. J. Larkin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Larkin</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Local Government when it is expected that the Dublin Corporation will commence construction of flats in the Vicar Street area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielSpring" hpid="Mr. Spring Mr. Spring">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Spring</NameTxt>
      <P>I am unable to say when the erection of the proposed scheme of flat-dwellings at Vicar Street is expected to commence, but I understand that the corporation hope to be in a position to invite tenders for the scheme early next year.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Beds for Kerry Patients">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Beds for Kerry Patients.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="HonorMaryCrowley" hpid="Mrs. Crowley Mrs. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>asked the Minister for Health whether he is aware that the Kerry County Council have been allocated only 17 beds in Gurranebraher Regional Orthopaedic Hospital, County <Col N="1096" /> Cork; and if, in view of the fact that there is a long waiting list, he will arrange for the allocation of at least 25 beds to Kerry patients.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell (for the Minister for Health) Mr. O'Donnell (for the Minister for Health)">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell (for the Minister for Health)</NameTxt>
      <P>It was agreed when the Gurranebraher Orthopaedic Hospital was established that 25 beds should be reserved for patients for whom the Kerry County Council are responsible. During my discussions in Tralee with members of the Kerry County Council in July last I was informed that there were only 13 Kerry patients in the hospital at that time.  I arranged to have the matter taken up with the South Cork Board of Public Assistance which is the authority responsible for the hospital. The board have replied that owing to the polio outbreak in Cork all admissions to the hospital have been slowed but that all urgent cases from Kerry have been admitted without delay and that the less urgent cases were being admitted as beds become available.</P>
      <P>I am keeping in constant touch with the situation and am endeavouring to ensure that 25 beds will be made available for Kerry patients at the earliest possible date.</P>
      <P>I might add that there is a large waiting list of Cork patients for admission to the hospital.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral Answers." RHead="- Caitheachas ar Roinn na Gaeltachta">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Caitheachas ar Roinn na Gaeltachta.</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Liam Mac Cuinneagáin Liam Mac Cuinneagáin">
      <NameTxt>Liam Mac Cuinneagáin</NameTxt>
      <P>d'Aire na Gaeltachta an abróidh sé cé mhéid airgid atáthar a braith a chaitheamh ar Roinn na Gaeltachta go dtí an 31 Márta, 1957, agus céard iad na slite ina gcaithfear an t-airgead sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Aire na Gaeltachta (Pádraig Mac Loingsigh) Aire na Gaeltachta (Pádraig Mac Loingsigh)">
      <NameTxt>Aire na Gaeltachta (Pádraig Mac Loingsigh)</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá an t-eolas a theastaíos ón Teachta le fáil sa mheastachán le haghaidh na Roinne a cheadaigh an Dáil ar an 25 Iúil seo caite agus sa ráiteas a rinne Aire na Gaeltachta ar an ócáid sin.  Chomh fada agus a bhaineas le Ceann-Oifig na Roinne, níl éinní le cur agam leis an ráiteas sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Liam Mac Cuinneagáin Liam Mac Cuinneagáin">
      <NameTxt>Liam Mac Cuinneagáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Níor fhreagair an tAire an chuid deireanach den cheist. Níor dhúirt sé cad iad na scéimeanna ar a bhfuiltear ag brath an t-airgead seo a chaitheamh.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1097" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Pádraig Mac Loingsigh Pádraig Mac Loingsigh">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Mac Loingsigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Níor dhúirt mé rud ar bith faoi airgead agus deinim iarracht freagra cruinn a thabhairt ar cheist chruinn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Liam Mac Cuinneagáin Liam Mac Cuinneagáin">
      <NameTxt>Liam Mac Cuinneagáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Níor dhúirt sé rud ar bith faoi airgead san bhfreagra ach chuir mé cheist cuige i dtaobh airgid.  D'fhiafraigh mé dhe cad iad na scéimeanna go bfuiltear ag brath airgead a chaitheamh orthu.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I dtaobh an airgid atá luaite ag an Aire, ná fuil ann airgead i gcóir cúrsaí riaracháin?</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions. Oral" RHead="Answers. - Limistéiri na Gaeltachta">
    <Title>Ceisteanna&mdash;Questions.   Oral Answers. - Limistéiri na Gaeltachta.</Title>
    <P>D'fhiafraigh</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Liam Mac Cuinneagáin Liam Mac Cuinneagáin">
      <NameTxt>Liam Mac Cuinneagáin</NameTxt>
      <P>d'Aire na Gaeltachta an bhfuil beartaithe aige ná téarmaí &ldquo;Fíor-Ghaeltacht&rdquo; agus &ldquo;Breac-Ghaeltacht&rdquo; a chur ar ceal agus na límistéirí go léir a ghrúpáil faoin teideal &ldquo;Gaeltacht&rdquo;, agus an fhóirithint chéanna a thabhairt don límistéar nua sin.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Pádraig Mac Loingsigh Pádraig Mac Loingsigh">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Mac Loingsigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl tagairt ar bith d'Fhíor-Ghaeltacht nó do Bhreac-Ghaeltacht san Acht Airí agus Rúnaithe (Leasú), 1956, faoinar bunaíodh Roinn na Gaeltachta.  Nil tagairt ann ach do Ghaeltacht.  Mar sin, ní éiríonn an dara chuid den cheist.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Liam Mac Cuinneagáin Liam Mac Cuinneagáin">
      <NameTxt>Liam Mac Cuinneagáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Cé nach bhfuil trácht ar Fhíor-Ghaeltacht nó Breac-Ghaeltacht, caithfear difríocht a dhéanamh eatorra.  An bhfuil an tAire chun na scéimeanna chéana a chur ar siúl ar fud na Gaeltachta ar fad, sé sin, ar fud na Fíor-Ghaeltachta agus na Breac-Ghealtachta mar atá luaite aige?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Pádraig Mac Loingsigh Pádraig Mac Loingsigh">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Mac Loingsigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Tá sé soileír nár léigh an Teachta an Bille nuair a bhí sé ag dul tríd an Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Liam Mac Cuinneagáin Liam Mac Cuinneagáin">
      <NameTxt>Liam Mac Cuinneagáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní freagra é sin ar mo cheist.  D'fhiafraigh me de'n Aire an mbeidh na scéimeanna céana ar síul ar fud an limistéir ar fad go dtugtar Gaeltacht uirthi faoin Acht.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Pádraig Mac Loingsigh Pádraig Mac Loingsigh">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Mac Loingsigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl ann acht aon Ghaeltacht anois.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamCunningham" hpid="Liam Mac Cuinneagáin Liam Mac Cuinneagáin">
      <NameTxt>Liam Mac Cuinneagáin</NameTxt>
      <P>Má tá an <Col N="1098" /> tAire chun na scéimeanna céana do chur ar siúl, an bhfuil fhios aige go bhfuil sé sin i gcoinne gach comhairle de gach ball de Comhdháil Náisiúnta na Gaelige, de gach ball de Comhalta Uladh, agus mar sin, agus go bhfuil sé i gcoinne gach polasaí atá acu?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Níl sé sin sa cheist atá ar an bPáipéar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>An abróidh an tAire gur thóg sé air féin cúramaí i leith limistéiri atá níos leithne ná na limistéiri atá luiate ins an Ordú a rinne sé le deannaí?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Pádraig Mac Loingsigh Pádraig Mac Loingsigh">
      <NameTxt>Pádraig Mac Loingsigh</NameTxt>
      <P>Sin ceist eile.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Ní bhaineann sé sin leis an gceist atá ar an bPáipéar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DanielMorrissey" hpid="Mr. Morrissey Mr. Morrissey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Morrissey</NameTxt>
      <P>It is also after 4 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldBartley" hpid="Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin">
      <NameTxt>Gearóid Mac Pharthaláin</NameTxt>
      <P>Más mar seo a riarfar cúrsaí na hAireachta nua seo&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is furast ceist mar sin do chur síos ar an bPáipéar.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Even though the subject matters of Questions Nos. 21 and 22 may be relatively unimportant, nevertheless, in view of the principle involved in these questions, that an outside&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy say what he wants?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>He cannot.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to raise the subject matter of these two questions on the Adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall communicate with the Deputy.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Bankruptcy Adjudication:" RHead="Statement by Ceann Comhairle">
    <Title>Bankruptcy Adjudication: Statement by Ceann Comhairle.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I have to announce that the Clerk of the Dáil has received from the Official Assignee in Bankruptcy a communication to the effect that Seán Dunne, a member of the Dáil, was adjudicated a bankrupt on the 4th October, 1956, and that an <Col N="1099" /> application to show cause against the adjudication was disallowed on the 13th November, 1956.  A telephone message received this afternoon by the Clerk from the Official Assignee indicates, I understand, that there are proceedings for an appeal.</P>
      <P>It appears proper that the general question of the effect of the adjudication of bankruptcy on Mr. Dunne's membership of the Dáil be referred to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges for examination and report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach (Mr. O'Sullivan) Denis J. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Taoiseach (Mr. O'Sullivan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the question of the effect of the bankruptcy of Seán Dunne on his membership of the Dáil be referred to the Committee of Procedure and Privileges for examination and report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the motion seconded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickSDonegan" hpid="Mr. Donegan Mr. Donegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I second.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>No. 6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. Lemass Mr. Lemass">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lemass</NameTxt>
      <P>When No. 6 is concluded, will the Dáil adjourn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnACostello" hpid="The Taoiseach John Aloysius Costello">
      <NameTxt>The Taoiseach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMaxEntee" hpid="Mr. MacEntee Mr. MacEntee">
      <NameTxt>Mr. MacEntee</NameTxt>
      <P>Shall we meet again?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GerardSweetman" hpid="Mr. Sweetman Mr. Sweetman">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Sweetman</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy should be rather careful about that.  He had a very narrow squeak the last time.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Voluntary Health Insurance Bill," RHead="1956&mdash;Order for Committee Stage Discharged">
    <Title>Voluntary Health Insurance Bill, 1956&mdash;Order for Committee Stage Discharged.</Title>
    <P>Order fixing Committee Stage of the Voluntary Health Insurance Bill, 1956, for Thursday, 29th November, 1956, discharged.</P>
    <P>Bill ordered to be considered in Committee of the whole Dáil on Wednesday, 21st November, 1956.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Statute of Limitations Bill," RHead="1954&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Statute of Limitations Bill, 1954&mdash;Committee Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1100" /> Section 3 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Everett) James Everett">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Everett)</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 22:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 7, line 31, to add, at the end of the section, &ldquo;under the Mercantile Marine Act, 1955 (No. 29 of 1955).&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Attorney-General (Mr. McGilligan) Attorney-General (Mr. McGilligan)">
      <NameTxt>Attorney-General (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that was covered last night.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Very good, Sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>On the amendment. How much wider is that than the original section under the Mercantile Marine Act, 1955?  I have not gone into it, but clearly, this amendment is limiting the exclusion of actions relating to ships merely to those that are embraced under the Mercantile Marine Act.  I have not checked up on the provisions of that Act.  Is there any substantive change in the effect of Section 4 or is this, as was stated, merely a drafting amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is all it is. Proceedings in respect of the forfeiture of a ship are now dealt with by the Mercantile Marine Act, 1955, which replaces the relevant provisions of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, and we might as well so indicate.  As the Minister stated on the Second Stage, proceedings for the forfeiture of a ship are now governed by Section 90 of the 1955 Act.  They arise where a ship unduly assumes Irish character, or conceals Irish or assumes foreign character, or an unqualified person assumes ownership of the ship.  In all cases the ship becomes forfeit to the State.  No period of limitation is prescribed and for obvious reasons.  The proceedings are more or less quasi-criminal proceedings, but it is desirable to exclude them specifically from the Bill.  They are not clearly excluded in the definition of &ldquo;action&rdquo; in Section 2 (1) as they could be held not to be criminal proceedings.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 4, as amended, put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1101" /> SECTION 5.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 5 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The only point that arises on Section 5 is that, although the equitable jurisdiction will be there, I presume equity will follow the law in this matter and that, to all intents and purposes, the law will be as it is in this Act?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, in most cases.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 6 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>The position with regard to counter-claims and set-offs is covered by this section.  It seems to me that&mdash;as far as I am aware, and possibly I am wrong&mdash;the position heretofore would have been that it was not until the date of the filing of the document in which the counter-claim was made that the statute would run.  If I am correct in that view&mdash;and I am not certain that I am&mdash;it seems to me that the position will arise in which, whilst a person's claim against another may be barred by the statute or may be in the process of being barred by the statute, it will be revised by the institution of proceedings against that person and, although there might be very considerable delay, as there often is, until a counter-claim is filed, the advantage of that delay would be lost to the original claimant and the person who owes the liability on the counter-claim. It may not be of any great importance.  It would not be if defence and counter-claim were always filed very soon after the institution of proceedings. Very often in regard to High Court proceedings in particular, there is a very lengthy delay. That delay does not seem to me to be any sound reason why the person who up to that time has slept on his rights should gain a further extension, except in so far as the subject of the counter-claim may be intertwined with the subject of the claim.  The rules permitting a counter-claim, not set off, are the widest <Col N="1102" /> possible.  There is no restriction on counter-claim to confine it to the same subject matter as the claim.  There could be a case made for leaving the provisions of Section 6 with regard to set-off by not extending the counter-claim.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister discussed this matter on the Second Stage and I should like to direct the Deputy's notice to what the Minister said in this respect at column 1134 of the Official Report on 1st March, 1956, which reads as follows:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Under Section 6 of the Bill, where a set-off or counter-claim is pleaded, the set-off or counter-claim shall be deemed to be a separate action for the purpose of fixing the limits of the limitation period applicable; and the date until which the statute runs against such set-off or counter-claim will be the date of the beginning of the action in which the set-off or counter-claim is pleaded.  At present the position, where the statute is pleaded to a set-off or counter-claim, is that time runs against the set-off until the beginning of the action in which it is raised, but it runs against the counter-claim until the date when the counter-claim is pleaded.  The section will, therefore, bring the law of limitation as to a counter-claim into line with the law as to set-off.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>That is what I object to. I appreciate that will be the position. I am suggesting that there is a real difference between counter-claim and set-off.  The rules of the court would confine set-off to the same subject matter as the claim.  Therefore, it would appear that a man against whom a claim is made would bide his time.  The claim, however, can be on any subject matter and, therefore, an entirely different claim could be brought by way of counter-claim which could not be brought by set-off.  I myself do not see the justification for giving an extension of the time merely by reason of the accident of a claim having been made by the same person, though not on the same subject.  It might not be of great importance between individuals, but between firms it would be of great importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1103" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy wants to have this section confined to set-off?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  I would make it a consolidation section only, leaving things as they are.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Notice taken that 20 Deputies were not present; House counted and 20 Deputies being present</i>,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is agreed to have this matter looked into.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 7 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 8</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 8 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder if the wording of sub-paragraph (b) of Section 8 is sufficient?  Is it necessary to put in there something like &ldquo;any right, claim or title in any action&rdquo;? Is any amendment of that nature necessary?  It will do on Report Stage, if necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Does the Deputy mean to extend the word &ldquo;action&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>What is clearly meant there is that the commencement of the action will serve all rights, claims and titles in issue in the action and prevent the statute running against it.  The wording here is: &ldquo;Nothing in this Act shall affect any action commenced before the operative date or the title to any property which is the subject of any such action.&rdquo;  If it had been <i>simpliciter</i>&ldquo;shall not affect any action,&rdquo; then, I think, you could feel reasonably safe that &ldquo;affect any action&rdquo; would affect all claims and disputes involved in the action, but it goes on to say: &ldquo;or the title to any property which is the subject of any such action.&rdquo;  Because you have been specific in that later on it seems to me you could take the stretched interpretation that the section only means the action will not affect the actual action itself.  It would be the subject of limitation, for instance, to bring an action in tort which was brought only within the statutory time.  There might be a case for argument whether the action itself were then in dispute. There might be some other claim or <Col N="1104" /> right <i>per se</i>, in other words, statute barred, and by reason of the fact that you are careful to specify &ldquo;the title to any property which is the subject of any such action,&rdquo; would it not also be safer to include any claim or right in issue in that action as well as the title?  I do not expect that the suggestion can be accepted immediately, but it might perhaps be wise to look into it before Report Stage.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 9 and 10 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 11.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 23:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), page 8, to delete paragraph (b) and substitute:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(b) actions founded on quasi-contract;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.  We are introducing a special category of actions, namely, actions for quasi-contracts.  These are the old actions based on what was called <i>assumpsit</i>, which comprised such actions as actions to recover money paid by mistake, actions on a <i>quantum meruit</i> for work done, and so on. Modern legal theory favours the introduction of quasi-contracts as a new classification.  The obligation arises neither in contract nor in tort.  There is no agreement and there is no wrong doing.  These actions are, as it has been put, actions <i>re</i> and not <i>consensu</i>; and a contract is imputed to the defendant by a fiction of law.  We now propose to use the expression &ldquo;actions founded on quasi-contract&rdquo; instead of the expression in Section 11 (1) &ldquo;actions commonly called actions arising <i>quasi ex contractu&rdquo;.</i>  The term &ldquo;quasi-contract&rdquo; is now well-established in law and we might as well use it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I completely agree that the amendment is in a much more appropriate form than the expression &ldquo;actions commonly called actions arising <i>quasi ex contractu&rdquo;</i>, which, if left in the Bill, would be very sloppy in the matter of draftsmanship.  The only point that will arise, when the Bill becomes a statutory enactment, is this matter of quasi-contract.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1105" /> After all the expression quasi-contract is a technical term, a legal technical term.  So far as I know it is not defined.  On the other hand, though it is the point I think the Attorney-General is making, it is hardly ancient enough to have acquired that certainty of conventional meaning, such as a word like mortgage or morgagee. Has it been considered whether a definition of quasi-contract is desirable? If it is, the only place that I can see that you can get it is from judgments.  To take it from academic legal theory could be dangerous.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>There may be legal textbooks in the background but certainly there are judgments.  The phrase has acquired a well-recognised meaning and it will acquire more when we put it in this Bill.  The present draft is, we think, better.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree; the original phrase would not do at all. The only place where it can be of any real importance is where there is a shorter limitation, say in tort or contract.  There is a shorter limitation in certain torts such as slander.  I do not know how you could get over that but perhaps it would not be beyond the ingenuity of Deputy Finlay.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 24:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1) (e), page 8, line 35, to delete &ldquo;1908&rdquo; and substitute:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;1908, or</P>
      <P>(iii) an amount recoverable by a tortfeasor under Section 4 or 5 of the Tortfeasors Act, 1951 (No. 1 of 1951).&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.  We propose to exclude actions for contribution under the Tortfeasors Act from the category of actions arising under statute and we are providing separately for them in amendments Nos. 16 and 26.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 25:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1106" /> In page 9, sub-section (2) (c), line 7, to delete &ldquo;two&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;three.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a substantive amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this amendment is to provide a period of three years for all slander actions.  The period at present is two years for slander actionable <i>per se</i> and six years for other slander.  Slander <i>per se</i> arises where the words themselves constitute a cause of action, as where one person imputes a criminal offence to another, or imputes dishonesty or unfitness for his trade or profession to him.  In these cases special damage need not be proved.</P>
      <P>The period proposed in the Bill for all slander is two years.  Deputy Finlay raised this matter on the Second Stage and suggested that it might be too short in some cases.  We reconsidered the proposal in the Bill and we are now suggesting three years in all cases. This is the same period as the period proposed for ordinary personal injuries actions.  Slander is a personal injury, though in a non-physical sense, and there is something to be said for having a period of three years in its case as well.  In libel the period is and will continue to be six years, but here different considerations apply as a libel is defamation in a permanent form and the difficulty of the memory of witnesses becoming vague after a long lapse of time does not arise.  What is written is permanent and there will be no doubt as to its exact content.  The actual words used are vital in both libel and slander.  As the years go on, people are less likely to be accurate as to what exactly was said.  We are of opinion that a period of three years ought to be satisfactory for the spoken word.  Another reason for distinguishing libel and slander is that libel is a more serious tort generally and, being often printed, can have a very wide circulation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I think there is nothing against this.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 26:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1107" /> In page 9, before sub-section (3), to insert the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
    <P>( ) An action to recover, in respect of the liability of a tortfeasor to an injured person, an amount recoverable by the tortfeasor under Section 4 or 5 of the Tortfeasors Act, 1951 (No. 1 of 1951), shall not be brought after the expiration of two years from the date on which the cause of action accrued.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this amendment is to provide a period of two years for actions for contribution by a tortfeasor under Section 4 or 5 of the Tortfeasors Act, 1951.  Under Section 4 of the Act, any tortfeasor who has paid an amount in excess of that apportioned to him in the judgment may recover the excess from any other tortfeasor who has not paid his apportioned amount.  Where apportionment has not been made in the judgment, a tortfeasor who has paid on foot of the judgment may recover contribution from another tortfeasor liable in respect of the injury sustained by the original plaintiff.</P>
      <P>Actions for contribution arise under statute and, but for the provision now proposed, the actions could be taken up to six years from the judgment of the court, which would mean in some cases up to 12 years from the date the original cause of action giving rise to the subsequent proceedings accrued.  In the case of personal injuries the whole period would be nine years.  We think that two years extra from the date of the judgment is sufficient in the case of actions for contribution.  We have proposed in amendment No. 16, already carried, that the cause of action in contribution cases will be deemed to accrue on the date of the judgment for the original plaintiff who is injured.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 27:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (4) and substitute the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>( ) The following actions shall not be brought after the expiration of <Col N="1108" /> 12 years from the date on which the cause of action accrued:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a) an action upon an instrument under seal, other than an action upon an instrument under seal to recover&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i)  arrears or a rentcharge or a conventional rent, or</P>
    <P>(ii)  any principal sum of money secured by a mortgage or other charge, or</P>
    <P>(iii)  arrears of interest in respect of any sum of money secured by a mortgage or other charge, or</P>
    <P>(iv)  arrears of an annuity charged on personal property;</P>
    <P>(b) an action to enforce an award where the arbitration agreement is under seal;</P>
    <P>(c) an action to recover a debt created by sub-section (2) of Section 14 or Section 125 of the Companies (Consolidation) Act, 1908.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to hear something about this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy has the new amendment before him.  The matter is put in a clearer and more concise way.  This is a drafting amendment. We are putting sub-section (4) of Section 11 in a form which can be more easily read, thus helping people to grasp the actual proposals.  The proposed sub-section will apply the 12 year period to (1) actions under seal, other than actions in respect of rentcharges, etc., (2) actions to enforce an award where the arbitration agreement is under seal, and (3) actions to recover a debt created by sub-section (2) of Section 14 or Section 125 of the Companies (Consolidation) Act, 1908. Section 14 (2) of that Act provides that all money payable by any member under the memorandum or articles of association shall be a specialty debt due to the company; and Section 125 provides that the debt of every person liable to contribute to the assets of a company in the event of its being wound up shall also be a specialty debt.  For specialty debts (which at present comprise debts on instruments <Col N="1109" /> under seal and debts arising from a statute) the present period is 20 years. We are getting rid in the Bill of the expression &ldquo;specialty&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Actions in respect of rentcharges, conventional rents and mortgages are separately dealt with in the Bill and it will be immaterial whether or not there is an instrument under seal.  It will be seen that paragraph (a) (iv) of the proposed sub-section refers to arrears of an annuity charged on personal property.  Actions in respect of such arrears are dealt with in amendment No. 35.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 11, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>On the section there are two matters I should like to mention.  Sub-section (3) of Section 11 provides that:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;An action for an account shall not be brought in respect of any matter which arose more than six years before the commencement of the action.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I think I mentioned this before.  I certainly considered it on the Second Reading.  I am in the position that I feel the expression &ldquo;any matter which arose&rdquo; is particularly loose.  I am in the awkward position of not being able to suggest an alternative straight away.  It may be that it has already been judicially defined and decided but it does seem to me that to say that an action shall not be brought in respect of any matter which arose more than six years before the commencement of the action is not sufficiently precise.  I would suggest it might be considered between this and Report Stage.  Even by elaborating the sub-section it might be more precise.</P>
      <P>There is one other matter.  It is possibly a small point and possibly merely a drafting point.  Sub-section (5) provides:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;An action shall not be brought upon a judgment after the expiration of 12 years from the date on which the judgment became enforceable.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1110" /> I take it that there does not appear anywhere in the Bill any definition as to when a judgment becomes enforceable. I do not know of any reason why that should not be when the judgment is delivered.  The becoming enforceable of the judgment is the appropriate date, but again there seems to be some difficulty of ascertainment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 9 of the Mercantile Law Amendment Act, 1856, is replaced by Section 11 (3) of this Bill.  The phrase which is being questioned occurs in Section 9 of that Act which provides that &ldquo;no claim in respect of a matter which <i>arose</i> more than six years before the commencement of such action or suit shall be enforceable, etc.&rdquo;  I shall look into what the Deputy says and see if any change should be made.</P>
      <P>With regard to the judgment becoming enforceable, ordinarily speaking the normal thing would be that the judgment becomes enforceable when it is given; but sometimes judgments are made to become enforceable at a later date.  We want to cover that.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 12 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 13 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, I do not know how far the Minister would be prepared to go on this section.  It does seem to me that the 40 years' limitation on the recovery of land in favour of the State has not got any real basis or justification.  I appreciate there are certain specific matters, particularly in connection with the Land Commission and the registering of land, in which to force the State to act within 12 years will probably make them harsher landlords than they need necessarily be under the existing situation.  What I am concerned with is that there are certain other rights of the State, or certain claims of the State, which certainly should be enforced and could be enforced, if they are ever going to be enforced, <Col N="1111" /> within 12 years.  I would press for even a partial reduction in the 40-year period applicable to a certain number of State claims, not necessarily to them all, not so much for the purpose of freeing people from an actual claim but for the purpose of simplifying title.  It may be that in some subsequent legislation which, I think, has been foreshadowed, with regard to title, this matter will be dealt with; but, if it is not going to be dealt with in that way, it does seem to me that some effort to restrict to 12 years a number of State claims against land would greatly simplify transactions in title.  In other words, put them in the same position as an individual with regard to certain of their claims.  I appreciate one cannot make it widespread because it would be a hindrance rather than a help to the relationship between, say, the Land Commission and tenants of the Land Commission. I know that is an argument in favour of the longer period, and it is a sound one, but there are certain other claims which might be dealt with separately and the period brought down to 12 years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is asking that sub-section (1) of Section 13 should be broken up into the various types of action which may be brought by a State authority, and that we might have a shorter period for some?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 14 to 16, inclusive, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 17.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 28:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (3) (a), page 13, line 10, before &ldquo;rents&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;conventional&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is again on the point of the conventional rent and the rentcharge.  It is a drafting amendment in line with the other amendments designed to ensure that when we mean &ldquo;conventional rent&rdquo; we will say &ldquo;conventional rent&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1112" /> Section 17, as amended, put and agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 18.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 29:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (4) (a), page 13, line 47, to delete &ldquo;rent&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;rentcharge&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We can look at amendment Nos. 29 and 30 together. The first deals with the deletion of the word &ldquo;rent&rdquo; and the substitution of the word &ldquo;rentcharge&rdquo; and then we want to delete paragraph (b), sub-section (4) and substitute a new paragraph. The rent is a rentcharge the whole time in Section 18 (4) (a).  In sub-section (4) (b) it is a conventional rent.  The latter paragraph has been redrafted to clarify exactly what is meant and the reference to Section 17 (3) is being omitted as it might lead to some confusion.</P>
      <P>Sub-section (4) of Section 18 is an important sub-section in that it provides that, where a person is in possession of land subject to a rentcharge and does not pay the rentcharge he will be in adverse possession of the rentcharge, and may acquire a title to it after 12 years.  In other words, he will be able to obtain an estate in fee in the lands free from the rentcharge which will be wiped out.  It also provides that, where a person wrongfully claiming the land in reversion under an ordinary lease receives the conventional rent, he will be deemed to be in adverse possession of the land, and after 12 years may acquire a title to it. In the case of an ordinary lease the owner in fee is the lessor and the tenant has no estate in fee in the lands.  In the case of a rentcharge, the occupier has the estate in fee in the lands and the person who is entitled to the rentcharge has an estate in fee in the rentcharge.  I dealt with this subject earlier in discussing amendments Nos. 6 and 13.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The point is that, apart from having the distinction, if somebody is in adverse receipt of rent &mdash;I am referring now to amendment No. 30&mdash;he becomes entitled to it after <Col N="1113" /> a certain period has expired.  Is not that simply what it means?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>It debars the superior interest again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Putting it the other way round, yes.  He certainly bars the person who would otherwise be entitled to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>It works both ways.  He bars both the person ahead of him and his receipt of the rent is sufficient to be an adverse rent to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>He bars the person ahead and the receipt to him means he is entitled to the rent thereafter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>He is in adverse possession of the land.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 30:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (4), page 13, to delete paragraph (b) and substitute:</P>
      <P>(b) receipt of the conventional rent under a lease by a person wrongfully claiming to be entitled to the land in reversion immediately expectant on the determination of the lease shall be deemed to be adverse possession of the land.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 18, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>This section has more practical effect than some of those we have had already.  It will apply, first of all, to the most common adverse possession which we know, and that is successive people in registered land. In that respect, by reason of another amendment to a later section of the Bill, it is quite clear that more people will acquire farms in future by adverse possession than even heretofore.  As I read this section, it will have the effect that in the common case usually found where, say, one son of a registered owner, there being no grants of administration, no flow of legal title, remains on for a period as a bachelor and hands over informally, as he very often does, to one chosen nephew, who then continues on.  Now, as I understand <Col N="1114" /> the existing law, the position would be that you would have periods of adverse possession, one succeeding the other.</P>
      <P>If I understand this section correctly it would mean that if there was even a very small gap between the actual possession of the two parties concerned, and if there was no will or deed transferring an interest by the first possessor to the second possessor, you would probably break your adverse possession and you would recreate the registered owner's right. I do not know whether the Attorney-General would think I am right in that interpretation or whether there is any danger that that would happen.  It would be undesirable if there is.  The purpose of this Bill quite clearly is that where people have stayed away from land and have not taken an interest in it, they should be debarred after a reasonable period of 12 years.  I have a feeling that sub-section (3) may have the other effect, and may be recreating a registered owner in the person of the representative of a man long since deceased.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Look at Section 2 (3) of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, that would seem to cover most of it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 19 to 23, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 24.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 31:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 14, line 32, to delete &ldquo;Registration of Title Act, 1891&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Act of 1891&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment consequent on amendment No. 2.  Throughout the Bill, the Registration of Title Act, 1891, will be referred to as &ldquo;the Act of 1891&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 25.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 32:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (2).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1115" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a somewhat difficult matter.  The amendment itself is merely aimed at deleting the sub-section but other consequential deletions follow later.</P>
      <P>This sub-section was inserted <i>ex abundanti cautela.</i>  On reconsideration, we are satisfied that there is no need for it and the same applies to Section 26 (2), Section 32 (2) and Section 33 (2).  Sub-section (2) of Section 26 does not appear in the section proposed to be inserted (instead of Section 26) by amendment No. 34.  The deletion of Section 32 (2) and Section 33 (2) is proposed in amendments Nos. 40 and 43, respectively.</P>
      <P>Section 25 (2), as it stands, proposes to re-enact Section 25 of the Real Property Limitation Act, 1833, which put the previously existing law into statutory form.  An express trustee as long as he has the property in his possession can never acquire a title to it as against the beneficiary.  This was always the rule in equity.  After the Act of 1833 was passed, a certain difficulty arose in regard to the interpretation of Section 25 in relation to Sections 40 and 42 of the Act.  Section 40 provided for a limitation period of 20 years (now 12 years since the 1874 Act) to any action to recover a sum of money secured by a mortgage or otherwise charged on land or rent and Section 42 put a limitation period of six years to any distress action or suit for arrears of rent, or of interest in respect of any sum of money charged upon or payable out of any land or rent.</P>
      <P>There were two types of case.  In the first class of case, land was held by the trustee for the payment of an annuity or rent to the beneficiary and, as the trustee held the property, he could never plead the Statute against the beneficiary.  The second class of case arose where the rent or annuity was payable to the trustee for the beneficiary or the annuity was secured by a trust term, but where in each instance the land charged was in the possession of and vested in an owner who was in no sense an express trustee.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1116" /> The first class of case gave rise to no difficulty, as the trustee being in possession could not obtain a title as against the beneficiary.</P>
    <P>The second class of case did give rise to difficulty, and the courts eventually interpreted the 1833 Act as if Section 25 applied to it also, so that once there was a trust instrument it did not matter who was in possession of the property.  In Ireland it had been held in earlier cases that an annuity charged on land in the possession of a third party, or a legacy similarly charged, and in each case payable to a trustee for an annuitant or legatee, was within Section 40 or Section 42 of the 1833 Act, and that a period of limitation applied in actions against the third party.</P>
    <P>In England, a different view was taken and it was finally held that, once there was a trust instrument, it did not matter whether the trustee was in possession of the property or not in so far as beneficiary's rights were concerned. All cases were held to come within Section 25 of the 1833 Act and no limitation period was applicable. There was, I may say, strong adverse criticism of the decisions in England. Section 10 of the Act of 1874 was designed to remedy the position.  There was no reason why an annuitant who was essentially a creditor should, in respect of time, be given enormous advantages merely because the annuity was payable not to himself directly but to a trustee.</P>
    <P>Where the annuity was payable by the trustee and the trustee was in possession of the property the position was different.  Unfortunately, Section 10 of the 1874 Act, which was designed to remedy the decisions in regard to cases where the property was in the possession of a third party, was misinterpreted to such an extent that it was held in <i>Turner's Case</i> (1917) 1 Ch. that the effect of Section 10 of the 1874 Act was to allow a trustee to plead the Statute where he was in possession of the property.  The section is as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;After the commencement of this Act no action, suit or other proceeding shall be brought to recover any <Col N="1117" /> sum of money or legacy charged upon or payable out of any land or rent <i>and secured by an express trust</i>, or to recover any arrears of rent or of interest in respect of any sum of money or legacy so charged or payable and so secured, or any damages in respect of such arrears, except within the time within which the same would be recoverable if there were not any such trust.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>On first reading, the words <i>&ldquo;and secured by an express trust&rdquo;</i> would seem to have imported into the law the revolutionary principle that a trustee in possession could plead the Statute against a beneficiary, but a study of the background of the section shows clearly that such was not and could not have been the intention.  The words are &ldquo;secured by an express trust&rdquo; and not &ldquo;held on an express trust&rdquo;, and the section was designed to overrule the line followed in the cases I have referred to, where possession by a non-trustee was held to be the same as possession by a trustee for the purposes of the Statute.</P>
    <P>Section 10 of the 1874 Act was, therefore, a gloss on Section 25 of the 1833 Act and a very necessary gloss in view of the attitude of the courts in England.  Unfortunately the position was confused as far as Ireland was concerned by a provision in the Irish Judicature Act of 1877, which although passed after Section 10 of the 1874 Act came into operation before it.  Section 28 (2) of the Irish Act of 1877 provided (like Section 25 (2) of the English Judicature Act of 1873) that no claims of a <i>cestui que trust</i> against his trustee for any property held on an express trust, or in respect of any breach of such trust, should be held to be barred by any Statute of Limitations, but the sub-section went on to add words (not found in the English provision) as follows:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;This provision, however, is not to affect the enactments contained in the tenth section of the Real Property Limitation Act, 1874, when the same shall come into effect.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The draftsman of the Irish provision obviously misinterpreted completely <Col N="1118" /> the intention and effect of Section 10 of the 1874 Act unless he had in mind (which is very doubtful) that Section 10 did modify the law to the extent that, in the case of arrears of an annuity, the annuitant could not claim, as the possession of the trustee, a possession obtained by the trustee after the annuitant's claim to arrears had been barred.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Turner's Case</i> was overruled in a later case before the Court of Appeal in England.  This is <i>Jordison's Case</i> (1922) 1 Ch. referred to in the sidenotes to Section 26 (2), Section 32 (2) and Section 33 (2).  These sub-sections were designed to enact the law as laid down in <i>Jordison's Case</i> and to make the position what I have suggested it is, despite what might appear on the surface to be conflicting provisions in Section 10 of the Real Property Limitation Act, 1874, and Section 28 (2) of the Irish Judicature Act, 1877.  We are satisfied that the difficulties which Section 10 of the 1874 Act were intended to remove and which are discussed in <i>Jordison's Case</i> can no longer arise under the proposals in the Bill.</P>
    <P>If land is held by trustees to raise sums by way of portions or otherwise, the Statute will not run because of the provisions of Section 37 of the Bill excluding the application of any limitation period where the property is in the possession of the trustees.  If the property is held by persons who are not trustees, the fact that the portioner's rights are provided for in a trust will be immaterial and the Statute will run.  The portions will be sums charged on land in the latter case and the Statute will apply in the ordinary way.</P>
    <P>Section 28 (2) of the Irish Judicature Act, 1877, is being repealed in the Schedule to the Bill, as, of course, also are all the provisions of the Real Property Limitation Acts.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 25, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 26.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 33:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In page 15, before Section 26 (and <Col N="1119" /> before line 15), to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Actions to recover settled chattels.</i>
    </P>
    <P>( ) (1)  Where any chattels are held upon a trust, including a trust for sale, and the period fixed by this Act has expired for the bringing of an action to recover the chattels by the trustees, the title of the trustees shall not be extinguished if and so long as the right of action of any person beneficially entitled to the chattels either has not accrued or has not been barred by this Act, but if and when such right of action has been so barred, the title of the trustees shall be extinguished.</P>
    <P>(2)  When any chattels are held upon a trust, including a trust for sale, an action to recover the chattels may be brought by the trustees on behalf of any person beneficially entitled in possession to the chattels or in the proceeds of sale whose right of action has not been barred by this Act notwithstanding that the right of action of the trustees would apart from this provision have been barred by this Act.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is an amendment which involves the insertion of a new section.  The object of the amendment is to provide a section dealing with actions to recover settled chattels. Under Section 12 of the Bill, where the period of limitation for bringing an action for wrongful detention or conversion has expired, the title to the chattel will be extinguished, whereas, under existing law, only the right of action is barred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Sub-section (1) of the proposed new section provides that, where the period of limitation for bringing an action by the trustee against a stranger in possession of settled chattels has expired, the title of the trustee shall not be extinguished so long as the action of any beneficiary has not accrued or been barred.  The title of the trustee is being preserved by this sub-section in order that he may, under sub-section (2), recover the chattels on behalf of a beneficiary whose right of action has not been barred.  The <Col N="1120" /> operation of the provisions of Section 12 in regard to conversion of goods will, therefore, be suspended in the case of the conversion of a settled chattel so long as the right of action of any beneficiary either has not accrued or has not been barred, but it will only be suspended in so far as the title of that beneficiary is concerned.</P>
    <P>The proposed provisions in the new section are analogous to those for settled land, which are contained in Section 25, sub-sections (3) and (4).  On Report Stage we may have to amend Section 12 to provide that it is to be subject to the section to be inserted by this amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I ask a question with regard to the amendment?  It does seem to me that this proposed new section is somewhat similar to sub-sections (3) and (4) of Section 25.  Am I right in thinking that the title trustees could become barred, and that we are preserving it to allow them to sue for a subsequent beneficiary?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is the intention.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 34:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 15, before Section 26, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P Just="Center">
        <i>Actions to recover arrears of rentcharges, conventional rents, dower and annuities charged on personal property.</i>
      </P>
      <P>( ) (1)  No action shall be brought or distress made to recover arrears of a rentcharge or damages in respect thereof after the expiration of six years from the date on which the arrears became due.</P>
      <P>(2) In sub-section (1) of this section the word &ldquo;action&rdquo; does not include proceedings under Section 37 of the Land Act, 1927 (No. 19 of 1927).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment consequential on the deletion of Section 26 (2) which I mentioned in discussing amendment No. 32. We propose to divide up sub-section (1) of the existing Section 26 into two sub-sections <Col N="1121" /> and to delete sub-section (2). There is no need for sub-section (2) which, like Section 25 (2), Section 32 (2) and Section 33 (2), was inserted just in case any difficulty might arise.  We are satisfied that no difficulty will arise. The amendment involves the deletion of Section 26 of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 26 deleted.</P>
      <P>Sections 27 to 29, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 30.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 35:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 16, before Section 30 (and before line 4), to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) No action shall be brought to recover arrears of an annuity charged on personal property or damages in respect thereof after the expiration of six years from the date on which the arrears became due.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment proposes to provide a limitation period of six years in the case of actions to recover arrears of an annuity charged on personal property or damages in respect thereof.  Unpaid instalments of an annuity charged on personal property are not subject to any limitation period under existing law or under the Bill.  The annuity is not a principal sum charged on property and will not therefore fall within Section 32 (1) of the Bill. Neither is it a rentcharge, as a rentcharge is a periodic sum charged on land.  We think that annuities charged on personal property ought to be covered in the same way as principal sums charged on land or personal property and annuities charged on land are covered.  Difficulty often arose where an annuity was charged on a mixed fund of land and personal property.  I shall mention this matter later on.  Where personal property charged is in the hands of trustees, no question arises in the case of an annuity charged on the property as the trustees cannot plead the Statute.  Being trustees in possession, they will not be able to plead it under the Bill either.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1122" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 36:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 16, before Section 30, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) (1)  No action shall be brought by a State authority claiming the sale of land which is subject to a mortgage or charge after the expiration of 40 years from the date on which the right of action accrued to a State authority or, if it first accrued to some person through whom a State authority claims, to that person.</P>
      <P>(2) The following provisions shall apply to an action by a person (other than a State authority) claiming the sale of land which is subject to a mortgage or charge:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) subject to paragraph (b) of this sub-section, no such action shall be brought after the expiration of 12 years from the date on which the right of action accrued to the person bringing it, or, if it first accrued to some person through whom he claims, to that person;</P>
      <P>(b)  if the right of action first accrued to a State authority, the action may be brought at any time before the expiration of the period during which the action could have been brought by a State authority, or of 12 years from the date on which the right of action accrued to some person other than a State authority, whichever period first expires.</P>
      <P>(3) Subject to Section 52 of the Act of 1891, at the expiration of the period fixed by sub-section (1) or (2) of this section for a mortgagee to bring an action claiming the sale of the mortgaged land, the title of the mortgagee to the land shall be extinguished.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this amendment is to provide specifically for actions by a mortgagee claiming the sale of land.  It is proposed to provide the same period&mdash;12 years, and 40 years in the case of a State authority&mdash;as in the case of actions to recover land, whether by a mortgagee or not.  I have dealt in detail with the <Col N="1123" /> actions that a mortgagee may take in discussing amendments Nos. 3 and 5. As I have explained foreclosure is unknown in this country.  An action by a mortgagee claiming sale will, we propose, no longer be an action to recover money charged on land.  It will be action on its own specifically provided for by this amendment.</P>
      <P>Under sub-section (3) of the new section, we propose that once the action is barred the right as well as the remedy will be barred.  In other words, the title of the mortgagee to land will be extinguished and the effect will be the same as in the case of an action to recover land under Section 24 of the Bill.  Both a mortgagee and a chargeant may bring an action claiming sale, but only a chargeant of registered land may recover the land.  A chargeant has no estate in the lands and the registered chargeant's powers of recovering the land exist only by reason of the special provisions of Section 13 of the Registration of Title Act, 1942, to which I referred in dealing with amendment No. 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister would consider on this question, the point I made on Section 11 regarding State authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We will certainly consider the Deputy's point.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 37:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 16, before section 30, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) Where the right of a mortgagee of land to bring an action to recover the mortgaged land is barred by this Act or the right of action of a person claiming as mortgagee or chargeant the sale of land is barred by this Act, the right of the mortgagee or chargeant to the principal sum and interest secured by the mortgage or charge shall be extinguished.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this section is to provide that where the <Col N="1124" /> right of action of a mortgagee claiming recovery of the land or sale is barred, his right to the principal sum and interest secured by the mortgagee should be extinguished.  This means that once the real remedy is barred the personal remedy will also be barred.  Barring the real remedy means extinguishing the title to the land under Section 24 of the Bill and the previous amendment.  We also want to ensure that barring the personal remedy will also extinguish the right in this type of case. This is the law at present, where a period of 20 years is the period in the case of a covenant under seal and 12 years in the case of an action to recover land or money charged thereon.  The period will be the same in both cases under the Bill, but the question of whether the personal remedy could subsist where an acknowledgement was made after the period of limitation had expired could still arise.  We think that an acknowledgement in such a case should have no effect and that once the remedy against the property is barred the personal remedy against the debtor should also be barred.  The existing law on the subject is clear from the judgment of the Supreme Court delivered by Murnaghan J. in <i>In re Huggard's Estate</i> (1930) I.R.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The material words of sect. 42 of 3 and 4 Will. 4, c. 27 (the Real Property Limitation Act, 1833), are: &lsquo;No arrears of rent or of interest in respect of any sum of money charged upon or payable out of any land or rent, or in respect of any legacy, or any damages in respect of any such arrears of rent or interest, shall be recovered by any distress, action, or suit, but within six years next after the same respectively shall have become due.&rsquo;  The respondent contends that the limitation imposed by this section is applicable, and that it is not possible to treat the charge as a mere charge upon personalty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;In <i>Henry v. Smith</i> at p. 390, Sugden L.C. gave his opinion as to the construction of this very section. He was dealing with judgments, which at that time created an encumbrance upon real estate, and were also available against the personal estate. He <Col N="1125" /> says: &lsquo;It was said that if judgment creditors are held to be included in this section, they still will be able to proceed against the personal estate of their debtor for the full arrears of interest.  I admit no such consequence. The two clauses (he refers to sects. 40 and 42) relate to money secured upon land, and to the interest of money so secured; and when the Act of Parliament says no action shall be maintained after a given number of years for the recovery of such sum or such interest, how can a man after that period bring any action in respect of his debt?  If the action is brought so as to charge the personal estate, the answer is obvious: &ldquo;You have brought your action in respect of a sum of money charged upon or payable out of real estate, you are therefore within the terms of the Act, and consequently your right is barred.&rdquo;  The personal estate may be an additional security to such a creditor, but however numerous his securities they could not carry his right farther; if his remedy under the real security is gone, it is also barred in respect of all the other securities.&rsquo;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;In <i>Sutton v. Sutton</i> the question arose before the Court of Appeal in England whether the words in sect. 8 of the Real Property Limitation Act, 1874 (replacing sect. 40 of 3 and 4 Will. 4, c. 27), and which limited the remedy against the land to 12 years, were intended to apply also to the personal remedy in the covenant contained in a mortgage. The Court of Appeal in England held that it did, and that the section could not be read as applying only to the recovery of the mortgage debt out of the lands.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;We are of opinion that the interpretation placed by Sugden L.C. on sect. 42 is the correct one.  A sum of money charged on land, and also on personal estate, is a sum of money charged upon or payable out of land.  No arrears of interest in respect of it are to be recovered by any distress, action, or suit.  The section does not say it is to be recovered out of the land charged, <Col N="1126" /> and it is impossible to make any such limitation harmonise with the words of the section itself.  The principle stated by Sugden L.C. is in reality that underlying the decision in <i>Sutton v. Sutton</i> which has moulded the rules dealing with mortgages for 50 years.  In some judicial minds there may be a tendency to limit any further extension of the decision.  We can, however, find nothing which would justify us in departing from the decision given by Sugden L.C. and the Court of Appeal in England.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>We may decide to propose the amendment of the proposed new section on Report Stage so as to apply its provisions to a principal sum charged on personal property.  This is being considered.</P>
    <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 30 deleted.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps it might help the Attorney-General if I say in regard to these drafting and consequential amendments that it is appreciated this Bill must be almost one of a pattern once we have decided the general framework of it.  The only things we are interested in at this stage are the actual substantive changes from the Second Stage.  It is quite obvious that in the case of a Bill like this, the rest must be left to the draftsman.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 31.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 38:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 16, before Section 31, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) (a)  Where a mortgagee of land has been in possession of any of the mortgaged land for a period of 12 years, no action to redeem the land of which the mortgagee has been so in possession shall thereafter be brought by the mortgagor or any person claiming through him.</P>
      <P>(b)  Paragraph (a) of this sub-section does not apply in respect of a Welsh mortgage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(2)  Where a mortgage of land under a Welsh mortgage which provides that the rents are to be applied <Col N="1127" /> in reduction of the principal moneys and interest has been in possession of the land for a period of 12 years commencing on the date on which all the principal moneys and interest have been satisfied, no action to redeem the land shall thereafter be brought by the mortgagor or any person claiming through him.</P>
    <P>(3)  Subject to Section 52 of the Act of 1891, at the expiration of the period fixed in that behalf by sub-section (1) or (2) (whichever is applicable) of this section for any person to bring an action to redeem land, the title of that person to the land shall be extinguished.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The section contained in this amendment is in substitution for Section 31 of the Bill.  We propose to cover what is called a Welsh mortgage.  This is a type of mortgage which arises where the mortgagee goes into possession of the land and recovers his debt and/or the interest thereon out of the rents and profits. Once the debt <i>and</i> interest have been paid off it is up to the mortgagor to redeem his land.  If he does not do so the mortgagee is in adverse possession and we propose to provide that after 12 years he will be entitled to the land. A Welsh mortgagee has no estate in fee in the lands as an ordinary mortgagee has, and he acquires no title. Welsh mortgages were common at one time in this country.</P>
      <P>The proposed section simply puts into statutory form the law as laid down by the courts in the cases cited in the sidenote.  By the way, the reference to <i>Fenton v. Walsh</i> should read &ldquo;(1909) 43 I.L.T.R. 54&rdquo; and not &ldquo;(1908) 42 I.L.T.R. 54&rdquo;.  A drafting amendment may be necessary to ensure that &ldquo;rents&rdquo; includes &ldquo;profits.&rdquo; It is to be noted that we are only dealing with one type of Welsh mortgage, namely the one where the mortgagee in possession recovers the principal <i>and</i> the interest out of the rents and profits.  In a Welsh mortgage where only the interest is recovered and the principal remains outstanding, the Statute can never apply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1128" /> Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 31 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 32.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 39:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1) (b), page 16, before sub-paragraph (ii), to insert the following new sub-paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(ii) a charge on land under Section 31 of the Land Law (Ireland) Act, 1881, or.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this amendment is to cover charges on land arising under Section 31 of the Land Law (Ireland) Act, 1881.  These are charges to cover sums advanced by the Office of Public Works for the reclamation of land, drainage, building cottages, or any other works of agricultural improvement.  In line with the other provisions governing State authorities in the Bill the period of limitation is to be 40 years.  The Office of Public Works in the case of these advances will be in the position of an ordinary chargeant except that the limitation period will be longer.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 40:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (2).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already dealt with this.  There is no need for the sub-section.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 41:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (3), page 16, line 40, before &ldquo;sum&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;principal&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment designed to make &ldquo;sum of money&rdquo; read &ldquo;principal sum of money&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 32, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 33.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 42:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (2).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1129" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is governed by the earlier discussion.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 33, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 34 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 35.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 43:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (3).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We propose to delete sub-section (3) which deals with executors and administrators.  We will deal with these separately in amendment No. 45; and as I explained, in discussing amendment No. 14, it is proposed to adopt a different policy in respect of personal representatives. Section 35, without sub-section (3), will now only deal with express trustees.  The Statute will apply to them, except, of course, where they are in possession of the property or guilty of fraud.  That is the existing law as contained in the Trustee Act, 1888.  The provisions in regard to possession of the property and fraud will be found in Section 37 of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 35, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 36 deleted.</P>
      <P>Section 37 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 38.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 44:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 18, before Section 38, but in Part II, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P Just="Center">
        <i>Actions in respect of the estates of deceased persons.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>( ) (1)  Subject to Section * of this Act, no action in respect of any claim to the personal estate of a deceased person or to any share or interest in such estate, whether under a will or on intestacy, shall be brought after the expiration of 12 years from the date when the <Col N="1130" /> right to receive the share or interest accrued.</P>
    <P>(2) Subject to Section * of this Act, no action to recover arrears of interest in respect of any legacy or damages in respect of such arrears shall be brought after the expiration of six years from the date on which the interest became due.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>This takes the place of Section 36?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are simply putting Section 36 in a different place in the Bill.  It will now come after Section 37 and before the new section proposed in amendment No. 45.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment No. 44 is a new section going in to replace Section No. 36.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Attorney-General say what is the period of limitation in the case of intestacy?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>Twelve years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The following section refers to the section which will be the following section, to qualify.  I think the scheme is all right.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 45:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 18, before Section 38, but in Part II, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) No period of limitation fixed by this Act shall apply to an action against a personal representative or any person claiming through him where the claim is founded on any fraud to which the personal representative was party or privy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment is designed to provide that no personal representative may plead the Statute where the claim against him is founded on fraud to <Col N="1131" /> which he was a party.  He will be able to plead the Statute in all other cases, because by reason of amendment No. 14 he will not be a trustee except where he is specifically created a trustee in the will.  We do not think that a personal representative guilty of fraud should be allowed to plead the Statute at all.  This amendment and the previous one will cover the point raised by Deputy Finlay as to the conflict between Section 36 and Section 37.  Section 37 will not apply to personal representatives and the new section replacing Section 36, and provided for in amendment No. 44, will be subject to the section contained in the present amendment.  In other words, actions to recover the estate of deceased persons will have a limitation period attached to them unless the personal representative is guilty of fraud.  Personal representatives will, of course, include personal representatives under Part IV of the Registration of Title Act, 1891, by reason of amendment No. 14 and we are overruling <i>In re Loughlin</i>, to which I referred in discussing that amendment.  Whether a personal representative is a representative in regard to registered freeholds, leaseholds and any other type of property, real or personal, he will be able to establish title.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 46:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In paragraph (a), page 18, before line 25, to insert&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) &ldquo;debt&rdquo; includes any liquidated pecuniary claim;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;statute-barred debt&rdquo; means a debt in respect of which the period fixed by this Act for the bringing of an action to recover it has expired.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 46, 47 and 48 go together.  These are all drafting amendments.  We are putting in the word &ldquo;debt&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;liquidated pecuniary claim&rdquo;; and the word &ldquo;claim&rdquo; is being taken out and we are substituting &ldquo;debt&rdquo; in another case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1132" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>That is much neater.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 47:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In paragraph (a) (ii), page 18, line 33, to delete &ldquo;liquidated pecuniary claim&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;debt&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 48:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In paragraph (a) (ii), page 18, line 35, to delete &ldquo;claim&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;debt&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 49:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-paragraph (iv) of paragraph (c) and substitute the following sub-paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(iv) in the case of an action to recover arrears of a rentcharge, a conventional rent, dower or interest or damages in respect thereof&mdash;be construed as references to the date on which the arrears became due.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 49 and 50 go together.  These are again drafting amendments.  We want to preserve throughout the Bill the distinction between a rentcharge and a conventional rent and to say which we mean in each case.  If we refer to both, we propose to specify both.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 50:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In paragraph (d) (i), page 19, line 15, to substitute &ldquo;rentcharge&rdquo; for &ldquo;rent&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 51:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add to the section the following new paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) reference to a debt&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1133" /> (i)  shall, in the case of a rentcharge or of a conventional rent, be construed as references to a gale of the rentcharge or of the conventional rent,</P>
    <P>(ii)  shall, in the case of interest, be constructed as references to an instalment of the interest.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment proposes to add to the section a new paragraph.  It is again a drafting amendment.  We want to provide that references to a debt shall for the purposes of this Part of the Act include references to a gale of a rentcharge or of a conventional rent or to an instalment of interest.  This will specifically apply the provisions as to acknowledgment and part-payment to gales of rentcharges and conventional rents and to instalments of interest.  Under the existing law, instalments of rent-charges, conventional rents and interest do not specifically come within the provisions of the law as to part-payment.</P>
      <P>Section 42 of the Real Property Limitations Act, 1833, which deals with the limitation period for arrears of rent and interest makes no provision for part-payment, though it does provide for acknowledgment.  This means that part-payment of an instalment of interest or of a rentcharge or of a conventional rent would not prevent the operation of the Statute as to the balance, unless, in the case of interest, there was a contract under seal and unless, in the case of a conventional rent, the rent was held to involve a simple contract debt and the part-payment amounted to a promise in writing to pay the remainder.  When the Bill was being drafted it was decided to leave the law as it was, and this was the object of sub-sections (2) and (3) of Section 53.  On going into the matter more fully, we are satisfied that the existing law is not sound in principle and ought to be changed.  This we propose to do in the present amendment coupled with amendments Nos. 71 and 72.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I think I ought to mention that each instalment, whether of a rentcharge, conventional rent or interest, is a separate debt and part-payment will <Col N="1134" /> apply only in respect of the remainder of the instalment due.  Part-payment of one debt does not involve part-payment of another; and the same is true for acknowledgment.  An acknowledgment by a person that he did not &ldquo;pay the rent&rdquo; on the last gale day is certainly not an acknowledgment that he did not pay it three gale days ago, and it would be little short of grotesque to treat it as such.  The same applies to an instalment of a rentcharge.  Similarly, an acknowledgment by a person that he failed to pay a gale of a conventional rent or of a rentcharge cannot be said to be an acknowledgment that his predecessor had failed to pay a previous instalment.  I am speaking of acknowledgment of the actual debt in question.  Acknowledgment of title to the rentcharge is a different matter. A gale of a rentcharge is not the rentcharge itself.  The rentcharge is a charge on the lands and the payments due on each gale day are the fruits of that charge.  A rentcharge is an incorporeal hereditament and the owner of it has an estate of inheritance in it. He can enforce his rights against the lands and he can have the court declare that the rentcharge is properly attached to the lands.</P>
    <P>I have gone into this matter at some length in order that there may not be any confusion as to what it proposed in the Bill and to show the clear distinction between a rentcharge as a right over land and a rentcharge (i.e. the gale of a rentcharge), as an ordinary debt arising out of that right. The distinction is maintained in the Bill.  For instance, for the purpose of the recovery of land, land includes a rentcharge, because there what is meant is the estate in or the title to the rentcharge.  In the case of the recovery of debts, rentcharge must of course mean a gale of the rentcharge, which is a debt involving a liquidated sum.  Where there are a number of gales of a rentcharge or conventional rent due, the question of the appropriation of part-payments not made in respect of any gale arises, and we propose to deal with this question in amendment No. 78.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Col N="1135" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 52:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add to the section the following paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;( ) references to a mortgagee who is by virtue of the mortgage in possession of any mortgaged land shall include references to a mortgagee who has obtained possession of the mortgaged land by virtue of an order of a court;&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is to ensure that the provisions in the Bill as to acknowledgment and part-payment will cover the case of a mortgagee in possession by order of the court.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 38, as amended, stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>The same point arises here as I made before.  Although I appreciate, as the Attorney-General has told me, that this expression, &ldquo;the date on which the matter arose&rdquo; has been enshrined before, it does seem to me, when we are revising statutes, that we might be able to tie it down more exactly with regard to the right of action in account.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The phrase the Deputy is speaking of is also in Section 11 (3).  We shall look into the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 39 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 40.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 53:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1) (e), page 20, line eight, to delete &ldquo;thereof&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;of penalty or forfeiture, recoverable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendments Nos. 53 and 54 go together.  Sub-section (1) of Section 40 provides for the extension of the limitation period in the case of disability, but we want to provide that this extension is not to occur in the <Col N="1136" /> case of actions for a penalty or forfeiture unless the action is brought by the party who suffers damage.  Actions to recover penalties or forfeitures are dealt with in Section 11 (6) of the Bill, and the period of limitation is to be two years.  The only field of operation of this sub-section is the action by the common informer.  Penalties or forfeitures recoverable by the Revenue Commissioners are excluded from the Bill by Section 3 (2) and so are ordinary criminal proceedings by reason of the definition of &ldquo;action,&rdquo; Section 2 (1).  Further, Section 11 (6) (a) provides that a &ldquo;penalty&rdquo; does not include a fine to which any person is liable on conviction of a criminal offence.</P>
      <P>We think it only reasonable that, where a common informer does not suffer from the act in question, the disability rule should not apply.  When a suitable opportunity arises we hope to rid our law completely of the common informer.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 54:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1) (e), page 20, line ten, to delete &ldquo;an aggrieved person&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;the party grieved&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 55:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2), page 20, before paragraph (b), to insert the following new paragraph:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) For the purposes of paragraph (a) of this sub-section, &ldquo;parent&rdquo; in relation to a person under a disability means his father, mother, grandfather, grandmother, stepfather or stepmother, notwithstanding that the relationship is illegitimate or in consequence of adoption under the Adoption Act, 1952 (No. 25 of 1952).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.  We are simply putting paragraph (c) of sub-section (2) after paragraph (a) where it more logically belongs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1137" />
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Attorney-General explain the effect of giving the definition &ldquo;grandfather&rdquo; or &ldquo;grandmother&rdquo; to a &ldquo;parent&rdquo; in relation to sub-section (2) (a) of Section 40?  Does it mean that if a person is under a disability and is in the custody of a grandparent, disability will not arise?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, in the case of personal injuries actions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the effect of that going to be that a person who will be in the custody of a grandparent will be excluded from this section for certain actions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It means that; yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I wonder is that a wise decision to take?  It is only a doubt I have.  I have no objection to. Section 40 (2) (a) but I would like the Attorney-General to look at the effect of this amendment.  There does seem to be some reason for this provision when the child is in the custody of its parents but it is conceivable that there might be some question of hardship arising if the custody of a grandfather or grandmother is to be the custody of the parent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall consider the Deputy's point.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 56 which is consequential on amendment No. 25:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2), page 20, to delete paragraphs (b) and (c) and substitute the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) In the case of actions for damages for slander, sub-section (1) of this section shall have effect as if for the words &ldquo;six years&rdquo; there were substituted the words &ldquo;three years&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 57:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To add to the section the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1138" /> ( ) In the case of&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a) an action to recover an amount recoverable by a tort-feasor under Section 4 or 5 of the Tortfeasors Act, 1951 (No. 1 of 1951), or</P>
    <P>(b)  an action to recover a penalty or forfeiture, or a sum by way of penalty or forfeiture, recoverable by virtue of any enactment where the action is brought by the party grieved,</P>
    <P>sub-section (1) of this section shall have effect as if for the words &ldquo;six years&rdquo; there were substituted the words &ldquo;two years&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a contribution matter again.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 40, as amended, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 41 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 42.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 58:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), page 20, lines 46 and 47, to delete &ldquo;(other than a foreclosure action)&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We propose to delete all references to foreclosure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>It is automatic.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 42, as amended, put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 43.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 59:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 21, before Section 43, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) Where&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  the right of a mortgagee of land to bring an action to recover the mortgaged land has accrued, and</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(b)  the person by whom the mortgage debt is payable acknowledges the right to the debt, <Col N="1139" /> the right of action shall be deemed to have accrued on and not before the date of the acknowledgment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.  We want to cover specifically the case where the mortgagee brings an action to obtain possession of the land and the mortgagor acknowledges the debt.  As I mentioned in dealing with amendment No. 3, it is desirable to have definite provisions in the Bill in regard to the various actions which can be taken by a mortgagee.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 60:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 21, before Section 43, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) Where&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  the right of an incumbrancer of land to bring an action claiming sale of the land has accrued, and</P>
      <P>(b)  the person by whom the debt secured by the incumbrance is payable acknowledges the right to the debt,</P>
      <P>the right shall be deemed to have accrued on and not before the date of the acknowledgment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This section is designed to cover the case of an incumbrancer who claims sale of the land. &ldquo;Incumbrancer&rdquo; includes a mortgagee, a registered chargeant and an ordinary chargeant.  Where an ordinary charge is under seal, the chargeant has the power of sale given to a mortgagee by the Conveyancing Act, 1881, where the mortgage instrument is under seal. Under Section 40 of the Registration of Title Act, 1891, the instrument of charge in the case of a registered charge has the same effect as a deed of mortgage.  The power of sale is, of course, different from the right to possession.  It is only where there is a conveyance of title that a right to possession arises, though there is an exception to this provided for in the case of a registered chargeant under Section 13 of the Registration of Title <Col N="1140" /> Act, 1942.  As I have explained in dealing with a previous amendment, a registered chargeant can obtain possession from the court by applying in a summary manner.  He is, however, not entitled as of right to possession in the same way as a legal mortgagee is, and the court acts under Section 13 of the 1942 Act only if it so thinks proper. An equitable mortgage arising, for instance, by deposit of title deeds does not give a right to possession, nor does it give a right to sale.  Rights to possession and sale are important questions in the case of all mortgages and charges as will be seen from the decision of the Supreme Court in <i>Bank of Ireland v. Feeney</i> (1930) I.R. where it was held that there was no right to possession although the instrument, which created an equitable charge, contained a covenant by the borrower declaring himself a trustee of the holding for the lender.</P>
      <P>Acknowledgment in the case of an action for possession is covered by Section 42 of the Bill.  As regards an action for sale, it is proposed to cover it by the new section contained in this amendment.</P>
      <P>Acceptance of this amendment involves the deletion of Section 43 of the Bill which purports to refer to foreclosure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>It means the section goes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CormacBreslin" hpid="An Leas-Cheann Comhairle Cormac Breslin">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Cheann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Section 43 is deleted.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 43 deleted.</P>
      <P>Section 44 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 45.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 61:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In paragraph (a), page 21, lines 17 and 18, to delete &ldquo;or other liquidated pecuniary claim&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The two amendments, Nos. 61 and 62, go together.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 62:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1141" /> In paragraph (b), page 21, line 19, to delete &ldquo;claim&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;debt&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <P>Section 45, as amended agreed to.</P>
    <P>Sections 46 and 47 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 48.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 63:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), page 21, lines 37 and 38, to delete &ldquo;or mortgaged personal property&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to delete the words &ldquo;or mortgaged personal property&rdquo; from Section 48, which deals with the effect of acknowledgment on persons other than the maker.  The section cannot apply to mortgaged personalty in the possession of the mortgagor, because the action of foreclosure does not lie in Ireland.  If the property is in the possession of the mortgagee, acknowledgment does not arise because we are not proposing to provide for any statutory period for the right to redeem a mortgage of personalty.  We are doing this deliberately because of the practical difficulties involved.  For instance, where a customer of a bank charges securities in favour of the bank to secure an overdraft, the securities would be lodged in the bank and an equitable mortgage created and they would, in a lot of cases, remain charged indefinitely to cover advances from time to time.  Unless the bank acknowledged the title of the customer, the effect of a period of limitation would be to extinguish the right to redeem.  It is because of this that Section 31 of the Bill covering the limitation of redemption actions refers only to land.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A mortgagee of land entitled to possession does not as a rule take possession of the land, except in order to enforce the mortgage debt.  A mortgagee of personalty, however, would normally have possession of the mortgaged property from the beginning as possession by him would be inherent in the transaction.  We have made special provision for charges on future interests and insurance policies <Col N="1142" /> in Sections 32 (3) and 33 (3) so that where a sum is charged on, say, an insurance policy the period of limitation will not begin to run until the policy matures.  Otherwise, the mortgagee (not in possession) might be forced to have the policy realised before it matured in order to obtain his money.  In most cases he would prefer to have the policy kept alive; and this is, generally, what the parties contemplate.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 64:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (3), page 22, and substitute the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) Where there are two or more mortgagors of land, and the title or right to redemption of one of the mortgagors is acknowledged, the acknowledgment shall be deemed to have been made to all the mortgagors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment consequential on amendment No. 63.  We want to make it clear that Section 48 (3) applies only to mortgages of land.  Acknowledgment of title would not arise in the case of personalty.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 65:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (4) (a), page 22, lines 23 and 24, to delete &ldquo;or other liquidated pecuniary claim&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 66:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (4) (b), page 22, to delete all words from &ldquo;An&rdquo; in line 26 down to and including &ldquo;any&rdquo; in line 28, and substitute&mdash;</P>
      <P>An acknowledgment of a statute-barred debt shall not bind any.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 48, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 49 and 50 agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1143" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 67:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 22, before Section 51, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) Where&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  the right of a mortgagee of land to bring an action to recover the land has accrued, and</P>
      <P>(b)  the person in possession of the land or the person liable for the mortgage debt makes any payment in respect thereof, whether of principal or interest,</P>
      <P>the right shall be deemed to have accrued on and not before the date of payment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment Nos. 67 and 68 go together and deal, respectively, with part-payment in the case of a mortgagee's action to recover land and with part-payment in the case of the right of an incumbrancer of land to bring an action claiming sale of the land.  I have dealt with those two types of action already in discussing amendments Nos. 3, 36, 37, 59 and 60. We propose to make specific provisions for part-payment in the two cases similar to those proposed in respect of acknowledgment in amendments Nos. 59 and 60.</P>
      <P>Acceptance of amendment No. 68 involves the deletion of Section 51 of the Bill referring to foreclosure actions.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 68:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 22, Section 51, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) Where&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  the right of an incumbrancer of land to bring an action claiming sale of the land has accrued, and</P>
      <P>(b)  the person in possession of the land or the person liable for the debt secured by the incumbrance makes any payment in respect thereof, whether of principal or interest,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>the right shall be deemed to have <Col N="1144" /> accrued on and not before the date of payment.</P>
    <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>Acceptance of this amendment means that Section 51 is deleted.</P>
      <P>Section 51 deleted.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 52.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 69:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete paragraph (b), page 23, and substitute&mdash;</P>
      <P>(b) the mortgagee receives any payment from the mortgagor in respect of the principal or interest of the mortgage debt,.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a drafting amendment.  The new wording puts the matter in a more logical way.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 52, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 53.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 70:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1) (a), page 23, lines 10 and 11, to delete &ldquo;or other liquidated pecuniary claim&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, this is a drafting amendment, consequential on amendment No. 46.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 71:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (2).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I referred to this earlier when speaking on amendment No. 51.  We think that part payment should apply to a sale of conventional rent and to a sale of a rentcharge.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 72:&mdash;</P>
      <P>To delete sub-section (3), page 23, and substitute the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(3) Payment of interest in whole or in part shall for the purposes of this <Col N="1145" /> Chapter be treated as a payment in respect of the principal debt.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment has a twofold object.  First of all, we want to overrule the existing law that part-payment of an instalment of interest does not extend the period for claiming the remainder of the instalment.  I have explained the reasons for our view in discussing amendment No. 51. Secondly, we want to correct a <i>casus omissus</i> in the second branch of Section 53 (3) as at present drafted. The effect of the sub-section in the Bill is to provide that a part-payment of a gale of interest is to be treated as a payment in respect of the principal debt, that is for the purpose of keeping the principal debt alive.  Nothing is said as to the effect of the payment of a full gale of an instalment of interest in keeping the principal debt alive, and we want to provide for this case also.</P>
      <P>The sub-section as now drafted in the amendment will, it is hoped, achieve what we have in mind.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 53, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 54 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 55</P>
      <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That Section 55 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>May I make a suggestion purely from the point of view of making the section clearer?  Instead of stating, as we see in this section,</P>
      <P>&ldquo;A payment&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  may be made by the agent of the person specified in that behalf in Section 51, 52, 53 or 54 (whichever is applicable) of this Act;...&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Perhaps the Minister would consider bringing in an amendment specifying the persons instead of the sections?  My remarks also apply to Section 47 which states:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(1) Every acknowledgment shall be in writing and signed by the person making the acknowledgment.</P>
      <P>(2) An acknowledgment&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(a) may be made by the agent of <Col N="1146" /> the person specified in that behalf in Section 42, 43, 44, 45 or 46 (whichever is applicable) of this Act, and....&rdquo;</P>
    <P>It is purely from the point of view of practitioners and persons who have to deal with this Act that I make this suggestion. It might be clearer if, in the drafting, the names of persons were specified rather than a reference to the sections.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall certainly have a look at these provisions again.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 56.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 73:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), page 23, lines 38 and 39, to delete &ldquo;foreclose or otherwise&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 74:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 23, before sub-section (2), to insert the following sub-section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( )  Where&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a) two or more mortgagees of land are by virtue of the mortgage in possession of the land, and</P>
      <P>(b)  one only of the mortgagees (in this sub-section referred to as the recipient) receives any payment in respect of the principal or interest of the mortgage debt,</P>
      <P>the following provisions shall have effect:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(i)  the payment shall bind only the recipient and his successors and shall not bind any other mortgagee or his successors;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(ii)  if the recipient is entitled to a part of the mortgaged land and not to any ascertained part of the mortgaged debt, the mortgagor shall be entitled to redeem that part of the land on payment, with interest, of the part of the mortgage debt which, immediately before the recipient received the payment, referred to in paragraph (b) of this sub-section, <Col N="1147" /> bore the same proportion to the whole of the debt as the value of that part of the land bears to the whole of the land, less the amount of the payment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a rather confusing matter here.  The object of this amendment is to cover the case where two or more mortgagees are in possession of land and one only receives a part-payment in respect of the mortgage debt.  It is proposed that the payment shall bind only the mortgagee recipient and his successors. It is also proposed that, where the recipient is entitled to a part of the mortgaged land, but not to any ascertained part of the mortgage debt, the mortgagor will be entitled to redeem that part of the land if he pays so much of the mortgage debt as bears the same proportion to the whole of the debt as the value of that part of the land bears to the whole of the mortgaged land, less the part-payment. An example will, perhaps, illustrate the effect of what is proposed in (b) (<i>ii</i>) of the sub-section in the amendment. If there are two mortgagees, X and Y, in the possession of land worth £2,400 in respect of a mortgage debt of £1,200, and if Y is entitled to part of the land worth £800 but is not entitled to any particular portion of the £2,400, the following will be the position if A (the mortgagor) makes a part-payment of £150 to Y:&mdash; A will be entitled to redeem Y's part of the land if he pays Y (whose land is worth one third of the whole land) one third of the debt or £400, less £150 which he has part paid.  In other words, he will be able to redeem Y's land if he pays Y £250.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The proposed sub-section will correspond to Section 48 (2), which deals with acknowledgment where there are two or more mortgagees and one only acknowledges the mortgagor's title or his equity of redemption.  The existing provision of the law is to be found in Section 7 of the Real Property Limitation Act, 1874 (replacing Section 28 of the Real Property Limitation Act, 1833), but the provision only covers acknowledgment.  We think that part-payment should be covered <Col N="1148" /> as well, as a mortgagee in possession who receives a part-payment should be in the same position in all cases as if he made an acknowledgment, that is so far as the mortgagor's equity of redemption is concerned.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>I can understand well enough the system provided for by the sub-section.  It seems to work out fairly.  However, it quite escapes me what justification there is for the whole sub-section.  Whatever the state of the law may have been before the sub-section, I cannot see why, where two mortagees were in possession and where payments were made to one of them, the other could still get title against the mortgagor.  Presumably the section is likely to apply in the case of a Welsh mortgage or something similar.  It may be that there is a very sound reason for all this, but I cannot see it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Deputy Finlay's remarks.  Mortgagees in possession are not very common.  At the same time, we have to legislate for such a contingency.  If a person makes a payment to one of two mortgagees, it seems to me that he presumes it would be a valid payment and would, in fact, stop the statute running against both mortgagees.  I should like the Minister to consider this question again, in the light of what could happen in everyday life.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The word &ldquo;receives&rdquo; gives point to that argument and the Minister might look into the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>We shall.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 75:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 23, before sub-section (2), to insert the following new sub-section:&mdash;</P>
      <P>( ) Where there are two or more mortgagors of land, and the mortgagee, being in possession of the land, is paid any sum in respect of the principal or interest of the mortgage debt by one of the mortgagors, the payment shall be deemed to have been made by all the mortgagors.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1149" />
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>The object of this amendment is to provide that where one or more of two mortgagors makes a part-payment, the payment shall be deemed to have been made by all the mortgagors.  The effect of this will be to preserve the equity of redemption of all the mortgagors.  There is, at present, a similar provision in regard to acknowledgment in Section 7 of the Real Property Limitation Act, 1874, and that provision is reproduced in Section 48 (3) of the Bill.  As I indicated in discussing the previous amendment, we think that, in so far as the mortgagor's equity of redemption is concerned, the same law should apply in the case of a part-payment as applies in the case of an acknowledgment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>That is clear enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment reinforces what Deputy Finlay and myself were saying, that, if one mortgagor makes payment, it is binding on both.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The law always leans strongly in favour of the equity of redemption.  There is logic enough in the section.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 76:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2) (a), page 23, lines 42 and 43, to delete &ldquo;or other liquidated pecuniary claim&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 77:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (2) (b), page 23, to delete all words from &ldquo;A&rdquo; in line 46 down to and including &ldquo;bind&rdquo; in line 49, and substitute&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(b) A payment in respect of a statute-barred debt shall not bind.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 56, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 57.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 78:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 24, before Section 57, to insert the following new section:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1150" /> ( ) (1) Where&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a) there exists a number of debts, and</P>
    <P>(b) the person liable therefor (in this section referred to as the debtor) makes any payment, whether on account or generally, to the person to whom he is liable (in this section referred to as the creditor), and</P>
    <P>(c) neither the debtor nor the creditor appropriates the sum paid to any particular debt or debts,</P>
    <P>the following provisions shall have effect:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(i)  if some of or all the debts are not statute-barred debts, the payment shall, for the purposes of this Chapter, unless the circumstances in which it was made indicate otherwise, be deemed to be appropriated <i>pari passu</i> in respect of each of the debts which are not statute-barred debts.</P>
    <P>(ii)  if all the debts are statute-barred debts, the payment shall, for the purposes of this Chapter, unless the circumstances in which it was made indicate otherwise, be deemed to be appropriated <i>pari passu</i> in respect of each of the debts.</P>
    <P>(2)  Nothing in sub-section (1) of this section shall, where the debtor does not appropriate, operate to prevent the creditor from appropriacting a payment made on account or generally to a particular debt or to particular debts or to all the debts (whether statute-barred debts or not), but such appropriation shall not by reason only of its being made by the creditor operate to make the payment a payment for the purposes of this Chapter in respect of such debt or debts, unless the circumstances in which the payment was made by the debtor so indicate.</P>
    <P>(3)  Where, under Section 16 of the Land Law (Ireland) Act, 1896, a tenant against whom an ejectment has been brought pays two years' rent, the payment shall, for the purposes of this Chapter, unless the circumstances in which it was made indicate <Col N="1151" /> otherwise, be deemed to be a payment in respect of all arrears which, at the date of the commencement of the proceedings in the ejectment, are not statute-barred debts.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a matter on which there may be some controversy. The amendment is a lengthy one.  It has to do with the question of payment in respect of debts and the matter is not as well covered by law as most people feel.  This is an effort to get things into a correct line.  The proposal contained in the amendment is an attempt to put into statutory form what we think the law is and ought to be where there are a number of debts and a part-payment is made generally.  The law is not very clear in some respects at the moment and we think it better to take this opportunity to clarify it.  Though part-payment where there are a number of debts must arise fairly often in practice, not very many cases are to be found in the reported judgments. <i>Nash v. Hodgson</i> referred to in the sidenote decided that where a number of debts are owed, some statute-barred and some not, and the debtor makes a payment to the creditor, it is, in the absence of further evidence, to be concluded that the payment is not on account of a debt that is statute-barred. This seems logical enough, because the debtor is deemed to be paying only in respect of what he is legally bound to pay.  Section 9 of the Mercantile Law Amendment Act, 1856 (now to be replaced by Section 11 (3) of the Bill), provides that &ldquo;no claim in respect of a matter which arose more than six years before the commencement of such action or suit shall be enforceable by action or suit by reason only of some other matter of claim comprised in the same account having arisen within six years next before the commencement of such action or suit.&rdquo; In <i>Mills v. Fowkes</i>, which was decided before <i>Nash v.</i><i>Hodgson</i> and which is also referred to in the sidenote, it was held that, though the creditor could only apply a payment so as to revive his right to sue on a statute-barred debt, yet, as there was no appropriation by the <Col N="1152" /> debtor, the creditor might apply the payment in satisfaction of the statute-barred debt.</P>
      <P>We must distinguish between appropriation in satisfaction of a debt and appropriation for the purposes of the Statute of Limitations.  The ordinary law of appropriation is that if the debtor does not appropriate, the creditor may appropriate.  <i>Mills v. Fowkes</i>, however, decides that though the creditor may appropriate to an old debt, the right of action for which is barred, such an appropriation will not operate to take the remainder of the debt out of the Statute.  Nevertheless, the circumstances of each particular case must be inquired into.  In another case, referred to in <i>Friend v. Young</i> (1697) 2 Ch., the law was stated as follows:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The principle that the payment must be such as to be an acknowledgment of the debt is right and not new.  I do not, however, by any means assent to the doctrine that, where there are two debts existing, and a payment is made, not specifically appropriated to either, there is necessarily no sufficient evidence of a payment on account of either of those debts to take it out of the Statute of Limitations.  It must depend on the special circumstances of each case.  In general, there would be evidence to go to the jury of a payment on account of both debts.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>In <i>Friend v. Young</i> a payment was made &ldquo;on account&rdquo; with reference to a statement of account which included as part of it statute-barred items, and there did not exist a balance equal to the payment made on account either on the face of the statement of account or in fact.  It was held that, in the circumstances, the payment covered the statute-barred items and amounted to an acknowledgment which made them recoverable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <i>Boswell's Case</i> (1906) 2 Ch. does not specifically decide whether, when a payment on account is made by the debtor and there has been no appropriation by either the debtor or the creditor, the law will appropriate it to the earliest of the items which at the date of the payment were not statute-barred, or will treat it as attributable <i>pari passu</i> to all such items so as to <Col N="1153" /> take them out of the operation of the statute, but the matter was referred to in the case.  There are, I am afraid, conflicting <i>dicta</i> on the subject in some of the other cases.</P>
    <P>I think I have said enough to show that a very useful purpose would be served by having a statutory provision dealing with the matter of appropriation in its various aspects.  What we propose to provide is that, where none of the debts is statute-barred, a payment on account or generally shall for the purpose of the statute be deemed to be made <i>pari passu</i> in respect of each debt so that the period of limitation will begin to run again in respect of each debt.  If all the debts are statute-barred, the same result will accrue.  If, however, some of the debts are statute-barred and some not, the payment will be a payment in respect of each of the debts which are not statute-barred.  There will, however, be the overriding consideration in all cases that the circumstances of the case may indicate what is to happen.</P>
    <P>Sub-section (2) proposes to preserve the creditor's legal right to appropriate in satisfaction of a particular debt or debts, but this appropriation will not, <i>ipso facto</i>, take the case out of the statute, unless, again, the circumstances of the payment so indicate.</P>
    <P>Sub-section (3) is designed to cover cases like <i>Eyre v. Coen</i> referred to in the sidenote.  Section 16 of the Land Law (Ireland) Act, 1896, allows a tenant to pay two years' arrears of rent to prevent himself being ejected. The balance due can then only be recovered as an ordinary debt and not by ejectment.  In <i>Eyre's Case</i>, the landlord appropriated the payment to the earlier rent so as to prevent the statutes from operating and gave a receipt which the tenant accepted for this rent.  It was held that the appropriation was, in the circumstances of the case, good.  We propose to provide that the payment of the two years' rent shall be effective in respect of all the arrears not statute-barred, provided the circumstances do not indicate to the contrary.</P>
    <P>We have given much consideration and study to this whole question of <Col N="1154" /> part-payment where there are a number of debts.  We are satisfied that the proposal in the amendment follows the line which can generally be drawn through all the cases and that it is both a fair and logical way to legislate for a problem which can be of much significance in practice.  We are, however, willing to consider between this and Report Stage any reasonable suggestions for the improvement of the provisions suggested.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>We have considered this matter and I think the amendment, as drafted, is good enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>If there are any other suggestions, they could be looked into and studied before the Report Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The important thing is simplicity.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is an extremely useful section.  It is very useful that the law will be clarified on this very important matter.  The effect of sub-section (2) in the proposed draft apparently is that where the debtor himself does not appropriate, the creditor will not be prevented from appropriating a payment made on account or generally in connection with a particular debt.  I frankly feel that a lot of difficulty could arise from the words &ldquo;unless the circumstances in which the payment was made by the debtor so indicate&rdquo;.  In the earlier part of this section, it is stated that the sub-section will arise where the debtor himself does not appropriate and it may be hard to see what circumstances would arise in which the debtor himself does not appropriate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>You are merely trying to keep the present position where you infer&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>You are requiring then the circumstances of the payment to be investigated where there has not been, in fact, any specific appropriation by the debtor.  I would be against making general payments revive statute-barred debts.  It strikes me <Col N="1155" /> that you might put the onus of proof on the creditor.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister might consider between this and the next stage the advisability of fixing, in some way, the method by which appropriations on the part of the creditor might be proved.  Where you permit a creditor to appropriate in any way he likes, I think you take away the force of paragraph (1) of sub-section (c).  It is quite obvious that no creditor is going to let the effect of paragraph (1) come into operation, spreading the payments among the statute-barred debts only.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>It is only a matter of a drafting amendment to the two lines of sub-section (2).  Will the Minister look into that by the Report Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to be strong enough.  However, we will consider all the remarks made.  This is an effort to have the law clarified. The debtor can always appropriate and we want to cover the case where he does not do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DeclanCostello" hpid="Mr. D. Costello Mr. D. Costello">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D. Costello</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Minister endeavour to clarify it in this sense&mdash; to make it hard for the creditor to prove that he has appropriated against the statute-barred debt?  I think the onus should be put as strongly as possible on the creditor.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 57, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 58 agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 59.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 79:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In sub-section (1), page 24, line 32, before &ldquo;run&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;begin to.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.  The words &ldquo;begin to&rdquo; should be inserted before &ldquo;run&rdquo; in the third line of sub-section (1).  By the way, &ldquo;line 32&rdquo; in the amendment should read &ldquo;line 33.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 59, as amended, agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1156" /> SECTION 60.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 80:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 24, lines 45 and 46, to delete the definitions of &ldquo;arbitration,&rdquo;&ldquo;arbitration agreement&rdquo; and &ldquo;award.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.  Amendment No. 4 proposed to transfer the definitions of &ldquo;arbitration,&rdquo; etc., to Section 2 of the Bill.  There are references to arbitration in Section 11 of the Bill and the definitions in the matter should come at the beginning of the Bill.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 60, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 61 to 67, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SCHEDULE</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 81:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In page 26, to delete Part I, and to substitute:</P>
      <P Just="Center">PART 1.</P>
      <P Just="Center">
        <i>Acts of the Parliament of Ireland.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="20*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="20*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Session and Chapter.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Title.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Extent of Repeal.</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>(1)</entry>
            <entry>(2)</entry>
            <entry>(3)</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>6 Ann. c. 10 (Ir.).</entry>
            <entry>An Act for the amendment of the law and the better advancement of justice.  (1707).</entry>
            <entry>Section 17 so far as unrepealed.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>8 Geo. 1.c. 14 (Ir.).</entry>
            <entry>An Act for the more effectual quieting of possessions, and preventing vexatious suits at law. (1721).</entry>
            <entry>The whole Act so far as unrepealed.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a drafting amendment.  We propose that every statute dealing with limitation should be totally repealed.  We are simply adding to Part I of the Schedule a provision in an old Act of 1721 dealing <Col N="1157" /> with specialty debts.  The amendment when it refers to 8 Geo. 1. C. 14 (Ir.) should refer to 8 Geo. 1. C. 4(Ir.).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the intention is that all other Statutes of Limitation should be replaced.  Am I right in thinking that the Local Government Act which had the limitation on the right to sue a local authority would still be in existence?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand it was repealed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAFinlay1954" hpid="Mr. Finlay Mr. Finlay">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Finlay</NameTxt>
      <P>Then the matter does not arise.</P>
      <P>Amendment altered, by leave, by the deletion of &ldquo;8 Geo. 1. C. 14.(Ir.)&rdquo; and the substitution of &ldquo;8 Geo. 1. C. 4 (Ir.)&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment, as altered, agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesEverett" hpid="Mr. Everett Mr. Everett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Everett</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 82:&mdash;</P>
      <P>In Part II, page 26, between the entries relating to 23 &amp; 24 Vic. c. 38 and 37 &amp; 38 Vic. c. 57, to insert&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="10*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="15*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="3" colnum="3" colwidth="25*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">33 &amp; 34 Vic. c. 46.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">The Landlord and Tenant (Ireland) Act, 1870.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">In section 50, the words &lsquo;No arrears of any annuity charged on land in pursuance of this Act shall be recoverable after the expiration of two years from the date at which the sum in arrear became due;&rsquo;</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Right">&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is again a drafting amendment.  We propose to repeal a provision in the Landlord and Tenant Act, 1870.  This was the first Land Purchase Act and annuities thereunder are payable to the Office of Public Works.  The period of limitation is two years.  No period is prescribed for annuities payable to the Land Commission, but a period of six years is being provided for in Sections 26 and 28 of the Bill.  In the interest of uniformity, it is desirable that the period should be the same for all annuities. The amount of money collectable as annuities under the 1870 Act is now <Col N="1158" /> very small.  The amendment will mean that a six-year period will apply to them.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Schedule, as amended, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported, with amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it proposed to take the next stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite a lot of material has been offered here.  I hope it has been understood.  It can be studied when the text of the Official Report is in hands.  That will not be until some day next week, so it might be as well to leave it for a fortnight or three weeks.</P>
      <P>Report Stage ordered for Wednesday, 5th December, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>Does that mean that we have no further business in the House to-day?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The only business ordered was Item No. 6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The Government has no business to bring forward to the Dáil to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>I have nothing to say about that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>The Dáil is going to adjourn because the Government has no business for it.  Is that the position?  Is the Dáil going to adjourn now because the Government has no business to bring before the House?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a motion on the Adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I think, Sir, I am entitled to reply to that question.  The Government brought in yesterday two Second Readings of very important Bills, the Civil Service Regulation Bill, 1956, and the Civil Service Commissioners Bill, 1956.  There was, too, a piece of legislation which has been shouted for for more than 20 years back.  When I was in Industry and <Col N="1159" /> Commerce, I got an urgent demand to set up a tribunal to inquire into coast protection.  I set up that tribunal in the early days of 1932.  Now there have been all sorts of agitation around the country, particularly in two counties in the east and west.  Yesterday, we brought in a piece of legislation to deal with that problem and it went through this House quicker than any coast erosion, even allowing for the 30 years' gap.  The Government, in fact, brought in so much business that the Opposition was not able to cope with it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>We have dealt with all the business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, in the way in which it was dealt with.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Major de Valera Major de Valera">
      <NameTxt>Major de Valera</NameTxt>
      <P>It is no wonder the Government is in the state it is, and the country as well, unfortunately.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment Debate&mdash;West" RHead="Cork Rural Improvement Scheme">
    <Title>Adjournment Debate&mdash;West Cork Rural Improvement Scheme.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>With some misgivings, I am allowing the subject matter of the second question to be raised.  I do not consider it a good principle that two questions should be raised on the Adjournment on the subject matter of one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>It may seem strange that the House should be troubled with a discussion on the subject matter of these questions because, at first glance, it may seem that they deal with relatively simple issues.  However, there is an important principle involved in both questions and it is in order to get clarification of that principle, that I am taking up the time of the House and raising this matter on the Adjournment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let me preface my remarks by stating that, so far as these two questions are concerned, protracted negotiations have taken place over a considerable period between the parties concerned and their representatives and the Special Employment Schemes Office with a view to arriving at some amicable arrangement.  Unfortunately, <Col N="1160" /> no such arrangement has been achieved.</P>
    <P>The important principle involved in Question 21 is whether or not, when a number of farmers apply for a grant under a rural improvement scheme for the improvement of a roadway and when that work has been approved in principle, some extraneous interest should intrude.  This work would be of extreme general public utility to about 15 farmers in the district and to a number of outsiders who would use this road, if it were improved, since it leads to the local creamery stand which caters for the farmers in the area.  There is no need for me to labour this question of general public utility as that is not at issue in this case.  The real question at issue is that a person outside who has no land whatever adjoining this roadway&mdash;let me emphasise that: no land whatsoever&mdash; addressed a letter to the Special Employment Schemes Office stating that, if this work were carried out, the blasting operations necessary may interfere with her sister, who is, I understand, an invalid, and may have an adverse effect on her health.</P>
    <P>The Special Employment Schemes Office upheld that objection.  That settles the big principle involved in this question.  Whilst it is true that this lady's house is situated adjacent to this roadway, some 20 or 30 yards from it, it is separated from the actual roadway by a river.  This person has no claim whatsoever to any land adjoining the roadway.  Neither is it proposed to interfere with any property which she owns good, bad or indifferent.  The Special Employment Schemes Office reached an unprecedented decision in upholding this lady's objection.  I have been asked by the parish priest, who interested himself deeply in this project, having regard to the advantage it would be to his parishioners, to do everything I possibly could to support the contention of the people affected that that objection should not be upheld and that the work should be carried out.  I may add that the parish priest has himself gone to endless trouble to bring about an amicable arrangement as between the conflicting parties, and <Col N="1161" /> so did a number of other people, but without success.</P>
    <P>Let us examine the nature of the objection.  Living, as I do, within one mile of this roadway, I am reasonably conversant with the facts.  They are these: unfortunately the family concerned, consisting of two ladies, living in this house adjacent to the roadway, who object to the work, are not on the best of terms with some of their neighbours.  Due to some matters which have no connection, good, bad or indifferent, with this roadway, I understand their relations are not of the best.  To my mind, consequently this lady apparently saw fit to object to this work for no other purpose but to deprive these farmers and neighbours of the benefit of having an improved roadway.  That was the only justification for her objection.</P>
    <P>It is, indeed, most strange that that objection should be upheld.  It is laid down in the regulations governing the granting of moneys for the improvement of rural roadways, such as this one, that if a person objects, good and solid grounds must be given for that objection.  No such grounds were given in this case other than the contention that, if the work were carried out and the blasting operations took place, they may have an adverse effect on this lady's sister's health.</P>
    <P>The local parish priest, in conjunction with a number of others, endeavouring to dispose amicably of this objection, guaranteed to this lady who objects that during the course of these operations, which would not take more than an hour at the outside, her sister would be removed to the local hospital only a mile or a mile and a half away, or to any neighbour's house to which she would elect to go.  In fact, the parish priest himself guaranteed the lady protection while the blasting would be carried out and so did the neighbours.  They made several appeals to her to allow the work to be carried out and in case it might have any effect on her or her sister, they offered to provide first-class accommodation for them.</P>
    <P>Surely no group of people in any district could make a better offer than these people made, and the fact that <Col N="1162" /> this offer was not accepted indicates that there is more behind the objection than this story that the blasting might affect their health adversely. The Special Employment Schemes officer was fairly conversant with the position because the director of the Special Employment Schemes Office is from the district himself and is in a much better position to adjudicate on this matter than any other person, knowing the neighbourhood as he does.  Despite this, and despite the many appeals made to the office, they were adamant in objecting to this work on the ground that if the blasting did cause any injury to this lady, or if the noise from the blasting caused any injury, the Special Employment Schemes Office would be liable for payment of compensation.  It is on that question that I am taking up the time of the House this evening.</P>
    <P>Surely no Department in the State ever tried to put over such a ridiculous assertion to a group of people who were anxious to get something done and which they were justly entitled to get done under enactments of this House?  I want to protest against the adherence of the Special Employment Schemes Office to its decision to uphold such a nonsensical objection, which was put forward from no other motives but spiteful ones.  I think that is accepted by every person from the parish priest down.  It is accepted by myself, living as I do, within one mile of these parties.</P>
    <P>If we have reached a position in this State in which people, because of ulterior motives, can object to improvements taking place in the lives of their neighbours&mdash;and these improvements mean a great deal to the people concerned, involving a roadway for which they have been agitating for a number of years and which would save some of these farmers as much as two miles in carting milk to and from the creamery &mdash;it is a sad situation.</P>
    <P>The Special Employment Schemes Office also said that the county council would not undertake such work, but I can tell them that the county council do undertake such work and that never has Cork County Council, or, I am sure, any other county council, upheld such a frivolous objection.</P>
    <Col N="1163" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Donnellan) Michael Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Finance (Mr. Donnellan)</NameTxt>
      <P>Why did they not do this work?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>This does not come within the scope of the Cork County Council.  It is work which, in my opinion merits at least a 90 per cent. contribution under existing enactments, subject to a local contribution of not more than 10 per cent. from the beneficiaries.  However, the contribution and the amount from the State have already been determined and there is no need to labour that point, but the excuse that the county council would not carry out similar work, if such an objection were made, is completely groundless.  I make that statement as Acting Chairman of Cork County Council and after having made specific inquiries so far as this matter is concerned.</P>
      <P>I had hoped that the director of the Special Employment Schemes Office would see fit to review the position and change his mind in this case because we are establishing a precedent.  This happens in Schull to-day, but it may happen in any other part of the country to-morrow so far as these schemes are concerned, if these frivolous objections are to be entertained from any person who is not benefiting under a particular scheme and who is living in the neighbourhood.  I think the Special Employment Schemes Office is quite satisfied that the only ground for this objection is that these ladies in this case are not on friendly terms with some of their neighbours.</P>
      <P>I am putting this question to the Parliamentary Secretary as the person for the time being responsible for the Special Employment Schemes Office, and I am asking him whether it is fair or not to accept and uphold such a frivolous objection in this case.  If it is, this House should busy itself in the not too distant future with removing the clauses which permit that sort of thing, but I do not think the existing regulations governing grants for these schemes do cover such nonsensical objections.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not want to take up any more time dealing with question 21, but I wish to emphasise again the desirability <Col N="1164" /> of not upholding objections made from ulterior motives, and no one knows better what is behind this objection than the director of the Special Employment Schemes Office&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickHogan" hpid="An Ceann Comhairle Patrick (Clare) Hogan">
      <NameTxt>An Ceann Comhairle</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy, of course, knows he has only 20 minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been asked to make representations on behalf of the people residing on the Lissacaha roadway to agitate for a grant towards improvement of the road for the benefit of two farmers and for the indirect benefit of a number of other farmers using the road which is the subject matter of Question No. 22. The special employment schemes manager is again quite conversant with this area and there was not much necessity for me to labour the point in making representations to him, as he has an intimate knowledge of the district concerned. I am therefore asking the Parliamentary Secretary why these people did not get the grant they are legally entitled to get under existing regulations?  The application form states that if the work benefits two or more farmers and is of reasonable general public utility, and if the cost is not out of proportion for carrying out the work, these people are entitled to a grant.</P>
      <P>I want to emphasise that this is a connecting road, by which I mean it is a roadway which links two public roads, and, if it were improved, not only would it advance the interests of the people directly concerned, but it would advance the interests of other farmers and other people in the neighbourhood who would use it as a short way to the creamery at Lowertown, Schull.  The director states that it would cost £900 to carry out a worthwhile job on this road.  I know the road fairly well and I have first-hand information from the local people themselves and from people who are conversant with costings of such work that £400 or £500 would make a reasonable job of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I believe the people of these areas are not getting a fair deal.  I am surprised at the attitude the Employment Schemes Office are adopting.  I shall conclude by repeating the remarks I <Col N="1165" /> made at the beginning regarding Question No. 21&mdash;that this involves a big question of principle.  It is outrageous that the frivolous objection of this lady should be upheld and that the work should not be proceeded with because of that objection.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly I have sympathy with Deputy Murphy.  No man has done more or could do more to fix up this dispute set out in Question No. 21 than he has.  He talked about the work done by the parish priest, but I think it can truly be said that nobody did as much work to have the matter fixed up as did the Deputy himself.  He went to the house of those two sisters and told them he would make provision in the hospital for the sister who is ill to get her out of the way while the work was being done.  However, the Deputy must realise we are not a law court and that no matter what Deputy Murphy or any other Deputy may say, I will not do anything, nor will the director do anything, that would involve the office in a law suit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>On what grounds could you be liable for damages?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Let me read from this letter:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;The doctor called this morning and said that as my sister is in a critical state, shock of any kind could cause death and owing to the road being only a few yards from the house I should see there should be nothing done to make her case worse than it is at present.  One man consoled me by telling me that if my sister would die of shock I could claim compensation.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>That is the gist of the case.  That is what the doctor told this lady and what some good neighbour told her. Deputy Murphy dealt with the utility of this road and the necessity for it. There is no doubt about it.  I gave a 94 per cent. grant for it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are quite satisfied with the grant.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>Outside the house of those ladies, there is a certain <Col N="1166" /> amount of rock which would have to be excavated.  Dynamite would have to be used on that.  This lady is in poor health and might be injured by such excavation work.  I think Deputy Murphy will realise how we sympathise with his case when he remembers that we gave a grant of £408, subject to a local contribution of £24, for this road.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickODonnell" hpid="Mr. O'Donnell Mr. O'Donnell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Donnell</NameTxt>
      <P>We cannot get grants like that in Donegal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the biggest grant I ever sanctioned.  It is 94 per cent. of the total cost of the road. Deputy Murphy pointed out that the director knows this place.  He does In fact, six of the people in that area were school pals of his.  Surely if it were possible to do this work, he would do it.  It just is not possible for us to do it.  A law case could be slapped at us that would involve us in thousands of pounds.  I will not allow that to happen.  However, the director has decided that at the earliest opportunity he will go down there. Where the Deputy has failed and where the parish priest has failed, the director might succeed.  He has decided to visit the area at the first opportunity and see if he can do anything to get those people out of the way for even two hours.  That is all we would want.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Parliamentary Secretary satisfied it is due to the bitter feeling that exists between the different parties that this scheme is not allowed to proceed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy is likely to know more about that than I am, What I do know is that we would be likely to cause the death of this lady and would be liable for damages.  We will not agree to carry out blasting operations that would cause injury to this lady.  As I have said, we have given a grant of 94 per cent. for this scheme and it is a pity that it cannot be settled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>Is it the contention of the Parliamentary Secretary that these people should be allowed to hold up a scheme that would benefit local farmers trying to make a living on their land?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1167" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>No, but we are not entitled to interfere with the property of any party against the will of that party.  Particularly we are not entitled to interfere with the life of any party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>You are not interfering with their property.  These ladies have no property, no land adjoining this road.  They live adjacent to the road.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>This lady owns her life, and the doctor says anything we may do might be responsible for her death.  We will not take that chance. I hope efforts to fix the matter up will be successful in the near future.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As regards the Deputy's other question, it refers to 150 perches of road in the townlands mentioned.  Application for a grant was made on 23rd October, 1954.  Four of the six beneficiaries signed the application form.  It is estimated that the cost of the scheme would be £920.  It is an old abandoned country road which is of no advantage to the general public.  Of the six landowners concerned, two did not sign the application form because they are not active beneficiaries at all.  They are only using small sections of the road at either end.  The third person concerned is only slightly interested because he uses only 45 perches at one end to gain access to some conacre. The three remaining families use 150 perches at the eastern end as an alternative <Col N="1168" /> access to their lands.  Thomas O'Neill and Thomas King are the two real beneficiaries.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>The Act says &ldquo;two or more farmers&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>We admit these two people suffer hardship, due to the bad condition of the part of the road that concerns them.  It is, however, not considered justifiable to carry out a scheme costing £920 to relieve the slight hardship imposed on two farmers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>These people would be satisfied with half that amount.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have been speaking to the director about this matter and I can tell the Deputy that he will look into the matter again and see if part of this road could not be repaired.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>I should be glad if the Parliamentary Secretary did that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDonnellan" hpid="Mr. Donnellan Mr. Donnellan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Donnellan</NameTxt>
      <P>I certainly shall.  As regards the other question, I hope the difficulty will be settled up in the near future because I consider it a very worthy project.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 6.30 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 21st November, 1956.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>