<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="6" Month="Oct" Year="2009" Vol="197" No="3" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 6 Deireadh Fómhair 2009" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 6 October 2009" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="119">
    <Col N="119"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title></Title>
       
        <P Just="Center">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Paidir.</i><br /><i>Prayer.</i></P><Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad"> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad.</Title>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have received notice from Senator Dominic Hannigan that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to introduce regulations to require all timber used in Government, semi-State and local authority procurement contracts to be sourced from certifiably sustainable timber producers.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to make a statement on the promise of gateway funding for the Cork docklands project and, in particular, the eastern gateway bridge.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Cecilia Keaveney of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Defence to give an appraisal of whether the bomb disposal unit should be returned to Finner, given the recent heightened security threats generally in Ulster.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Fidelma Healy Eames of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Education and Science to clarify if Colaiste na Coiribe, Galway city, will be included in the next PPP bundle and when that is likely to be in order that the school may proceed to meet the large pupil enrolment on waiting lists for accommodation.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Eugene Regan of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to clarify whether a fault has been discovered in the Lion Intoxilyzer and a notification issued from the Chief Prosecution Solicitor to persons convicted in D&uacute;n Laoghaire District Court of an offence under section 13(2) of the Road Traffic Act 1994 concerning a failure to provide breath specimens.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Nicky McFadden of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister of Finance to expand the amenity that is Corlea Project, Kenagh, County Longford.</P><Col N="120"/>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Health and Children to ensure the home support service will be protected, given the importance of the service to the disabled and elderly in County Donegal.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Hannigan, Buttimer and Keaveney and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is No. 1, Public Transport Regulation Bill 2009 &mdash; Committee Stage, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business and adjourn not later than 6 p.m., if not previously concluded.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>Members of Fine Gael and many Members of this House are delighted with the result of the referendum on the Lisbon treaty and the central role Ireland will continue to play within the European Union.  In its campaign, led by Deputy Kenny, Fine Gael put the country first.  It is important that the Government does not interpret the result of the vote as an endorsement of its work.  If there was one emotion obvious on the campaign trail, it was people&rsquo;s fury at the excesses they had seen, be they in respect of F&Aacute;S, ministerial expenses and those of the Ceann Comhairle, waste in government or Departments.  A comprehensive plan for governance in respect of these issues is not coming from the Government.  I ask the Leader to respond by inviting some Ministers, if not the Taoiseach, to address the core issue of governance and standards.</P>
        <P>The new Labour Services (Amendment) Bill purports to reform the board of F&Aacute;S.  It does so to a degree, but this is not true reform.  Fine Gael brought forward a public appointments transparency Bill to ensure greater transparency.  Under that Bill, a committee of the D&aacute;il would have had more of a role and there would have been greater scrutiny of those appointed.  This is not allowed for in the Government Bill, which I regret.  The people are asking how can the Government convince them that it is putting in place mechanisms to show that the culture of excess has changed.  Negotiations are taking place this week between the Green Party and Fianna F&aacute;il and many would like to be offered an election at the end of that process.  People want a new team with different standards being applied.  It is extraordinary how little emphasis there is in the programme discussions on job creation and helping employers.  That element seems to be missing.  From what we have heard so far, a plan for economic recovery does not appear to be part of the negotiations.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>That is idle speculation. The Senator is not part of the negotiations.  </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>People struggling with unemployment and trying to pay their mortgage and bills are certainly looking for solutions.  They want to see more than what they have received so far.  I would like the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Coughlan, to come before the House to discuss employment and the provision of incentives to see how we can begin to tackle the long unemployment queues.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>The big issue being discussed today in the newspapers and everywhere else is that of expenses, although the focus is on the other House.  It must be acknowledged that the level of trust and confidence in politicians is at an all-time low.  We must also acknowl<Col N="121"/>edge that we all share, to some extent, in that failure.  Whether people were individually part of the excesses, there is a view abroad that as a political class we have let down the people we represent.  We must move forward from that position and make whatever changes are required.  The matter of politicians&rsquo; expenses must be taken from our own hands.  Perhaps we should take advice from outside the House &mdash; the private sector &mdash; in looking at the nature of the job Members do and outlining how expenses should be claimed.  It would not save the State money but it is the approach we must take for the sake of transparency.  It would require much work but it must be done.  It should be recognised that it is very hard to compare the job done where somebody living on the west coast must be in Dublin three or four days a week and also travel around a constituency with any job in the private sector.  Nevertheless, the approaches adopted in the private sector could be used in measuring and quantifying the work done and bringing forward a system in which the people could have trust and confidence.  We should begin such a process but I despair about whether we will do so.  </P>
        <P>As Senator Fitzgerald correctly stated, the F&Aacute;S legislation which has emerged today is appalling.  The social partners have been taken out.  As I have a vested interest in it, I will say nothing about that matter.  What is being put in its place is a system in which the Minister will look into his or her own heart, lift the telephone to speak to two other Ministers and, without consultation with anybody else, decide who will sit on the board.  That is a step backwards.  We are already in a position where at least half of the members of the broadcasting authority will come through a joint committee of the Houses.  It is an appalling and unacceptably regressive measure that the new F&Aacute;S board will be put together without the involvement of anybody outside the Cabinet.  I ask the Leader to recognise that an amendment will have to be made to the Bill to at least bring the decision before a joint committee of the Houses when Members would be able to show their expertise and knowledge in these areas and give trust and confidence to the people.  This is a classic example where governance begins with legislation.  We must insist on it happening in such a way.</P>
        <P>In responding to the big issue of the day, from here on we must work like this every day.  We must put up our hands and say what we have been doing so far is unacceptable to the people and that the excesses about which we have read are not acceptable.  In looking to the future we must change the system.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P>There are no doubts about what Senator O&rsquo;Toole said, that the level of trust and confidence in politicians is at an all-time low.  That is absolutely true.  Any Member who is in contact with people &mdash; I am sure that is the case with all of my colleagues &mdash; must know that there is an unprecedented level of anger and frustration evident across all levels of society.  The question of expenses is but one flashpoint.  It is, however, a serious flashpoint.  This matter arose earlier in the year in Britain and a debate on the fundamental issues involved came about as a result.  That debate went to the very heart of the constitution, no less, of that country.</P>
        <P>There is a serious issue with which we must deal.  Some of the proposals put forward by Senator O&rsquo;Toole have merit but there is no substitute for people in public life exercising their own judgement in respect of both their actions and what they do with public money.  I have no intention of referring to or making suggestions regarding any individual.  However, if every single person in public life is not prepared to exercise judgment over what he or she is doing in respect of the use of public money, there is no hope with regard to the restoration of public trust and confidence in politics or the political system.</P>
        <P>I wish to ask the Leader a question in respect of that matter.  The question to which I refer relates to the trust and confidence of the public in the debate in which we will be obliged to engage in the coming months with regard to the overall budgetary situation and the serious <Col N="122"/>difficulties we face.  I wish to ask a single, tight question.  One of the hazards of asking three or four questions, not only of the Leader but also of others, one tends to not necessarily receive a reply.  Has a Government decision been made in respect of the figure of &euro;4 billion required to be obtained in savings in December&rsquo;s budget?  Has the Government decided to change the balance which it indicated would apply in respect of that &euro;4 billion, namely, that there would be &euro;2.5 billion in expenditure cuts and &euro;1.5 billion in taxation measures?  When was it decided that the entire &euro;4 billion in savings would be obtained through public expenditure cuts?  Was a decision made and when was it made?</P>
        <P>Everyone has a view on the correct balance that should apply and we could engage in a debate on the matter.  However, in the first instance I wish to know the answer to the question I have posed.  As stated last week, during the summer the McCarthy report and the report of the Commission on Taxation were published.  In my naivety, I had understood that these reports would form the basis for the debate in which we were going to engage this autumn.  The McCarthy report contains much that I do not like but it sets out in stark terms where expenditure is being made and where there may be opportunities for savings.  There is much with which I agree and much with which I disagree in the report.  However, at least it is a written document.  The Commission on Taxation&rsquo;s report sets out the basis on which we might reform the tax system in the future.</P>
        <P>We were, therefore, presented with the McCarthy report on expenditure and the commission report on taxation.  I accept that matters are not that simple but at least these reports could provide us with some assistance.  However, we have been informed that the report of the Commission on Taxation has been abandoned.  In addition, and if we are to believe the newspapers, it appears that rather than going through the detail of the McCarthy report and engaging in the requisite debate, the Government intends to have one or two major whacks, as it were.  In other words, it will have a go at either public service pay or social welfare payments.  That is just not good enough because it contributes to the lack of trust.  If the Government wants the Opposition to put forward proposals for discussion, why then is it not possible to engage in a debate on these reports, which were commissioned in our name, rather than merely jettisoning them?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NedOSullivan"><NameTxt>Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>I congratulate the Government and the main Opposition parties on working so well together for the good of the country and on putting aside normal politics during the past couple of weeks to deliver a resoundingly successful result in the referendum.  I wish to congratulate the Taoiseach in particular because the buck stopped with him.  It was a major achievement for him to preside over this success.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Toole referred to the attitude of the people to politicians&rsquo; expenses.  I agree with the Senator&rsquo;s assertion that there is a perception abroad which is not desirable from our point of view.  We must put our hands up and state that mistakes were made.  Those mistakes were not all made by one Government, nor were they made by one party.  They certainly were not made by one individual.  That individual has been extremely unfairly treated by the media in recent weeks.  We must consider the role the media is playing in creating the perception to which Senator O&rsquo;Toole referred and also people&rsquo;s distrust of politicians.</P>
        <P>Some of the recent revelations would remind us of the worst excesses of the McCarthy era in the United States.  I have been a Member for barely two years, during which time I have been subjected to seven freedom of information requests.  I have no problem with them and I am happy to put on view my meagre expenses in the Oireachtas Library at any time.  However, Members should consider the time and cost involved to the taxpayer.  Staff in Leinster House have more to do than answer all journalists who, on lazy days when they can find nothing <Col N="123"/>better to do, delve into the individual or collective expenses of Members.  While some fee is payable for this service, it should be examined to ascertain whether value for money is being achieved in respect of the data being given out.  If such information is so important, if the public wants it so much and if the media are so concerned about its relevance and importance, the latter should be prepared to pay for it.</P>
        <P>On the filling of State boards, I wish to return to a point that several other Members and I have raised previously in the House, namely, the attitude displayed during the years towards city, county and town councillors.  They were considered to be pariahs and people held their noses at the idea of sharing responsibility with them on boards.  Many of those who held their noses are the type of people who have brought the entire body politic into disrepute.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator&rsquo;s point is made.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NedOSullivan"><NameTxt>Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>Business people and the self-employed are not the sole repository of wisdom and prudence.  County councillors are the salt of the earth; they are good and decent people who show good judgment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator&rsquo;s point is made.  Elections are not due for a while.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="NedOSullivan"><NameTxt>Senator Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan</NameTxt>
	<P>They should be included in the new set-up.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>Members should record the extraordinary success achieved in the Lisbon treaty referendum debate, as measured by a &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote of 67%.  It is a &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote to a modern Ireland at the heart of the European Union.  Everyone worked on the campaign closely and effectively and the message got through.  In particular, I welcome the very high &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote of 81% in the constituency of D&uacute;n Laoghaire.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P>It was the second highest &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P>After Dublin South.  It is in the second league.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Regan to continue without interruption, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>After the first Lisbon treaty referendum, when the highest &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote nationwide at 63% was recorded in D&uacute;n Laoghaire, I predicted the rest of the country eventually would follow suit.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should put a question to the Leader.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>The turnout in D&uacute;n Laoghaire was 74%.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>This is a matter for the local or national newspapers.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>From Sallynoggin to Killiney and from Monkstown Farm to Shankill&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>There was a strong &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote in all those areas, which is to be welcomed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Keep the home fires burning.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should ask a question of the Leader.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="124"/>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate that normal hostilities had been suspended while Members were pursuing the referendum campaign.  However, an issue that came up at the doors while one was canvassing was that of the expenses and expenditure of none other than the Ceann Comhairle, Deputy O&rsquo;Donoghue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>No, that matter is not relevant to this House; it is one for the other House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>Another issue was that of the additional &euro;1 million in compensation for Mr. Rody Molloy.  These issues&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator, please.  I am tired of telling Members that I do not want anyone to be named.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;are tearing at the heart of politics.  It is important to record that Members do not stand over such expenditure and that someone must be held to account.  I do not know whether Members on the Government side of the House are happy with this abuse of office because that is what it is.  While there will be further debate on the issue this week, I consider this expenditure to be unsustainable and indefensible.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>Members are aware that there were scapegoats in the Hebrew tradition.  Incidentally, they also had sacrificial bulls and lambs.  If the Opposition and the fainthearted in Fianna F&aacute;il seek a sacrificial bull and if the Ceann Comhairle did something wrong a few weeks ago&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I am not discussing him.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>Okay.  If anyone had done something wrong, his head should have been sought.  However, as his head was not sought, therefore, he must not have done anything wrong.  If he did, the matter should have been dealt with.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>No one in this House should discuss the Ceann Comhairle.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>Fair enough; I will move on.  However, if one is afraid to take on a sacrificial bull, it is wrong to take on a sacrificial lamb.  I refer to the person who has been targeted as an alleged political adviser.  He is not a political adviser.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>No, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>He is a cultural adviser who has never been a member of a political party.  He has never engaged in political activities.  He is a distinguished former RTE producer who has done great work in outreach programmes on this House.  He was appointed by the commission to publicise the work of the Oireachtas.  He has done so with great ability&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Please&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and it is very wrong to target, for sacrificial purposes&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Not individuals, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>I have never mentioned his name.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I know that.  He is easily identifiable.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="125"/>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>It is very rare that I defend public servants.  I am defending a minor public servant who has been targeted when his employer is being let off the hook.  That is very wrong.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I share with other Senators the relief that the country passed the Lisbon treaty referendum last weekend.  As someone who was on the doorsteps, many people expressed concern about our defence and neutrality.  I am somewhat concerned to read in Fionnan Sheahan&rsquo;s column in the <i>Sunday Independent</i> about the Taoiseach&rsquo;s support for a potential candidacy by Mr. Tony Blair.  As someone who supported Mr. Tony Blair when he ran for leader of the Labour Party, I am aware of his many talents and appreciate the good work he did in the Northern Ireland peace process.  However, the man brought his country to war on flawed evidence and without a UN mandate.  I would like a debate about whether he is the type of person we want as president of the EU before the Taoiseach supports his candidacy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.  Put it down and I will sign it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinBrady"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>I want to raise an issue that a number of small business people raised with me.  They received correspondence from various local authorities informing them that their rates will be increased.  In one case, it amounts to a 35% increase.  One man owns three restaurants and his rates are being increased.  In some cases the business done by these enterprises has decreased by 50%.  The person I was referring to employs 70 staff but he will have to close because one cannot give it out if one is not getting it in at the till.  I made the necessary inquiries of the local authority, Fingal County Council, and the manager replied by saying that he agreed with me but that there was nothing he could do because it was the responsibility of the Valuation Office which was basing its increases on 2005 valuations.  If these people must close their businesses, one of which employs 70 staff, because they are barely ticking over at the moment, the employees will have to receive unemployment assistance and this will cost the State &euro;2.5 million.  It does not make sense.</P>
        <P>I suggest we bring in the relevant Minister, who I believe is the Minister for Finance, to make him aware of this situation and to ask what can be done about it.  This must be stopped.  We should examine giving small business people a break and reducing rates and rents in some cases.  These are matters we should examine to help small businesses because they are the backbone of the economy.  If we do not have small businesses, everything collapses.  I ask the Leader to invite the relevant Minister to discuss this in the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order, I really want to protest at my treatment today.  The Cathaoirleach was prompted by the Clerk to interfere with me but I never mentioned any names.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>No&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>How dare anyone&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>No, please, Senator.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>The Cathaoirleach was prompted to interfere with me.  I did not mention any names.  I stood up and made a legitimate protection of a public servant&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;who is being targeted by the media as a political adviser when he is not a political adviser.  The Cathaoirleach interrupted me.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="126"/>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>I protest; the Cathaoirleach behaved disgracefully.  The Cathaoirleach had no right to interfere with me.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>It is quite easy to identify the person without naming them, and I do not want that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>I did not identify the person.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask Senator Harris to resume his seat.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>What is really disgusting is that I spoke to the Cathaoirleach before this sitting and I told him that I was not going to mention names&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;but that I was going to defend Mr. Dan Collins.  I am now going to mention his name.  The Cathaoirleach agreed with me at that time&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and now he has dodged it on prompting from the side.  This is disgraceful treatment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciated Senator Harris not naming the person.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>I did not name anyone.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I said that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>The Cathaoirleach was prompted and ran in to protect something that he was wrong about.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>No.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>The Cathaoirleach should have the decency to give me a chance.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>I never mentioned any names.  I did not mention John O&rsquo;Donoghue&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>No, and I am after saying to you&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>I did not mention Dan Collins.  I said &ldquo;Ceann Comhairle&rdquo; and the Cathaoirleach had no right to stop me.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have clearly stated&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EoghanHarris"><NameTxt>Senator Eoghan Harris</NameTxt>
	<P>I am getting out of here.</P>
     
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have clearly stated the Senator did not mention any name but I do not want Members to continue to speak in such a way that a person can be identified by a statement made.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="127"/>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Senators Fitzgerald and O&rsquo;Toole raised a very important issue regarding the legislation which provides for the new board of F&Aacute;S.  I am sure that, in common with most reasonable Members on all sides of the House, I regard this proposal as a totally retrograde step.  It does not provide for any checks or balances.  I am not opposed necessarily to political appointments; I recognise that people of talent may be members of a party.  However, as parliamentarians we have a duty to ensure provision for the vetting of appointees; this safety measure should be provided for in the Bill.  I strongly support those Senators who have raised the matter today.  I suggest that, at a minimum, such appointees should appear before a joint committee of both Houses prior to appointment.</P>
        <P>I want to return to a matter we have discussed previously, namely, safety at the world heritage site of Sceilig Mhich&iacute;l where sadly, as Senators are aware, we had the death of a second elderly person.  The steps are very steep; I know because I have been there.  Going up is all right but if one has any deficiency in one&rsquo;s eyesight, coming down is tricky, not to say precarious.  I do not see how a safety rope or rail would interfere.  I am sure all reasonable people would agree that safety must be paramount.  I urge the Leader to ensure the Minister accepts this point; it would not interfere one whit with the outstanding universal value of this ancient monastic site.  It is vital that we do not lose further time in ensuring the provision of a safety measure.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader arrange for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Eamon Ryan, to come to the House to discuss an anomaly whereby the midlands fisheries group of the Shannon Regional Fisheries Board has imposed charges for coarse and pike fishing?  Permits are required at a cost of &euro;37 annually, &euro;11 for one day, &euro;19 for 21 days, &euro;2 for juveniles, &euro;19 for pensioners and &euro;13 for juveniles annually.  These charges only apply to the River Suck, River Inny, River Bronsa, Little Brosna river and River Camlin, some of which are in the Leader&rsquo;s area.  It is grossly unfair that the charges apply in these areas but do not apply on the River Shannon which is only 10 km away.  We are trying to attract tourists to our area where imposing and enforcing these charges is very damaging to tourism.  We are trying to develop walkways in the Suck basin and encourage people to fish.  Having to pay for a permit will detract and discourage them.  It is not a level playing pitch.  Will the Leader arrange for the Minister to come to the House to explain why of all the fisheries board, the Shannon Regional Fisheries Board is the only one to impose these permit and licence charges?  This has been not a good year for tourism, particularly angling tourism.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader also ask the Minister to outline the position on Lanesboro and Shannonbridge peat power stations which will require serious levels of maintenance in 2010?  These flagship projects were well heralded in the area but it seems there are some deficiencies with the equipment and pipes which are causing erosion.  I would like the Minister to come to the House to explain the situation, to state whether the companies which built these stations gave compensation for the damage they caused and to outline the position regarding the ESB and Bord na M&oacute;na workers.  These are important issues and I hope the Leader will arrange for the Minister to attend the House to discuss them.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>I very much regret the incident that took place with Senator Harris some moments ago.  Whereas I am sometimes at the receiving end of your gavel, a Chathaoirligh, I believe you are entitled to have your response heard out.</P>
        <P>There is no doubt that the one issue being discussed is that of the Ceann Comhairle&rsquo;s expenses.  I would like a Seanad debate on the issue of our expenses as public representatives.  I do not believe in hanging courts or media-led campaigns to punish people for not complying with standards that were not properly laid out in the past.  I believe, however, in urgent and, if necessary, painful reform.  It is clear to people that many in the political class have been profli<Col N="128"/>gate.  It is fair to say we have scandalised the public.  It is also fair to say that self-regulation is a thing of the past.  It does not work.  I do not believe in self-regulation of the media and we certainly cannot rely on bankers to engage in ethical conduct on their own without assistance for regulation.  Civil servants do not appear to have been capable of reining in prolificacy.  While I am convinced that the Oireachtas commission is made up of good and sincere people, the public will not have confidence in the deliberations of an organisation, membership of which itself attracts expenses.</P>
        <P>We must face up to the fact that we need to seek the services of a trusted outside person.  I am thinking of somebody above reproach such as Mr. Justice Peter Kelly, who is well regarded, or a member of the Institute of Chartered Accountants who would take a root-and-branch look at the expenses of public representatives in the Legislature and also ministerial expenses.  The person must, however, be able to understand the political system and know there are expenses with which politicians must deal.  The person in question must take a realistic look at them and come up with a set of recommendations which we will all accept as fair but also adequate.  The bottom line is that we will have to get used to dealing with less.  That fact alone will bring us closer to the people we represent.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I was delighted with the significant &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote across the country but I must express my disappointment that it was not similar in Donegal.  I also believe, just like after the first Lisbon treaty referendum, those people who voted &ldquo;No&rdquo; should be asked why.  It may throw up some interesting answers as to the claims made by the &ldquo;No&rdquo; side.  It is to be hoped such an exercise could allay those voters&rsquo; fears.</P>
        <P>I respect people&rsquo;s right to vote either way.  Yesterday, I attended a Council of Europe meeting at which the response from other EU countries was unbelievably positive.  The youth directorate made great play of ensuring we told the people back in Ireland that they thought we did the right thing.  They were proud to see us back in the centre of the European Union.</P>
        <P>Will the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform attend the House to discuss the current status of the devolving of policing and justice powers to Northern Ireland.  Those of us in Donegal encounter an increased level of security when travelling in the North.  I accept this is due to a real terrorist risk which I do not underestimate.</P>
        <P>On the other side of security, I commend all involved in the recent police forces&rsquo; GAA tournament in Belfast in which the Garda team beat the New York Police Department, the London Metropolitan Police and the PSNI to win the tournament.  It was a queer change in times to have a GAA tournament of the security forces from four different backgrounds in Belfast and attended by the Minister for Culture, Arts and Leisure, Nelson McCausland, MLA.</P>
        <P>At this time of year we always talk about Hallowe&rsquo;en and the danger of fireworks.  This lunchtime I watched a report on UTV on the concerted effort that will be made through television and radio advertisements to achieve a two thirds reduction in injuries caused by fireworks in the North.  I ask that Senators contact RTE and the broadcasting media to see if they will and can contribute to making this Hallowe&rsquo;en a safer one for all who are going to enjoy themselves, legally or otherwise, with fireworks.  Too often we commend the work of the fire brigade etc. after the events that occur during Hallowe&rsquo;en rather than trying to pre-empt those events.</P>
    <HtmlBk SectId="2" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
      <Speaker pid="PaudieCoffey"><NameTxt>Senator Paudie Coffey</NameTxt>
	<P>Every politician of whatever hue should be concerned about the major damage done to the body politic.  Our democratic institutions are under attack, probably for very good reason.  Many of us who were on doorsteps campaigning for the Lisbon treaty know that people gritted their teeth and voted &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; to give themselves and the country every <Col N="129"/>opportunity to recover.  The public&rsquo;s angry mood is caused by the culture of excessive spending in the past ten to 15 years in which money was thrown at problems without regard to the implications or consequences.  Public finances have been wasted and we are hearing from the media and in this Chamber about excessive spending.  We can see that there has been a lack of transparency and accountability at the top in State agencies such as F&Aacute;S which I am sure is only the tip of the iceberg.  I reflect the view of ordinary people, colleagues, workers and families, who are seriously angry and losing faith and trust in the political democratic institutions of the State.  That is good reason to be concerned.  </P>
        <P>We need to debate the future of politics.  That people are losing trust is a reality, not a perception, as Senator Keaveney calls it.  I call on the Leader to arrange a debate on the future of politics and what politicians mean in this society because if we cannot lead from the front, I do not know what will happen to this society.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGerardHanafin"><NameTxt>Senator John Hanafin</NameTxt>
	<P>I share Senator Brady&rsquo;s concern about valuations.  It is time to have a debate about how the public service reacts to various situations.  The fact is a valuation made in 2005 affects a business in 2009 when the world economy has changed significantly and the retail and service sectors here are having an extremely difficult time.  We need to make it clear to the public service that we would like a fast-track reaction in order that businesses can be saved and jobs will not be lost.  The State ends up paying more than it loses in making sure business does not suffer excessive cost.</P>
        <P>I also share the views of those who would like to have a debate about how the public regards politicians.  Some members of the Opposition have misrepresented the situation in which the Government has found itself and its reasons for taking action.  The Opposition has often suggested the banks were bailed out to save the developers but nothing could be further from the truth.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should try another one. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGerardHanafin"><NameTxt>Senator John Hanafin</NameTxt>
	<P>They lauded other countries for doing the same and making sure their economies were safe.  When it happens here, they suggest it is done to save developers.  The spreading of such obvious untruths is not worthy of certain members of the Opposition.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Keaveney has asked that those who changed their minds on the Lisbon treaty be instructed to say why.  I am one of those who did so.  I was the first, or among the first, in this House to oppose, campaign and vote against the Lisbon treaty but I changed my mind because we had made substantial gains &mdash; we had retained the Commissioner and protected the tax regime.  Most important, however, from my point of view approximately two weeks before the referendum was held I received a written undertaking from the Government, in the form of a letter from the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Martin, that Ireland would oppose any attempt to create a Europe-wide munitions industry for export and commit itself to continuing to highlight the human rights of civilians in areas of armed conflict.  On balance, that was enough for me to change my mind and I make no apologies for campaigning against the first time and for this time.  </P>
        <P>The atmosphere outside the House today and on the airwaves is like that which preceded the French Revolution.  We are regarded as self-centred, self-appointed aristocrats who are uncaring and disinterested.  I fear the wheels of the tumbrils are beginning to turn.  I am not going to open up the case of the Ceann Comhairle but I will offer this little piece of advice.  There are a few elderly Senators such as I who remember when I made political charges against the then Cathaoirleach, charges which he was wise enough to know I could sustain.  However, I was a little brat and people looked forward to the opportunity of putting me in my box.  I <Col N="130"/>was hauled before a very undemocratic committee of inquiry to which I said I would go but only if I were allowed to cross examine and introduce witnesses etc.  The final point was that the Cathaoirleach could not be judge and jury.  He could not sit in the chair during an investigation of his own conduct.  I respectfully suggest to the Ceann Comhairle that he take the same decision because my view was sustained by the High Court.  That was a legal precedent and the Ceann Comhairle would be most unwise to chair an inquiry into his own case.</P>
        <P>On this matter, I disagree totally with Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan about trying to charge large amounts of money to the press for freedom of information searches.  These may be very uncomfortable for some of us &mdash; I am sure they are &mdash; and sometimes the facts are wildly misinterpreted by the journalists who seek them.  However, they are perfectly entitled to make the searches and trying to charge them excessively for this is mean-spirited, against the freedom of the press and completely wrong.</P>
        <P>I am very glad to see my colleague, Senator Ivana Bacik, in the House.  I am torn because it grieves me that she is now on the Labour Party benches.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes, yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>She will be greatly missed here.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>This is not relevant to the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>It is very relevant, if I may, with the greatest respect, contradict the Cathaoirleach.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator has contradicted me enough already.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I hope Senator Bacik will take a seat in the Government to come and that she will be made Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform in the tradition of Nora Owen from Fine Gael and M&aacute;ire Geoghegan Quinn from Fianna F&aacute;il.  I believe she will be outstanding in that role.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Norris, your time is well up.  I call on Senator MacSharry.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>(Interruptions).</i></P>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator MacSharry, without interruption, please.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Senator Marc MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>I agree with others, especially Senators Mullen, Norris and O&rsquo;Toole, that we should debate the issue of our expenses and remuneration.  I have said many times, most recently on &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; some weeks ago, there should be a reform of the remuneration of the entire public sector including those elected to these Houses, along with the expenses that pertain to all such positions, not least in the Seanad and D&aacute;il, but also at all levels within the Civil Service.  That should be done independently as a matter of the utmost urgency because I agree that anger is understandably palpable throughout all sections of civil society.  It is incumbent on all of us to deal with the issue decisively and very quickly.</P>
        <P>Regarding what Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan said, my perspective is that our expenses, and all public remuneration whether in RTE or in this House, whether as expenses or otherwise, should be a matter of public record.  It should be the case that when expenses are drawn down they are then available on a website, on that day or at that time.  Nobody has any issue they should wish to hide.  I certainly do not and if it should be the case that it is assessed independently that such expenses should be much lower then so be it.  I consider it a great honour to be in this <Col N="131"/>House, and it is as a matter of public service that any of us should be here.  I do not believe that any of my colleagues, on any side of the House, are here to make money.  However, if an independent assessment finds that our expenses should be significantly less, then so be it.  Let us do this as a matter of the utmost urgency.  I was particularly taken by Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s suggestion that it should be benchmarked against the private sector.</P>
         <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">3 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>I appeal to the Leader to initiate any steps that can be taken in this House to encourage social partnership to re-engage in a major way.  It should not be for IBEC and employers on the one hand, or the unions on the other, to dictate terms in advance regarding what can or cannot be on the table for discussion.  It is incumbent on them and all of us to encourage a process of social partnership.  At no other time in the history of the State was it more important to have co-operation and agreement.  People from all sides should be locked in a room until agreement is reached.  It is in the interests of all of us and was never as important as it is today.  I ask that we encourage the process to begin with the utmost urgency.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>I request an urgent debate and that the Minister for Health and Children, Deputy Mary Harney, should come to the House to discuss and guide Irish families on the issue of foreign adoption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid=""><NameTxt>Senators</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Regarding Vietnamese adoptions, over 250 couples are stuck in limbo.  They do not know where they are going and need direction and certainty.  Equally, 29 couples are on a Russian blacklist because the Minister of State has not completed the post-placement reports.  This is a very urgent matter.</P>
        <P>I join others in expressing the public&rsquo;s genuine and palpable anger at the high levels of excess in the public service.  I would like the Minister for Finance to come to the House to address this excess, especially at chief executive officer level.  We have heard the outrage with regard to Mr. Rody Molloy, the &euro;1.1 million add-on to his pension and the car.  The Minister who approved this, whether it was the Minister for Finance or the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, must be accountable for his or her actions.  This is taxpayers&rsquo; money which is needed to put toilet paper in schools, to offset education cuts and appease farmers who are at their wits&rsquo; end and are finding it difficult to make a living.  One cannot give away taxpayers&rsquo; money without being accountable for it.</P>
        <P>I agree with Deputy Enda Kenny.  If there is excess by a Minister, a Ceann Comhairle or a public servant, that person must be made pay it back.  If not, the Minister who approved the excess without bringing the matter before the Oireachtas for approval should pay it back.  The same is true of excess by the chief executive officer of the ESB or by Dr. Brendan Drumm who presided over the greatest failed experiment in this State, namely, the HSE.  This is wrong, obscene and immoral.</P>
        <P>I appeal to the Leader to bring the Minister for Finance to the House to tell Members what he will do about excess at these levels of the public service.  What are these people worth?  We do not know their outputs.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I call Senator Feeney.  Senator Healy Eames&rsquo;s time is up.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>We know they are failing us in terms of the State monopolies of which I have spoken.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator, you have made your point.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="132"/>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Senator Geraldine Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>I support colleagues who called for a debate on our expenses, on politicians in general and on our relationship with the public.  I agree with everyone who spoke.  There is palpable anger, frustration and annoyance among the public.  I agree with Senator Coffey when he says we must lead from the front.  If the public saw and heard us debating our expenses, they would be quite surprised to see there is nothing going on.  None of us is in politics to do wrong or to make money from our expenses.  None of us does.  However, when something goes wrong we are all tarred with the one brush.</P>
        <P>Some very reasonable and good suggestions have been made today.  I smiled when I heard Senator Mullen suggest we bring in an independent person to look at our expenses.  I thought that was done some months ago when A&amp;L Goodbody examined our expenses and Members, including myself, were interviewed about many matters, including expenses.  I smiled when I heard Senator Mullen suggest that a member of the Judiciary might be brought in.  What would the public think with regard to tribunals and the millionaires we have made out of them?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Do we really need them?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Senator Geraldine Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>When the Judiciary puts its own house in order with regard to the pension levy, its members might be considered.</P>
        <P>Senator Hannigan did not agree with the Taoiseach&rsquo;s endorsement of Mr. Tony Blair.  I commend the Taoiseach on supporting the candidature of Mr. Blair for president of Europe.  Eaten bread is soon forgotten.  Do we not recall Mr. Blair bringing peace to this small island?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>We remember him bringing war to Iraq.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Senator Geraldine Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>He brought peace to Senator Norris&rsquo;s island.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I call Senator Buttimer.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader join me in congratulating Deputy Enda Kenny on his Trojan work in the Lisbon treaty referendum campaign and the Fine Gael voters who bailed the Government out yet again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="GeraldineFeeney"><NameTxt>Senator Geraldine Feeney</NameTxt>
	<P>The Taoiseach has done so publicly.  Senator Buttimer should take a bow.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Perhaps the Cathaoirleach may clarify something for me.  It may be the Cork man in me, but I see nothing wrong in naming people in the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I do.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Two issues are dominating the homes, pubs and schoolyards of Ireland.  The first is the excesses in F&Aacute;S and the hand-out to Mr. Molloy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>These authorities can be discussed without naming officials or people outside the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Did I say anything wrong in the last sentence?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not want anyone to be named.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Mr. Molloy was given a hand-out that the Cathaoirleach, members of the public or I would not have received.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Hand-outs may have been justified.  I am not one to judge.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="133"/>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I will discuss the second largest issue being discussed today on &ldquo;Liveline&rdquo;, although I am not a fan of Joe Duffy&rsquo;s radio show.  If the Leader had canvassed with me last night, he would have seen that people were incensed by the excesses, not just of the Ceann Comhairle, but of the Government.  Will the Leader arrange a debate on the cost of running the Government?  It is absurd that a Minister who gets off a jet at an airport in any part of the country should have a State car waiting.  It is wrong.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Obscene.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator O&rsquo;Toole was right to mention governance by legislation, but governance begins with leadership.  Sadly, the Government is bereft of leadership because it has been in power for too long.  Government Members believe that &euro;400 for dinner is the norm, but it is not.  Thousands are struggling.</P>
        <P>The role of politicians should be enhanced &mdash; many fine people are involved &mdash; but Senator Coffey&rsquo;s point was a good one; we need a debate on the future of politics.  In approximately two months there will be anarchy on the streets.  It is building up.  Were Government Senators to canvass with us, they would see it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>They would be afraid to do so.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Ordinary people cannot pay their mortgage or meet child care costs and are sacrificing dinners, for example, to pay for medicines, uniforms or books for their children.  That is the reality.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State, Deputy Barry Andrews, is sitting on his hands while hundreds of families are distressed by the problems encountered in inter-country adoptions.  The T&aacute;naiste has not discussed in the House the matter of job creation, a debate I seek as a matter of urgency.  It is the greatest issue facing us, but the Government has no plan to deal with it.  The Duke of York, Senator Boyle, will roll down from the hilltop but, like Humpty Dumpty, the Government will not be able to put him or itself back together.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is enough.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CamillusGlynn"><NameTxt>Senator Camillus Glynn</NameTxt>
	<P>I join those who expressed satisfaction at the passing of the Lisbon treaty in the referendum.  I warmly congratulate the Taoiseach, the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Martin, and the Minister of State, Deputy Roche.  I also acknowledge the involvement of parties on the other side of the House.  The winning of the referendum was a victory for the people and common sense.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader invite the appropriate person, the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment &mdash; to come to the House at the earliest opportunity to debate the matter of insurance premia?  Some time ago the House rightly rejoiced in the fact that insurance premia had fallen.  However, the position has been reversed.  Someone I know received a quote for house insurance which showed an increase of slightly in excess of 125%.  Car insurance premia have increased in all cases.  When the person in question approached the insurance company involved, it stated, &ldquo;That is it.&rdquo;  In other words, like it or lump it.  It did not tell him to look elsewhere, but it might as well have done so.  At a time when hotels and the retail trade are reducing their prices and every Member has taken a cut in salary and expenses, something which might have been missed by some sections of the media, one section of the community is levying extravagant and outrageous percentage increases on those who desire car, company or house insurance.  Will this debate be held as soon as possible?</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="134"/>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>As time is almost up, I call Senator Quinn.  The five Members who have missed out will be called first tomorrow.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I will be brief.  Two weeks ago I raised the issue of the illegal importation of cigarettes.  The figures involved are considerable, amounting to some &euro;500 million to &euro;750 million a year.  What jolted me the most was the number of counterfeit cigarettes being imported into or produced in the country.  All cigarettes are dangerous, but counterfeits are even more so.</P>
        <P>My attention has since been drawn to the fact that counterfeit medicines, which are very dangerous, are also coming in.  My attention was drawn also to the fact that in two countries in Europe &mdash; Italy and Belgium &mdash; they have found a solution they believe works, that is, a barcoding of medicines to enable pharmacists detect counterfeit medicines.  I mention this because the figure I was given was 200,000 capsules or tablets coming into the country that are regarded as either illegal or counterfeit.  It is possible to do something about it.  They found a solution in Belgium and Italy.  It is called track and trace.  I ask the Leader to draw the Minister&rsquo;s attention to this as it is possible to use technology to solve these problems.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senators Fitzgerald, O&rsquo;Toole, Alex White, O&rsquo;Sullivan, Regan, Hannigan, Coghlan, Mullen, Coffey, Norris and Glynn congratulated everyone on the successful &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote in the Lisbon treaty referendum.  I congratulate the Taoiseach, the Government and the leaders of all other parties that supported the &ldquo;Yes&rdquo; vote.  I congratulate the people of Ireland, 58% of whom came out to vote in the Lisbon treaty referendum.  I salute them for the serious approach they took to their vote.  Taking account of the fact that non-nationals are not allowed vote in a local referendum it is possible that in excess of 70% of the population voted on that day while a further 10% may have been out of the country on holidays or for some other reason.  Therefore, the turnout for the referendum last Friday was huge.  It was uplifting for the people and the good example given by all political parties when they get together and show co-operation in the national interest shows how we can motivate our people to respond.  I say that because never was it more necessary to get an all-party consensus in regard to the challenges that will face us in the next 12 months in particular.  I say that also to those in the media who have a major responsibility to bring our people with us in these difficult times, particularly those in the media who earn very large salaries every week, month and year.  They have a duty and a responsibility in this regard.  The popularity of their radio and television shows can help to lead our people through these very difficult times.</P>
        <P>On the Bill published by the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, the Labour Services (Amendment) Bill and the regulations regarding F&Aacute;S, the Minister will be in the House and we look forward to discussing the Bill during its passage.  As Senator O&rsquo;Sullivan said earlier, we saw the good work local authority members did as members of health boards.  We saw the services our people got when local authority members were members of health boards at very little cost, although at huge cost in terms of time on the local authority member.  Members of local authorities, as well as Members on all sides of this House, should be allowed to serve on those boards because they are the voice and the watchdog of the people.  That is what is needed when we see what has emanated in the years during which local authority members have not been serving on various boards.</P>
        <P>Regarding the banks issue highlighted, it is my intention that we will have a discussion on the banks in the House at least once a fortnight.  I have given a commitment to the House in that regard.  I will endeavour to ensure that takes place next week as every day this week legislation will be before the House for the consideration of Members.</P><Col N="135"/>
        <P>Senators O&rsquo;Toole, Alex White, O&rsquo;Sullivan, Regan, Harris, Norris, MacSharry and Feeney expressed their concerns about issues in the public domain regarding Members&rsquo; expenses.  A root and branch review of Members&rsquo; expenses by Goodbody Economic Consultants has taken place.  The review is before the commission and it is up to the commission to make a decision regarding the proposals that have been placed before it by Goodbody&rsquo;s.  We have all taken a 25% reduction in our travel expenses, as have the public service, and we also have taken a 10% reduction in overnight allowances and whatever else goes with that, bringing us back to 1993 levels.  These are issues that should be brought to the attention of the people we in the Oireachtas are here to serve.  As Senator MacSharry said, it is a privilege bestowed on very few in any nation and we appreciate the privilege and honour of serving here in the Upper House.  We will not be found wanting in terms of anything that can be done to correct the current imbalance and tell the people the truth of the news.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I am sorry that INN will not continue as a broadcaster.  It gave a terrific service, particularly to those in rural areas where we were able to have local radio served.  I hope that some other format will be put in place because information about the truth of the news is the essence of democracy and I do not want democracy to be undermined in any shape or form, whether it is inside the country or outside it, by those who are paying tax here or those tax exiles who do not pay tax here.  We must be honest and frank with everyone because we as parliamentarians have done our bit in terms of bringing Ireland to where it is today from the time of the men and women of 1916 and 1921.  We have nothing to be ashamed of.  We are proud of the good work done on all sides of the House by all political parties, taoisigh and leaders who had the great honour to represent our country.  A serious imbalance is being created in the media morning, noon and night by people involved in the print media and those on the radio and television.</P>
        <P>We will have a debate in this House on the role of the media and I invite submissions from anyone in the media who has something to say in that regard.  The Broadcasting Commission of Ireland should take on the issue immediately.  Democracy must not be undermined by anybody, especially in our hour of need when there is a recession and a downturn in the economy worldwide.</P>
        <P>Senator Alex White asked me about the &euro;4 billion required to be obtained in savings in the budget.  I understood that was part of &euro;12 billion to &euro;13 billion in savings that would be required in the coming years.  It was around budget time that I realised that this &euro;4 billion in savings would be required in the coming budget.  I may be wrong about that.  I will get the matter clarified for the Deputy and come back to the House in the morning and inform the Senator of the up to date position on the serious question he asked.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P>That was not the question I asked.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I compliment Senator O&rsquo;Toole on a masterful performance last Sunday night on &ldquo;The Week in Politics&rdquo;.  He was around in 1987.  He has the enormous experience of addressing the need of the nation previously and someone like him, who is a distinguished Member of this House, gives people hope when he appears on such a popular show as &ldquo;The Week in Politics&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>On the issue raised by Senators O&rsquo;Sullivan, Harris and MacSharry, I have already addressed that in regard to the role of the media.  I agree with the Senators&rsquo; call this afternoon.</P>
        <P>Senators Brady and Hanafin called for a debate with the Minister for Finance present on the increase in rates.  Any local authority that quotes the valuations of 2005 is not living in the real world.  I will arrange to have an urgent debate here next week on the banks and other Department of Finance issues.  As Senator Buttimer said, the most important issue currently is <Col N="136"/>the sustainability of jobs.  We must do everything we can to help those who are in employment at the present time and quoting a 2005 valuation is not living in the real world when the valuations of today are at least one third less than what they were in 2005.  I hope Senator Brady&rsquo;s request to have the Minister present to make the case that has been made here earlier will be granted next week.</P>
        <P>I will pass Senator Coghlan&rsquo;s views on to the Minister regarding the world heritage site where, unfortunately, the person died.  I realise there is an urgent need&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>That is the second in a short space of time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;for safety measures.  I will pass on the Senator&rsquo;s request.  I am aware the Senator will be speaking to his county manager who is working very closely with the OPW on this issue with a view to seeing if it can be addressed in the coming week.</P>
        <P>Senator Leyden called for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Eamon Ryan, to address in the House the issues he highlighted, namely, the imposition of fees and charges by the Shannon Regional Fisheries Board, especially in respect of fishing on the rivers Suck and Inny, which is in my area in County Westmeath.  I will certainly mention this to the Minister and ask him to come to the House to clarify this matter and the matter of Lanesborough and Shannonbridge power stations, which are being refurbished, and to clarify the position on the ESB and Bord na M&oacute;na workers.</P>
        <P>Senator Keaveney called for the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to be called to the House to update Members on the transfer of the justice portfolio from Britain to the North.  I can certainly make inquiries into this.  I commend all those involved in the GAA tournament.  Who would have thought some years ago that this would occur?  Senator Keaveney also pointed out the dangers of Hallowe&rsquo;en fireworks and highlighted the need to make everywhere safe at Hallowe&rsquo;en.  I agree with her in this regard and will pass on her request to the Minister.</P>
        <P>Senator Coffey called for a debate on the future of politics in this country.  I have no difficulty in allowing time for this.  The debate may be coupled with other debates.</P>
        <P>Senator MacSharry referred to the need for a return to social partnership, which is of the utmost importance.  We have always said the success of the country over the past 22 years was based on the great work done through social partnership.  I agree with Senator MacSharry and will pass on his strong views to the Minister after the Order of Business.</P>
        <P>Senator Healy Eames referred to foreign adoptions and the difficulties being experienced by many couples in Ireland in this regard.  I certainly agree with her in respect of her concerns.  As we all know, the Minister of State went to Vietnam to try to do whatever he could in this area.  When I receive a further update on the matter, I will bring the information to the attention of the House.  I will pass on the Senator&rsquo;s views to the Minister of State.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister of State needs to come to the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>With regard to Senator Buttimer&rsquo;s remarks, I have already responded on the call for a debate on the future of politics.  I fully agree with the Senator&rsquo;s sentiments on job creation.</P>
        <P>Senator Glynn called for a debate on insurance premia, including for public liability, employers&rsquo; liability and commercial and private motor insurance.  As the Senator stated, there <Col N="137"/>has been a huge increase in the cost of insurance.  As the person who chaired the insurance inquiry for four years, from 2003 to 2007, I certainly do not understand why the cost of insurance premia is now increasing.  Our colleague, Deputy Willie Penrose, will be examining this matter as Chairman of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Enterprise, Trade and Employment.</P>
        <P>My advice to the public is to shop around for insurance.  Given that I am still very closely involved with the insurance industry and that the committee I chaired worked for four years to lower the cost of insurance and save tens of millions of euro for the premium holders in 2007, I conclude that customers should go back to their brokers and determine whether they can get a better deal.  I understand brokers are now doing very good work to lower premia for premium holders.  If the premium holders do not know where to go and have no recourse, they should ask a different broker to obtain a quotation.  Although circumstances may have been different in the past, my dealings with brokers have been pretty successful.</P>
        <P>Senator Quinn referred to illegal cigarettes and the confiscation thereof by Customs and Excise and the Garda.  I certainly agree with the Senator&rsquo;s sentiments, including on the need for bar codes on medicines and other products.  This is certainly a very good idea and I fully support the call.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Transport Regulation Bill 2009:" RHead="Committee Stage"> 
    <Title>Public Transport Regulation Bill 2009: Committee Stage. </Title>
        <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 2.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 1 and 12 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 1:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 6, between lines 44 and 45, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2" el="5">&ldquo;<?oasys _is0p2- ?>&ldquo;road passenger transport operator&rsquo;s licence&rdquo; means a national or international road passenger transport operator&rsquo;s licence within the meaning of section 2 of the Road Traffic and Transport Act 2006;&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P el="0">It is a requirement in law that a bus operator hold a valid road passenger transport operator&rsquo;s licence.  It was brought to the Minister&rsquo;s attention in the discussions in the Chamber on Second Stage and elsewhere that it is currently not the case that an individual who has his road passenger transport operator&rsquo;s licence revoked automatically has his bus licence revoked.  The point was made very strongly in the Chamber and elsewhere that an applicant who must demonstrate he is of sound financial standing, good repute and holds a certificate of professional competence but who, for whatever reason, has his licence revoked, ought also to have his other licence revoked.  The provisions in amendment No. 1, which pertains to section 2, and amendment No. 12, which pertains to section 19, give effect to this desirable objective.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I am not sure I understand exactly the point the Minister of State is making but it seems the limited reform effected by this Bill will not apply to the vast majority of the public transport services.  The amendment states a road passenger transport operator&rsquo;s licence means a national or international road passenger transport operator&rsquo;s licence within the meaning of section 2 of the Road Traffic and Transport Act 2006.  Is the Government currently <Col N="138"/>negotiating contracts for public service obligations with CIE companies?  Are they to be completed before this Bill is adopted?  If so, this will keep the services provided by Dublin Bus, Bus &Eacute;ireann and Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann outside the remit of the new transport authority.  Is it correct that this will be for ten years?  By preventing competition in the procurement of the services, is the Government not depriving the public of the opportunity to have public transport services provided in an efficient way?  I am not sure this is the point of the legislation.  I do not understand the reason for it, bearing in mind the possibility of the negotiations being delayed.  The Government needs to refrain from entering into the ten-year contracts with the CIE companies in advance of the implementation of this legislation to allow some sort of competition.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the amendment which seems obvious and logical.  If an operator is deemed unfit, he should be deemed unfit right across the board, in which case it would be inappropriate for him to operate with another licence.  I have no difficulty in supporting the amendment which seems to be logical and which should be dealt with quickly.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</P>
        <P>Sections 3 to 5, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 6.</P>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 7, subsection (1), line 25, to delete &ldquo;licence&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;contract&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Tony Killeen.  I am delighted, as I am sure all my colleagues are, to see him operating at full capacity again and I wish him very well in future.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>This is the first substantial legislation in 77 years to deal with public transport.  It is vital to get it right because the opportunity may not arise again for a considerable period.  This is a real opportunity to introduce healthy and open competition into the public transport system and finally end the predatory practices of both Dublin Bus and Bus &Eacute;ireann in trying to force transparent and healthy competitors off the public transport market.</P>
        <P>The amendment changes the word &ldquo;licence&rdquo; to &ldquo;contract&rdquo; and although this may seem a little pedantic on first glance, the difference between those two words, in my opinion, can dictate in what direction we want to move in order to reform our public transport system.  My party and I believe that retaining the word &ldquo;licence&rdquo; in this instance implies we will more or less continue with the <i>status quo</i>.  It also implies that the newly constituted national transport authority will simply take over the licensing of bus routes from the Department of Transport nationally, as distinct from what happens within the greater Dublin area.</P>
        <P>Use of the word &ldquo;contract&rdquo; would imply a far different approach nationally and reflect the approach taken by the Minister, Deputy Noel Dempsey, in bringing forward the legislation last year for the Dublin Transport Authority.  It would ensure that every aspect of servicing a new or existing bus route would be part of a new tendering process, including, for example, whether a new operator might choose to avail of PSO subsidies.</P>
        <P>The word &ldquo;contract&rdquo;, as used in the DTA Act of 2008, implies that following a comprehensive assessment of a particular transport need, a real competitive tendering process to fulfil that <Col N="139"/>need would take place, and similar to all public tenders, such a tender would be openly advertised.  The licensing system implies that a cloak and dagger aspect would remain in how these public transport needs are serviced.  An open and transparent tendering process, with a contract awarded at the end, would address that fear.</P>
        <P>The explanatory memorandum for the Bill states this legislation will provide for the introduction of new contractual arrangements for the procurement of public land transport services.  This would lead one to believe that the Bill would use the word &ldquo;contract&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;licence&rdquo; but the word &ldquo;licence&rdquo; is used liberally throughout the legislation.  The difference may be subtle but it dictates exactly where the Minister wishes to go with the Bill.  He does not want to go the route of transparent and open competition but rather a less attractive route of retaining some of the more protectionist aspects of the current system.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Cannon has put the point eminently and I second the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the amendment.  I had not quite understood the difference between the two words but I understand why the amendment, to delete &ldquo;licence&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;contract&rdquo;, has been proposed.  This Bill does not apply to services which are the subject of a public transport service contract entered into under section 48 of the 2008 Act.  The Minister of State might correct me on that.</P>
        <P>These service contracts are for any public transport where there is an element of public service obligation, and these include all the activities of Dublin Bus, the vast majority of activities of Bus &Eacute;ireann and under the 2008 Act, the Dublin Transport Authority, soon to be renamed the national transport authority, will enter into a long-term public service contract of ten or more years for the provision of these services.  The CIE group will continue to provide these services when the 2008 Act is commenced.</P>
        <P>Will the Minister of State assure me of the implications of this?  The effort of this amendment, which was explained well by Senator Cannon, is aimed at doing this precisely.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I have a small point.  This is a refining of the import of the Bill because as I see it, a licence is a permission to operate.  A contract suggests both the permission to operate and a slightly greater emphasis on the duties, obligations and responsibilities of the operator, both morally and legally.  For that reason it is perhaps the better word.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>The difference between &ldquo;contract&rdquo; and &ldquo;licence&rdquo; in this Bill is that in the case of a contract, there is a public service obligation; in other words it is a loss-making service.  A licence applies to commercial services, which is an important distinction in the 2008 Bill and continues in this one.  I understand the point being made by Senator Cannon, which is slightly different and perhaps more pertinent to different legislation.</P>
        <P>In response to the original point made by Senator Quinn, I should have made it clear that this is one of a number of pieces of legislation which will be brought forward by the Minister for Transport.  In some cases, elements mentioned by the Senator are more appropriate to the other legislation.</P>
        <P>It is important to point out that the road transport operator licence applies to all operators, both public and private, and that is an important element of the Bill.  Contracts of five years are being negotiated and issues regarding contracts are somewhat different.  This relates to some extent to amendments Nos. 1 and 12.  With regard to this amendment, the contract regime applies to the public service obligation and the licensing regime applies to the licence for a service which is commercial.</P><Col N="140"/>
        <P>The primary focus of this Bill is to establish a modern system for the licensing of commercial and public bus passenger services.  The sections in Part 2 of the Bill set out the parameters to support the new framework.  Section 6 provides that national bus passenger services other than those provided subject to public transport services contracts or an international service may only be provided under a licence granted under this particular Bill.  A person who provides such a service without the required licence would be committing an offence.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">4 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>The Bill provides for the introduction of new contractual arrangements for the procurement of public land transport services on a national basis, and it is modelled on the approach established in the DTA Act from 2008 in respect of the greater Dublin area.  That is facilitated by the amendment of the DTA Act in Part 3 of the Bill.  The provisions of section 6 relate to the bus licensing regime and in that context the use of the term &ldquo;contract&rdquo; to describe the bus licence involved would be inappropriate.  It would also lead to confusion, with the separate contracting regime relating to the procurement of public transport services as provided in the DTA Act of 2008.</P>
        <P>As this would undermine elements of the Bill, the term &ldquo;contract&rdquo; would relate to public service obligations or loss-making services, and &ldquo;licence&rdquo; would relate to commercial services.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
      
        <P Just="Left">The Seanad divided by electronic means.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>In the absence of one of the tellers, this vote must be retaken.  I apologise to the Members present.  As there also was some confusion regarding the change in seating arrangements, this may be rectified for the next vote.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order, in such circumstances should Members not have a manual vote?  The place where my colleague should vote does not appear to be clear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not have any problem with that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Did Senator Mullen seek a manual vote?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RonanMullen"><NameTxt>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I will allow it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I have no objection.</P></Speaker>
        <P>Question again put: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
      
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Committee divided: T&aacute;, 28; N&iacute;l, 15.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading>
        <YesVote pid="IvanaBacik">Bacik, Ivana.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MartinBrady">Brady, Martin.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LarryButler">Butler, Larry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PeterCallanan">Callanan, Peter.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="IvorCallely">Callely, Ivor.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnCartyFF">Carty, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DonnieCassidyFF">Cassidy, Donie.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MariaCorrigan">Corrigan, Maria.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarkDaly">Daly, Mark.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="GeraldineFeeney">Feeney, Geraldine.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnGerardHanafin">Hanafin, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DominicHannigan">Hannigan, Dominic.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="CeciliaKeaveney">Keaveney, Cecilia.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="TerryLeyden">Leyden, Terry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarcMacSharry">MacSharry, Marc.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LisaMcDonald">McDonald, Lisa.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianODomhnaill">&Oacute; Domhnaill, Brian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DennisODonovan">O&rsquo;Donovan, Denis.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="NedOSullivan">O&rsquo;Sullivan, Ned.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AnnOrmonde">Ormonde, Ann.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="KieranPhelan">Phelan, Kieran.</YesVote><Col N="141"/>
        <YesVote pid="PhilPrendergast" head="y">Prendergast, Phil.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrendanRyan"><?oasys _mv-7- ?>Ryan, Brendan.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JimWalsh"><?oasys _mv-7- ?>Walsh, Jim.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AlexWhite">White, Alex.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MaryMWhite">White, Mary M.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</YesVote>
        <NHeading>N&iacute;l</NHeading>
        <NoVote pid="PaulBradford">Bradford, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaddyBurke">Burke, Paddy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JerryButtimer">Buttimer, Jerry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CiaranCannon">Cannon, Ciaran.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaudieCoffey">Coffey, Paudie.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulCoghlan">Coghlan, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FrancesFitzgerald">Fitzgerald, Frances.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FidelmaHealyEames">Healy Eames, Fidelma.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="NickyMcFadden">McFadden, Nicky.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="RonanMullen">Mullen, R&oacute;n&aacute;n.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DavidNorris">Norris, David.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JoeOReilly">O&rsquo;Reilly, Joe.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FergalQuinn">Quinn, Feargal.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="EugeneRegan">Regan, Eugene.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="ShaneRoss">Ross, Shane.</NoVote>
        <Tellers>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Denis O&rsquo;Donovan and Diarmuid Wilson; N&iacute;l, Senators Ciaran Cannon and Paul Coghlan.</Tellers>
        <Decision><?oasys _is0p11- ?>Question declared carried.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <HtmlBk SectId="3" />
        <P>Section 6 agreed to.</P>
        <P>Sections 7 to 9, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 10.</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 8, subsection (1), between lines 28 and 29, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;(<i>a</i>) shall have regard to the desirability of ensuring that operators of public bus services are not treated less favourably than operators of private bus services,&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This amendment proposes to insert text into the general provisions for the consideration of applications for grant of licences section.  The amendment seeks a level playing field so public operators are not discriminated against.  I referred to this aspect, which is important to the Labour Party, on Second Stage.  The Minister indicated he intended to provide a level playing field.  There is now an emphasis on new contractors and new people coming in.  The statement should be made that this is particularly important.  Public service operators should not be treated less favourably than operators of private bus services.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I support this amendment.  This is an important section because it decides the principle under which large elements of the legislation will operate.  It is important that we support our public transport system as strongly as possible.  I was never an advocate of privatisation.  I regard the privatisation of Aer Lingus and Eircom as disasters.  Without any suggestion of a party affiliation, which I do not have, one could suggest that I am an old-fashioned Lemass-style supporter of public investment in public utilities.  It is a good thing that we ensure we have a strong public transport sector.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The amendment states that, among the principles to be regarded under this section, it will have regard to the desirability of ensuring that operators of public bus services are not treated less favourably than operators of private bus services but they are quite often.  One example is that the State bus company is required to provide off-street parking for vehicles but there <Col N="142"/>appears to be no such requirement on private bus companies.  The latter park all over the joint.  I can give an example from my local area, which I raised at the central area policing committee on Monday.  Mountjoy Square is lined from end to end with buses, mostly private buses, despite the fact there are no less than four cr&egrave;ches on the square.  Small children, infants and toddlers are emerging from between the buses yet there is no requirement, as there is on Bus &Eacute;ireann, to provide off-street parking.  We should have a level playing field.  That is one area the Minister of State would be well advised to examine.</P>
        <P>I wish to comment on the general context in which this takes place.  I welcome much of what is included in the section and the language used, particularly in section 10(1)(<i>b</i>)(i) which reads, &ldquo;the need to provide a well-functioning, attractive, competitive, integrated and safe public transport system of services and networks for all users&rdquo;.  I commend the Minister of State, his advisers and the drafters for including the word &ldquo;attractive&rdquo;.  If the public is given a scuttery, old, diseased looking service with awful buses, it will treat it with the contempt that the bus service treats passengers.</P>
        <P>I very much hope the metro project will go ahead.  If it does, it will be in a period of financial stringency.  Nevertheless, it should be an attractive service.  We should not have ugly, functional, concrete metro stations because they would be a waste of time and money and would be treated with contempt and vandalised.  When I was a member of the Joint Committee on Transport, I expressed ideas about how it should be done.  While I am positive towards many elements of the Bill, I strongly agree with the Labour Party&rsquo;s amendment on supporting public transport.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I forgot to welcome the Minister of State earlier.  The amendment proposes to include the wording, &ldquo;shall have regard to the desirability of ensuring that operators of public bus services are not treated less favourably than operators of private bus services&rdquo;.  I am happy to support this on condition that it would also ensure a provision that private bus operators would not be discriminated against in favour of public bus operators.  I am a huge believer in competition which I believe is worthwhile and worthy of support.  I am delighted to see Senator O&rsquo;Malley present because I know she has the same view.  Senator Norris and I agree on many things but I do not agree with him on Mr. Lemass who was a great supporter of public utilities until they were able to hold their own.  He then believed in putting them in private hands.</P>
        <P>Recently, I came through the airport and was impressed by the bus services which operate from there compared to five or six years ago when there was only one bus service to Bus&aacute;ras.  Now, there is a wealth of services to various destinations.  This has improved the service to the public no end.  We are also familiar with competition between airlines.  I am sure all of us remember that it used to cost &pound;290 to get to London because only two state companies operated on the route.  Since competition was introduced the difference has been huge.</P>
        <P>I fully believe in ensuring we do not discriminate against private bus services but I also support the public bus services and it must be ensured they can provide services also.  We should not discriminate.  I support what Senator Ryan stated on condition that we would add another amendment on private bus operators not being discriminated against in favour of public bus operators.  However, it would be far better to have no amendment rather than two which contradict each other.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FionnaOMalleyPD"><NameTxt>Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Malley</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I agree with what Senator Quinn stated; one cannot include an amendment which gives preferential treatment to one group over another.  One should expect that all will be treated equally and that is what we expect to happen under the Bill.  It would be incorrect to include a provision to express that one group of operators would be given <Col N="143"/>preference over others; we should leave out this type of provision.  We need to have a level playing field as soon as possible.</P>
        <P>I am glad Senator Quinn recognises competition has been very good for the public bus service.  The travelling public needs to remember this.  Time and again Members decry what competition has done and state it is outrageous and dreadful and that anybody who wants to provide a service in competition to a public service is some type of fly by night profiteer.  I lament this.  It is most unfortunate to suggest private operators operate to different safety standards.  Of course, everybody operates to the same high standards, which is as it should be.  The Bill will introduce an expectation that everybody will be treated equally.  That is why we cannot countenance an amendment which would offer preference to a particular group.  References such as this need to be left out.  We need to keep matters as clear and easy as possible for everybody who wants to provide a service for the travelling public.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I support the stance adopted by Senators Quinn and O&rsquo;Malley on this issue.  I have grave concerns about affording preference to one sector over another.  I do not agree with Senator Norris on what he terms retaining a public transport system.  The transport system he described as public has only one function, which is to serve the public need.  Whether that service is provided by the public or private sector is irrelevant as long as it is provided to the proper standard and complies with whatever regulations are in place on safety.</P>
        <P>The country&rsquo;s experience in the past 20 years has been that when the private sector is offered the opportunity to provide a service for the public, it does so with great aplomb.  In the case of public transport, it ends up not alone with a saving for those availing of the service but also with a saving for the taxpayer.  In the mid-1980s my brother lived in London, where he secured his first job after he left college.  He rang home to Galway at weekends because he was able to do so for free.  This was at a time when we had only Eircom which charged us punitive rates.  I found it extraordinary that he could ring his home in the west free of charge from London at weekends.  That happened because the British Government had introduced competition into the arena.  We have seen what happened with Ryanair and mobile phone companies.</P>
        <P>The public service transport system is in place to serve the public and provide the best possible value for the taxpayer.  It is not in place to serve those who want to engage in outmoded work practices harking back to the 19th century when it was dictated that buses must pass along O&rsquo;Connell Street with other such nonsense.  I do not subscribe to an amendment that seeks to provide favoured treatment for one sector over another.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I am not shattered by surprise that Senator Cannon agrees with his former colleague, Senator O&rsquo;Malley.  They would not be ideologically poles apart.  </P>
        <P>With regard to the transport service, I am reading a very interesting history of north Dublin city and county, illustrated by antique photographs.  One of the stories is about the collapse of certain sections of the private transport service in that area in the early and middle part of the 20th century; therefore, it does not always work.  The people were left stranded.</P>
        <P>I will make one delicate comment; I admire immensely my colleague, Senator Quinn, and like to believe we share a friendship but, of course, we do not agree on everything.  He stated he had seen the buses at Dublin Airport and rather admired them.  He did not state he had taken one.  I rest my case.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to point out to Senators Cannon and O&rsquo;Malley that the amendment does not seek more favourable treatment for the operators of public bus services.  It would require that they not be treated less favourably; in other words, that they be treated equally.  In the push for the privatisation of Irish Rail, Dublin Bus and Bus &Eacute;ireann, there is a <Col N="144"/>danger that we will throw the baby out with the bath water.  The public operators which have done a good job during the years and can compete may be forgotten.  The amendment is not seeking preferable treatment for the operators of public bus services.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister for Transport, Deputy Noel Dempsey, has made it clear he wants a level playing field between the public and private sector.  However, Senator Ryan and his party colleagues have concerns in this regard.  The Minister is satisfied the provisions of the Bill, as drafted, make it clear that they apply to all licence applicants, both privately and publicly owned services, and offer no distinction between bus licence applications submitted by either private or public sector operators.</P>
        <P>The need for the inclusion of the amendment is not well founded.  It has been suggested the inclusion of such a provision might give rise to some doubt as to whether the substantive provisions of the Bill were based on the level playing field concept that the Minister has referred to as a starting point.  If the amendment were accepted, it would set off the concerns raised by Senators Quinn, O&rsquo;Malley and Cannon about unbalancing the legislation&rsquo;s provisions.  Accepting the amendment would not contribute to good legislation.</P>
        <P>The Bill&rsquo;s primary purpose is to establish a modern system for the licensing of commercial public bus passenger services and to promote regulated competition in the provision of licensed public bus passenger services on a national basis in the public interest.  Some believe regulated competition is an inherently self-contradictory concept.  There are, however, many successful such provisions at European level.  Many of us will have seen such success in other European cities and aspire to having the same standard of public transport here.  Part 2 was prepared on this basis.  It establishes a new regulatory licensing regime that will apply to all commercial public bus services, including those provided by Bus &Eacute;ireann and Dublin Bus.  It also features a modern set of criteria against which applications for licences will be considered.  In this regard, section 10 sets down the factors to be taken into account by the authority when considering applications.  These criteria have to be considered equally, regardless of whether it is a private or public sector applicant.  Such considerations must be pursued, having regard to the general objectives of the authority provided for in section 10 of the Dublin Transport Authority Act 2008.  This will be updated through a proposed amendment to section 28 of the Bill.  These objectives also highlight the development of an integrated transport system and achieving regulated competition in the provision of licensed public bus passenger services in the public interest.</P>
        <P>Bus stops and bus parking, issues raised by Senator Norris, are regulated by local authorities and the regulations enforced by the Garda and local authority traffic wardens.  The issue is not pertinent to this legislation.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 4 to 6, inclusive, are related and will be discussed together.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 4:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 8, subsection (1)(<i>b</i>), line 37, to delete &ldquo;any or all of&rdquo; and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;subparagraph (iii) of, and such other subparagraphs as are appropriate of,&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">The problem with section 10(1)(<i>b</i>) is that the phrase &ldquo;any or all of&rdquo; leaves it too open for the authority when considering the 11 factors in granting a licence.  Section 10(1)(<i>b</i>)(<i>iii</i>) refers to <Col N="145"/>&ldquo;the impact a proposed public bus passenger service would have on public passenger transport services&rdquo;.  The Labour Party believes the section, as drafted, could allow the national transport authority to ignore this factor.  The impact on public services must be considered in every case.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>Section 10 establishes a set of general provisions which will inform the consideration of applications for bus licences by the authority.  Section 10(1)(<i>b</i>) sets out 11 matters which the authority may consider.  It is important to remember that not all of these may be pertinent to particular applications.  In the case of certain categories, the consideration of all, or any of these matters, may not be warranted.  This is particularly the case in section 10(1)(<i>b</i>)(<i>iii</i>) which relates to the potential impact of a proposed service on public bus passenger services being provided under the terms of a public transport services contract.</P>
        <P>A definite policy decision was made in the preparation of the legislation that the consideration of the impact on contract services would not be mandatory in respect of all applications and instead would be a matter for determination by the authority.  It was recognised that to require the consideration of this matter in all cases was unnecessary, given the range of bus services that present themselves for licensing, many of which would have no impact on public service obligation services.  It will be left to the discretion of the authority to decide, for example, whether once-off services would need to be considered in the context of the 11 provisions listed in the section.  For example, it would not be required of the authority to consider all 11 provisions for a one-off service to a concert, a ploughing championship or sports event.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">5 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>Amendment No. 5 relates to section 10(1)(<i>b</i>) and the development of an integrated transport system which contributes to environmental sustainability and social cohesion, promotes economic progress and the provision of a well functioning, attractive, integrated and safe public transport system.  I note Senator Norris welcomed the term &ldquo;attractive&rdquo;.  It should be noted that the consideration to be addressed by the authority in section 10 relating to bus licence applications must also have regard to the general objectives of the authority.  Section 10(1)(<i>b</i>)(<i>i</i>) also states, &ldquo;the need to provide a well-functioning, attractive, competitive, integrated and safe public transport system of services and networks for all users&rdquo;.  The Minister is satisfied these provisions are sufficient to provide adequate protection for the integrity of national, urban and local bus networks.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 6 also relates to section 10 of the 2008 Act, as substituted by the amendment in section 28(1)(<i>c</i>).  These include the objective of seeking to achieve regulated competition in the provision of licensed public transport bus passenger services.  This is further developed by the provisions of the following section which recognises the need to provide a well functioning service.  The Minister believes these considerations would not be enhanced by the wording proposed in the three amendments.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>The object of amendment No. 5 is to prevent the cherry-picking of profitable routes while leaving loss-making and more troublesome routes to State companies.  It would also ensure a free-for-all would not be allowed in the bus sector with competition strictly regulated.  These are important amendments which would improve the legislation and are worthy of acceptance by the Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>Many aspects of the legislation are enabling.  For example, section 23 requires the authority to consider and prepare guidelines against many of the considerations which are of concern to Senator Ryan. It is difficult in primary legislation of this nature to provide all of the detail which the authority would need to consider.  The 11 considerations set out in the Bill are, in the Minister&rsquo;s view and mine, sufficiently inclusive and comprehensive to take account of the concerns of Senator Ryan and others and to give the authority the flexibility it needs to enable it to do its job efficiently and effectively.   </P>
      </Speaker><Col N="146"/>
        <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Committee divided: T&aacute;, 25; N&iacute;l, 6.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading>
        <YesVote pid="MartinBrady">Brady, Martin.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LarryButler">Butler, Larry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PeterCallanan">Callanan, Peter.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="IvorCallely">Callely, Ivor.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnCartyFF">Carty, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DonnieCassidyFF">Cassidy, Donie.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MariaCorrigan">Corrigan, Maria.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarkDaly">Daly, Mark.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="GeraldineFeeney">Feeney, Geraldine.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="CeciliaKeaveney">Keaveney, Cecilia.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="TerryLeyden">Leyden, Terry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarcMacSharry">MacSharry, Marc.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="RonanMullen">Mullen, R&oacute;n&aacute;n.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianODomhnaill">&Oacute; Domhnaill, Brian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DennisODonovan">O&rsquo;Donovan, Denis.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FionnaOMalleyPD">O&rsquo;Malley, Fiona.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="NedOSullivan">O&rsquo;Sullivan, Ned.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AnnOrmonde">Ormonde, Ann.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="KieranPhelan">Phelan, Kieran.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FergalQuinn">Quinn, Feargal.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="ShaneRoss">Ross, Shane.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MaryMWhite">White, Mary M.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</YesVote>
        <NHeading>N&iacute;l</NHeading>
        <NoVote pid="IvanaBacik">Bacik, Ivana.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DominicHannigan"><?oasys _mv-7- ?>Hannigan, Dominic.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DavidNorris"><?oasys _mv-7- ?>Norris, David.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JoeOToole">O&rsquo;Toole, Joe.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="BrendanRyan">Ryan, Brendan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="AlexWhite">White, Alex.</NoVote>
        <Tellers>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Fiona O&rsquo;Malley and Diarmuid Wilson; N&iacute;l, Senators Dominic Hannigan and Brendan Ryan.</Tellers>
        <Decision><?oasys _is0p11- ?>Question declared carried.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
      
        <P>Amendments Nos. 5 and 6 not moved.</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 7:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 9, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following subsections:</P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;(3) The Authority shall invite and consider submissions from any local authority whose functional area includes a place to which the application relates.</P>
        <P LI="1">(4) The making of a submission under <i>subsection (3) </i>shall be a reserved function.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Amendment No. 7 speaks for itself.  It ensures that applications for bus routes are considered by local authorities and, therefore, by local representatives.  This should form part of the Bill and would improve it by involving local authorities and councillors.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>The existing provisions of section 10(2) of the Bill allow the authority to consider submissions from or on behalf of a licensed applicant, to invite submissions or information from the applicant or any other party and to examine any other matter it deems relevant to the public interest.  These provisions are such to facilitate the invitation and consideration of submissions from any local authority that may have an interest in individual applications, particularly where the proposed bus routes would operate within the functional area of the local authority concerned.  However, section 10(2)<i>(b)</i> gives discretion to seek the views of interested parties where appropriate, including local authorities.</P><Col N="147"/>
        <P>The Minister, Deputy Noel Dempsey, is satisfied the existing wording of subsection (2) allows the local authority participation in the application process.  Amendment No. 7 seeks to introduce the requirement for the authority to invite and consider local authority submissions in the case of all bus licence applications.  The amendment also stipulates that the making of a submission by the local authority will be a reserved function of the local authority which would require input from the elected members and a resolution to be passed at a meeting of the authority.</P>
        <P>The Minister is not convinced of the need for such a provision and has some concerns that it would result in unnecessary delays in the consideration of some bus licence applications by the authority.  It is clear that not all bus licence applications would warrant a specific input from the individual local authorities, for example, in the case of occasional licences for one-off events.  In addition, the introduction of a reserve function in respect of the making of submissions and applications would delay unduly the processing of applications and does not assist in improving the processing of bus licence applications in the interests of the need of the public and of consumers in general.  The Minister&rsquo;s view is that the authority needs flexibility to decide these matters.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>I accept the comments of the Minister of State and do not intend to press this amendment today.  There may be some merit in his words.  As we see it, the difference, or strengthening, the amendment would bring about is that the authority would invite and consider submissions from any local authority whose functional area is affected.  The amendment would strengthen the Bill and we feel it is appropriate.  I will not press it but reserve the possibility of doing so on Report Stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P Just="Left">Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 8:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 9, subsection (3), between lines 23 and 24, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="1">&ldquo;(<i>a</i>) he or she complies strictly with the best labour, health and safety standards,&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Amendment No. 8 is self-explanatory and I have nothing further to say.  Senator Bacik wishes to speak on it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I support this amendment because I believe it is essential to the principle of the licensing scheme envisaged in the Bill, namely, that standards would be applied to the provision of such services.  Given the current economic context, it is very important that we stipulate that certain standards should be maintained in respect of labour conditions and health and safety matters.  The Minister may respond by saying this is unnecessary because there is legislation in place already to protect health and safety matters and labour conditions.  It is important, nonetheless, to insert a specific provision on this where we are providing the conditions for the grant of a licence and the criteria by which such grant of licence may be carried out.  It is worth inserting these specific obligations even if, as I anticipate, the Minister of State will say it is unnecessary.  It sends out important signals.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Bacik is partially correct, at least with regard to my likely reply.  Section 10(3) provides that it is a prerequisite for the consideration of an application that the applicant must establish that he or she has the capacity to provide the proposed bus service to which the application refers, that he or she has complied with relevant national and international legislation and that he or she holds a tax clearance certificate.</P><Col N="148"/>
        <P>Senators will remember from amendment No. 1 that a provision was introduced whereby if a person loses one licence for any reason he or she will automatically lose the licence provided for under this legislation.  This was not previously the case.  It is considered that issues raised in the proposed amendment are more relevant to the existing regulatory code relating to access to the profession of bus operator, and a separate road passenger operator licensing is the subject of separate amendments proposed to section 2 and 19 of the Bill, rather than bus market access which is dealt with in this section.  In that regard, they seem more appropriate to other legislative codes in the area of labour law and health and safety legislation as well as road passenger licensing legislation.  As it transpires, further legislation in the area of road passenger licensing is planned to address recent EU regulations on the matter and the issues will be considered in the preparation of that legislation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State for his response, which lived up, or rather down, to my expectation of it.  I am glad to hear that similar provisions may be made in other legislation.  However, there is a tendency on the part of the Government to put off making provisions, particularly those guaranteeing minimum standards, and suggest that they be put into other legislation.  I am thinking of other Bills where we were assured that certain measures would be incorporated into other legislation.  Is there not a case for having legislation which covers all areas of licensing of bus services rather than putting minimum conditions into other legislation?  It seems to me it would be more sensible to have it all in the one place.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>Consolidated legislation of the kind referred to by the Senator is often desirable and fairly difficult to achieve in many instances.  I was honoured to bring the Safety, Health and Welfare at Work Act 2005 through the Oireachtas.  The provisions of that legislation have stood up very well and the inspectorate does its job well.  We are well served in that regard.  The road passenger licensing legislation, which will have to take account of European directives, is a more appropriate place for this element of what is proposed in the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 10 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I have difficulty with paragraph 10(1)(<i>a</i>).  I could agree to the passage of the section only if we deleted that paragraph.  It requires the authority to consider the likely level of demand when licensing a new commercial transport service.  I see no reason for a regulator of commercial services to consider whether or not there is sufficient demand for a service.</P>
        <P>This goes against the whole ethos of commercial competition and of what happens when people or commercial bodies take a risk.  For example, when I started in my business there were no self-service shops.  It is as though the State were saying the old counter service shops should stay because starting a self-service shop is too big a risk.  What would have happened if civil servants had to take account of the risk shopkeepers were taking before they were allowed to get into a new area?  The same would have applied to Ryanair.  What if someone had to take into account the risk Ryanair was taking before it was given permission to go into competition with other airlines?</P>
        <P>I disagree with the principle of this measure.  If we are to have competition it is up to those who are in business to take risks.  The essence of competition is to encourage risk takers to say they are going to attempt to make this succeed.  I do not think it is up to the authority to decide not to allow a person to compete.  It should not have to take that into account.  Risk takers and business people will take a chance if they believe there will be success.  They will not take a <Col N="149"/>risk if they do not believe there will be success.  I do not believe this provision should be included in the Bill.  I am opposed to paragraph 10(1)(<i>a</i>).  Otherwise, I am happy with the section.  I urge the Minister of State to give serious consideration to that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FionnaOMalleyPD"><NameTxt>Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Malley</NameTxt>
	<P>I have some sympathy with what Senator Quinn is saying.  Being too prescriptive in legislation is a bad idea.  My instincts are the same as Senator Quinn&rsquo;s.  Legislation should not deny people the opportunity to take a risk. I ask the Minister of State to think about the inclusion of this paragraph.</P>
        <P>Legislation dates very quickly in some instances.  The Bill might be improved by the removal of this measure.  It is not for the authority to decide commercial risk values.  I ask the Minister of State to consider this a little further.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I support the views of Senators Quinn and O&rsquo;Malley.  Senator Quinn mentioned that he was at Dublin Airport a number of weeks ago and remarked on the efficient bus service which operates from that facility.  The bus service was initially provided by Aircoach.  That company identified this niche and, with no assistance from the State, did market research and decided to take a risk.  That is what business people do.  The service has now been aped by Dublin Bus and it is attempting to compete with Aircoach on the same routes.  If this legislation had been in place at the time, Aircoach might not have had that opportunity.  I also ask the Minister of State to reconsider this paragraph.</P>
        
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>The intent of this section does not relate to competition matters, which are of concern to Senators Quinn, O&rsquo;Malley and Cannon.  It relates to a case where, for example, there is an existing service at 9 a.m. and an application for one or more services at exactly the same time on exactly the same route.  The authority, on foot of this provision, has the capacity to take account of the potential demand that exists for bus passenger services.  In such a case the effect of competition might be, not the provision of several services but the diminution of the service which is already in place.  The Bill does not set out to regulate the competitive elements which might exist.  In the example I give it might be sensible to operate a second service at 9.05 a.m. or 9.10 a.m or perhaps on a slightly different route.  Requiring the authority to &ldquo;take account of the demand or potential demand that exists for the public bus passenger services to which the application refers having regard to the needs of consumers and any existing public bus passenger services on or in the vicinity of the route to be served by the proposed public bus passenger service&rdquo; is probably very sensible.  It certainly complies with the requirements of regulated competition, which is what the legislation is about, in terms of providing the best range of services for people while not undermining existing services in an unacceptable manner.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FionnaOMalleyPD"><NameTxt>Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Malley</NameTxt>
	<P>I have listened to what the Minister of State said but I do not accept that anyone who is providing a bus service is determined to diminish the level of service being provided by someone else.  Someone who proposes to provide a service or go into competition with another provider is making a commercial decision.  Such a person will not invest in something which will not work.</P>
        <P>I am reminded of what is happening since the collapse of the viaduct in Malahide.  There was a sudden need for a bus service, and I understand Dublin Bus and others stepped admirably into the breach.  A very good bus service is being provided.  Would this legislation have prevented that happening?  Would the authority have been required to carry out an assessment of need?</P>
        <P>I believe this provision is too restrictive.  The Minister of State&rsquo;s aim is laudable but he must have faith in people who are running businesses and are prepared to take risks.  They are doing <Col N="150"/>so because they feel there is a commercial need for their product.  The State should involve itself as little as possible when private operators are prepared to take risks and provide services which give much better value to the taxpayer.  We should provide the taxpayer with as few opportunities for waste of money as possible.  This measure will restrict competition.  Notwithstanding what the Minister of State has said, I worry that it will stand in the way of the development of competition.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>Section 10(1)(<i>a</i>) sets out to do two things, the first of which it does not have the capacity to do, namely, decide what demand or potential demand for a service might exist.  The authority would not have the expertise or business acumen to do this.  The subsection also seeks to protect current public bus passenger services.  However, subsection (1)(<i>b</i>)(iii) goes a long way towards doing so and, with a slight beefing up, could dispense with the need for subsection (1)(<i>a</i>).  In certain cases, the protection of those services might be laudable, but the first element of the subsection, which could stop a service from being provided because, in someone&rsquo;s opinion, there was no demand, would stifle competition and the creation of new business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I will not repeat the remarks of Senators Cannon and O&rsquo;Malley, but the spirit of the sections is not the correct thinking.  It almost looks like we are trying to protect bus operators from one another.  The essence of competition is to encourage new people into the market.  While I understand the Minister of State&rsquo;s point, the wording of the section is over the top.  I urge him to reconsider it, if not in the coming minutes, before Report Stage, and to introduce an amendment to take our concerns into account and delete subsection (1)(<i>a</i>).</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not normally rise to defend a Minister of State but I see the merit of the subsection and it is not unduly restrictive.  It is a question of the licensing of bus services for the consumer, so the interests of the consumer must be foremost in the legislation.  The subsection will not restrict an operator who wishes to enter the market, as it asks him or her to put forward a good business plan for the intended service in his or her application.  Anyone who identifies a gap in the market will be able to do so within the terms of the subsection.  It does not pose the problem identified by Senator O&rsquo;Malley on the Government side or by my colleagues on this side.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>If I am interpreting the subsection correctly, it would also apply to public operators applying for a route in the hands of a private operator.  As there seems to be equality, I do not have a problem with the section.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>I will convey to the Minister, Deputy Dempsey, the concerns expressed by Senators on both sides of the House regarding the overall impact of the section and how one element balances against another.  It is important we remember Senator Norris&rsquo;s points on the types of services and difficulties we had in the less regulated market of the 1930s.  It is also important to remember that the Bill provides 77 different ways in which the authority will be answerable to the Minister and an Oireachtas committee regarding its decisions.  This will ensure the decisions made will not step over the mark in any particular direction.</P>
        <P>The alternative transport arrangements put in place by Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann in respect of the Dublin-Belfast Enterprise service operate from Drogheda with connecting express bus services to and from Dublin via the Dublin Port tunnel.  Commuter rail services between Drogheda and Donabate have been replaced by Bus &Eacute;ireann and Bus &Aacute;tha Cliath services and the DART is operating as normal to and from Malahide.  To be fair to the people concerned, they have <Col N="151"/>quickly made provision to accommodate those who have been discommoded by the unfortunate collapse of the bridge.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I will not pursue the matter at this stage, but I would like to be able to report back on Report Stage.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
        <P>Sections 11 and 12 agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 13.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 9 to 11, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 9:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 11, subsection (2), between lines 11 and 12, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;(<i>j</i>) the fare system to be used.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This seeks to ensure a consistency of approach between this Bill and the Dublin Transport Authority Act which includes a provision for the assessment of a fare system to be used during the licensing process.  It is strange that in this Bill, every aspect of the operation of a route, from scheduling to routing to the quality of the buses and so on, is included in the licensing process but the details of the fare system to be used are omitted.  As there may be a valid reason, I look forward to the Minister of State&rsquo;s response.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>Section 13 provides that the authority may apply conditions to the grant of either an original, amended or renewed bus licence.  Notwithstanding the generality of subsection (1), subsection (2) sets out a series of specific areas relating to the licence holder&rsquo;s provision of a service, ticketing, number of vehicles, accessibility and emissions standards in respect of which conditions may be imposed.  Subsection (3) allows the authority to require licence holders to provide and publish a timetable for the licensed service and subsection (4) provides that the authority may require that the details of the licence be displayed on the vehicle providing the service.</P>
        <P>The provisions of the section were prepared having regard to a range of practical considerations relating to the licensing of commercial bus route operations.  To revert to our previous discussion, it must be remembered that the decision to apply for a licence to provide a specific bus passenger service is a commercial one taken by the applicant independently of the authority.</P>
        <P>While a primary objective of the licensing regime in Part 2 is to promote regulated competition in the provision of licensed public bus passenger services in the public interest, the provisions of the Bill have been framed with due regard to the fact that certain aspects of the proposed bus operations are not intended to be regulated by the authority, given that decisions in those areas must be taken by the licence applicant having regard to commercial considerations.</P>
        <P>Under the licensing regime of the Road Transport Act 1932, the Department does not interfere in the fare levels or structures of particular licensed bus services.  The view is that decisions on the fare system to be applied to a commercial public bus passenger service are matters for determination by the service operator having regard to market conditions and the operator&rsquo;s <Col N="152"/>particular circumstances.  No merit is seen in revising this practice at this time, given the experience heretofore.</P>
        <P>Section 13(3) allows the authority to require a licence holder to provide and publish a timetable for the licensed service.  Subsection (4) provides that the authority may require that the details of the licence be displayed.  These provisions give the authority discretion having regard to the fact that, in some bus licence applications, for example, a licence for a one-off event such as a concert or football match, these requirements would not arise.  It is considered that &ldquo;may&rdquo; is more appropriate than the alternatives in amendments Nos. 10 and 11.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister of State is saying that, once all the other conditions have been satisfied, it is for the operator to decide what fare structure will be imposed.  I would have no problem with that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>It is a commercial decision.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>May I discuss amendments Nos. 10 and 11 together?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>They were discussed together with amendment No. 9.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>May I elaborate briefly?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Briefly, as we must move through the three amendments together.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 10:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 11, subsection (3), line 12, to delete &ldquo;may&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;shall&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This may be semantics on our part, but the word &ldquo;may&rdquo; offers the national transport authority too much latitude.  &ldquo;Shall&rdquo; would leave less room for manoeuvre.  The Minister of State has agreed that it would be a prerequisite for any licensed contractor to display a timetable of services and details of its licence or contracts.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>This discretion is allowed to the authority, given that in some instances such as the ploughing championships of two weeks ago or a concert, a service might be provided for two or three days.  &ldquo;May&rdquo; allows the authority discretion to separate one-off or somewhat temporary events from permanent services.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Amendment No. 11 not moved.</P>
        <P>Section 13 agreed to.</P>
    <HtmlBk SectId="4" />
        <P>Sections 14 to 18, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 19.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 12:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 14, between lines 3 and 4, to insert the following subsection:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">&ldquo;(4) Where a road passenger transport operator&rsquo;s licence is revoked or withdrawn under an act of an institution of the European Communities in relation to road passenger transport, <Col N="153"/>under an Act of the Oireachtas in relation to road passenger transport, or under any regulation made under section 3 of the European Communities Act 1972 giving effect to an act of an institution of the European Communities in relation to road passenger transport, a licence granted under this Part to the person who held the road passenger transport operator&rsquo;s licence concerned stands revoked.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Section 19, as amended, agreed to.</P>
        <P>Sections 20 to 23, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 24.</P>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 13:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 17, subsection (3), lines 4 and 5, to delete &ldquo;or by a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">This is a drafting amendment to correct a provision that seems to misunderstand the authorisation for summary prosecution.  It has never been the practice to authorise garda&iacute; to prosecute summary offences because they have that authority at common law.  The authority needs that power because it is a statutory body having no common law powers but to authorise the garda&iacute; to prosecute a summary offence would be contrary to all known drafting precedents and is legally inappropriate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>I was not entirely clear prior to the Senator&rsquo;s contribution about the rationale for the amendment.  Section 24 provides that offences under the bus licensing regime can be prosecuted by the authority or by a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  This recognised the general enforcement role of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in regard to breaches of legislation in the State and is highly appropriate, particularly given the interaction of bus services and the general public.  The Minister is not disposed to accepting the amendment on the basis that the proposed involvement of garda&iacute; in the enforcement regime is both desirable and consistent with other legislative regimes, and garda&iacute; always had an enforcement role in this area.  However, having heard the point made by Senator Ryan and the element in regard to drafting, I will raise it with the Minister with a view to his considering it in advance of Report Stage.  If an issue arises I will ask him to address it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrendanRyan"><NameTxt>Senator Brendan Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>On the basis that the Minister of State will discuss it with the senior Minister and will consider the possibility of having that section deleted, I am prepared to give him that space but I ask him to ask the Minister if there are any previous examples of such powers being given to garda&iacute; in other legislation.  I believe they will be difficult to find.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Section 24 agreed to.</P>
        <P>Sections 25 and 26 agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 14:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 18, before section 27, to insert the following new section:</P><Col N="154"/>
        <P LI="1" el="5">27.&mdash;(1) Notwithstanding the repeal of the Act of 1932 under <i>section 27(a)</i>, where a person has made an application for a licence under that Act before its repeal, the application shall be considered under that Act by the Authority and any reference in that Act to the Minister in respect of the application shall be read as a reference to the Authority.</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">(2) Where an application for a licence under the Act of 1932 is dealt with under <i>subsection (1) </i>and the licence is granted, the licence is deemed to be a licence granted under this Part and to be in force to a date to be determined by the Authority, which shall not be more than 2 years after the day of the next anniversary of the date of the grant of the licence under the Act of 1932 and may be renewed under <i>section 16</i>.&rdquo;.</P>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>While the provisions of section 20 set out arrangements through which existing commercial services being operated by Dublin Bus, Bus &Eacute;ireann and private operators can be brought within the new licensing regime, it came to the attention of the Department in the course of recent discussions that a further provision was desirable to cater for bus licence applications that may be submitted to the Department in the period between the establishment of the authority and the repeal of the Road Transport Act 1932 and the commencement of provisions to facilitate the introduction of the new bus licensing regime.</P>
        <P>The purpose of the new section 27 is to provide a transitional arrangement to facilitate the consideration of applications for a public bus passenger licence made to the Minister under section 8 of the 1932 Act that have not been decided on the date of the repeal of the 1932 Act and the introduction of the new bus licensing regime under Part 2 of the Bill, which will be administered by the authority.  Given that such applicants will have applied under the 1932 regime, there will be an expectation that they should be considered under that regime and the proposed section provides for this.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FionnaOMalleyPD"><NameTxt>Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Malley</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Is the process so long and complicated that it would stop a decision being made before the enactment of this Bill?  Would it not be preferable to have everybody starting from the same position, that is, in modernised, updated legislation?  Would it be possible to stop applications by people under the 1932 Act being taken in the light of this new Bill being drafted?  Is it open to abuse in that it may be favourable for people to seek a licence, for whatever reasons, under more outmoded terms and legislation?  Would it not be wise to have a close-off date?  Is that possible so all licences will be considered under the new legislation?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>The expectation would be that the period would be very short and in this instance there may well be slightly more advantage for people to apply under the new regime.  Regarding ceasing taking all new applications, applications for urgent services unfortunately do arise and would surely arise in the interim period.  The Department has much experience in these matters and would see spurious applications for what they are if there were to be a flood of applications, which is probably what the Senator is concerned about.  Although in this instance there might be an intervening period that needs to be catered for, one possibility would have been to decide not to accept new applications during that period but the provision of the new section 27, which if I recall provides for a limit of two years, is probably a fairer way to deal with anything that might arise.  Nothing may arise in any event.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 27.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 15:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 18, paragraph (<i>b</i>), line 16, to delete &ldquo;69&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;73&rdquo;.</P><Col N="155"/>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>The number of sections of the 1932 Act to be disposed of has increased from 69 to 73.  The purpose of the amendment is to repeal a number of additional sections of the Road Transport Act 1933 which are no longer needed arising from the new legislative regime for public bus passenger services in Part 2 of the Public Transport Regulation Bill 2009.  I will list them for the House.</P>
        <P>Section 66 of the 1933 Act provides for the amendment of the meaning of the expression &ldquo;passenger road service&rdquo; in the 1932 Act.  Section 67 provides for an extension of the duration of the passenger licences in force on 31 October 1933 to cover the period until the 1933 Act came into force.  Regarding sections 68 to 71, inclusive, section 71 provides for the revocation of passenger licences by the Minister in the event of fraud or misrepresentation.  Section 72 provides that passenger licences transferred to another person under the 1932 Act are deemed to have been transferred to such a person on the date of transfer of ownership.  Section 73 provides for the acceptance of a certificate signed by an officer of the Minister as evidence.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
        <P>Section 27, as amended, agreed to.</P>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 28.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 16:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 19, subsection (1)(<i>d</i>), line 29, to delete &ldquo;11&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;11(1)&rdquo;.</P>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>The purpose of this amendment is to address a technical error in the section reference in the text of the Bill which should refer to section 11(1) of the Dublin Transport Authority Act 2008 rather than section 11, which is what is in the text.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Amendment No. 17 in the names of Senators Cannon and Donohoe is not in order as it involves a potential charge on the Revenue.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment No. 17 not moved.</P>
        <P>Government amendment No. 18:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">In page 20, line 2, after &ldquo;contract&rdquo; to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="1" el="5">&ldquo;, other than a direct award contract to which section 52(3) refers,&rdquo;.</P>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>This proposed amendment seeks to clarify the provision of section 28(1)(<i>f</i>) of the Bill.  This section provides for the amendment of section 48 of the Dublin Transport Authority Bill 2008 which relates to the making of public transport services contracts so as to introduce a new subsection (12).  This provides that the authority must advise any local authority in whose functional area the proposed transport service will operate that there is such a proposal and invite the local authority to submit written views on the proposal.</P>
        <P>In view of the fact that the initial direct-award contracts with Dublin Bus, Bus &Eacute;ireann and Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann will be made by the authority as soon as the Bill is enacted &mdash; probably before 3 December &mdash; and the relevant provisions, both in this Bill and the Dublin Transport Authority Act 2008, are commenced, it will not be possible to comply with the new subsection (12) in respect of these contracts.  The amendment seeks to confirm this by excluding the initial contracts with the CIE companies from the requirements of the section.  As the deadline for <Col N="156"/>signing the contracts is 2 December, at the latest, there would not be time to consult local authorities.  However, the provisions will apply to all future contracts.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 19:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 20, subsection (1), lines 10 to 13, to delete paragraph (<i>g</i>) and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;(<i>g</i>) by the repeal of section 52.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have no doubt as to the intended thrust of this legislation.  Senators Quinn, O&rsquo;Malley and I are very much on the same wavelength in regard to what exactly we would like to see achieved.  I have one major concern, namely, that the element of the Bill that seeks to provide real, effective, open and transparent competition in public transport service provision will not be achieved.  As I stated, I have no issue with a public body providing a public transport service provided it provides the best possible value for the taxpayer who ultimately funds it and for the consumer who avails of it.  I do not particularly care whether the service from Dublin to Galway is provided by Bus &Eacute;ireann or another entity as long as it is a proper service at the best possible price.</P>
        <P>Section 52 of the Dublin Transport Authority Act 2008 goes against everything the Bill sets out to achieve.  It allows the Minister to arrange, before the Bill is enacted, to draw up new public service contracts with Bus &Eacute;ireann, Dublin Bus and Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann.  These contracts will be binding, possibly for the next ten to 15 years.  While the object of the proposed new regime is very admirable, section 52 of the Dublin Transport Authority Act will serve to neuter the legislation for many years.  It does not allow other operators to tender to operate on the routes in question for the next ten to 15 years.  This is one of the most disturbing aspects of the Bill and I do not know the logic behind it.  Perhaps the Minister of State will outline it.  I look forward to hearing his response.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FionnaOMalleyPD"><NameTxt>Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Malley</NameTxt>
	<P>I share some of the concerns of Senator Cannon.  I fear the legislation is in danger of being damaged by the continuation of section 52 of the Dublin Transport Authority Act.  We should be trying to prepare legislation that is adaptable and flexible and which allows people to compete on an even keel.  When the Minister spoke in the House two weeks ago, he assured us he was trying to achieve this.  However, I have some reservations.  While competition is always desirable, I accept there should be some regulation because things can go wrong if there is a free for all.  I am worried there is capacity to leave the competition elements of this legislation hamstrung.  That is not desirable.</P>
        <P>I am interested in hearing the Minister of State&rsquo;s rationale for retaining section 52.  It is time we acknowledged that it is important that any operator seeking to provide a public bus service has access to all routes.  The less differentiation between public and private providers, the better.  As Senator Cannon implied, one does not mind who one&rsquo;s bus service provider is as long as one has a bus service.  The legislation must ensure standards will be the same and that everybody will be subject to the same rules and regulations.</P>
        <P>I worry that a provision that allows licences to be given away in advance of enactment of the Bill is not desirable.  I await the Minister of State&rsquo;s comments on the rationale behind the reference to section 52 of the Dublin Transport Authority Act 2008.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="157"/>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>As Senator Cannon will be aware, Dublin-Galway services are commercial.  Direct-award contracts are for a period of five years only and are already provided for in the Dublin Transport Authority Act 2008.  All new services are to be put out to tender.  One tends to forget there is a review clause applying to the operation of existing contracts.</P>
        <P>The purpose of section 28(1)(<i>g</i>) is to provide for the amendment of section 52 of the 2008 Act which relates to direct-award contracts between the authority and the three State transport companies.  It is a matter of expanding the remit of the section from the greater Dublin area to the full geographical area of the State.  This is fundamental to the provisions of the Bill.  In other words, the authority will be responsible for public service contracts on a national basis.</P>
        <P>Section 52 is a pivotal section of the 2008 Act, as it establishes the basis for the continued provision of the existing public bus and rail passenger services provided by Bus &Eacute;ireann, Dublin Bus and Irish Rail in the greater Dublin area and for which State funding is made available.  This empowers the authority to enter into direct-award contracts &mdash; contracts that do not involve open tendering &mdash; with the three CIE companies in respect of the provision of existing funded public bus and rail services in the greater Dublin area.  To facilitate the making of the contracts in respect of the public bus services, the section establishes that Dublin Bus and Bus &Eacute;ireann have exclusive rights to continue to operate their current funded services, subject to the granting of bus licences under the Road Transport Act 1932 and future legislative changes.  These arrangements will support the continued operation of the services in question in the general public interest.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">6 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>The section also provides that the contracts can be reviewed and that subsequent contracts may be made.  A review of a direct-award contract is mandated on the authority where it establishes that the maintenance of the contract is no longer necessary in respect of certain services.  In these circumstances and where it is proposed to make subsequent direct-award contracts, the authority must invite submissions from interested parties before renewing or replacing the contract.  All compensation paid by the authority under the direct-award contracts must be calculated and paid in accordance with the annex to Regulation (EC) No. 1370/2007 of 23 October 2007 on public transport services by rail and road.  The section also empowers the Minister to issue directions on the provision of public passenger transport services to achieve the Government&rsquo;s transport objectives or to comply with EU law.</P>
        <P>The contractual structure established in the Dublin Transport Authority Act 2008, particularly in section 52, is in compliance with Regulation (EC) No. 1370/2007 on public service obligations which comes into force on 3 December this year and provides for a new contractual framework regulating how member states award exclusive rights and pay compensation for services deemed to meet public service obligations.  Having regard to these considerations, retention of section 52 of the Dublin Transport Authority Act is of some considerable importance, as are the amendments to this section.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>The provision goes against the spirit of what the legislation sets out to achieve.  The Minister of State mentioned Galway-Dublin bus services, a number of which are provided by private operators.  Healthy competition has allowed the public to benefit from a very efficient and well operated service from Galway to Dublin for a fraction of the price the public service operator was charging 20 or 30 years ago.  What is the timescale applying to the exclusion of private sector operators from the routes in question? Will these routes be protected for the next ten or 15 years?  If so, it goes against the very heart of what this legislation sets out to achieve.</P>
        <P>On routes currently subsidised by the taxpayer, we will not find out for a considerable period whether a private operator could come in to service one of those routes as effectively as a <Col N="158"/>public service operator and perhaps avail of only a portion or none of the available public service subsidy.  We will not be allowed to know that until such a time as these contracts are terminated in ten or 15 years.</P>
        <P>I welcome the legislation in general but the retention of this element, which harks back to what was wrong in the past, drags it down.  It is an undesirable part of the Bill.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FionnaOMalleyPD"><NameTxt>Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Malley</NameTxt>
	<P>To nobody&rsquo;s surprise, my instincts are the same as those of Senator Cannon in this area.  Listening to the Minister of State&rsquo;s response, it screams of protectionism, which is not really what we want.  I am worried about that.  I have listened to the Minister of State&rsquo;s laudable aims and provisions within the legislation but he is asking us to forget the experience we have had.  Nobody, and private bus operators in particular, can forget how Dublin Bus and other public companies have operated.</P>
        <P>Senator Cannon touched on the issue of us not being allowed to see the figures and as an example we have had the traumatic experience of trying to make integrated ticketing a reality.  Many Ministers responsible for transport have dealt with this, including the late S&eacute;amus Brennan, Deputy Martin Cullen and the current Minister, and yet we still do not have integrated ticketing because Dublin Bus will not provide figures or play ball.  As the company has been allowed to dominate, the Ministers have been able to do very little.</P>
        <P>This is worrying.  I accept the reasoning behind the Minister of State&rsquo;s actions but the experience is different.  Senator Cannon has raised a good point about figures.  As there will be a level of protectionism and commercial operators will not be allowed on certain services if this element remains in the Bill, we will never really know the real commercial levels.  That sort of protectionism must be left behind, and as I previously indicated, the Bill would be improved by deleting this provision.</P>
        <P>We cannot lose sight of the public we are here to serve as we seek the best possible public transport service.  All our experience has shown that the private and public sectors working as a competitive force provide the best service.  We were promised a level playing field and we must keep that field as even as possible.  This element flies in the face of that effort so I ask the Minister of State to consider it further.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TonyKilleen"><NameTxt>Deputy Tony Killeen</NameTxt>
	<P>The duration of the contract is five years rather than ten, which has been a concern for a number of Senators.  It can be reviewed or altered by the authority at any stage, which is important.  The CIE companies are obliged to pass an efficient operator test and it is very important for existing services to continue where their operation is urgently needed.</P>
        <P>The other important consideration is that the EU regulations are such that a degree of openness and transparency which has not always been the experience heretofore, as mentioned by Senator O&rsquo;Malley, is a requirement.  If people came slowly to the table in that respect, we could expect to see more movement in the near future.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
      
      <Vote>
        <Result>The Committee divided: T&aacute;, 27; N&iacute;l, 11.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading>
        <YesVote pid="IvanaBacik">Bacik, Ivana.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MartinBrady">Brady, Martin.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LarryButler">Butler, Larry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PeterCallanan">Callanan, Peter.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="IvorCallely">Callely, Ivor.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnCartyFF">Carty, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DonnieCassidyFF">Cassidy, Donie.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MariaCorrigan">Corrigan, Maria.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarkDaly">Daly, Mark.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="GeraldineFeeney">Feeney, Geraldine.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DominicHannigan">Hannigan, Dominic.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="CeciliaKeaveney">Keaveney, Cecilia.</YesVote><Col N="159"/>
        <YesVote pid="TerryLeyden" head="y">Leyden, Terry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarcMacSharry">MacSharry, Marc.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianODomhnaill">&Oacute; Domhnaill, Brian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="LabhrasOMurchu">&Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DennisODonovan">O&rsquo;Donovan, Denis.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FionnaOMalleyPD">O&rsquo;Malley, Fiona.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="NedOSullivan">O&rsquo;Sullivan, Ned.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JoeOToole">O&rsquo;Toole, Joe.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AnnOrmonde">Ormonde, Ann.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="KieranPhelan">Phelan, Kieran.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrendanRyan">Ryan, Brendan.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AlexWhite">White, Alex.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MaryMWhite">White, Mary M.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</YesVote>
        <NHeading>N&iacute;l</NHeading>
        <NoVote pid="PaulBradford">Bradford, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaddyBurke">Burke, Paddy.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JerryButtimer">Buttimer, Jerry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CiaranCannon">Cannon, Ciaran.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaudieCoffey">Coffey, Paudie.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FrancesFitzgerald">Fitzgerald, Frances.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FidelmaHealyEames">Healy Eames, Fidelma.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="NickyMcFadden">McFadden, Nicky.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="RonanMullen">Mullen, R&oacute;n&aacute;n.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JoeOReilly">O&rsquo;Reilly, Joe.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="EugeneRegan">Regan, Eugene.</NoVote>
        <Tellers>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Denis O&rsquo;Donovan and Diarmuid Wilson; N&iacute;l, Senators Jerry Buttimer and Ciaran Cannon.</Tellers>
        <Decision><?oasys _is0p11- ?>Question declared carried.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
        <P>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="5" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. </Title>
  </MainHeading><Line />
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Procurement" RHead="Policy"> 
    <Title>Public Procurement Policy. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DiarmuidWilson"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Diarmuid Wilson</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy &Aacute;ine Brady.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State and thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise this issue.  I seek the introduction of regulations requiring that all timber used in Government, semi-State and local authority procurement contracts is sourced from certifiably sustainable timber producers.  Both deforestation and illegal logging are having a major impact on climate change.  While forests used to cover half the planet&rsquo;s land area, they now only cover 30% and this figure reduces annually.  Some countries in particular are suffering heavily.  In the last century, the forested area of Ghana, Africa, dwindled from 8 million hectares, which is approximately the size of Ireland, to 1.2 million hectares, which is slightly bigger than County Cork.  As a result, one of the key ways to eat up carbon dioxide across the world is being lost.  It is estimated that deforestation is responsible for approximately 20% of global greenhouse gas emissions, which constitutes a greater quantity of emissions than are produced by the transport sector.</P>
        <P>Some countries in particular are experiencing significant amounts of illegal logging.  In Bolivia, Peru and Cambodia, more than 80% of logging is illegal, which means there is a loss of Government revenue in respect of unpaid taxes at a local level.  It is estimated that globally, <Col N="160"/>approximately one quarter of imports from six key countries could be illegal.  Given that Ireland is providing aid to many developing countries to improve the manner in which they manage their timber, it makes no sense if, at the same time, we import large amounts of illegal timber.  This problem is being tackled in other countries.  For instance, the United Kingdom, the Netherlands, Germany, France and Denmark all have introduced public procurement policies specifying that only certified timber may be used.</P>
        <P>We in Ireland are part of the problem.  The Irish Government is the biggest purchaser of illegal timber products in the country and probably accounts for up to 20% of the timber used here.  However, minor changes in regulations can have a big impact in practice.  Were central Departments to purchase wood products that are known to be legal, not only would it set a good example to others, it also would reduce the scale of illegal imports.  There are two ways in which one can verify that timber has been sourced legally, namely, forest certification schemes and voluntary partnership agreements.  The Dutch and the British have undertaken market research studies on the impact of their changes to their public procurement policies and the studies from both countries showed that certified timber product imports have grown steadily and now account for approximately 50% of the timber on the market there.  Moreover, experience from other EU countries also suggests no significant additional cost arises as a result of introducing such policies.  The Government has been challenged previously on the use of illegal timber in a number of high-profile construction projects, including the Irish Aid visitor centre in Dublin.  The World Wildlife Fund&rsquo;s annual report on governments suggests that Ireland has the worst record in respect of illegal logging within the European Union.  Although the Office of Public Works has a general commitment to use sustainable timber, we must go further.  We should copy the policies introduced by our European partners and I ask the Minister of State to make a statement on this matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AineBrady"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy &Aacute;ine Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator Hannigan.  The Government is fully committed to the protection of our planet&rsquo;s precious forest resources.  Ecologically sustainable public procurement has a central role in ensuring that Ireland plays its part.  I therefore sincerely thank the Senator for his question.  I am delighted to have this opportunity to apprise the House of our actions with regard to the public procurement of wood and wood products.  These initiatives will help ensure the utilisation of our forest resources in a cost-effective manner while also safeguarding them for the benefit of future generations.</P>
        <P>In 2004, the European Union adopted two directives on public procurement, namely, directives 17 and 18 of 2004, for entities in the utilities and public sectors, respectively.  These directives clarify the possibilities for public sector procurers to include environmental and social criteria in their tenders.  In other words, the legislation already exists to enable green public procurement, GPP, not least for wood and wood products.</P>
        <P>In response to the enhanced possibilities clarified by these directives, the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government advised local authorities in 2006 on environmental considerations in public infrastructure procurement.  Local authorities planning such procurement were urged to consider how they can contribute to the protection of the environment and promote sustainable development, while also ensuring that best value for money is obtained in the award of contracts.  The Department pointed out in this circular that a range of environmentally sustainable systems and materials are increasingly being incorporated into public capital projects.  These include wood pellet boilers and materials such as timber frame windows certified from sustainable forest sources.</P><Col N="161"/>
        <P>I should point out the limitations of the procurement role of the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government.  Since its establishment in 2002, the national public procurement policy unit of the Department of Finance has had overall responsibility for procurement modernisation.  The Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government has worked with this unit chiefly in two respects, namely, in helping the procurement modernisation process with regard to local authorities and in advocating green public procurement more generally.  In recent months, the establishment of the national public procurement operations unit is a highly welcome development.  The Government has decided that this unit will be the mechanism to embed green public procurement principles deeply into our procurement practices.  We have some distance to go before green procurement becomes as central to public procurement in Ireland as it is in some other member states.  The national public procurement operations unit will be instrumental in making the necessary progress.</P>
        <P>Recently, the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy Gormley, met the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Mansergh, about the preparation of Ireland&rsquo;s first national action plan for green public procurement and agreed that a joint approach is preferable in its development.  This is particularly the case in respect of the alignment of GPP principles with the promotion of green jobs and other elements of the Government&rsquo;s drive towards the smart economy.  As work on the action plan progresses, the Government will of course incorporate the latest examples of best practice in respect of wood and wood products.</P>
        <P>One such development is a new European Union regulation that will require timber traders operating in the EU market for the first time to operate due diligence systems to minimise the risk of trade in illegally sourced timber.  This is being negotiated on Ireland&rsquo;s behalf by my colleague, the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food.  The GPP national action plan will reflect this EU legislative initiative promoting legal and sustainable timber products.  More broadly, it is intended that the action plan will demonstrate and promote both the environmental and economic value of green purchasing of timber products across the Irish public sector.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State for her response.  Can she provide the publication date for the action plan to which she referred?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AineBrady"><NameTxt>Deputy &Aacute;ine Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>I cannot.  However, I will try to procure it for Senator Hannigan.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Local" RHead="Development"> 
    <Title>Local Development. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise this matter.  I also welcome the Minister of State, Deputy &Aacute;ine Brady.  It is ironic that the Minister of State also responded to a similar Adjournment matter I raised on 16 June last regarding the Cork docklands.  Given the economic recession, it is fitting to note that Cork City Council and the Port of Cork have reached agreement regarding the docklands.  In her previous reply to me on this issue, the Minister of State noted that redevelopment of the Cork docklands was identified as a priority in the national development plan and the national spatial strategy.</P>
        <P>I will add to that by observing that Cork is the second city of our country.  It is the gateway to Munster and the southern region and in many people&rsquo;s eyes is the real capital.  However, this is a serious motion.  It is important, given the point the Minister of State made in her previous response to the effect that the project has been identified in the national development plan and the spatial strategy, that Cork as a gateway city should receive support from the Government in the provision of funding for the docklands project and the eastern gateway bridge.  The docklands project is pivotal to the growth of Cork&rsquo;s population.  It will be an <Col N="162"/>instrumental driver of the Cork economic region and will create thousands of jobs, add thousands of houses and create a vibrancy in Cork city that has not been experienced for a long time.</P>
        <P>I acknowledge the establishment of the Cork Docklands Development Forum.  However, we still await publication of its report.  The report&rsquo;s contents and the reason it cannot be published rapidly are becoming additional secrets of Fatima..  The Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Martin, recently spoke about the entire issue being changed.  However, the fundamentals have not changed in that Cork City Council this week entered an agreement with the Port of Cork.  This enables the relocation of port activities and in addition, RPIF plc, or Topaz, has intimated that it is preparing a planning application.  The plan by Topaz will allow the freeing up of 50% of the land in the docklands.  This means that private investment is coming and one now awaits public investment through Government funding.  I have raised this matter numerous times on the Adjournment since I became a Member of this House.  The eastern gateway bridge and the docklands development are tied as a key indicator in the development of Cork, advancing the city and creating a new urban hub.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State knows the extent of unemployment, which has hit Cork particularly hard.  The development is a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity to build another major pillar to spread the city given that we cannot get agreement with Cork County Council on the extension of the boundary.  This development is the only opportunity to organise and regenerate Cork city further.</P>
        <P>We need triggers and stimulus plans.  We need opportunities to put Cork forward as the gateway to the south.  An announcement was made concerning the ferry last week but we are still awaiting the debt free airport development and the independent autonomy of that.  The docklands is the catalyst that can be used in creating a new Cork.</P>
        <P>I reserve my comments until I hear the reply of the Minister of State.  I hope she has good news because we need good news regarding the promotion of this plan by the Government.  I look forward to the reply of the Minister of State.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of information, the bad news is that Cork is the third city after Belfast.  Up the Republic.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>To us it is a major city and the only city that matters.  After last weekend people in Donegal cannot really comment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AineBrady"><NameTxt>Deputy &Aacute;ine Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator Buttimer for the opportunity to restate the Government&rsquo;s firm commitment to the development of key city centre sites in the gateway cities and its recognition of the significant potential and opportunities afforded by the Cork docklands development project.  The redevelopment of Cork docklands has been identified as a priority project in the 2002 national spatial strategy, the 2006 gateway investment priority study and more recently in the national development plan 2007-13, acknowledging the significant potential to accelerate the city&rsquo;s growth through targeted investment in regenerating the docklands area by means of roads, bridges, public transport and water services, which will in turn trigger private development and investment.</P>
        <P>As Ireland&rsquo;s second city, Cork has the potential to create a second major internationally competitive node of development in Ireland, both by itself and as a key linked gateway city along the Atlantic gateway corridor.  Building on the significant progress and planning made by the two councils under the Cork area strategic plan, the Government established the Cork Docklands Development Forum in 2007.  It was tasked with promoting effective co-ordination <Col N="163"/>and delivery of sustainable investment by the State in key infrastructure to facilitate and realise docklands regeneration.  The forum also addressed options for incentives to overcome barriers to development of the area.  The forum submitted its report last year, setting out the policy and economic rationale for the regeneration project.  Among its outputs were identification of economic and other drivers essential to realising the docklands vision; identification and costing of critical public infrastructure required over the lifetime of the project, to at least 2027, to underpin subsequent private investment; consideration of significant constraints on barriers to the intended development; consideration of how this redevelopment might be incentivised; and recommendations regarding institutional arrangements to bring the project forward.  The report envisaged significant investment in public infrastructure, including the proposed eastern gateway bridge and link roads as well as possible supports for the relocation of port and other activities.  While funding decisions on the bridge and the port relocation projects submitted under the gateway innovation fund have been deferred, the Finance Bill 2009 provided for a tax incentive scheme to solicit the relocation of Seveso-listed industrial facilities that hinder the regeneration of docklands in urban areas.  The scheme is subject to European Commission clearance regarding compliance with State aid rules.</P>
        <P>The Government has committed significant resources in the Cork area to improve water services, under the Department&rsquo;s water services investment programme and the enhancement of public transport services under Transport 21.  Furthermore my Department is continuing to work closely with the councils and, in particular, with the special directorate and docklands policy committee to move the project forward.</P>
        <P>The Cork docklands area has also been designated as one of the strategically located developing areas under the Government&rsquo;s developing areas initiative.  The Government remains fully behind the redevelopment of the Cork docklands as a means to creating a sustainable and compact urban city that would be attractive to prospective investment and its residents.  The interdepartmental group established by the Government and chaired by my Department to consider the analysis and recommendations in the report is urgently considering the enabling measures that can be put in place to progress development in the Cork docklands.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>This is a non-reply.  Once again, the Government has made pious platitudes.  Will this be another missed opportunity in the regeneration and development of Cork?  Will we have mere words?  I do not mean to be disrespectful to the Minister of State but this is a carbon copy of the reply received in June and October 2008.</P>
        <P>This is an opportunity to create a stimulus plan for the Cork region.  This is not just about Cork but about the province of Munster.  We are missing this opportunity.  Senator Boyle and the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Martin, refer to renegotiation of the programme for Government but we cannot get a reply about the Cork docklands.  I know this matter does not concern the Department of the Minister of State but this is a very disappointing reply.  I will keep raising the matter and I will keep asking Deputy Gormley about this.  He should attend this House to explain why he is not prepared to move on this matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Defence Forces" RHead="Operations"> 
    <Title>Defence Forces Operations. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I refer to the need for the bomb disposal unit to be brought back to Finner, County Donegal.  I appreciate that the Minister of State is in the House.  So far on in the peace process, the last thing anyone in the Border region or County Donegal wants to do is to seek more security.  My call comes as a result of a number of specific incidents as well as the general situation.  When Officer Steven Carroll was murdered along with two British soldiers earlier this year everything moved closer to home and when this happens people tend to focus on the danger that a small number of dissidents, who are very effective, can pose.  On <Col N="164"/>11 September, a pipe bomb was found in Donegal.  This was a viable device and while people were told at 7 a.m. about the device, it was not until midday that the bomb disposal unit arrived in Donegal from Athlone.  We are glad the unit was there and that it defused the viable device but in respect of the economy of the area everything was closed for five hours while waiting for the unit.</P>
        <P>Given the geographical area, the distance between Donegal town and Finner is very short and, had the bomb disposal unit been in Finner, the matter would have been dealt with much faster.  The device was viable and, had it exploded, it would have been too late to wait for the bomb disposal unit.  There could have been consequences to this.</P>
        <P>I also want to consider what happened in the middle of September.  The mayor of Donegal County Council, Councillor Brendan Byrne, received death threats because he sought a memorial to those murdered in Mullaghmore to be situated in Donegal, overlooking the location where the murders took place.  At some times and in some countries, one could look at this as being only a death threat on a piece of paper but we cannot afford this luxury and we must take this seriously.  It is wrong that we cannot move the peace process on by understanding that others in this country have different perspectives.  We should learn to live with each other and with those who hold different perspectives.</P>
        <P>A 600 lb bomb in South Armagh was found but had moved from South to North.  As a person who drives frequently through the North and as someone who knows many people living in the North, I am concerned.  Security is now as tight as it was many years ago.  It was unusual for me to be asked for my driver&rsquo;s licence at a checkpoint late at night last week.  I cannot remember the previous occasion on which I was asked for it.  It is a very bad sign that we need to have the police out.  I commend the police on being out but I do not commend the reasons police officers need to be.  I would like to think that policing and justice will be devolved to the North soon and they will become issues that can be dealt with there.  I like to think we will be in a position to get over the fact we have dissidents and that people will continue to provide information to police officers to ensure the dissidents are demobilised.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State may not be aware we saw another side of the police service at the weekend which was much more what we want to see in this era of peace and tranquility to which we aspire.  The Garda was involved in a GAA tournament in south Belfast with the PSNI, the London Metropolitan Police and the New York Police Department.  The Garda team won on this occasion and it was great to see a Gaelic tournament in south Belfast with police forces from various jurisdictions attended by the Northern Ireland Minister for Culture, Arts and Leisure, Nelson McCausland.  That Fachtna Murphy and the new police chief constable were there is what it should be about and where we should be at.</P>
        <P>Unfortunately, I am raising this matter on the Adjournment because we are not at the stage we want to be and we need to consider returning the disposal unit to the heart of the area where it can reach more locations faster than being based in Athlone.  If I was being honest I would like to think the Minister for Defence would consider the barracks at Letterkenny and Lifford which were closed recently.  If the security threat is deemed to be as high as it seems to be, perhaps we should review the situation on the Border.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AineBrady"><NameTxt>Deputy &Aacute;ine Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>I am taking the Adjournment on behalf of the Minister for Defence, Deputy Willie O&rsquo;Dea.  The primary responsibility for the maintenance of law and order rests with the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The Defence Forces, pursuant to their role of rendering aid to the civil power, assist the Garda as required.  The explosive ordnance disposal, EOD, team responds when a request for assistance is made to the relevant brigade by a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na not below the rank of inspector.</P><Col N="165"/>
        <P>EOD teams are on call throughout the country 24 hours a day, seven days a week to deal with any suspicious objects or devices that are identified.  EOD teams operating in their role as aid to the civil power provide a unique response capability within the State to deal with such incidents.  This capability has been developed over many years in operational environments at home and overseas.  EOD teams have been provided with significant training and specialised equipment to allow personnel to operate safely in dealing with incidents involving suspect devices.  Historically, EOD deployments have been subdivided out to formations that have the territorial responsibility for a particular area.  With the onset of violence in Northern Ireland, additional teams were deployed along the Border.  The EOD team based at Finner Camp provided the western brigade with a rapid deployable EOD capability in response to subversive activity within its area of Border responsibility.  The team was deployed on the basis of evaluation and assessment of the then existing threat.</P>
        <P>The Defence Forces EOD assets are deployed in proportion to current operational requirements, which are in turn informed by ongoing intelligence and threat evaluation.  In recent years, the assessments by the Defence Forces, in consultation with the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, suggested that threat levels in the region had reduced to such an extent that the requirement to have an EOD team based permanently in Finner Camp was no longer warranted.  The statistical evidence provided by the Defence Forces shows that EOD call-outs are now predominantly urban-based in areas such as Dublin, Cork, Limerick and Waterford.  The emphasis has moved from subversive to criminal activity-based EOD call-outs with attention focused in the larger cities.  The figures for 2008 show that of a total of 180 EOD call-outs, the eastern brigade responded to 111, the southern brigade responded to 37, the Defence Forces Training Centre responded to 12 and the western brigade responded to 20.  Only three of the 180 call-outs related to the Border area of the western brigade which stretches between Donegal and Cavan.</P>
        <P>The EOD team does not deal solely with suspect devices.  The 180 call-outs responded to in 2008 included assistance with the removal of old ordnance, the disposal of so-called time expired pyrotechnics, and flares and objects washed ashore.  To date in 2009 there have been only five EOD call-outs in the Donegal area, one of which related to the disposal of fireworks.  The security situation prevailing in the Donegal area is assessed as not requiring an EOD team committed full time in the area.</P>
        <P>As part of an ongoing review of operational activity and, in particular, aid to civil power operations, the Minister for Defence, Deputy O&rsquo;Dea, agreed in November 2008, having considered the advice of the military authorities, that EOD resources could be utilised more efficiently in the western brigade area by relocating the EOD capability from Finner Camp to Custume Barracks, Athlone.  Pre-deployed equipment and vehicles remain located at Finner Camp.  This EOD cover is similar to that provided to other Border areas.  This rationalisation of EOD capacity provides for more efficient, effective and economic use of EOD personnel, resources and equipment having regard to the area to be covered and the predominant locations where call-outs occur.  The placement of the ordnance officer in brigade headquarters also provides the ordnance officer with greater operational and administrative back-up in respect of his duties for the entire brigade area.</P>
        <P>The conditions which pertained in the Border area during the Troubles are generally absent today and do not require the same resource commitment as heretofore.  In the event of a need to react urgently to an emergency situation, the EOD team can be moved rapidly from Custume Barracks to Finner Camp.</P>
        <P>There are well-established channels of consultation and co-operation between representatives of the Defence Forces and the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  EOD operations are discussed at regular meetings of the improvised explosive device working group.  The Defence Forces also liaise <Col N="166"/>with the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in the technical analysis of evidence recovered from EOD operations.  The Defence Forces, in conjunction with the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, keep the threat assessment under continual review.  The Minister, Deputy O&rsquo;Dea, has been informed by his military officials that they are of the view that there has been no increase in the threat level to warrant the redeployment of the EOD team to Finner Camp, despite recent incidents in Northern Ireland.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CeciliaKeaveney"><NameTxt>Senator Cecilia Keaveney</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State for her reply.  In her final sentence she stated:</P>
        <P LI="1">The Minister for Defence, Deputy O&rsquo;Dea, has been informed by his military officials that they are of the view that there has been no increase in the threat level to warrant the redeployment of the EOD team to Finner Camp, despite recent incidents in Northern Ireland.</P>
        <P FLI="0">We are concerned that there has been an increase in incidents in the Republic of Ireland, in which Donegal is located.  While there might have been only five call-outs, they were for viable pipe bomb devices.  Where were other viable pipe bomb devices found in the country?  It is not always about the quantity but about the quality.  If the quality of the threat is high then the quantity is not as significant and that is why we ask for resources to be placed in Donegal.  I accept that the situation is under review and I implore the Minister of State to be conscious that Northern Ireland has its difficulties and in September 2009, for the first time in quite some time, Donegal saw two incidents which we did not like.  We are concerned that if we are not able to react faster than five hours, someone will be killed or injured.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AineBrady"><NameTxt>Deputy &Aacute;ine Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator and I will pass on her comments to the Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 6.40 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 7 October 2009.</adjournment>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
