<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="29" Month="Jan" Year="2009" Vol="193" No="8" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 29 Eanáir 2009" DateEnglish="Thursday, 29 January 2009" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="503">
    <Col N="503"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead=""> 
    <Title></Title>
        <P Just="Center">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Paidir.</i><br /><i>Prayer.</i></P><Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad"> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I have notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Health and Children to approve the appointment of a second neurologist in the Health Service Executive north-west region.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Ciaran Cannon of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Education and Science to provide a new second level school in Kinvara, County Galway, to give a comprehensive report on the up-to-date situation regarding the provision of this school and on the progress being made by the Office of Public Works in identifying and acquiring a site for the school.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Shane Ross of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources to improve existing methods of carbon emission reduction and to support the development of alternative methods.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is No. 1, Electoral (Amendment) Bill 2008, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business and adjourn no later than 1.30 p.m., if not previously concluded, with spokespersons having 15 minutes, other Senators ten, and on which Senators may share time.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>Today&rsquo;s edition of <i>The Irish Times</i> contains a copy of the Government&rsquo;s framework document on economic renewal.  It has been raised several times in the D&aacute;il and the Seanad that when they returned, they both had a general debate on the future of the economy without the Government outlining any of its plans, policies or details.  Very little thought was given to the role of the D&aacute;il and the Seanad in handling this crisis.  This week it is clearer than ever that social partnership has replaced democracy.  It does not have to be one or the other; it can be both.  The Government will have to give some thought to the role of the <Col N="504"/>D&aacute;il, the Seanad and our democracy, alongside the role of social partnership, because what happened this week was not good enough.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FrancesFitzgerald"><NameTxt>Senator Frances Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
	<P>It was not good enough to have the general debate we had this week.  Yesterday&rsquo;s display by the Minister for Transport, Deputy Noel Dempsey, and other Ministers, in dealing with the debate in the D&aacute;il was appalling.  They did not come with any detailed plans from their Departments or detail how they intended to handle the crisis.  They did not speak on priorities or cutbacks and where they would take place.  No details were given to either the D&aacute;il or the Seanad in the debates on the economy.</P>
        <P>The lack of accountability to the D&aacute;il and the Seanad was extraordinary.  It marked a turning point, one which must be taken seriously.  The Government must examine the matter in detail and put democracy and accountability back into the process.  Accountability has been missing from the public finances over the past ten years and that is why there has been so much waste.  If we are to use this crisis as an opportunity, the least we must do is learn the lessons of the past and change the way we prepare our budgets and give account to the Oireachtas.  This week&rsquo;s events gave us a bird&rsquo;s eye view of arrogance and lack of accountability and I suggest the Green Party and Fianna F&aacute;il should examine how they dealt with the return of these Houses because their approach is not acceptable in any country that calls itself a democracy.</P>
        <P>I support the calls which were made yesterday by several Senators on the Government side for a debate on child protection.  A number of cases were reported in today&rsquo;s newspapers which involved inconsistency and, indeed, mistakes in sentencing.  It is clear that debate is needed in this House on these matters.  We are awaiting a new report from the Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse, which received an extension to its deadline, on historic abuse over the past five decades.  However, while we thought abuse was an historic issue, we can see from recent cases that our society still has a lot to learn about child protection and putting in place services that ensure we are fully protecting children.  I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on these issues at the earliest opportunity.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>It would be useful if this House held a debate on the Eames-Bradley report, which forces us to confront certain issues.  It is easy to understand why it was met with an extraordinary degree of emotion in the North.  However, being able to understand the reaction of all the parties concerned does not necessarily mean one would agree with them.  It behoves us to examine the report and to determine our views on it.  If somebody dies, his or her family probably suffers the same sense of loss regardless of whether he or she was Ireland&rsquo;s worst terrorist or most innocent victim or an upholder of law and order.  That has to be considered.  It is not a question of equating one with the other.  I do not want to debate the issues now but the point I want to make is that we would be forced to address issues we have not previously raised in terms of how the community and family lives have been affected.</P>
        <P>Wearing my hat as chair of the North-South co-operation Ireland group in Leinster House, which recently visited a number of places in the North and held a meeting with the North-South Ministerial Council, I became aware for the first time of certain issues.  Senator Boyle, who was also part of the group, can confirm that the work of the North-South Ministerial Council continues between meetings even though we hear nothing about this.  We regularly ask what is happening in regard to the Good Friday Agreement but Ministers and junior ministers meet weekly or fortnightly on various issues.  At the end of each meeting, the Northern Minister reports to the Northern Ireland Assembly.  It would be useful if that practice were followed here.  The Seanad would be an appropriate forum to discuss reports of ministerial meetings and <Col N="505"/>I ask the Leader to consider my suggestion and raise it with the Department of the Taoiseach or the Department of Foreign Affairs, both of which deal with these matters.</P>
        <P>Senator Fitzgerald is correct about the current round of social partnership talks.  As one with many years of experience in social partnership, I can see the matter from both sides.  I can see how these Houses are being excluded from discussions.  We need to consider the matter very carefully because it should not be a question of our being part of the negotiations or of democracy being undermined in Government Buildings.  I concur with Senator Fitzgerald that we can have it both ways.  The public sector unions are meeting at present with their employer, that is, the Government, and the private sector unions are meeting with representatives of their employers, IBEC and others.  It is the only place discussions of this nature can take place but, in terms of keeping people up to date, this should be done by reporting to the Houses.  That is the missing element from the effort to ensure everyone gets behind the process.  I would like to receive a report in this House.  We are not going to read the details in <i>The Irish Times </i>because a basic rule of negotiation is that nothing is agreed publicly before it is agreed in private.  I did not even read the report in today&rsquo;s edition of <i>The Irish Times </i>because I know there is nothing in it.  If I was in charge of negotiations I would ensure that such reports contained only the vaguest of details.  That does not mean, however, that responsible Members of the Opposition should not be informed and that is where we are lacking at present.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AlexWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Alex White</NameTxt>
	<P>The document to which Senator O&rsquo;Toole referred is the one which the Leader told us yesterday we had been discussing on Tuesday.  It was published in <i>The Irish Times</i> yesterday and we manifestly could not have discussed it the previous day because we did not have it in our possession.  I ask the Leader to acknowledge that, unless he was confusing it with the other frameworks that are knocking around, including one from before Christmas.  We asked for the most recent document to be made available to assist and inform us in our debate on the economy.  It was not made available and while I do not infer that the Leader was trying to mislead Members, it was simply wrong and inaccurate of him to state in his closing comments yesterday that we had debated it the previous day.  How could we have debated something we had not seen?  I ask for the matter to be corrected on the record.</P>
        <P>Senator Fitzgerald is correct that a serious democratic deficit, to coin a phrase, must be addressed.  I take the view that the Government has not the slightest intention of involving these Houses in this debate at a serious level, despite what Senator Boyle believes should happen.  I give him credit for some of the statements he has made in this House but, if he is pushing that position, he has not got far with his colleagues in Government because they are excluding these Houses entirely.  The Minister for Social and Family Affairs, Deputy Hanafin, gave the game away on &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; this morning.  I am interested in words and what they mean.  I am not a subscriber to the Humpty Dumpty approach of words meaning what people want them to mean.  The Minister said this morning that negotiations would proceed and that the Government would seek the agreement of the social partners and the support of the Oireachtas.  That is the Government&rsquo;s position.  It regards the Houses of the Oireachtas as cheerleaders for an agreement reached elsewhere.  I entirely agree with Senator Fitzgerald.  This is a serious issue and it is not good enough in any democracy for the Taoiseach and his Ministers to have fits of pique and storm away like schoolboys when asked for a debate in these Houses.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to arrange a debate with the Minister for Transport on the cuts in Dublin Bus.  Again on the issue of language, Senator Boyle sought to persuade us last night that these were not cuts even though his colleague, Deputy Cuffe, has described them in print as service cutbacks.  The company has made 290 staff redundant and 120 buses have been taken off the streets.  If these are not cuts, what are they?  Surely, they will impact on service.  Bus lanes in the north and south of the city have been set aside for buses which are being taken off the <Col N="506"/>streets.  This is coming from a Government party which proclaimed prior to the general election that it favoured public over private transport.  It is ludicrous.  We need to hold a debate on the question of public transport and I ask the Leader to facilitate this.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>Senator Denis O&rsquo;Donovan</NameTxt>
	<P>On the issue of child protection and the proposal for a referendum on the rights of children, I was the Chairman of the Joint Committee on the Constitution when it was asked by the then Taoiseach, Deputy Bertie Ahern, to examine the issue of children&rsquo;s welfare.  The committee unanimously agreed that the current constitutional protections of the rights of the child within the family was inadequate and proposed that a referendum should be held to protect and enhance the rights of the child as opposed to the family.  I am somewhat disappointed this has been delayed given that we were told in some of our discussions that the Kilkenny incest case was a unique event that would never be repeated.  I support the calls made in this regard.  However, it is a very delicate issue.  The majority of submissions felt the child was adequately protected among family.  If the wording of such a referendum is not completely right, it could have an adverse effect and we might see a result that was never envisaged.  In principle, I support the idea of a constitutional referendum, although the right wording will be difficult to achieve.  We found it extremely difficult to agree on the wording; we failed to do so.  It must be correct or else, like the abortion referendum, there may be a result that was never intended.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to have a debate on aquaculture, mariculture and seafood.  We have a fantastic coastline but the industry has been neglected and we are over-regulated.  There is an ongoing debate on AZA toxins which affect mussels, oysters and other seafood.  It is a shame that the economy is contracting and the construction industry is in disarray, yet we have the potential to create jobs along our coastline in fish farming.  The biggest abalone factory in the northern hemisphere is on the Beara peninsula.  There is much potential for the mussel industry.</P>
        <P>On the one hand, Bord Iascaigh Mhara is promoting these products but on the other, there is over-regulation.  I see much potential for job creation.  The plan for the mussel industry in the mid-1990s proposed an increase in output to 30,000 tonnes but we have stagnated at 10,000 tonnes.  As an example, the Chileans started with zero tonnage in 1990 and their fish farming, especially with salmon, employs 40,000 people in the remote southern part of Chile.  Their mussel industry has increased to approximately 400,000 tonnes.  The French, Spanish and our UK partners are laughing at us because they have progressed and we have not.  There are jobs to be created along the coastline.</P>
        <P>I had a meeting with the Irish Shellfish Association, and its representatives are deeply concerned that a lack of licensing, over-regulation and all these special areas of conservation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>We are looking for agreement on the debate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>Senator Denis O&rsquo;Donovan</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;stymie and could destroy any potential.  I am seeking a debate on this, possibly a four-hour debate like we had yesterday on Bantry Harbour.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EugeneRegan"><NameTxt>Senator Eugene Regan</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to address the talks between the Government and the social partners.  These talks began as discussions on expenditure cuts and pay.  Issues of taxation were left to the Commission on Taxation, which would report later in the year.  The Minister for Finance had indicated there was no scope for further increases in taxation in 2009.  In a concession in those talks, the emphasis has shifted and the Government has conceded that taxation issues will be part of whatever agreement is arrived at.  There are intimations of increases in the different levels of taxation.</P><Col N="507"/>
        <P>It seems that increased taxes are the easy option, which avoids the real decisions that need to be made on the curtailment of public expenditure.  There is a serious risk that under this Government we will return to a high taxation economy, when we know a low taxation regime contributed to the growth we have enjoyed over the past ten years.</P>
        <P>This exemplifies how the social partnership process is providing a straitjacket for Government decision making.  Although the social partnership process has been very beneficial in its initial phases, it has provided political cover for the worst ten years of economic management of this economy, which has contributed to the problems we have today.  In particular, IBEC bears much responsibility for indulging in and providing in that period the political cover for the waste introduced, either through benchmarking, decentralisation or not calling a halt and raising concerns about the way the housing market was managed.</P>
        <P>This is a fundamental problem, which we can see from the Draft Framework for a Pact for Stabilisation, Social Solidarity and Economic Renewal.  The document is so all-embracing, inclusive and wordy as to be meaningless.  The recommendations include building on strengths in the agriculture, fisheries and food sector, supporting the manufacturing sector, encouraging entrepreneurship and business start-ups.  What is new?  Resolutions of the United Nations are more specific and meaningful than this type of document.  I am concerned that even if we reach agreement, it will not be what the Government initially set out to achieve, namely, cutbacks in public expenditure.  I ask the Leader to comment on the implications for the tax regime in 2009 with regard to these discussions.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvorCallely"><NameTxt>Senator Ivor Callely</NameTxt>
	<P>Unlike my colleagues on the opposite side of the House, I welcome the collective agreement of our political leadership and social partners to commence what one will appreciate will be very difficult negotiations.  It is an unprecedented approach to address the country&rsquo;s current challenges for economic renewal.  When we are borrowing &euro;50 million a day, with an annual shortfall of &euro;18 billion or thereabout, there is a great need to prioritise the stabilisation of our public finances.  I am delighted that all parties have signed in to address this without delay and I wish them well in the very difficult negotiations likely to take place in the coming days and weeks.</P>
        <P>From this side of the House I wish those involved in the discussions every success and let them know clearly that many ordinary working class people are deeply concerned about the position we are in and would like to see agreement to rectify the problem and bring about economic recovery as quickly as possible.</P>
        <P>I welcome the Health Service Executive report on progress to reduce the spread of MRSI infection in our hospitals.  The progress should be noted as the targets set will be met, and it is not every day of the week that we can stand up and applaud the HSE in some of its endeavours in this regard.  The improved hygiene and cleanliness is very noticeable in hospitals in my own region, such as the Mater, Beaumont, St. Joseph&rsquo;s and the Incorporated Orthopaedic Hospital of Ireland, and I congratulate all involved because we know it is a difficult task.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader raise with the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform the case of the serious and repeated paedophilia case before the Court of Criminal Appeal yesterday?  I am appalled that a ten-page judgment has been issued that is critical of the trial judge, indicating he made an error in principle.  The judge has a great reputation and I have great personal admiration for him.</P>
        <P>Having said that, we must deal with the fact that a person whom the Court of Criminal Appeal agreed was a threat to society has had a life sentence reduced to 12 and a half years.  He is likely to be on the streets before that period is up.  It is a serious case that warrants the <Col N="508"/>Leader taking the matter up with the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform.  I would appreciate a full and detailed brief on the prevailing position in this case.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader for a debate on what can be done in the aftermath of the Israeli onslaught on Gaza.  In the general doom and gloom of the news over Christmas and the early part of this month, the worst news of all was undoubtedly of the carnage inflicted upon the people of Gaza by Israel.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I know others have raised the matter in this House.  I ask that we take some time in this House in the next week or so to debate what can be done to ensure Israel is held accountable for the undoubted war crimes that it committed in inflicting such appalling onslaughts and attacks on the people of Gaza.  We saw 1,300 Palestinians killed, with a third of them children, there were an enormous number of injuries, and homes and infrastructure were destroyed.  We must ask what can now be done.  It appears the worst is over but Israel is continuing to perpetrate attacks and kill innocent Palestinians.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">11 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>Everyone welcomes President Obama&rsquo;s appointment of George Mitchell as Middle East envoy.  That is certainly a development about which we can be optimistic.  However, Members must ask what action the Seanad can take in the context of seeing to it that pressure continues to be applied at EU level to ensure Israel is held accountable.  The Government has been extremely strong in respect of this matter.  However, the Seanad could play an important role in supporting the Ireland Palestine Solidarity Campaign&rsquo;s call that the favourable position Israel currently holds in the context of trading with the EU should no longer apply.  We could also support the campaign&rsquo;s call for a consumer boycott of Israeli goods and services.  When Ministers are calling on us, as Irish citizens, to do our patriotic duty by not shopping in Northern Ireland&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator has made her point.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;it would be far more important if we did our patriotic duty as citizens of the world by not buying Israeli goods and services.  Israel deserves to be treated as a pariah state.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Well said.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I was among those who called for an end to diplomatic relations with Israel at the height of the appalling carnage that occurred.  That was an appropriate call to make at the time.  The Seanad could take a strong role &mdash; I am aware that there is cross-party support for this &mdash; in the context of trying to hold Israel accountable in respect of what was done.</P>
        <P>I also wish to request a debate on female genital mutilation, especially in the wake of the recent judgment in the case of Pamela Izevbekhai case.  A number of Senators have raised this matter in recent months.  I am of the view that there might be support in the House for a <?oasys _dc18- ?>cross-party motion calling on the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform to allow Ms Izevbekhai<?oasys _dc0- ?> to remain in this country on humanitarian grounds.  The House previously passed an all-party motion expressing solidarity with Ingrid Betancourt, the French-Colombian detainee.  It would be appropriate for us to draw up a motion relating to Ms Izevbekhai&rsquo;s case, particularly in light of the appalling circumstances of female genital mutilation.  Everyone recognises that in any civilised country the latter must be seen as torture.  I ask the Leader to accede to my call in <Col N="509"/>respect of this matter.  I would be happy to assist in drafting a wording that might garner cross-party support.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P><?oasys _dc18- ?>I echo Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s comments regarding the Eames-Bradley<?oasys _dc0- ?> report on the Troubles in Northern Ireland.  The two gentlemen involved in compiling this report played a central role in finding a resolution to the Troubles.  Archbishop Eames in particular never received the credit he deserved for the role he played.  When the Troubles were at their height, he came forward and spoke with a moderate voice.  It must have taken great courage to do so.  In my opinion, his action was vital at a particular juncture during the Troubles.  The position as regards Mr. Bradley is similar.</P>
        <P>It is a pity that people had to wait until a press conference was held before they had an opportunity to express their grief, anger and other emotions.  Would it be possible to request the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, CPP, to consider allowing the Seanad to play a consultative role in respect of the Eames Bradley report?  When we were trying to find a way forward in the context of arriving at a solution to the Troubles, people were allowed to go before the New Ireland Forum to express their diverse views in a very controlled manner.  The Seanad also played a consultative role in respect of its own reform and various individuals were allowed to appear before us to make contributions.</P>
        <P>It is much more difficult to make peace than it is to make war.  We are making peace at present and everyone has witnessed the results brought about on foot of the Good Friday Agreement.  I salute everyone who has played a role in this regard.  However, I am of the view that we are taking the results and benefits of the Agreement for granted and forgetting the suffering of people who lost loved ones.  Even normality can exacerbate the grief individuals feel because they must continue with their lives against the background thereof.</P>
        <P>In light of its status, I am of the view that the House might be in a position to play a consultative role and allow people to express their view.  I suggest that this matter be discussed by the Government and not merely the CPP.  It would be a grave injustice to the thousands who suffered as a result of the Troubles if they were to simply be ignored because progress is being made.  I ask that the CPP consider this matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>With respect to Senator Callely&rsquo;s comments, there is no question of anybody on this side of the House not wishing the negotiations between the Government and the social partners well.  Everyone wishes those negotiations well because their outcome is vital to the national interest.  However, Senators Fitzgerald, O&rsquo;Toole and Alex White commented upon the fact that a democratic deficit exists in the Houses.  This is a line of thinking to which I also subscribe.  The Leader recalled the Seanad this week and the first item on our agenda was a debate on the economy.  However, Members were not presented with a framework document, an options document or any other kind of document which might have indicated the nature of the Government&rsquo;s thinking on the matter.  As other Senators and I commented in recent days, the debate took place in isolation and was disjointed as a result.</P>
        <P>There is a need for the D&aacute;il and Seanad to be involved in a more structured way in the current process.  The Oireachtas must be made more meaningful.  We did not do justice to the debate on the economy or give to it the detailed consideration it required because we were not presented with an options or framework document.  That is what is wrong and what has given rise to the lack of accountability.  Everyone accepts that it is to the Houses of the Oireachtas that people should be accountable.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Toole referred to North-South co-operation and the meetings that take place regularly, not merely at ministerial level but also among agencies and bodies of an official or <Col N="510"/>semi-official nature.  It would be useful if Ministers could make occasional reports to the Seanad in respect of this matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Senator Marc MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Bacik requested a debate on female genital mutilation, FGM, and the case of Ms Pamela Izevbekhai and her children, who are based in Sligo.  Irrespective of a debate, an outcome, a court judgment on FGM or whatever, people must recognise that this is a very human case.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Senator Marc MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>I know those involved and I can state that Ms Izevbekhai&rsquo;s children speak with Sligo accents.  Regardless of the law or any considerations relating to FGM, these people have lived in Sligo &mdash; they call it home &mdash; for quite a period of years.  It is clear that a large proportion of the local community would like them to remain living in the area.  On the basis of the human considerations involved, a decision should be made to allow these people to stay in Ireland.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.  Well said.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Senator Marc MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>We could then debate FGM and other issues.  It is not possible to have a completely open-door policy.  Legal proceedings in this case are ongoing but the children involved are trying to go about their daily lives.  They are more native to Sligo than they are to anywhere else.  If one of the county&rsquo;s teams reached an All-Ireland Final, they would support it.  I would appreciate it if the Leader could bring this matter to the attention of the Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, Deputy Dermot Ahern.</P>
        <P>All of the various pillars are represented at the social partnership negotiations.  Seanad &Eacute;ireann and D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann are represented there by the Government.  Those acting on behalf of the Government are mandated by us to obtain the best deal possible.  That deal will then be brought back to the Houses and Members can approve or disapprove of it as the case may be.  As Senator Coghlan, as a member of the industrial and commercial panel, is aware, if he had gone in a different direction with his career, he could be on the other side of the fence and could be involved in representing the social partners in the negotiations.  Everyone wishes those involved in the negotiations well.</P>
        <P>Unlike Senator Regan, I will not prejudge the outcome and state that whatever deal is arrived at will be the wrong one.  I completely disagree with the sentiments expressed by the Senator.  Like Senator Callely, I wish those involved well.  There is no stronger message that could be put forth than by having the social partners and the Government &mdash; which represents the Houses of the Oireachtas &mdash; emerge next week with a deal in place and a statement of intent to the effect that the country is in control of its affairs and is prepared to take all necessary action.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>That is what I said.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Senator Marc MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Leader make time available for a debate on banking and banking regulation?  We need to give careful consideration to the regulatory environment that applies in respect of banking.  Momentum is building in the United States for the establishment of an aggregator bank.  Under this model, bad debts could be pooled and managed centrally.  This would allow banks that in a stronger position to proceed with their main business, namely, the supply of credit to the domestic and commercial markets.  I am not necessarily saying we should do that, nor am I saying we should not do so.  A debate on that issue would be positive. <Col N="511"/> The aggregator bank idea is gathering momentum, in particular in the United States and the UK, and we should consider it.</P>
        <P>Clearly some progress has been made in recent days and we have seen the markets rally since last Friday.  I do not believe there have been five days over the past eight months when we have seen such a rally, so that is welcome.  On a pan-European basis at the very least &mdash; I do not know if there are grounds to do so internationally &mdash; we need to begin to put together some basic regulatory conditions which we will operate into the future so that the disastrous situation in which we find ourselves internationally is not replicated in the future.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I was glad to see this morning the publication by the National Roads Authority of its plans for roads expenditure for 2009.  It is approximately &euro;1.5 billion in expenditure with some particularly worthwhile schemes throughout the country.  In County Meath, major schemes like the Slane bypass will be progressed as will minor safety schemes such as improved measures at Kilmoon Cross.</P>
        <P>In this current climate, it is clear there are benefits to be gained and savings to be made from procurement policies.  I do not know whether a cost-effectiveness study of these schemes will be done.  However, I suggest the Leader asks the Minister to do a value for money appraisal of these schemes to ensure where there are savings to be made, they can be put towards fighting the cutbacks on Dublin Bus and commuter bus services so that we see a much more evenly balanced commuter policy and not only expenditure on roads, which is worthwhile and necessary, but also expenditure on the maintenance of our public transport services.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Leader back.  I do so because he very kindly welcomed me back yesterday.  It was excessively courteous of him and I would not like him to think he was under any slight because I did not do the same to him.  He is a Castlepollard man in whom there is no guile.  Had it been anybody else, I would have thought it might have been a sly attempt to suggest I was not here at some stage.  As he knows well, like himself, I have been here every day and, as some people think, have spoken a little too much.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Some would agree.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Leader for his constructive suggestion yesterday that we might be able to put together an all-party motion to support the Government&rsquo;s moves in regard to a war crimes tribunal on Gaza.  The Minister for Foreign Affairs advanced this measure with other EU foreign ministers.  He was supported by Cyprus, Portugal and Sweden.  I suggest that the Government might be encouraged to continue to talk to these countries to see if this can be done because, as Senator Ivana Bacik said very powerfully, there is <i>prima facie</i> evidence of war crimes in this instance.</P>
        <P>We should monitor external trade association agreements.  That is a non-violent matter.  Some 75% of Israeli agricultural products come into the European Union.  The Union could have switched that war off if it had threatened agricultural imports.  That is a good reason I will again campaign against the Lisbon treaty if it is put before us because that is the kind of thing with which we have to put up.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader about the fate of two Bills, the first being the immigration Bill.  We had a briefing about the immigration Bill in the audio-visual room which was well attended by Members of both Houses.  It is quite defective and needs to be amended by this House.  When is it proposed to take it?</P>
        <P>When will the domestic partnership Bill, the civil partnership Bill or whatever it is being called now be introduced?  I notice that in the past week Sweden has joined a growing number <Col N="512"/>of countries to introduce a Bill on full gay marriage.  Could we have a clear and firm commitment on that?</P>
        <P>Will the Leader get the Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food or the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government to welcome the EU directive on pesticides, herbicides, fungicides and insecticides in which 22 substances have been banned?  A number of Members on both sides have raised the extraordinary destruction perpetrated on the hedgerows in County Meath with the dangerous use of these products.  As a result of this directive, they will be controlled and instruction will be given to local authority staff when they are used close to schools, hospitals and so on.  This is a really positive move from the Union and I would like it to be officially welcomed.  It has been met by silence even though a case was highlighted in this House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I support Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute; in his promotion of the concept of the Seanad playing a larger part in regard to Northern Ireland, whether by way of debate, as in the past, or in the manner which the Senator and, I believe, Senator O&rsquo;Toole proposed.  There is a danger that we will accept peace in Northern Ireland without recognition of the horrors which took place over the years.  We can help in some way.</P>
        <P>There was criticism in recent days of Denis Bradley and Archbishop Eames because they proposed that money should be paid to all those families which suffered during the difficulties in Northern Ireland, even those who were responsible for planting bombs and for creating some of that horror on both sides.  It is very easy for us to criticise decisions such as that but these two men have thought this through and have come up with what they believe is a solution.  That would be worthy of discussion but Northern Ireland should be on our agenda more regularly.</P>
        <P>My postman reminded me the other day that An Post is 25 years old this month.  I have not seen any sign of celebration but at an Oireachtas committee the other day, a member said he or she did not want any more e-mails while another said he or she gets so many e-mails that he or she does not give them the attention they deserve and that if he or she wants to get attention, he or she sends a fax.  Another member said that if he or she really wants to get attention, he or she sends a letter.  The handwritten letters I receive get much more attention.</P>
        <P>We should ensure we continue to use An Post to maintain a healthy postal service in Ireland.  One area in which we can help to do so is to concentrate on handwriting in primary school.  I see my grandchildren here pay a little less attention to handwriting.  I have grandchildren in school in France and the attention given to handwriting at primary school there is so much better than it seems in Ireland.  In the long term, the ability to write letters by hand is essential if we are to have a thriving postal service in the future.  Let us ensure we recognise the benefit of handwritten letters rather than just electronically delivered mail.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMcCarthy"><NameTxt>Senator Michael McCarthy</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish the social partners well in the economic recovery talks.  There is an obligation on all the social partners to ensure we bring the public finances back under control.  However, I issue a warning that scapegoating young garda&iacute;, teachers and nurses is not the way in which these partnership talks should be approached.  We need to be cognisant of the fact that many young families are struggling.  There are people who this time a year and a half ago would have been looking at a bright future but they have lost their jobs and are drawing the dole.  The schemes to help those people need to be looked at.  For example, a root and branch reform of the back to education allowance needs to take place along with other schemes which would put people back into training to ensure we can reboot the economy.</P><Col N="513"/>
        <P Just="Left">An important point made by Senator O&rsquo;Toole last week on &ldquo;The Week in Politics&rdquo; and again last night by Vincent Browne on<i> &ldquo;</i>Nightly News with Vincent Browne&rdquo; on TV3 was that back in the 1980s, when social partnership was used as a model to get this economy going, we were told there was no money in the country.  We now know that was not the case.  Millions of pounds were siphoned out of this country.  If everyone is expected to make a decent attempt to get public finances in order, we need to know the correct state of play and ensure a bit of fair play.  Can we get a commitment that the banks will not repossess the homes of those who have recently found themselves unemployed?  It is important this House plays a vital role in contributing to the debate on the recovery of the economy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senators Fitzgerald, O&rsquo;Toole, Alex White, Regan, Callely, Coghlan and McCarthy all expressed their views on and wished the talks the success they deserve.  I want to correct Senator Alex White on one issue he raised.  The document I referred to, which I understand was of assistance to most Senators, was the one produced by the Taoiseach in Dublin Castle just before Christmas.  That clarifies the position.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>That clarifies it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P>An historic document.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader, without interruption.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>I said also that any request for time to debate the economy would find favour and would be facilitated on a weekly and monthly basis.  The Taoiseach&rsquo;s words in the D&aacute;il yesterday brought home the stark reality of the position in which we find ourselves.  All participants in the talks are to be congratulated on the responsible way they are addressing the difficult position.  The most eminent people at those talks said yesterday that even the suggestion a month or two months ago of the various directions in which the talks must proceed would be unthinkable.  The Taoiseach said yesterday that we are facing the most difficult global economic conditions in 70 years.  The most severe financial crisis since the great depression is taking its toll.  For example, the United States is now in the middle of a recession that began in December 2007 and may prove to be the longest and most severe in the post-war period.  Those are stark statements from the Taoiseach and everyone in a responsible position is expected to act in accordance with the difficulties we face.  </P>
        <P>It is uplifting to see the way the talks are proceeding.  We hope that over the weekend they will come to a conclusion in time for the Cabinet meeting next Tuesday morning.  We can then address the difficulty as a nation, with each of us playing our part.  Regardless of our position in life, everyone would like to be able to play their part and I look forward to a successful conclusion to the talks.  On the conclusion of the talks I will propose to the House that we suspend whatever business is on the agenda to allow Senators to express their views on the merits of the proposals, with the Minister present.</P>
        <P>Senators O&rsquo;Toole, &Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Coghlan and Quinn called for a debate on the report by Archbishop Eames and Mr. Bradley, which was launched yesterday.  I join all Senators in congratulating those two eminent and responsible citizens on the way they have worked steadfastly in the interest of everyone on the island of Ireland.  I have no difficulty affording time in the House for that debate.  As has been said, suffering has been experienced by families for the past 20, 30 and 40 years, going back to pre-1968 and 1969.  That is a long time ago.  Those of us who were working in the North of Ireland to make progress in every possible area are aware of that.  Senator Quinn is someone I listen to attentively regarding matters pertaining to Northern Ireland because I am aware he has close family ties there and a great deal of experience pre-1969 and since then.</P><Col N="514"/>
        <P>The suggestion made by Senator O&rsquo;Toole regarding the North-South talks is a very good one.  We should invite the Minister to the Seanad after each round of talks, where possible, and give Members and the general public an update on issues, as is done in the Assembly in Belfast.</P>
        <P>Senators Alex White and Hannigan called for a debate on transport.  I welcome the massive allocation of funding made available by the Minister for our road infrastructure and the huge sum of money being spent on our motorways and dual carriageways, in particular those from Dublin to Cork, Dublin to Galway, Dublin to Limerick and Dublin to Belfast.  Who would have thought 25 years ago that this would be the case?  We used to travel to the North of Ireland to experience the good roads in that part of the country.  One would know when one came across the Border that one was back in the different territory.  There has been a transformation in our road network.  To be parochial with Senator Hannigan, I understand the road from Clonee to Kells in our constituency is seven or eight months ahead of time and will be completed by the end of this year.  That is tremendous news for those of us who have to sit in our cars for an hour and a half or two hours some evenings when travelling home.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator could take the bus.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>We will now have the benefits of the M3, just as others use the M4, the M6 and all those dual carriageways.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>All the buses are gone now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Those who use the train have had that comfort for years also.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>(Interruptions).</i></P>
      <Speaker pid="DonnieCassidyFF"><NameTxt>Senator Donie Cassidy</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator O&rsquo;Donovan called for a debate on all aspects of the seafood industry, including mariculture, agriculture and all those areas.  We have an advantage in being a coastal country and there is a major opportunity for job creation.  Time will be made available for that debate in the near future.</P>
        <P>Senator Callely offered congratulations to the Health Service Executive on the major improvement in standards of hygiene in our hospitals.  I join him in that regard.  He expressed views also on the court case which took place yesterday and the reduction in the life sentence for a paedophile offence.  I will pass on his strong views to the Minister.</P>
        <P>Senators Bacik and Norris called for a debate on Gaza.  I have already made a commitment in that regard.  I am in contact with the Minister&rsquo;s office to determine when this debate can be facilitated at the earliest time.  I will pass on to the Minister Senator Bacik&rsquo;s views regarding Israeli produce.</P>
        <P>Senators MacSharry, Norris and Bacik expressed support once again for Pamela Izevbekhai and her family in Sligo.  I will convey their views to the Minister.  A decision has been made on that case in the High Court and I understand the intention is to proceed to the Supreme Court.  The difficulty for Oireachtas Members is that when a case is before any court, we must not interfere under any circumstances, regardless of the strongly held views of most Members of this House on this case.</P>
        <P>Senator MacSharry called for an urgent debate on banking.  I have no difficulty in allocating time for that debate and hope to have it in the next three or four weeks.</P>
        <P>Senator Quinn offered congratulations to An Post on its 25th anniversary and on the postal service, which is quite good here.  He also offered words of advice to our young people, partic<Col N="515"/>ularly those in our primary schools, on the importance of ensuring that hand writing is kept to the required standard, which is a major personal advantage to every individual.  If I receive a handwritten letter from someone it speaks a great deal in terms of the content before I even read it.  It puts me in a positive mood and I join with the Senator in his views, which I will pass on to the Minister.  It is rare occasion when one receives a handwritten letter, with the modern technology available to us.</P>
        <P>Senator Norris asked for an update on three items of legislation.  I have the details in my office of the immigration Bill and the civil partnership Bill.  I will get back to the Senator later this afternoon on those matters.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="2" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Electoral (Amendment) Bill 2008:" RHead="Second Stage"> 
    <Title>Electoral (Amendment) Bill 2008: Second Stage. </Title>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGormley"><TitleTxt>Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy John Gormley</NameTxt>
	<P>The main purpose of the Bill is to implement the recommendations in the report of the independent Constituency Commission published in October 2007 on revisions to D&aacute;il and European Parliament constituencies.  In addition, the Bill amends the law relating to the constituency revision process and provides for the introduction of alternative procedures for the nomination of non-party candidates at European Parliament and local elections.</P>
        <P>Parts 2 and 3 of the Bill provide for implementation of the recommendations of the Constituency Commission&rsquo;s report on D&aacute;il and European Parliament constituencies.  In considering these Parts, it may be helpful for the House if I outline the principal constitutional and legal requirements in these matters.</P>
        <P>Article 16.2.3&deg; of the Constitution provides that: &ldquo;The ratio between the number of members to be elected at any time for each constituency and the population of each constituency, as ascertained at the last preceding census, shall, so far as it is practicable, be the same throughout the country&rdquo;.  This provision was considered by the courts in two cases in 1961, namely, the High Court case of John O&rsquo;Donovan <i>v</i>. the Attorney General, and the Supreme Court reference case relating to the Electoral (Amendment) Bill 1961.  It was again considered in a High Court case in 2007 taken by Deputy Finian McGrath and former Deputy Catherine Murphy where it was argued that the constituencies on which the general election was being fought did not comply with the constitutional requirement contained in that article.  In none of these cases did the courts quantify the precise degree of equality of representation required by the Constitution.  Examples of significant disparities in terms of population to seat ratio based on census 2006 include: 21% above the national average in Dublin West; 18% above the national average in Dublin North; 14% above the national average in Meath East; and 10% below the national average in D&uacute;n Laoghaire.</P>
        <P>Article 16.2.4&deg; of the Constitution provides that: &ldquo;The Oireachtas shall revise the constituencies at least once in every twelve years, with due regard to changes in distribution of the population&rdquo;.  This, in effect, requires that the constituencies be revised whenever population changes, as shown in a census, lead to population to Deputy ratios in individual constituencies that are significantly out of line with the national average.  That is the case at present and the Oireachtas must respond accordingly.</P>
        <P>Section 5 of the Electoral Act 1997 provides that, on publication of the relevant Central Statistics Office report on a census, the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government must set up a commission to report on D&aacute;il and European constituencies.  The <Col N="516"/>terms of reference of the commission are specified in the Act and subordinate to the relevant constitutional provisions.</P>
        <P>As the House is aware, for more than half a century after the founding of the State, changes in constituencies were formulated and advanced by the Government of the day.  The first Constituency Commission was set up in 1977 to report on constituencies for the direct elections to the European Parliament in 1979.  The first D&aacute;il Constituency Commission was established in 1980 on a non-statutory basis and such commissions continued to report on constituency revisions until the enactment of the Electoral Act 1997.  The commission which reported in October 2007 was the third statutory commission established under the Act.</P>
        <P>Volume 1 of the 2006 census reports was published in April 2007.  This showed an increase in total population from 2002 of more than 322,000, giving a total population in the State of 4.24 million.  Thus, each of the 166 Deputies represented an average of 25,541 persons in 2006.</P>
        <P Just="Left">As I stated, the detailed population figures for each constituency showed that there were serious variances from the national average population per Deputy in a number of constituencies.  Nineteen constituencies had variances from national average representation in excess of 5% and 11 had deviations in excess of 8%.  The most under-represented constituencies were Dublin West and Dublin North with variances of +21% and +18%, respectively.  The most over-represented constituencies were D&uacute;n Laoghaire and Cork North-Central with variances of -10% each.  Clearly, significant changes have become necessary in some areas to secure equality of representation between constituencies based on the 2006 census.  Therefore, in accordance with section 5 of the 1997 Act, a Constituency Commission was set up in April 2007, chaired by Mr Justice larfhlaith O&rsquo;Neill.  The other members of the commission were: Mr. Kieran Coughlan, Clerk of the D&aacute;il; Ms Deirdre Lane, Clerk of the Seanad; Ms Geraldine Tallon, Secretary General of the Department of the Environment, Heritage and Local Government; and Ms Emily O&rsquo;Reilly, the Ombudsman.  I thank the commission members for the conscientious and impartial manner in which they carried out their work.</P>
        <P>The main features of the commission&rsquo;s report on D&aacute;il constituencies are as follows.  First, there should be no change in the existing level of D&aacute;il membership, that is, 166 seats.  Second, the total number of constituencies should remain at 43 and no change should be made in 19 constituencies.  Third, there should be an increase of one seat in both the Louth and Dublin West constituencies, together with changes in the areas covered by the constituencies.  Fourth, there should be a reduction of one seat in both the D&uacute;n Laoghaire and Limerick East constituencies, with the latter to be renamed as Limerick City, and there should be changes in the areas covered by the constituencies.  Fifth, the area and name of two constituencies should change, with Kerry North and Limerick West to be amended to Kerry North-West Limerick and Limerick, respectively.  Sixth, changes, many of them small, should be made to the areas of 18 other constituencies.</P>
        <P>The main features of the commission&rsquo;s report on European Parliament constituencies are, in a context of 12 Irish Members of the Parliament, a reduction of one seat in the Dublin constituency and the transfer of the population of counties Longford and Westmeath from the East to the North-West constituency.  The Government has accepted the commission&rsquo;s recommendations as a single package of interlinked measures bringing D&aacute;il and European Parliament constituencies into line with the prevailing population patterns, in accordance with constitutional imperatives and other legal requirements.  We can all recognise that it might have been possible for the commission to suggest solutions other than those recommended in the report and I appreciate fully the concerns that arise, including relating to breaches of county boundaries.  However, the commission has completed its work in accordance with its statutory terms of reference and its independent determination of the issues should now be respected.  Cherry-<Col N="517"/>picking individual recommendations would undermine the reasons for establishing an independent commission in the first place.  It is the Government&rsquo;s firm view that the precedent of adhering to the commission&rsquo;s advice should be adhered to.</P>
        <P>Part 4 revises the procedures to be followed by constituency commissions.  In terms of the form of this element of the Bill, it was decided that in view of the importance of these procedures, the amendments should be made by way of repeal and re-enactment with amendments of the full part of the Electoral Act 1997 dealing with the constituency revision process.  In this way, the two Houses, in considering the Bill and others subsequently, will be able to see in one place the full text of the law regarding a commission.</P>
        <P>As regards the substance, most of the existing law in this area is being retained.  The main change is that in the future commissions will be established on publication by the Central Statistics Office, following a census of population, of the census report setting out the preliminary result of the census in respect of the total population of the State.  A commission will have to report as soon as possible after publication by the CSO of the census report setting out the final result of the census in respect of the total population of the State and not later than three months after such publication.  Previously, commissions had to await final results before starting work and then had six months to complete their task.  This change responds fully to the High Court judgment in the case of Murphy and McGrath<i> v.</i> Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government and others in June 2007.  The court concluded that, having regard to constitutional requirements and the high quality of CSO preliminary population data, consideration should be given to initiation of constituency revisions on publication of the CSO preliminary report on a census, with the revision work being completed when the final data were available.  This is an important new provision which I hope will be welcomed on both sides of the House.</P>
        <P>The opportunity is also being taken in the Bill to update and improve the consultation processes followed by a commission in the course of its work.  The Bill requires a commission to allow at least three months for the making of submissions to it.  At present, a commission has discretion as to the length of time allowed which is inevitably influenced by the six-month time limit on a commission to produce its report.  With future commissions commencing work on the basis of preliminary data, greater time can be made available for consultation with interested organisations and individuals, for which specific provision has been made in the Bill.  This will ensure a fuller opportunity for political and wider public input to the revision process.</P>
        <P>The Bill also expressly provides that background information statements prepared by the commission are to be made available free of charge.  Previous provision that fees had to be paid to obtain copies of submissions made to a commission has been replaced by a requirement that they also are to be made available free of charge.  A requirement in the existing law regarding physical inspection of submissions at specified times and places has been revised to allow the commission to decide on the detailed arrangements for making these publicly available.  In this way, best use can be made, for example, of the Internet to allow access to submissions.  Taken together, these are significant and worthwhile improvements to the consultation processes followed by constituency commissions during the course of their work, while retaining the essential features of commission procedures which have operated effectively for many years.  This part of the Bill also updates the fines provisions in sections 14 and 15 of the 1997 Act and references in the law to specific offices and other legislation that have changed in the decade since the Act came into operation.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The final elements of the Bill, Parts 5 and 6, deal primarily with providing alternative procedures for nomination of non-party candidates at European Parliament and local elections.  The need for alternative procedures for nomination of such candidates arises from a judgment <Col N="518"/>of the Supreme Court in November 2006 in the case of King, Cooney and Riordan <i>v.</i> Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, the Attorney General and others.  The judgment deals with the assentor requirements for the nomination of D&aacute;il candidates who are not members of registered political parties.  In particular, the court upheld the main requirement for obtaining assentors to help ensure the proper regulation of elections but struck down the provision requiring personal attendance by all assentors at a single location in a constituency on the basis that it could involve excessive demands on the time of assentors.  The court found the provision was disproportionate to the objective to be achieved, namely, the due authentication of nomination papers and declared the relevant section of the Electoral Act 1992 to be unconstitutional.</P>
        <P>The implications of the Supreme Court judgment were dealt with by the enactment of the Electoral (Amendment) Act 2007.  Owing, however, to the limited time available and the urgent need for enactment and implementation before the 2007 general election, the text of the 2007 Act provided for alternative nomination procedures, nomination deposits or assents, for non-party candidates at general elections only.  Corresponding procedures for European Parliament and local elections are required in advance of the upcoming elections and are included in the Bill on that basis.  The procedures proposed follow those enacted in 2007 for general elections.</P>
        <P>Parts 5 and 6 provide for two alternative mechanisms to regulate the nomination of candidates at European Parliament and local elections who are not in possession of a certificate of political affiliation.  The first mechanism is by way of assents requiring the completion of statutory declarations, 60 in the case of European Parliament elections and 15 in respect of local elections, by assentors in the constituency or local electoral area which may be witnessed by a commissioner for oaths, peace commissioner, notary public, garda or local authority official.  The second mechanism is by way of the candidate, or someone on his or her behalf, lodging a deposit with the returning officer.  The amount required is &euro;1,800 for European Parliament elections, &euro;100 in the case of the election of members of a county or city council or &euro;50 in the case of any other local election.</P>
        <P>The nomination procedures for candidates not in possession of a certificate of political affiliation standing at European Parliament and local elections are being brought into line with the procedures in place for such candidates at a general election.  This alignment of the nomination procedure, in Parts 5 and 6, represents a necessary improvement on previous arrangements and fully meets the relevant constitutional requirements.  Parts 5 and 6 also include two other provisions.  Section 13(<i>a</i>) increases the number of replacement candidates at European Parliament elections.  Section 20, reflecting developments in the law relating to use of primary and secondary legislation, provides that local election regulations shall have statutory effect as if they were an Act of the Oireachtas.</P>
        <P>The programme for Government contains a commitment to examine spending limits at local elections as part of the Green Paper on local government.  Such limits already apply to other categories of election.  Submissions made in the course of preparing the Green Paper which was published in April 2008 were generally supportive of some expenditure limit.</P>
        <P>I met the Oireachtas Joint Committee on the Environment, Heritage and Local Government on 7 October last, at my request, to seek the committee&rsquo;s views on the introduction of spending limits at local elections.  Members of the committee were generally in favour of this.  Following on from that, I indicated that I intend to introduce spending limits at local elections and to have the limits in place in time for the local elections to be held in June.  I also indicated that my preferred legislative route was to introduce the required changes by way of amendment to this Bill on Committee Stage during its passage through this House.</P><Col N="519"/>
        <P>However, I have recently been advised by the Attorney General that in view of the important issues provided for in the Bill it is essential that it be enacted at an early date and that the spending limit provisions should be brought forward in a separate Bill.  Work is therefore proceeding on the preparation of such a Bill to implement spending limits at the forthcoming local elections and I intend that it will be before the Houses for consideration as soon as possible.</P>
        <P>I stress the need to maintain the long-established practice of implementing in full the recommendations of constituency commissions.  The Bill now before the House does this.  The Government believes this is the right approach.  The Bill also makes significant and worthwhile improvements to the processes followed by constituency commissions in their work, as well as implementing measures to facilitate the holding of the upcoming European and local elections.</P>
        <P>I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order, will the Minister clarify something in his speech?  With regard to the commission&rsquo;s 2007 report, he stated:</P>
        <P LI="1">The main features of the commission&rsquo;s report in relation to D&aacute;il constituencies are as follows: firstly, no change in the existing level of D&aacute;il membership &mdash; that is to say, 166 seats.</P>
        <P FLI="0">Is that the true position?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGormley"><NameTxt>Deputy John Gormley</NameTxt>
	<P>That is correct.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  This side of the Chamber embraces the principle of an independent electoral commission.  As the Minister said, the commission is composed of eminent and suitably qualified people.  I thank the members of the commission for their diligent work.  It is not an easy task to represent the people by reviewing, redrawing and planning electoral boundaries.  Those of us who are old enough can remember the Tullymander of 1977 which was meant to insulate the coalition Government, and what happened afterwards.  Since the 1980s we have had an independent commission, which is welcome.  However, I have a difficulty with the fact that the commission receives a ministerial order concerning the type of constituencies &mdash; whether they should be four or five-seat constituencies.  I refer to the commission that changed the boundaries for the local elections, with specific reference to the city of Cork.  That did a complete disservice to the north side of Cork city by moving seats from the north to the south side.  The cynic in me would say that by taking six and seven-seat constituencies, the commission has favoured some of the smaller parties, the Minister&rsquo;s included, which normally win the last seat in some Cork constituencies.  That move was wrong and has done a disservice to local government.  I hope people will recognise that in the June local elections.</P>
        <P>The Minister referred to various changes to the commission.  I hope the commission will take to the road and meet people at town hall meetings to get their views.  The system is a bit off-putting for ordinary citizens who may not be well versed in making submissions to Departments.  They have the right to do so, as outlined in the commission&rsquo;s advertisements at appropriate times, but the commission should hold public meetings to hear their views.</P>
        <P>As the Minister knows, there has been a proposal this week to reduce the voting age for local elections to 16 years.  I am not necessarily sold on the idea of reducing the age to 16, although I am open to a debate it.  Perhaps the commission could use third level institutions and transition year modules to elicit students&rsquo; views.  It is important to hear public opinion because people can feel excluded despite the good will of the commission.</P><Col N="520"/>
        <P>Anomalies undoubtedly occur in the composition of electoral districts and constituencies.  The people of Leitrim rightly feel aggrieved in this respect.  Senator Ellis has eloquently put the case for that county, as has the former Deputy, Gerry Reynolds.  By the same token, some of the changes made by the commission in some counties do not make sense.  They do not take cognisance of the recommendation to examine natural county boundaries.  In the case of Cork, the Minister has left my constituency alone but he has changed Cork North-Central to a four-seat constituency.  Meanwhile, part of Cork East has been moved into Cork North-Central.  I had hoped Cork would be re-examined in an imaginative way.  The current composition of Cork constituencies has, by and large, been the same since the 1980s.  It needs to be changed.</P>
        <P>I am intrigued that this week the Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism, Deputy Cullen, said there will be no sports capital programme this year, yet the local elections will be held in June.  Meanwhile, the Minister, Deputy Gormley, has done a complete U-turn on what he said last weekend.  On national radio he waved the flag.  I support him regarding spending limits for elections, which is the best thing we could ever do.  Today, however, he has retreated on that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGormley"><NameTxt>Deputy John Gormley</NameTxt>
	<P>No, I have not.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I will explain my position.  We have 19 weeks to the local elections in June. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGormley"><NameTxt>Deputy John Gormley</NameTxt>
	<P>There will be spending limits for that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I hope the Minister will bring that in.  My party may not be in favour of it, but I am.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnGormley"><NameTxt>Deputy John Gormley</NameTxt>
	<P>Good.</P>
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">12 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
      </Speaker>
      <?oasys _mv-10- ?><Speaker pid="JerryButtimer"><NameTxt>Senator Jerry Buttimer</NameTxt>
	<P>I am in favour of it because it is most important.  During his reign, the Minister might also look at the issue of spending between elections.  In my humble opinion, that is a joke at the moment.  There is nothing to stop a candidate spending thousands or hundreds of thousands of euro up to the day the election is called.  When an election is called, however, we bring in a spending limit but it makes no sense.  Democracy should not be about getting elected through spending money.  Despite what people think of President Obama in America, if one looks at the amount of money he and the other candidates raised and spent, it is wrong.  Democracy is being fixed at a price but it should not be that way.  The Minister assured us that we will have spending limits, but I hope they will come into effect long before the elections so that we can have a meaningful debate on them.  Many people are afraid that to become involved in politics and get elected to any office requires a big expenditure, but we should not exclude anybody from running for office.  </P>
        <P>The Minister referred to Mr. Justice Clarke&rsquo;s judgment, which makes for interesting reading.  In the context of the next census &mdash; if this Government runs its course and stays in office &mdash; will we have a new review before us for 2012?  If so, what will that present to us?  Will we have the former Deputy, Gerry Reynolds, and Senator Ellis appearing on the plinth to talk about Leitrim and other parts of the country?</P>
        <P>The commission took a minimalist approach the last time, but it missed an opportunity in doing so.  Perhaps it is time for the Minister to re-examine Article 16.2 of the Constitution which refers to the ratio between the number of Deputies and the population of each constituency.  Given the way in which the country&rsquo;s population has grown towards the east, there is a fear that Cork and other areas will lose representation.</P><Col N="521"/>
        <P>I do not subscribe to the view that Ireland begins and ends at the Red Cow roundabout because people living in Kiltimagh, Bishopstown or Ballinamore deserve representation.  I accept changes had to be made to the European Parliament constituency boundaries because of the reduction in the number of seats.  However, natural boundaries have been changed for D&aacute;il elections and I am worried that people will not be represented by Members from their area.  The Schedule lists the townlands and boundaries, and the way some are fitted together does not make geographical sense and does not provide proper representation in a number of counties.  West Limerick and north Kerry are close but the ethos of representation in the area has been changed, as is the case in Cork East and Cork North-Central.</P>
        <P>Is the Minister willing to examine Article 16 and hold a constitutional referendum on the number of seats?  We do not have too many Deputies and Senators but we need to ask whether the population is best served by the current number of politicians.  This week the Government treated both Houses of the Oireachtas with disrespect by not engaging properly with Members on the economic framework document.</P>
        <P>I had hoped the Minister would spell out in his contribution what he meant by introducing spending limits for local elections.  The composition of the independent review group is a matter for him and I do not have a difficulty with the people on it because if the Minister appointed people associated with different political parties, he would be accused of gerrymandering, cronyism and so on.  The composition of the group is fair.</P>
        <P>The Bill has taken a long time to come to the House following the report in 2007.  We have no difficulty with it in principle.  I hope there will be meaningful reform of spending limits and that, in future, the Minister will desist from making recommendations regarding the number of seats in constituencies and leave it to the commission because it is important that it has a free hand in this regard.  I also hope the practice of reducing representation in areas suffering from depopulation will cease.  I understand the principle underpinning this approach, but it is wrong.  We will not oppose the Bill but we will table amendments.  I am pleased the Bill has been introduced but I hope the running of elections, the composition of the electoral commission and decisions on D&aacute;il boundaries will be independent because that would best serve democracy.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I do not welcome the Bill and I have made statements in this regard long before today.  The Minister is committed to the legislation because he inherited the commission report, which has become the most secretive document we have had in the country for a long time.  I have made requests under the Freedom of Information Act 1997 regarding the report, only to be told that no information can be provided and this is a sacrosanct decision.  I also contacted the Ombudsman who made the same decision and said the only place it could be challenged was the High Court.  That is not transparent.  Issues such as this are of grave importance to people throughout the country.</P>
        <P>Over the past 14 or 15 months, I have put on record my disgust and that of the people of County Leitrim at the way the county has again been gerrymandered.  The county was divided for 20 years until 1981 when it was reunited as part of the Sligo-Leitirm constituency.  The Murphy judgment and population figures are used as a cover by the commission for its actions.  The judgment states equality should be achieved but, in doing so, there were other means for dealing with the situation in Leitrim.  Some 75% of the submissions to the Constituency Commission prior to its most recent report came from Country Leitrim.  I am reliably informed that individuals, including the chairman of the commission, wanted the county to remain intact in one constituency.  I could not say this outside the House but I have privilege to say that.  That is the reason the relevant documents are being kept from the public.  It is wrong that the people of Leitrim, no more than the people of west Limerick who have been kicked into Kerry or the people of north Meath who have been kicked into Louth, are subject to the commission break<Col N="522"/>ing every one of its terms of reference, yet its recommendations are accepted as a <i>fait accompli</i>.  However, the Minister&rsquo;s comments today will ensure the report is not a <i>fait accompli</i>.</P>
        <P>The Minister confirmed that the decisions taken by the commission in the order in which he gave them, mean the members of the commission were not fair and objective in their assessment of everything that came before them.  Their terms of reference stated they had the right to increase the number of Deputies from 166 to 168.  As Senator Buttimer said, people might think there are too many Deputies and Senators but those who do not have representation in County Leitrim do not think so.  The people of west Limerick who have been kicked into Kerry or the people of south Offaly who have been moved into a Tipperary constituency do not think that either.</P>
        <P>The county boundary has always been sacrosanct in the State.  Football is played to the county boundary while local authorities are county-based, yet the D&aacute;il electoral system is not county-based but it should be.  A constitutional amendment is needed to make county boundaries sacrosanct and to allow the number of Members to vary according to population.  That must be done because it is open to challenge.  The Minister might not be happy with a number of the Bill&rsquo;s provision but the precedent had been set for him.  If we could read the documentation that was produced before decisions on boundaries were reached, we would understand why the commission delivered its recommendations.</P>
        <P>The commission members broke their terms of reference, which stated that county boundaries should be adhered to where possible and, if not, natural boundaries should be adhered to.  The trust placed in the commission by the Houses of the Oireachtas to prepare this review under the Minister has been broken.  Even at this late stage the Minister should seek a legal opinion on whether the breaking of the terms of reference means the report is flawed.</P>
        <P>I acknowledge that the Minister has a problem regarding the constituencies for European Parliament elections.  We all accept they are what they must be, and are going to be, as they are European Parliament constituencies.  There is time to review the D&aacute;il constituencies.  The Bill will disenfranchise people right across the country.  Instead of being represented by their own, people will be represented by outsiders.  I am not being critical of any of the people who represent Leitrim at the moment and who live outside the county.  However, if it comes to loyalty everyone accepts that they will stand up for their own county first and take that position.</P>
        <P>The Constituency Commission could have dealt with the problems of Leitrim and other areas had it changed from having 166 Members to 168.  It would have allowed the tolerances to be such that county boundaries would not need to be broken.  There were a number of opportunities open to it even to have left all of Leitrim in the one constituency.  Leitrim and Cavan would have had exactly the numbers for a four-seat constituency.  I accept that the six-seat constituency comprising Sligo, Leitrim and Roscommon was not within the commission&rsquo;s terms of reference.  However, it was a constituency that would have ensured no breaking of county boundaries.</P>
        <P>A number of other permutations could have been considered elsewhere in the country to prevent what has happened here.  I wonder how far the commission went within its terms of reference and how clear-cut it was.  I am convinced there is a cover-up here.  I have made applications under the Freedom of Information Act right up to the Ombudsman, which was as far as I could go short of the High Court, in an attempt to get the detail that was not being made available.  No other papers are unavailable in this way.  Even with a freedom of information application to discover what goes on in government, a certain amount of information will be made available.  This is the nearest thing I have seen to somebody handing out a report and saying: &ldquo;This is our report and there is no come back on it.&rdquo;  While I can understand there <Col N="523"/>being no comeback, the documentation used to produce that report should be made available to the public.</P>
        <P>I have no doubt that if this is challenged &mdash; as I believe it will be &mdash; the commission will be found not to have acted within its terms of reference in the report it prepared.  If it decided at the outset that it was going to have only 166 Members rather than examining having 168, which was within its terms of reference, it was not being objective or constructive within its terms of reference.  That is quite obvious.  That is why I asked the Minister to confirm that the first decision taken by the commission was to have only 166 Members in the D&aacute;il.  When it decided not to examine the possibility of having 168, it broke its terms of reference.  The public should be made aware of this.  It is the sort of thing that probably could not be said on the street, but it can be said in this House.  The Minister has a responsibility to have the report reviewed in the context of the legal advice available to him and I hope he does so.</P>
        <P>Some of the people in Meath have been moved into the Louth constituency, with county boundaries being broken again.  Part of Westmeath is in the Meath West constituency &mdash; a double break.  Based on natural geography, areas that were divided in Meath down the years have been subdivided again.  I wonder if personal agendas were involved with regard to some of the action that was taken.  I know there could have been, but to prove that is beyond the capacity of any Member of this House or of the Minister.  Certain people had certain agendas when it came to dealing with this situation, which is very wrong.  It is very unfair that somebody with local interests should be involved in this process.  That matter needs to be investigated.</P>
        <P>Let us consider west Limerick.  Kerry is a natural five-seat constituency because as we discussed earlier, rural areas are being depopulated of Deputies because of the change in the balance of population.  It is considerably easier for a Deputy to run a five-seat constituency in Dublin when it takes a maximum of ten or 15 minutes to get from one end of it to the other, than to run a five-seat or even a four-seat constituency in a rural area, which might be 100 miles from one end to the other.  These are the sorts of problems we all face.</P>
        <P>The Constituency Commission has made a total mess of its terms of reference in producing its report.  I appeal to the Minister to review the Bill even at this late stage.  I ask him to ask a new commission to act within the terms of reference provided, which have been totally broken, as the Minister has confirmed to me today.  It is important that the Minister has it reviewed.  I am convinced that the commission was not objective when it decided not to review every situation before reaching its decision.  The net result is that the people I represented in Leitrim no longer have a voice in the D&aacute;il and following this revision have no chance of having it for the foreseeable future.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I wish to share my time with Senator Bacik.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JoeOToole"><NameTxt>Senator Joe O&rsquo;Toole</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House and I express my respect for his keen interest in local and national democracy.  It has been very helpful that he has offered views on it regularly since his appointment as Minister.  I very much agree with the comments made by the previous speaker.  I am very concerned about the shift eastwards of the representatives in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  There is a problem there.  I do not disagree with what the Minister said in his speech.  I recognise and accept what is in the Constitution.  However, I believe representation should be based not just on population, but also on geography.  While I accept that would require a constitutional amendment, I would like to have a debate on it.</P>
        <P>I believe I have heard the Minister say that county boundaries should be kept and we should stick with those to some extent.  I am not sure I would agree because the shift in population <Col N="524"/>might overrule that and counties could be left with their boundaries intact but without representation.  We need a combination of both, which meets the point the Minister is making and the other points made about it.</P>
        <P>It is appalling that in my time in politics places like Mayo, Leitrim, Kerry, Limerick, Monaghan and others have lost representation which is moving to the east coast.  That will result in an imbalance that will be contrary to the philosophy of the Minister&rsquo;s party, if I may say so.  Although he is an urban Deputy, I am sure he knows the point I am making about the importance of regionalisation and regional representation.  There is a rational argument to be made along those lines.</P>
        <P>The Constituency Commission bottled it in the sense that it could have increased the number of Deputies.  The reason it did not do so is because it is afraid of the media.  I will give a good example of why that should be faced up to.  It is either a good idea or a bad idea and let us talk to reasonable people about it.  If people believe we have too many Deputies, to get rid of that argument once and for all, the Minister should have a referendum in every county to ascertain how many counties want to lose a Deputy.  We can then ask the question as to whether the number of Deputies should be reduced.  That will finish that argument.</P>
        <P>There were appalling reports yesterday by media people, who should know better, informing the population that only two or three people were sitting in the D&aacute;il Chamber for a debate.  There is a very simple answer to that.  By the way there was only one person in the Press Gallery.  What were the journalists doing?  All 36 of them are being paid in here.  They were not in there at all.  In reality the members of the press, like Members of the Houses, were watching it in their offices.  They were doing work, watching it on television monitors and coming in when their speaking time was allocated to them.  It would have been a total waste of time to have them sitting in the D&aacute;il Chamber listening to the debate if they could not make a contribution, which they would subsequently make in their own time.  That is not a difficult message to get across to people.  I am not saying that cynical people will accept that, but ordinary people need to hear that message.  I ask the Minister to examine this issue.  Some counties, particularly in the west, will lose their voice in national politics.</P>
        <P>The Minister referred to local democracy and stated he would bring forward introduce legislation.  I look forward to reading the White Paper in the next few weeks.  I would like him to indicate the date of its launch, rather than saying it will be in a few weeks.  Two issues concern me with regard to look democracy, one of which relates to my home town of Dingle and which I will not raise now.  The other relates to respect and funding for local democracy, even if it means bringing back local charges.  We must give power to local democracy, which means spending money.  People must see the money they are contributing being spent in their area for their good by those they elect to represent them.  People will gravitate towards direct mayoral elections, which should not be restricted to a couple of large cities.  Local democracy is enhanced all over Europe by the fact that in small towns and villages people of significance are honoured and respected because they will run for mayor.</P>
        <P>The Minister should press ahead with Seanad reform.  There is a cynical view that many of us who call for such reform are not really looking for it.  We want this done.  I understand the difficulties of the Independent Senators and those elected through panels but let us find a way forward.  The Minister should give us enough time to do so.  As long as we take irrevocable decisions, I am not opposed to allowing colleagues a full electoral period to adjust; therefore, the necessary changes would not have to come into operation until after the next election.</P>
        <P>I wished the Minister well with the White Paper on local government and the subsequent legislation.  I have also referred to the need for a geographical element in the determination of D&aacute;il representation and the need for Seanad reform.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="525"/>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senator O&rsquo;Toole for sharing time with me.  </P>
        <P>I support some of the reforming elements of this legislation.  It is welcome to hear the Minister say he intends to impose spending limits on local election candidates.  That is an important change and will ensure greater democracy and equity in the running of local elections.  I am concerned to hear, however, that this matter was not considered sufficiently urgent to be dealt with in this Bill.  The Minister might clarify whether the reforms he is proposing will be in place in time for this year&rsquo;s local elections.  I am conscious that some people have been selected as candidates and are already spending money on canvassing.</P>
        <P>I am concerned about some aspects of the Bill such as Parts 5 and 6 on the nomination of non-party candidates for the European Parliament and local elections.  While I understand the imperative for introducing an alternative procedure, I wonder why it was considered necessary to include a procedure, albeit as an alternative, whereby money would be lodged.  A sum of &euro;1,800 is required for a non-party candidate who wishes to stand in the European Parliament elections.  The lesser sum of &euro;100 is required for those who wish to stand for D&aacute;il elections and &euro;50 for local elections.  While the D&aacute;il and the local elections sums are less significant, I wonder why it was necessary to include that measure that one should have to pay money to stand as a candidate if one could not get 60 assentors for the European Parliament elections or fewer in the case of other elections.  A challenge was made to the idea of a monetary deposit in Redmond <i>v.</i> Minister for the Environment, Ireland and the Attorney General.  Why has the Minister seen fit to include it in the Bill and why is the sum so high, to the extent that it will be off-putting, for European Parliament elections?  What is the problem with allowing individuals to put their names forward for election on whatever basis they wish?  It is a matter for the electorate to decide whether they are worth supporting.  I do not see why we need this proviso.</P>
        <P>In Part 6 I welcome the Minister&rsquo;s commitment to adhere to the advice of the Constituency Commission in respect of the revision of constituencies.  However, the Bill is a missed opportunity because establishing constituency commissions on a similar basis as before misses the opportunity to provide for a more far-reaching commission in the form of an independent electoral commission which would have a more permanent and long-term role in the running of elections as recommended by an independent think tank on which I sat with people from a variety of political perspectives.  It was established under the auspices of the think tank for action on social change, TASC.  It set up a democracy commission under the chairpersonship of Mr. David Begg which reported in 2005.  I do not know if the Minister is familiar with the report entitled, Engaging Citizens &mdash; The Case for Democratic Renewal in Ireland, which made a number of interesting and important recommendations.  One of its primary recommendations was that there be an electoral commission in Ireland which would have a variety of roles but its primary function would be as an independent regulatory agency to supervise and assist in the running of elections at local and national level.  This idea is important because it would oversee the revision of constituency boundaries and also provide for outreach, research and voter education programmes, with the aim of increasing participation.</P>
        <P>The Minister is well aware of the disturbing figures indicating low levels of participation among young voters.  The National Youth Council of Ireland provides research showing that the level of participation in elections among young people has been declining.  This can be contrasted with very high participation rates among the older population.  In the general election of 2002 only 40% of young adults aged 18 and 19 years voted, whereas 90% of those aged between 65 and 74 voted.  Something must be done to increase participation.  There is a campaign to do so, run by the National Youth Council of Ireland.  Voter participation levels in socially disadvantaged communities tend to be lower than in middle-class communities, something an independent electoral commission could address.  This is a missed opportunity to <Col N="526"/>provide for something of that nature on a more permanent and statutory footing than the more limited functions of the constituency commissions replicated in the Bill.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Toole referred to the missed opportunity in respect of Seanad reform.  I accept that this is a matter on which the Minister is engaged and hope to see the fruits of that process sooner rather than later.  In the long term we should examine the basis for our electoral system.  Others have called for a reduction in the number of Deputies and Senators, although Seanad reform is a separate matter, one on which we have a number of reports.  There are a number of far-reaching proposals on how the Seanad could be reformed.</P>
        <P>On how we elect our politicians, changing the basis of election for some Deputies from a geographical constituency basis to a list system might be beneficial in strengthening our democracy.  The Ceann Comhairle recently commented on the need to change procedures in the D&aacute;il.  His comments could apply equally to the Seanad to make D&aacute;il and Seanad proceedings more accessible to the public resulting in greater interest and relevance but perhaps that is outside the scope of the Electoral (Amendment) Bill and a matter for the Houses.  If we examined the need for reform, we might examine our somewhat archaic procedures and how we might reform them to make them more relevant, to make people more aware of what is taking place in the D&aacute;il and the Seanad and to make us more accountable and our procedures, transparent.</P>
    <HtmlBk SectId="3" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>This Bill is narrow in focus.  It does not go anywhere near meeting many of the commitments in the programme for Government on electoral and democratic reform.  There is already a clear commitment to establish an independent electoral commission and I look forward to that legislation.  There is also a commitment to local government reform and democratic reform in general.  The Minister will publish a White Paper soon and I hope it will help that process.</P>
        <P>Recent court judgments allow individual citizens to participate properly in elections, some of which will be held this year and this is a welcome change.  The idea of individual citizens choosing to forsake a political party banner should be a consideration in every democratic system.  The Bill proposes a combination of showing a degree of support that would allow a nomination along with a relatively small charge.  In the old system as I recollect it, the court judgment decided that the money was used as a barrier to people taking part in elections.  The fee for European elections was &pound;5,000 at the time of the judgment.</P>
        <P>There is a value in the retention of the current electoral commissions in that they are not set up on a needs basis and therefore the formation of electoral boundaries will happen as a matter of course.  However, this work needs to be informed by changing the terms of reference on an ongoing basis.</P>
        <P>There is a curious situation with regard to the European elections.  Because Ireland has 12 seats in four constituencies of three seats each, my party is at a particular disadvantage even though we have won two seats in European elections in the past in five-seat and four-seat constituencies, when Ireland had 15 MEPs.  There is a case to be made that for the following European elections in five years&rsquo; time, we should at least debate the notion of a 12-seat Ireland constituency.  While PRSTV has served this country well as it is one of the better systems in terms of reflecting in seat numbers how people have voted, Ireland now has one of the least democratic systems for electing MEPs.</P>
        <P>I refer to the report of the commission set up a number of years ago and which the Minister, by obligation and by custom and practice, and I am pleased he operates on that basis, is bound to accept.  This is the same principle that informs the boundary report on general elections.  I know there are ongoing concerns about how particular areas are represented and under-represented.  In the first instance there is a constitutional difficulty to overcome in that the Consti<Col N="527"/>tution refers to the minimum number of seats required in a constituency.  I would not be averse to such a debate or such a constitutional change.  Perhaps the Oireachtas Joint Committee on the Constitution could examine this aspect and also whether the time is right for introducing different electoral systems.  This would be a useful debate.  The Constitution does not specify the upper number of seats per constituency.  The Minister has been obliged to accept the report which refers to three-seat, four-seat and five-seat constituencies.</P>
        <P>In the early life of this country some constituencies had nine and 11 seats.  I would like future boundary commissions to consider not having County Meath divided into two constituencies but rather to have a six-seater constituency&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>A seven-seater.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DanBoyle"><NameTxt>Senator Dan Boyle</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;and not having two three-seat constituencies in County Donegal.  It should be whatever the population demands.  I would like to see County Donegal having five or six seats and I would like to see County Kerry having five to six seats.  North-east Dublin has three three-seat constituencies and I would like to see two constituencies of five seats and four seats as this would better reflect the votes of the people in this country.  The terms of reference given to the commission governed its recommendations and the Minister, by custom and practice, as is right, has accepted those recommendations and we also need to accept them.  However, we can seek to change the future terms of reference of the ongoing commissions in order to bring about those democratic changes and we have an obligation to do so.</P>
        <P>Other issues have been referred to such as Seanad reform and the participation of young people.  The National Youth Council of Ireland has been promoting the idea of lowering the voting age to 16 years.  My own party was the first party to suggest this change in the case of local elections.  There is one such example in the European Union, where last year young people at age 16 participated in a general election to the national Parliament in Austria.  Unfortunately one of the effects of this change to include new voters between the ages of 16 and 18 was a rise in the vote for far-right parties.  I am not sure if there is a link.</P>
        <P>There should be a mechanism, at least at local elections, by which people between the ages of 16 and 18 could be encouraged to participate.  This might help overcome one of the significant difficulties whereby participation by voters between the ages of 18 and 25 is only half that for the general population.  We need to concentrate on education and ongoing programmes and we need particular mechanisms to involve young people in electoral life.  This Bill deals with the minutiae of electoral boundaries and the procedure for nomination.  The wider question of the quality of democracy, about participation in democracy and how we can become a more democratic country, will happen in future debates which will be informed by the White Paper on local government and other democratic reforms such as the reform of this House.  We should use that opportunity to try to ensure the best quality democracy possible.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DominicHannigan"><NameTxt>Senator Dominic Hannigan</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  In the context of our current difficulties it strikes me as rather an academic exercise to be discussing this Bill.  I concur with Deputies in the other House and also Members of this House who questioned the usefulness of spending further time on a Bill that is more or less out of date before it is even enacted.</P>
        <P>However, I commend the useful work undertaken on Committee Stage by both Deputies and Senators.  I do not wish to speak at length about the Bill in general but I will make a few specific points.</P>
        <P>For those of us who have paid attention to the Green Party policies over the years there is no doubt that the Minister is personally committed to ensuring that electoral reform is carried <Col N="528"/>out.  I refer to a point raised by Senator Boyle about allowing younger people to vote in local elections.  I am disappointed the Minister has not taken the opportunity, bearing in mind the time between now and June, to include an amendment to allow 16 and 17 year olds vote in the local elections.  As I said in this House before, many German <i>l&auml;nder</i>  now allow 16 and 17 year olds to vote in local elections and this is also the case in Austria and in a number of Swiss cantons.  A referendum would be required to allow such young people to vote in a D&aacute;il election but it could be made possible through legislation in the case of voting in the local elections.  It is a missed opportunity not to include an amendment and I am in agreement with Senator Boyle that we need to extend the vote.  Time is moving on and it is only 18 short weeks to the local elections.</P>
        <P>While I admire the Minister&rsquo;s commitment to electoral reform, I worry about the capacity of the Minister to deliver.  I do not question his bona fides but there has been inertia on the part of the larger Government party, Fianna F&aacute;il, on this issue throughout the years.  Successive Fianna F&aacute;il Governments have had little interest in changing the system and this is one of the reasons we have seen such tardiness on the subject of reform.</P>
        <P>I welcome the Minister&rsquo;s general announcement of his intention to set up a new electoral commission.  The successful operation of our political system and electoral process has been more or less outsourced to local authorities.  While I do not wish to denigrate the work of the local authorities in this regard, it is clear they have consistently proved that this task is a step beyond them and this is a question of resources.  We need to remove the responsibility from local authorities.   I refer to difficulties with the electoral register and attempts to match the electoral register with the people on the ground.  This is an area which requires a lot of work and currently falls short of the mark.  This issue arose at the Oireachtas Committee on the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, of which I am a member, in discussions with the Minister.  I am glad he is set on addressing and improving the whole process.</P>
        <P>According to recent media reports, it is expected the new commission will take responsibility, not just for the electoral register, but for party registration and the administration of nominations, and so on.  If this is true, then it is an eminently sensible idea as these tasks should not belong with local authorities.  An efficient, independent and focused central electoral authority would have much more success in dealing with this and more public confidence would be gained in the overall electoral process.</P>
        <P>The establishment of such an agency would be of enormous historical value as a one-stop-shop for electoral records.  Most other European countries have a central government system for maintaining information on previous elections whereas Ireland does not.  It would be valuable if such a function were contained in the remit of such an agency.  Will the Minister make available the full report on the proposed commission?  Will he give a commitment that its recommendations will be implemented during the Government&rsquo;s lifetime.</P>
        <P>The issue of proportionality and equality of representation also arises.  We are moving away from five-seat constituencies &mdash; which up to recently were seen to be fair &mdash; to three-seat constituencies.  This does a disservice to smaller parties.  It is in the interest of the larger parties to maximise the number of three-seat constituencies but it does not do much for the democratic process.  I agree with my colleague in the other House, Deputy Tuffy, when she addressed the commission&rsquo;s terms of reference and called for avoidance of three-seat constituencies unless they are necessary.</P>
        <P>Senator Ellis spoke about the redrawing of the Leitrim constituency boundary and other Members have similarly referred to Kerry and Limerick.  It is also an issue in the Meath East constituency.  The current ban on six-seat and seven-seat constituencies means the commission <Col N="529"/>has no alternative but to split counties to ensure proper representation.  The problem is that such a split means the constituencies bear little resemblance to the counties they are meant to represent.  For instance, when the Bill is enacted, thousands of people living in east Meath will vote in Louth, thousands in the west of the county will vote in the Meath East constituency while people in Westmeath will vote in the Meath West constituency.  It is clear county boundaries are being crossed and I am not sure this was the House&rsquo;s intention when it gave the commission its remit.</P>
        <P>Some Members in the Lower House raised concerns over the delivery of the Constituency Commission&rsquo;s report.  While the independence of the commission is not in doubt, the validity of every decision it arrives at is.  It is desirable that a draft report should be presented in advance of the final version.</P>
        <P>I reiterate the Labour Party&rsquo;s support for general reform in the electoral area.  We would also like to see more such as extending the voting age to 16 for local elections and Seanad reform.  We have awaited these for some time and the Government, in its lifetime, needs to deliver.  The Labour Party supports the Bill.  The establishment of an empowered, efficient and independent electoral commission would represent a considerable body of work.  I look forward to the Minister providing a timeline for this and further detail on the formulation and implementation of such a body.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinBrady"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Brady</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Hannigan is correct that young people are more tuned into politics, despite what some people claim.  The points made by the Senator in this regard are relevant.</P>
        <P>It is agreed changes in the electoral boundaries were needed to secure equality in representation.  There are many articles and comments claiming there are too many Deputies and Senators.  Senator Buttimer is correct that it should be established if there are too many, or not enough, to put the matter to bed once and for ever.  It is interesting that when the State was founded, the ratio for representation was 16,000 people per Member while today it is 25,000 people.</P>
        <P>Senator O&rsquo;Toole referred to direct elections for mayors such as those held in France.  I recall asking the mayor of Montpellier about his terrific light rail project for the city and if he had any opposition to it.  He informed me he did not have opposition because as a directly elected mayor he had no problem in bringing the people with him on the project.  Directly elected mayoralties is a terrific system.  The mayors have their own funding with no layers of bureaucracy, allowing them to do their job quickly.  It is an efficient way of doing business.  Doing public service business in Ireland has become too cumbersome for everyone because there are too many layers blocking the system.  This must be reduced to make it easier and will, in turn, ensure better value for money.</P>
        <P>It has been established, as the Minister stated, that the Constituency Commission&rsquo;s terms of reference were not adhered to.  From my days in the trade union movement, if terms of reference were not adhered to when making a decision, the decision was declared null and void and we had to go back to the drawing board.  In this instance, the opposite happened.  Those who challenged the findings were told they had to go to court.  In a democracy that type of answer is not acceptable.  With all of this, people were deprived of the representation to which they are entitled.  As in Senator Ellis&rsquo;s area, if one got 75% of the electoral quota, one could still not get elected.  Is that democracy?  Is that fair?  It is about fairness for those in the political arena and the people, giving them the service to which they are entitled.</P>
        <P>Another issue is spending on local elections.  There is not an even playing pitch in this area.  If I were up against a millionaire in a local election, I would not stand a chance.  He would <Col N="530"/>have the spending resources to beat the band, give people holidays and take out advertisements everywhere.  What are the plans for spending limits in local elections?  In the last local elections, one candidate spent &euro;60,000 on his campaign.  What chance has, say an unemployed person, running in an election against such a candidate?</P>
        <P>When I spoke to the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government privately, he indicated he intended to ban election postering.  I would like to know what proposals have been made in that regard.  I do not personally have a problem with the issue but a person beginning his or her career might find it a challenge.  Many members of the public do not agree with election posters from an environmental perspective and we could save a lot of money given that they cost &euro;8 each.  I am not completely opposed to that perspective.</P>
        <P>I have nothing against anybody sitting on the commission but we should examine its composition and the views and range of experience of its members because, as Senator Ellis noted, a vested interest must have arisen somewhere along the line if the terms of reference were not adhered to.  Its response to queries was to give the two fingers and to say that the courts should be used if people wanted to do business with it.</P>
        <P>I think we are at one on this issue and several Opposition speakers have made valuable contributions to the debate.  It is important that we respect each other and reach agreement.</P>
      
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulBradford"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Bradford</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the opportunity to speak on this important Bill.  I wish to make some comments in regard to my area and other constituencies, as well as raise broader political issues on how we should proceed.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">1 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>While I respect the fact that the commission is an independent agency, some of its proposed changes make no sense.  Several Senators referred to changes in the Kerry and Limerick regions.  Any reasonable person would find it impossible to justify merging parts of County Kerry with County Limerick to form a new constituency rather than the straightforward arrangement of leaving Limerick as two constituencies while taking one seat from the two Kerry constituencies and merging them into one.  To put it mildly, the decision suggests that inappropriate influence was brought to bear.  I fail to see how we have arrived at this arrangement.  It makes neither political nor geographical sense to include people in the western part of County Limerick with Kerry North.  I appreciate that the present regulatory regime requires that demographic considerations are to the fore in decisions on constituency configurations but common sense is also necessary.  Constituency, county and parochial traditions appear to have been disregarded in the case of counties Kerry and Limerick.</P>
        <P>I am again disappointed, as I was when we last debated electoral boundary legislation, that County Leitrim remains the forgotten part of Ireland in terms of politics.  I accept that the county is represented by Deputies who live in adjacent counties and I am sure they do their best to represent it.  However, if we had told the people of Leitrim when the State was founded that the day would arrive when they would be politically irrelevant or find it impossible to be elected to the D&aacute;il, they would have regarded themselves as having a very limited form of independence.  I hope we will reconsider the constituencies of Roscommon-South Leitrim and Sligo-North Leitrim.  They may be electorally fair or demographically proper but it is unfair to set an impossible obstacle before those people of the proud county of Leitrim who want to become Members of the D&aacute;il.</P>
        <P>I wish to introduce an element of political parochialism to this debate by expressing my disappointment at the changes that have been introduced to County Cork.  When these changes were announced more than 12 months ago, much of the reaction was focused on the potential political winners and losers.  The fact that nobody seemed to note that my prospects for election <Col N="531"/>in Cork East were affected is an indication that I have fallen off the political radar.  The unusual decision to remove a chunk of the most northerly part of Cork East and a part of the former Cork North-West stretching almost to the Kerry border and to include these areas in a Cork city constituency makes no geographical or socioeconomic sense.  Residents of the centre of Cork city will now be in the same D&aacute;il constituency as people living on the Limerick and Kerry borders.  I am aware this decision will not be reversed but I want to formally express my disappointment with it.</P>
        <P>I concede that every Electoral (Amendment) Act has introduced changes which do not appear sensible and realise that we need to consider the broader picture.  The Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government or his officials were reported in the media last weekend as suggesting the possibility of fixed D&aacute;il constituencies, although I do not know how these could be made to withstand constitutional challenge.  From the perspective of political certainty the present situation whereby people can be moved from A to B literally overnight does not make for good politics or governance.  It would be helpful if we could have greater certainty regarding constituency boundaries.</P>
        <P>We have a duty to examine our electoral system regularly.  We have fooled ourselves into believing that multi-seat proportional representational politics is good for democracy and governance.  To be blunt, many of the economic, cultural and social successes we have enjoyed since the foundation of the State have happened accidentally rather than due to political leadership.  We have at times succeeded despite the system rather than because of it.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Our present political system, which makes colleagues compete against each other, means that the competition for ideas takes second place.  That does not make good sense but as long as multi-seat proportional representation remains, the easiest way for any Fianna F&aacute;il or Fine Gael candidate to win is by taking the seat of his or her party colleague because there will always be a seat available for the bigger parties.  That does not make for good politics.  Election results reveal that multi-seat constituencies have not lived up to their aspiration of bringing people in from the margins.  Perhaps the reduction in the number of five and six-seat constituencies will give a broader spread of representation.</P>
        <P>I hope we will have further debate on electoral reform because we need to consider other fair electoral systems, including single-seat proportional representational constituencies and list systems.  There would be a bonus for political parties to fight on the question of their policies and programmes rather than in-fighting among candidates within constituencies.</P>
        <P>We must remove the internal contest between party colleagues and focus political debate on a battle of ideas and skill between the various political parties.  The present system of proportional representation within multi-seat constituencies does not help in that regard.  The current legislation does not provide for debate on this but if the Minister is looking at the possibility of reforming politics and making it more real, relevant and responsive, we must admit that what we have been doing in our elections should be reviewed.</P>
        <P>I refer to local elections and government which are so important.  These have been neglected from a funding and reform perspective, although the Minister made some comments on electoral expenditure for local elections.  The local elections are coming down the tracks and trying to change the goalposts four or five months from an election date is very difficult.  If the Minister has proposals, they would need to be published very quickly and I hope he will consult widely in any changes he may wish to make.</P>
        <P>We can sometimes get hung up on the expense of local elections and what candidates may spend.  Considering the electoral areas down the years, the people who have spent the most money did not necessarily get all the votes.  Local elections and government are generally more locally oriented, and the track record or reputation of the candidates can account for much <Col N="532"/>more than money spent on a campaign.  Large sums of money would not necessarily dictate results to the same degree as general elections.</P>
        <P>There may not be a problem in this regard so before we go fixing an issue, we should check how severe the Minister believes the present problem to be.  I look forward to him returning pretty quickly with any ideas or proposals he has on local elections.  It would be very unfair to only tell local election candidates the new rules of engagement in April.</P>
        <P>I formally express my disappointment, and not only from a personal perspective, about some of the constituency changes, including those in Cork.  They are ill-thought out and make no geographical sense.  One can argue about the political sense they make but in the context of our current electoral system, all people in the constituency should feel close &mdash; politically and geographically &mdash; to their representatives.  Some of the new configurations of constituencies do not provide for this and seem to have been made up as we went along.  I am disappointed as a result.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="LabhrasOMurchu"><NameTxt>Senator Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</NameTxt>
	<P>I have found the contributions so far from both sides of the House very helpful.  A common thread has run through most of the contributions, which helps to underline our realisation that democracy is a very precious concept, although the implementation of democracy can be very delicate at times.</P>
        <P>There is a fair degree of unanimity on the Electoral (Amendment) Bill, which reminds us of the various levels of democracy as they operate in the different councils, the Oireachtas, the European Parliament and so on.  We are particularly fortunate, if one considers local authorities for example, with the amount of media coverage by local newspapers and radio.  At that level, one is very much at the coalface.  I recall sitting on Cashel Urban District Council and on the night of an estimates meeting I would hardly be outside the front door when the locals would be waiting to discuss what happened inside.  That is how close we would be to the operation of the system.</P>
        <P>In those days there was very little money and not much of the debate would deal with anything except how to keep the ship floating and how to survive.  I have one anecdote in this regard.  I recall going to a particular county in later years and meeting the county manager on the day a large project was being officially opened.  I went to say &ldquo;hello&rdquo; because the person had formerly been the town clerk in Cashel.  I told him things had come a long way since he was in Cashel as we looked at the multi-million euro development we were celebrating.  He said he would tell me how much it had changed with a story of how he was working on the estimates and wanted to buy a small calculator.  He went to the chairman, a businessman, to see if he could buy one.  The chairman said that a calculator should not be bought, and the man in question could have the use of one in his shop.  A calculator may have been &pound;3 or &pound;4.  We all know exactly how much we have changed in the intervening years.</P>
        <P>As a result of this one must look at the system and consider how to adapt it and what is currently required.  I have always believed that the essence of democracy is where the elected members have the maximum input into what is happening in policies, expenditure and so on.  With the County Management Act, certain restrictions were brought in and some were understandable.  Like any corporate business, there had to be a professional input.</P>
        <P>I have always believed that local councillors in particular bring with them significant expertise and have an ear to the ground.  They know the consensus in the community and often they are so wise that they would even be ahead of the professional input.  Whatever happens in the reorganisation of local authorities, I would like to think we will always see the member as being paramount.  After all, the member must go back to face the electorate and take responsibility for decisions.  It is the greatest test of all.</P><Col N="533"/>
        <P>When people speak of accountability, in how many walks of life does a person put himself or herself back before an electorate indicating what has been done and asking whether the people are satisfied to re-elect that person?  That is precisely what happens with local authorities so I would not like to see the role of members being diminished or sidelined.</P>
        <P>We must be careful about any kind of a populist caricature of local authority members.  This is unfair in the main and one can see this if one takes time out to see the amount of work put into a local authority.  I know business people in my area who gave more time to the local authority than they gave to their businesses.  One cannot buy that sort of input so we must be careful not to respond to a kind of contrived lobby each time somebody wants to have a go, as it were, at local councillors.  I hope that whatever happens, we will strengthen, consolidate and copperfasten the position of local councillors.</P>
        <P>Senator John Ellis has very strong views on the issue of the geographic identity of constituencies, which is very understandable.  I find much the same views coming across from the other side and the Cathaoirleach is probably aware of what is happening <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i> Offaly and north Tipperary and the crisis of identity there.  I know of this because I have spoken to relatives in that part of the country.  There is a belief that the problem is superficial or there is no hurt as a result but this is wrong.  People are shocked by the identity they had being taken from them.</P>
        <P>We must balance the numerical notion of how many people are to elect a single member of a statutory forum with the tradition of an area.  County Leitrim played a major role in the War of Independence and the development of the State.  As a small county, it also provided a lead in the development of the tourism industry.  There are many issues which should be taken into account in the context of Leitrim&rsquo;s proximity to the North of Ireland.  I do not wish to take from the work of the commission but it is impossible to justify the removal of a county&rsquo;s identity.</P>
        <P>As Members are aware, people&rsquo;s loyalty to their counties is probably the strongest form of loyalty across which one will come.  Regardless of whether it be in the context of sport, the Tidy Towns competition or whatever, the county is the identifiable geographic entity.  This matter must be revisited and county boundaries must be maintained.  Even if a degree of slippage occurs in the context of numbers, I do not see the problem.  This will be compensated for in other ways.  I do not believe the numbers are sacrosanct or written in stone.  There must be flexibility so that social, cultural and other aspects are taken into account in the interests of maintaining the identity of a county.</P>
        <P>The terms of reference must be considered in a clearer way.  We have a major advantage in respect of this matter.  If only one political party was arguing in favour of this, matters would be extremely difficult.  However, there has been a cross-party response on this issue because Members are receiving representations from their constituents and others in respect of it.  If one talks to those who are to all intents and purposes disenfranchised, one will discover that they are of the view that they will never vote again because they are not part of the system.</P>
        <P>This happened previously when constituencies in our cities were redrawn.  The position with regard to cities is somewhat different because the communities there may be fragmented or only recently devised.  However, even in cities, the response to which I refer would be forthcoming.  In the rural or provincial setting, that response can be extreme.</P>
        <P>I hope this matter can be revisited as a matter of urgency.  If this is not done, we will merely diminish the democratic system by failing to take into account the many variables that exist in the many constituencies.</P>
        <P>The suggestion that the voting age should be reduced to 16 is worthy of debate.  Young people are very much to the fore at present.  Unfortunately, however, there is not as much interest on the part of young people in the electoral system or in the workings of democracy as we would like.  When we were their age, we would have had a greater interest in this area. <Col N="534"/> Any mechanism that might be used to bring them back into the loop is important.  As already stated, society is changing and we must be in a position to respond in this regard.</P>
        <P>The concept of public representation has taken somewhat of a battering, but only as a result of isolated incidents or particular scandals.  However, 99% of the time our system is well served by public representatives with diverse views.  There is nothing wrong with being critical of public representatives.  However, it behoves those who engage in such criticism to try to be fair.  Such criticism must be fair because if we damage the body politic or undermine it in a general rather than a specific way, we do harm to ourselves in the process, especially in a competitive world.</P>
        <P>I hope there will be a greater understanding among people of the work of public representatives, their responsibilities and the transparency, accountability, etc. attaching thereto.  If the Electoral (Amendment) Bill makes a contribution to the process in that regard, then it represents a step in the right direction.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaddyBurke"><NameTxt>Senator Paddy Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the opportunity to comment on this legislation.  I am not sure whether I welcome the Bill.  Nevertheless, it provides a good opportunity to remark upon our electoral system as it relates to general and local elections and how it operates.</P>
        <P>Everyone agrees in respect of the case that has been made for Leitrim.  People do not fully appreciate the strength of county boundaries.  Such boundaries are so strong it is unbelievable.  I live in the third largest county in the country, Mayo, which has five Deputies.  Mayo previously had six D&aacute;il seats but it lost one a number of years ago.  The smallest county in the country, Louth, also has five Deputies, which makes its level of representation equivalent to that of County Mayo.  I agree with Senator O&rsquo;Toole&rsquo;s assertion that assessments should be carried out in each constituencies to discover whether people want to lose their D&aacute;il representatives.  I am sure it would emerge that they do not want to lose them.</P>
        <P>When Mayo was divided into two constituencies &mdash; Mayo West and Mayo East &mdash; two areas of County Galway, namely, part of Headford and Milltown, were included in one of these.  The people in these areas of Galway did not appreciate being included in the constituency of Mayo East and did not feel at home there.  I can understand why that was the case.  These people continued to align themselves with the constituencies in which they lived &mdash; Galway West and Galway East &mdash; and the next review of the constituencies saw them returned to these.</P>
        <P>When the terms of reference of the commission are being drafted, as Senator Ellis stated, it should be stipulated that county boundaries should not be broken.  There is a somewhat farcical situation in the constituencies surrounding the area in which the Leader lives.  Part of County Westmeath is incorporated into one of the constituencies of Meath East and Meath West and part of County Meath is incorporated into the constituency of Louth.  In addition, part of County Louth is also incorporated into one of the Meath constituencies.  This level of gerrymandering is farcical.  I have great sympathy with counties the boundaries of which are broken in the interests of creating electoral constituencies.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator O&rsquo;Toole inquired whether there are too many Deputies.  There may not be too many of them and if the election of a further two meant that county boundaries would not be broken, I would have to agree with the number being increased.  The Senator made the point that the western seaboard and rural areas are losing Deputies who are gravitating towards the larger urban areas around Dublin.  In my opinion, this matter will have to be examined not only on the basis of population but also in geographical terms.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Minister stated that he has been advised by the Attorney General to introduce separate legislation in respect of the spending controls relating to local elections.  Far be it from me to <Col N="535"/>question the advice of the Attorney General.  Quite a number of the sections contained in the Bill before us relate to local elections but the Attorney General has advised that we should introduce further legislation in respect of spending controls.  I am mystified as to why provision cannot be made in respect of those controls in the Electoral (Amendment) Bill in order that the various matters relating to elections might be dealt with in one fell swoop.</P>
        <P>In the past, emergency legislative measures were tacked on to various Bills.  I do not understand why the spending controls relating to local authority elections could not have been dealt with in this Bill and why they have to be catered for in separate legislation.  Like Senator Bacik, I hope the Minister will introduce this legislation in the not too distant future in plenty of time for the local elections.  We will then be able to see where we are going in that regard.</P>
        <P>I will ask a number of questions about the Bill on Committee Stage.  Once the census report is published, the Constituency Commission will automatically be put in place.  It comprises a judge of the Supreme Court, the Ombudsman, the Secretary General of the Department and the Clerks of the D&aacute;il and the Seanad and must report back within a given period.  The census report may be published six or 12 months before a general election or there could be a snap election.  In that case would the commission have to report back within a couple of months and would the new constituency boundaries be put in place?  Are there safeguards to ensure the boundaries would be those decided by the previous commission?  This should be spelled out more clearly.  The Bill does not state the new commission should report back before a general election takes place.</P>
        <P>I thought this legislation would cover the electoral register.  Two or three years ago there was great anxiety over its compilation.  It is an issue at which we should look in detail.  We are back to where we were before Members raised concerns about it.  Despite the money given to local authorities, new structures have not been put in place to compile it.  I hope the Minister will use the legislation he proposes to introduce before the local elections as an opportunity to provide for them.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I have much to say on the Bill but do not have the opportunity to do so now.  However, we will have time on Committee Stage to go through some of the issues raised.  The Bill covers D&aacute;il and local elections and how candidates are nominated.  A number of years ago in the run-up to the presidential election there were arguments about how independent candidates could be nominated.  Will this issue be dealt with in the forthcoming Bill?  I hope it will be put to bed in it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State and have listened with interest to the debate.  We are living at a time when the status of politicians is not very high.  It is popular in the media and elsewhere for the denigration of politicians to be the order of the day but a better system than the democratic one in place has not been devised.  It is very easy, therefore, for people to be critical of every move those who put their names forward for election make.</P>
        <P Just="Left">When I was in school and we learned history, I was struck by the actions of the good leaders during the centuries who were referred to as &ldquo;benevolent despots&rdquo;.  They governed with a degree of concern and compassion but for each one of them, there were at least 100 malevolent despots who oppressed the people.  The essence of the democratic system is that it is the people who decide, whether it be every four or five years, who will represent and govern them.  We should be open to criticism where it is fair, valid and balanced but much of it is not and is designed to sell newspapers or attract listening audiences.  There is a void in the system, an absence of a voice to support and defend where criticism is most unjustified.  This should be looked at.  If we do not value and defend our democracy, others will not do so and the result will not benefit anyone.  We have seen examples in the recent past and at present of undemo<Col N="536"/>cratic systems under which people suffer horrendously as a consequence.  The Bill will be an important component of regulating how our system operates.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator &Oacute; Murch&uacute; mentioned voting at 16 years of age.  I am inclined to think the right to vote is valued and that the current age limit is not in need of revision.  One needs to reach a certain age of maturity before one should cast one&rsquo;s vote.  It is a privilege and an honour which we should protect.</P>
        <P>Senator Ellis has mentioned County Leitrim a number of times.  It is almost unconscionable that there is a county which does not have a D&aacute;il representative.  The system which allows this to happen must be questioned and the Bill does this.  The number of counties, the boundaries of which have not been contravened by commission recommendations, is small.  Under the Constitution, there is a criterion which must be met as regards representation on the basis of population.  Applying exclusively a mathematical formula to meet this requirement is highly questionable.  There are geographical and boundary considerations.  We may need to refine some local election boundaries such as in urban areas which are contentious.  However, county boundaries should not be contravened.  That is my opinion.</P>
        <P>A number of Members raised the issue of the multi-seat constituencies.  We have a requirement that there should be three, four or five seat constituencies.  I listened with interest to what Senator Bradford said.  I have long been an advocate of a system of single seat constituencies.  I live in a five seat constituency.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnEllis"><NameTxt>Senator John Ellis</NameTxt>
	<P>At 2.30 p.m. next Tuesday, 3 February 2008.</P>
 <HtmlBk SectId="4" />
    </Speaker><!--Fix-->
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters. </Title>
    <Sect LHead="Hospital" RHead="Services"> 
      <sTitle>Hospital Services.</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="PatMoylan"><NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Wallace, to the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>I raise the issue of the neurology service in the Health Service Executive north-west region.  This is a matter of concern to MS Ireland, which is located in Donegal.  MS Ireland brought the matter to my attention, as did other patients seeking appointments for this service in Letterkenny General Hospital and in Sligo General Hospital.</P>
        <P>There is one consultant neurologist for the HSE north-west region located at Sligo General Hospital.  It has been well documented that neurology services in the Republic of Ireland are under-developed generally in comparison to other European and developed countries.  Neurological disease affects approximately 700,000 people in Ireland.  Each year, 44,000 new patients are diagnosed with neurological problems.  Stroke is the third most common cause of death and the leading cause of disability in this country.  With an ageing population, neurological diseases such as Alzheimer&rsquo;s and Parkinson&rsquo;s will become an even more serious public health issue in the future.</P>
        <P>There are 21 consultant neurologists and five consultant neurophysiologists in the public service in the Republic of Ireland.  In April 2003, the report by Comhairle na nOspid&eacute;al, the National Hospitals Office, on neurology and neurophysiology services recommended one consultant neurologist per 100,000 of population, with a suggested total of 39 in the Republic, which <Col N="537"/>would translate into approximately 42, given the 2006 census figures.  The recommendation for clinical neurophysiology was for a total of nine consultants compared to three in 2003.  The current figure is five neurophysiologists in the Republic.</P>
        <P>The consultant neurologist at Sligo General Hospital is doing a tremendous job.  He rotates between Sligo General Hospital and Letterkenny General Hospital.  I pay tribute to that consultant neurologist for the work he is doing but he cannot do that work alone because the population of the region is 250,000.  Based on the Comhairle na nOspid&eacute;al report of 2003, there should be 2.5 neurologists in an area catering for 250,000 people.  I am calling for the appointment of a second consultant neurologist to cover the Letterkenny-Sligo area, the north-west area, to ensure that the backlog of appointments is cleared.</P>
        <P>The demands on the service are overwhelming.  Between the two hospitals, Letterkenny General and Sligo General, there are almost 900 people on an outpatient waiting list, with an estimated waiting time of at least 18 months for routine appointments.  That list includes patients who to date have been treated in neurology services elsewhere in the country and who have a reasonable expectation that the treatment can be continued locally now that a neurology service has commenced.</P>
        <P>I welcome the fact that there is a consultant neurologist at Sligo General Hospital.  However, that consultant is under increasing pressure to deal with the demand.  The Department of Health and Children and the HSE should consider the appointment of the second neurologist in the north-west region and adopting the recommendations made in the 2003 Comhairle na nOspid&eacute;al report.</P>
        <P>There are many other people on waiting lists for EEG appointments etc.  The north-west region is only one example; it is the area for which I am fighting.  I ask that the people on the waiting list from Donegal and the west region be facilitated by the appointment, based on a recommendation from Comhairle na nOspid&eacute;al, of a second neurologist in the north-west region.</P>
        <P>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Wallace, for coming into the House to take this Adjournment matter and look forward to her response.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryWallace"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health and Children</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Mary Wallace</NameTxt>
	<P>As we are in the form for praising each other I would like to say that the Senator&rsquo;s contribution was well researched and that he presented an excellent case.  As I read through the report before me, I find that his thought process is similar to the position of the Department of Health and Children and the Health Service Executive on developing these services throughout the country.  There has been a slight improvement in the statistics also, which will be a help.</P>
        <P>I am responding on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Harney.  The Minister has identified the development of neurology services as a policy priority.  Additional revenue funding of &euro;7 million was provided to the HSE in 2006 and 2007 for the development of services in the area of neurosciences, which comprises neurology, neurophysiology and neurosurgery, as the Senator has said.  This has allowed the HSE to appoint additional consultant neurologists, which included the appointment for the first time of the neurologist the Senator referred to at Sligo General Hospital.  That post was filled in early 2008 and provides neurology services to the north-west region.</P>
        <P>Of the development funding for the provision of neurology services in the north west, &euro;80,000 has gone towards the establishment of a pilot tele-neurophysiology link which is in operation between Sligo General and Beaumont hospitals.  This has facilitated patients in receiving their EEGs locally, thus avoiding the need for them to travel to Galway or to Dublin.</P><Col N="538"/>
        <P>Nationally, this investment has helped to increase the number of approved consultant neurologist posts, which now stands at 24 compared with 14 in 2003.  In addition, we have moved to a position where we have seven approved consultant clinical neurophysiologist posts, an increase of four approved posts since 2003.  The Senator is encouraging us to appoint more people and the statistics are moving in an upward direction.</P>
        <P>The HSE has undertaken a national review of neurology services to improve integration of services and optimise patient outcomes.  It took particular account of likely future levels of demand and rapid technological advances in the area.  Following consideration of the outcome of the review, the HSE decided to seek an external expert opinion on the model of care proposed to ensure the recommendations were properly aligned with the HSE transformation programme.  The expert panel expects to conclude its work within the next three months, after which time the HSE can proceed to the implementation phase and arrange for publication.</P>
        <P>Government policy is to have a consultant delivered rather than a consultant led service.  The new consultant contract is designed to support this and, as in many areas of our health services, service improvements will depend to a much greater extent on the ability to successfully mobilise and re-configure existing resources than on additional funds.</P>
        <P>The creation and funding of further consultant posts will be driven by service priorities, as reflected in the HSE&rsquo;s annual service plan, and in particular the policy of achieving a better balance between the numbers of consultants and non-consultant hospital doctors.  There is to be a significant reduction in the number of non-consultant hospital doctors employed in each of the years 2009, 2010 and 2011.  This would generate savings that would be used to fund the recruitment of additional consultants.  I thank Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill for raising this important matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
    </Sect>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Schools Building" RHead="Projects"> 
    <Title>Schools Building Projects. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="CiaranCannon"><NameTxt>Senator Ciaran Cannon</NameTxt>
	<P>I listened with interest to the debate on the Electoral (Amendment) Bill and the wonderful thing that is democracy.  The essence of a healthy, thriving democracy must be the level of trust which exists between those who are elected and those who elect.  While that trust is in general healthily maintained in Galway East, there is a danger that it may be about to break down, particularly in an area of south Galway which was given a commitment a couple of weeks before the general election that a new 700 pupil, co-educational second level school would be provided in Kinvara to serve the people of the area.</P>
        <P>This commitment was given in May 2007.  In January 2008, the Commission on School Accommodation, which had been requested by the Minister to establish whether there was sufficient need for a new second level school in the area, submitted its report to the Minister.  It concluded that there was definitely a need for a new co-educational post-primary school, with a capacity of approximately 800 students, to be provided in the environs of Kinvara to serve the whole of south Galway.  It stated the school would be required for the 2012-13 school year to coincide with the planned closure of Seamount College.</P>
        <P>In a response to the report, given to me in the House on 24 April last, the then Minister for Education and Science, Deputy Hanafin, stated it was her intention that the school would be built.  She indicated that the Office of Public Works, which acts on behalf of the Department on the acquisition of school sites, was being requested to source a suitable site for the school in question.  As we approach the first anniversary of the date on which that commitment was given, I hope the Minister of State will inform me that significant progress has been made on the acquisition of a site.</P><Col N="539"/>
        <P>South Galway has a serious need for a new second level school.  The Sisters of Mercy have been very co-operative in this matter and have given a commitment to keep open Seamount College until the 2012-13 school year.  Unfortunately, this commitment does not extend beyond that date.  It is possible, therefore, that in three years the second level school will close without a replacement being available.  I look forward to the Minister of State&rsquo;s reply.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryWallace"><NameTxt>Deputy Mary Wallace</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator for raising the important matter of a second level school in Kinvara as it provides an opportunity to outline to the House the Government&rsquo;s strategy for capital investment in education projects and the current position regarding the provision of a new second level school in Kinvara, County Galway.</P>
        <P>Modernising facilities in our building stock and the need to respond to emerging needs in areas of rapid population growth is a significant challenge and one which the Minister intends will be among his priorities.  The Government has dramatically increased investment in the school building programme to almost &euro;581.3 million this year.  Almost &euro;4.5 billion will be invested in schools during the lifetime of the national development plan.  This is an unprecedented level of capital investment which reflects the commitment of the Government to continue its programme of sustained investment in primary and post-primary schools.</P>
        <P>This programme will underpin a particular emphasis on the delivery of additional school places in rapidly developing areas, while continuing to develop on the Government&rsquo;s commitment to delivering improvements in the quality of existing primary and post-primary accommodation throughout the country.</P>
        <P>The position regarding the provision of a new second level school in the northern environs of the area referred to is as follows.  As Senator Cannon indicated, the Commission on School Accommodation conducted a survey of school accommodation in the area to determine the location of the proposed post-primary school and identify other locations where additional school places may be required over the next five to ten years.  The commission, as the Senator noted, published its report in January 2008.  It recommended that a co-educational post-primary school for circa 800 students should be provided in the northern environs of the area in question.</P>
        <P>When a new school has been approved a number of procedures and processes must be undertaken and these can take some time to complete.  The main stages are as follows: the identification and acquisition of a suitable site; design of the building; application for and granting of planning permission; invitation to seek tenders; and construction.  The further progression of the proposed project, including the acquisition of a site, for the school will be considered in the context of the capital budget available to the Department for school buildings generally.  In light of many competing demands on the capital budget of the Department, it is not possible to give an indicative timeframe for the progression of the project at this time.</P>
        <P>Senator Cannon expressed concerns arising from the proposed closure of Seamount College, Kinvara.  With this proposal in mind, in November 2008 officials from the Department met the trustees of the college to discuss the provision of a new school.  Arising from these discussions the Department wrote to the trustees requesting their views on the possibility of extending the deadline for the school closure until a timeframe for developing a new school can be determined in light of the current economic climate and-or on whether the trustees would consider the possibility of leasing the buildings to the Department for the operation of a school.  The Minister has been advised that this request is being considered by the trustees.</P>
        <P>The Minister conveys his thanks to the Senator for affording him the opportunity to outline to the House the current position regarding the provision of a new second level school in Kinvara, County Galway.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <Col N="540"/><MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Alternative" RHead="Energy Projects"> 
    <Title>Alternative Energy Projects. </Title>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>The matter I raise is the need for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources to improve existing methods of carbon emissions reduction and support the development of alternative methods.  It may surprise the Minister to learn that I have received a large number of representations recently about the slow development of alternative methods of energy generation.  This is especially surprising given the significant and important Green Party element in the Government.  I wonder why this is the case.  The reason may be that such representations are made by vested interests.  I see nothing wrong with vested interests where alternative energy is concerned.  It is our job to promote the vested interests of alternative energy producers because they coincide with the national interest. </P>
        <P>This issue is especially topical this month because of the initiatives which have been taken by President Obama in the United States where carbon emissions regulations have been lifted and now appear to be a matter for individual states.  This measure will obviously give a major boost to alternative energy initiatives and will, I hope, change regulations for the better.  It is certainly a turnaround from the hardline stance taken by President Bush and other governments on alternative energy.  I suppose it has been taken in light of the bail out in Detroit and the need to create alternatives to using fossil fuels.</P>
        <P>The impression is abroad that whereas bio-fuels are a problem for Ireland owing to the distance to areas where sugar cane is grown, other alternatives are not sufficiently promoted.  I have been requested specifically to ask the Minister what action is being taken on the use of seaweed as a source of energy.  Ireland has a fantastic opportunity to improve its carbon emissions reductions by promoting seaweed or algae as an energy source.  It is easy to generate energy from seaweed and the material is reasonably cheap and accessible.</P>
        <P>I understand heating and fuel account for approximately 75% of our energy consumption.  Seaweed would be a particularly appropriate source of energy for this purpose.  The reason the use of seaweed as a source of energy is not being more actively promoted by the Government is not clear.  I am interested in learning from the Minister what the obstacles are to encouraging the use of seaweed as an alternative source of energy.</P>
        <P>I have received representations, over several years, about wave energy.  I have knocked my head against the wall about various projects of this type.  I am happy to admit the representations came from people who wanted to promote wave energy projects and who found the frustrations of dealing with bureaucracy almost impossible to overcome.  Many of them have given up, some have died and some are old and dispirited because their championing of wave or tidal energy has been so frustrating.  The outlook now, based on the latest figures, suggests that wave energy is 20 years away and tidal energy might be five years away.  I see the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Eamon Ryan, is shaking his head.</P>
        <P>Wind energy is another matter which it would be interesting to hear about.  There are two types, offshore and onshore, and offshore is double the expense of onshore.  I understand the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, Deputy John Gormley, said that the Government wants to reach a wind energy target of 30% or 40% by 2020, whereas we currently get approximately 6% or 7%.  Those aims are quite unambitious.  The issue is not simply that fossil fuel is expensive and may run out, but also that it is damaging to the environment and we have alternatives which we can promote more rapidly.  I know there is a funding problem but it is a long-term investment which I suspect will pay off in the end.</P>
        <P>The main obstructions, about which I hear from people involved in all of these industries, are not just ESB and the grid infrastructure &mdash; which is being delayed, particularly in the area of wind energy &mdash; but also the regulator.  The complaints I receive are that the allocation of contracts by the regulator is on a first-come, first-served basis and that it might be better if a <Col N="541"/>clearer, more competitive and totally transparent basis were used for the allocation of contracts so there would be no delays.  There is no excuse, if the alternatives are available and there are entrepreneurs ready to promote them, in having bureaucratic or semi-State obstacles to prevent this particularly laudable form of alternative energy being promoted.  It has not only good financial effects but also great environmental effects.</P>
      
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonRyanGP"><TitleTxt>Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Eamon Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the opportunity to respond to the points raised by Senator Ross and to outline some of the developments which will, hopefully, give some reassurance to the people he has talked to regarding the development of renewable energy power within our island.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">2 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>It is centre stage in Government policy to pursue, with the greatest haste and proper management, the development of such resources.  That is why I went to Government and got agreement on a change in the targets we are setting ourselves so we can move towards a 40% renewable energy component in our electricity supply by 2020.  I did so on the back of real concerns.  One concern is that we are facing a peak in global oil production and the secure availability of alternative fossil fuels is far from clear.  We have seen the gas supply cut off from Russia to Ukraine this year.  This is, I believe, a warning we should heed and switch to our indigenous resources.  The commitments we are entering into at European and, I hope, international level to tackle climate change require us to do everything we can to reduce our electricity from such high carbon emission sources.  The target for 2020 is an interim one and is not a limit to our ambitions.  We should be aiming to decarbonise our power generation sector to go towards a 100% carbon-free power supply in the next number of decades.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I will concentrate on what the State can do to assist the private sector and the country to meet the targets.  Another thing which gives us confidence to reach those targets is a very important piece of planning work we did which was published a year ago, the all-island grid study.  It looked at the whole island of Ireland and what level of renewables could be reached by the system if the grid was built in a certain way.  It may not seem topical, high profile or sexy but it is the key development consideration.  If one looks at developments in Europe, yesterday an announcement mentioned the support for grid development was centre stage in the economic renewal package.  In the United States it was agreed yesterday that grid development was the cornerstone of anything being done on the energy side.  It is the same here.</P>
        <P>Unless we develop that grid we will not be able to meet our targets.  I will be looking for support from this House for EirGrid, which is tasked in its Grid 25 study to do exactly that.  It will deliver, effectively and quickly, on the east-west interconnector, which is the first major project in developing the grid, with the support of the European Union, as announced yesterday.  Other projects, such as the development of the north-south interconnection and transmission line and the building up and reinforcing of our transmission system across the country, particularly in the north and west, are centre stage.  The plan is in place, it is progressing and we have engineers delivering on it today.  It is the first priority, even though it may not be glamorous or high profile.</P>
        <P>Another issue is to provide a market environment which encourages the development of renewables, and to put in place pricing and other regulatory systems, which is complex.  In the last year changes in oil prices from $50 per barrel to $150 and back down to $30 messed up many business plans people may have had.  The financial crisis we are seeing is having an effect in the energy area, as it is in every other area in terms of the availability of capital.  It behoves us to give some price and investment certainty in this area.</P>
        <P>I believe the support price system we have in place in the correct one.  People can argue for an alternative, such as in the UK where one has a renewables obligations certificate.  In practice, <Col N="542"/>if one looks at what has worked in countries such as Germany, Spain, Portugal and others, it is guaranteed prices over a certain timeframe which is the correct mechanism.  We have the correct price supports in areas such as wind, particularly where we have a very extensive resource in comparison to other countries, and it is important to have that mechanism in place.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There have been difficulties, which are ongoing, in getting grid connections, as Senator Ross has said, and in the queue for projects to proceed in that regard.  The regulator has set out its strategy on the further development, which comprises some 3,900 MW of additional projects it now has in a gate system where we try to bunch projects together so that grid development goes hand in hand with the development of projects.  I have heard from the Irish Wind Energy Association and others that while they are constantly looking for refinements or improvements, we should proceed in the direction we are going in because certainty and clarity of purpose are more important to them than an approach which chops and changes.</P>
        <P>I am always available for suggestions and encouragement to try to push the process more quickly.  However, when I listen to the bankers and project managers involved, they are saying the pricing mechanism and grid connection system are improving and are not the impediment to development they have been, particularly when we had a moratorium on any developments some two or three years ago.</P>
        <P>I will now deal with the issue of wind offshore and onshore because the bulk of our renewables target will have to be met by wind power.  It is not simply close to commercial reality but is now cheaper than the alternative and its supply is much more secure.  It is interesting to see that the regulator published a report the day before yesterday with a detailed analysis behind the targets the Government has set and the implications for energy prices for us in meeting such renewable targets.  It is very encouraging that, at a time when energy price rises are a real concern for many industries, its modelling analysis has shown it will lower prices significantly.  This is a technology which will be good for the environment and, crucially, good for our economy.</P>
        <P>The initial large tranche will come from onshore wind but in the follow up, real opportunities exist offshore.  The scaleability of offshore and its ability to go towards much larger plants without planning difficulties is where the real opportunity exists.  I hope it can go in tandem with what Senator Ross mentioned, which is the development of wave and tidal energy.  I can see the prospect down the line of having a common regulatory and planning system that treats that offshore resource in a well-thought out, transparent and fair manner.</P>
        <P>I shook my head when the Senator indicated that wave power would be 20 years off because that goes against the information I am receiving from some serious international investors who are looking to come here.  They are indicating that within two to three years we will see the deployment of fairly sizeable but pre-commercial devices on a scale above anything we have at the present time.  Beyond that five-year time horizon, however, they expect such pre-commercial projects to translate into larger commercial ones that will be deployed in Irish waters.</P>
        <P>It is not certain what technology will be used, or how, because the technology is still evolving.  Even in the past year, since my Department published its updated planning for the process, we are seeing greater confidence that such technology will be scaled up and will prove to be commercial.  Our planning in that respect is important because one must give investors long-term certainty.  One cannot do this through a chop-and-change or stop-and-start process.</P>
        <P>We have a ten-year planning horizon on it which began about three years ago.  Last year, we went through the first quarter phase.  There is a four-stage process as we move towards commercialisation which set out an initial two and a half year timeframe to do the sort of research required, including the first offshore trial in Galway Bay and the development of wave <Col N="543"/>testing centres and prototype devices.  We said that at the end of the first quarter of that ten-year period, we would do a review and then decide whether to go on to the second phase, which is what we decided last year.  In doing so we gave clear signals to the international community that we want to be a centre of this development.  We gave a support price of 22 cent per kw/hour, which is twice the retail electricity rate, as a signal that we want to encourage those prototype commercial and sub-commercial devices.  We set out a commitment to grant support for new prototype devices as well as a new offshore grid-connected test facility which we are now developing in Belmullet, County Mayo.  We also agreed a number of other measures.  That sort of proper planning is crucial to attracting investment for a ten, 20 or 30-year time horizon for this technology.  We must arrange our offshore planning within that context.</P>
        <P>I welcome the work that has been done by the Joint Committee on Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, including its suggestions for an integrated approach to foreshore licensing and planning for offshore energy facilities.  I will work with that committee on these matters, together with the Minister for the Environment, Heritage and Local Government, to establish a planning regime to give such certainty for investment.  That is the crucial next step in the wave and wind energy area.  We do not want it to become a speculative, haphazard, queue system, but rather one that takes into account more than the time of an application.  It also needs to take into account the possibility of a developer proceeding to scale up the technology.</P>
        <P>The bio-fuels area has seen significant difficulties and changes in recent years.  I have consistently said that we need the development of bio-fuels as a strategic supply in the event of an oil crunch.  I believe we can get a significant percentage that would be useful in running strategic public transport, agriculture or other industrial equipment in the event of a real oil shortage.  However, it is not the panacea for the peak oil environment ahead of us.  The approach of the European Union is correct in setting out a graduated approach towards increasing the level of bio-fuels here.  Crucially, it seeks to encourage the generation both of electric vehicles, which will be a major development and will benefit our storage of wind power supplies, and of second generation bio-fuels.  The latter includes the development of algae and seaweed for such uses.</P>
        <P>From what I understand of the science, it is one of those technologies that is not yet at the commercial application stage.  While some of the basic chemistry, biotechnology and biopharmacy applications are now coming closer to reality, the commercial one would require very large ponds close to power generation so that one could use a combined heat and power approach.  That scaling up of test-tube technology into the real world is not yet complete, however.  A number of universities on the west coast are examining this technology in some detail, which is exactly what we should be doing as part of the Government&rsquo;s overall strategy for a smart, innovative and green economy.  There will be solutions from that basic research but it is not equivalent to wind energy or biomass heat markets that are now grant supported towards commercial deployment rather than towards research and development.</P>
        <P>It has been said that the bureaucratic system is slow and that we are not responding quickly enough.  However, Senators should heed the Government&rsquo;s words that this is not a time for a slow or poor response from State bodies.  The situation requires us to be innovative, flexible and quick to attract investment.  It also requires us to take risks, be bold and trust our ingenuity and ability to adapt to new tasks.  The regulatory system, the energy agency and Departments must bend to those tasks.  In these difficult economic times we need to instil a sense of confidence, vision and purpose.  The public service is required to provide that, just as much as the private sector, so that we can get jobs from the new emerging technology.  In addition, we will save money that is going out of the country to Kuwait or Qatar.  In the process, we will also protect the planet from irreversible climate change.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="544"/>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>That is one of the most outrageous performances I have ever come across on the Adjournment.  I think the Minister does not understand the protocol here.  Ministers usually read a speech that is written before they hear a Senator&rsquo;s question and then sit down.  I am being facetious.  I am grateful to the Minister for the fact that he actually listened to what I had to say and responded to it, which is unique in this House.  It sets a precedent that should be followed by other Ministers.  Whether we agree or disagree, it is extremely helpful to have a Minister who take one&rsquo;s points and responds to them individually.  The normal procedure in this House is that a Minister &mdash; sometimes the wrong Minister &mdash; reads a script and then disappears.  I am grateful that he took my contribution seriously and addressed it point by point.</P>
        <P>The Minister stated that seaweed is not well developed.  Is it Government policy to depend on the leadership of Europe in this regard?  Will the Government introduce initiatives in this area, since we are well placed to exploit it ourselves?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonRyanGP"><NameTxt>Deputy Eamon Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>This approach to questions means one&rsquo;s ignorance can be exposed quickly and my knowledge of seaweed is limited, other than a lifelong career pass in Kilkieran where there is a seaweed processing business which extracts nutrients and iodine, in particular, for use in industrial processing.  The bio-fuels strategy we are following encourages the development of such second generation technologies.  Our bio-fuels obligations scheme gives incentives to the development of such technologies and the obligations will be adjusted accordingly regarding what suppliers must do.  In this circumstance, it is no harm to go hand in hand with Europe on policy formulation because it provides a wider market and a scientific certainty that also helps.  When standards are being set on bio-fuels, it is difficult for a country of our size with a relatively limited seaweed capacity, even though we have a long coastline.  It is much better to do this in co-operation with other countries.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ShaneRoss"><NameTxt>Senator Shane Ross</NameTxt>
	<P>Would that not slow things up?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="EamonRyanGP"><NameTxt>Deputy Eamon Ryan</NameTxt>
	<P>In fairness to Commissioner Piebalgs, one of the experiences I have had in Government is that the European Commission has been more progressive in the energy area than many national governments.  Far from slowing it up, it has kicked a few governments into action.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 2.15 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 3 February 2009.</adjournment>
    <HtmlBk SectId="0" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
