<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="24" Month="Nov" Year="1926" Vol="7" No="19" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 24 Samhain 1926" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 24 November 1926" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1131">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1131" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 a clog.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="PROCLAMATION OF" RHead="NATIONAL EMERGENCY">
    <Title>PROCLAMATION OF NATIONAL EMERGENCY.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>The House will recollect that under the provisions of an Act which, with the help of this House, was passed into law last week, that is, the Public Safety (Emergency Powers) Act, 1926, it was provided that if a Proclamation of Emergency under that Act was made at any time when the Oireachtas, or either House of the Oireachtas, stood adjourned, the Proclamation itself would summon both Houses at a date of not more than five days from the date of the Proclamation.  The Proclamation was duly issued on Saturday last, and as a consequence the Oireachtas was summoned to meet to-day.  As you will see from the Order Paper, no notice of motion has been handed in for the purpose of setting aside this Proclamation, and as that is the only business that could be transacted to-day as a result of this summons, and in the absence of any motion of that kind, we have no business to discharge.  At the same time I want the House, if they will pardon me for saying so, not to think they have wasted this day.  They are here for the purpose of exercising, if they think fit, a very grave responsibility, and at the same time to put into force an invaluable safeguard for public liberty and public safety, and, it so happens, under the conditions and circumstances we do not require to occupy much time.  I ask the House not to consider that their time is being wasted, but to recollect that the time may come when, in the hands of a strong and autocratic Government, with perhaps a majority of the other House, this House in its courage and patriotism might think it its duty to set aside any such Proclamation.  I want them to recollect that, and to realise that they <Col N="1132" /> have in that safeguard a grave and serious responsibility placed upon them. There being no further business, I shall now declare the Seanad to stand adjourned.</P>
      <P>As far as I can make out, I anticipate there is no measure likely to reach this House calling for discussion, consideration and dispatch before the Christmas Recess, except the Expiring Laws Bill.  That, of course, must be passed before the Recess.  I do not think it is at all likely to reach us before 15th December, but it must reach us some time about that date or a little later.  I think, therefore, the best thing for us to do to-day is to agree that the House do now stand adjourned, leaving it to me to convene a meeting at some convenient date on the approach of Christmas to deal with any business that may have to be dispatched.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the Ministers, having summoned the House, are entunity of making a statement before we adjourn?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>On what subject?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. DOUGLAS Mr. DOUGLAS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DOUGLAS</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the Ministers having summoned the House are entitled to make a statement if they think it necessary?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not possibly preclude a discussion if Ministers were to make a statement now on general policy.  That is not what we met here for, and that is not what the Act of Parliament provides. The Act provides for the calling of this sitting for one purpose only, and that is to reject, if either House thinks fit, the Proclamation of Emergency.  It meets for no other purpose, and a general discussion on Government policy would, I think, be extremely unwise from every point of view, and certainly, I think, would not be in order.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="COPYRIGHT" RHead="BILL">
    <Title>COPYRIGHT BILL.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamYeats" hpid="Dr. YEATS Dr. YEATS">
      <NameTxt>Dr. YEATS</NameTxt>
      <P>When are we likely to be able to discuss the Bill dealing with copyright?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I think about mid-summer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1133" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamYeats" hpid="Dr. YEATS Dr. YEATS">
      <NameTxt>Dr. YEATS</NameTxt>
      <P>I rather press the point because we Irish authors are under the difficulty that we cannot at present copyright our books in America.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not quite serious when I said mid-summer.  That is an exaggeration.  It is a Bill that will require very careful consideration. It is a long Bill and deals with a variety of subjects.  I am sure most of the Senators will be interested in some portion of it, at least, and, therefore, it is a Bill the consideration of which will take up a good deal of time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. GUINNESS Mr. GUINNESS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GUINNESS</NameTxt>
      <P>Is the Bill going to be referred to a Joint Committee as on the last occasion?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>It is eminently suited for a Joint Committee, but that is a matter for the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1134" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The President The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT</NameTxt>
      <P>Without having any information on the subject, I would say that it is unlikely the Bill would be sent to a Joint Committee because of the fact that the previous one which was before the Joint Committee was withdrawn.  I think the work of the Joint Committee will most probably be evidenced in the present measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CATHAOIRLEACH CATHAOIRLEACH">
      <NameTxt>CATHAOIRLEACH</NameTxt>
      <P>Of course that is a matter, so far as this House is concerned, on which they would be better able to form an opinion when they come to see the contents of the Bill, and how far the recommendations of the previous Joint Committee have been incorporated in it.  I understand they have practically all been incorporated in it.  The House stands adjourned until a date of which Senators shall receive due notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>