<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="D&aacute;il Debate" Day="Thu" Date="28" Month="Sep" Year="1922" Vol="1" No="14" DateIrish="" DateEnglish="" House="D" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="885">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="885" /> Do cromadh ar obair an lac ar a 3.15 p.m.  Bhí an Ceann Comhairle, Micheál O h-Aodha, sa Chathaoir.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- TAXES ON MOTOR CARS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - TAXES ON MOTOR CARS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DanielOCallaghan" hpid="DOMHNALL O CEALLACHAIN DOMHNALL O CEALLACHAIN">
      <NameTxt>DOMHNALL O CEALLACHAIN:</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Finance how it is expected that taxes on motor cars are to be paid, in view of the fact that their earning powers for the past three years were practically nil, owing to bad roads and the disturbed conditions of the country; further, to ask the Minister for Finance why private owners should be expected to pay such a tax as 10s. per week for the use of a car, and whether he is aware that this is retarding the development of the country by the non-use of motors, both private and hackney, and also increasing the ranks of the unemployed by compelling owners of motor cars to dispense with drivers and mechanics, and even, in fact, to close down their garages.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesmondFitzgerald" hpid="MINISTER for FOREIGN AFFAIRS (Mr. Desmond Fitzgerald) MINISTER for FOREIGN AFFAIRS (Mr. Desmond Fitzgerald)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FOREIGN AFFAIRS (Mr. Desmond Fitzgerald)</NameTxt>
      <P>replying for the Minister for Finance: There is no option but to continue the collection of motor tax, as of other taxes, on the present basis, unless and until alterations of the law are made by this Dáil on any points where that course may be thought proper.  Unless the taxes are duly collected the public services cannot be maintained, and, in particular, the collection of motor tax is essential for maintaining the Road Fund, out of which assistance is given to local authorities for the upkeep of roads.  The case where a motor vehicle, for any reason, cannot be kept in use for the whole of any year may be met to some extent by the provision which enables a licence to be taken out in respect of portion of the year.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS." RHead="- PROTECTION OF FISHERIES">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - PROTECTION OF FISHERIES.</Title>
    <Col N="886" />
    <Speaker pid="DanielOCallaghan" hpid="DOMHNALL O CEALLACHAIN DOMHNALL O CEALLACHAIN">
      <NameTxt>DOMHNALL O CEALLACHAIN:</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the Minister for Agriculture what steps the Government intend to take to protect the inshore fisheries around the East and South East coasts of Ireland?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. Kevin O'Higgins), answering for the Minister for Agriculture Kevin O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for HOME AFFAIRS (Mr. Kevin O'Higgins),</NameTxt>
      <P>answering for the Minister for Agriculture: In the opinion of the Government the observance of the existing bye-laws should afford ample protection to the fisheries in question.  It is, however, open to persons interested in the inshore fisheries to submit for consideration their views as to the need for alteration in the present regulations should they consider such to be desirable.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="OA" LHead="CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - CAPTURED" RHead="DOCUMENTS. QUESTION OF NEGOTIATIONS">
    <Title>CEISTEANNA&mdash;QUESTIONS. - CAPTURED DOCUMENTS.  QUESTION OF NEGOTIATIONS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="DARGHAL FIGES DARGHAL FIGES">
      <NameTxt>DARGHAL FIGES:</NameTxt>
      <P>To ask the President, in view of the document signed by Liam Mellowes, recently published by the Ministry, if a document of even greater importance had not been taken, signed or issued by Eamon de Valera, and why this document has not also been published?  Further, to ask the President if any negotiations are at the present time proceeding, either with Eamon de Valera direct, or with any persons acting in his behalf, and if so, if he will inform the Dáil as to the progress of these negotiations?  In putting this question to the President I might tell him that since the question was put part of it has been answered by the speech that was made by the Minister for Defence yesterday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="MINISTER for FOREIGN AFFAIRS (answering for the President) MINISTER for FOREIGN AFFAIRS (answering for the President)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for FOREIGN AFFAIRS</NameTxt>
      <P>(answering for the President): In reply to the first part of the question, we are issuing the document captured as a Parliamentary Paper.  There are no such negotiations with Mr. de Valera as mentioned in the question.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="TRUCE" RHead="PROPOSAL">
    <Title>TRUCE PROPOSAL.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>Before going on to the regular business, I would like to move under Section 14 of the Standing Orders that the consideration of this Agenda be postponed at 7 o'clock to <Col N="887" /> discuss a matter of public importance, and I beg to move the following motion:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;To move that under Section 14 of Standing Orders the consideration of this day's Agenda be suspended at 7 p.m., for the discussion of a matter of public importance&mdash;namely, that this Dáil being responsible for the government of the country, hereby proclaims the necessity for an immediate Truce, to last not less than fourteen days, with a view to restoring peace, and thus saving the country from economic disaster, and hereby appoints the Commander-in-Chief, the Minister for Education, Mr. Deputy Johnson and Mr. Deputy Fitzgibbon as its delegates to negotiate the terms of the Truce.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I see one of the Ministers smiles at this, but it is the alternative to the monstrous proposal that comes from the Ministerial benches.  Peace, all will admit, is essential for the country.  I believe in dealing with Irishmen you can deal better by a method such as this than by threatening them with execution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>We may later on have a discussion on the matter, provided it has the support of twelve Deputies.  A speech on the subject now is out of order.  Would the Deputy hand the exact terms of his motion to the Clerk?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think a Truce will do any harm, and I think the Minister for Defence will bear me out in that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for LOCAL GOVERNMENT (Mr. E. Blythe):</NameTxt>
      <P>I think under the Standing Orders there is no power to bring on a motion like that at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>Under Sec. 14, it is allowable.  If, in the opinion of the Commander-in-Chief, it interferes with the military situation, I will not press it, but I do not think a Truce would do any harm.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>What is provided for in Articles 14 and 15 is the discussion of a matter of urgent public importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but is not peace a matter of public importance?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but a motion is not provided for.  The matter can be discussed without a motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="888" />
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>If we get a discussion it will be the same thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, if we say that the Orders of the Day be suspended at 7 o'clock for the discussion of a question of a Truce, that would meet the case.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The request therefore is, that in pursuance of Standing Order 14 we suspend the Orders of the Day for the discussion of a matter of public importance&mdash;namely, to appoint a Committee to negotiate peace. That request is made by Deputy McCartan. Those Deputies who support that request will hold up their hands.</P>
      <P>Over twelve Deputies held up their hands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The request is granted, and the matter will arise at 7 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE PRESIDENT'S MOTION." RHead="- THE DÁIL IN COMMITTEE">
    <Title>THE PRESIDENT'S MOTION. - THE DÁIL IN COMMITTEE.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The Dáil in accordance with the resolution passed on the adjournment yesterday evening, will go into Committee on the President's motion.  And we have, as you see it in the Orders of the Day, numbered the paragraphs of the resolution and arranged the amendments proposed in the order in which they occur in the clauses of the resolution.  The procedure would be that the first clause would be moved, and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>I formally move Clause No. 1.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a certain difficulty in meeting it in this way, that the resolution was not originally framed so, but we will have to get over it.  Perhaps, if Clauses 1 and 2 were moved together it would be the most expeditious way.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE PRESIDENT'S MOTION." RHead="- CLAUSES 1 AND 2 MOVED">
    <Title>THE PRESIDENT'S MOTION. - CLAUSES 1 AND 2 MOVED.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well.  I move Clauses 1 and 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>There is an amendment.  Amendment 1 refers to Clauses 1 and 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>In moving Amendment 1, I would like to say that <Col N="889" /> it was pointed out to me yesterday by members of the Ministry that the substitution of the word &ldquo;Ministry&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;Government&rdquo; in all cases would scarcely suit the purpose I had in mind, and I admit the justice of the criticism.  In some cases, therefore, the word &ldquo;Government,&rdquo; which means not specifically portion of this Dáil, but rather the general fact of government must necessarily remain by the retention of that word, and to that extent I would like, with your permission, to change the meaning of my amendment so that the two paragraphs under the discussion of the Dáil at the present moment would thereby read in the following manner:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;WHEREAS the Ministry has entrusted to the Army the duty of securing the public safety and restoring order throughout the country, and has placed on the Army the responsibility for the establishment of the authority of Government in all parts of the country in which that authority is challenged by force.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>In that case it would merely mean the elimination of the word &ldquo;the.&rdquo;  In the second amendment, instead of the words &ldquo;Army Authorities,&rdquo; we should substitute the words &ldquo;Minister for Defence,&rdquo; the purport being, as I explained to the Dáil, instead of putting into the hands of undefined persons the penalty of death in respect of undescribed offences and unscheduled offences, the defined Army Authorities be the Minister for Defence, and substitute the words &ldquo;Minister for Defence,&rdquo; so as to give the charge to some person who is a member of this Dáil, and as a Minister appointed by this Dáil is responsible to this Dáil.  The second paragraph would then read:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;AND WHEREAS the Minister for Defence has represented to the Ministry that in order to discharge effectively the duty and responsibility so placed on him it is essential that he should have power to establish Military Courts or Committees with full powers of inquiring into charges and inflicting punishment on persons found guilty of acts calculated to interfere with or delay the effective establishment of the authority of Government, and that he should have power to detain in places whether <Col N="890" /> within or without the area of the jurisdiction of the Government persons arrested by him, and power to control the dealing in and possession of firearms.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In the second place the word &ldquo;Government&rdquo; is substituted by &ldquo;Military,&rdquo; and where &ldquo;Military Authorities&rdquo; appears the substitution is &ldquo;Minister for Defence.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not inclined to accept that amendment in its entirety.  We are prepared in certain places where the Army authorities are mentioned to be more explicit, and to state what the Army authority in question is.  We will insert there, in the first line of paragraph 2:&mdash;&ldquo;And whereas the Army Council has represented to the Government,&rdquo; and so on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Who are they?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>The Army Council consists of the Commander-in-Chief, Chief of Staff, Adjutant-General, the Director of Organisation, and the Director of Intelligence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Since when?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>Deputies must not speak, when sitting down, across the Dáil to one another.  The questions must be put to any Minister through me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, in places where there is mention of &ldquo;Army Authorities&rdquo; we would insert there &ldquo;Army Council,&rdquo; and so on throughout that paragraph&mdash;&ldquo;and that the Army Council should have power to authorise the detention in places whether within or without the area of persons in military custody, and power to control the dealing in and possession of fire arms.&rdquo;  As to the suggested change of the word &ldquo;Government&rdquo; to the word &ldquo;Ministry,&rdquo; that is not acceptable, and the reason for its non-acceptance is, it is not in accordance with the facts of the situation. We are at the moment a Provisional Government, and this Parliament is at the moment a Parliament to which the Provisional Government is responsible. It is not proposed by any act of ours to acquiesce in any departure from that position.  If pressed for a reason, I can give it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="891" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Can the Minister give us the date of the official notification of the change in the Army Council?  Since the death of the late Commander-in-Chief there was a vacancy of course.  I understand, if I am not mistaken, there were three members to whom authority was given.  Now there appear to be five.  Has that been officially announced at any time?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>No, it has not been officially announced; but it is realised that in these cases where there is great responsibility, that that responsibility should be shared by the most responsible officers in the Army.  This Council has been constituted an Army Council by reason of the standing of each one of the officers&mdash;the position which he holds in the Army.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Will that supersede the Council of Three?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  The Council of Three has already been superseded&mdash; in one case by death and in another case by transfer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Can we speak of the Army Council as existing when no official announcement has been given?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>Certainly.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Has this appointment of a new Army Council been made by the Provisional Government or made by the Army?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>It has been made by the Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to have some answer to two enquiries I want to put to the Minister on this subject. If this Dáil authorises the Army Council to do certain acts, is the Army Council directly answerable to this Dáil, and through whom?  If I am not correct in saying the Army Council is directly answerable to this Dáil, the Army being, as we all admit, the servant of this Dáil, through the Minister for Defence, therefore the authority for this should be given to the person authorised to speak in this Dáil on behalf of the Army Council.  The second question is with regard to the substitution of &ldquo;Ministry&rdquo; for &ldquo;Government.&rdquo;  In view of the fact that the President stated that the Government was the whole Assembly <Col N="892" /> of the Dáil, then the statement made by the Minister for Home Affairs is to be taken as a withdrawal of these words by the President of the Ministry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>The answer to the first question is, the Minister for Defence; the second is metaphysical.  I might have it my way, and other people their way, and that is all I have to say about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we should dispose of Amendment 1 first; that is, the substitution of &ldquo;Ministry&rdquo; for &ldquo;Government&rdquo; in certain places.</P>
      <P>The amendment was put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>Now with regard to the second matter, to substitute the words &ldquo;Minister for Defence&rdquo; for the words &ldquo;Army Authorities,&rdquo; the Minister for Home Affairs has suggested that there are really two amendments there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the official amendment.  That the second paragraph will read:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;AND WHEREAS the Army Council have represented to the Government that in order to discharge effectively the duty and responsibility so placed on them it is essential that the Army Council should have power to set up Military Courts or Committees with full powers of inquiring into charges and inflicting punishment on persons found guilty of acts calculated to interfere with or delay the effective establishment of the authority of the Government, and that the Army Council should have power to authorise the detention whether within or without the area of the jurisdiction of the Government persons in military custody, and power to control the dealing in and possession of firearms.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I move this amendment, A Chinn Chomhairle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>We can take this amendment first, and then take the other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Whatever course is agreeable to you.  I would just like before it is being put to say I am not bringing this with any desire to impede the course of this amendment, but, in view of the fact that subsequent criticism will be made that this might <Col N="893" /> mean the setting up of a Military Dictatorship, I will vote for &ldquo;Minister for Defence&rdquo; in preference to &ldquo;the Army Council,&rdquo; because the Minister for Defence is a member of this Dáil and the Army Council is not directly responsible.</P>
      <P>The Clause as amended was then read and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Now, there is my amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, there <Col N="894" /> is your amendment to substitute in the Clause &ldquo;Minister for Defence&rdquo; for &ldquo;Army Council.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment (<i>b</i>):&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Wherever the words `Army Authorities' appear to substitute the words `Minister for Defence.&rdquo;'</P>
      <P>was put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>As perhaps this might create a precedent for future action, I should like to ask for a vote upon it.</P>
      <P>On a division the amendment was declared lost, the voting being 18 for and 41 against:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Tá.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Níl.</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Pádraig Ó Gamhna.<br />Tomás de Nógla.<br />Riobard Ó Deaghaidh.<br />Darghal Figes.<br />Tomás Mac Eóin.<br />Seoirse Ghabhain Ui Dhubhthaigh.<br />Ailfrid Ó Broin.<br />Tomás Ó Conaill.<br />Aodh Ó Cúlacháin.<br />Séamus Eabhróid.<br />Liam Ó Daimhin.<br />Pádraig Mac Artain.<br />Cathal Ó Seanain.<br />Seán Buitléir.<br />Nioclas Ó Faolain.<br />Domhnall Ó Muirgheasa.<br />Risteard Mac Fheorais.<br />Séamus Ó Dubhghaill</entry>
            <entry>Liam T. Mac Cosgair.<br />Donchadh Ó Gúaire.<br />Uaitear Mac Cúmhaill.<br />Seán Ó Duinnin.<br />Micheál Ó hAonghusa.<br />Domhnall Ó Mócháin.<br />Seán Ó hAodha.<br />Liam de Roiste.<br />Pádraig Mag Ualghairg.<br />Peadar Mac a' Bháird.<br />Deasmhumhain Mac Gearailt.<br />Seán Ó Rúanaidh.<br />Pilib Mac Cosgair.<br />Micheál de Staineas.<br />Domhnall Mac Carthaigh.<br />Earnán Altún.<br />Sir Séamus Craig.<br />Gearóid Mac Giobuin.<br />Liam Thrift.<br />Eóin Mac Néill.<br />Pádraic Ó Máille.<br />Seosamh Ó Faoileachain.<br />Seoirse Mac Niocaill.<br />Séamus Ó Cruadhlaoich.<br />Risteard Mac Liam.<br />Caoimhghin Ó hUigín.<br />Proinsias Bulfin.<br />Tomás Mac Artuir.<br />Séamus Ó Dóláin.<br />Liam Ó hAodha.<br />Seán Mac Eóin.<br />Proinsias Mag Aonghusa.<br />Éamon Ó Dúgáin.<br />Peadar Ó hAodha.<br />Séamus Ó Murchadha.<br />Liam Mac Sioghaird.<br />Earnan de Blaghd.<br />Uinseann de Faoite.<br />Domhnall Ó Broin.<br />Séamus de Burca.<br />Micheál Ó Dúbhghaill.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The Clerk will read the two clauses as they now stand.</P>
      <P>The Clerk of the Dáil having read the two clauses, a motion that they stand as part of the resolution was put, and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE PRESIDENT'S" RHead="MOTION. - CLAUSE 3">
    <Title>THE PRESIDENT'S MOTION. - CLAUSE 3</Title>
    <P>(3)  And whereas the Government recognising the force of such representations has sanctioned the doing by the Army Authorities of all or any of the following matters and things.</P>
    <P>(<i>a</i>)  The setting up of Military <Col N="895" /> Courts or Committees for the enquiring into charges against persons in respect of any of the offences hereinafter mentioned provided however that every such Military Court or Committee shall include as a member thereof at least one person nominated by the Minister of Defence and certified by the Law Officer to be a person of legal knowledge and experience.</P>
    <P>(<i>b</i>)  The enquiry by such Military Courts or Committees into the cases of persons charged with any of the offences following that is to say:&mdash;</P>
    <P>(I.)  Taking part in or aiding or abetting any attack upon or using force against the National Forces.</P>
    <P>(II.)  Looting, arson, destruction, seizure, unlawful possession or removal of or damage to any public or private property.</P>
    <P>(III.)  Having possession without proper authority of any bomb or article in the nature of a, bomb or any dynamite, gelignite or other explosive substance or any revolver, rifle, gun or other firearm or lethal weapon or any ammunition for such firearm.</P>
    <P>(IV)  The breach of any general order or regulation made by the Army Authorities.</P>
    <P>and the infliction by such Military Courts or Committees of the punishment of death or of penal servitude for any period or of imprisonment for any period or of a fine of any amount either with or without imprisonment on any person found guilty by such Court or Committee of any of the offences aforesaid.</P>
    <P>(<i>c</i>)  The removal by Army Authorities of all or any persons taken prisoner, arrested or detained by the National Forces to any place or places whether within or without the area of jurisdiction of the Government and the detention or imprisonment of any such persons in any place or places within or without the area aforesaid.</P>
    <P>(<i>d</i>)  The regulation and control of the sale, possession, transfer of and dealing in revolvers, rifles, guns and other firearms.</P>
    <Col N="896" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>I move the adoption of No. 3 down to (<i>d</i>).  With regard to what I said yesterday about these Army regulations, or orders, being laid on the Table of the Dáil, an amendment will be moved at the end of Clause 4 which will provide for that.  It will also provide for the maximum penalty which will attach to any such general order or regulation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>There is an amendment on the paper in your name.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, but it is not so complete.  It reads: &ldquo;Provided, however, that, as regards such general order or regulation as aforesaid, the same shall be laid on the Table of this Dáil, and shall take effect on the expiration of four sitting days thereafter, unless this Dáil shall have previously passed a resolution disallowing same.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>It is to be presumed the words &ldquo;Army Authorities&rdquo; will now read &ldquo;Army Council&rdquo;?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The first paragraph is to read: &ldquo;The doing by the Army Council,&rdquo; and the last paragraph, &ldquo;The removal under the authority of the Army Council.&rdquo;  Perhaps we would take the motion as it actually is, with the general assumption, in accordance with the amendment already passed, that the words &ldquo;Army Authorities&rdquo; will now read &ldquo;Army Council,&rdquo; and we will take amendments as they arise.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>Amendment (<i>c</i>)&mdash;&ldquo;In the third paragraph, at the end of Sub-section (a) to read: `One person of legal knowledge and experience appointed by the Minister for Defence,' instead of the words that now conclude the sub-section.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Before that comes forward, there is an earlier matter I spoke to you about with regard to Paragraph 3, which you suggested might be met if I were to hand in, in writing, an amendment.  I will do so, but I am reluctant to do it if it is going to be opposed, because on a matter of this kind, where I am in such entire agreement with the Government, I do not care to <Col N="897" /> be proposing an amendment as if opposition were there, when there is really no opposition at all.  In this Clause 3, as it reads, it states that the Government has done&mdash;the Ministry, that is to say&mdash; has done such a thing.  Clause 4 states this Body, then, is asked to come in, and &mdash;to use an expression which was used yesterday&mdash;confirm as by way of rubber stamp something it could not very well avert.  I am rather anxious, if the Ministry will consider the matter, to introduce, right here, in this paragraph, responsibility of the Dáil for undertaking such action, by setting forth the reason and cause of such order in the form of words: &ldquo;Now, therefore, this Dáil, recognising the force of such representation, and the perilous state of the country, and recognising further that, in the absence of Civil Courts, extraordinary courts and processes are rendered necessary to deal with persons conspiring to set aside and defy the authority of the Irish people, sanctions the doing by the Minister for Defence of all or any of the following acts.&rdquo;  I would move that, if I may. I have it written out here.  I do not care to press it if the Government will oppose it and keep to the form they have here.  I think the form I am suggesting puts them in a stronger and better position, inasmuch as it enables this Dáil at once to assume authority of its own initiative, and not because some Committee has gone ahead and done work which the Dáil is merely to confirm after it has been done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment will be proposed, substituting &ldquo;Army Council&rdquo; for &ldquo;Minister for Defence.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. E. BLYTHE Mr. E. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. BLYTHE:</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment cannot be accepted.  The fact is that the Ministry actually did sanction these things some time ago, although not yet acted upon, and there is no valid objection, and can be no valid objection to the recital of that fact. It is a very proper thing for the Government, in the first instance, to sanction this emergency method, and it is preferable that it should be done as an executive and administrative act approved by Parliament rather than an act of an administrative or executive kind directed by Parliament.  There is another objection to the amendment as it stands, which is that there is not a complete <Col N="898" /> absence of civil courts.  The fact is that, owing to the terrorism and a variety of things, civil courts are not, and would not, for many purposes be effective, but they are there.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case I will not press my amendment.  I only say the effect of my amendment would be that this Dáil would be made primarily responsible for this very grave act that is about to be undertaken, and the effect of the Minister's statement is that the Dáil is only secondarily responsible, because the act has been already undertaken apart from its responsibility.  I think that is a very unfortunate statement to be made in this Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move as an amendment.  At the end of paragraph (<i>a</i>) Clause 3 (Military Court or Committee shall include as a member) to add the words &ldquo;who shall be President of the Court.&rdquo;  The intention is to provide that the person of legal experience who shall be appointed to each Court shall preside over the Court.  I think nothing further need be said in favour of that, and I beg to move it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>There is very little objection to what is the object of this amendment; in fact, this legal gentleman will be the pivot man of the Tribunal, but it must be remembered that this resolution entrusts a certain task to the Army, and, having done that, to make this gentleman, who should act rather as an adviser to the Court and one who is to help them and to weigh up accurately the value of the evidence and so on&mdash;to make him President is almost taking back again from the Army what you had entrusted to them.  It seems to us that, while a military officer should be President of the Court, he would understand that his professional assistant was more skilled in the appreciation of evidence and so on than he would be by the nature of his particular occupation, and he would rely a good deal upon the professional assistance that would be supplied.  I think it is objectionable to make a lawyer President of the Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Minister does not appreciate that what he said now is not quite consistent with the document as drafted.  The draft proposed <Col N="899" /> by the Government says:&mdash;&ldquo;A legal man is to be a member of the Court,&rdquo; not by any means their adviser, or a man in the position of the Judge Advocate.  He is to be a legal man nominated by the Minister and certified by the Law Officer to be a person of legal knowledge and experience, but he is to be a member of the Court and not its legal adviser.  I think there is every reason for the proposal of Deputy Johnson.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfEoinMacNeill" hpid="General SEAN McKEON General SEAN McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General SEAN McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I oppose the proposal that this legal adviser should be the President of the Court.  There is no reason why the Army Council and the Army Authorities should not carry on this Court.  All that is necessary is that some person with full legal knowledge capable of weighing properly the evidence should advise the Court.  That is all that is required.  If you accept this amendment, you are giving authority with one hand, and withdrawing it with the other.  That will not do.  You must have it one way or the other.  Personally speaking, I have no respect whatever for any legal adviser, because all legal advisers, as I know them, could be compared with some of the members of this Dáil in that they will play-act with words and play with phrases and start every sort of devilment you could possibly imagine.  But if you come down to hard realities there is not one drachm of common sense in all their legal knowledge, because every bit of the legal knowledge they have is seen through a British glass.  I do not care the weight of my finger for them.  Make the President of the Court an Army Officer who thoroughly understands and thoroughly appreciates the position, and even though he is in arms against some other Irishman, or if some other Irishman is in arms against him, yet at the same time he can appreciate that position, and he can be just and he can have full sympathy and appreciation of the other man's position.  That is the man to make President of the Court, and do not put the fellow who can advise him in the position. The President of the Court can use his own discretion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>The proposals themselves promise that there shall be more than one member of the Court; the President is merely the President of the Court; and that that Court <Col N="900" /> shall include not more than one person &mdash;as it must&mdash;who is certified by the Law Officer to be a person of legal knowledge and experience.  Presumably there is some intention in that, and presumably also that person with legal knowledge will desire to have a say in the judgment, and not merely say &ldquo;ditto&rdquo; to the President, whoever he may be. And I am tempted to say that probable Presidents of Courts have declared in public that if they had caught a certain individual, that if they had been assured that that certain individual was guilty of a certain act, they would there and then have shot him dead.  That is the statement of the Deputy who has just sat down, a man who has undoubtedly done his utmost, so far as public speech is concerned&mdash;and that is the only criterion that I have&mdash;to ensure that the military forces shall be the servants of the civil authority.  I give him credit to the utmost that he, more than any other man, so far as I know, in the country, has laid it down emphatically time after time that the military forces should be the servants of the civil authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General McKEON General McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Correct.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>But even he, not having that legal knowledge and legal training, allowed himself to say, in the cool of a court, that if he had known that a particular individual had been guilty of a particular act, he would have shot him there and then.  That is one of the things we want to try to guard against.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General McKEON General McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I would shoot him now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>We want to try to guard against that; and I want to protest against a suggestion that has been made that it is out of our regard for the Irregulars and their acts.  It is out of regard for the good name of the Army itself, and for the good name of the nation, and to protect the Army from the risks and the dangers to its good name that will follow the adoption of this.  I would say, further, that the danger arises, not to the participants in the warfare, but to the people who may be assumed, or presumed, or suspected of being participators in the warfare, and who may eventually be found to be perfectly innocent.  I maintain, however little respect members of the Ministerial <Col N="901" /> benches may have for the lawyers, that there is something in legal training, and there is something to be said for legal training, and in a Court of this kind it is an advantage, and I am sure it will be a protection to the Army and to the good name of the Army to have the President of that Court a man of legal training.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General McKEON General McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Deputy mention on what particular occasion I made that reference?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. THOS. JOHNSON Mr. THOS. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. THOS. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>The enquiry into the death of General Adamson.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General McKEON General McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite correct.  If I was sure of the man who murdered General Adamson, and if I met him on the street, I would shoot him.  The reason I would shoot him then was because there was no law but the law that was vested in me as the Competent Authority of the area.  Pass the law that is now asked for, and there would be no necessity for me to shoot him, because there would be a legal method of dealing with that individual.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely that is not sufficient reason why the President of this Court would not be a man of legal experience.  One of the primary reasons why we oppose these regulations is because we object to any Court having the powers specified here, and because of that Court not being in the proper sense of the word a judicial Court. Deputy Sean McKeon has said some things just now which, to my mind, seem to make it more necessary that the more judicial you can make the Court the better.  It may be, if we follow something the President said yesterday afternoon, that the Senior Officer, who may be acting as President of the Court, would be trying for life some of the people to-day who were fighting against him last night.  It is not, I think, in human nature that that officer could preside over that Court and, being the Senior Officer, could look on that case and weigh the evidence with that impartiality and that spirit of judicial fairness which would be got from someone else.  There is no Army that I know of in any part of the world that does not purposely get supplied from the Civil Authorities when Military Courts are likely to be called into use.  There is no Army that does not get from the Civil <Col N="902" /> Authorities a sufficient supply of legal gentlemen, trained in all these things, in order that there may not be the least doubt, either in the mind of the prisoner before the Court or in the minds of the people, that that prisoner is going to get the strictest justice.  The utmost effort should be made to give persons coming before those Courts justice.  Now, Deputy McKeon and others who have gone through British Courts-martial know that, whatever may have happened under the Black and Tan regime or under the later stages of Greenwood's regime, where Military Courts were held there has not been a single Irish prisoner who would not have preferred the British system of Military Courts, because at those Courts they took care to provide all the legal help that could be got.  In my own experience the President was often chosen because of his legal knowledge.  We protested again and again that these were not courts in the true sense of the word, and that they were merely committees with the power to execute, and that is what you are setting up now&mdash;committees with power of execution and deportation.  I support the amendment as strongly as I can.  Although we differ from them in many things, the more legal men you have, the better for the Army, and the better for the men into whose hands you are putting this great responsibility over life and death.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General McKEON General McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>The only man sympathetic to me was an officer, and not the legal adviser.  The legal adviser there was afraid of his life to open his mouth.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a question of sympathy, but of justice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General McKEON General McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>As for justice the fellow who offered all the justice was an officer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="MINISTER for DEFENCE (General R. Mulcahy) Richard (General) Mulcahy">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for DEFENCE (General R. Mulcahy):</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the intention to get from the civil side men with legal training, the best that can be got, to help us in this work.  For the purpose of their duties with us and for the period of their service, they will be vested with military rank.  The particular type of rank is not yet decided, whether it will be a senior or a junior rank, and the chance of an officer sitting on any Court Martial being President of the Court will depend upon <Col N="903" /> the rank of the other officers associated with him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>Will the Minister for Defence allow me to point out to him one thing which I think he has overlooked in the British Court Martial system which, personally, I consider to be an admirable one once you leave out the political element; you have it expressly provided that every Court Martial sentence, and all Court Martial proceedings are to be sent to the Judge Advocate General for review, so there is a definite check on mistakes.  Here we have not got that check, and for that reason the motion proposed by Deputy Johnson has an added importance.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General R. MULCAHY General R. MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General R. MULCAHY:</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think, at the moment, it is apparent what kind of check you have.  There is no reason why it could not come before the Judge Advocate General or any similar person who exists in that capacity, and the intention is that sentences in all these cases will come at any rate to some headquarters for confirmation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked the Minister yesterday whether there would be a Judge Advocate General.  I may have misunderstood him, but I thought he said not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General R. MULCAHY General R. MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General R. MULCAHY:</NameTxt>
      <P>There is one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>If there is I am perfectly satisfied, but that is not expressed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General R. MULCAHY General R. MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General R. MULCAHY:</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing here with the powers we are going to get, and then we will deal with the regulations under which we will put these powers into action.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephHenness" hpid="Mr. WILLIAM HENNESSY Mr. WILLIAM HENNESSY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILLIAM HENNESSY:</NameTxt>
      <P>I suppose those courts will be open to the public or the Press?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General R. MULCAHY General R. MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General R. MULCAHY:</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not our intention that these Courts will be open either to the Press or the public. The person charged will have the benefit of legal assistance to whatever reasonable extent is possible, and will have power to examine witnesses.</P>
      <P>The Amendment, &ldquo;To add at the end of Section (<i>a</i>) `who will act as President of the Court,&rdquo;' was put and lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="904" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>I interrupted Deputy Figgis, unwittingly, when his amendment was reached.  May I ask permission to have it moved?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not give permission.  People who put amendments on the paper should be ready to move them when called upon, and neither the President nor anyone else should interrupt them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Quite content, sir.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>I move Amendment (3).  I said yesterday I was in sympathy with the motion before the Dáil, on the assumption that this important amendment or the spirit of it was accepted.  I was in sympathy, shortly, because I felt that the nearer you get in this business to the pure military spirit the nearer you will get to justice. In every war the bitterness comes not from the military, but from the civilians.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>You know very little about war when you say that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>It is essential, particularly when there is no definite system of defined military law&mdash;it is essential that these general principles under which the military are empowered to act should be fairly laid down.  I ask the members to realise that in this motion, as distinct from the later motion on the paper dealing with the question of prisoners of war, I am distinctly not raising the question of status, as to which I know there is difference of opinion.  I am not asking you to say that the Irregulars are legitimately taking the action they are taking.  I am not even asking you to say that they should be treated as belligerents.  Those are separate questions.  The immediate question now is, can we have a definite basic principle upon which those rules shall go; and my suggestion to the Diál is that there can be no more satisfactory basic principle for drastic action such as is proposed&mdash;no more satisfactory principle than that which has international recognition as its basis.  I can deal with this matter very shortly by referring the Dáil to two or three passages from conventions and regulations mentioned.  The amendment reads: &ldquo;Provided that no punishment (as mentioned in the Clause) shall be inflicted <Col N="905" /> otherwise than in pursuance of an Ordinance by the Commander-in-Chief based upon the principles laid down by the Hague Convention of 1907 `concerning the laws and customs of war on land' and the Regulations annexed thereto, such Ordinance to be made and promulgated for the information of all concerned as soon as possible.&rdquo;  It is based upon this bedrock principle that law, military law or any other law, must be certain and must be public.  That is why I refer you to the promulgation at the end.  Now, the Powers in 1907 came to a Convention in which they declared that the contracting Powers shall issue instructions to their armed land forces, which shall be in conformity with the Regulations respecting the law and custom of war on land, and the Powers in coming to these provisions or resolutions, after several clauses say:&mdash;&ldquo;According to the views of the High Contracting Parties, these provisions, the drafting of which has been inspired by the desire to diminish the evils of war, so far as military requirements permit, are intended to serve as a general rule of conduct for the belligerents in their mutual relations, and in their relations with the inhabitants.  It has not, however, been found possible at present to concert stipulations covering all the circumstances which arise in practice.  On the other hand, the High Contracting Parties clearly do not intend that unforeseen cases should, in default of written agreements, be left to the arbitrary opinion of military commanders. Until a more complete code of the laws of war can be drawn up the High Contracting Parties deem it expedient to declare in cases not covered by the rules adopted by them, the inhabitants and the belligerents remain under the protection and governance of the principles of the law of nations derived from the usages established among civilised peoples, from the laws of humanity, and from the dictates of public conscience.&rdquo; Now, in my amendment, I use the words &ldquo;based upon&rdquo; to meet the case which will be obvious to all the members of the Dáil, that these regulations were intended, primarily, not for civil war.  Nevertheless, the basic principles of these regulations are principles of universal application, and so much of them as is inapplicable one would not expect the Minister for <Col N="906" /> Defence to apply.  Therefore, I urge in the resolution that the order should be based upon the principles enunciated here.  I need say very little more about that, except to quote you another passage or two.  I want to impress upon the Dáil the desirability of treating the men as soldiers, and to let them know they are going to be so treated, in order that this measure may not be regarded as the Propagandist will seek to have it regarded, as a signal for a vendetta.  We do not want that.  Whether you consider this is war or not, I do.  The judges did, the other day.  Whatever you call it, there are some general rules that ought to be applied.  Tell the people on the other side that you are going to base your action on these rules.  Now, there are four distinct sorts of offenders recognised in these cases&mdash;or four distinct kinds of offences, and I should say these are:&mdash;(1) Violations of the recognised rules of warfare by members of armed forces, (2) illegitimate hostilities in arms committed by individuals who are not members of the armed forces, (3) espionage and war treason, (4) marauding.  These things, mind you, cut both ways.  There are very severe provisions here, and if the Irregulars are not observing the laws of war&mdash;certainly things have occurred which no one can defend&mdash;I suggest to the Minister for Defence, and I hope he will be with me in this, that the very fact of treating these men according to the rules of war will have its reaction upon any of them who break those rules themselves and it will tend to diminish the infraction of those rules of war of which we have been told in the Press. There are, I say, things that cut both ways&mdash;things such as making use of poisoned and otherwise forbidden arms and ammunition, killing of the wounded, refusal of quarter, treacherous request of quarter, maltreatment of dead bodies in the field, ill-treatment of prisoners of war, breaking of parole of prisoners of war, firing on undefended localities, abuse of the flag of truce, firing on the flags of truce, abuse of the Red Cross and badge, and other violations of the Geneva Convention, use of civilian clothing by troops to conceal their military character during battle, bombardment of hospitals and other privileged buildings, poisoning of wells and streams, pillage and purposeless destruction, ill-treatment of inhabitants in occupied territory.  It <Col N="907" /> is forbidden to declare that no quarter will be given, and the use of dum-dum bullets is forbidden.  At all events, the short argument for some such principles being adopted is that it has behind it the experience of the Nations.  There are things in it which are inapplicable in civil war, where men on one side are not uniformed at all.  But, taking it all round, it establishes principles, and if we are told those principles will be the basis of the Ordinances of the Commander-in-Chief, we shall know that in our civil war here we are applying a code which has the sanction of international usage.  I think that would be valuable to the cause which we are defending.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. GOREY Mr. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GOREY:</NameTxt>
      <P>What about ambushes without any warning?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>Regarding these Ordinances, they include measures for dealing with attacks upon the National forces, looting, arson, destruction or damage to public or private property. Now, we hear great speeches about humanity, and so on.  Those are the offences, and the penalties attaching to them are down in the next paragraph. We have all heard of The Hague.  Some of us do not know what went on at The Hague, or what was said at The Hague. I do.  I heard of it.  I am after hearing of it now.  The Deputy, I think, did not go to any great pains to let us know what all these high contracting parties did.  We know they pledged themselves to great things and broke their pledges. These are our regulations here, and if they are objected to let us know in what particular they object to them, and if there is anything wrong, put in something that we have not put in.  That is, I think, the business of the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister of Defence has the whole thing in the Manual of Military Law.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I support Deputy Gavan Duffy's suggestion, and in supporting it I want to say a word or two about what the President said now.  The President said if there is not enough&mdash;or if the right things are not in the regulations, then let the Dáil put them in.  There is no use at all in trying to alter that resolution, because anything <Col N="908" /> that is intended to make this thing look even decent&mdash;not alone to be decent, but to look decent&mdash;is not to be put in, is not going to be put in by the Ministry and the Ministry's supporters in this Dáil.  Certainly, I have definitely come to the conclusion that there is not the least use at all in attempting to amend these things&mdash;not the least. There is talk about humanitarianism, talk about The Hague, and a whole lot of things, and the putting into practice and the setting up of these Courts is going to be a test not only of the humanity of the people, but a test whether, even in this age, there is any civilisation left.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfEoinMacNeill" hpid="MINISTER for EDUCATION (Prof. MacNeill) MINISTER for EDUCATION (Prof. MacNeill)">
      <NameTxt>MINISTER for EDUCATION (Prof. MacNeill):</NameTxt>
      <P>The suggestion is nothing short of a monstrous one that the Ministry is using any means whatsoever to prevent any Deputy here from voting freely.  If there be any means whatsoever&mdash;any undue influence on any man&mdash; brought to bear on any Deputy here not to vote freely on this or any other question, then the sooner it is stated here the better.  We have heard over and over again that those who vote in support of this or that proposal brought forward by the Ministry vote unfreely, vote as if under some sort of compulsion, vote as if they were compelled to be part of some machine.  These suggestions come to us from what I do not hesitate to describe as the most efficiently regimented party in this Dáil.  (Hear, hear.) Now, sir, I merely make that statement in order to clear the air or with regard to the fact and this particular amendment before us.  And having made that statement, I go further and say that I trust every single Deputy here present will not vote <i>en bloc</i>, but give attention to this thing, and vote for or against it as the merits are brought before them.  The seconder of the amendment seconded it apparently for no other purpose than to discharge that attack, because he himself&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of explanation, I do not second the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The Deputy supported it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I supported it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfEoinMacNeill" hpid="Prof. MacNEILL Prof. MacNEILL">
      <NameTxt>Prof. MacNEILL:</NameTxt>
      <P>He supported it apparently for no other purpose than <Col N="909" /> to discharge that attack, because, to judge from what he said, he knew absolutely nothing of what the principles of The Hague Convention provided. Perhaps he did; but if he did, it is a pity he did not give us the facts instead of imaginary fictions.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chinn Comhairle, I did not, as a matter of fact, say that the Ministry or anybody else was bringing any particular kind of undue pressure on its supporter, but that Members supporting them, and I will remind the Minister for Education that yesterday afternoon the Minister for Home Affairs asked Deputies, as he has asked them on several occasions, each of them to weigh carefully when about to vote on this, to consider the thing, to treat the thing as if the whole matter depended on his vote alone.  Now, he did that when we were discussing the Constitution. The Ministry have been pretty well doing that all along since we came in here.  We are quite agreed on that, and we heard him all the time on that.  But before we did we wanted the Teachtai to weigh these things in their own minds.  The Minister for Foreign Affairs yesterday pooh-poohed the idea of humanitarianism.  The President almost goes so far as to do the same to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>I must object to that.  I said plainly and distinctly that if we have gone too far, show us where we have gone, and if we have not gone far enough, show us where.  You have done neither one nor the other, and you know it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister for Education says the most perfectly regimented machine is on this side of the Dáil.  Now, if the Minister for Education, or any other Minister knows anything of my colleagues who sit beside me here, they know that on these questions&mdash;on every one of these questions&mdash;each and every one of them is as free to vote and say what he likes as I am, or as any Teachta in this Dáil, because, as a matter of fact, there are many questions in which we leave the utmost freedom, but there are many ways of bringing in pressure than by regimenting your Teachtaí.  I think the impression certainly that I have got, if not the impression of every Teachtaí, is this, that when <Col N="910" /> the President gets up and says this thing must be done, we have got to do this thing, then the majority of the Dáil without exercising, in my opinion, any judgment at all&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>You do not know them as well as I do.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>They vote straight.  I did get up not in order to explain The Hague Convention or anything else, but I think I know if not quite so much, almost as much as the Minister for Education&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfEoinMacNeill" hpid="Professor MacNEILL Professor MacNEILL">
      <NameTxt>Professor MacNEILL:</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be easy for you.  (Laughter.)</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="CathalOShannon" hpid="CATHAL O'SHANNON CATHAL O'SHANNON">
      <NameTxt>CATHAL O'SHANNON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Because I made a certain study of that, but it is not the words of this thing that matters, it is the spirit.  It is the spirit in which this whole debate has been carried on, and I did get up not to exactly ask the Ministry to adopt Deputy Gavan Duffy's suggestion, but to express my own personal feeling, that there is no use in saying or making any attempt to amend this, as the Ministry get up and oppose it, and when they do that the majority of the Dáil will vote against it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfEoinMacNeill" hpid="Professor MacNEILL Professor MacNEILL">
      <NameTxt>Professor MacNEILL:</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask how often is it in order for a Deputy to make a speech in the same kind of way?  Does the Deputy think if he repeats a statement twice no additional proof is required?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>I must remind Teachtaí that we are discussing an amendment moved by Deputy Gavan Duffy, which has some connection with the Hague Convention, and any further discussion about the regimenting of the Dáil, or portion thereof, is out of order. The Minister for Education's questions I think answered themselves.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfEoinMacNeill" hpid="Professor MacNEILL Professor MacNEILL">
      <NameTxt>Professor MacNEILL:</NameTxt>
      <P>They were meant to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General R. MULCAHY General R. MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General R. MULCAHY:</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to the amendment, I want to say that we feel from every point of view it would be wrong to bind ourselves by such a clause as this, or to do what it would propose as it is much more likely to open up avenues for us by which we might seek to inflict perhaps very drastic punishment upon those we are out to <Col N="911" /> punish, no doubt, at the present time. We have our own intentions with regard to the length to which we wish to go in dealing with this matter, and it would be very inadvisable, I think, by passing Clauses that might, by binding us in certain ways, open up certain other ways of defending ourselves by any regulations that were violations of the recognised rules of war.  What was marauding?  What was espionage.  What was the illegal use of weapons of one kind or another?  It would be therefore much better to leave them to the intentions we have at the present moment than that we are to be confronted to consider this, that or the other were maraudings or violations of the rules of war, and say they are definitely punishable by death.  The great high contracting parties have made Europe what Europe is to-day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>There is only one thing I urge might not be pressed. I think the general principles underlying this Ordinance, the principles laid down in this august Assembly, might be remembered in this Dáil when we come to deal with the actual provisions themselves as they will be put before this Dáil later on by the Minister for Defence or the Ministry.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Instead of the amendment as it stands in my name, No. 4, I would ask your permission, sir, if I may, in view of the debate that occurred yesterday, and that has made the amendment as it stands unnecessary and incomplete, to substitute for it an amendment in this form, i.e., to say that the words &ldquo;and the infliction by such Military Courts of the punishment of death or penal servitude,&rdquo; etc., right down to the end stand, and that these words be added:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>&ldquo;Provided that the punishment of death be not given save in respect of offences set out under Sections (1), (2), (3).  Provided that no such sentence of death be executed save under the counter-signature of the President and the Ministry by and with the authority of the Ministry.  Provided that such Military Courts be set up within areas scheduled from time to time by the Minister of Defence, or areas within which Civil Courts <Col N="912" /> are not open and are not capable of being held; and provided, lastly, that no person may be removed from one area to another for the purpose of creating jurisdiction of such Courts.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>These are the four extra provisions. They were dealt with yesterday in one form or another.  They were, I understand&mdash;I was not present on the occasion (laughter)&mdash;in answers to questions by myself that the punishment of death would not be given save in respect of offences set out under certain sections.  That proviso I have put here.  It was stated that such offences would come under the Ministry.  That proviso I have also put here.  It was stated by the Minister for Defence, unless I misunderstood him, that it would not be necessary to set up such Courts in all parts of the country, but that there were certain parts of the country in which Civil Courts would be set up.  The last two provisos I have put in here to enable this resolution to square with the Constitution put forward by the Government in their draft.  That provided in the first place that where Civil Courts can be set up they shall be set up. Where Civil Courts are set up, as long as they continue to function, the people within these areas shall be tried by Civil Courts, and shall not be removed to other areas for the purpose of creating military jurisdiction.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any portion of that amendment accepted by the Ministry?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>We would undertake, as far as the Civil Courts being established in any area, that we would not remove a prisoner from that district to an area in which they are not functioning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General R. MULCAHY General R. MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General R. MULCAHY:</NameTxt>
      <P>If a prisoner committed an offence in that area and cleared out of it, it might be absolutely necessary to bring him back to that area.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>Take No. 2.  One of the cases which has come under my notice is that of the destruction of waterworks or private supply to a town.  That is only property, but it really strikes at more than property.  Certainly any such <Col N="913" /> interference as that, where a huge number of people would be concerned, and who would suffer from that inconvenience, perhaps causing their death, would, to my mind, merit the death penalty.  Therefore, I would not agree to exclude No. 2.  It reads: &ldquo;And on the infliction by such Military Courts, provided that the punishment of death be not given, save in respect of offences set out under Sections 1, 2, and 3.&rdquo;  Of course, by including No. 2, I do not say that if a man steals £5 he is going to be shot for it.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Provided further that no such sentences of death be executed except under the counter signature of the President of the Ministry, by and with the authority of the Ministry, and provided further that such Military Court is set up within areas scheduled from time to time by the Minister for Defence, or areas in which the Civil Courts are not open,&rdquo; and so on.  Well, I think I take that down to the &ldquo;Minister for Defence.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Provided that punishment be not given, save in respect of offences set out,&rdquo; and also &ldquo;Provided that no such sentence of death be executed save by the counter signature of the President and the Ministry, and by and with the authority of the Ministry.&rdquo;  There is a provision later on in which we say there may be further regulation which may entail the death penalty.  Does this amendment limit that?  &ldquo;And further that such Military Courts be set up within areas scheduled from time to time by the Minister for Defence.&rdquo;  I think we can agree with that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General R. MULCAHY General R. MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General R. MULCAHY:</NameTxt>
      <P>&ldquo;Provided that the punishment of death be not given save under Sections 1, 2 and 3 set out above.&rdquo;  That is unnecessary, because with regard to No. 4 you are going to provide it at the end.</P>
      <P>&ldquo;That no such sentence of death be executed except under the counter signature of the President of the Ministry, by and with the authority of the Ministry.&rdquo; Now, I think nobody wants to take upon themselves the individual responsibility for bearing that authority, and my own feeling in the matter is that we could very well leave the affirming authority for all sentences passed by these Military Courts in the hands of any two of the Army Council.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="914" />&ldquo;Provided further that such Military Courts be set up in such areas scheduled from time to time for Military Courts by the Minister of Defence.&rdquo;  Now, there are eight Command Areas in the country, and in each of these Commands at the present time it might be necessary to set up Courts to deal with offences occurring there.  I suggest you tackle the question of controlling the areas for which these courts may be set up by a receding method, because at any moment it may be necessary to set up Courts in any of these eight areas, and we ask for authority for that, particularly in view of the type of offences that are being committed in them at the present time. You are faced with the question of reestablishing your courts.  You will have areas in the country in which your civil courts will be set up.  We ask for authority to establish these.  Let us have this receding method from time to time in areas from which the Military Authorities will be drawn.  Not only have you to consider the fact that you have to provide Courts in certain areas, and that you cannot safely withdraw this authority from certain areas until you can satisfy yourself that you have set up Courts which will be unfettered or unrestricted by any interference or threats of violence. I do not agree with this.</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Provided lastly that no person shall be moved from one area to another for the purpose of creating jurisdiction of the Courts.&rdquo;  Now, we are not anxious to bring a very great amount of trade to these Courts, and I think you may take it our intention is that offences will be tried in the Command Area in which they are committed.  That provision might give a situation in which you would have one belt of the country without Civil Courts and another belt of the country in which you have Civil Courts set up, but not quite established, and other courts put fairly on their feet.  Cases will arise where persons who commit offences in one belt of the country will slip over to another belt which has passed completely into the hands of the Civil Administration.  I think we should have authority to return such persons to the particular area in which they committed their offences.  I myself do not want any of these amendments, as I do not wish to put on the Army Council, or any two members of it, the painful duty of confirming death sentences.  I do not think <Col N="915" /> it is necessary that these death sentences should go before the whole Army Council.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say, sir, I find it a little difficult to follow the procedure of the Ministry from one day to another.  I put these two items in that are now being objected to, because they were offered by the President of the Ministry yesterday evening.  I understood the President did definitely state that the punishment of death would be confined to certain sections.  Some of us may think that they should not be confined to these sections, but, however, these are the statements, I understand, of the President.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>I am prepared to stand by that statement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>It was also stated by the President that the Ministry would have the confirmation of these sentences.  These proposals of mine were put forward for the purpose of giving effect to the Ministerial statements in this Dáil.  A criticism was made yesterday that two Government documents were put before the Dáil on the one day, and that they did not square easily with each other, and I put in this amendment for the purpose of getting these documents to square with Article 69 of the Constitution put before us by the Government.  Quite clearly under them if a man commits an offence in an area of a Military Court where a Civil Court cannot run, and if that man runs to a Civil Court in an area from where Military Courts have been withdrawn and Civil Courts could not be set up, it is clearly right that that man should be taken to the area in which he committed the offence, and not where he happened to be taken.  That was clearly foreseen in Article 73 of the Constitution, which they themselves issued.  I urge the Government to take that because, to use a now familiar phrase, it does implement the Constitution and it does implement Presidential assurances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>May I say, if I was under sentence of death I should far prefer that the stay of execution should be in the hands of two members of the Army Council rather than in the hands of the Ministry?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeraldFitzgibbon" hpid="Mr. G. FITZGIBBON Mr. G. FITZGIBBON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. G. FITZGIBBON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I understood the President to say last night, and I understand him to say now, that the <Col N="916" /> Ministry are prepared to confine the death penalty to death sentences coming between 1, 2 and 3.  I understood him to say a few moments ago that he had no objection to the amendment of Deputy Figgis down to the part &ldquo;punishment of death shall not be given except in respect of the indictments in 1, 2 and 3.  I suggest that the sentence should be carried out by some high authority.  I understood from what he said last night that that authority should be the Commander-in-Chief and the Minister of Defence.  So far as I am concerned, if I was being tried as a prisoner I would be satisfied to have the justice of the sentence left in the hands of either, and not have it brought before the Ministry at all.  We know there is a natural tendency for people to be merciful, but I believe that the Army Authorities who have tried the particular cases in question are the best authority to deal with such a matter.  I do not see why the signature of the President and the whole Ministry should be required.  They have now added the regulations, which certainly satisfies me.  They are that these cases should be laid before this Dáil, who will have the power to say what penalty is to be inflicted for any breach of these.  That seems to preserve our authority over the penalty to be inflicted, and unless this Dáil thinks that some of these regulations cover an offence for which the death penalty should not be inflicted, the Dáil can cut it out.  Therefore, it seems to me that if the Ministry would accept this amendment, that no such death penalty should be inflicted, it is quite clear that they do not want to set up Military Courts except in areas where they are really wanted.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>There are several parts in this amendment, and the question of the distinction with regard to the death penalty between 1, 2, 3, and 4 hardly arises at all, now.  In so far as No. 4&mdash;&ldquo;The breach of any general order or regulation made by the Army Authorities&rdquo;&mdash;is transferred, I understand, to the very end of the resolution, and carries with it the amendment to be moved by the Minister for Home Affairs, providing that any such order or regulation shall be laid on the Table of the Dáil, and the Dáil shall define the punishment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="917" />
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>I am quite willing.  I understand the pledge was the President of the Ministry.  I think it may be just as well the Commander-in-Chief.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>I am not referring to the question of the counter-signature at all.  I am discussing the nature of the penalty.  The nature of the penalty does not arise now, in so far as it will come on at the end, and there need not be a discussion on it at all now.  The next point in the amendment, as I understand it, is, if the death penalty is inflicted by a Court Martial is there to be a counter-signature, and, if so, by whom?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand the pledge was that it would be the President or the Minister for Defence.  So long as there was some person, I think it would be an advantage certainly.  A pledge was given, but it was only for the sake of putting it into effect that I brought it up here.  I suggest it might be two members of the Army Council, without mentioning any names.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment is therefore altered.  We have not yet been supplied with any copies of the amendment.</P>
      <P>The amendment was handed in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment proposed is to add certain words to the end of Clause 3, Section (<i>b</i>).  The Clerk will read the words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CLERK of the DAIL CLERK of the DAIL">
      <NameTxt>CLERK of the DAIL:</NameTxt>
      <P>To add the following words: &ldquo;Provided that no such sentence of death be executed except under the counter-signature of two Members of the Army Council.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>The amendment was put and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards the remainder of the amendment, there is a question of scheduling certain areas by the Commander-in-Chief.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>The Commander-in-Chief's point was that at the present moment it might be necessary to schedule the whole of the areas in command.  Then they would be so scheduled, and as it became possible in one area after another to set up Civil Courts, <Col N="918" /> we would be informed of that, and so as the Legislature here, we would know what was being done, and would have an intelligent interest in the progress of the setting up of these Courts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to that I have only to say that Civil Courts, of a kind, will be set up very rapidly, practically throughout the whole country, but these Civil Courts will not be of the kind that could deal adequately or reliably with the class of offences set out in this resolution; and, giving the Army this particular task does not mean that in no area in which these Military Courts sit will there be a civil jurisdiction of any kind.  There will be the ordinary civil jurisdiction for the ordinary offences, and concurrently with it there must be in many places Military Courts also.  The people that I propose, from my Department, to send out to the country, in place of the British R.M.'s that have been withdrawn, will not have a jurisdiction that would enable them to deal with those people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Then they would be scheduled as areas within the meaning of the phrase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>I will ask the Clerk to read the Amendment with regard to the Scheduling of Areas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="CLERK of the DAIL CLERK of the DAIL">
      <NameTxt>CLERK of the DAIL:</NameTxt>
      <P>To add the following words:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Provided further that such Military Courts be set up within the area scheduled, from time to time, by the Minister for Defence.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a last matter of the removal of prisoners from one area to another.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>The last of that is conscquential on the loss of the third.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>That is therefore withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Four is withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>In addition to amendment 5, standing in the <Col N="919" /> name of Deputy Gavan Duffy, I have received an amendment from him which, I think, properly goes before the one that is actually on the paper.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose to move the omission from the paragraph of the words, &ldquo;whether within or without the area of jurisdiction of the Government,&rdquo; and the words &ldquo;within or without the area aforesaid.&rdquo;  This is the Spitzbergen part of the resolution, and we have had no explanation from the Government of the necessity for it.  We do not know where this desert island is, we do not know when this new Armada is setting out.  It does seem a little odd for the Free State, before it is born, to start colonisation. Strange things happen in our days. I think this thing does not need any speech; it is obviously the wrong thing. Before we are invited to agree that captive Irishmen be sent to some island in a latitude we know not, and under a flag we know not, we must have some very good reason from the Ministry.  I do not know what reason would be good enough to justify such a procedure, but until we hear the reason we cannot say. It is conceivable there may be some reason to justify it.  At all events what is proposed is to deport prisoners and to give the Ministry general powers to deport them, and all we are told is that they are in negotiation for the acquisition of an island.  I suggest that is not sufficient for the Dáil to act upon. Let the Government tell us, frankly, what they mean, where is the island, what class of prisoner is going to be sent there, with whom are they negotiating, and above all what is the justification for this extraordinary procedure, and what jurisdiction will Dáil Eireann have over the gentlemen whom you relegate to a desert island, perhaps St. Helena.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>One would think from the speech of Deputy Gavan Duffy that he had just returned from the Continent and that he had very little knowledge, or appreciation, of the things that have been taking place in this country, for some time back.  He does not remember for instance, what took place in Dundalk, where there was a large concentration of prisoners, and those prisoners were released, and it took quite a lot of time, and the loss of <Col N="920" /> very valuable lives, before that particular area was again under effective control by the Government's forces.  Now the bald fact is that a large concentration of prisoners within the country is a menace, and the bald fact is, that a large concentration of prisoners in an area near Dublin is a standing menace to the State and the Government, and to the capital of the country.  There are probably more arms in the possession of the Irregulars than they have men to use them, and an escape, or a release, on a large scale, and the sudden arming of the released prisoners, may very materially affect the military position. That is, as it seems to me, a lay-man&mdash;for my period of service in the army was very short, though very brilliant&mdash;certainly the position.  Now, as to the island, granted that it is an island, I don't see that it makes very much difference where it is.  If it were a peninsula, the narrow neck running out from the mainland might be supposed to transmit certain sentimental thought waves that would keep the prisoners comforted; but, granted that it is an island, I think it does not matter whether that island is five, seven, or seventy miles from the Irish coast.  Granted that the climate is good, and that the conditions there are reasonable&mdash;and it is the intention of the Government to see that they are reasonable&mdash;I think that the curiosity that arises as to the exact latitude, or the exact whereabouts, of this island is to be deprecated at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, the British tried this game with the Egyptians, and sent them to Malta, but they had very soon to send them back again.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeGDuffy" hpid="Mr. GAVAN DUFFY Mr. GAVAN DUFFY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. GAVAN DUFFY:</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to move as an amendment at the end of Clause 3, Section (<i>c</i>) to add the words &ldquo;Provided that every such prisoner shall be considered and treated as a prisoner of war.&rdquo;  The Ministry will, perhaps, do me the justice to admit that this is not an afterthought.  I have been hoping that they would take this course from the early stages of the war, and I hope to hear to-day that the Minister for Defence agrees with this proposal.  I propose to detain the Dáil very shortly on this amendment, because I think it is quite clear, without argument, that the prisoners <Col N="921" /> should be treated as prisoners of war.  There is good authority for that proposal&mdash;not an authority binding upon this Dáil, but an authority entitled to the greatest respect from this Dáil. An International Conference of the Red Cross was held at Geneva last year, and it was attended by delegates of distinction and eminence from fifty different countries, and they passed a certain resolution, after certain questions had been examined by special Committees.  One of these questions was the treatment of persons taken prisoners or interned as political suspects in time of civil war.  I have the resolution here.  The countries represented included South Africa, Argentina, Australia, Germany, Great Britain, Canada, Denmark, Spain, Greece, Hungary, India, Italy, Japan, New Zealand, Norway, Holland, Poland, Roumania, Russia, Servia, Sweden, Switzerland, Czecho-Slovakia, and Turkey.  After examination, as a result of the report of the Committee they resolved as follows:&mdash;&ldquo;This 10th Conference deplores the boundless suffering to which prisoners and internees are sometimes subjected in countries where civil war is raging, and it holds that persons imprisoned for reasons of State in time of civil war ought to be considered and treated by the belligerent parties as prisoners of war, that is to say, according to the principle of The Hague Convention of 1907.&rdquo;  I have tried to give as accurate a rendering as I can of that resolution, the original of which is in French.  And I think there can be no dispute as to the meaning of the text, of which the French print is in the hands of the Minister for Foreign Affairs.  It clearly means and recognises that there are two classes of persons whom you imprison in time of civil war&mdash;the soldiers whom you capture and the civilians whom you think it necessary to intern&mdash; and this Conference considers that both classes, whom they bring together in the French phrase I have tried to render as persons imprisoned for reasons of the State, should be treated as prisoners of war.  I may be told, and perhaps will be told, by somebody that the prisoners taken in fact get as good treatment as prisoners of war.  I do not know whether they do or not.  But I think it is important that there should be a definite code governing their treatment.  There is a definite code governing the treatment of <Col N="922" /> prisoners of war.  I think, further, that even if the treatment accorded to the present prisoners is prisoner-of-war treatment you ought to give them that status which they have claimed from the beginning, and I do not think it is any answer to say &ldquo;Oh, they are outlaws and rebels.&rdquo;  You have here an expression of International opinion from persons familiar with war because of their war work, not binding I agree, but entitled to the greatest respect, and showing that people in the position of the Irregulars ought to be treated as prisoners of war. And to grant that treatment to them by naming them as prisoners of war would remove the grievance which they feel.  Surely it cannot be the policy at the moment of the Government to increase bitterness over questions of that sort when there are so many questions about which people may disagree more reasonably.  There is no reason for discrimination here against these prisoners. They are our fellow-countrymen; and let me remind you that in the American Civil War, great as the bitterness was, the Yankees decided that they would give the Southerners the treatment of prisoners of war, though I believe at the beginning they did not recognise them.  If this wretched affair goes on long enough we too shall have in the end to do that. Why not do it now?  Obviously it is right here if it is right in the view of those forty-nine or fifty countries I have cited.  Why should it not be right in Ireland?  I say one thing more.  Prisoner-of-war treatment is drastic treatment, but it is just; it is not any favour you are conferring by conferring prisoner-of-war treatment, unless for the civil internee, you consider the conferring of the status as a favour.  It is drastic treatment.  Nobody knows that better than the Minister for Defence, but it is treatment under a definite code, which anybody can see for himself&mdash;a definite code open to the public and based upon well recognised principles of justice.  I suggest that the Government will be putting itself right in the eyes of the country over this matter if it takes what is the better stand, and says we will agree to give prisoner of war treatment to these men.  I hope the Minister for Defence will support this amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to support this amendment.  Let us just examine <Col N="923" /> what the original position was.  The men whom the Ministry now refuse to regard as Prisoners of War were in military occupation of the larger section of what is now known as the Free State, when the Four Courts were attacked.  They had advanced, mile by mile, in order to reconquer that territory in the interest of the Free State.  If they were in military possession, and military means were used against them, why does the Ministry now stick its head in the sand and refuse to recognise them as Prisoners of War? There is no other status possible for them and you will have to recognise that sooner or later, and you may as well do it sooner, and the sooner you do it the better.  It may be hard because they are just our own countrymen; but, I advise the Ministry to look back, a few months, at the time when they were dealing with the English.  The English did not want to treat their prisoners as Prisoners of War, but as murderers and criminals, and the arch murderer was Dick Mulcahy.  If a man is to be executed for an ambush at the present time, is it not as wrong now as it was then?  If an ambush is wrong in the streets of Dublin to-day, it was wrong when Dick Mulcahy ordered it.  If you treat them as Prisoners of War you cannot execute them.  The Minister for Defence dis tinguishes them in three different classes &mdash;Politicians, Criminals and Soldiers.  I take that as correct.  Criminals you can deal with in a criminal manner, but the backbone of the men opposed to you are the soldiers of the former Republic, and we are the traitors to that Republic. Those who voted for the Treaty were traitors to the Republic.  We are the rebels, and they are the patriots.  I voted for the Treaty, and I submit I swallowed my oath, and every one of you who voted for the Treaty swallowed your oaths for the Republic.  Do not disguise the fact, and do not take refuge behind&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>This matter is not relevant to what is under discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. P. McCARTAN Dr. P. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. P. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit these men should be treated as Prisoners of War.  It is the only way you can treat them and they deserve it.  They fought. The only ones deserving consideration fought well for Ireland and deserve more from Ireland, and deserve other consideration from their own comrades in this Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="924" />
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General R. MULCAHY General R. MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General R. MULCAHY:</NameTxt>
      <P>When we were dealing with the English we had a very, very small percentage of that material which it is wished now to get, called Prisoners of War, giving us a helping hand.  And if we do divide the people against us into three classes, the percentage of No. 3 class, that we are dealing with at the present moment, is a percentage that is a very, very high one. You would not be dealing fairly with this country, or with the people of the country, if at this particular moment, before you have been able to sift the material that you have and divide these different classes from one another, you threw over all that material that we have got in prisons in Ireland the grand high cloak of a prisoner of war.  We have lost, as I said yesterday, the sense of the meaning of words to-day, and words that it was proper for us to use with regard to certain people and certain actions, it is not proper for us to use them in the changed circumstances.  I do not approve of this amendment, and I am not prepared to throw over the material which is inside the prisons now, and which is working outside the prisons, the cloak of prisoners of war.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. E. BLYTHE Mr. E. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. BLYTHE:</NameTxt>
      <P>All through we have changed &ldquo;Army Authorities&rdquo; to &ldquo;Army Council,&rdquo; and then in one or two places we have made further verbal changes, as, for instance, in the second paragraph, which reads towards the end of it &ldquo;that the Army Authorities should have power to detain in places within or without.&rdquo;  We want to make the change &ldquo;that the Army Council should have power to authorise the detention in places, whether within or without.&rdquo; Those are consequential verbal changes of the word &ldquo;Authority&rdquo; to &ldquo;Council.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The change has been made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE:</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, then in the next paragraph&mdash;&ldquo;Whereas the Government, recognising the force of such representation, has sanctioned the doing `under the authority of the Army Council,' instead of by the `Army Authorities.&rdquo;'</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHayes" hpid="AN CEANN COMHAIRLE Michael Hayes">
      <NameTxt>AN CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>That is only a verbal change.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE:</NameTxt>
      <P>They are entirely consequential. Then in Paragraph C&mdash;<Col N="925" />&ldquo;The removal under the Army Council of all or any person taken prisoner.&rdquo;  I now move that Clause 3 as amended be put and inserted.</P>
      <P>The Clause as amended was adopted.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="THE PRESIDENT'S" RHead="MOTION. - CLAUSE 4">
    <Title>THE PRESIDENT'S MOTION. - CLAUSE 4.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>I now move No. 4.  &ldquo;Now this Dáil, being of opinion, that the doing by or under the authority of the Army Council of the several matters aforesaid, is a matter of military necessity, doth hereby ratify and approve of the sanction given by the Government, and of the doing by, or under the authority of the Army Council of all or any of the acts, and matters aforesaid, provided however that as regards such general order or regulation as aforesaid, the same shall specify the maximum penalty which may be inflicted for any breach thereof, and shall be laid on the table of this Dáil and shall take effect on the expiration of four days thereafter, during which this Dáil shall be in session, unless this Dáil shall have previously passed a resolution disallowing the same.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DarrellFiggis" hpid="Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. DARRELL FIGGIS:</NameTxt>
      <P>My amendment to that reads:&mdash;&ldquo;And it confirms such sanction for a further period of fourteen days from the date of the passing of this resolution, subject to the renewal of such sanction for further periods of time, in no one case to exceed fourteen days, as and when the Army Council shall show cause on a report to the Dáil on the state of the country under these powers hereby granted to it.&rdquo;  It may be more desirable to make the period one month, if found agreeable, and I don't propose that we should be put under the necessity of going through this lengthy debate every time this comes up.  It would automatically arise and I would merely point out <Col N="926" /> to the Ministry that this is merely a form that is adopted under such circumstances in all legislature so as to keep the matter within some control of the legislature, if only as a matter of form.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. BLYTHE Mr. BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. BLYTHE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The amendment moved by Deputy Figgis is not accepted, and its rejection by the movers of the resolution is not due to the fact that a period of 14 days is specified. It would exist just as strongly if the period were double or treble that time. The position is that a state of armed rebellion exists, and, in fact, all these powers that are asked for in this resolution for the Army already exist for the Army.  And it is merely so that each Deputy here may realise the position, and may take what is properly his share of the responsibilities of the time. It is merely to secure that this resolution is brought forward at all.  When the state of armed rebellion ends these powers, or the exercise of these powers by the Army Council, naturally lapses. That is the position, and to put on an amendment of this kind, that this was something that the Parliament was giving, and would take away, or reconsider in fourteen days, or some specified period, presents a false picture of the situation, the situation being that the life of the country is challenged, and the existence of the Parliament is challenged, that its authority and jurisdiction are challenged.  And until it is reasserted, and until the life of the country is safe, then the Army has these powers automactically and apart from any Act of this Parliament, and must have these powers if the State has to live and in every State would have these powers quite apart from a specific resolution of legislature.</P>
      <P>The amendment was put, and declared lost.</P>
      <P>The resolution, as amended, was then put and declared carried.  It read as follows:&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">
            </entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">TRANSLATION.</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>(1)  DE BHRÍ gur chuir an Rialtas mar dhualgas ar an Arm an pobal do chosaint ó bhaol agus dea-órdú do bhunú arís ar fnaid na tíre agus gur chuireadar de chúram ar an Arm údarás an Rialtais do dhaingniú I ngach páirt den tír ina bhfuiltear ag cur I gcoinne an údaráis sin le fóiréigean.</entry>
            <entry>&ldquo;(1)  WHEREAS the Government has entrusted to the Army the duty of securing the public safety and restoring order throughout the country and has placed on the Army the responsibility for the establishment of the authority of the Government in all parts of the country in which that authority is challenged by force:</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <Col N="927" />&ldquo;,(2)  AGUS DE BHRÍ gur chuir Comhairle an Airm in úil don Rialtas go bhfuil sé riachtanach chun an dualgas agus an cúram do cuireadh ortha do chólíona le héifeacht go mbeadh comhacht ag Comhairle an Airm chun Cúirteanna no Coistí Airm do chur ar bun ag a mbeadh lán-chomhacht chun cúiseanna do scrúdú agus daoine do phionósú ar iad d'fháil ciontach I ngíomhartha do thiocfadh trasna ar no do mhoilleodh údarás an Rialtais do lán-dhaingniú agus go mbeadh comhacht ag Comhairle an Airm údarás do thabhairt le daoine atá I mbraighdeanas Airm ag Comhairle an Airm do chimeád in áiteanna atá laistigh no lasmuich de líomatáiste dlí an Rialtais agus fós go mbeadh comracht acu deighleáil agus seilbh in airm theine do rialú.</entry>
            <entry>
              <Col N="928" />&ldquo;(2)  AND WHEREAS the Army Council has represented to the Government that in order to discharge effectively the duty and responsibility so placed on them it is essential that the Army Council should have power to set up Military Courts or Committees with full powers of enquiring into charges and inflicting punishments on persons found guilty of acts calculated to interfere with or delay the effective establishment of the authority of the Government, and that the Army Council should have power to authorise the detention in places whether within or without the area of the jurisdiction of the Government of persons in Military custody and power to control the dealing in and possession of firearms;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&ldquo;(3)  AGUS DE BHRÍ gur soiléir don Rialtas fírinne na faisnéise sin agus gur thoiligheadar go ndéanfaí fé údarás Chomhairle an Airm gach no aon cheann de sna nithe agus na rudaí seo leanas.</entry>
            <entry>&ldquo;(3)  AND WHEREAS the Government, recognising the force of such representations, has sanctioned the doing under the authority of the Army Council of all or any of the following matters and things:</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>(a)  Cúirteanna no Coistí Airm do chur ar bun chun cúiseanna I gcoinne daoine I dtaobh aon cheann de sna cionta a luaidhtear 'na dhiaidh seo do sgrúdú ar choiníoll, amh, go mbeidh mar bhall de gach Cúirt no Coiste Airm dá leithéid duine ambain ar a luighead a ainmneoidh an t-Aire un Chosaint agus a dheimhneoidh an Dlí-Oigigeach bheith 'na dhuine go bhfuil eolas agus taithí dlí aige.</entry>
            <entry>(a)  The setting up of Military Courts or Committees for the enquiring into charges against persons in respect of any of the offences hereinafter mentioned provided however that every such Military Court or Committee shall include as a member thereof at least one person nominated by the Minister of Defence and certified by the Law Officer to be a person of legal knowledge and experience;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>(b)  Na Cúirteanna no Coistí Airm sin do sgrúdú chás daoine go bhfuil aon cheann de sna cionta so leanas curtha 'na leith sé sin le rá:&mdash;</entry>
            <entry>(b)  The enquiry by such Military Courts or Committees into the cases of persons charged with any of the offences following that is to say&mdash;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>(1)  Bheith páirteach I no do chabhrú le no do chur suas chun aon ionsuidhe do dhéanamh ar no fórsa d'úsáid I gcoinne an Airm Náisiúnta.</entry>
            <entry>(1)  Taking part in or aiding or abetting any attack upon or using force against the National Forces;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>(2)  Creach tóiteán lot gabháil seilbh no aistriú no díobháil mhídhleathach do déanamh do mhaoin phuiblí no phríobháideach.</entry>
            <entry>(2)  Looting arson destruction seizure unlawful possession or removal of or damage to any public or private property;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
(3)  Bheith I seilbh gan údarás chóir aon bhoma no aon rud de nádúir bhoma no aon dynamite, gelignite, no aon stuff phléasgach eile no aon phiostal, rifle, gunna no <Col N="929" />arm teine eile no arm marbhthach no aon lón d'aon arm teine dá leithéid.</entry>
            <entry>
(3)  Having possession without proper authority of any bomb or article in the nature of a bomb or any dynamite gelignite or other explosive substance or any <Col N="930" />revolver rifle gun or other firearm or lethal weapon or any ammunition for such firearm;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>(4)  Aon ordú no riail ghenerálta a dhéanfaidh Comhairle an Airm do bhrise agus na Cúirteanna no Coistí Airm sin do thabhairt bhreith bháis no bhreith dhaorphríosúin ar feadh aon téarma no bhreith phríosúin ar feadh aon téarma no do chur fíneála d'aon mhéid le no gan phríosún ar aon duine a ciontófar ag aon Chúirt no Choiste mar sin in aon cheann de sna cionta roimhráite.  Ar choiníoll ná cuirfear aon bhreith bháis mar sin I bhfeidhm ach fé cho-shighniú dhá bhall de Chomhairle an Airm.</entry>
            <entry>(4)  The breach of any general order or regulation made by the Army Council and the infliction by such Military Courts or Committees of the punishment of death or of penal servitude for any period or of imprisonment for any period or of a fine for any amount either with or without imprisonment on any person found guilty by such Court or Committee of any of the offences aforesaid.  Provided that no such sentence of death be executed except under the countersignature of two members of the Army Council;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>(c)  Fé údarás Chomhairle an Airm gach no aon duine atá tógtha no cimeádtha 'na phríosúnach ag an Arm Náisiúnta d'aistriú go dtí aon áit no áiteanna laistigh no lasmuich de liómatáiste dlí an Rialtais agus aon duine mar sin do chimeád no do chur don phríosún in aon áit no áiteanna laistigh no lasmuich den líomatáiste dlí roimh-ráite.</entry>
            <entry>(c)  The removal under authority of the Army Council of any person taken prisoner arrested or detained by the National Forces to any place or places whether within or without the area of jurisdiction of the Government and the detention or imprisonment of any such persons in any place or places within or without the area aforesaid;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>(d)  Díol seilbh aistriú agus deighleáil I bpiostail riflí gunnaí agus airm theine eile do rialú agus do riara.</entry>
            <entry>(d)  The regulation and control of the sale possession transfer of and dealing in revolvers rifles guns and other firearms;</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&ldquo;(4)  ANOIS deimhnigheann agus molann an Dáil seo déanamh gach no aon cheann de sna gníomhartha agus na nithe roimh-ráite ag no fé údarás Chomhairle an Airm agus an cead ata tugtha ag an Rialtas uatha mar gurb é tuairim na Dála gur riachtanas Airm déanamh na nithe uile roimh-ráite ag no fé údarás Chomhairle an Airm.  Ar choiníoll amh maidir le n-a leithéid d'órdú no de riail ghenearalta mar roimh-ráite go luaidhfear ann an pionós is mó is féidir do chur ar dhuine as ucht a bhriste agus go leagfar é ar bhord na Dála so agus go mbeidh feidhm aige ar chríochnú cheithre lá ar a mbeidh an Dáil I siosóin 'na dhiaidh sin mara mbeidh rún curtha I bhfeidhm ag an nDáil seo roimhe sin á chur ar ceal.</entry>
            <entry>&ldquo;(4)  NOW this Dáil being of opinion that the doing by or under the authority of the Army Council of the several matters aforesaid is a matter of Military necessity doth hereby ratify and approve of the sanction given by the Government and of the doing by or under the Authority of the Army Council of all or any of the acts and matters aforesaid. Provided however that as regards such general order or regulation as aforesaid the same shall specify the maximum penalty which may be inflicted for any breach thereof and shall be laid on the table of this Dáil and shall take effect on the expiration of four days thereafter during which this Dáil shall be in session unless this Dáil shall have previously passed a resolution disallowing the same.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&ldquo;Baile Atha Cliath an 28adh lá so de Mheadhon Foghmhair, 1922.&rdquo;</entry>
            <entry>&ldquo;Dublin this 28th day of September, 1922.&rdquo;</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>A division was demanded by Mr. William O'Brien.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="931" />
      <Col N="932" /> On a division the President's motion was declared carried, the voting being 47 For and 15 Against.:&mdash;</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Tá.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Níl.</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Liam T. Mac Cosgair.<br />Donchadh Ó Gúaire.<br />Uaitear Mac Cúmhaill.<br />Seán Ó Maolruaidh.<br />Micheál Ó hAonghusa.<br />Domhnall Ó Mocháin.<br />Seán Ó hAodha.<br />Séamus Breathnach.<br />Pádraig Mag Ualghairg.<br />Deasmhúmhain Mac Gearailt.<br />Seán Ó Ruanaidh.<br />Micheál de Duram.<br />Seán Mac Garaidh.<br />Risteárd Ó Máolchatha.<br />Pilib Mac Cosgair.<br />Micheál de Staineas.<br />Seosamh Mag Craith.<br />Domhnall Mac Carthaigh.<br />Maolmhuire Mac Eochadha.<br />Earnán Altun.<br />Sir Séamus Craig.<br />Gearóid Mac Giobuin.<br />Liam Thrift.<br />Seosamh Ó Faóileachain.<br />Seoirse Mac Niocaill.<br />Piaras Béaslaí.<br />Séamus Ó Cruadhláoich.<br />Criostóir Ó Broin.<br />Risteard Mac Liam.<br />Cáoimhghín Ó hUigín.<br />Proinsias Bulfin.<br />Tomás Mac Artuir.<br />Séamus Ó Dóláin.<br />Aindriu Ó Laimhín.<br />Risteard Ó hAodha.<br />Liam Ó hAodha.<br />Éamon Ó Dúgáin.<br />Peadar Ó hAodha.<br />Séamus Ó Murchadhá.<br />Liam Mac Sioghaird.<br />Alasdair Mac Cába.<br />Tomás Ó Domhnaill.<br />Earnan de Blaghd.<br />Uinseann de Faoite.<br />Domhnall Ó Broin.<br />Séamus de Burca.<br />Micheál Ó Dubhghaill.</entry>
            <entry>Pádraig Ó Gamhna.<br />Tomás de Nógla.<br />Riobard Ó Deághaidh.<br />Tomás Mac Eoin.<br />Liam Ó Briain.<br />Tomás Ó Conaill.<br />Aodh Ó Culachain.<br />Séamus Eabhroid.<br />Liam Ó Daimhin.<br />Cathal Ó Seanain.<br />Seán Buitléir.<br />Nioclas Ó Faoláin.<br />Domhnall Ó Muirgheasa.<br />Risteard Mac Fheorais.<br />Domhnall Ó Dubhghaill.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="MOTION&mdash;MINISTER" RHead="FOR HOME AFFAIRS">
    <Title>MOTION&mdash;MINISTER FOR HOME AFFAIRS.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="KevinChristopher" hpid="Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. KEVIN O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a motion in my name on the Agenda, but it is rather late in the day to start a discussion on that particular matter, and we are, so to speak, absolutely in your hands.  It is a choice between my motion and a couple of articles of the Constitution, or taking Dr. McCartan's peace motion.  And as between those three we leave it entirely to the Assembly to say.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="AN LEAS CEANN COMHAIRLE AN LEAS CEANN COMHAIRLE">
      <NameTxt>AN LEAS CEANN COMHAIRLE:</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that Dr. McCartan's motion will not come on until 7 o'clock, and you have threequarters of an hour then.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it this is a sovereign Assembly, and we can take anything we like.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamOBrien1922" hpid="Mr. WILLIAM O'BRIEN Mr. WILLIAM O'BRIEN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. WILLIAM O'BRIEN:</NameTxt>
      <P>So long as it does not disagree with you.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>We could go ahead with this motion about the Constitution, or about Civil Administration, or any other thing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="933" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not know what was the idea of pressing forward a discussion for Civil Administration in particular.  I gathered that it was expected that it would be rather a general discussion on matters affecting civil life, and that a day was promised.  I took it that in the minds of the Ministers as well as the Members a longer time than threequarters of an hour would be necessary.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>That was our intention too.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it that then the discussion on the matter of Civil Administration is deferred to another day.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, in view of the fact that we meet five days this week, and that the general understanding was that we should adjourn at 7 instead of 8.30, as in the Standing Orders.  We would be willing to take up this resolution now, if it meets with the approval of the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>Very well.  I will move it now.  Perhaps a discussion like this to advocate a Truce is unpopular in the Dáil, but I would like the Members to think over it very seriously and not to reject it lightly.  I know that some men have been anxious for peace, and I submit that the Government have been anxious for peace all along and wanted to avoid war.  I think it was the general knowledge that the Government wanted to avoid civil war which was responsible for Civil War, paradoxical as that may seem.  I think I am right in saying that they still want peace, and Parliament and we all want peace.  There are two ways of securing peace.  You can have peace by extermination, or by negotiation. It is easier by negotiation than by war, because it will not take so much time.  I know it will be said &ldquo;it is useless to negotiate with these men.&rdquo; It will be said &ldquo;we have negotiated before and failed&rdquo;; but I am an optimist and I would say try, try again.  Examine the situation and consider the individuals on the opposite side. Take, for instance, Tom Hales.  He was one of the five officers who signed the agreement for the Truce.  Liam Lynch left Dublin intending not to take any part in the fight at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardJamesMulcahy" hpid="General R. MULCAHY General R. MULCAHY">
      <NameTxt>General R. MULCAHY:</NameTxt>
      <P>He did not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="934" />
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I do not know these men.  I only met Hales once.  The men who have been in negotiation with them know more about their character than I do.  I am only looking at it in a detached kind of way.  I am inclined to think that he did not believe very strongly in civil war when he left Dublin, and further that he does not believe very strongly in civil war, even now.  I quite frankly admit that it may be of no use trying to negotiate peace, but it may be worth a trial.  I do not think a truce could affect the military situation, and here I am willing to bow to the Commander-in-Chief.  The Army is in possession of all the territory&mdash;as far as an Army can be&mdash;of Ireland, and a truce for two weeks, at least, I think cannot increase the strength or the military position of the Irregulars.  I do not think the Government can very well be affected in any way, and the only hope is that it may bring peace, and I hope it will bring peace.  Possibly it may not.  It is worth a trial, and it is better at all events than putting into force the resolutions that have just been adopted.  It is very easy to execute men, perhaps, and I am inclined to think&mdash;but I do not know as I have not been talking to the Commander-in-Chief for a long time&mdash;but I am inclined to think that he does not intend to execute men at the present time.  It would be the last thing he would like to do.  I am convinced of that.  But if this thing goes on, the force of circumstances will compel him to enforce the decree you have just adopted.  To avoid all that I think a truce and getting the men who are in arms against the Government together and getting a peace spirit created would tend to bring about this. Some may consider it a humiliation for the Government to arrange terms of a peace with these men.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>No, not terms of peace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very glad to hear the President say so, and it is a good sign.  If there are any Deputies who would think it a humiliation&mdash;it was a humiliation for England, for instance, to agree to a truce with us some years ago. They spoke of us as murderers, and we spoke of these men as looters, and I forget the rest of it&mdash;not very pleasant terms anyway.  We do not mind these <Col N="935" /> terms, however.  They are our countrymen, whether good or bad.  They are what the civilisation of this country has made them.  They are our countrymen, and it is no humiliation if we can bring peace to the country.  It is the only way you can separate the criminals from the men who are actuated by high motives. It will not affect the military situation, I submit, and I submit also it is no humiliation. England had to do it, and it was not any humiliation for her.  The Americans, as has been said here before, during the American Civil War did not want to recognise the Southern States as enemies or belligerents, but finally they had to do it, and they were all good friends afterwards. If we could settle this trouble in an amicable way and be good friends afterwards, so much the better.  There has been bitterness enough in the country as a result of this, and the marvel is that it has not been worse.  If it can be stopped now, I think it would prevent it becoming much worse than it is at the present time.  Now peace, everyone will agree, is the urgent thing.  The Minister for Defence referred to the situation in the South yesterday, I think it was, in his speech, and he said the railway lines were torn up, and that that interfered with the economic business of the country.  The quickest way to bring about peace is by negotiations.  When the Truce comes into operation, reconstruction begins immediately, and the probability is that once the order to cease fire is given, there may never be another shot fired by Irishmen against Irishmen.  In dealing with Irishmen, you can always deal with them better by reasoning than by bullying. We saw the English here, the Aberdeens and the Birrells, who gave us plenty of palaver.  They were successful, more or less, and it was the types that came here and shouted about swords and prisons and the rest of it that were failures.  I think if we talked to these men who are in opposition on patriotic lines, it would be best.  The best of them, the backbone of them, the men who count are just as patriotic as any men in this Dáil.  I still maintain you can deal with these men's patriotism and reason.  If you had the opportunity to come together and discuss the situation, the possibilities of peace would be greater.  I ask the Dáil seriously to consider giving this a trial. It may not result in peace, but I think it is worth a trial.  I do not see that it <Col N="936" /> can interfere with the military situation in any way.  I would like to hear the Commander-in-Chief's views.  He may not have much faith in the proposal, as I know he has had much negotiation with these men, and may not have much belief in further negotiations, but it is better than forcing the resolution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NocholasFrancisPhela" hpid="Mr. N. PHELAN Mr. N. PHELAN">
      <NameTxt>Mr. N. PHELAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise to support the suggestion of Deputy Dr. McCartan because of what I have seen.  I represent a constituency which has suffered much, and as late as last week I happened to visit an area in which I found things that would touch any Irishman's heart. I do not wish to speak much on this suggestion, but I want to ask the Dáil to take into consideration that we are not now fighting the common enemy, and it is harder on us at present to realise the position of the country.  The Second Dáil disagreed on a political matter, which we all agree was a matter of life or death to the country, and that was the Treaty. We cannot say why men who are now leaders of the Anti-Treaty party disagreed on that, but we know that the men in the country at the present moment do not know how the Dáil is working.  We have a Propaganda Department at the head of affairs, which is giving out certain information and is, as a matter of fact, trying to blind us every day of the week. That is all the people know.  I certainly believe the men who are fighting are sincere and believe they are doing the best for the country.  A truce at the present moment will not show weakness on behalf of this Government, but will show that the strongest man is always the most generous.  The Government has stated on several occasions that it would not close the door against peace, and I hope they will not.  If the Government opposes the suggestion for peace, this proposal will be defeated.  I hope and trust when we realise it is Irishmen we are fighting, and now when it is proposed to pass a particular document that will take away liberties from us and that we know must pass in some form or other, I think I am expressing the feelings of the men on the opposite side in saying that they do not want it to come into operation.  Every man knows his hardest duty is shooting a man in cold blood.  If there is any possible chance of getting away from that terrible act, we will try to do so.  For that reason I would ask the <Col N="937" /> Government to accept the suggestion, and I urge it on the Members of this Dáil who know the situation.  These people are going to be reasonable, and the Government, if it fails in its efforts for peace will have the full support of this Dáil and the country in carrying out their programme.  The peace efforts made on a previous occasion were made by the second Dáil, which represented only one political party, that split into two.  At the present moment we have a Dáil representing every interest in Ireland, and I certainly say this Dáil will have a better voice in making peace; and I hope it will never be said again that the peace negotiations were secret, but that they were open negotiations by this Dáil.  If the negotiations fail we will know who will be the cause of the failure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickGaffnet" hpid="Mr. P. GAFFNEY Mr. P. GAFFNEY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. GAFFNEY:</NameTxt>
      <P>I rise to support the motion of the previous speaker.  In doing so, I believe the time is ripe.  I believe that in this matter there is every possible chance of a settlement being adjusted, whereby every political belief in the country will come to this Dáil and do its best so that the Government of the country can be carried out in accordance with the full wishes of the Irish people.  I do not think that this is the time to say very much, but I believe that deep down in the heart of every Irishman and Irishwoman, fighting against one another at present, there is a longing for an honourable peace. Whatever has happened in the past, we should be prepared to cast aside and all should try, each in his way, to co-operate for the better government of the country. I heartily support the remarks of Deputy McCartan and Deputy Phelan.  I had intended to bring forward such a proposal as this.  Looking at the matter calmly and dispassionately, I do believe that there is a deepening feeling throughout Ireland for peace, and that the time for it is now ripe.  I believe that if by this Dáil there were appointed a certain number of members representative of the Government benches, the Farmers, the Workers, and the Independents here, that the result would be a truce followed by a peace, which all of us would be thankful for, and that will place our land in the proud position of&mdash;&ldquo;First flower of the earth and first gem of the sea.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterHughes" hpid="Mr. P. HUGHES Mr. P. HUGHES">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. HUGHES:</NameTxt>
      <P>I may say I did not intend to interpose in this discussion, <Col N="938" /> but I wish to say that there is nobody in this Dáil would wish to see peace as much as I would.  I desire to see peace as well as the bulk of the Dáil or any of the gentlemen who spoke from the Labour Benches.  At the same time if peace is to come, it should come in a generous, straightforward manner and not as a result of a truce for any length of time.  The Government has stated over and over again that they are anxious for peace.  These men can have peace to-morrow if they want it, but the conditions which they must fulfil are that they must lay down their arms and submit to this Parliament.  It is not very much indeed to ask any Irishman that he should submit to the authority of the elected representatives of the people of Ireland.  It is not our fault if the men who are bearing arms at the present time are not here to put their views before us.  It is their duty to be here, having accepted that duty and I believe under these circumstances that they are not sincere in asking for a general peace.  Now if that peace is to come soon, and I hope it will come soon, and that the resolution we have passed here will not ever have to be put into effect, for none of us wish that the blood of any Irishman should be shed as the result of this resolution, if these men who are out to destroy the economic life of the country cannot see what they are doing and pay no heed to the views of the public through the Representatives of this Dáil, lay down their arms, they will be treated as friends and as if they never took arms against this country or Parliament. Therefore I think the resolution proposed by Deputy McCartan is not the class of resolution which should come from this Dáil.  But if he puts forward a resolution which states these men should lay down their arms and come here to a free and unfettered Parliament I think this Dáil would accept it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamTCosgrave" hpid="The PRESIDENT The PRESIDENT">
      <NameTxt>The PRESIDENT:</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Peace offensive is not a very strong one, and I think that the real weakness in this Peace offensive is that no terms are given from those who are anxious to get Peace for the other side.  There is nobody in this Dáil, I believe, empowered to speak and say that for the other side they are in a position to give terms.  I do not think that there is any person <Col N="939" /> qualified to speak for those who are in arms against the National Forces at the present moment.  I think that will be admitted.  If, for instance, this Dáil were willing to send out a Peace Delegation, to whom are they to send it to?  Who are the responsible parties on the other side with whom they are to treat, and what are the terms on which you are going to treat?  The Dáil is perfectly entitled, and I will not stand in the way, nor will the Government stand in the way of any attempts towards making peace, but we are not entitled to make peace now in the same way as we were entitled to make it previous to the elections.  The Deputy who represents the same constituency as I do may not know what I said to the people or may not have heard it.  I said if I were elected again to this Dáil, and had any responsibility in the Government, that I was going to implement the Treaty, to do away with the dual Government, have but one army, suppress disorder, and have but one authority throughout the land.  The policy on which the Government is engaged is tending towards that end.  If it is possible to effect a Peace we are willing to-day to do it, but I am not authorised to go one step further than I have when I laid down that there must be obedience to the Parliament, and that order must be restored. If you can succeed in restoring order I am willing, as far as I am concerned, to give any other person that chance.  Personally I am satisfied you can only have peace on these terms. Now as regards the truce we have had a truce.  We had these peaceable conditions for six months.  Dr. McCartan spoke, and I think Members opposite know the effect of that false Treaty Truce.  Within six months, gentlemen on these benches know that after having the armed truce with those who are now fighting against us that Truce was broken and we were warned that that Truce would not operate as from a particular date.  There is, in my opinion, I hope I am wrong, one course open if you are to have an eventual peace, and that is to show you are determined to make a good peace when it is made, and that peace can only be laid on the fundamental provisions of our Constitution, that respect must be paid to the majority of the people's will. Any peace not based on this proposal <Col N="940" /> would be fatal, and might only encourage others in the Community to arm themselves for the purpose of holding up Government.  If there are Members of this Dáil who think that it is possible to make terms of peace, and to restore order, let them in God's name start about it at once.  But there is no use, in my opinion at any rate, in bringing forward these proposals here unless there is something behind them, and that the people who speak about it here are authorised to bring it forward on their behalf and unless there is a conception that these people are wrong.  We have heard of the statements of some of them to the effect that they thought they were beaten, but there is added to that statement, &ldquo;My God, if we won what would happen.&rdquo;  Supposing they had success and wiped out the National Army, where are they then?  Have they got the support of the people behind them, or would they get the support of the people if there were a General Election?  We know they would not, and while the Government is most anxious and do not want to humiliate those against them, and while we appreciate that there are many brave men amongst them who fought well during the late war whom we would be glad to welcome back as citizens of the country, we cannot deny that there are others amongst them who are unworthy.  If they show and acknowledge that they are on the wrong track and retrace their steps, we will not stand in their way.  Real peace is the intention of the Government policy in this matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say how greatly I appreciate the speech that the President has just made.  I think I can say I agree with every word of it. I believe, in the circumstances that face us, no one who has any regard to realities, and any regard to what is conceived to be democratic, but must say that peace can only be arrived at through a recognition that the position created by the Treaty must be accepted, that the Treaty position must be allowed to be worked.  It does not mean that every individual at present in revolt against the Treaty must formally accept it, but that he must relinquish his claim to resist it in arms.  That we subscribe to absolutely.  I had no notice, except a few minutes before coming into the Dáil <Col N="941" /> to-day, that such a resolution was to be proposed.  I think it might be very valuable that the Dáil could express itself freely in this way on this subject, and let it be understood by those in arms against the elected Government of the country, that there is now an opportunity to abide by the decision of the country, whether formally taken or not. It must be admitted that there was much informality about it.  But there is no one who has any regard for realities, but will admit frankly that the country takes the Treaty and says the Treaty must be worked.  There have been decisions taken to-day which I think should be allowed to remain in abeyance for a period to allow of an opportunity for the hopes of the Dáil to come into effect.  I do not know what is intended exactly by a Truce, I do not know how it is going to be made.  I think the President's position was a sound one, that so far as we know there is no one to whom an appeal could be made who could speak for the Republican Forces.  But having passed this resolution to-day, having made this gesture, if notice were given that it would only come into operation in fourteen days, and that in the meantime there was, say, a Committee appointed from various sections of the Dáil who would be empowered to, at least, enter into&mdash;I do not want to use the term negotiation &mdash;relationship&mdash;with whoever claims to speak on behalf of the opposition forces&mdash; the Irregulars&mdash;that, in itself, might lead to the possibility of a formal abdication of their position.  I hope that Members from various sections in the Dáil will express themselves on this matter, and that if anything arises out of this motion, we shall all be sincerely thankful for the occasion having been provided.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>A Chinn Chomhairle, in one sense this Government is in a most unfortunate position.  It is in the unfortunate position of having absolutely nothing to give away.  The things that we are fighting for are so sacred, so fundamental, that we cannot surrender, or compromise, on one jot or tittle of them.  That, as I have said, is an unfortunate position.  It would be better if we had something to bargain, but we have not.  Not to take arms against the Parliament elected by the Irish people or the Government for the <Col N="942" /> time being responsible thereto, not to interfere unlawfully with the person or property of one's fellow citizens, are these things that it is the right of a Government to compromise on?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. JOHNSON Mr. JOHNSON">
      <NameTxt>Mr. JOHNSON:</NameTxt>
      <P>No.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Mr. O'HIGGINS Mr. O'HIGGINS">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'HIGGINS:</NameTxt>
      <P>Assuredly not, and yet we stand bare upon that, and the men who stand against us challenge all that.  We are not fighting an offensive war; we are fighting a defensive war, a war for the elementary fundamental rights of the Irish people, and we do not want any Truce.  We want peace, and the way to peace is for the people who are fighting the Government's army to stop fighting the Government's army. We must think straight, or go down in confusion.  And who is the man who is going to lead them back along the paths to peace?  Who is the man who is going to say to them, you must bow to the majority will of your people, of your country? You may have your own political opinions, you may have your own principles, but you cannot stand with your gun in the path of the majority of your fellow citizens and say, &ldquo;you must not do this and you must not do that.&rdquo; Is it the man who a few months ago preached that the people had no right to do wrong, and that he was the judge, or he and a select body of his advisers? And yet we must have peace.  If it is not that man, then who is it?  And if there is no such man, we must go along and finish this thing, or go down trying. That is our clear duty as a Government.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ProfWilliamEThrift" hpid="Professor THRIFT Professor THRIFT">
      <NameTxt>Professor THRIFT:</NameTxt>
      <P>I think this Dáil is to be congratulated upon the ideas that have lain behind the words of the various speakers, who have ventured to approach this subject, and upon the words of moderation with which they have expressed their ideas.  They have shown their sense of the grave responsibility with which they have faced this occasion.  And I think they are to be congratulated on the way they met it. I also realise that I speak with grave responsibility.  But I think that anyone who imagines that he has, in the suggestion he ventures to make, any possible hope, should not shrink from making it.  We all desire peace, and I think we all realise that the way in which the President expressed his desire <Col N="943" /> for peace&mdash;the Government having put their hand to the plough would not draw back, and could not draw back&mdash; brought us a very great step upon the road to the goal we desire.  I do not want, and I feel sure that none of the Government want, even though these misguided men have done, and are doing, grievous injury to our country, to hunt them down for the sake of revenge, or to drive them to the last resort.  We would much rather, if we could, find some common ground upon which we might bring them here to discuss their different views with us in peace and quiet.  I venture to make this suggestion, it is not quite the same as Deputy Johnson made, but it is somewhat on the same lines&mdash;that the Government should realise that they are placed now for the first time, perhaps, in a strong position, with this Dáil behind them in determination to get peace and that they should offer in the strength of that position, up to a certain date, a political amnesty and express at the same time that if that political amnesty is not taken advantage of by everyone up to a certain date that they are determined to make use to the fullest of the fresh weapons with which this Dáil has provided them.  I venture merely to throw out that to the Government for their consideration; perhaps they have considered it, and if so, I may not have spoken in vain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Mr. ERNEST BLYTHE Mr. ERNEST BLYTHE">
      <NameTxt>Mr. ERNEST BLYTHE:</NameTxt>
      <P>The discussion has resolved itself rather into one of peace than of a truce for the purpose of getting peace.  Deputy McCartan, I think, hardly stood up to his own suggestion that a Truce should be offered or that hostilities should be brought to an end in that way.  Anybody at all who is in touch with the realities of the situation must realise that anything in the nature of a truce or any negotiation that involved a truce would be fatal and would at least have the most undesirable results.  In asking for these powers that the Government has got to-day for the Army it did not ask for powers to inflict punishment, it asks for powers to take certain steps with a view to achieving results.  There was no desire that any of these men should be punished, once hostilities were at an end, once the resistance to the Government was broken finally.  It is in that spirit that the Government would meet any proposals for peace.  We have no desire to punish <Col N="944" /> these men if they will give obedience to the Government and to the Parliament; they will be met as generously as anybody could suggest they should be met; but the generosity can begin only when the resistance to the Government ceases. Our efforts against them are military efforts, which cannot be slackened until these military efforts have succeeded. If anyone were to come here with any message from them&mdash;if Doctor McCartan were to come here with any message from them, the proposal contained in that message would not be dealt with in any harsh or in any unbending spirit, but whatever it might be the Government would have to hold that it was failing in its duty if even with such a message it slackened in the work that it has in hands.  It is very doubtful indeed whether there is anybody from the other side who could send any message.  The most prominent Military leaders like Lynch and Barry are not honourable men.  The political leaders, I think, have not the power to give anything in the way proposed, so that from that angle there does not seem to be much hope. The hope of peace, I think, must come in a recognition on the part of the others, that the Government and the Army acting with them are determined to carry through the military operations to absolute success.  But at the same time the Government is prepared to extend complete forgiveness and to meet with the fullest generosity anybody who ceases his resistance and accepts the fact that the Government must rule in this country and that the authority of this Parliament must not be challenged in arms.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>There seems to be some idea or some suspicion that I have some message from the Irregulars.  I have not.  I have not been in touch with any of them.  I proposed a truce. As regards the reason given by the President that you have no one to negotiate with, if I wanted to get in touch with any of them I would not know where to go.  But you must allow that there must be leaders somewhere or other&mdash;some kind of leaders of the men who are in opposition.  My real point is that the Government should allow them to come together and discuss the situation because the situation is entirely different now from what it was when the Four Courts were attacked.  I believed, and I still believe, though you may think me <Col N="945" /> optimistic, that if they get an opportunity of coming together now peace would be possible, and I think the only way to an immediate peace is a truce. Again I say you are dealing with Irishmen, and although the Minister for Home Affairs said we have nothing to give away, you can give them a ladder to climb down upon.  You can give them that, and if you do give it there is hope that they will climb down.  Make it as little difficult as possible, make it as easy as possible for them to climb down. The Government are strong enough to do that.  If it was possible to proclaim a truce I would advocate it and proclaim it strongly, but my object is that you give them an opportunity to climb down and that is really what I have in view.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamdeRoiste" hpid="LIAM DE ROISTE LIAM DE ROISTE">
      <NameTxt>LIAM DE ROISTE:</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to associate myself with the plea made by Deputy McCartan, and I do so for this reason: While I have no authority particularly to speak for any section of those who are in arms against the Dáil, even quite lately certain deputations approached me, when I was in the city of Cork, and said that if the road were made easy for certain sections of the Irregulars, the Irregulars&mdash;some of them, at all events; some companies, as I understand&mdash;are prepared to recognise the authority of this Assembly.  Now, if that is the fact, as I was led to believe, I would join in the plea that was made by Deputy McCartan, that the Ministry here might make the way easy for any sections that are of that mind.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General McKEON General McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say one word about a truce.  Deputy McCartan has asked the Dáil to give these men a ladder upon which they might come down.  There is no man in Ireland to-day prepared to give these men a ladder to come down sooner than I am, if I thought it was going to have the desired effect; but, if you acquiesce in Deputy McCartan's plea, it will simply mean that you will be fooled in the same way as an effort was made to fool me in the West.  Instead of your giving them a ladder to come down on by offering a truce, you will be simply preparing an avenue to enable them to strengthen their military position.  Do not make any mistake about this.  A delegation&mdash; I have the documents relating to it&mdash; was sent to me with a request to arrange <Col N="946" /> a truce between the two forces in the West.  The gentleman who came to propose it was quite possibly honest, but I doubt it.  The idea underlying the thing was that I would agree to a three days' truce for the purpose of settling our differences, and that if Sean McKeon of the Western Command, and some other body in command on the other side had a chat, they were going to smooth the thing over, not minding the Dáil or anybody else.  But the motive was this: during those three days a ship would enter Sligo port, carrying sufficient stuff which, if carefully handled, would put the Irregulars in a position not only to negotiate terms with me, but perhaps to dictate them.  Now, that would be the ladder you would give these men if you negotiate a truce.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisJohnGorey" hpid="Mr. D.J. GOREY Mr. D.J. GOREY">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. GOREY:</NameTxt>
      <P>Give them a ladder of rifles.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General McKEON General McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes; a ladder of rifles.  Now if there is to be peace&mdash;I speak as a soldier and with all the responsibility of a soldier who knows what he is talking about&mdash;there is only one basis upon which that peace can be established; that is, every soldier in the Nation must be submissive, not to the Government or to any set of men as a Government, but to the majority of the votes of the Irish people.  There is great talk about Governments.  I recognise one Government only in the sense of Government and that is that whatever the majority of the Irish people want, that will, I am willing to serve with my life.  I am willing to do it now as in the past and there is not a soldier under my command who is not willing to do the same, and until everyone accepts that position you can never have peace or never will.  So the only thing is, anyone who wants a truce let them say that they are prepared to abide by the will of the majority of the Irish people. I am prepared to abide by that will whether the Government be Labour, Unionist, or Sinn Fein, or whatever you like to call it.  Let the Government be composed of merchants, traders, farmers. That includes the whole lot here. Whatever is the particular form of Government the country has a right to elect it.  The Irish people have the right to put in who they like.  In the Army we have men of all kinds, labourers, farmers, men who are soldiers of fortune and <Col N="947" /> who do not give a damn about anybody; men, perhaps, who ought to be millionaires or something like that, and men, none of whom would agree to any form of Government whatsoever, but they must submit their will to whatever the particular form of Government is, and that is the only position on which you can have peace, and until that is accepted you will not have peace.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatMcCartan" hpid="Dr. McCARTAN Dr. McCARTAN">
      <NameTxt>Dr. McCARTAN:</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not expect that <Col N="948" /> the National soldiers would go asleep during the truce and let the others do as they like.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GenSeanMacEoin" hpid="General McKEON General McKEON">
      <NameTxt>General McKEON:</NameTxt>
      <P>It will be the same as the last truce; it will be all one-sided, and you cannot have that.</P>
      <P>Motion: &ldquo;That the Dáil do now adjourn,&rdquo; put and carried.</P>
      <P>The Dáil adjourned at 7.10 p.m.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>