<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="28" Month="Jul" Year="1965" Vol="59" No="5" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 28 Iúil 1965" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 28 July 1965" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="485">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="485" />Do chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Huguenot Cemetery Dublin" RHead="(Peter Street) Bill, 1965">
    <Title>Huguenot Cemetery Dublin (Peter Street) Bill, 1965.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The following message has been received from Dáil Éireann:</P>
      <P>Dáil Éireann has made the following Order:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Huguenot Cemetery Dublin (Peter Street) Bill, 1965, which has lapsed and which before lapsing stood referred to Joint Committee be revived and proceeded with at that stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1 to 7, inclusive, on the Order Paper, and then No. 9. No. 9 will be taken immediately after the tea recess.  It is proposed to discuss together the Second Stages of Nos. 5, 6 and 7 and, when completed, to take the remaining stages of No. 6, the Appropriation Bill.  As there is a time limit on No. 5, the Finance Bill, it is also proposed to take the Committee and remaining stages of that Bill on Friday.  The remaining stages of the Prices Bill and the Succession Bill will be taken next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Huguenot Cemetery Dublin" RHead="(Peter Street) Bill, 1965: Joint Committee">
    <Title>Private Business. - Huguenot Cemetery Dublin (Peter Street) Bill, 1965: Joint Committee.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Joint Committee on Standing Orders (Private Business) reports that it has nominated the following Senators to serve on the Joint Committee on the Huguenot Cemetery Dublin (Peter Street) Bill, 1965:&mdash;</P>
      <P>John J. Nash, John B. O'Quigley and William A. W. Sheldon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="486" /> I move:</P>
    <P>That the Report be laid before the Seanad.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Pursuant to Standing Order 71 of the Standing Orders of the Dáil and the Seanad relative to Private Business, we, the Ceann Comhairle of the Dáil and the Cathaoirleach of the Seanad, jointly appoint Deputy Gerard Sweetman to be Chairman of the Joint Committee on the Huguenot Cemetery Dublin (Peter Street) Bill, 1965.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Institute of Chartered Accountants in Ireland (Charter" RHead="Amendment) Bill, 1965&mdash;Report from Examiner of Private Bills">
    <Title>Private Business. - Institute of Chartered Accountants in Ireland (Charter Amendment) Bill, 1965&mdash;Report from Examiner of Private Bills.</Title>
    <P>Report from the Examiner of Private Bills that in the case of the application for leave to introduce the Institute of Chartered Accountants in Ireland (Charter Amendment) Bill, 1965, the Standing Orders have been complied with.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the Report be laid before the Seanad.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="LiamOBuachalla" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill is now deemed to be read the First Time.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Social Welfare (Miscellaneous" RHead="Provisions) Bill, 1965: Second and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Public Business. - Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1965: Second and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: That the Bill be now read a Second Time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Boland) Kevin Boland">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Boland)</NameTxt>
      <P>Cúis áthais dom an Bille seo a chur ós comhair Seanad Éireann.  Mar is léir ón mheamram míniúcháin a cuireadh ar fáil le téacs an Bhille séard atá ann ná forálacha is gá chun na méadaithe tathagacha a fógraíodh sa Cháinfhaisnéis i rátaí sochar agus pinsean árachais shóisialaigh agus freisin i rátaí pinsean seanaoise, daille agus baintrí neamh-ranníocach agus cúnamh dífhostaíochta a chur i bhfeidhm.  Tá foráil sa Bhille, freisin, leis an dteorainn ioncaim chun árachais éigintigh faoi na hAchtanna <Col N="487" /> Leasa Shóisialaigh a árdú ó £800 go £1,200 i n-aghaidh na bliana.  Chomh maith leis sin tá forálacha tábhachtacha sa Bhille a bhaineann le módh nua chun acmhainn sealbhóirí feirmeacha beaga i gCeantair Chúnga d'áireamh i gcomhair cúnamh dífhostaíochta. Ina dteannta sin tá roint feabhsanna éagsúla ann ar na scéimeanna árachais shóisialaigh agus chúnaimh.</P>
      <P>Fórálann an Bille go bhfaighidh na pinsinéirí neamh-ranníocacha uilig sean-aoise, daille nó baintrí, nach mó ná £26. 5s. 0d a n-acmhainn bliantúil, 10/- breise i n-aghaidh na seachtaine agus go bhfaighidh an chuid eile de na pinsinéirí 5/- i n-aghaidh na seachtaine. Tá uas-ráta pinsean neamh-ranníocach dilleachta dá mhéadú freisin do réir 5/- i n-aghaidh na seachtaine.  De thoradh na méadaithe seo pinsean táthar arís ag leathnú ar na teorainneacha bliantiúla acmhainne agus na rátaí pinsean i dtreo's go mbeidh ráta breise ag an bpointe is ísle de gach scála iníoctha le daoine nach raibh ach díreach taobh amuigh den teorainn acmhainne d'aon phinsin go nuige seo.</P>
      <P>Táthar ag méadú ar na rátaí cúnaimh dífhostaíochta do réir 5/- i n-aghaidh na seachtaine don fhaighteoir féin agus beidh 5/- breise iníoctha i leith cleithiúnaí aosaithe nuair is ann dó.  Chomh maith leis an méadú i rátaí cúnaimh dífhostaíochta beidh a chomhthrom de leathnú ar an dteorainn acmhainne i gcomhair cáilithe chun cúnaimh dífhostaíochta.</P>
      <P>Beidh na méadaithe ar shochair leasa shóisialaigh i bhfeidhm ó thosach Mí Eanáir seo chugainn agus dá réir soláthrófar 10/- breise i n-aghaidh na seachtaine d'fhaighteoirí sochar míchumais, sochair dífhostaíochta, sochar máithreachais, pinsean ranníocach baintrí, liúntas ranníocach dilleachta agus pinsean seanaoise (ranníocach) maille le 10/- breise i n-aghaidh na seachtaine i leith cleithiúnaí aosaithe más ann dó.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Táthar chun na ranníoca fostaíochta a árdú dá réir freisin.  Is é an méadú ar ráta gnáthach na ranníoca do fhear oibre ná 2s. 10d i n-aghaidh na seachtaine i dtreo's gurab ionann is 14s. 8d i n-aghaidh na seachtaine an ráta <Col N="488" /> sin agus é rointe go comhthrom idir an fostóir agus an fostaí.</P>
    <P>Tá beartaithe ag an Rialtas freisin an teorainn pá is cuí chun árachais éigintigh faoi na hAchtanna Leasa Shóisialaigh i gcás daoine atá i bhfostaíocht seachas i mbun obair láimhe a árdú ó £800 i naghaidh na bliana go £1,200.  Cuirfear an t-athrú seo i bhfeidhm ar dáta a sochrófar trí bhíthin Órdaithe.</P>
    <P>Rud a cabhróidh go mór le mílte sealbhóirí feirmeacha beaga i gceantair chúnga is ea an t-athrú a fhorálann an Bille, maidir le módh áirmhithe ioncaim ó thalamh faoi na hAchtanna Um Cúnamh Dífhostaíochta.  Is ar éifeacht táirgiúil na feirme do réir mar a thaisbeánann luacháil measaithe na talún é agus ní ar an líon stoc agus barraí, &amp; rl. a bunófar áireamh na h-acmhainne feasta.  Is é cuspóir na h-athraithe seo go mbeidh ar a gcumas d'fheirmeóirí beaga ins na ceantair chúnga an toradh is mó is féidir a fháisceadh as a bhfeirmeacha agus páirt a ghlacadh go pras ins na scéimeanna uilig atá ceapaithe chun méadú ar thoradh talmhaíochta ach gan bheith imníoch faoi chúnamh dífhostaíochta a chailliúint de bhárr a saothair.</P>
    <P>Tá mar pholasaí agam le linn dom bheith im Aire na scéimeanna leasa shóisialaigh a choimeád fé scrúdú d'fhonn iad a fheabhsú tré pé easnamh, aimhrialtachta, nó lochta eile a tcítear dom a bheith ionntu a leasú chomh fada agus is féidir é.  Cuige sin, seo go hachomair cuid de na leasaithe atá sa Bhille: Tá cúig athraithe ann a bhaineann le h-áireamh acmhainne i gcomhair pinsean neamh-ranníocach seanaoise, daille, baintrí nó dilleachta a ligfidh do roint mhaith daoine cáiliú chun pinsean, nó chun rátaí níos aoirde, feasta.</P>
    <P>Tá feabhsanna beartaithe ar na hAchtanna Um Liúntais Leanaí freisin.  Faoi cheann díobh íocfar liúntas leanaí le h-oifigigh Airm le linn bheith i gcéin dóibh, agus faoin gceann eile íocfar liúntas faoi dhó i leith gach linbh a mhaireann i gcás breithe iolraí seachas cúpla.</P>
    <P>Maidir le costas na bhforálacha éagsúla: ar an dtaobh cúnamh shóisialaigh de is é an costas iomlán ná <Col N="489" /> £4,337,900 i mbliain iomlán agus £2,484,100 sa bhliain reatha.  Ar an dtaobh árachais shóisialaigh de is é costas iomlán na moltaí ná £5,190,000 i mbliain iomlán.  Is é an chuid de sin a íocfar as an Stát-Chiste ná £1,290,000 i mbliain iomlán agus £668,000 sa bhliain reatha.</P>
    <P>This Bill as a result of which the gross expenditure on Social Welfare will be increased by £9.53 millions in a full year represents a considerable advance in the field of social welfare in this country.  From the explanatory memorandum circulated with the text, it will be seen that the Bill includes the provisions to implement the decision announced by the Minister for Finance in his Budget speech on 11th May last to give substantial increases in rates of social insurance benefits and pensions, and also in rates of non-contributory old age, blind and widows' pensions and unemployment assistance.  The Bill also includes provision to increase the income limit for compulsory insurance under the Social Welfare Acts from £800 to £1,200 a year.  There are, in addition, important provisions in the Bill for a new method of assessing means for the purposes of unemployment assistance in the case of smallholders in congested areas, and, finally, the Bill provides for a number of miscellaneous improvements in existing social insurance and assistance schemes.</P>
    <P>Senators will observe that the explanatory memorandum issued with the Bill is much more detailed than has previously been the case.  I have had this done to help resolve the difficulty in understanding and following amending legislation of this nature which necessarily must be by reference to the existing Acts.  My aim has been to make clear, as far as possible, what each amendment really does, where the text itself is not self-explanatory.</P>
    <P>The Budget increases on the social assistance side, to be effective as from the beginning of next month, will give an extra 10/- a week for all existing non-contributory old age, blind or widow pensioners whose yearly means do not exceed £26 5s. while all the remaining pensioners will get an increase of 5/- a week.  It is estimated <Col N="490" /> that some 71,000 persons who are old age or blind pensioners will qualify for the 10/- increase and 41,000 for the 5/- increase, while over 11,000 widows will obtain the 10/- increase, the remainder getting the 5/- increase.  The maximum rate of orphan's non-contributory pension is also being increased by 5/- a week.  The opportunity is again being taken to extend the scales of means and rates of pension in each case so as to add an additional rate at the minimum of each scale which will be payable to persons previously just outside the means limit for any pension.  As a result the scale for an old age pensioner without a qualified child will be extended to £156 15s., as against the present £143 15s. and therefore a married pensioner without a qualified child can have means of £313 10s. and still qualify for the minimun rate of old age pension.  The means limit, of course, increases with each qualified child.</P>
    <P>The rates of unemployment assistance for persons in urban and rural areas are being increased by 5/- a week for the recipient himself and by a further 5/- where there is an adult dependant.  This will have the consequential effect of automatically extending the means limit for qualification for unemployment assistance by equivalent amounts.</P>
    <P>The increases in payments in social insurance benefits will become operative at the beginning of January next, and will provide an extra 10/- a week for recipients of disability benefit, unemployment benefit, maternity benefit, widow's contributory pension, orphan's contributory allowance and old age (contributory) pension, with an additional 10/- a week where an adult dependant's allowance is payable with a pension or benefit.  The extra cost will be paid for, as are all insurance benefits, by increases in the contributions from employers, insured employees and from the Exchequer.  The consequential increase in the rates of social insurance contribution will be 2/10d. a week in the ordinary rate for male workers, making it 14/8d. a week, to be shared equally by the employer and worker.  Increases in the rates of <Col N="491" /> contribution for other classes will be 2/10d. where all the insurance benefits are insured against, with appropriately lesser amounts where some only of the benefits of the scheme are covered.</P>
    <P>Rising levels of remuneration generally as a result of successive rounds of pay increases over the past few years, has affected the social insurance scheme by giving increasing numbers of persons who are employed otherwise than by way of manual labour, pay which was in excess of the limit for compulsory insurance under the Social Welfare Acts.  The Government have decided to increase this limit which, of course, applies only to persons employed otherwise than by way of manual labour, from the existing level of £800, fixed in 1958, to £1,200 a year.  The Bill provides that this increase will take effect from a date to be determined by Order.  This is necessary not only to give employers and persons likely to be affected, reasonable notice of the change after the relevant provision becomes law but also to permit regulations to be made for the purpose of awarding credited contributions to persons brought back into compulsory insurance by reason of the raising of the limit.</P>
    <P>These credited contributions will enable a person brought back into compulsory insurance to qualify at once for disability benefit or unemployment benefit, provided he otherwise satisfies the conditions for benefit.  They will not, however, count for purposes of old age or widows' (contributory) pensions as any person going out of insurance by reason of going over the remuneration limit could have maintained his insurance for pension purposes by becoming a voluntary contributor.  There is provision in the Bill to enable future variations in the remuneration limit to be made by Government Order and in such a case it will be necessary that the Draft of the Order be placed before each House of the Oireachtas and approved by resolution of each House before the Order can be made.</P>
    <P>Many thousands of smallholders in the congested areas will benefit from <Col N="492" /> the radical change, which the Bill provides for, in the method of assessing income from land under the Unemployment Assistance Acts.  Means derived from their land by smallholders in Congested Districts will, in general, no longer be calculated by reference to the actual number of stock, area and type of crops, etc. on a holding but by reference to the productive capacity of the holding as indicated by the rateable valuation of the land. Under this new system all holdings bearing the same land valuation will normally be deemed to produce the same fixed rate of means regardless of the extent to which the occupiers are in fact working the lands.  The idea is that each smallholder in the congested areas should be free to work his holding to maximum capacity, and to participate readily in all schemes designed to increase agricultural output, without being concerned about losing some or all of his unemployment assistance as a result of an expanding farm income arising from greater effort and enterprise on his part.</P>
    <P>The Bill proposes to give the Government power to specify by order the areas in which the new system will operate.  It is proposed to apply it in the 11 full counties of Donegal, Sligo, Leitrim, Roscommon, Mayo, Galway, Cavan, Monaghan, Longford, Clare and Kerry together with the congested portions of West Cork and West Limerick.  Thus the scheme will embrace the congested areas in the widest sense of that term.  The areas I have mentioned are substantially the same as the areas which have been selected for the purposes of measures recently introduced for the development of the West such, for example, as the county development teams and pilot area schemes.  The essential feature of the unemployment assistance scheme will be unaltered, but in the congested areas income from a holding will be calculated on the basis of £20 a year for each £1 of net land valuation.  The present disregard of 5/- per week in respect of a married smallholder will, of course, continue to operate so that, in effect, the means assessed in his case for a £3 land valuation farm will be £47 per year and £67 for a £4 land <Col N="493" /> valuation farm and so on.  The means figure thus calculated will stay unchanged irrespective of changes in the output of the farm.  In this way, a person who neglects his holding will lose any advantage in the scale of unemployment assistance payments which he enjoys at present over his more industrious neighbour with a similar valuation.</P>
    <P>Special transitional arrangements will enable existing smallholder recipients of unemployment assistance in the selected areas to adapt themselves gradually to the amended scheme.  In any case where it would be to their advantage they may for a period of five years continue to have their means assessed as at present on the basis of current values, for stock, crops etc., but in no case will the assessment exceed the figure which would be arrived at by calculating their means by reference to land valuation.  In the absence of actual experience it is not possible to say with any firmness how many smallholders will benefit from the proposals or what the additional cost will be.  We have, however, estimated, that some 24,000 smallholders in the selected areas will be affected including about 8,000 who are already recipients of unemployment assistance and that the additional cost of the change, on the basis of these numbers, will be something over £1,000,000 a year.</P>
    <P>I feel I can say with full justification that when these changes are brought into force in January next there will be no reason why a smallholder in the congested areas in receipt of unemployment assistance should not make an all-out effort to increase the production from his holding by making the maximum use of his skill and energy, and of whatever financial and technical aids and advice are available to him, and by enthusiastic co-operation with his neighbours and full participation in government schemes designed to raise income levels in these areas.</P>
    <P>It has been my policy as Minister to keep the various social welfare schemes instantly under review and to seek to improve them whenever and wherever possible.  In each Social Welfare <Col N="494" /> Bill introduced over the past few years, provision has been made for a variety of improvements, some great and some relatively small, but each of them of considerable benefit to the persons affected.  The present is no exception as it includes provision for a number of improvements or extensions of existing schemes.</P>
    <P>Section 15, for instance, deals with five modifications of the means test as applied for the purposes of non-contributory old age, blind, widows' or orphans' pensions and will undoubtedly enable a considerable number of persons to qualify for such pensions or to qualify for a higher rate of pension.  These include an increase in the amount which may be disregarded from the earnings of a blind person in assessing his means for pension purposes by £13 for himself, his wife, and each qualified child and the complete disregard for the purposes of non-contributory old age, blind and widows' pensions of all payments from charitable organisations.</P>
    <P>Another concession will permit an annuity payable under the Land Act, 1965 to an elderly or blind person who surrenders a holding to the Land Commission, to be ignored in so far as it does not exceed £3 a week in assessing means for old age or blind pension.</P>
    <P>The remaining concessions in the group affect widows' non-contributory pensions and are the extension of the present disregard of £39 from earnings from insurable employment in respect of each qualified child so that it will apply also to a widow's earnings from any form of employment or self-employment involving personal exertions and the limitation of the amount of a qualified child's means which can be assessed against a widow to £26 where she has one such child and to £52 where she has more than one.</P>
    <P>The position of non-contributory old age pensioners detained in mental hospitals is also being improved.  At present their pensions are appropriated by the hospital authorities towards the cost of their maintenance and treatment but if the person in charge of the hospital feels that the pensioner is capable of using money properly, the <Col N="495" /> pensioner may be allowed up to 10/- a week out of his pension as pocket money.  Section 11 of the Bill will increase the amount that may be so allowed to a maximum of £1 a week and will also permit the person in charge of the hospital, over and above any payment he makes to the pensioner or even where he cannot make such payment to the pensioner, to pay on behalf of the pensioner portion of the pension towards such liabilities as the pensioner may have for rent, mortgages, insurance <i>et cetera.</i></P>
    <P>A proposed extension of the children's allowances scheme will enable allowances to be paid to State servants, including Army officers, who go abroad in the service of the State or Government, or of the United Nations or other affiliated or similar international body and who bring their children to live with them.  Another extension of that scheme while not of very wide application, will be of considerable value to those who benefit from it.  It will enable double the appropriate rate of children's allowance to be paid, in respect of the survivors of multiple births, other than twins, while there are at least three such survivors.</P>
    <P>Finally, it is proposed to amend the unemployment assistance scheme in order that a qualification certificate may be granted with retrospective effect to the date of application thus enabling unemployment assistance to be paid for a period of unemployment prior to the grant of the qualification certificate.  At present, unemployment assistance cannot be paid until the applicant, no matter what his circumstances may be, is the holder of a qualification certificate.  This amendment is in line with that made last year in relation to a revised decision affecting the grant of qualification certificates.</P>
    <P>I do not think that I need go into any greater detail now but it may be helpful if I summarise the cost of the various proposals in the Bill.  On the social assistance side, the total cost will be £4,337,900 in a full year, of which £3,165,000 arises from the <Col N="496" /> Budget proposals, £1,084,000 from the concessions for smallholders in congested districts, and £88,900 from the remaining provisions.  All of this cost will fall on the Exchequer, but the amount to be met in the current year will total only £2,484,100, that is, £2,076,000 in respect of the Budget proposals, £350,000 in respect of the smallholders' concession and £58,100 in respect of the remaining provisions.</P>
    <P>The gross annual cost of the improvements on the social insurance scheme will be £5,190,000, of which £5,120,000 arises from the Budget proposals. It is, however, estimated that the increases in rates of contribution, will bring in an additional £3,900,000 to the Social Insurance Fund, leaving the cost to be met by the Exchequer at £1,290,000 in a full year and £668,000 in the current year.</P>
    <P>These are very large sums but I am sure Senators will appreciate that substantial improvements cannot be effected in social welfare schemes without appropriate increases in the contributions of employers, insured workers and of the Exchequer.  I am satisfied that the proposed increased expenditure on our social welfare schemes is more than justified and that it is a measure of a further great step forward in the evolution of our social welfare system.  I have much pleasure, therefore, in recommending this Bill to Seanad Éireann.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>We welcome the provisions of this Bill and I may say, in opening my remarks on it, that never was a Social Welfare Bill presented to the Oireachtas in circumstances in which the public were better conditioned to its reception.  One can look back over the years and find that certain newspapers, particularly the <i>Irish Independent</i>, have for a long time advocated improved standards of pensions for the people who are worst off in our society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Then we had in recent months a general election in which the emphasis changed relative to the issues involved as the campaign developed.  The subject of improved social welfare benefits was sparked off initially by the new policy statement of the Fine Gael <Col N="497" /> Party in relation to its place in a just society.  The Labour Party have been for a long time, in several manifestoes, advocating improved pensions for those people whose lot it falls to the community at large to assist.  As I have said, the emphasis changed as the general election campaign progressed and we can say, therefore, that the newly-elected Government, irrespective of the side they came from, were given a clear indication from the electorate in recent months that one of the tasks to which they should immediately apply themselves was the improvement of the lot of the various categories who rely on our social welfare system to get the bare minimum necessary to maintain them in what we frequently hear described as our affluent society.</P>
    <P>We have many vehicles of propaganda presenting the affluence of our people but we find in the Minister's statement today the cold undeniable facts that there are 71,000 persons in our community who, on investigation, have less than £26 5s. Od. per annum by way of income and that 11,000 widows qualify under the same assessment of means.  Surely, with the tremendous increase in the cost of living, with the reduced value of money, these people must find it extremely difficult to contend with the ordinary demands upon them irrespective of the very least that will give them food and some measure of comfort in their homes in their declining years?</P>
    <P>This year in the Budget Statement the Minister for Finance gave particulars of deliberate taxes which were imposed and accepted&mdash;in retrospect, we can say they have been accepted by the people&mdash;for the specific purpose of coming to the aid of these people. I do not speak of all the taxes but of many of them.  I exempt the petrol tax and the fact that for the first time hard-pressed tobacco was not excluded from taxation.  This indicated a certain cynicism in relation to the recovery of some of the money intended to go for the benefit of the male old age pensioner.</P>
    <P>Reference has been made in recent times to the introduction of the human <Col N="498" /> approach by the Minister for Social Welfare and the Department in the administration of the Department. This is very welcome, if true.  The pronouncements made have been welcomed and we await their implementation. Since the Minister spoke in those terms, I have evidence of an instance in Dublin where an official of his Department was obliged to visit a family on the question of a means test. While he was there, an old lady was engaged for an hour or two to carry out some chores.  She happened to pass through the hallway.  The official asked the head of the house if she was in receipt of an old age pension and how much he paid her per week.  The head of the house declined to give the information and the official returned during the week and again insisted on getting the identity of this poor person.  Again there was a denial of information and the official said: &ldquo;Despite your non-co-operation, I shall track her down.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Are these Gestapo methods to be continued by certain officials of this Department in relation to the possibility that this person might be in receipt of a contributory old age pension while engaged in some work to supplement her income by a few shillings a week?  If the Minister implements his promise of a human approach on this question of the means test, it will be welcomed by all.</P>
    <P>With regard to the methods employed to disburse the moneys the Minister says are available for improving the lot of those people in our society, we are entitled to question the arbitrary fashion in which the increases have been allocated.  We have the figure of £26 5s. Od. and if a person has 10/- more he is denied the full increase of 10/- Would it not have been better to give particular attention to those aged people who live alone and have neither the ordinary comforts of life nor the company of their families around them to sustain them, to advise them, and to assist them&mdash; we read of the tragedy that occurs to many of those people living alone&mdash; and to evolve some system whereby the home assistance officers would be permitted to take pity on them and <Col N="499" /> award an effective supplement to assist them?</P>
    <P>We have an assessment of means in relation to medical card applications and it would not be too difficult a task to ascertain the numbers of those people and the conditions in which they live, particularly in built-up areas.  I feel those people should be a first charge on us and should get an effective increase to assist them in maintaining some standard of dignity in their declining years.  If has often been discussed among people with an interest in this aspect of administration whether it would be a wise course or not to spend the moneys available in other ways, relative to the old age pensioner, whether the means test should not be abolished and whether we should not reduce the qualifying age.</P>
    <P>I am inclined to agree with the Minister, weighing up the pros and cons of this matter, when he states he would retain the means test.  He provided very convincing figures regarding the cost of administering the means test, as it exists.  I agree we owe the greatest debt to those among us who have the least.  Consequently, the retention of the means test is desirable to ensure that the greater part of the moneys available goes to those most in need.  Likewise, we note the social implications particularly in farming areas, of the retention of the means test.  It has the effect of encouraging farmers of limited valuation to hand over their property to sons or daughters and so qualify for the pension.  It encourages them to give over the reins of office to their families, with consequential benefit to all the community. If the means test were abolished, it might entail some diminution of this activity which is encouraged by the present arrangement.</P>
    <P>A tribute is due, when referring to the human approach, to the members of the old age pension sub-committees throughout the country who apply their interest and time, quite often at considerable inconvenience, to attendance at meetings and who assist their neighbours in obtaining the pension. I would like to see better co-operation <Col N="500" /> between the committees and the officers of the Minister's Department regarding the decisions taken by these committees.  I feel the development of the human approach could be further implemented if more attention were paid to the views expressed by such committees.</P>
    <P>I would like to see improved the position of some people who were unsuccessful in the past in their applications for assistance.  I refer particularly to the section who may have small businesses.  They have repeatedly applied in the past but have been rejected.  They have given up the ghost in regard to their applications.  We know, with the trend of affairs today, the diminution that has occurred in the turnover of these little shops, due to the development of multiple stores and other factors.  Many of these people are entitled to the pension but they have really despaired, having tried so often and having failed.</P>
    <P>With regard to the qualifying age for pensions, I would make a plea to the Minister to lower the age for spinsters to 65.  It is not too often ladies will admit reaching that age but we know there are many of those people in our community at present.  At the time some of those spinsters were of marriageable age, opportunities did not exist: the home circumstances at that time were not favourable to their securing a partner in life.  Many of them have now very limited means! many are in failing health, incapable of providing for themselves and are finding it very difficult in the years up to the point at which they reach the qualifying age.  A very special case could be made for those people.  This would be a diminishing problem, but at the present moment there are many of those people among us who are very badly off.  I would appeal to the Minister to consider lowering the qualifying age for this category.</P>
    <P>I also wish to repeat an appeal I made quite frequently in the other House regarding another category of ladies.  There are not many of them but nevertheless they are extremely deserving cases.  I refer to those unfortunate ladies who have failed to satisfy the Department that their husbands <Col N="501" /> are in fact dead.  They cannot afford to avail of the legal process to enable them to qualify them for the widows' pension.  Some of these people, despite their efforts over periods of 20, 22 or 25 years have failed to trace their missing spouses.  Despite this, their claims are rejected on the basis that there is no conclusive evidence that they are in fact widows.  Surely it should be within the competence of the Department, where such time has expired, to decide that payment be made and moneys paid recovered, if at any time the defaulter is proved to be alive and can be made to live up to his responsibilities.  I make that appeal again and I would ask the Minister to look more favourably on it.</P>
    <P>With regard to unemployment benefit, I find one very difficult situation regarding insured workers who own licensed premises in remote country villages.  We know that these people could not possibly live off the income they receive.  Their licensed premises may be their homes which have been handed down to them from their parents.  A profitable business may have been transacted in these premises in the day at a time when the fairs brought so many people into those villages, but now, with the development of cattle marts, this business has gone and heads of families in some of these remote villages have to take up employment.  It only applies, I understand, in the case of a licensed premises but it is permissible to engage in other business and draw unemployment benefit, although for some peculiar reason, a person is disqualified if his name appears as being the licensee of these premises.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>The interpretation is changed now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to know that because it was something about which I was concerned for some time and I am pleased to learn that it has been changed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As I said at the commencement, I welcome the provisions of the Bill and the favourable atmosphere in which the people are prepared to accept the taxation necessary to provide more <Col N="502" /> for the people who are unfortunate enough to require assistance from the State.  There is one inclusion by the Minister which is somewhat arbitrary. It is in relation to the definition of areas for unemployment assistance. The Minister has defined that 11 full counties plus the congested portions of West Cork and West Limerick would be included for this purpose. Again, there are regions outside the named areas which could be classed as poor as those named.  If an amendment could be effected in this respect I feel it would be merely applying justice all round.</P>
    <P>It is unfortunate that this is one of an important group of Bills unloaded on us for discussion during these few days.  No doubt the Minister will seek all Stages of the Bill and this may not give the House the time and opportunity it may well desire regarding amendment of the Bill. However, we welcome the general provisions, though they are belated. Furthermore, and on this note I shall conclude, despite improvements in our administration, we have the delay in implementing budgetary provisions in relation to the disbursing of money, while there is instant application of taxes.  We have the situation of tax now but pay later.  Is it necessary that so many months should elapse between the decision to implement these increases and the actual effecting of them?  Surely we could progress to the point where, despite the fact that the taxation to meet this situation is evoked immediately after the passage of the Budget, so many months should not elapse and that so many people in our society should not have to wait so long for the benefits.  Very many of them, as we know, tragically will not live to enjoy the increases.</P>
    <P>I should like the Minister to deal with that point and to indicate whether or not it is the intention, in bringing in Bills of this nature in future, to effect any shortening of the administrative period so as to guarantee that the purposes of the Bill will be fully implemented within a reasonable time.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>Ar an gcéad dul síos, ba mhaith liom comhgháirdeachas a dhéanamh leis an Rialtas agus go h-áirithe leis an Aire as ucht an Bhille <Col N="503" /> seo a thabhairt isteach.  Is eol do gach éinne an spéis atá ag an Aire i ngnóthaí a bhaineann le cúrsaí leasa shóisialaigh agus ní taise don ócáid seo é.  Níor ghá aon ghríosú ó Fhine Gael nó ón bhFreasúra uilig chun an Aire nó an Rialtas a spreagadh le rud fónta a dhéanamh ar son na bpinsinéirí, na mbaintreach, na leanaí nó ar son na ndaoine atá gan obair.  Ní inniu ná inné a thosnaigh nó a ghlac Fianna Fáil an dúngaois seo.  Chomh fada siar le 1932 agus ó shoin i leith thug an Pairtí seo Billí os comhair na Dála a raibh sé de chuspóir acu feabhas a chur ar shlí bheatha na ndaoine atá aosta, tinn nó orthu siúd nach bhfuil mórán airgid acu.</P>
      <P>D'éirigh linn na cuspóirí úd a chur i gcrích, fiú amháin nuair a bhí an cogadh ar siúl.  Rinneamar amhlaidh nuair a bhí breis sa Dáil againn ar lucht an Fhreasúra agus gan brú nó spreagadh ó dhream ar bith.  Ní h-amháin sin, ach is é an Pairtí seo, nuair a bhíodar i gcumhacht, a rith na hAchtanna uilig beagnach a thug leath-lá, laethe saoire agus tráthanna rialta oibre do na daoine atá ag obtair i siopaí, i monarchain agus sna comhairlí contae ar fud na tíre.</P>
      <P>Is fiú go mór dearcadh anois ar stair lucht an Fhreasúra&mdash;go h-áirithe ar stair Fhine Gael, daoine a bhain 1/-dena sean-phinsinéirí.  Is beag a rinne an Comh-Rialtas ach oiread agus ní gá ach féachaint sna hAchtanna chun sin a dheimhniú.  Mar sin, ní gá do Fhine Gael aon chreidiúint a ghlacadh chucu féin mar, go deimhin, is suarach an méid a rinne siad ar son lucht leasa sóisialaigh.</P>
      <P>Moltaí maithe atá sa Bhille seo agus cosnaíonn siad airgead.  Tá an Rialtas sásta an t-airgead sin a chur ar fáil.  Tá ár gcroíthe san obair seo agus tá a fhios againn nach bhfuilimid sásta agus ní bheidh.  Fhad agus atá an Rialtas seo i réim agus staid eacnamaíochta na tíre ag dul chun cinn cuirfimid níos mó airgid i leataobh chun cabhrú leis na daoine bochta seo.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Molaim an tAire mar gheall ar an athrú a rinne sé maidir leis an módh áirithe ioncaim ó thalamh faoi na hAchtanna um chúnamh dífhostaíochta. <Col N="504" /> Cabhróidh sin go mór leis na feirmeoirí beaga agus tá a lán acu sin im chontae féin.  As seo amach ní bheidh scannradh orthu breis oibre a dhéanamh ar eagla go gcaillfidh siad pé airgead a bhí le fáil acu ón Roinn.</P>
    <P>Cuirim fáilte roimh an mBille agus iarraim ar an Aire leanúint leis an ndea-obair ó bhliain go bliain.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>We are dealing again at this time of the year with a Bill to provide for increased social welfare benefits.  These Bills are traditionally welcomed on all sides of the House. I should like to try to put this matter into perspective because I fear we are becoming rather smug in regard to social welfare benefits and the improvements we enact year by year.</P>
      <P>It is true that benefits are being improved.  It is unfortunately true also that traditionally, as is usual, we are waiting until this time of the year to provide certain benefits as from 1st August and others as from 1st January next.  Are we not being a little too complacent when we remember that there have been thousands of old age pensioners trying to exist on 37/6d per week in the past 12 months, a period during which food costs have risen by about 14 per cent?  We are glad that under this measure these benefits will be increased by 5/- and 10/- in some cases, bringing the figures up to 42/6d and 47/6d per week.  We are all congratulating ourselves on these new figures, forgetting, for the moment, that, even with these increases, it is virtually impossible to exist on that sort of income.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to attempt further to put the matter into perspective by drawing the attention of all sides of the House to the fact that I think we spend a lower proportion of our national income on social services than practically any other western European country.  It is an appalling thought that we, a christian country, should have this situation that we are spending less of the wealth available to all members of our community, proportionately, than practically any other western European country.  I think that we should, on all sides of the House, <Col N="505" /> be ashamed of that situation.</P>
    <P>Let me draw attention to the extent of the problem.  It is calculated that about one in six of the population of the Republic is dependent upon some sort of social service&mdash;old age pensioners, widows and orphans, unemployment recipients, all these sorts of social services.  About half of our population are involved and dependent upon these social services.  They are a real lifeline to about one-sixth of our population.  I am talking not simply of the recipients of these benefits but of their families as well.  I think a rough calculation is that about one-sixth of our entire population is involved in these social services which, admittedly, are amongst the lowest in Western Europe.  I think we should all&mdash;every one of us&mdash;be ashamed of that situation.</P>
    <P>I should especially like the Minister to say what is intended in regard to the future of our social services.  I think they are still largely based on the poor law concept.  They have not changed fundamentally since 1911.  We still have a flat rate benefit based on a flat rate contribution for many of our social welfare benefits and, again, I think we are unique in Western Europe in that matter.  I think that in all Western European countries, they have the principle of a graduated benefit and a graduated contribution.  It seems to me that so long as we have this flat rate contribution and flat rate benefit, we are tied back to what can be afforded by the lowest paid worker.  I should like the Minister to say something of what is in his mind and what is his policy in this regard.</P>
    <P>As I said, we welcome this Bill.  We traditionally welcome any Bill which provides some improvement for social welfare recipients.  It is terrible that we have to wait until this time every year to give these benefits.  There may be administrative difficulties, but I am sure that if there were a will, these administrative difficulties could be overcome.  The real difficulty, I know, is the spending of the money.  We have had the situation that people have been trying to exist on these inadequate benefits and that we have been slow in making this improvement.  Having said <Col N="506" /> that, I may say, of course, that I welcome this Bill.  We shall not oppose it and we shall give every co-operation towards having it passed through this House quickly and having the benefits implemented from the date set out in the measure.</P>
    <P>There is one small point which I want to make&mdash;again, a note of welcome.  It is that, at last, the Minister has increased to £1,200 the limit of £800 for social insurance purposes.  It was last fixed in 1958. There have been quite a number of wage adjustments since that time.  I think the Irish Congress of Trade Unions nearly gave up in despair writing to the Minister on this problem of urging that he adjust the income limit in view of the successive increases in wages and salaries.  The Minister has been particularly slow in doing this.  However, he has come, in this Bill, to make this change.  He has also provided in this Bill that subsequent changes can be made by way of an order and I should like to press on him the importance of making these orders currently, when and if they become necessary.  It complicates matters for people when they find they come out of insurance because their income has exceeded the limit, due to a round of wage increases, come back in again, after a gap of a few years, and again go out.  I do not know that it is good administration at all on the part of the Minister.  It creates difficulties for the workers involved. It must create an awful lot of difficulties for the Department as well.  I think it would be sensible and good business if, in the future, the Minister made the necessary orders currently rather than to allow these sorts of difficulties to accumulate.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill and would be quite agreeable to its passing all Stages in this House today.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall be brief.  I echo what Senator Murphy has been saying.  This is too little and too late in many cases.  Nevertheless, I think we must recognise that the Minister is sincere in his desire to increase the level of assistance given. I think that, even in a short few years <Col N="507" /> ahead, we shall look back with horror and shame at the notion that a person who has the munificent income of over £26 a year is precluded from the full 10/- benefit foreseen here for old age pensioners, for widows and for the blind.</P>
      <P>I should like to have seen, with this Bill, a very definite raising of the limits of the means test if we cannot go as far as the removal of the means test because the notion that the increase for the blind, the aged and the widows is cut in half from 10/- to 5/- if their ordinary income exceeds 10/- a week seems to me monstrous.  I imagine it seems monstrous to everybody here.  It is something of which it would be well to be ashamed now rather than waiting for years to look back and wonder how we could have been so niggardly in the treatment of the very seriously underprivileged members of our community.</P>
      <P>The Estimates indicate that there will be an approximate increase of ten per cent of expenditure on Defence while the increase on Social Welfare is something like six per cent.  The Minister is well situated, as a former Minister for Defence, to know how one manages to get from the Government or the Department of Finance an increase of the order of ten per cent for Defence while it becomes possible to increase Social Welfare in the Estimate, by only about six per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Mention has been made of taxation. I want to say only one thing about it. Tobacco has been mentioned.  It always seems to me a curious contradiction that we spend a lot of money trying to discourage people from smoking, due to the danger of lung cancer, and so on.  Yet successive Ministers are afraid radically to discourage smoking by putting on such a tax that all but the most inveterate will reduce their purchases, because this thing which is recognised by the Department of Health as injurious to health is seen by the Minister for Finance as a lucrative form of tax.  It would, in fact, be possible to do double good by increasing taxation on tobacco to increase the intake of money and, perhaps, to <Col N="508" /> decrease the intake of smoke and nicotine.</P>
    <P>That is all I wish to say at this stage.  I think the Minister's intentions are good.  I think it is a pity&mdash;and I imagine the Minister feels the same way&mdash;that it has not proved possible to go far enough and it will not be very long before we feel very much ashamed of not being able to give the full 10/- increase, which is wretched enough, to all old age pensioners, widows and blind instead of putting up a barrier and cutting the increase in half if these unfortunate people happen to have an income in excess of £26. 6s.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>We can all welcome this Bill in the spirit in which Senator Murphy welcomed it.  We would all wish to see very much more provided.  We recognise the necessity for this, and we hope that the Government in the next Budget will be able to move much faster than they have.</P>
      <P>Some two years ago the Government set what could be a useful precedent. At that time they wished to give an increase of 1d per gallon on milk and put on a specific tax for that purpose.  That tax was 1d on the packet of cigarettes.  They linked the two closely together.  There was a great deal of resentment by the smokers to it.  I feel that if special selected luxury taxes were linked with direct increases in social welfare benefits, these luxury taxes would be much more readily accepted by the people concerned and would be a positive way of giving the real and direct increase that should be given in social welfare benefits to improve in some way the lot of those people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Any payments transferred from that luxury section to the social welfare section would, by and large, reduce the corresponding demand on imports. The spending of the social welfare recipient is far more likely to be on the necessaries of life, on what is produced at home, rather than on articles that have to be imported.  Consequently, at a time when we are feeling the strain of the balance of payments and seeing how difficult it is for us to <Col N="509" /> keep imports within bounds, any transfer payment from the luxury section to the social welfare section has the added merit also of helping to curb excessive imports.</P>
    <P>There is one other point.  Sections 8 and 9 make provision for the much heralded scheme to enable smallholders apply for and avail of unemployment assistance without many of the restrictions that prevailed in the past.  This was promised to us at the time of the Land Bill, and, on the surface, it appears something necessary and desirable.  But the figure involved seems an extraordinary one on the calculations I have been making here &mdash;the figure of an income of £20 for each £1 valuation.  By and large, an average acre of arable land has a valuation of £1.  The total net agricultural production last year was just around £200 million from 12 million plus acres.  Making some allowance for the 5 million other acres that make some contribution, you might say that the net output per arable acre is not more than £15.</P>
    <P>How then in the congested districts can the Government hold that the net income to the person working the acre is to be valued at £20?  To get a net income of £20 from an acre of agricultural land the gross output must be approximately at least of the order of £30 per acre.  With a gross output of £30 per acre the net remaining as labour income on that would be about 60 per cent of the £30 or something under £20 per acre.  Consequently, the Government in framing section 8 are assuming that there is a gross output of £30 per acre from each of the small-holdings coming within the scope of the Bill while the national output is about £18 an acre.</P>
    <P>I should like to hear from the Minister how he can justify this present figure.  It would seem to me extraordinary, using that figure, that it would prove of any benefit to the people concerned over and above having a direct valuation of their stock and assets and so on, which, of course, is a cumbersome and rather invidious way of doing it.  A valuation of around £10 would be much closer <Col N="510" /> the mark than the £20 being suggested by the Government.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Such as it is, I should like to welcome this Bill, particularly the increases and the new method of assessing the income of smallholders, which I feel owe something to the campaign by Peadar O'Donnell and the &ldquo;Save the West&rdquo; Committee, and also the higher limits. I should like to hear from the Minister why a limit on earnings is still thought necessary.  What are the reasons which today make the Minister feel it desirable that our social welfare scheme in Ireland should not be comprehensive, as in many other countries similarly placed where it is comprehensive and without an income limit?  I should like to ask the Minister in how many countries in Europe the social welfare scheme is not comprehensive and in how many countries in western Europe, if any, there is a system of having a limit of this kind.</P>
      <P>As regards the postponement of the operative dates, I should like to make the point that it is not alone bad social justice to postpone the payment but bad finance.  It has been a feature of our Budgets for a number of years past that the Minister for Finance imposes taxation forthwith and grants increases beyond what, in fact, he is prepared to provide the money for through taxation and produces these popular increases but gets out of the difficulty by postponing the payment until much later in the year, in respect of some increases, in fact, nine months later, so that he only has to budget for three months' increase in that year.  One result is that when he comes to face the Budget next year, before providing any increase in services, he finds a large part of the buoyancy of the revenue has been pre-empted by the Budget decisions of the previous year. So that, not alone on grounds of social justice but on grounds of financial considerations and good finance, I think this is a practice which should be reviewed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The main point I should like to make is that we do need to give serious consideration to the whole question of the share of our national output that <Col N="511" /> we devote to social welfare.  Over the years since 1957, this share has fallen, not fallen rapidly, but has fallen slightly and steadily year by year.  This is contrary to what is happening in other countries.  It is contrary to what one would expect to find in a country such as this, particularly during a period of relatively rapid economic growth, when it would have been appropriate to have allocated an increasing share of our growing wealth to social welfare, to what are called technically transfer payments.  It is particularly disturbing that in the <i>Second Programme for Economic Expansion</i> the provision made for these transfer payments or social welfare payments is shown to decline still further and that this still downward trend in the share of our resources that we allocate to this purpose is apparently to decline, and planned to decline still further when, instead, we should be planning to increase it.</P>
    <P>I believe that this is unnecessary.  We could, within the framework of the Programme, without going outside it, without over-straining our economy, but, by a reallocation of our resources, provide the means required, the resources needed, for a significant expansion of our social provisions beyond the limited provisions contemplated in the Programme.</P>
    <P>If we examine the make-up or breakdown of public expenditure in the Programme in the years to 1970, we find that a very large increase indeed, over 50 per cent, and double the rate of our national growth, is provided for public consumption, for the type of spending by which the Government use up resources in paying salaries and providing the services but not redistributive expenditure.  We find also the provision for subsidies shows a very big increase and here the Programme specifically mentions that this is liberal and has a contingency element.  There is leeway here in the subsidy figure to allow for resources being reallocated to social benefits, as well as leeway in the figure of public consumption, of Government direct expenditure.  Moreover, <Col N="512" /> the revenue calculations for non-tax revenue in the Programme show an extraordinarily modest increase and, in fact, unless there are good reasons for it, it would appear on the surface that the Government have underestimated the growth of this kind of revenue.  To my mind, the Programme should be reviewed with a view to reallocating the resources from Government consumption, from subsidies, to social welfare payments and taking credit for a rather more realistic growth in non-tax revenue.  I feel, realistically, within these limits it would be possible to reallocate resources sufficient even to as much as double the growth of social welfare benefits proposed in the period.</P>
    <P>I should like to emphasise that if we did that, if we went that far and attempted this reallocation of resources along lines much more appropriate to our social needs in this country, we would still only have brought the share of our national output that we devote to social welfare half-way up from its present level towards the level at which it stands in countries such as Austria and Italy.  I suggest Austria and Italy because they are countries whose standard of living and national wealth per head are similar to ours and I am not comparing ourselves with Britain, Germany, Sweden and other countries which are much wealthier and can afford much more lavish social welfare.</P>
    <P>I am saying that if we reallocated our resources in the way I have suggested, we might be able, by doubling the rate of growth the Government provides for in the Second Programme, to move halfway towards the level of expenditure which countries with much the same type of standard of living and the same national growth as ours at present afford.  God knows what they will be allocating in 1970.  Could we even achieve any reallocation of resources which would bring us half-way towards the expenditure that other countries have achieved which give a higher priority to social welfare than we have been doing and propose to do?</P>
    <P>Finally, I should like to ask that something much more radical should be done about reviewing our social <Col N="513" /> programme.  It has been said here today that every year since 1957 the Government have brought in a Social Welfare Bill, and so they have.  Every year there has been an extra half-crown, and this year something bigger. Every year there have been some improvements.  But this is tinkering. This is not the kind of radical review of the social programme we require. In the general election campaign, under certain pressure, the Taoiseach, with what appeared to be some reluctance, admitted that it might be possible to prepare a social programme but it would be very difficult.  I cannot see where the difficulty lies.  If you have a Government Department doing its job and reviewing the whole area of its activity imaginatively and with dynamism, not alone could this be done without difficulty but it would have been done some years ago.</P>
    <P>There are many things we need to look at.  Senator Murphy has mentioned one&mdash;this absurd, antiquated system of flat rate contributions and flat rate benefits, a system which is unjust to the better off worker who finds his standard of living, not reduced, not even halved, but cut to a fraction of its normal level in the event of illness or unemployment, a system which also drags down the whole level of the social fees to that level which can be afforded in the form of contributions by the lowest paid worker.  If one wanted to design a system which would inhibit an adequate social welfare system, which would ensure that you would not have it, you would have a flat rate system.</P>
    <P>As far as I know, this system is not very common, for the good reasons I have mentioned.  I know in one case that I have studied the particular area of social welfare, the official publication of the ILO shows only two countries as well as Ireland that apply flat rate contributions and flat rate benefits&mdash;the United Kingdom and Iceland.  I cannot speak for Iceland but anybody who is familiar with social welfare matters and with social planning will know that, apart from the health service, Britain lies behind most European countries in social welfare. <Col N="514" /> The system is antiquated.  Its level of benefits in the form of family allowances and provision for redundancy and things of this kind are out of date and inadequate.  Yet, we have persistently copied the British, copied the worst features of the British system and in this area we are still doing so.</P>
    <P>I feel that the Minister must review this, must examine the possibility&mdash; and there is no serious problem about this&mdash; of introducing a scheme with varying benefits and a scheme under which, I would suggest, the contribution to be paid by the lowest paid workers should be somewhat reduced and the contribution paid by the higher paid workers increased, perhaps even significantly, in order to provide a range tribution now being imposed increased significantly, in order to provide a range of benefits, at the lowest, better than they are and, at the highest, very much better than they are, to ensure that skilled workers who find themselves unemployed or sick will not be reduced to a standard of living a fraction of what they are used to because of the absence of a civilised social welfare scheme.  We lack such a scheme in this country.</P>
    <P>This flat rate system is one away from which even the United Kingdom is moving as regards retirement pensions.  They have introduced a graded system.  So that, if we do not hurry up we will not be just the third last in Europe, but the second last, and for all I know the Icelanders may have moved since I last looked at the picture and we may even find ourselves the most backward in this respect.</P>
    <P>I would also urge the Minister to look at the whole question of social welfare schemes, apart from payments of money.  Here we are seriously defective. One of the great contributions which the Fine Gael Party made in the last election was in putting forward proposals for an adequate domiciliary welfare scheme to help people in their own homes and to keep them out of the institutions into which we push them against social justice and, indeed, against even good economics because there is no more expensive <Col N="515" /> way to look after people than in an institution.  This is something the Minister should look at, in respect of which I should hope to see appropriate proposals in next year's Budget.</P>
    <P>The question of redundancy provisions may be something rather outside the scope of what we are talking about now.  If we are to have an economy in which modernisation of industry is to go ahead with the full co-operation of the workers, adequate redundancy provision should be built into the social code so that workers are not, as at the moment, left to fend for themselves with very limited unemployment benefits when redundancy occurs.  I know the Government are working on this and I would only urge speed.  It is not only socially but economically desirable, if we are to achieve the progress we need to achieve in the modernisation of our economy.</P>
    <P>To sum up, the Bill is useful. Everything it does is good and on that basis it should have our support. By and large, however, it is tinkering with the system and there is an absence here of vision, of imagination, of dynamism and constructive thinking. There is a gap which needs to be filled, a gap which the Minister and his Department should see about filling.  If they are not able to fill it, some steps should be taken by the Government to alter the structures which are inhibiting the, development of an adequate social welfare programme.</P>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Senators in general for the manner in which they have received this Bill and for the speedy way in which it has been dealt with here.  It is, as Senators are aware, a matter of urgency that it should be passed today and I wish to thank the Senators on the opposite side of the House for agreeing to give all Stages today.  The Bill was generally met in what I would consider a better spirit here than in the Dáil.  There was some appreciation on both sides of the House of the difficulties involved in improving our social welfare arrangements to the standard which we would all like them to achieve.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="516" /> It was stated, and I agree, that there was a clear indication at the time of the general election that the Government were expected to improve social welfare benefits.  I will not pursue that but I could say with Senator Dolan that there was hardly any need for this in the case of the present Government because we have over the years given annual proof of our concern for the people who have to depend on social welfare.  We have been giving increases in difficult times and effecting relative improvements in the rates of payment of all the schemes of social welfare having regard to the cost of living in so far as it is indicated by the Consumer Price Index.  It was only to be expected that now that we have reached the stage where the economy appears to be expanding satisfactorily, we should increase the allocations of money for these purposes.</P>
    <P>In regard to the case made by Senator FitzGerald that the percentage of our national income devoted to social welfare has been decreasing since 1957, I do not know where he got those figures.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>From the national accounts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>But they do not tally with the information at my disposal. The gross expenditure on social welfare, exclusive of administration costs, expressed as a percentage of gross national product has not shown any great tendency to decline over those years.  I have these percentages since 1955-56 and I think I should place them on the records of the House.  In 1955-56, gross expenditure on social welfare, exclusive of administration costs, as a percentage of gross national product was 4.7 per cent; in 1956-57 it was 4.9 per cent; in 1957-58, 5.2 per cent; in 1958-59, 5 per cent; in 1959-60, 4.8 per cent; in 1960-61, 4.7 per cent; in 1961-62, 5 per cent; in 1962-63, 4.9 per cent; in 1963-64 5.2 per cent; and in 1964-65, 5.1 per cent.  The forecast of gross national product in the year 1965-66 is £1,016 millions and at the rate of expenditure provided for in this Bill, the gross expenditure on social welfare expressed as a percentage of <Col N="517" /> that amount in a full year will be at the rate of 6.1 per cent.</P>
      <P>Therefore, I do not think there has been any significant or noticeable reduction in this figure.  In any case one cannot very well decide that this percentage should be kept at any definite rate.  Certain rates of payment are provided for the different social welfare schemes and expenditure will depend, to a certain extent at any rate, on the state of the economy, for instance, on the level of unemployment in the year.  As I have said, the forecast for the coming year is 6.1 per cent and that is a significant advance to make in a single year.  Apart from that, the total increased expenditure on social welfare provided for in this Bill in a full financial year is £9.53 million.  In addition to that, there are the increases being granted in the other transfer income schemes, the disabled person's maintenance allowance, and infectious diseases allowance, which bring this amount up to £10 million. This shows that in this Bill we are making provision for an increase in the gross expenditure on social welfare of 19.3 per cent in this one year.  That is a major step to take in one year in increased transfer of income to the people depending on social welfare.</P>
      <P>I do not think it gives any indication of smugness or complacency, as was suggested.  Certainly I am not in any way complacent about the level of our social welfare and I do not think this Government have shown any indication of that over the years.  Even in the difficult circumstances in which we found ourselves on the change of Government in 1957 and in spite of the urgent and compelling necessity, in so far as it was possible to do so, of rehabilitating the economy and promoting economic expansion, we found it possible in every year except one to make substantial provision for increases in social welfare in our annual Budget, with the result that at every stage since 1957 it has been possible to show that the rates of payment under every one of the social welfare schemes had made some slight advance on the cost of living as indicated by the Consumer Price Index.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="518" />
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>According to the Minister's figures, in five of the eight years, the percentage fell and last year it was lower than it was in 1957-58.  Could the Minister say what the percentage is expected to be in 1970, according to his figures?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>I am dealing with the Social Welfare Bill, 1965.  In regard to 1970, our undertaking in relation to social welfare is very clear and explicit. It was expressed by the Taoiseach that it was our intention to devote an increasing proportion of the rising national resources to the expansion and improvement of social welfare. That is the principle on which we are operating and which we are implementing in this Bill.  Senator FitzGerald will see further examples of our adherence to that principle in the coming years.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>That is not what the Second Programme proposes, but, if the Government are proposing to review the Second Programme upwards in this respect, that is good news for us all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not fully agree at all with Senator FitzGerald's interpretation of the Second Programme. However, the Second Programme is not before the Seanad at the moment; the Social Welfare Bill is.  It is the immediate implementation of the undertaking given by the Taoiseach during the election, an undertaking which the people accepted because it was so much in character with the previous record of the Fianna Fáil Party.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>It took an election to get the undertaking out of the Taoiseach, though.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad Senator D. J. O'Sullivan agrees with the principle of a means test as applied to the assistance classes but I find it very hard to reconcile that with the indication&mdash;at least with what I think was an indication &mdash;of some objection to the giving of an extra increase to those whose means are under £26.5/- per annum. It is not a case, as I explained in the <Col N="519" /> Dáil, of giving a 10/- increase and then deciding to give less to those whose means are over £26.  5/- per annum.  It is a case of having a sum of money available sufficient to give 5/- all round to social assistance recipients generally and a decision then to give an extra 5/- increase to those in greatest need.  Senator D.J. O'Sullivan mentioned the desirability of giving something more to those old age pensioners, in particular, who have no means and who are living alone. We are, I think, taking a first step towards that in this Bill in giving an extra allocation to certain categories whose need is greater than others.</P>
      <P>With regard to the question of delay in implementing the increases, Senators will surely realise that there is a difficulty in implementing them straight away.  It takes time to make all the necessary administrative arrangements.  Even now we have to take special steps to have this Bill enacted and signed by the President in time to make the social assistance payments on 1st August as provided in the Bill.  It has only been possible to bring the Bill before the Seanad today. Payments are due to be made as from 1st August.  Obviously then, we are acting with the greatest possible expedition. If I could have been here last week, I should have been here, and I would not be here today.  It is unavoidable that this delay should take place.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In regard to social insurance payments, the new stamps have to be printed and put on sale.  Employers are entitled to notice as to the new stamping arrangements.  There is also the question of printing books and so on. All these take time and it is not administratively feasible to make these payments any earlier.  It is a fact, of course, as Senator Garret FitzGerald said, that this results in some of the buoyancy of revenue that would occur at the beginning of the next financial year being already foreclosed on by the Department of Social Welfare, but that is not an unsual feature.  State servants have also managed to foreclose on quite an amount of this <Col N="520" /> buoyancy of revenue by means of conciliation and arbitration awards.  That has been one of the difficulties, in my experience as Minister for Social Welfare, in trying to get money for social welfare purposes at Budget time. The fact is the buoyancy on which I had been counting was to a large extent swallowed up and I do not think there is anything particularly objectionable in the Minister for Social Welfare, as well as others, having to get some of this buoyancy in advance.</P>
    <P>The question of wage related benefits is one which has to be considered. It is all very well to say that the flat rate benefits provided now are miserable and represent a drastic decrease in the standard of living for all but the lowest paid workers, but the fact is that these benefits were as much as could be provided, up to this at any rate.  We have now reached the stage at which the unemployment or disability benefit for a person in the lower wage group, £8 a week or under, will represent something over 60 per cent of the wage for a man and his wife; for a man, his wife and two children, the benefit will represent 77.6 per cent of the £8 wage taking account of the insurance contribution.</P>
    <P>It may be that we have reached the stage now where further increases in benefits and contributions might be related only to the higher wage rates. Perhaps we can gradually move towards a wage related scheme.  That is obviously a desirable thing but, while the decrease of the standard of living for a single man, or a married man with no dependent children, is fairly severe, it is lessened in the case of those with dependent children because of the structure of the benefits which provides for increases in respect of dependent children.  While I admit there is a serious lowering of the standard of living in certain cases, it is not as bad as some people allege in the case of those with families, and they are those most in need.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to this statement, which is bandied about, that we are the second worst country in Europe in so far as the percentage of <Col N="521" /> our national income devoted to social welfare is concerned.  First of all, it is a fact that the information available is completely out of date.  The latest figures are those for 1960 and in addition it is by no means certain that we are comparing like with like in every case.  It could be fairly easily established, in fact, that that is not so, and, if a full comparison were made between this and other countries, we would find that statement one that cannot be substantiated.</P>
    <P>The question of delay in raising the limit for compulsory insurance of non-manual workers from £800 to £1,200 was raised.  There was a delay.  Senator Garret FitzGerald asked what was the reason why there should be any limit at all in this matter.  Strictly speaking, from the point of view of social welfare, there is not any reason at all. The Social Insurance Fund would benefit, in fact, by the inclusion of people in the upper wages brackets, but the difficulty that arose in regard to this matter was the fact that the middle income group, or one section of it, was described, for the purposes of the Health Acts, as people who are insured under the Social Insurance Acts.  As Senators know, for the past two or three years a Select Committee was sitting on the health services and a decision on the raising of the limit for compulsory insurance of non-manual workers was postponed while that Committee was in session.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DenisOSullivan" hpid="Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. D.J. O'Sullivan</NameTxt>
      <P>Sitting?  It was recumbent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>It was in session, as far as I know, for practically the full period of the previous Dáil.  The repercussions it would have on the health services was the only reason for the delay in raising this limit.  In future the position under the provisions of this Bill is that this limit can be raised by order, the order to be laid before the two Houses of the Oireachtas for confirmation. That should make for speedier adjustments in future.  It should be possible to keep pace with the increase in rates of remuneration.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="522" /> Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill considered in Committee.</P>
    <P>Sections 1 to 7, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 8.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 8 stand part of the Bill&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Could the Minister indicate how the figure of £20, as a reasonable net income remaining from land valued at £1 poor law valuation, was arrived at because, in my Second Reading speech, I showed that it is substantially above the national level.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry I forgot to refer to the Senator's remarks on this matter.  A national farm survey was carried out in 1955/1956, and 1957/ 1958, and in Table 3 of that survey figures are given for family farm income per £1 valuation of land and buildings for subsistence farms.  The figure there per £1 valuation of land and buildings for subsistence farms in the 5-15 acres group is £17.9 and in the 15-30 acres group, £18.4.  Under this Bill I propose to take a figure £20 per £1 land valuation only.  I think that is reasonable.  The figures I have given were for ten years ago and they were for lands and buildings.  Therefore £20 per £1 land valuation seems reasonable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>It should be observed that agricultural prices for the type of produce coming from the small farm have not changed in that period, certainly not in any way commensurate with the increase in money valuations.  Neither have output figures changed.  The latest figures given in the Budget Statistics of 1963 show there was only ? per cent change between 1958 and today so that it seems that the £20 figure for £1 valuation is the maximum.  In other words, there is certainly no concession in that figure and therefore if any investigation of income has been made by other means and if that investigation were to establish the true income, that true income should be substantially in accord with <Col N="523" /> the figure revealed by the national survey.  Therefore, on the Minister's statement, it should be substantially in accord with the £20 per £1 valuation as revealed by the Minister.  How then, can we say that anything has been done or anything given or that any increased cost should be incurred by the Government due to this concession?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>The figures I have given were the average family farm figures, not the maximum.  I think it should be clear that there are probably some who are producing less. Some of these may be people who have fallen victim to the disincentive effect of the existing system of assessing means for unemployment assistance purposes and there are also obviously a number who are extracting more from their land than the figures suggested here and they are probably people who, by their own industry, have put themselves outside the scope of unemployment assistance and, as I said earlier, people who have succumbed to the disincentive effect will now lose the advantage they gained in the scales of payment of unemployment assistance.  Also, as I have pointed out, this is based on the per £1 valuation of land and buildings. The £20 per £1 valuation I am taking in this Bill is for land only, excluding the valuation of the buildings.  I think it would have been a reasonable figure to accept even at that time when the National Farm Survey was taken and I think it is a fairly favourable one to take at present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>If people are to be penalised under this, they have a five-year period in which they can opt for the old system.  On the Minister's presentation of the case, it would seem that most of those on the western seaboard will opt for the old system.  The Minister has rightly said that averages are very dangerous, but in this case I think it should be conceded that we have several very fine farms in regions where milk production is possible, where creameries and other facilities are supplied, but in the congested districts, such facilities are not available, <Col N="524" /> and if the Minister were to examine the farm survey tables by regions, he would find that the regions in the west, in Connacht and so on, had an output very much below the output in Munster, due to the presence of these facilities for intensified working.  Therefore, I contend that the figure of £20 is likely to be very much in excess of what the average smallholder in Connacht or in the congested districts is earning today from his land.</P>
      <P>The Government should use the provisions of this Bill to have another look at this figure which can be altered by order.  The Minister may have to invoke the order within the next year to alter this figure which should be drastically altered.  I suggest that not more than £10 per £1 valuation is likely to provide any incentive and likely to get people away from the old system and on to the new system which is preferable in every way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="KevinBoland" hpid="Mr. K. Boland Mr. K. Boland">
      <NameTxt>Mr. K. Boland</NameTxt>
      <P>These average figures, as I said, relate to subsistence farming, that is, the lowest pattern of farm working, not to the more intensive pattern of farming to which the Senator referred.  I am aware that many smallholders are drawing unemployment assistance at the moment who are not earning £20 per £1 valuation from their land, but in view of the fact that side by side with them there are smallholder neighbours who have placed themselves outside the scope of unemployment assistance, it appears to be reasonable to assume. initially at any rate, that it is possible for them to raise their production to this level.  It is a reasonable figure to take, for a start at any rate, and as Senator Quinlan says, it can be reviewed in the light of experience, but personally I doubt if there will be any strong case that can be made for a reduction of the figure.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 9 to 19, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Social Welfare (Miscellaneous" RHead="Provisions) Bill, 1965: Earlier Signature">
    <Title>Public Business. - Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1965: Earlier Signature.</Title>
    <Col N="525" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That, pursuant to subsection 2º of section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad Éireann concur with the Government in a request to the President to sign the Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill, 1965, on a date which is earlier than the fifth day after the date on which the Bill shall have been presented to him.</P>
      <P>This motion is necessary because of the fact that the payments are to date from August 1st and it is essential that the Bill become law before that date.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Finance Bill, 1965" RHead="(Certified Money Bill): Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Finance Bill, 1965    (Certified Money Bill):    Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. J. Lynch) Jack Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. J. Lynch)</NameTxt>
      <P>I understand that there is agreement that Nos. 5, 6 and 7 be taken together on Second Reading.  Therefore I propose to deal in this speech with the Finance Bill, the Prices (Amendment) Bill and the Appropriation Bill, and to take them in that order.</P>
      <P>The provisions in the Finance Bill may be grouped into three broad categories.  There are, first, those sections which incorporate in permanent legislation the matters referred to in the Financial Resolutions passed in Dáil Éireann on budget day.  Secondly, the Bill makes legislative provision for other proposals of which notice was given in the Financial Statement. Thirdly, it deals with some matters which were not mentioned in the budget statement and I shall refer to these in the order in which they occur.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The explanatory memorandum, which accompanied the text of the Bill as introduced in Dáil Éireann, indicates briefly the purpose of each of the sections.  I do not propose to occupy the time of the Seanad by covering this ground again and I will confine myself to a general outline of each of the ten parts of the Bill.  A number of amendments were <Col N="526" /> made to the Bill during its passage through Dáil Éireann, including the introduction of four new sections.  I propose to draw the attention of the Seanad to the more important of these in the course of my review.</P>
    <P>Part I deals with income taxation and contains eleven sections, of which sections 10 and 11 were added on Committee Stage in Dáil Éireann.  The first section imposes income tax and sur-tax for the year 1965-66 at the existing rates.  Sections 2 and 6 provide reliefs for industry; the former shortens from five years to one year the period for writing-off capital expenditure on scientific research relating to a trade, while the latter extends our existing exports relief in accordance with the recommendations of the National Industrial Economic Council.  Section 3 further implements the principle of &ldquo;one taxpayer, one charge&rdquo; by providing for separate assessments under Schedules A and B where a property changes hands.  Sections 4 and 5 extend the rights of appeal of both the taxpayer and the Revenue and empower an inspector of taxes to admit late appeals in certain circumstances. Sections 7 to 9 are concerned with technical amendments in preparation for consolidation.  The remaining two sections in this part, sections 10 and 11, were, as I have mentioned, the result of amendments which I proposed on the Committee Stage of the Bill and which had for their purpose the encouragement of savings.  Section 10 increases from £25 to £50 the amount of deposit interest which is disregarded for tax purposes.  Section 11 raises from £15 to £50 the limit below which returns of interest are not required from banks and other financial institutions.</P>
    <P>Part II of the Bill deals with customs and excise matters.  The budget increases in duties on beer, spirits, hydrocarbon oils, tobacco and wine are covered in Sections 12 to 16. Section 17, which was not mentioned in the budget speech, makes it necessary to obtain the consent of the Minister for Industry and Commerce before special duty-free import facilities may be granted for goods for re-export. Section 18 prescribes revised rates of <Col N="527" /> excise duties payable by pawnbrokers following the Pawnbrokers Act, 1964. Section 19, which was the subject of a Financial Resolution at the Committee Stage in Dáil Éireann, is intended to rationalise and simplify our road-tax system by doing away with quarterly road-tax licences for £3 or less.</P>
    <P>Part III of the Bill, which deals with death duties, has attracted a good deal of comment, some of which was, perhaps, due to misconception arising from the technical nature of the provisions. I have tried to make it clear that the basic purpose of this part of the Bill is one to which, I think, no one can take exception&mdash;that is to ensure that persons of means will make their fair contribution to the revenue from death duties and that they will be prevented from entering into arrangements designed to shift the burden to other sections of the community which are less able to bear it.</P>
    <P>Sections 20 to 23 are designed to counter avoidance by way of the transfer of assets to companies, the establishment of discretionary trusts, the purchase of foreign immovable property other than land and the determination of settlements by the purchase by the life tenant of the interest in remainder.</P>
    <P>Section 24 deals with the liability of death benefits payable under superannuation schemes.  Section 25 is concerned with the aggregation, with the deceased's other assets, of property such as the proceeds of certain insurance policies effected by the deceased under the Married Women's Status Act, 1957.  Both of these sections were the subject of severe criticism, both inside and outside the House, in the form in which they were originally introduced.  The criticisms were directed, in the main, to the effect which these sections would have had in the case of estates of persons of moderate means.  In consideration of the many representations I received and in fulfilment of an undertaking which I gave on Committee Stage in Dáil Éireann, section 24 has been redrafted and section 25A has been introduced as a new section at the <Col N="528" /> Report Stage of the Bill.  The purpose of the changes in section 24 is to clarify the position in the case of noncontributory superannuation schemes and of death benefits provided by a company for a director's dependants. The original exemption limit of £5,000 is preserved and a measure of marginal relief is introduced for death benefits slightly above that figure.  Section 25A will provide substantial relief in relation to insurance policies indefeasibly vested in a donee more than five years before the death of the assured.</P>
    <P>Section 26, in its original form, extended from three years to five years the period prior to death within which gifts <i>inter vivos</i> and property released from trust will be liable to estate duty. It also provided that gifts or releases made three years or more before the passing of the Bill are not affected and it raised the exemption limit for such gifts from £100 to £500.  At the Committee Stage of the Bill in Dáil Éireann, I modified these provisions considerably by introducing tapering provisions in the case of deaths occurring in the third, fourth or last year of the five-year period and by providing for marginal relief where the gift exceeds the exemption limit of £500 by a comparatively small amount.</P>
    <P>Section 27 makes it clear that the exemption from estate duty applying to gifts in consideration of marriage is to be confined to the parties to the marriage and to issue of the marriage. In my budget speech I referred to abatements of estate duty on benefits to widows and children and to the abolition of legacy and succession duty in certain cases.  These reliefs are implemented by sections 28 and 29 respectively, except that on Report Stage in the Dáil I raised the abatements for dependants from £150, as I had originally announced, to £250 in respect of the widow and from £100 to £150 in respect of a child.</P>
    <P>Part IV contains only section 30 which deals with stamp duties and provides exemption from capital duty and transfer duty in cases of amalgamation or reconstruction of companies.</P>
    <P>All the sections in Part V, which is concerned with corporation profits tax, <Col N="529" /> were referred to in the Budget speech. Section 31 continues for a further three years the temporary exemption from corporation profits tax of certain public utility companies, building societies and the Agricultural Credit Corporation Ltd.  The extension of exports relief granted for income tax purposes by section 6 of the Bill is applied for the purposes of corporation profits tax by section 32.</P>
    <P>Section 33 provides that the treatment of the profits of a parent company for corporation profits tax purposes under section 14 of the Finance Act, 1944, shall not apply to accounting periods ending after 31 December, 1964.  Section 34 extends to corporation profits tax the provisions governing the taxation of profits from lettings of buildings and land, which are contained in Part IX of the Finance Act, 1963.</P>
    <P>Part VI of the Bill introduces certain minor changes in relation to turnover tax.  Section 35 makes it clear that turnover tax is payable by clubs on receipts from sales to members. Section 36 confirms the liability of persons legally entitled to money from taxable activities, even though they may not have carried on the activities themselves.  This section also provides an exemption limit of £150 a month below which registration is not obligatory for certain small concerns, instead of the limits of £250 and £100 in force at present.  Retail sales by farmers and fishermen of their own produce will, under the provisions of sections 36 and 37, be liable if the proceeds are in excess of £150 in each of two successive months.  The concluding two sections, sections 38 and 39, deal with the taxpayer's right of appeal from decisions of the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
    <P>Part VII is concerned with profits from dealing in or developing land. Under the existing provisions, that is under section 6 of the Finance Act, 1935, liability to tax on the proceeds of sale or demise arises only where the land has been acquired with the intention of reselling or developing it. Under this arrangement taxable gains have been escaping taxation since it is <Col N="530" /> virtually impossible for the Revenue to dispute a taxpayer's statement as to what his intentions were.  The purpose of the provisions of this part of the Bill, covering sections 40 to 47, is to ensure that if lands are sold or leased after they have been developed, or after arrangements for their development have been made, the profits will be taxable.</P>
    <P>Normal sales of agricultural land between farmers are not included and the Bill also provides specific exemption for profits arising on the sale of a person's own residence, notwithstanding certain development.  I introduced an amendment at the Committee Stage in Dáil Éireann to ensure that certain developments of farm buildings would not attract liability to tax.  A number of additional amendments were introduced on Report State with the intention of improving the efficiency of this part of the Bill in achieving its purpose which, as I have indicated, is broadly to catch profits arising to a person who embarks on a scheme of profit-making involving the development of land.</P>
    <P>Part VIII secures that, in accordance with the principle of &ldquo;one taxpayer, one charge&rdquo;, each member of a partnership will be assessed according to his share of the profits instead of the partnership being regarded as one unit for tax purposes.</P>
    <P>The necessity for Part IX of the Bill arises from certain weaknesses in Part IX of the Finance Act, 1963, which deals with the taxation of profits from lettings of buildings and land.  Sections 55 to 59 are designed to bring within the tax net receipts by property owners which are in reality of the nature of rent, but which, under the existing general law, would fall to be treated as capital receipts.</P>
    <P>Part X of the Bill relates to miscellaneous matters which, with one exception, are dealt with, section by section, in the explanatory memorandum. I might refer in particular to sections 61 and 62 which deal with the extension of the period of double initial allowances and mining relief respectively.  Section 62A is a new <Col N="531" /> section which I introduced on the Report Stage in response to representations which I have received.  It provides that gifts of money made to the Minister for Finance for purposes for which public moneys are provided, will be deductible in computing the donor's liability to tax.</P>
    <P>Section 63 provides for payments on account of income tax or corporation profits tax where the Special Commissioners postpone or adjourn the hearing of an appeal.  Section 64 and the Third Schedule deal with repeals and provide for the abolition of the 25 per cent rate of stamp duty on acquisitions of land by non-nationals since the passing of the Land Act, 1965.  The remaining sections are self-explanatory.</P>
    <P>This is just a brief outline of the objects of this year's Finance Bill.  I shall be glad to deal with any points of detail on Committee Stage.</P>
    <P>I now propose to speak about the Prices (Amendment) Bill.</P>
    <P>In brief, the Bill will insert provisions in the 1958 Act to enable the Government, if they satisfied that the condition of the national economy is such that it is necessary for the time being to maintain prices at a stable level, to make an order empowering the Minister for Industry and Commerce to do any or all of the following things:</P>
    <P>(a) to carry out an investigation of all prices of articles of any description and of all charges for the rendering of any service;</P>
    <P>(b) to require any person connected with any of these investigations to furnish any relevant information in his possession or any relevant document in his power or control;</P>
    <P>(c) to require manufacturers, wholesalers and importers to notify the Minister of any proposed increases in the prices charged by them for their commodities;</P>
    <P>(d) to fix the maximum price at which any article of any description may be sold and the maximum charge which may be made for the rendering of any service:</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="532" /> (e) to impose a standstill on prices and charges in relation to all or any prices of all or any articles and in relation to the charges for the rendering of any service;</P>
    <P>(f) to appoint an Advisory Body or Bodies, with appropriate powers, to enquire into any prices or charges, or to advise the Minister as to the prices or charges which should be investigated.</P>
    <P>Any order made under these provisions will have a maximum life of six months, but it may be renewed.</P>
    <P>For the purpose of the investigation of prices and charges, the Minister wishes to be able to use the machinery of Prices Advisory Committees as constituted by the 1958 Act.  As that Act cannot be related to a temporary condition of the economy a permanent amending Act is necessary.  The Bill, therefore, provides for the setting up of Prices Advisory Committees to investigate any prices or charges; a consequential amendment of the Act is also being carried out by the Bill to extend the scope of orders, fixing maximum prices and charges, which the Minister may make on receipt of Prices Advisory Committees' reports.</P>
    <P>To summarise the position, in this Bill the Minister is seeking very flexible powers to be able to make a speedy examination of prices at all levels and to make orders, when necessary, controlling prices at their various levels.  The Minister is also seeking powers to establish Prices Advisory Bodies and an extension of the scope of Prices Advisory Committees' inquiries, which is limited in the 1958 Act.</P>
    <P>The third Bill I propose to deal with in this speech is the Appropriation Bill, 1965.</P>
    <P>This year's Appropriation Bill makes the usual provisions for issues from the Central Fund and appropriations to particular services.  The only novel provision is section 4 which relates to foreign borrowings.  It had always been assumed that there were no limitations on the currencies in which the State could borrow.  In fact, direct State borrowing in dollars was made in New York in 1927 and under <Col N="533" /> the Marshall Aid Agreement in 1949-52.  The law officers advised, however, in connection with the Aer Lingus dollar borrowings last December, for which an amendment of the State Guarantees Act, 1954, was necessary, that the State had no power to borrow in a currency other than its own.  As the possibility of external borrowing by the Government is mentioned in the <i>Second Programme for Economic Expansion</i> and inquiries are currently being made, it is desirable to ensure that, should the need arise, there would be no lack of statutory authority for such borrowing.</P>
    <P>The Finance and Appropriation Bills cover such a wide sweep of Government activity&mdash;in relation both to taxation and expenditure&mdash;that their introduction together in the Seanad this year provides a good opportunity for a discussion of the economic and financial situation.  I have no doubt that Senators will avail themselves of this opportunity.</P>
    <P>It is not necessary for me to review the current situation in detail.  That was done in the Dáil a fortnight ago by the Taoiseach.  I intend to sketch it very broadly, and to refer to the measures taken to deal with it, for the purpose of establishing the right perspective. In particular, without in any way detracting from the need for effective action to correct the adverse trends&mdash;indeed this need is obvious and has been generally understood&mdash;I want to dispel any notion of a crisis. We are, I hope, a mature society.  What we have to do at present is to make adjustments in our economy so that we can continue our advance without running into serious trouble.  There is no occasion for panic or sensationalism.</P>
    <P>Managing our economic affairs is a much more complex and difficult matter than, say, driving a car is for the individual.  Impediments and dangers, unforeseen as well as foreseen, have constantly to be contended with. Never to run any risk at all would imply an over-cautious attitude, which would overtax everyone's patience. Reasonable risks must be run for the sake of developing the economy and <Col N="534" /> increasing employment.  When, however, the dangers become too threatening, there has to be some change of course&mdash;but this should neither be too late nor too drastic so that we may continue safely on the road rather than be plunged in the ditch.</P>
    <P>In comparison with the experience of other countries, many of them more highly developed than we are, Ireland has enjoyed since 1958 a period of sustained economic growth averaging over 4 per cent per annum.  The number in employment in industries and services has been raised by some 50,000. The rate of emigration has been halved. The population has begun to increase again.  The numbers at secondary school and university have been rising steeply.</P>
    <P>In the early years of the First Programme, our economic advance was achieved without incurring a deficit in the balance of payments.  In fact, official reserves accumulated as a result of foreign investment in Ireland. We were able to make good progress, independently of external resources, largely because there was unused capacity in Irish industry at that time.  Recently, however, economic growth has depended more directly on new investment, and external resources have had to be drawn into use by incurring balance of payments deficits on a rising scale&mdash;£13 million in 1962, £22 million in 1963 and £31 million in 1964.  These deficits were more than covered by capital inflows, so that the external reserves continued to rise. Apart from £25 million of direct borrowing in 1964 (about one-fourth of the total inflow for that year), the capital inflow was an independent voluntary affair, expressing active external interest in our development potentialities.  It was judged right to use this inflow to promote economic growth rather than add to reserves. That it was being so used was indicated by the rise in the ratio of gross capital formation to GNP from 15 per cent in 1960 to almost 21 per cent last year.</P>
    <P>At the same time, we were concerned that total demand should not rise so high as to cause unduly large deficits in the balance of payments&mdash;deficits which might not be capable of being <Col N="535" /> met continuously from capital inflows and a reasonable use of reserves.  The 1964 deficit of £31 million, though more than covered by the unprecedentedly high capital inflow of that year, was well above the average deficit of £16 million contemplated in the Second Programme, which covers the years 1964-1970.  Our policy, therefore, for 1965&mdash;in line with the recommendations of the OECD&mdash;was, as I said in my Budget speech, to try to keep the deficit from rising above £31 million and even to reduce it, if this was compatible with the maintenance of a 4 per cent growth rate.</P>
    <P>As things have turned out, this policy objective seems to be incapable of achievement this year.  For reasons I shall mention in a moment, we are faced with a much bigger deficit in the balance of payments which must be corrected.  Our growth rate will fall below 4 per cent this year but, I should emphasise, there is no risk of growth being stopped; it is expected that we will register an improvement in national production of about 3 per cent.  The capital inflow has dropped sharply under the impact of the restrictive measures taken in the United States and Britain. The possibility of direct borrowing on favourable terms in the United States has been upset by a Presidential order removing our immunity from the interest equalisation tax.  Our external reserves, which the OECD rightly said could decline somewhat without cause for concern, have in fact fallen from £242 million at end-December last to £208 million at end-June.</P>
    <P>What accounts for this adverse change?  The answer is a combination of external and internal factors.  On the external side, there is the growing international tightness of capital and credit according as the United States and Britain drive on towards reducing their overall balance of payments deficits, while France and some other countries continue to accumulate reserves without making any special arrangements to facilitate foreign lending.  A second external factor is the continued operation of the British <Col N="536" /> import surcharge which affects a high proportion of Irish industrial exports. In fact, we rely on expansion of industrial exports as one of the chief points in our development programme; an expansion of 24 per cent was achieved in 1964.  We have managed merely to hold the line this year by offsetting part of the surcharge.</P>
    <P>Amongst the internal factors we have, first, a purely temporary one&mdash; a reduction in exports of live cattle, which, with the mark-time in industrial exports, is responsible for an actual fall in total exports this year. There has been a big increase in cattle stocks but the animals are still too young for export and, as the June trade figures showed, are only now beginning to swell our export figures.</P>
    <P>Imports in June amounted to just £31 million, exports to £19 million and the import excess to £12 million.  The import excess was £1.6 million less than in June 1964, whereas in the preceding four months it was £6½ million greater on average than in the corresponding months of 1964.</P>
    <P>We can draw some comfort from the fact that the import excess in June, although still very high, was the lowest since January.  Imports slackened off somewhat as compared with earlier months and were £2 million below the June 1964 level.  Exports were still marginally less than the June, 1964 figure but showed a substantial recovery from the depressed level of the early months of this year.  While no details are available as yet of the composition of the June trade returns, figures for shipments by sea and air show that cattle contributed to the increase in exports.  Shipments amounted to 28,600 head in June, 1965, or 9,000 more than the May, 1965 figure of 19,600.  The improvement in cattle shipments has continued in July.  In the absence of commodity returns, it is not possible to assess whether manufactured exports in June have begun to resume the momentum which was lost in the earlier months of 1965.</P>
    <P>The expected improvement in cattle exports of itself will not be enough to right our trade figures and bring the balance of payments deficit down to tolerable size.  The deficit still looks <Col N="537" /> like being in the neighbourhood of £50 million for 1965.  At the same time as exports have fallen, imports have risen under the impact of higher incomes, increased credit, and higher public and private expenditure.</P>
    <P>This situation is being tackled in a number of ways.  A restraint has been imposed on the overall increase in bank credit this year and priority is being reserved for productive purposes. Bank deposit and lending rates are being held at a high level to encourage saving and discourage less essential spending.  Further incentives to increase exports have been announced.  Public expenditure is being reviewed to bring it as close as possible to the Second Programme figures.  Savings incentives have been improved; the Finance Bill doubles the tax exemption for interest on deposits in the savings banks and commercial banks.  Hire purchase restrictions have been introduced to check the rise in expenditure on less essential imports. The Government have initiated talks with trade unions and employers' organisations to try to secure a realisation of the need to avoid a further raising of money incomes while the present difficulties are being dealt with.  I have already outlined the purposes of the Prices Bill.  The possibility of raising some external capital for development needs by direct Government borrowing is being explored. Developments are being closely watched so that, if necessary, further action can be taken to safeguard the long-term interests of the economy and sustain the growth of production and employment.</P>
    <P>Clearly, the difficulties of a small country, which relies for a moderate rate of economic development on selling most of its increased production on export markets and on supplementing its savings by recourse to external resources, are accentuated by the present international tendency towards contraction of capital supplies and slackening of the rate of growth of trade and output.  In part, this tendency must be ascribed to imperfect economic co-operation&mdash;for example, to the extra difficulty created by some countries having to reduce deficits <Col N="538" /> very quickly while others continue to have surpluses and yet operate their economies below capacity.  An increase in international liquidity would ease this problem without seriously delaying or discouraging the achievement of long-term balance by the present deficit countries.</P>
    <P>However, we have to take the international situation as we find it and do what we can, not merely to correct our balance of payments, but to maintain a high rate of economic progress. Because of our small home market, it is mainly through exports that economic expansion must be sought.  It is particularly important at the present time that there should be a vigorous expansion of exports.  This depends fundamentally on the cost and quality of our goods and services being competitive. It depends also on our having advantageous terms of access to export markets.</P>
    <P>Earlier this week, with the Taoiseach and my colleagues, the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries and the Minister for Industry and Commerce, I was in London for trade discussions with the British Government.  Britain is our principal market and up to now our trade relations with Britain have been governmed by agreements which themselves go back to 1938 but which are based on the preferential system formalised in 1932 at Ottawa.  It has become increasingly clear that in recent years this is no longer an adequate basis for our trade relations. World developments have run ahead of the preferential system and nowadays trade relations, particularly in the matter of tariffs and quotas, are either determined multilaterally under the auspices of GATT or regionally in the context of a free trade area, customs union or common market.  Indeed, events have so overtaken our trade agreements with Britain that, already in some cases, the members of EFTA enjoy lower tariffs entering Britain than our so-called preferential rate of duty.  An important example of this is the duty on man-made fibres which is now lower for, say, Sweden and Denmark than it is for Ireland.  The deterioration in our position occurs <Col N="539" /> also in the realm of agriculture where the forms of support given to British producers and the restrictions applied to imports into Britain have resulted in the erosion of benefits we once enjoyed in the British market.</P>
    <P>We cannot put the clock back and, indeed, we have recognised, through our application for membership of the EEC, the need to join this new movement towards freer trade in industrial products and improved conditions of trade for agricultural products.  Our principal objective still remains that of membership of the EEC in common with Britain.  This objective cannot be realised at present.  It may be some years before our application can be reactivated.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>That is a big change.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>We have to be realistic about these things.  Meanwhile, the only sensible course is to try to secure whatever trading advantages we can in other contexts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the international plane, the only trade benefits we can secure are those provided by the general tariff reductions negotiated under the auspices of GATT.  Without being members of GATT we have up to now been accorded the advantages of these multilateral tariff reductions.  To make sure of benefiting in the future, and for other substantial reasons, we are in process of acceding to GATT.  Members of GATT bind themselves not to give preferential treatment to any individual country; benefits accorded to any member must be accorded to all.  We cannot, therefore, hope to receive from individual members of GATT any particular advantages in return even for offering them special cuts in our tariffs. In fact, the rules do not allow any member country to grant special benefits to another except they are coming together in a free trade area or customs union.  This means that, apart from whatever we are prepared to do for the whole world in return from what we receive in multilateral tariff negotiations such as the Kennedy round, the only practical scope we have for <Col N="540" /> negotiating improved trading terms is by entry into a free trade area or customs union.</P>
    <P>Our position in relation to the European Economic Community I have already mentioned.  Our position in relation to EFTA has also many times been explained.  The fact is that most of our exports are still agricultural and, as things stand, can be marketed, for the greater part, only in Britain.  We, on the other hand, are one of Britain's largest customers. To achieve improved terms of trade we have to envisage the progressive reduction of our tariffs against British goods and they, on their side, can offer us only the removal of the few but important British duties applicable to Irish industrial exports and improved terms of access for our agricultural products.  Special bilateral tariff and marketing concessions are, however, not permissible under GATT unless they can be fitted within the context of a free trade area or customs union. Clearly, a free trade area in industrial products alone between Ireland and Britain would be entirely unbalanced. The removal of the few British duties on industrial products, including the man-made fibre duty, would not be adequate compensation for the elimination of our protective tariffs against British industrial goods even over a period of years.  There must be a satisfactory agricultural element to provide a reasonable balance.  This is the kind of arrangement we have been discussing and I am hopeful that it will be possible over the coming months to bring the negotiations to a satisfactory conclusion.  If we can reach agreement on the basis of a free trade area arrangement, this will modernise our trade relations with Britain, setting them on a new and permanent footing, and providing a stimulus to exports and, therefore, to economic expansion.</P>
    <P>Industries which merely cater for the home market behind a protective barrier will yield no increase in employment.  More jobs can be provided only by industries that equip themselves to sell increasing amounts abroad.  There are substantial State aids available for adaptation and reequipment. The kind of Anglo-Irish <Col N="541" /> free trade arrangement we envisage will give reasonable time to complete the process of modernisation so that full competitiveness can be reached according as tariffs are lowered over a period of years.  It will also provide new trading opportunities in the British market.</P>
    <P>An Anglo-Irish free trade area, if it can be established with a fair balance of advantages, will not merely be consistent with, but will actually facilitate, future membership by both countries of the European Economic Community.  It will represent substantial interim progress in the right direction.</P>
    <P>I thought it only right that I should deal with this.  As the Seanad will appreciate, we cannot deal with it in any great detail but inevitably these talks would be mentioned in the course of this debate.  I think I have given a reasonably comprehensive outline not only of the purpose of the Prices Bill, the Finance Bill and the Appropriation Bill but of the present position of the economy and the steps we feel it necessary to take at this stage.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We appreciate the Minister's survey which has covered such a wide field, the care he has taken to go through the Finance Bill with us, his economic review and what little he has been able to say about the proposed free trade area agreement.</P>
      <P>The Government's decision to negotiate with Britain a free trade area agreement is one of the most far-reaching decisions ever taken by an Irish Government.  It is arguable that in practical terms it is more far-reaching even than the decision to introduce a new Constitution in 1937 or to declare a Republic in 1949, neither of which had as great an impact as this move may have on this country's ability to control its own destiny&mdash;the fundamental test of sovereignty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>One must presume that this agreement will bring some significant economic benefits to some sectors of the community, otherwise the Government would not be embarking on a <Col N="542" /> course which will involve serious lossess for other sectors, and which will increase substantially, perhaps irrevocably, economic and political dependence on the United Kingdom.  One is entitled, however, to ask two questions &mdash;(1) what net gains for our economy does the Government see emerging from this agreement and, (2) how does it view the loss of independence <i>vis-á-vis</i> Britain which such an agreement must necessarily entail?  As regards the first point, the net balance of advantage, we need more information to judge this.  One is disturbed to think that this negotiation has been announced at a time when the Dáil is in recess and no questions can be asked and, if the Taoiseach's forecast of two to three months is correct, the agreement may be concluded before the Dáil resumes.  It is desirable that something more should be said about the shape of this agreement&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry to interrupt the Senator, but I believe, in view of the importance of this debate, that the motion which has been entered in the name of the Labour Party should be taken, namely, that the Taoiseach be asked to attend here to answer rather than a Deputy or the Minister for Finance, for whom I have great personal regard but who, in the circumstances, is not, I think, in a reasonable position to answer the grave cases that are about to be made in this House on the implications of a proposed free trade area with Britain.  Consequently, I would ask that the motion which the Labour Party have submitted should be heard and we respectfully request that the Taoiseach attend.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirlecah An Leas-Chathaoirlecah">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirlecah</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no motion on the Order Paper and consequently the House could not consider the question whether or not it be taken in conjunction with the Finance Bill, the Prices Bill and the Appropriation Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>In the circumstances, I imagine that there should be no standing on a matter of a quibble in this regard.  The motion has been submitted&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not a quibble.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="543" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>I object to the word &ldquo;quibble&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>I submit that no information was given to this House that the Minister would here today deal with the negotiations that have taken place and, on that basis, I believe that one discussion should now take place, namely, a discussion at which the Taoiseach should be present.  I would not have raised this except for the fact that the House had no intimation that the Minister proposed to deal with these discussions.  If the Minister now tells me that the Taoiseach will deal with the wider aspects of the matter, I am prepared to leave it at that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister anticipated Senator McQuillan that he would refer to the negotiations and just gave a cursory&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is very undesirable that we should leave the debate on the Finance Bill to consider whether or not a motion should be discussed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister has taken the opportunity to give, in some detail, his version of the discussions which took place yesterday.  That is something new.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will have an opportunity, during the debate, of commenting on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>We have put in a motion for a special discussion on that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanODonovan" hpid="Seán Ó Donnabháin Seán Ó Donnabháin">
      <NameTxt>Seán Ó Donnabháin</NameTxt>
      <P>Where is the motion?  Why should we discuss it?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We never heard of it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>It merely means a few extra days.  We are all prepared to sit here.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I think we are entitled to ask, for example, whether we can be assured that this agreement which, from what the Taoiseach has said, will clearly involve the complete freeing of trade in industrial products as far as we are <Col N="544" /> concerned, will give us, in return, a complete freeing of our trade into Britain.  There is a disturbing rumour in fact that in return for giving free entry to the Irish market we may not, in fact, secure the removal of the quotas in Britain in respect of butter and bacon.  If that should be so an agreement of this kind, with the advantage remaining to the more powerful country of keeping quota restrictions while we give up our protection completely despite our weaker position, would be an inequitable one.</P>
      <P>We can also reasonably ask for some indication as to the period of years over which this free trade area would come fully into effect.  The Taoiseach has indicated already that it would be a longer period than that which we anticipated in regard to EEC. I take it that this means that it will be longer than 1970?  Again, there is a rumour that the period will run to 1975.  Surely, we can at least be told a basic fact of that kind?  The Taoiseach has already hinted at what the position will be.  Can we not be told something more specific about what he has in mind?  Can we also be given an assurance that there will be some flexibility in the reduction of our tariffs and that the reduction will not be rigidly held to one of ten per cent every year on all tariffs?  We might find it desirable to reduce tariffs more rapidly on some goods than others. This is something we have to consider because of the irrational structure of our tariffs.</P>
      <P>Again, can we be assured that the existing limitations which prevent us from importing materials from outside the United Kingdom without paying a ten per cent tariff will be removed? It is one of the extraordinary features of our present trading position that we are bound to pay a ten per cent duty, for example, on paper imported from Scandinavia lest we should undermine the British market, when the British themselves have reduced their tariffs on paper imported from Scandinavia to a lower figure.  This kind of impediment to legitimate and fair trade is something we would like to be assured would be removed under this agreement.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We can also fairly ask can we have <Col N="545" /> an absolute guarantee that the import levy imposed last autumn contrary to the most stringent and specific clauses of the Anglo-Irish trade agreement, will not be imposed again?  I ask this question a little bit with my tongue in my cheek because I am not quite sure how one sovereign country can offer any more absolute guarantee to another than the one we had and which proved to be worthless last October. Are we to enter into a free trade arrangement on the strength of an assurance of the same kind as that disregarded in so cavalier a fashion some months ago?</P>
    <P>Secondly, I should like to ask what steps the Government have taken to establish the impact that an Anglo-Irish free trade area will have on Irish Industry.  We know that the Government in co-operation with the Federation of Irish Industries and the Congress of Irish Unions have gone to great pains to establish, both in the CIO reports and in the Second Programme consultations with industry, what the impact would be of a complete free trade area between Ireland, on the one hand, and the EEC and EFTA, including Britain, on the other, by 1970.  These two sets of consultations have given the Government the firmest kind of basis it is humanly possible to have for negotiations of this kind.  There is now proposed, however, something different&mdash;entirely different from the point of view of industry, involving more difficulty and more danger, and something in respect to which, to my knowledge, there does not exist any study, any information or solid guidance upon which the Government can base an assessment of what will happen to this country's industry if the proposed agreement is carried through.</P>
    <P>Within the EEC we would have had, in return for freer trade access to new markets in a dozen different European countries, markets which up to now are effectively closed to our manufacturers because of tariff barriers.  The whole concept of the EEC proposals as far as industry was concerned was that the losses industry would suffer on the home market would be at least compensated by the gains it would secure in these new markets <Col N="546" /> being opened up.  It was on this basis, carefully assessed by the Government in the CIO reports and later confirmed by the Second Programme consultations, that the EEC negotiations went forward.</P>
    <P>We do not have any similar assessment of what the effect will be in what must <i>prima facie</i> be a much more stringent situation for Irish industry. We do not know how much of the gains in exports which Irish industry contemplated&mdash;and the expectation of which made it possible for it to view the prospect of free trade in this country with reasonable equanimity&mdash; were expected in EEC.  Irish industry was never asked this question.  The Government do not know the answer. We do not know how much of the benefits we expected from free trade would have been in these new markets which will not now be available to us. Therefore, we do not know from any solid study of the facts what the export position of this country will be in an Anglo-Irish free trade arrangement. What we do know is that the great bulk of the damage to be done to Irish industry by free trade and the great bulk of the difficulties it would face will without doubt have to be faced in an Anglo-Irish free trade area. British industry has such free access to this country, it is so near geographically, its goods are so well known&mdash; British branded products are advertised on Independent television which can be received throughout half of this country, and in newspapers and magazines which circulate freely here&mdash; that competition from Britain would be the main part of the competition Irish industry would face within a European Common Market.  The extra competition it would have to face from goods from France and Germany would in certain areas be important but, by and large, it would tend to make only a marginal difference.  In the agreement now proposed to be entered into virtually none of the benefits to Irish industry from increased exports can be attained.  The only important sector in which we are likely to gain is the textile and clothing trade, which will certainly be offered a reduction of the export duties in Britain on fabrics, yarns or cloths containing manmade <Col N="547" /> fibres.  Apart from this industry, other industries have nothing to gain because they already enjoy free access to Britain.  Therefore, the great bulk of the losses that would face us in the European Common Market will face us in this new context.</P>
    <P>What kind of balance sheet can we draw up in this regard?  We have not got the facts.  We only know that the Government are now negotiating for an agreement which will give us only a fraction of the benefits we expected in the Common Market while giving us the great bulk of its disadvantages. What will the impact of this be on our industry?  We do not know.  The Government frankly do not know.  Yet this is something of vital importance, something in respect of which some more information should be given to us.</P>
    <P>It is disturbing that in the absence of any such concrete study these negotiations were launched and brought to this point&mdash;a point so far advanced that it is difficult to see any going back at this stage&mdash;without any consultations with either agriculture or industry. They are only brought into consultation now after the <i>fait accompli.</i> One would have thought that in the absence of any proper study at least the views and impressions of industrialists and farmers would have been sought before the die was cast.</P>
    <P>The second point to which we have to address ourselves is just how serious for us will be our dependence economically, and ultimately, therefore, politically, on the United Kingdom, which participation in an Anglo-Irish free trade area would entail.  It is quite clear that we will become more dependent.  The whole point of the exercise&mdash;to increase trade with the United Kingdom at the expense of other countries&mdash;makes this inevitable. Moreover, it is clear from what the Taoiseach said that much of the benefits we can expect from this agreement will come in the form of the payment to Irish farmers of direct deficiency payments from the British Exchequer to which they at present have no direct access.  Not only the extent of our dependence on the United Kingdom, but its character is likely <Col N="548" /> to change with the payment of something which must be akin to or may in practice even take the form of a monetary subsidy to this country from a foreign power.</P>
    <P>An agreement of this kind which will increase our dependence in this way and to this extent is something not readily reversible.  We know it is the view of the Government and the general view of most people that even today, with the present more limited dependence on the United Kingdom market, it would be very difficult indeed for us to join the EEC without Britain. However difficult it may be today, once an agreement of this kind was entered into it would be virtually impossible for us, without total disruption of our economy, to make the shift out of the British sphere of influence.</P>
    <P>The Government may answer and, indeed, the Minister hinted at this, that this problem will not be a serious one if we are all absorbed later in the EEC, and this would be true if we could count on it.  If we could be sure that Ireland and Britain would join the EEC in the 1970s, the temporary increase in dependence on Britain which this agreement would involve would be acceptable but we have no assurance of this.</P>
    <P>It is true that, despite the pessimists, the EEC is likely to survive its present difficulty but will it have room for the United Kingdom in the foreseeable future?  No one can be sure of this.  The Government in expressing the hope are &ldquo;whistling in the dark&rdquo;. There can be no guarantee that Britain will join the Community and if it does not, we would no longer be free to orientate ourselves in that direction. We would no longer be free to determine our own policy but would be seen by others as we now see Northern Ireland, as Britain's dependent pensioners.</P>
    <P>There is, further, the problem that the economy on which we propose to make ourselves most dependent is one of the most stagnant in Europe.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at</i> 6.0 <i>p.m. and resumed at</i> 7.15 <i>p.m.</i></P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Defence Forces (Pensions)" RHead="(Amendment) Scheme, 1965: Motion">
    <Title>Public Business. - Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Scheme, 1965: Motion.</Title>
    <Col N="549" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Scheme, 1965, prepared by the Minister for Defence with the consent of the Minister for Finance under Sections 2, 3 and 5 of the Defence Forces (Pensions) Act, 1932 and Section 4 of the Defence Forces (Pensions) (Amendment) Act, 1938 and laid before the House on the 14th day of July, 1965, be confirmed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it these provisions are in line with those in the previous Bill which we recently passed, that this is the carrying into effect of the provisions in the Pensions Abatement Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Minister for Defence (Mr. Hilliard) Michael Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Defence (Mr. Hilliard)</NameTxt>
      <P>In so far as it relates to the abatement of the pensions of retired officers who are in public employment, yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>And there are no substantial discrepancies between the provisions here and those in the Pensions Abatement Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>There is none.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="Professor Dooge Professor Dooge">
      <NameTxt>Professor Dooge</NameTxt>
      <P>They are completely in line?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelHilliard" hpid="Mr. Hilliard Mr. Hilliard">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hilliard</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Finance Bill, 1965 (Certified" RHead="Money Bill) &mdash; Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Public Business. - Finance Bill, 1965    (Certified Money Bill) &mdash;  Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Another point that must be made in connection with this proposed agreement is that the country to which it is proposed that we should tie ourselves more closely than hitherto is one whose economy has been in difficulties and, by continental standards, relatively stagnant in years past.  Moreover, a recent OECD report published in the last day or two, in whose preparation I believe we ourselves have had some <Col N="550" /> share, offers no prospect of improvement in this situation for many years to come, and writes down Britain's maximum growth rate for the years ahead from the not very ambitious 4 per cent, which the British Government had hoped for, to a figure of 3 to 3½ per cent, which would certainly be one of the slowest growth rates in Europe.  This raises the question as to whether it is wise for us to tie ourselves more closely to the &ldquo;Sick Man of Europe&rdquo; of the 20th century, as by doing so we may hold up our own long-term advancement.</P>
      <P>Again, perhaps if this were a matter of an arrangement for a couple of years, pending membership of the EEC by ourselves and the United Kingdom, this would certainly be acceptable.  It must also be recognised that the immediate impact of this agreement on the agricultural sector, within the first couple of years, will probably be beneficial and will help our economy for a few years.  After that period, however, the slow growth of the British economy would inevitably tend to impede our growth rather than assist it.  The whole economic purpose of the Government's EEC policy, which seems now to be forgotten, was to link us with the faster growing economies of the continental countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In making these points, I am certainly not speaking with any animus against Great Britain.  On the contrary, I personally deeply value the relationship we have with Britain, to whom we owe so much of our traditions and culture.  Our Parliament itself is owed to Britain.  The integrity of our public service is derived from the British connection.  So are the high standards of public life, our legal system and the language employed by the great bulk of our people.  We also owe Britain a debt for protection during the war from the Nazis.  However inadvertent it may have been, it saved us from a brutal occupation beside which our old friends, the Black and Tans, would really seem like family friends.  But, no matter how close we feel ourselves to Britain, no matter how close our cultural ties and relationships with that country may be, <Col N="551" /> it would be unwise to place ourselves at her mercy.  To do so would be bad for our morale.  We have seen during the past 40 years how that part of Ireland, which was once so self-reliant, has become less self-reliant and less able to act for itself, while that part of Ireland, our own part, which was more lackadaisical, has become more self-reliant and has, in recent years, tended to lead Northern Ireland in this respect.</P>
    <P>There is also a danger that too close association with the United Kingdom would reduce our freedom of action.  One can readily imagine the kind of pressures that would exist to support British policies&mdash;that would have existed, indeed, at the time of Suez, had we then been in the position of receiving actual direct subsides from Britain.  Moreover, in this relationship, we should have no control whatever over British policy, no voice even.  At least up to 1921 we had a rather loud voice in the British Parliament!</P>
    <P>Britain's spurning of her obligations to her EFTA partners to negotiate with the EEC jointly with them and her decision to negotiate separately and without them, despite that undertaking, and the imposition of the import levy on our goods last October, despite a solemn agreement with us not to use this form of control, even in a balance of payments difficulty, shows that even as civilised and liberal a country as Britain cannot be relied on to stand by her word when her vital interests are threatened.</P>
    <P>The War of Independence won us the right to work towards sovereign in-independence in the Commonwealth. The Government of the 1920s used this right to push the Canadians, to wake up General Hertzog (which I understand was frequently necessary), to jolly along the Australians and New Zealanders, until in 1931 we achieved sovereign independence.  This gave us power to separate ourselves from Britain as regards trade, currency and so on, should we wish to do so.  We have not chosen to do so but we have retained the power and we could exercise <Col N="552" /> it now to join EEC without Britain.  This would be uncomfortable and we prefer not to do so because of adverse economic effects.  Would we in the Anglo-Irish free trade area retain in practice the same power? Theoretically, we could denounce the agreement and set up again on our own, but in practice how free would we then be to assert our independence? Should we give up our freedom of action even for massive gains, much less for the relatively small gains such as we might have from our closer association with the sluggish economy of the United Kingdom where we already enjoy the privilege of free entry for most of our products?</P>
    <P>One must contrast this with association or membership of EEC about which so much was written and spoken some years ago.  One must contrast dependence on a single power with participation in the deliberations of a group.  One must contrast the proposed treaty relationship with Britain with the community arrangements of the EEC; participation in the work of the Commission and membership of the European Parliament, with the right merely to make representations to London which, like those of last October, might fall on deaf ears.  One must contrast dependence on a single power wrapped up in its own problems against the carefully balanced voting arrangements of EEC; with its over-weighting of the voices of small countries; we must contrast its qualified majority voting, its balancing of the interests of six powers, three large and three small, against the prospect of dependence on one power.</P>
    <P>What would be the effect of this agreement on our relations with EEC?  We have a commitment here. Until a few weeks ago, the Government were insisting, unrealistically on the probability that we should be members by 1970.  Our application for membership still stands.  How will this move be viewed in Brussels? Have the Government been in contact with the European Commission and have they consulted the Commission in relation to this proposed agreement or have they, despite all their protestations of European-ness, ignored EEC? <Col N="553" /> Three years ago the Taoiseach in carefully chosen and deliberately ambiguous words, led European journalists to believe that we would join EEC even without Britain, but now the proposal is: Britain without EEC.</P>
    <P>In a recent issue of <i>Business and Finance</i>, it was stated&mdash;apparently prophetically&mdash;that there was a growing feeling in Irish Government and semi-State circles that &ldquo;both Britain and Ireland would gain if the present controversies on the `Six' led to its breaking up.  They believe that there is a lot to be said for the 19th century British policy of a divided Europe.&rdquo;  Is this true?  If so, it is a bad mistake, because the EEC, although going through difficult times, will survive, and the future lies there, as the Taoiseach and his Ministers have so frequently said, apparently without believing very much of what they said.</P>
    <P>If this report is not true, it would be desirable that the contrary be stated.  I think we are one of the few countries in Western Europe whose Government is not on record in recent weeks as regretting the difficulties the EEC is facing, whose Government despite what has been said about our anxiety to participate in EEC, have not put themselves on record as being concerned about what is happening in Brussels.  It would be well, perhaps, if the Minister when replying to the debate, could say something along these lines: it would certainly be well received in Brussels where our lack of concern and lack of interest will not have gone unnoticed.</P>
    <P>Can this agreement leave open the possibility of association with EEC along the lines now being negotiated by Austria?  One must doubt whether this can be the case: I should like to hear the Minister's reply on this point. Just as the door to some form of association appears to be opening for Austria, we seem to be shutting it.  If Western Germany can be a member of the EEC while permitting free entry of goods from East Germany and if Austria can negotiate, as she seems to be doing, an agreement for association <Col N="554" /> that would leave her the right to give free entry to some goods from Communist Eastern Europe without payment of the common external tariff, might we not have hoped for some such agreement under which we could have associated ourselves with the EEC and permitted free entry to this country of certain goods from non-communist Britain, in return for which we might retain a right of free entry to the United Kingdom for certain products which we might have difficulty in exporting to the EEC even with free entry to the Community?  That is the kind of agreement the Government might have sought to obtain.  It is not outside the bounds of possibility now, but it may become so if this proposal goes through in a few months time.</P>
    <P>One must ask: why this reversal of policy on our part, in the direction of the United Kingdom and away from Europe?  It is not in line with the older tradition of the Party on the opposite Benches.  Is it, perhaps, a revival of our foreign policy of the 1950s when the then Prime Minister lined us up with Britain against European unity and in favour of a system of national sovereignty which means big boys can push little boys around.</P>
    <P>Has the lesson of EEC as an answer to the problems of small countries not been learned, despite all the words spoken on this subject in this country in the past?  Are we still fundamentally old fashioned, power-politics nationalists, favouring Britain, favouring the De Gaulle attitude of deep suspicion of the supranational community approach?  Is this why the Minister for External Affairs never mentions EEC but keeps his face rigidly towards Africa and New York? It would be remarkable and ironical if the ultimate logic of the traditional nationalist politics of the Party on the opposite Benches were to line us up with isolationist Britain and to lead to the subordination of this country once again to Britain in an Anglo-Irish free trade area.</P>
    <P>Having voiced these doubts and concerns, it must be said that judgment must be suspended, pending an early clarification of what is involved in this agreement.</P>
    <Col N="555" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I was wondering when the Senator would come to that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Did the Government perhaps expect that the cat-in-the-bag approach might produce enthusiasm of the 1938 type that gave Fianna Fáil the only overall majority of votes ever secured in this country?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>We had it three times.  The Senator's figures are wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Not mathematically, you didn't.  Was it thought wiser not to disclose the lines of the agreement until the people had been sold the &ldquo;cat-in-the-bag&rdquo; and then to let it out gradually in the hope that the actual terms would not be noticed?  Is this why the negotiations were opened immediately after the Dáil had risen when there was no Question Time?  Is it intended to have it signed, sealed and delivered before the Dáil resumes?</P>
      <P>If this proposed agreement is in the national interest, not just in the short, economic term but in the long economic and political term; and if our people are told, <i>before</i> it is signed, sealed and delivered, the details of it, and what are the reasons for it, then they may then accept it, but a hole-in-the-corner approach will, I think, be unacceptable not only to the Dáil and the Seanad, but also to the people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to turn now to the economic problems which face this country at present.  These difficulties, as the Minister has properly indicated, do not find their origin in any single cause.  We are faced with a complex variety of problems, some of which have arisen independent of any possibility of control by the Government or anybody else, others of which have been the responsibility of the Government or of other sections of the community. We face difficulties arising from the temporary fall in cattle prices, from the impact of the British import levy, the overexpansion of credit by the banks last year, the magnitude of the wage increases agreed in one lump <Col N="556" /> in the ninth round and also from the abnormal rise in consumer prices&mdash; itself attributable to a multiplicity of causes.  All these have contributed to our present situation.  Above all, there has been failure by the Government to cope adequately with these problems to which, indeed the Government have contributed something, for example, by pushing up prices through the tax increases of the past two years, by failing to stand by the Second Programme targets in the current year's Budget, by failing to get off the ground an incomes policy and by failing to develop credit and prices policies in good time.</P>
    <P>There are, in fact, four inter-related problems: the balance of payments, the credit situation, the sharp rise in prices and the confusion in regard to industrial relations and wage claims.  It is worth while trying to disentangle these four issues so as to determine responsibility for the difficulties that have arisen in respect of each and to see how best to get out of these difficulties and to seek to avoid a recurrence.</P>
    <P>The Minister has dealt quite fully with the present external payments position and the reason why this has arisen.  He has not referred to one of the reasons which I believe has been important in the decline in the net inflow of capital, that is, the fact that from October to June our interest rate position <i>vis-à-vis</i> Britain was so unattractive to the Irish depositor, and perhaps also to English investors here, that there was an outflow of funds which might have been avoided if the Government or the banks&mdash;one is never quite sure who is responsible&mdash;had not pursued, during this period, an inappropriate cheap money policy which has been carried, up to recently, to extremes at the expense of encouraging savings.</P>
    <P>Apart from that qualification, I would not disagree with the Minister's analysis of the reasons for our external payments difficulties.  I would make one point, however, about the fall in our external assets.  The Taoiseach, and the Minister if I recall correctly, spoke of a very sharp decline in these assets in the first six months of this year and it ought be said, and from the <Col N="557" /> point of view of maintaining confidence it is desirable to say, that some part of this decline&mdash;perhaps £10 million to £15 million&mdash;is attributable to normal seasonal pressures.  When the Taoiseach spoke of a drop of £33½ millions, it should be remembered that only part of this, little more than half, represents a genuine decline.</P>
    <P>Turning from the balance of payments to the credit shortage, it has to be said that a large part of the problems that have arisen are due to the over-extension of credit by the banks up to the spring of this year, often for indefensible purposes.  This is something that should have been dealt with earlier.  The banks are to blame for this and one cannot help feeling that the Central Bank should have intervened earlier and that the Government should have concerned themselves also about this over-extension of credit in the face of the quite evident certainty of a disimprovement in the deposit situation, with the smaller inflow of funds that was bound to occur after the British election and the raising of the British bank rate.</P>
    <P>In the face of this certainty of a slower growth of resources, this overexpansion of credit was something that should not have been allowed to happen and which has contributed significantly to our difficulties.  It must also be said that our credit difficulties are due not only to a temporary shortage of resources, and an over-extension of credit, but also to the fact that after a period of rapid economic growth and with the development of inflationary pressures this year, there have been exceptional demands for credit.  The gap between the availability of credit and the demand for it has been widened by movements on both sides, by a rise in the demand for credit and a levelling off of the growth of the resources available.</P>
    <P>A third problem is the increase in prices.  It is worthwhile looking at this very closely.  There has been a good deal of misguided talk and of oversimplification in regard to this matter. There have been two useful analyses produced about what has been responsible for this position, what are <Col N="558" /> the factors that led to it.  One was in the NIEC comments on the Progress Report on the Second Programme and the other was in <i>Economic Statistics</i>, published before the Budget.  Both are a little incomplete in one or two respects and neither is completely up-to-date. For that reason I have attempted to bring them up-to-date and to make them more complete and the results of the work which I have done in this regard come out as follows.</P>
    <P>We have had an increase of 13? per cent in the cost of living between August, 1963 and May, 1965, but it is only due to a technicality that the figure is not 14 per cent.  It was only because we had a late Budget that the figure was not 14 per cent.  If the Budget had been a few days earlier, the full effects of it would have been included because the work on compiling statistics on prices for the cost of living was then going on.  However, we are faced in reality with a figure of a 14 per cent increase over 21 months, an increase which was more rapid in that short period than the increase for the whole of the preceding six years.</P>
    <P>Of this 14 per cent, four and a half per cent was directly due to Government action, to increases in taxation and also, to some small extent, to the increase in milk prices. Two per cent was due to increases in meat prices, reflecting improved external demand for meat, inevitably to the disadvantage of the housewife. Two per cent was due to the abnormal rise in potato prices, due to last year's harvest.  This is something that should remedy itself if this year's harvest is better, but if not, it will remedy itself next year.  It is, in any event, a temporary factor due to special causes.</P>
    <P>Minor items which have affected prices are higher import prices, (about one half per cent) and increased housing rents &mdash; three-quarters per cent.  When you add up all those, you are left with a residue, an increase of four and a half per cent in the cost of living which must almost by definition, be due to wages and profits.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="559" /> I think we can track this down a bit further.  In this country wages represent about 30 per cent of final consumption.  If wages go up by 12 per cent&mdash;as they did in the ninth round&mdash;this pushes up the costs of the goods we consume by about three and a half per cent.  That is the immediate effect.  But in the months that followed the wage round, earnings have risen by only one per cent while labour productivity in industry has risen by six per cent in 12 months.  When you take account of these factors, the net effect of the wage increases, allowing for increased output by workers during this twelve month period, on prices must have been something like two to two and one-quarter per cent.</P>
    <P>You cannot of course assume that this applies generally outside industry as productivity rises in other sectors more slowly.  Taking these factors into account, the effect of wages over this period of 21 months on the cost of living must have been something like two and a half per cent to three per cent.  One is then left with a residue, an unaccounted-for residue, of one per cent to one and a half per cent, or perhaps even two per cent.  It seems almost certain that this must have been accounted for by an increase in profits, as disproportionate to output as the increase in wages.</P>
    <P>Between 1962 and 1964, profits, total profits including professional earnings, rose by over 20 per cent.  In the past company profits have tended to rise more rapidly than total profits.  We have not got figures for 1964, but relying on this past form, company profits must have risen by something like 25 per cent in this two-year period while output rose by 15 per cent.  It thus appears that profits like wages have been outstripping productivity.</P>
    <P>Thus the blame for price increases is not to be allocated solely to the Government although they have played their part; it is not to be allocated solely to the unions or to the workers, although they, too, have played their part.  Some at least of the blame&mdash; this is implicit in the legislation introduced to control prices&mdash;must be due <Col N="560" /> to employers&mdash;to businesses which have raised their prices more than was necessary to keep their profits rising in step with the general increase in output and have thereby pushed up prices.  In the past 12 months, there are indications that this process has been rapid. In the 12 months ended May last the price of sundries rose by four per cent, and the price of clothing rose by 2½ per cent.  This was during a period in which output per worker in industry increased by six per cent but in which earnings rose by only one.  It may perhaps be argued that this situation came about because industrialists did not raise their prices automatically, immediately, when wages went up by 12 per cent last year.  That is not a satisfactory explanation.  The increase in prices last year was approximately appropriate to the increase in wages that then took place, and if prices have gone up further since, then at some stage either last year or this year there has been an excessive increase in prices and profits.</P>
    <P>Turning to wage increases, I have stated that the 12 per cent increase immediately boosted costs by 3½ per cent and thus prices.  There was no prospect of recovering that, in the short term.  The point which has to be made is that, since then, as labour productivity in industry has risen, prices did not come down&mdash;in fact they have risen further.  The fact that this has happened is something that needs to be pressed home to the people responsible.  It is something the trade unions should consider because many of the difficulties we face have arisen because a wage increase of such magnitude came about in one big jump.  A 12 per cent increase in wages to cover a period of 2½ years is not, perhaps, in itself excessive.  The problem arises not so much because we cannot afford a 12 per cent increase in each 2½ year period, even if this is perhaps a little excessive, but because it comes in a single jump.</P>
    <P>A single jump of 12 per cent in wages pushes up prices.  It forces the Government to raise taxes and forces industrialists to raise prices.  But neither the Government nor the industrialists lower taxes or prices in the period that follows a general wage <Col N="561" /> increase.  It would be much more in the interests of the workers and of the economy if the trade unions would face the fact that there would be much less disruption if wages rose by smaller jumps, say four per cent or five per cent each year rather than this enormous increase of 12 per cent in a single year.  It would be much more in line with the practice in other countries.</P>
    <P>Also, from the trade unions' viewpoint, 2½ year periods impose excessive strains on the unions.  Workers get restless and their loyalty to their unions is tested.  It is difficult for unions to do nothing for 2½ years and workers tend to look for other benefits such as shorter hours and three weeks holidays in between times.  We aggravate these pressures by leaving too long an interval between wage rounds. We can take a lesson in this respect from what has been happening since the last wage round.  All, with the possible exception of those who have made short-term profits, can learn a lesson beneficial to them.</P>
    <P>The position may be summed up by saying that a temporary worsening of our external payments position, not in itself intrinsically serious, has been seriously aggravated by the emergence of inflationary pressures and this is due partly, though only very partly, to an excessive rise in wages, partly to an excessive rise in profits, partly to an excessive expansion of credit and partly to an inordinate increase in taxation, unaccompanied by a corresponding improvement in the welfare of the community.  For this situation responsibility is divided&mdash;between the trade unions, the employers, the banks and the Government.  Of course, the primary responsibility attaches to the Government whose responsibility it is to mantain equilibrium and to secure an orderly expansion of the economy.</P>
    <P>This Government have secured much of the credit for our economic expansion since 1959 by virtue of coming into power at the bottom of the 1956-57 recession, by virtue of their willingness to abandon their traditional policies and by virtue of their preparedness to adopt policies proposed to them by their advisers.  They have made obvious efforts to expand <Col N="562" /> the economy along lines that seemed appropriate to them.  Having gained perhaps more credit than they deserved for the favourable evolution of the economy during the years 1959 to 1964, the Government must equally accept responsibility for our present difficulties to which, indeed, their own actions and inaction have contributed. I shall list the weaknesses of Government policy that have contributed to this situation.  I emphasise &ldquo;contributed&rdquo; because it must be said that it is not all their fault.</P>
    <P>Firstly, there has been the lack of a credit policy other than the shortsighted pressure in favour of low interest rates which caused part of the trouble.  Low interest rates have led to an outflow of capital, for with unduly low interest rates, deposits in Irish banks have proved unattractive to Irish investors and the banks have been no longer able to attract the money.  This has now been reversed by the decision of the banks not to lower their interest rates when the British interest rate went down.  It is better to have a higher interest rate that will attract the resources we need, than to carry on with an out of date policy of low interest rates.  This change in policy has been justified. Moreover, until recently the Central Bank and the Government did not have an active credit policy.  This permitted the banks to expand credit excessively for the wrong purposes and blame attaches to them for this.</P>
    <P>Secondly, the Government are to blame in that they have failed to secure, either internally or externally, the competition necessary to prevent prices rising.  As prices rose sharply, the Government have been forced to bring in emergency legislation of the most repellent kind.  There is no doubt that competition is inadequate and where the blame for this lies it is difficult to say.  However, it is the Government's job to see that the machinery necessary is there&mdash;that, for instance, the Fair Trade Commission are given power to ensure the existence of competition.  External tariffs should be lowered where necessary, a process which was begun but was halted by the British import levy.  From the balance of payments point of view, <Col N="563" /> one can understand why this halt may have been thought desirable, but it had the effect of slowing down the development of competition.</P>
    <P>Thirdly, the Government are to blame for their failure to act to control building.  It has been evident during the past 12 months that the building industry's expansion has been too rapid, that its uncontrolled expansion has often involved heavy resources being put into buildings of limited economic and social benefit&mdash;office blocks, for instance.  This has been overstraining the economy and creating pressures which are undesirable. It is both feasible and desirable that some control should be exercised on building, that some licensing system should be worked out in conjunction with the industry.</P>
    <P>It need not involve an enormous bureaucratic mechanism.  It requires some control that would enable the Government to know what is going on so that they would be able to put their foot on the brake or on the accelerator as the occasion demanded. A National Building Advisory Council has been established but it has proved remarkably ineffective.  The only action it seems to have taken is to submit report to the Government in the last couple of weeks which is shutting the stable door when the horse has certainly left.  Has the Council the necessary powers?  It has been the subject of criticism within the industry. Should it be given power to go ahead with an investigation of the industry? The Government should give attention to this.</P>
    <P>Fourthly, the Government are to blame for their failure to control their own current expenditure.  The Government have announced that efforts are to be made to prune current expenditure. You do not prune something which has already been pruned or which has been kept under control. We know that much of the difficulty here has arisen because of increases in the remuneration to the public service.  The Government point out that the increases which have been given to Government servants have been as a result of arbitration awards <Col N="564" /> which the Government are bound to meet.  There are two possibilities here. On the one hand the arbitrator may give a fairly large increase in salaries and wages to Government servants, because those people have been left without increases while the rest of the community has received them.  In other words, the arbitration tribunal grants these awards because a good case has been made to it that they should be granted and because it has been shown that there has been a time-lag in giving them, in which case the Government are clearly to blame for allowing this time-lag to take place. It is most undesirable that any group in the community should have its remuneration held back over a period so that at some point justice demands it be sharply increased.  Other groups or other sections in the community will not remember that the remuneration to public servants has been allowed to lag behind.  They simply notice the huge increases that have been granted and they in turn look for further increases.</P>
    <P>The alternative to this is that the increases in remuneration to public servants are unjustified in which case they should not have been awarded.  More probably, however, they are largely justified but are proof that the Government did not run their affairs properly, that they allowed a time-lag to occur which has caused the granting of these large increases to this big group of workers and has thus brought about this &ldquo;leapfrogging&rdquo;.  There are so many different arbitration tribunals that a case could be made for having one particular one to deal with all public service cases.  If there were only one tribunal, it would check the inherent disadvantages of the present system and would prevent any leapfrogging.</P>
    <P>It is notable that almost all the industrial trouble with regard to wages in the past few months has been in the public service.  The only major dispute outside has been the printing strike. The rest of manufacturing industry has been free from trouble.  There have been no excessive claims by unions. There have been no large-scale strikes apart from the printing strike, caused <Col N="565" /> by a claim for a 33? per cent status increase in line with the public service. When I speak of 33? per cent status increase in the public service, I am including the 12 per cent increase given last year.  The Government must take responsibility for what has happened in this matter.</P>
    <P>Fifthly, the Government can be criticised for allowing their capital programme to get out of hand in the very first year of their economic programme. The Second Programme makes provision for a certain amount of capital expenditure.  The purpose of the Programme is to put constraints on Government action to ensure that we proceed in an orderly manner.  This does not mean that nothing can ever be changed but it does mean, particularly in the early stages of the Programme, that you do not permit expenditure to jump and then start cutting back within a matter of weeks.  The Government's capital expenditure in this year's capital budget was in excess of what it provided for in the first year of the Second Programme.  They must learn to accept the constraints of that programme.</P>
    <P>Sixthly, the Government are to be criticised for having failed to control hire-purchase in good time.  This led to excessive growth this spring in the demand for cars and other consumer goods.  This is something in regard to which action could have been taken sooner.  I shall give some figures in regard to this.  In the 12 months ended November, 1964, the increase in the volume of car sales was nine per cent more than in the 12 months ended November, 1963.  This was, of course, more than the increase in national output but cars are one of the things to which people give priority&mdash;the sale of cars always tend to rise more than the national output.  During the following three months, ending February, there was an increase of 37½ per cent in the sale of cars over the same three months of the previous year.  The fact that for three successive months the increase had been at this level was known in March or early April, I would have thought this must have been apparent to the Government and that they should have taken action then with regard to hire-purchase, <Col N="566" /> which of course is a controlling factor with regard to cars.  The Government did not take any such action until July.  Even the motor trade itself expected that earlier action would be taken.  They expected that action would be taken in the Budget but nothing was done about it then.</P>
    <P>Lastly so far as I am concerned&mdash; I am not suggesting this is an absolutely comprehensive indictment of Government policy because there may be others on these benches who will bring up other matters&mdash;there has been the Government's failure to evolve an incomes policy.  It is of course easy to be destructively critical but the fact is that the Government's performance in this area has not been good.  It has not been up to the level of their performance in other areas.  Let us just run over the record.  The Taoiseach, on 10th March, 1960 spoke in the Dáil on the seventh round of wage increases. This was an eight per cent increase. Our economy was recovering at that time and it was highly desirable that some of the benefits should be spread to the community at large and the increase given was entirely appropriate and timely.  I am quoting from vol. 180, No. 3, columns 320 to 325.  I am not giving the quotation in full but some extracts from it.</P>
    <P>The Government have been most seriously concerned by the possible consequences of the recent general round of wage and salary increases. ... We were, and are, particularly concerned by three aspects of this increase in wages and salaries.  The first of these is the effect on the cost of living; secondly, the effect of a higher general wage level for workers and those employed in industrial and urban occupations, at a time when agricultural income is declining; and thirdly, the possible effect upon the country's export trade...  I think it is certain that because of these wage increases, some increase in the general price level will take place during the coming year....  All over the whole situation, it is inevitable that the effect of wages upon prices will begin to appear in the months immediately ahead of us.  There is no good pretending that it may not <Col N="567" /> happen....  It is quite clear that unless the effect of these higher wages is completely offset by greater efficiency, by harder work, by all the measures which can contribute to improved productivity&mdash;measures to offset the higher wages bill upon the unit costs of production&mdash;our hopes for economic expansion can be entirely destroyed.</P>
    <P>The unions cannot have been terribly impressed when one and a half years after this highly exaggerated indictment of a very reasonable wage round the Government repeatedly intervened in the electricians' dispute to push up the amount of the award with the result that the level of the eighth round as it had evolved up to that point was doubled.  Government intervention in the electricians' dispute was entirely out of line with what the Taoiseach had said 18 months previously.</P>
    <P>After this we had the <i>Closing the Gap</i> proposals to hold back wage increases for the time being, but which did not express any similar intention to take action with regard to non-wage incomes.  This did not make a good impression on the trade union movement.</P>
    <P>The Government launched the ninth round nine months later.  Although the timing of this announcement was appropriate, and cannot I think fairly be criticised, the fact that the Government appeared to claim credit for it by announcing that the time had come for it, obviously undermined the unions' confidence in the Government, a confidence which it is essential to maintain if we are to build up an incomes policy.</P>
    <P>The next intervention was in the ninth round negotiations.  Having waited until ten per cent had been offered by the employers, the Government intervened and said that agreement must be reached because negotiations had at that stage broken down but that not more than eight per cent must be paid&mdash;after ten per cent had already been offered!  This was an entirely inconsistent attitude.</P>
    <P>The next thing we had was the mess up in the public sector because of the time lag in Civil Service status increases. <Col N="568" /> As well as all these &ldquo;stop-go&rdquo; policies there was a failure to launch an incomes policy, or to accept the need for restraints on incomes other than wages, which must be a prerequisite of any incomes policy.  I am afraid the country is caught between, on the one hand, the Government's unwillingness to contemplate seriously restraint on the growth of non-wage incomes, incomes getting into the hands of individuals after taxation, and, on the other hand, the Labour Party's doctrinaire desire to control profits, dividends and prices, regardless of the impact of such policies on economic growth.</P>
    <P>I think, however, a way out is now beginning to appear.  The Irish Congress of Trade Unions at its conference in Cork passed a resolution which when carefully read seems to me to provide what the Government have not provided so far&mdash;a possible basis for a genuine incomes policy which would be in advance of anything so far achieved in any other country.  The resolution states that an incomes policy must involve a just distribution of incomes but, recognising that this is difficult to achieve in the short term, it says that this is a matter for long-term negotiation.</P>
    <P>For the immediate future it says that any incomes policy must involve reconciling claims of lower paid workers with those of higher paid workers.  There must be substantial increases in the incomes of lower paid workers and pensioners, male and female and of persons dependent on social welfare benefits and public assistance payments.  In other words, such a policy must involve a bigger increase for the less well-off than for better off members of the community. We can all agree with this.  The increase in incomes of workers generally must be sufficient to offset price increases.  That is not asking anything enormous.  Again it says that the increases in workers' incomes must enable people to enjoy steadily increasing standards of living.  That is what any incomes policy must involve.  Finally, to achieve this, it says that Congress must resist any limitation on wage or <Col N="569" /> salary increases not equally applicable to other incomes, and not taking account of the level of such incomes. That is not unreasonable.</P>
    <P>Here then we have, I think, the basis for an incomes policy.  It will not be easy to achieve, but there is no fundamental obstacle in the way.  There is the problem of reconciling the lower paid worker with the higher paid worker but this can be solved with the co-operation of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, which is clearly available.  With regard to social welfare benefits, all are agreed that these should rise as rapidly as possible, but we have discussed that already today.</P>
    <P>In this non-doctrinaire approach of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, I think there is hope of a solution. The greatest difficulty will be in devising some method of ensuring that the incomes people receive after taxation&mdash;what are described as unearned incomes&mdash;do not rise unduly.  A solution to this will, I think, be found in the Fine Gael proposals during the election campaign for a Dividend Equalisation Tax.  It would be quite undesirable, though I fear that some of my colleagues on the Labour benches may not agree, that any proposals should involve restraint or control of profits or dividends earned competitively.  This could inhibit economic growth.  But it would not necessarily be undesirable that the total amount of income which people in receipt of dividends get after tax should be so controlled.  This would involve no disincentive to people to invest in progressive companies.  They would get more than less intelligent investors because there would be the same rate of tax applying throughout to all dividends.  But this would meet the reasonable requirements of Congress. I recommend this Congress proposal and the Fine Gael proposal to the Minister for his consideration because in these I believe we may find the beginnings of an incomes policy.</P>
    <P>To sum up what needs to be done &mdash;first, the credit policy role of the Central Bank which it has taken on in the past few weeks must be maintained. <Col N="570" /> It must continue to co-operate with the banks and to guide them as to how much and for what purpose credit is given.  It must avoid any repetition of last year's excessive expansion of credit.  I think it should also initiate a general review of banking policy.  It is 30 years since we had a Banking Commission here and during that time a lot of things have happened and there have been enormous changes in our economy and in the structure of our financial system.</P>
    <P>There are many questions which could properly be examined by a Banking Commission.  There is the question of whether the banks should continue to be permitted to hide a large part of their assets.  I am not saying that this should be changed&mdash; I am inclined to think that it should still continue in order to ensure the maintenance of confidence in the Banks, but it should in any event be looked at.  There is then the question of whether the banks should have power to disclose only a fraction of their profits.  I am not convinced about this.  I cannot see that the disclosure that bank profits are perhaps twice the figure disclosed would undermine confidence in the banking system, which is the reason given for permitting non-disclosure of all the profits.  It seems to me there is no reason why they should not be disclosed.</P>
    <P>Is the margin between advance and deposit rates, out of which bank profits come, too high?  That is something which, I understand, is being examined in Northern Ireland.  Should it not be examined here also?  Is it in the public interest that bank advance rates should be agreed between the banks instead of being the subject of competition?  Is this not contrary to the practice permitted in other sectors by the Fair Trade Commission?  Is the duplication of banking facilities by having so many banks competing with one another desirable?  This was criticised in Economic Development but nothing has been done about it. There has been a bank amalgamation since then but the bank taken over has been expanding more rapidly than previously and even more rapidly than the bank which took it over!</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="571" /> What should our interest rates be in the light of the failure of our cheap money policy?  What should our attitude be to external financial institutions coming in here?  This is something to which, the Central Bank tells us, it is giving consideration.  Should certain banks be able to take advantage of the Companies Act, 1963, to stop disclosing, as hitherto, data on the basis of valuation of their investments? I understand this Act was designed to strengthen the position of the shareholder and to require the disclosure of additional information, yet two of our banks have stopped disclosing certain information because they are permitted to do so by this Act!  Is this desirable?  Again, is it desirable that banks should publish accounts giving no comparable data for the previous year as one bank has done this year?  Is it desirable that the consolidated accounts should be so drawn up as to make it quite impossible to distinguish relationship between the bank and its various subsidiaries? Is it desirable that bank chairmen should tell the public and their shareholders in their annual reports and speeches little or nothing about banking or the performance of their bank?</P>
    <P>These are matters which should be looked into, and I think I have raised more than sufficient points to justify the setting up of a committee or commission for this purpose.</P>
    <P>Secondly, the Government must initiate a permanent prices policy for which there is a need.  The Bill now before the House is inherently objectionable in the powers it gives to the Minister and to the Government without appeal.  It is intolerable that this legislation should be required in peacetime. It is also unnecessary.  Either prices are fixed by agreement between firms, in which case the Government should ensure that they are dealt with by the Fair Trade Commission, or they are not fixed by agreement but by competition and no action is required except Government action to stimulate internal and external competition and restrain the development of monopolies.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="572" /> I was disturbed to find that the Labour Party have fallen for this Bill. In the terms in which it has been put to the Dáil, this Bill appears to be the most stringent piece of wage control legislation we have had in this country for a long time.  This may not be the intention but it is certainly what it sounds like.  We have been told that it is the intention of the Minister, using the powers under this Bill, not to permit any increase in price arising out of circumstances under the control of the firm and further that price increases will be permitted only where there has been an increase in the cost of materials, thereby specifically excluding increases in wages.  If an industry chooses to increase its wages it may do so only if it is able to do so without increasing prices.  This would clearly be the most effective way to put a curb on wages.  It would be interesting to hear an explanation by the Labour Party of their support for such stringent wage freeze proposals.</P>
    <P>Price control is always objectionable except as an emergency measure. It creates black markets, shortages and distortions of competition.  It encourages combinations.  It is undesirable in any mixed economy in the interest of the public.  The answer lies in making the price system work.  The Irish public&mdash;in this part of the country, anyway&mdash;are not, I think sufficiently price conscious.  Indeed, if anything, there is a tendency for people to pretend that they do not care much about prices and to think it is mean to go from one shop to another to see where the cheapest goods can be found, but that is exactly what we should encourage them to do.</P>
    <P>We have the example of a new town in Britain where the town authority there sets up a board showing the prices of goods in the different shops so that the people are enabled to see where they should go to get each item at the cheapest price.  Why should we not do that here instead of having price control of the most brutal kind?  Why should that type of information not be available to us here?  Why should there not be a programme at 8.15 a.m. on Radio Éireann, say, telling people <Col N="573" /> where in the principal towns, they can get articles at the cheapest prices? Why should we not have that rather than this rigid price control?  Some manufacturers and shopkeepers might dislike this but they will dislike price control even more.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. J. Fitzgerald Mr. J. Fitzgerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Fitzgerald</NameTxt>
      <P>We know the shops that would be publicised on that radio programme.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>Also, there is this question of notification of increases in prices by manufacturers. While that might be practicable and desirable in some degree in the industrial sector, it is clearly not practicable for many agricultural products with fluctuating prices, or for shops.  Price notification by manufacturers might be desirable and has been found to be practical in Norway and Holland, for example, where it has acted as a disincentive to price increases.</P>
      <P>We need an active price policy, not negative controls which are most unlikely to be effective.  Above all we need appeal machinery.  It is undoubtedly contrary to the whole spirit of the Constitution, if not to its letter, that a Government Department can bankrupt any firm or prevent a wage increase, however justified, arbitrarily and without appeal.  It is a most dangerous power which no Government should have and there can be no certainty that it will always be exercised wisely.  I think we can reasonably be certain that such a power will not be used in any wrong way here to do deliberate damage to a firm or industry.  I think we may be assured that no Government here will act like that but there is no certainty that a private investigation in a Department will always come to the right answer.  In fact, I am aware of a price inquiry where one Government Department has even refused to take into account evidence from another Government Department about a matter and has come to a conclusion which seems contrary to the facts as stated by another Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Then there are the other matters that I dealt with&mdash;the need for building controls&mdash;a licensing system of some kind <Col N="574" /> in the interest of stability in the building trade and to avoid fluctuations; a review of the conciliation and arbitration machinery in the public service and of the whole salary negotiation system which encourages claims and leap-frogging and whose slowness gives rise to these problems; acceptance of the discipline of the <i>Second Programme for Economic Expansion</i> rejected in this year's Budget&mdash;which is something I want to come back to in concluding; the need for permanent hire purchase controls which should be kept in being permanently and varied according to the requirements of the situation; and, above all, an incomes policy.  As regards the immediate economic situation, it was encouraging to hear from the Minister that the picture is somewhat better. One cannot, of course, rely on one month's figures&mdash;the June figures may be simply a freak.  On the other hand the figures for April and May may have been somewhat abnormal and the June figures may represent a genuine improvement.  It is particularly encouraging that cattle exports have recovered.  It would seem most unwise in these circumstances to take further deflationary action for some months to come until we see how the situation evolves and how the measures taken work out.</P>
    <P>Looking ahead to the future, I think perhaps one of the great needs here is for a fundamental acceptance of economic planning.  The significance of economic planning is not yet appreciated inside or outside the public sector.  Great progress has been made, of course.</P>
    <P>The <i>Report on Economic Planning</i> by the National Industrial Economic Council makes this clear but we have a long way to go still.  Much more needs to be done in involving management and workers fully in the planning sphere; much more needs to be done to secure the acceptance of planning in the public sector.  Here, the NIEC report makes it clear that there are serious problems.  It says, at Paragraph II of its most recent <i>Report on Economic Planning</i>, page 14:</P>
    <P>There should be much less danger in the public sector, therefore, that <Col N="575" /> the plan will be ignored when new measures are being formulated or old measures modified.</P>
    <P>It goes on to say, however, at Paragraph 12, referring to the <i>Second Programme</i>, that:</P>
    <P>The need for steps to ensure that all departments of the public service and State enterprises play their full part in implementing the programme is reinforced by the priority given to the attainment of economic growth in the Second Programme. The implication of this development and the need for a realignment of policies and administrative machinery may not be completely realised as yet in some parts of the public service and in all the State enterprises.</P>
    <P>Paragraph 13 states:</P>
    <P>In our view, existing administrative arrangements should be developed and extended to secure a continuing overall appraisal of the policies and actions of the public service and of State enterprises so as to ensure that they are in keeping with the objectives of the programme, especially in such areas as manpower policy and policies which affect the level of costs of basic materials and services used by industry and agriculture.  This will require continued development of the co-ordinating role of the Department of Finance in planning within the public service.</P>
    <P>The report goes on to say, at paragraph 14:</P>
    <P>It is of interest that some commentators on French planning believe that some of the main obstacles to effective planning lie in the public sector...  We quote these views to emphasise the fact that it would be best if such problems were not allowed to arise here. French experience of nearly 20 years of economic planning suggests that when such problems do appear they can be very intractable.</P>
    <P>Paragraph 23 states:</P>
    <P>The Ministers and Secretaries Acts assign functions to each government department.  In some cases, <Col N="576" /> the objectives and powers of each semi-state body are set out in the Act by which it was established; in other cases, where the body is incorporated under the Companies Acts the objectives are stated only in very general terms.  The management of each body is responsible for its day to day running, but major changes in policy require Ministerial approval.  In Ireland, the public sector accounts for almost one-fifth of non-agricultural employment and a much larger proportion of annual investment expenditure.  Its activities, therefore have a considerable influence on the level and composition of national production.  The public sector takes the initiative in economic planning and plays a key role in ensuring that the plan is fulfilled. The experience of other countries where democratic economic planning is practised would suggest that paradoxically it is within the public sector itself that the guide lines which an economic plan provides are least often followed, and that targets&mdash;especially for capital expenditure&mdash;are most often revised. Whatever the reasons for this, there can be no escape from the conclusion that an economic plan which is soundly based on available resources cannot succeed unless the public sector obeys its precepts.</P>
    <P>There can be no escape from the conclusion that an economic plan which is soundly based on available resources cannot succeed unless the public sector opens its precepts.  In this country, we do not have any proper co-ordination of the activities of Government Departments except at Government level.  It is like a firm with a board of directors but no management. The Government itself does not seem fully informed on what planning is all about.  A tendency is evidenced on the part of Ministers and Departments to regard the NIEC and the Programme as peripheral, with a nuisance value but no more.</P>
    <P>Some teeth will be required before we get this sorted out and get a coordinated development of our economy with everybody pulling their weight instead of pulling in opposite directions. This may involve dismantling <Col N="577" /> some of the more independent fiefs in the feudal system, for instance the Department of Agriculture which still hangs on to the setting of agricultural targets and to the consultations with the farmers and which still rejects agriculture's participation in NIEC, thereby weakening the work of that body.</P>
    <P>However, it is not only the Department of Agriculture that is involved here.  The Department of Transport and Power comes into the picture, too.  The Minister for Transport and Power has shown himself in this House in the past couple of weeks most unwilling to review policies in regard to the pricing of the services and goods provided by bodies under that Department's control which have the effect of pushing up costs and slowing growth &mdash;the very type of activity of a Government Department which has been referred to by the NIEC as something requiring action.  The Department of Industry and Commerce have completely ignored the fact that free trade is on the way by expanding Irish Steel Holdings on an uneconomic basis at the cost of steel users whose tariffs are being cut.  Strangely, this expansion involves the imposition of tariffs at a time when everybody else is dismantling them!  Those are tariffs to protect the public sector while tariffs are cut in the private sector.</P>
    <P>The Department of Local Government have dashed ahead creating their own planning regions and regional plans without regard to the national economic plan.  The Department of Education have selected centres for regional colleges, regardless of where the development centres are likely to be set up.  The Department of Social Welfare have failed, as I mentioned earlier, to produce a social programme to employ the resources allocated for this purpose.</P>
    <P>This may sound chaotic.  It is not really as chaotic as it sounds because the Civil Service runs along, but growth and progress can be unnecessarily held up by the fact that these Departments do not fully appreciate what economic planning is about and do not accept the discipline of programming.  This is <Col N="578" /> to some degree an automatic reaction by civil servants against the threat to the independence of Departments. Sometimes they are supported in this by weak Ministers who are primarily concerned to protect their own areas and do not work as a team as a Government should.  Sometimes the Ministers and Secretaries Act seems almost like a licence to administrative feudalism.  This whole question is something which needs to be looked at.</P>
    <P>As far as the Ministers are concerned, there appears to be a lack of contact between the politicians and the economic programming process.  Oddly enough&mdash;and I do not say this in any critical way&mdash;this may be more marked in Fianna Fáil for a certain reason. The Labour Party have close contact with the economic programming process through the participation of the trade union representatives in the work of the National Industrial and Economic Council, the CIO and other bodies.  Fine Gael are represented on the NIEC by Mr. McGuire.  He is still a member of the Council and was until recently also a member of the Seanad. There is some link there.  There is not any similar link between the Fianna Fáil Party and the economic programming process.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>That is drawing a pretty long bow.  I was prepared to listen to a lot of the Senator's suggestions, but is he suggesting we should put a Fianna Fáil man on this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I will come to what should be done in a moment. Even the Government's knowledge of economic programming appears to be limited, filtering through Departments, unlike the United Kingdom where a number of Ministers are in fact members of the equivalent council.  I am not suggesting that that is necessarily the solution here.  Even the Taoiseach himself has shown signs of being cut off from the whole process as when, at the first press conference launching the Second Programme, he rejected out of hand the idea of an annual review of progress when this was put to him, although in fact the whole process of planning is based on the annual review process which shows <Col N="579" /> up deficiencies and the need for action to remedy them.</P>
      <P>The answer here is for Ministers to familiarise themselves more than has hitherto been the case with this whole process of planned programming.  I think also that it is possible&mdash;I throw this out as a personal suggestion in reply to the Minister&mdash;that there may be something to be said for having a representative of each Party as an observer at meetings of the NIEC.  At least, they would be fully informed as to what is going on.  There would be no need to bring Party politics into it. If they were genuine observers and not allowed to speak, Party politics could not be brought into it!  I should like to ask if it is the practice of the Government to meet and consult with their own representatives on the Council? The other bodies who have representatives on the Council do so.  Do the Government keep themselves informed through contact with their own representatives?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Finally, I should like to stress in relation to economic planning the importance of regional planning. Because we are a small country, there is a tendency to disregard this question or to consider it in very broad or over-sentimental terms of saving the West. But even in small countries there can be&mdash;and there are in our case&mdash;very marked deficiencies in income levels and the level of unemployment between different parts of the country.  This is something we need to tackle within the framework of our social programme. The solution to it is not an easy one. Among the things which would contribute to it would be acceptance by the Government of development centres instead of putting off a decision on the question by referring it from one committee to another.  Throughout much of the country, the nomination of development centres and the concentration of activity in these centres could provide focal points for regional development which could remedy the existing concentration of industry and economic activity in Dublin and, if I may say so in the presence of the Minister, to a lesser extent in Cork.  This would not be a solution for all parts of the <Col N="580" /> country.  In the northern part, from Monaghan to Mayo and up to Donegal, you have really no centre, except perhaps Sligo, of a size that could be readily developed into a major industrial centre.  Perhaps what is required there is a policy that would involve closer co-operation with Northern Ireland.  Certainly, it is difficult to see how the problems of Donegal will be solved unless a much closer link is forged between Donegal and Derry.</P>
    <P>A third measure to assist in regional development could be a concentration of educational development in these regions.  It is an interesting fact that in Norway the problem of regional im-balance&mdash;the fact that some parts are poor and others are rich&mdash;has been tackled by putting much more effort into the provision of educational facilities in the poorer areas.  This is something we could consider.</P>
    <P>Above all, I would suggest that regional development programmes must be formulated within the general economic plan framework.  We must avoid the mistakes made in France where for years regional planning went on independently of central economic planning to the confusion of everybody until finally co-ordination was achieved within the framework of the central economic planning mechanism. There is a danger of that happening here.  There is a danger that Foras Forbartha will dash ahead with regional planning out of line with or in disregard of national economic planning arrangements.  This is something we should look at to ensure we are not faced with the difficulties they were faced with in France.</P>
    <P>Our basic policy may be summed up as follows.  First, economic development by incentives; secondly, social progress in the fields of social welfare, housing, health and social services; thirdly, and this is something to which we have not paid sufficient attention, cultural development &mdash; educational reform, a revision of some of our attitudes on matters such as the preservation of amenities, censorship and perhaps some of our national aims: there should be a broader approach to our whole cultural heritage rather than thinking <Col N="581" /> simply in terms of one single aspect of it as we have done hitherto; fourthly, a stronger link with Northern Ireland and&mdash;I would end deliberately on this note despite recent events&mdash;a strengthening of our links with EEC where I believe our future ultimately lies, whatever direction these new developments may take.</P>
    <Speaker pid="DominickMurphy" hpid="Mr. Murphy Mr. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>In this debate we have a variety of things to which we can address ourselves.  In view of the fact there are many speakers with much to say, my contribution will be as brief as possible.  I want to start with the Prices Bill.  It is welcome, but it is long overdue. I recall the efforts of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions away back in March 1964 to persuade the Minister to do something about prices.  That was immediately after the ninth round when it was quite obvious many people were using the excuse of the 12 per cent increase to pass on undue increases in prices.  Quite frankly, we in Congress felt our representations and our efforts in this respect were being treated with contempt by the Minister.  We were told, and this was emphasised by the Taoiseach, that competition was the best way of governing prices.  Now, apparently, there is an acceptance by the Government that, in fact, competition is not real competition in this economy.  In other words, we are now having an effort to control prices more than a year too late, at a point in time when the benefits of the ninth round for the workers negotiated by the unions and the employers have largely been eaten up by price increases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>This places the unions in a great difficulty because not alone have we the current situation of which it can be said that the cost of living has gone up by 11 per cent since November but &mdash;and this is more important from the unions' point of view&mdash;the cost of food has gone up by 14 per cent in the same period.  This means&mdash;and Senators, I am sure, will appreciate this&mdash;that lower paid workers who proportionately spend more of their income on food and buying the necessities of life are struck particularly hard and we now find that whilst we negotiated a national agreement in good faith to lift the <Col N="582" /> position and give the benefit to trade union members, before the term of the agreement had expired, particularly in the case of the lower paid workers, they are worse off than before the agreement was negotiated.</P>
    <P>We blame the Government for failure in that respect.  I do not want to go into details in regard to the figures&mdash;we have already been given them by Senator FitzGerald&mdash;about the effect of wage increases on the cost of living. Anybody who looks at these figures will realise and agree that the 12 per cent, while having some effect on the cost of living, does not come anywhere near explaining or accounting for the very steep increase in the cost of living which has taken place since the national agreement was signed.</P>
    <P>However, the Minister is now taking power, very belatedly, but we want to stress the importance, now that he is being given this power, as I assume he will be by this House, of his exercising it, that the Prices Act will not be something to be put away in a pigeonhole, something which he cannot avail of, but that he will exercise his powers effectively.</P>
    <P>In this respect, I want to urge the desirability of having public investigations. I do so because I feel that the fact that there is no public investigation of prices tends to reassure the public and it is also a deterrent on people who are inclined to put up prices unduly.</P>
    <P>I accept that there are bound to be price increases, that you cannot in all circumstances and for all commodities keep prices at a certain level.  There are occasions when a price increase is quite justified but what I am critical of is the atmosphere which has been engendered or encouraged by the Government in recent years, that price increases are all right, that it is good business to increase your prices and get as much as you can for the commodities you have to sell.  I think it is true that there is this atmosphere.  I blame the Government for permitting or encouraging that atmosphere.  If they had done something about prices legislation, or at least given an indication that they were concerned about it, <Col N="583" /> we would not have the situation we now have facing employers, the trade unions and the Government.</P>
    <P>In regard to the investigations, as well as the desirability of having them public, I should like to stress that regard should be had not merely to the factors causing the increases but&mdash; and this is important&mdash;to means by which these factors can be mitigated or overcome.  In other words, where there is inefficiency, where there is bad management, where there is inefficient distribution, these should be pinpointed and it should be publicly stated that this is the situation and we should not have a situation in which inefficiency is glossed over no matter in what quarter it exists and price increases excused simply because this is the position.  The policy of the British Government in this direction as far as I understand it is to pinpoint inefficiency and where price increases can be avoided by improved efficiency and by other methods, to show that they are against such price increases.</P>
    <P>Again, on this question of fixing the level of prices, I do not think they should be fixed at levels which provide profits or a cushion for inefficient concerns.  In other words, we should not have a situation where the inefficient producer, the inefficient merchant, should have a price level geared to his position, thereby providing excessive profits for the efficient concern, the efficient manufacturer or producer of the same commodity.  We must bring down prices and at the same time, it would be a useful method of improving efficiency both in regard to production and distribution.</P>
    <P>I notice that the Minister accepted an amendment by the Labour Party in the Dáil on notification of price increases.  I welcome that.  I think it improves the Bill somewhat.</P>
    <P>The trade union point of view in regard to prices legislation is that we would not simply be satisfied with stabilisation of prices at the present level.  We feel that in many cases prices are excessive and must be rolled back.  We are not asking simply for a price freeze.  That would be impossible. <Col N="584" /> We must in many cases look for a rolling back, a reduction, of prices at present being charged.  In this respect&mdash; this has been analysed by Senator FitzGerald&mdash;the trade unions have in the present circumstances behaved responsibly.  The line they have adopted at their recent conference is a responsible line and I think we are entitled in this respect to ask the Government to recognise that and to act forcefully and quickly in regard to prices so that the members of trade unions can be similarly asked to maintain their sense of responsibility in the present situation.</P>
    <P>Turning from prices to the economic situation, again I agree with Senator FitzGerald, we are not facing a crisis. It has been said, and rightly so, that we might be in danger of talking ourselves into one.  The actual burden of the speech we have had from the previous Senator was that what we are facing are problems of growth, that you are bound to have these difficulties when you are trying to encourage the economy to grow and to grow as quickly as possible and we will always have to face such difficulties and try to learn from previous mistakes.</P>
    <P>We are not facing 1956 all over again.  We are not facing a situation that the Opposition Party are engaged in sniping the Government in any economic difficulties that come about and we on the Labour side here are prepared to adopt a responsible approach in the present circumstances. We hope, referring to 1956, that this Government have learned by previous mistakes.  Mistakes have been made on previous occasions and it behoves us all to learn from these mistakes and not make similar ones again.  Granted, this Government, any Government, may make other mistakes but what I am saying is that we must learn from mistakes previously made and not allow the same thing to happen again.</P>
    <P>In this respect I want particularly to refer to a danger that it might be thought that credit restrictions leading to a slowing down of the building industry might help in present circumstances. I want to say that, personally, I feel there is an awful lot to be said <Col N="585" /> for physical control of building but what I am against, especially in the circumstances in which we are at the moment, is that the Government would consider it desirable in the present circumstances to restrict credit for building which would inevitably lead to a set-back in the building industry.  I feel &mdash;and I think this is widely accepted&mdash; that building is the touchstone of our economy, that if there is a slowing up in building it finds its way throughout the whole economy.  We would all agree that a slowing down and consequent unemployment in the building industry would lead to the loss of skilled workers which would be to the detriment of the economy not simply at the present time but in the long term as well.  It would completely close off any hopes there are of improving or developing new techniques in the building industry. It is essential if new techniques are to be agreed and applied that there should be confidence in the long-term prospects of the building industry, that the workers do not feel there is a danger of being thrown out of employment and having to emigrate once again.</P>
    <P>I want to urge that the Government should give top priority to the flow of capital for house building.  I want an assurance from the Minister on behalf of the Labour Party that money will be available for building and that decisions are not now being taken which would lead to a cut-back later in the building programme.</P>
    <P>It is true, as Senator FitzGerald said that the principal factors creating difficulties in our economy are of external origin, Britain's economic difficulties, the import surcharge, restrictions on the export of capital from other countries.  We in this House, indeed in political Parties and in the trade union movement need to emphasise the desirability of positive measures to meet the situation.  In this respect I want to refer to the desirability of doing everything possible to encourage industrial exports.  I know the Government have already taken positive steps in this direction but they should consider whether they could further encourage exports.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="586" /> The great bulk of exports from this country are accounted for by a small number of firms.  The British Prime Minister, Mr. Harold Wilson, has been telling manufacturers in Britain to get up off their backsides and to go out and find export markets.  The same remarks could be directed to many firms in this country.  There are only a comparatively small number of firms engaged in exports.  They should be forced by whatever means are available to go out and find markets as best they can outside the country.  It would be worthwhile to give further consideration to the possibility of co-operative exports. This was considered previously but no action was taken.  This might be an appropriate time to reconsider that matter and see whether any positive steps could be taken by the Government to encourage firms who are not already exporting to do so.</P>
    <P>To turn to the Finance Bill for a moment, there are two points of detail I want to make and it might save time later on in relation to amendments if I were to refer to them now.  The first one is a point which was mentioned in the Debate on the Second Stage of the Finance Bill in the Dáil.  Deputy Corish referred to it at Columns 1369-70 in Volume 216 of the Official Report of 23rd June, 1965.  He said that income tax was imposed on co-operatives some years ago, agricultural and fishery co-operatives were then exempted from income tax but the tax was left on what we call industrial co-operatives.  Deputy Corish was particularly concerned about one co-operative which is a real co-operative in every sense of the term and which is being hard hit by the imposition of income tax.  Perhaps between now and the Committee Stage the Minister might look at the matter.  It was discussed in an amendment on 9th June, 1964, at columns 924-926 of the Official Report.  Reading the exchanges on that occasion I gather that the then Minister was accepting the point.  He thought it was desirable that the matter referred to should be dealt with but that there was difficulty in finding legal words specifically to deal with the problem and there was a promise that the matter would be considered <Col N="587" /> in the Department.  I should like to raise it on the Committee Stage and perhaps the Minister would have an opportunity of looking at it between now and then.</P>
    <P>The second point I wish to raise is in relation to sections 10 and 11 of the Finance Bill.  Here provision is being made in regard to notification of interest held by credit companies, banks, etc. and the disclosure of deposits.  The position is, I understand &mdash;the Minister is probably more familiar with the details than I am&mdash; that help is being given to commercial banks, etc., but similar assistance is not being given to friendly societies, registered societies.  I want to refer to this matter also on the Committee Stage and again perhaps the Minister would have a look at it in the meantime.</P>
    <P>We also have before us the Appropriation Bill and this gives us an opportunity&mdash;the only opportunity the Seanad has&mdash;of dealing with the administration of various Departments. Again I do not wish to delay the House.  I know there will be many speakers after me but I should like to say a few words about Local Government.  We have all had experience in recent months of getting around the country and I was horrified, and I am sure other Senators were also, at the condition of the roads.  I was horrified at the condition of roads in Donegal which is a major tourist resort.  Considering there are many visitors from across the Border, it is deplorable that the Minister responsible does not seem to be looking after his own county.  There is a major road programme being carried out there but the ordinary roads seem to be neglected and it struck me as being the worst in the whole of the Twenty-Six Counties.</P>
    <P>On the subject of roads, may I make this small point which may seem very unimportant in dealing with this major Bill but which is nevertheless worth making.  It is the question of the ivycoloured trees along our roadsides which ruin the appearance of many of our beautiful places.  I do not know <Col N="588" /> if it is the responsibility of the Minister for Local Government but some encouragement should be given to or pressure brought to bear on the owners of these trees, which will eventually prove dangerous to road users and which spoil the beauty of our countryside.</P>
    <P>In connection also with the Department of Local Government, I am apalled at the way the Department apparently deals with appeals from ordinary citizens against planning decisions.  I was following up recently a case of a member of my trade union who was a year waiting for a decision on a simple appeal.  Another Senator here had exactly the same experience and I am sure he met with similar frustration in trying to get a decision, where an ordinary person could not be told by a Government Department or by the local authority what he should do in order to get permission to build a certain structure.  He could not be given a straight answer.  After about 18 months he got a decision.  It was a satisfactory decision but what I am complaining about is the fact that a citizen could not get a straight answer from a Government Department: No decision could be taken; somebody was sick: somebody was on holidays; the file was with somebody else.  I made about 20 telephone calls in this regard. I do not know if that is typical.  Other Senators may know more about it than I do.  It is bad that citizens should be treated like this.  It gives the appearance of inefficiency in a Government Department which should not be the case.</P>
    <P>Coming along to this debate today, many of us did not expect that we would be faced with this problem of a free trade area, this possibility of a free trade agreement with Great Britain.  I should like to be cautious in this matter.  I would not like to say anything which would be unhelpful in the circumstances, and I would not like to be thought irresponsible.  However, the Minister did strike me as being rather casual in this whole matter.  I would have thought that if this was to be debated at all we would have a clearer statement and a greater effort would have been made to explain the <Col N="589" /> implications to this House and to the public.</P>
    <P>What is involved in this?  Does this mean that we shall go back to the situation where we shall be simply the rancher, the food producer, for Great Britain?  Does it mean that for the doubtful benefit of agriculture our industries and our industrial workers will be sacrificed?  I do not know.  We are entitled to some better explanations and some firmer undertakings from the Minister or from the Taoiseach.  This must raise with many of us great fears. I was never terribly keen on this idea of EEC membership.  The only thing that encouraged me about the EEC was that I felt that here at last was the possibility of getting away from dependance on our larger and more powerful neighbour.  I am not anti-British but if you are living next door to a big and powerful country you must be affected by that very fact alone.  It is our nearest and our biggest market and while it is the duty of the Government there to act in its own best interests, sometimes it harms us as it did in the case of the recent import levy.  I thought that with the possibility of joining the Common Market we would have the opportunity of getting away from the difficulties in which this situation places us, that we would be part of a larger unit and would have more say in our economic future.</P>
    <P>Now apparently, that is not to be. Under the present situation we are tying ourselves more firmly to Britain. It is envisaged that there will be a free trade area, with all that that involves. Again, I want to speak with restraint in this matter.  I do not want to be irresponsible.  The Minister introduced it.  I think he might have given us a better explanation and, from a trade union point of view, we are at least entitled to assurances in regard to the future of the workers at present employed in industry here.  We cannot allow a situation in which they would be sacrificed for the sake of what I describe as rather questionable benefits for agriculture, benefits about which nobody seems to be very clear.  I hope the Minister, in reply, will give us more <Col N="590" /> information about this free trade area and that, when we come to deal with the Committee Stage of the Bill, he will try to help me in regard to the two small points I mentioned.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>It is important, I think, that the House should be reminded that we are discussing three separate measures in this debate.  This is the first occasion I can recall over quite a long period of years in which we have adopted this type of procedure and I have yet to be convinced that it is the best type of procedure.  However, I appreciate the situation in which this position has arisen.  What I am troubled about is that, this afternoon, I felt we had quite a full bill in being expected to deal with three important measures at one and the same time.  Like Senator Murphy, I certainly did not anticipate that, on top of that, we would be expected to deal also with the serious, if not momentous, matter which has arisen as the result of the announcement within the past couple of days of the establishment of a free trade area between here and Britain.</P>
      <P>I shall deal with the last subject first and offer my own comments, for what they are worth, on the situation as I see it.  I shall begin by saying that I regard it as rather poor treatment of the Oireachtas that this particular matter should be announced within a matter of days after the Dáil has risen. That is one of the worst features of the present situation.  It seems to me&mdash; I hope I am wrong &mdash; to indicate a rather callous disregard of the Oireachtas. I certainly am not prepared to accept that the Government did not know a week ago that this announcement was, in fact, to be made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>We only had our meeting on Monday.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that, but I still am not convinced that the Government did not know a week ago that this announcement was to be made this week.  What troubles me is that we have had the announcement within a week, more or less, of the Dáil having risen. If we are to accept the statement of the Taoiseach, which I heard him make on <Col N="591" /> television, he estimates that, in a matter of two or three months, we will be within sight of complete agreement, it appears to me from that statement that we could well have a situation in which agreement would be accomplished, completed, finalised, signed, sealed and delivered before either the other House or this House had an opportunity of discussing it.  I hope I am wrong in that, but that is the way it appears to me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator means it should not be signed until it is first discussed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>My belief is that no agreement of such far-reaching consequences as this would appear to be, should, in fact, be signed without the full sanction and authority of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  Compare this with the long discussion about the merits and demerits of EEC which preceded even the opening of negotiations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>That reminds me of the National Busmen's Union.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said, I hope I am wrong.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>But the Senator does not mind saying it anyway.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>I expect the Minister will be quite categoric in his assurance on that point if he expects us to leave here in any way satisfied.  In introducing this matter in conjunction with the three Bills that have been alluded to, the Minister went to some pains in an effort to dispel any notion of a crisis. Perhaps I am uninitiated in these matters&mdash;I may even confess that, perhaps, I am&mdash;but if this is not a crisis I should like to ask the Minister what is?  Why all the concern and all the haste?  I should like to think we have not a serious crisis but I feel, however, that at the present moment there is every reason to be at least apprehensive of the future.  I assert there are thousands of people in the country who are very apprehensive of the future as a result of the announcement made in the last few days and if <Col N="592" /> that is not a crisis I do not know what is.</P>
      <P>For some 30 years we have been deluding ourselves, it would now seem, into the belief that we could make this country entirely self-sufficient and independent of anything we were getting from our neighbours across the channel.  Overnight we have a situation in which our people are supposed to forget all we have said over those years and start re-thinking their entire economic outlook in new and different terms.  That is a crisis for every citizen and yet the Government approach this in such a manner as to expect the people to believe that we have not a serious problem on our hands.</P>
      <P>I should like to ask: what are the circumstances that either prompted or forced the Government seriously to consider at this stage of our development the possibility of promoting a free trade area with Britain?  Only a few years ago some of us at least were trying to convince our neighbours that the best thing that could be done for this country would be to cut it adrift entirely from Britain.  Obviously something has happened which is fundamental to create the new situation and it is something that needs very definite and detailed explanation. The Government owe that explanation to every citizen in the utmost detail.</P>
      <P>While not quite sure of my dates I am prepared to throw my hat into the ring and say that two, or perhaps, three years ago we had quite a lot of people convinced of the tremendous advantage and benefit it would be to us if we could march into the Common Market with or without Britain.  In anticipation of that we had already undertaken to reduce tariffs at an agreed rate of 10 per cent per annum. I am not quite sure whether that reduction was effected over one or two years.  I believe it was two and that, at the least, it was one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am aware that the decision to reduce our tariffs was suspended last year because the door was slammed in our face so far as EEC was concerned and the urgency in regard to the reduction of 10 per cent apparently no longer operated.  However, some reduction has taken place and I want <Col N="593" /> to know who benefited from it.  Is there anybody here or in the country who can say that any part of the benefit of that reduction has been passed on to any section of the community either by way of reduced prices or better service or otherwise?  I do not think so and if we are to be honest with ourselves we must accept a situation already alluded to by Senator FitzGerald and Senator Murphy who reminded us that over the past 18 or 20 months we have been speaking of an actual increase of not less than 14 per cent in prices.  At this stage we should do a little plain thinking and talking. People are asking questions.</P>
    <P>I was among the 400 or 500 delegates attending the Trade Union Congress meeting last week and many people there were asking many questions but I am not thinking in terms of those people but in terms of the ordinary man in the street and his wife who must go shopping every Friday or Saturday, if they can, and who week after week over the past 12 months could tell us a great deal more about these prices than we appear either to know or to admit in this House.  I think you will not find any of those people prepared to accept any suggestion that any of the developments which have been alluded to in any way benefited them.  Today, they find themselves in such a position that even the 12 per cent wage adjustment of a year and a half ago is no longer of any use to them and now in July of 1965 after some 20 months they are worse off than they were in November or December of 1963.</P>
    <P>That is a fact we must face and admit and be finished with and, having done that, we should ask ourselves what we should do about it.  Is the cure the promotion of a free trade area with Britain in which our industries must be thrown open to the blast of competition in which as was pointed out earlier many of our products can hardly be expected to survive?</P>
    <P>Over that same period, as we have been reminded, we have seen profits going in the opposite direction and they are still going in that direction, I suggest.  In the year ended in May, <Col N="594" /> 1965, over the same period in which consumer prices were steadily rising, profits were still soaring although we know that the actual cost of production in terms of wages fell.  I think Senator FitzGerald also mentioned that point. Somebody obviously is benefiting from a situation in which that sort of thing can occur.  Clearly it is not the ordinary worker, the farmer or the ordinary man in the street.  I do not have to be an expert to point out that if you eliminate those main groups you are then left with the suspicion, at least, that a very small number of people are doing very well out of the type of situation which we are now reviewing.</P>
    <P>The Prices Bill has now been introduced and I regard its introduction almost as a confession of failure on the part of the Government, failure to face up to the reality of the situation, and a failure to admit that at any time they could have been wrong.  On more than one occasion in this House I have heard appeals being addressed to the Government for some effective form of control over prices and profits and on every occasion there has been the same answer, that the free play of competition and so on, was the most effective safeguard the public could have.  I would ask them are they now satisfied that that in fact is not the case?  Clearly by their actions they tacitly admit that it is not.  Why not come clean and tell us plainly what is the position?  Again I would ask what has happened to convince the Government that there was a necessity to introduce a Prices Bill?  Even at this late stage&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackLynch" hpid="Mr. J. Lynch Mr. J. Lynch">
      <NameTxt>Mr. J. Lynch</NameTxt>
      <P>We are not doing it for fun.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;the Bill must be welcomed.  I am not objecting to the introduction of the Bill but simply trying to emphasise that the Government have no monopoly on clear thinking either in this House or outside it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasMullins" hpid="Tomás Ó Maoláin Tomás Ó Maoláin">
      <NameTxt>Tomás Ó Maoláin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am beginning to think they have.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickCrowley" hpid="Mr. Crowley Mr. Crowley">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Crowley</NameTxt>
      <P>Perhaps the Senator is right, in one sense.  One must admit that some of the facts to which we are <Col N="595" /> alluding make it pretty obvious that in some aspects of their thinking they have proved to be very much wrong in the last two and a half years.  However, I am not prepared to castigate them at this stage; I want to make the point that the lesson should now be benefited from.  I hope this Bill is not going to be a bit of showmanship or another bit of bluff, pretending to do something while we are not serious about it at all.  The Bill must be made to work and while Senator Murphy a moment ago said that the Bill should be implemented by public investigation and inquiry into prices where necessary I assert that it must be made fully effective and must provide for public inquiry and must provide also that these inquiries or investigations will not be confined to further increases in prices but addressed to the present level of prices of many commodities.</P>
      <P>I submit that it is not sufficient to peg prices at present levels.  I am saying this as a trade unionist, that we cannot restrain people from demanding compensation for the present level of prices unless we make a serious effort to bring back these prices or reduce them effectively.  I would hope that the manufacturers and retailers who have been responsible for pushing up prices to their present levels would now examine their consciences and assist the Government to overcome some at least of the present difficulties and by voluntary effort on their part effect some reductions in those prices.  There is not the slightest doubt but that there is plenty of room for reductions and if these people would examine their consciences and make their small contribution to the public interest at present they would be doing something which they owe to the people, the country and to the Government who have been pretty good friends of theirs in the past.  Like Senator Murphy I am looking forward to the Minister's reply and I hope he can be specific in his assurances on these points.  I hope he will be clear in his explanation of why we are faced with this situation, where on top of three major measures we also have to debate this wide and momentous question of a free trade area with Britain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="596" />
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>We are engaged now on a triple debate, or perhaps a quadruple debate if we consider the free trade area question which has been touched on, but I do not think that this is altogether a bad thing.  In the past some of us found that if we tried to talk in detail on one of these Bills we were told that it was the wrong Bill on which to discuss the matter, and if we talked about general policy we were again told that it was on the wrong Bill.  I intend to say something in some detail on some matters which arise on the Appropriation Bill.  I want to speak mainly about education, but before I come to that I want to mention some initial points connected with a variety of attitudes in Government policy and administration.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The first point I want to make is in connection with pensions.  We had what seemed to me to be a very enlightened attitude put before us by the Minister for Justice on the Succession Bill, with which we have not quite finished, when he desired us to recognise the legal right of the surviving spouse to a specific proportion of her dead husband's property, recognising that it was in fact joint property.  We had in another recent debate a semi-formal recognition, by some Senators at any rate, of pensions as being a manner of deferred salary payments.  What I should like to see is a general Government policy on those pensions over which they have control, and can therefore set an example to others, that is to say the pensions of retired State servants.  I should like to see a recognition of the simple fact in justice, of widows having a legal right to one-half of the pension.  At the moment the right of the widow of a civil servant as far as a pension is concerned is nil, unless her husband has made some sacrifice in regard to his pension some years before he dies.  I should also like to see a recognition by the Government of the fact that when the cost of living goes up for people in the Civil Service it also goes up for retired State servants, and there should be recognition of the fact that pensions ought be raised whenever salaries are raised. <Col N="597" /> In all equity, former State servants should be treated as requiring every bit as urgently, if not more so, increases in allowances when present State servants have their salaries increased.</P>
    <P>This brings me to the old question of the cost of living.  The Government seem to me to speak with two voices here, because they preach that the cost of living must be kept down, that prices must be kept down, that as far as possible wage demands must be restrained.  Twelve per cent is considered quite enough, but when the Government decide to put up the cost of telephones and postage charges, they think nothing of putting them up by 25 per cent or 33? per cent, at the very time that they are telling others that they must realise they have to hold demands back to 12 per cent or less. Senator FitzGerald, in an extremely able speech, mentioned a figure which I do not think will be contested.  He said the cost of living in less than two years has increased by very nearly 14 per cent.</P>
    <P>Now, this Government who have put up quite an amount of cost in telephone charges, postage and so on, and admitted the raising of other prices, are now talking about &ldquo;price fixing&rdquo;.  I should like to feel as optimistic about this Bill as other Senators apparently do.  It will admittedly have some effect, <i>in terrorem</i>, on people who have been raising prices without any justification. However, the mechanism is so cumbrous that the whole thing seems to me to be largely windowdressing.  If the prices bodies do not hold their inquiries in public, the Prices Bill is not worth the paper on which it is, not printed but duplicated.  Consequently, I remain very wary about it and wonder whether it can be efficacious.</P>
    <P>I pass to a point not so much of detail as of general Government policy &mdash;the whole attitude towards the national health scheme.  We were told many years ago by a former Minister for Health that five-sixths of the people of the country were then covered by the national health scheme, and he was very proud that the other sixth were rugged individualists who insisted on paying for their hospitalisation, <Col N="598" /> their doctors' fees, and their medicine or, if they liked, they could engage in a very expensive voluntary health insurance scheme.  I urge on the Minister tonight the necessity for a national health scheme which will be an over-all scheme without a means test&mdash;in other words, not so much a radical change in Government policy but an extension of the health scheme so that it can be in fact a national over-all scheme, and not a scheme applying to a portion only of the population.</P>
    <P>I should now like to say something about State companies.  We can be quite proud of the achievements of many of the State companies but I do not think we, as Members of Parliament, can be so very proud of the present lack of parliamentary control or even check, or even the right to question the way in which these companies are being run.  It seems to me that we have to consider whether as part of our policy, we are willing to consider the setting up of some sort of Joint Oireachtas Committee, somewhat like the Committee of Public Accounts, with power to put questions and inquire into the running of these companies. At least we should avoid the situation in which Ministers, asked in Seanad or Dáil to justify certain attitudes or actions of State companies, are able to say that the affairs of State companies are not matters of Ministerial responsibility.  While independence can be useful, it can be carried too far if Parliament has not some responsibility or capacity to check.</P>
    <P>There was mention earlier, certainly indirectly by the Minister, of the attitude and policy of the Government towards city development.  We see city development going on all around us in Dublin and elsewhere.  It raises a very big potential danger.  The Minister today at least hinted he felt somewhat this way about it.  What we should very much oppose is city or municipal development of an area of this city which, by community effort, puts up the theoretical value of the land all round the community development, a situation in which speculators thrive and in which the increment accruing to the speculators is out of all proportion <Col N="599" /> to any contribution they have made or ever will make to the city.  What I should like to see is the municipalisation of city land, because the value of that land depends not on its owners' efforts but on the community living and thriving around it.  I should like to see any increment-return from the enhanced value of that land going to the community which produced it.</P>
    <P>The free trade area was touched on, surprisingly, by the Minister&mdash;surprisingly for some, but those who were most surprised had carefully prepared answers to this surprising reference by the Minister.  The suggestion in newspapers and on the radio is that we might have a little EFTA with Britain &mdash;a free trade area.  Free trade area is a relatively new term.  It used to be called the United Kingdom.  I do not know whether everybody here is old enough to remember that phrase.  We used to be in it.  We were entirely united, and we had what you could call in modern terms a free trade area with Britain.  We did not like it, and there were many aspects of it which thoroughly justified our dislike.</P>
    <P>I felt that Senator Garret FitzGerald, in pointing out the possible disadvantages extremely cogently, looked far back into 1927, and made a Fianna Fáil out-of-office speech on the dangers of being under the domination of the United Kingdom, of our not being self-sufficient enough, of not having our own industries or the freedom in protecting them.  All the dangers were brought out by Senator Garret FitzGerald, and it seemed to me to be like old times&mdash;like Fianna Fáil out of office in 1927 and anytime up to 1932. I looked forward, consequently, with a certain element of detached amusement, to hearing a strong Fine Gael answer coming from Senator Ó Maoláin, or from any of the Senators on the Government side.  What we are asked to argue about is whether we should now drop all tariff barriers.  One of the things which was so extremely important in the past was our right to erect these barriers.  Now, in a wonderful new solution, we can move in, dropping all barriers, with the United <Col N="600" /> Kingdom.  It would be unfair to make the kind of criticism of the Government in this respect made by people thirty years ago writing slogans on the walls: &ldquo;Heads up and into the British Empire.&rdquo;  Those slogans were then written of course by Fianna Fáil against a Cumann na nGaedheal Government.  This is the kind of thing then felt by them to be relevant to the political situation of that day.  To use this slogan today would be, in my opinion, wrong and unfair.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GarrettFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Garret FitzGerald Mr. Garret FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garret FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>No empire left.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>It would be exaggerated.  Nevertheless, Senator Garret FitzGerald, I felt, was quite right to enter a <i>caveat</i> to make us realise that if we were to enter a free trade area with Britain alone the increased dependency on Britain, economically and industrially would be enormous.  It would be disingenuous of us not to recognise that now.  I hope I am not misquoting the Minister, but he seemed to say rather plaintively that in recent years Britain had not been treating us quite as well as they used to.  He talked about &ldquo;the erosion of benefits which we previously enjoyed.&rdquo; What particular right had we to enjoy such benefits, if we were in effect a separate nation, having full control over our own destinies?  What right had we to expect &ldquo;benefits&rdquo; from them? Why should we whine because Britain preferred to offer these benefits to the Scandinavian countries?  Can we say to them &ldquo;Well you used to be nice to us, and now we must make up to you again.  We would like to wipe out all barriers now&rdquo;.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I find myself wondering whether, in getting into such close economic association with Britain, we should be in a very different position from what would have been accepted fifty or sixty years ago by the old Irish Party, the Nationalist Party, who wanted a local Government here, but Ireland still within the United Kingdom.  This Irish Party policy had scorn poured upon it by the more revolutionary republicans at that time, but it seems to me we are getting back to the <Col N="601" /> situation which would have been approved of by John Redmond.  This does not condemn the situation or the solution now offered but we might perhaps now be a little less rude about John Redmond, if we find ourselves asked to recognise that perhaps we have tried to be too independent.</P>
    <P>I have said many times in this House before that if an industry requires the protection of a tariff of 50 per cent in order to start off and in the first five years or so, and if at the end of those five years or ten years it still needs this level of protection in order to keep going, then, in my opinion, there are one or two things wrong: either the industry has been supremely inefficiently run if it still can be run only behind the same tariff protection after ten years as it needed when it was started off, or else it has been making grossly exaggerated profits behind this unnecessarily high tariff barrier.  I remember making this point in the presence of the same Minister who is here today, when he was Minister for Industry and Commerce, but in those days he was quite uninterested in the possibility of dropping these tariffs.  He used then to come before us with successive Imposition of Duties Bills raising individual tariffs from 25 per cent to 33? per cent, from 33? per cent to 50 per cent, or from 50 per cent to 75 per cent.  He was quite indignant then, when I suggested that this sort of thing was being done rather in the manner of the &ldquo;bargain&rdquo; sale: &ldquo;Let us put up our tariffs further now before we go into the European Common Market, so that later we can claim to be `slashing' our protective tariffs.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>Apart from the European Common Market it has always seemed to me that our Government in trying to build up protection for industry has failed in its duty to the country, by not demanding that these over-protected industries should make themselves sufficiently efficient to do with less tariff-protection year by year or at five-yearly intervals.  I feel that the present Government stands indicted in this respect, because they have not made any attempt to say to the industries, which they have over-coddled and over-protected &ldquo;You must learn to <Col N="602" /> make yourself sufficiently efficient to do without excessively high tariff barriers ten or 20 years after starting off.  These are the points I have in mind when I hear representatives of the same Government, and the very same Minister, coming before us now vaunting the desirability of dropping all tariff barriers in order to get us nicely and cosily close to the United Kingdom.</P>
    <P>Senator Garret FitzGerald has made the point better than I can, but there is no doubt that a case can be made for a continued measure of protection and of self-sufficiency, and that there is a grave danger that if all barriers were dropped we should be, as has been suggested, simply swallowed up.  We already have, of course, very great economic links with Britain, and we do not, in fact, so very often publicly recognise them.  I remember seeing long accounts of our adverse balance of trade with practically every country in the world being printed in various newspapers, almost all of which omitted to mention that we have a favourable balance of trade with Britain and that we have very close and useful links with them.  I do not think however, that these links should ever again be allowed to become chains.  I feel almost as if I am being more Fianna Fáil than Fianna Fáil itself when I say that a large measure of our independence must surely be retained, even economically.</P>
    <P>This, of course, all goes back to what was said nearly 70 years ago by James Connolly when he said: &ldquo;If you could drive the English Army out tomorrow and hoist the green flag over Dublin Castle, unless you set about founding the Socialist Republic your efforts will be in vain.&rdquo;  His reason for saying that was that as he said in effect: &ldquo;You will be in the power of the financiers, banks, industrialists and merchants of your great and powerful neighbour, unless you set about genuine planning in the community interest and not just in the interest of the privileged few.&rdquo;  This, in fact, is where the present Government and successive Governments have fallen down.</P>
    <P>It is true the Taoiseach told us, not so very long ago, that the time <Col N="603" /> had come to go a little bit more to the left.  Senator FitzGerald has been telling us quite clearly we must have more planning.  I would say Socialist planning, and by that I mean planning for the community good and not simply for the satisfaction of the greed of the privileged few.  After having said that, I want to turn to the main point I want to speak on tonight, and possibly tomorrow, I am afraid, and that is the question of education in this country.</P>
    <P>I was very interested by the speech of the new Minister for Education in the Dáil.  I am quoting from the English version of his speech, page 16, when he said:</P>
    <P>The House may naturally wish to inquire of a new Minister where he expects to go from there.  For this reason I propose now to discuss some of the matters to which I intend to devote special attention.</P>
    <P>This seems to me to be not only excellent, but though one might say perfectly normal, but not so very usual, I am afraid, in this country.  In fact, I would be inclined to say it is entirely new for a Minister for Education, and I say that in the presence of a Minister who, as well as having been Minister for Industry and Commerce, was, once Minister for Education, to say that.  It is entirely a new thing that a new Minister for Education, and I salute him as a man in whom one can place a lot of hope, should say that he is going to tell us about what kind of policy he is going to devote special attention to.  I recall, in sharp contrast, a speech made by a previous Minister for Education, Deputy General Mulcahy, in July, 1956.  General Mulcahy was asked by a Fianna Fáil Deputy what was his ministerial policy and general attitude towards education. In his reply to the debate on the Estimate for Education, the then Minister for Education answered thus, on 19th July, 1956:</P>
    <P>Deputy Moylan has asked me to philosophise, to give my views on educational technique or educational practice.  I do not regard that as my <Col N="604" /> function in the Department of Education in the circumstances of the educational set-up in this country.</P>
    <P>He went on later:</P>
    <P>I regard the position as Minister in the Department of Education as that of a kind of dungaree man, the plumber who will make the satisfactory communication and streamline the forces and potentialities of the educational workers and educational management in this country. He will take the knock out of the pipes, will link up everything. I would be blind to my responsibility if I insisted on pontificating or lapsed into an easy acceptance of an imagined duty to philosophise here on educational matters.</P>
    <P>This was Deputy Mulcahy representing, in fact, the attitude of every Minister for Education up to now in this country, that all they were there to do was to &ldquo;link up&rdquo; the various mysterious forces.  They were not to be concerned with what was flowing through the pipes.  They were there to see that there were no leaks.  They were to keep their dungarees clean, and they would be all right.  It was not their duty to &ldquo;philosophise&rdquo; about education. I make the point now that I welcome a Minister for Education who is prepared to get up and say: &ldquo;Here are the things I would do in regard to education.&rdquo;  I regard that a big difference from those Ministers for Education who did not aim to do anything.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator will frighten the Minister is he says that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>That is one of the risks one has to run.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnMcQuillan" hpid="Mr. McQuillan Mr. McQuillan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McQuillan</NameTxt>
      <P>Let him do it without realising he is doing it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OwenSkeffington" hpid="Dr. Sheehy Skeffington Dr. Sheehy Skeffington">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Sheehy Skeffington</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already praised Senator Garret FitzGerald which will probably ruin his career, but I should not like to do that any more than I want to ruin the career of the present Minister for Education.  Nevertheless, I must give <Col N="605" /> praise where it seems to me that praise is due.</P>
      <P>I should now like to make some detailed references to what the Minister hopes to do, and to his remarks on the position of education.  I find, for instance, in his speech he talks about the scholarships which will be available thanks to the Department this year.  He mentioned that £30,000 will be spent by the Department this year on university scholarships.  I am not quite sure how many scholars £30,000 will cover.  There obviously is some progress, but I want to make the point that progress has been far too slow, and I hope it will move faster under the present Minister.</P>
      <P>The Minister says that post-primary scholarships have been increased from 2,668 in 1961-62 to about 7,500 in the year 1964-65.  These are post-primary scholarships, but you will recognise readily that the figure for 1964-65 is very small indeed still when you compare it with the total of half a million children in the primary schools, or even the 60,000 or 70,000 children leaving the primary schools every year. The expected expenditure, he says, by local authorities for 1965-66 is estimated at about £550,000.  This compares, he says, rightly, most favourably with a total expenditure of £150,000 four years ago.  Things are moving forward, but I want to make the point that we still have a very long way to go, if we are in any sense to implement the expressed desire both of Fianna Fáil and of Fine Gael and also, for a long time past, of the Labour Party, to give an equal chance of education to every Irish child.  It is no good saying that 7,500 post-primary scholarships, though it is certainly an enormous increase on four years ago, is giving an equal share to every child or, according to the words of the proclamation, cherishing all the children of the nation equally.</P>
      <P>On page 5 of his speech the Minister says:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>By 1970, I expect that, on the basis of the present values of scholarships, about 20,000 pupils in post-primary schools will be in receipt of scholarships and that there will be <Col N="606" /> nearly 2,000 university scholarship holders.</P>
    <P>Again, the Minister is here concerned with something which should vitally concern the whole country.  Nevertheless, I see, for instance, provision for only 2,000 scholarship holders out of a total university student population of between 14,000/15,000.  About 15 years ago, figures were given for Oxford and Cambridge, which are not regarded as unusually democratic institutions, which showed that 65 per cent of their students were by then grant-aided students.  If we manage by 1970 to have university students to the number of 2,000 thus grant-aided, I feel we still shall be pretty far short at university level, just as we are short at the primary and secondary levels, of what we might legitimately hope for after forty-three years of Irish Government.</P>
    <P>I should like to quote figures from the <i>Irish Times</i> of 9th April, 1965.  The figures given were figures for the nine counties of Ulster, six of them being part of the United Kingdom, to which we will be turning hopefully soon, and three which are still part of the Republic.  The local authorities in the six Ulster counties gave for the year ended 31st July, 1964 a figure of 2,456 university scholarships at a cost of £698,978.  For a similar year the three counties of Donegal, Cavan and Monaghan, which admittedly are not amongst the wealthiest counties in the Republic, gave a total not of 2,400 university scholarships but of only 54, at a cost of some £10,800.</P>
    <P>One could add to what was spent by the six Ulster counties a further 1,236 such scholarships granted by Belfast Corporation alone at a cost of £295,270.  I quote these figures from the North just in case we might feel too smug and self-satisfied at the progress we have been making in this regard, and to point to the fact that we have still a long way to go if we are to fulfil our ambition to make education freely available to all who merit it among our children.</P>
    <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Thursday, 29th July, 1965.</P>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>