<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="19" Month="Jul" Year="2011" Vol="209" No="10" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 19 Iúil 2011" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 19 July 2011" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="611">
    <Col N="611"/><HtmlBk SectId="1" />
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead=""> 
    <Title></Title>
        <P Just="Center">Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 2.30 p.m.</P>
        <Line />
        <P Just="Center"><i>Paidir.</i></P>
        <P Just="Center"><i>Prayer.</i></P>
        <Line />
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Business" RHead="of Seanad."> 
    <Title>Business of Seanad</Title>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I have received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Health to have the full rheumatology service restored at Letterkenny General Hospital, County Donegal.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Paschal Mooney of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1" Just="Left">The need for the Minister for Health to clarify if he recognises the vital support provided by Foroige&rsquo;s Big Brothers Big Sisters of Ireland initiative; the social and economic benefits resulting from the initiative; accepts the need for the service to continue, and if he will make a statement on the matter.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1">The need for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to establish a missing children&rsquo;s hotline in Ireland.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I have also received notice from Senator David Cullinane of the following matter:</P>
        <P LI="1" Just="Left">The need for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources to publish, as a matter of urgency, the Cahill/Frontier Economics report on the ESB and to commit to the future of the ESB as a vertically integrated utility.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business"> 
    <Title>Order of Business</Title>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re amendment of Standing Order 57 of the Standing Orders of Seanad &Eacute;ireann Relative to Public Business, to be taken without debate; No. 2, motion to adopt the terms of reference for the Seanad Public Petitions Committee, established under Standing Orders 92 to 95, inclusive, and in accordance with the report of the sub-committee of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges on the establishment of a public petitions committee, to be taken without debate; No. 4, Finance (No. 3) Bill 2011 [<i>Certified Money Bill</i>] &mdash; Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken from<Col N="612"/>3.45 p.m. and to conclude at 5.45 p.m., if not previously concluded; No. 5, Residential Institutions Redress (Amendment) Bill 2011 &mdash; all Stages, to commence at the conclusion of No. 4 and conclude not later than 8 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the contributions of group spokespersons on Second Stage not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">First, I acknowledge the work that has been done by the Leader and the leaders of the other groups in the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  I welcome the establishment of the Seanad Public Petitions Committee.  In the course of the first session of this Seanad we have made progress on changing how we do our work.  They are small steps but it is important that we get the foundations right.  I commend the Leader for his commitment to this.  I also commend the other group leaders and the members of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Last week I tabled a proposed motion on the recognition of a Palestinian state based on the pre-1967 borders.  Although a week has passed, I have not yet received a response to it from the Government parties.  I have received responses from the other groups, and I thank them for those.  It is a non-political, cross-party motion.  It is crucial that we deal with it as the D&aacute;il rises this week and the Seanad rises next week for the summer recess.  What progress has been made on the Government side on this?  Does it support the wording of the motion?</P>
        <P>Regarding the business ordered for this week, the Electoral (Amendment) Bill is an important Bill that will be brought before the House on Second Stage tomorrow.  Committee and Remaining Stages are being held on Thursday.  This Bill is very important as it confers powers on the new Constituency Commission, which I believe did a very poor job the last time it drew up the boundaries of D&aacute;il constituencies.  It paid no heed to county boundaries even though it was supposed to do so.  My concern is that the Bill is being dealt with on Wednesday and Thursday, with no time between Committee and Report Stages which are being taken on the same day.  My party will table a number of amendments.  This brings us back to the point which I and other Members have raised about the proper scrutiny of legislation.  I believe the reason this is being done on Thursday is that the D&aacute;il is not sitting next week, so the Bill is simply being run through the Seanad.  It shows the Government&rsquo;s, although not the Leader&rsquo;s, scant regard for the Seanad.</P>
        <P>In recent weeks many valid points on health have been raised in this Chamber, specifically on local hospitals and services.  The Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly, has still not attended the House to answer questions on who is managing the health service.  Is it the Minister or the HSE?  The Minister attended the House to deal with a Bill on female genital mutilation which had cross-party support and was non-contentious.  However, he has not seen fit to attend the House since then.  Is the reason that his colleague, the Minister, Deputy Shatter, was discommoded somewhat when he came into the Chamber?  I note with interest a letter in which the Minister, Deputy Shatter, complained about the way he felt he was treated in this House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That is not relevant to the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>It is because I want to stand up for my colleagues on this side of the House who raised some&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is reopening an issue dealt with by the Cathaoirleach last week.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="613"/>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>True.  I did not think the Minister, Deputy Shatter, was as precious as he seems based on the letter sent.  I thought the cut and thrust of politics in south Dublin would have enabled him to deal with colleagues in the Seanad.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Cathaoirleach already has dealt with this matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">To get back to my original point, assuming the Minister for Health is not taking a line from the Minister, Deputy Shatter, on this, when will he attend the House for a proper debate on regional hospitals, services and psychiatric care?  Last week I raised the issue of the psychiatric hospital in Portrane on the north side of Dublin with the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch.  While that discussion was useful, this Government does not have a cohesive approach in regard to health and further issues are coming down the line.  I cannot understand why the Minister for Health will not attend the House to answer questions and deal with issues which Members of all parties and of none have raised.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>The Labour Party Ministers of State in the Department of Health have attended this House on a number of occasions, and I think Senator O&rsquo;Brien will acknowledge that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.  The Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, was in the House last week.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>The Ministers of State, Deputies Kathleen Lynch and R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall, have attended the House on numerous occasions.  I apologise to Senator O&rsquo;Brien for the delay on the Palestine motion.  We will get back to him on that today.  It took a little time toing and froing.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I commend the Leader and the Committee on Procedure and Privileges for Nos. 1 and 2 on the Order Paper.  Both are noteworthy developments and changes to the business of the Seanad which will make our business much more relevant and effective in the coming term.  As colleagues will see, the first change we have made is that with the leave of the House, representatives and persons in public and civic life may attend and be heard in the Seanad.  The impetus for that came largely from the Independent nominees groups and we should acknowledge that.  However, all of us on the Committee on Procedure and Privileges were very anxious to see it facilitated and that we would be able to hear from individuals outside the Seanad who would be able to come in and inform our debate.  That will strengthen the quality of our debate.</P>
        <P>The other change concerns the Seanad Public Petitions Committee which already exists under our Standing Orders but which we are now activating through the new terms we have adopted on the SPPC.  I am very optimistic that will really change the way we do business for the better.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader arrange a debate on the continuing fallout from the <i>News of the World</i> scandal and crisis?  It has become a full blown crisis not only in Britain but internationally as it has affected News International and media business worldwide.  It was very sad to hear of a death in England which seems to have followed from it.  There is also continuing fallout in terms of resignations of senior police officers as well as News International officers.</P>
        <P>It should generate debate in this House on two particular issues.  One is an issue on which a number of us in the Labour Party have called for debate, namely, the ownership of the media and the fact it should not be concentrated in the hands of one individual to such an extent that he or she feels he or she can abuse power in the way Rupert Murdoch did.</P>
        <P>Today&rsquo;s hearings in the House of Commons should generate some debate in this House on the powers of Oireachtas committees.  The programme for Government states that we should <Col N="614"/>strengthen Oireachtas committees.  The House of Commons committee is very much in the news today and it will call before it not only the senior members of News International but also senior police officers.  We need to look at how we can strengthen the powers of our committees to ensure they have that level of scrutiny over individuals and officers.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JillianVanTurnhout"><NameTxt>Senator Jillian van Turnhout</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I join the leaders of other groups in thanking the Committee on Procedure and Privileges and the Leader for bringing forward motions Nos. 1 and 2.  These will give life to the motion which, though put forward by the Independent group, was worked on by Senators from all sides together.  It is great to see this expression of our joint work.  I hope we can reap the riches of this in the months ahead and demonstrate the importance of this House.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to allow time for the House to inform and guide policy and legislation to underpin the safety, welfare, protection and rights of children.  In the past week we had the Cloyne report, which was debated during the Order of Business last week.  We have had much debate on this matter over the last few days.  I send a strong message to all adults that there is only one State authority.  If one has reasonable grounds for concern about the abuse of a child one should report it to the HSE or the Garda.  That is the only answer.</P>
        <P>Yesterday, we saw the conviction of Mr. Michael Ferry, from Donegal.  He had been convicted but yet was allowed to continue to work in a school in Derrybeg, Donegal despite that conviction.  This resonated with me because I went to summer school in Derrybeg, Donegal.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Later today, the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs will lay before the Oireachtas the second progress report on the Ryan report, which is something to which the House should give consideration.  This report contains 99 actions.  It could greatly improve outcomes for children.  I note that the Minister, despite previous resistance, decided a few months ago that the oversight group should be more than just a public service group and invited a non-governmental organisation, the Children&rsquo;s Rights Alliance, to be part of the group.  I welcome her decision and look forward to seeing the report.</P>
        <P>It is natural that we Senators should express our hurt, anger or shock at the recent reports, but the House has a stronger role to play.  We need to remember that children are being abused in Ireland today.  This is not about the past.  It is about the here and now.  On Friday, the Minister published Children First: National Guidelines for the Protection and Welfare of Children, and will bring forward legislation.  The House could help inform that legislation.  We should have a debate on what needs to be done.  There is fear among the public about statutory reporting.  We should also talk about mandatory protection to ensure that State agencies co-operate and share information.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on what the Seanad can do to underpin the safety, welfare, protection and rights of children in Ireland today.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The grocery business in Ireland has been a very competitive one, as I have experienced in the last 50 or 51 years.  I have been concerned for some time that the purchasing policies of companies based outside Ireland do not always support Irish products and Irish producers.  What really concerns me at present is the intention of the Minister to introduce legislation putting a regulatory control on the purchasing policies of retailers in Ireland.  That cannot apply to those whose headquarters are in Dusseldorf, Berlin, London or elsewhere.  The measure will place restraints and restrictions on the ability of Irish retailers to negotiate the best deals they can with suppliers, whether in Ireland or elsewhere.  It does not place the restriction on those who are not based in Ireland and whose headquarters are based elsewhere.  A voluntary code of practice that could be agreed to by everybody would be much <Col N="615"/>better.  I have some concern about this because it has not always been proved that non-Irish companies have supported Irish suppliers.</P>
        <P>While I am on my feet, may I express my concern, which has turned to pleasure, that Superquinn, the company I headed for many years, has been placed in the hands of an Irish family company?  I am very pleased to see this and I am confident that the jobs of the 2,800 people who work there appear to have been secured.  I am also pleased that the suppliers will continue to supply that company.  Many of them are Irish companies.   Concern has been expressed that some of the debts due to suppliers are not fully covered at this stage, but I am hopeful a solution will be found in that regard.</P>
        <P>The grocery trade is a very competitive business and we must ensure consumers continue to reap the benefits of that competition.  However, four of the larger retailers in this State are not based in Ireland and that development will not be reversed.  Irish companies will continue to have to compete with foreign companies.  In that context, it is good to see an Irish-owned family business growing stronger and strengthening its ability to compete into the future.  We must do nothing to restrict the ability of Irish companies to compete.  In the long term it is consumers who will win if there is a competitive and non-restrictive market.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ColmBurke"><NameTxt>Senator Colm Burke</NameTxt>
	<P>Last week a judge of the Supreme Court made strongly critical comments about modern tribunals, describing their powers are &ldquo;truly awesome&rdquo;, their expense &ldquo;enormous&rdquo;, the cost of participating in them &ldquo;grotesque&rdquo; and the duration of some &ldquo;nothing else than appalling&rdquo;.  The comments were made in the context of an application by the Director of Corporate Enforcement to take certain actions in respect of individuals who had appeared before a tribunal in the past.  Concerns in this regard go back to 1992 when Mr. Justice Finlay found that tribunal reports were sterile of legal effect.  Despite this caution, we have had several tribunals in the following 20 years, at enormous expense to the State, and now find ourselves apparently powerless to act on some of the findings of those tribunals.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader invite the Minister for Justice and Equality to the House to discuss this matter?  How do we deal with matters like these, which for some reason, cannot be addressed within the current courts structure?  Are changes required to that structure to deal with such matters without recourse to tribunals of inquiry?  Tribunals have not worked, will not work and cannot work.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimWalsh"><NameTxt>Senator Jim Walsh</NameTxt>
	<P>I echo Senator Colm Burke&rsquo;s comments regarding remarks by Mr. Justice Hardiman, who has proved prescient in his strong criticism of tribunals.  Unfortunately, the tribunals themselves have become a greater scandal than anything they have investigated in the past 13 years.  This House should debate the complete repeal of the relevant legislation.  We must find a mechanism for inquiring into issues of public importance to replace the tribunal system, which operates as a lottery for people in the Law Library.  What has happened is a great shame.</P>
        <P>An announcement was made today that roads throughout the State will be tolled as part of the continuing persecution of motorists.  I have no objection to tolling long stretches of roadway which connect cities; there is a competitive advantage in that to the economy and to motorists who use them.  However, I object strongly to the notion being promulgated by the Minister of State at the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Alan Kelly, that every small section of the M50, for example, should have a toll.  I am fortunate to be able to travel to Leinster House via three different routes, the first involving a succession of regional roads, the second using the M9 from Waterford to Dublin &mdash; which is motorway all the way and in respect of which I would not object to the imposition of a toll &mdash; and the third involving the N11, which has short stretches of motorway.  The suggestion that a toll should be imposed on the <Col N="616"/>latter is crazy.  If we were to do that, car tax should be removed.  It behoves the Government to tackle the waste in expenditure across the subheads in the various Departments.  I urge that this be done.</P>
        <P>I concur with Senator Bacik&rsquo;s remarks on the media scandal in Britain.  I have no doubt that what happens there will happen here shortly.  The former Minister for Justice, Equality and Law Reform, the then Deputy Michael McDowell, organised a conference in UCD in advance of the privacy and defamation Bill, which has been enacted.  The then secretary of the NUJ stood up and stated that standards here were being lowered and that standards across the water were diabolical.  We need to look at ways of ensuring that people&rsquo;s privacy is safeguarded.  The power of the media can be used and abused.  Whether its use is legal or illegal, it is onerous on people and we, the Oireachtas, have a duty to protect vulnerable people who do not have the financial resources to restore their reputation to challenge the media, which is controlled by large corporations with financial resources.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I wish to raise two issues.  I compliment the Minister for Health on extending the remit of pharmacists to give the flu vaccine from next autumn onwards.  This is smart innovative thinking, which is very much needed.  The pharmacists have been looking for an expanded role.  Could the role of the pharmacist be extended to administering the BCG vaccine?  We have had a crisis in counties such as Cork and Galway, where we have large numbers of at-risk non-national children, with one parent not vaccinated.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In respect of child protection, I welcome the Minister, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald&rsquo;s comments that we can no longer rely on voluntary reporting of child abuse.  I have long been a proponent of mandatory reporting and I have spoken about it in this House.  When I taught abroad, I had to mandatorily report any suspicion of child abuse.  I welcome the remarks of Senator Jillian van Turnhout on the need for a debate to flesh out the issues.  How will we deal with the pressure on the services that will result from mandatory reporting, given the way the health services are stretched already?</P>
          <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">3 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
        <P Just="Left">Great steps have been taken to promote Ireland abroad.  We have hosted the visit of Her Royal Majesty, the Queen and President Obama.  Now we have the fillip from the Irish golfers who have won majors.  What initiatives are being taken to promote Ireland to the domestic market?  This week the Galway Arts Festival is on and next week we will have the largest racing festival in Europe, the Galway Races, with eight days of racing.  We have an incredible experience to offer.  Will an invitation be extended to the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Leo Varadkar, to come to the Seanad to look at the initiative to attract the domestic visitor?  I do not expect him to change the weather.  The word is out among Irish people that it is expensive to holiday at home.  We need to see more synergy between the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food and the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to look at the range of holidays and the value for money that can be found.  That is the way to grow the economy  and distribute wealth across the country.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that we stay with what is on the original Order Paper and deal only with Second Stage of the Residential Institutions Redress (Amendment) Bill 2011 today.  It is an important Bill and the idea of taking all Stages, with a possible guillotine &mdash; although it is a very short Bill and it may not come to that &mdash; is bad parliamentary practice.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I ask the Leader if he can look at the Government possibly reintroducing a Bill on involuntary use of ECT, which was introduced in this House during the previous session with support <Col N="617"/>from his party.  It was introduced by Dan Boyle and D&eacute;irdre de B&uacute;rca of the Green Party and me.  I raise this on foot of reports that a man recovering from heroin addiction was going through the withdrawal process and was committed to a hospital.  He was scheduled to be subject to an involuntary application of this procedure in defiance of his wishes and the wishes of his family.  The family applied to receive information about this treatment but they were denied it.  One of the reasons given by this hospital in County Kildare was that, since the family had been in contact with the press, they had no right.  That seems very high-handed.  The family also asked for a second opinion.  For a long time I have said we should not make such clear distinctions between physical illness and mental illness.  They are counterparts, as was pointed as early as the late, great Dr. Jonathan Swift.  One does not have such a fuss made if one seeks a second opinion on a physical illness.  It seems extraordinary the family should be frustrated in seeking a second opinion on a diagnosis of paranoid schizophrenia, which is a very easy diagnosis to make.</P>
        <P>Will the Leader consider reintroducing this Bill?  It is a violation of human rights that someone should be subjected involuntarily to a treatment with a dubious background although it may be successful in some cases and, in particular, denying the concerned family access to news and information about what is being done to the son and brother.  This is wrong and the Bill should be reintroduced with all-party support.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>For clarification, does Senator Norris propose an amendment to the Order of Business?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Is that in regard to Second Stage?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>Instead of taking all Stages as per the revised Order Paper, I propose taking the Second Stage only today.  The other Stages can be taken tomorrow or before the close of the session.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FiachMacConghail"><NameTxt>Senator Fiach Mac Conghail</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I record my appreciation of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, CPP, and the Leader of the House proceeding so efficiently with the new Standing Order concerning the invitation of significant persons in public and civic life to attend the Seanad.  There is an extraordinary, devastating famine occurring in the Horn of Africa.  It is an increasing threat to human dignity and human life and to our understanding of the horror of famine and what is happening in terms of climate control.  The former President of Ireland, Mary Robinson, visited the Horn of Africa and has been there for the past two days.  Events are being broadcast on television.  My recommendation is that the Leader discusses with the CPP whether we can invite the former President, Mary Robinson, to the Seanad.  She is a former Senator and could brief us on what is happening.  It would be a gesture of solidarity with what is happening in the Horn of Africa and the Seanad could become a conduit for further clarification and information.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I second the amendment proposed by Senator Norris.  I record the opposition of the Sinn F&eacute;in Party to any motion from the CPP as long as Sinn F&eacute;in is prevented from having group status.  We are not against the substance of the two motions but as a matter of protest, we will stand against them.  Does the Leader agree that the comments from the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, about people who are out of work were inappropriate?  Will the Leader join me in recognising that people do not make a lifestyle choice to be out of work?  The only lifestyle choice that those people make is between the dole and the aeroplane ticket out of this country.  Some 100,000 young people have emigrated from <Col N="618"/>our shores and 500,000 people have lost their jobs since 2008.  Some 460,000 people are out of work and all of those people are victims of very bad policies by politicians.  It was not their fault that they ended up in that position.</P>
        <P>It is wrong to blame the victims and engage in name calling and stigmatising of the many young people who are out of work.  It is an attempt by the Labour Party especially and by the Government to divert attention away from the fact that the promises made by that party to create tens of thousands of jobs and to protect the vulnerable in society are not being honoured and have disappeared.  Those young people, and many young people out of work, get up every day of the week and face into a process of sending off letters and CVs to companies seeking employment.  Many of them have low self-esteem because it is so difficult to get a job in this State.  When they hear comments such as those made by the Minister for Social Protection it adds to the self-esteem problem many of those people experience.  It is appalling that well-paid Ministers and other politicians who sometimes live in ivory towers have no idea what it is like to have to try to find a job today.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Does the Leader agree with me that this was a spineless attack on some of the most vulnerable people in the State and that people do not make those lifestyle choices?  Does he, or anybody else in this Chamber, believe that people in their own counties make those lifestyle choices?  I do not believe that is the case.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The issue of long-term unemployment is complex and should not be trivialised in the manner done by the Minister for Social Protection.  That was wrong.  We should have a debate in this Chamber on how we can get those people back to work and deliver on the promises made but since abandoned by the two parties in government.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelMullins"><NameTxt>Senator Michael Mullins</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I join Senator Quinn in welcoming the acquisition of Superquinn by Musgrave&rsquo;s and that 2,800 jobs will be saved.  It is particularly appropriate and a source of pleasure that the company is Irish owned.  I have a concern, however, and I ask the Leader to contact the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food to ensure that suppliers, particularly the many small suppliers and farmers throughout the country who supply to Superquinn, are paid for the goods they supplied to the company previously because many of them, unfortunately, will go out of business if they are not looked after in that way.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I support what Senator van Turnhout requested, namely, a debate on child welfare and proposed legislation in that area.  Many Senators spoke last week about the horrific accounts of abuse in the Cloyne report but equally horrific was the abuse by a mother of eight children which was reported and came before the courts in Galway last week.  It is unimaginable that despite the involvement of the Health Service Executive the abuse could have continued for so many years and that those children could have endured the abuse we all read about in the newspapers last week.  That case and many others that have come before the courts indicate an alarming level of abuse within families.  We must ask ourselves whether the procedures in place are fit for purpose and whether the support services in place are properly resourced.  We must have a discussion in this House on the need for us to invest in parenting education.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FidelmaHealyEames"><NameTxt>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames</NameTxt>
	<P>Hear, hear.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I note with interest correspondence between the Minister, Deputy Shatter, and not just the Cathaoirleach but the Leader of the House as well.  I would like to know what the Leader said in response to the Minister.  The fact is that the Leas-Chathaoirleach, Senator O&rsquo;Donovan, Senator Mullen and I, to a lesser extent, raised a number of important <Col N="619"/>issues which were not addressed by the Minister in his Second Stage contribution but which were addressed when we dragged it out of him&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The matter has been dealt with in committee.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;on Committee and Report Stages, and which were fully addressed on Second Stage in the D&aacute;il as a result of statements the Minister made here.  We have a very sensitive Minister for Justice and Equality.  Had he simply briefed spokespersons in advance or come into the House and given the full story in advance this would not have arisen.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator, that is not appropriate to today&rsquo;s business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister has a hard neck complaining about Senators exercising their constitutional rights and meeting their constitutional obligations to raise issues of importance in the Seanad.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>That matter was dealt with already.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The Minister will not muzzle me or any Senator on this side of the House.</P>
        <P>With regard to the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Burton, what happened was that she signed up to a four-year plan stating a certain amount would have to be cut from the social welfare budget overall.  She reasoned with herself and, I suppose, her party and concluded all the money would be obtained from combating social welfare fraud.  She gives an estimate of 3%, which amounts to approximately &euro;600 million.  She realises now she cannot obtain this.  I fear she will target people who may not be guilty of fraud or remove benefits from certain individuals in order not to have to make an across-the-board cut.  She will fail to keep her promise and it is fair to say she already has through cutting various benefits.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Related to this matter is the jobs budget.  One of the best decisions I made since being re-elected was to vote against the Finance (No. 2) Bill.  Unless there is some movement in the labour market, that legislation will have to be repealed.  Essentially, we have given &euro;400 million to the private sector without securing a jobs benefit therefrom.  We will have to review this very quickly.  It must not continue for a number of years unless there is a jobs benefit.</P>
        <P>With regard to health, Fianna F&aacute;il proposes an amendment to the Order of Business, namely, that the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, be invited to the House to discuss local hospital services around the country.  The Minister has absented himself from this House.  It is ironic that we had motions on the Order Paper inviting anyone and everyone into the House when we cannot get Ministers to come here to discuss important issues.</P>
        <P>Promises were made in Roscommon and also in County Meath.  There are severe threats to accident and emergency services in County Meath.  The latter services were always due to be moved elsewhere but not until appropriate facilities become available elsewhere.  There are no such facilities.  There is a now threat to orthopaedic services also.</P>
        <P>I am critical to some extent of the Save Navan Hospital campaign, which is chaired by a Sinn F&eacute;in Deputy.  The group emerged from a meeting with the Minister last week claiming a major victory when all it got from him was a six-month stay of execution on the accident and emergency facility and the first-ever public threat to orthopaedic services in Navan hospital.  The Minister will come into the House to discuss a matter such as the Female Genital Mutilation Bill, which is admittedly very important, but will not come here to discuss issues that are discussed around kitchen tables all over the country.  We cannot get the briefing that the Fine Gael Members of the Oireachtas got and we cannot give the Minister the flak they gave him.  This is most unfortunate.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="620"/>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>It was not enough.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>Not enough, of course.  They need to keep the pressure on because promises were made on every single hospital.  In this regard, the announcement on Navan hospital stated the removal of the accident and emergency facility therefrom would have devastating effects on patient safety in County Meath.  There were no promises made about orthopaedic services because they were never under threat under Fianna F&aacute;il, yet, all of a sudden, there is talk of moving the orthopaedic service to Cappagh as soon as possible.  It is very important that the Minister for Health come to the House to discuss this matter.  It is a stain on his record that he was pushed into meeting local representatives and we cannot get him into the Seanad to discuss the matter.  He should be brought here as quickly as possible to discuss these issues and Fine Gael should be made account for promises it made all over Ireland.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Deputy&rsquo;s amendment stipulate that the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, should come to the House to discuss health in general?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>He should come here to discuss the issue of local hospital services.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnKelly"><NameTxt>Senator John Kelly</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I am glad Senator Byrne touched on social welfare fraud.  A couple of weeks ago, I dropped some kind of clanger in the House when I suggested we should introduce a method of fingerprinting to combat social welfare fraud.  As a result, great debate was generated in the media in recent weeks.  There is an appetite to clamp down considerably on social welfare fraud in areas where it did not occur in the past.  One will hear a lot more whistleblowing because people are now looking at their financial circumstances and realise the only way we can come up with money is to clean up our act.  We cannot put a figure on what social welfare fraud is costing us.  If the Minister for Social Protection suggests it is responsible for 3% of the budget, which would amount to &euro;600 million, I suggest it may cost up to &euro;1 billion per year.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Over the weekend I heard some absolutely scary stories that I will not tell right now.  I hope the Minister can be invited to the House to have an open debate on social welfare fraud.  A form of biometric fingerprinting is being used in other jurisdictions and we must consider it with a view to saving money to provide services we have been talking about cutting in recent years because of the downturn in the economy.  By making savings, we could have money to invest in the health service and all the other services for which we do not have money.  I ask that the Minister for Social Protection be invited to the House for an open debate on this.  This is something I want to follow through to the end and I know the Minister is also committed to doing so.  I hope all sides of the House support it.  If we save money we will not shut down our hospitals.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I share the concerns expressed across the floor with regard to the Minister for Social Protection.  While I agree with everything said by Senator Kelly, I would like him to take note that during the debate on social protection issues in recent weeks, I and others on this side of the House pointed out the considerable savings that have been made.  The most recent report from the Department related to 2010 and showed almost &euro;500,000 had been saved through the anti-fraud measures initiated by the previous Administration, particularly by the previous Minister Mary Hanafin and her successor, Deputy &Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v.  There is no diminution of the need on this side of the House to be reminded that the Department would continue to monitor anti-fraud measures and I welcome Senator Kelly&rsquo;s intervention in this regard.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There is growing concern not only about the remarks of the Minister, Deputy Burton, at the weekend which have been discussed by other Members of the House with whom I largely <Col N="621"/>agree, but also about the question put repeatedly inside and outside the House on where the Government will find the money to fund essential services into 2012.  If the T&aacute;naiste has stated there will be no income tax increases, the Taoiseach has stated there will be no reduction in social welfare payments and the Croke Park agreement will continue to 2013 under its present arrangements whereby there will be no diminution of pay or status, in other words, nobody will lose their jobs, the question remains as to from where the money will come for the essential services.  Even as matters stand, Members on all sides are constantly complaining aboutthem.</P>
        <P>The comments of the Minister, Deputy Burton, at the weekend indicated a chink in the Government&rsquo;s thinking on this and that there are plans to reduce the social welfare budget irrespective of what the T&aacute;naiste and Taoiseach stated.  This is important for all of the people about whom Senator Cullinane spoke, namely, those who suffer from low esteem and who woke up this morning with no prospect of a job, in light of all of the commitments and promises made by the Government.  Far be it from me this early in the mandate of the Government, to which everyone on this side of the House gave fair wind and continue to do so in the national interest, but there is a need for clarity and transparency to give these people some hope that the Government has some answers at least to improving their job prospects.  It is important that the Minister for Social Protection come to the House for a debate in this regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Like Senators Quinn and Mullins, I pay tribute to all involved in the Superquinn project, particularly the Musgrave family for purchasing the business, keeping it in Ireland and retaining the Superquinn name.  Senator Quinn can take great pride from the fact that the Superquinn name has serious credibility in the marketplace in the country.  Coming from a background of running a small retail business with my wife, I agree with Senator Quinn&rsquo;s comments regarding buying Irish and supporting Irish produce and businesses.</P>
        <P>I recall a very prominent GAA person seriously advocating the opening of Croke Park to rugby and soccer getting a dressing down on the street from a certain individual who accused him of being unpatriotic.  He told this individual in return that he would take a lecture on patriotism from him when he stopped shopping in Tesco, as he had a Tesco shopping bag in his hand.  I suggest to Members that useful reading over the summer is a good book on the domination of Tesco and how it has destroyed retail in England.  The book is called <i>Tescopoly</i>.  The research and findings in the book are frightening.  Will the Leader ensure the Government continues to promote the buy Irish campaign, ensures the resources exist to facilitate quality branding in agribusiness and retail in general in the country and continues to promote the concept of being patriotic and spending our money with Irish businesses and supporting Irish products?</P>
        
      </Speaker>
        <P Just="Left">I commend An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na for being one of the first public State agencies to issue electronic payslips.  It appears from media reports earlier that this will save the taxpayer &euro;400,000.  Were teachers to follow suit, it would save the taxpayer &euro;1.2 million.  Will the Leader ask all senior Ministers to instruct their Department to issue pay slips electronically anymore because it is farcical in this day and age that this cannot be done?  Millions of euro could be saved.  It is a simple method to save money and I ask the Leader in correspondence with Ministers to bring that to their attention.</P>
      <Speaker pid="JohnCrown"><NameTxt>Senator John Crown</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Will the Leader ask the Minister for Health to come to the House to explain to us, in the context of lengthy briefings he will give us on matters we wish to bring to his attention, what is the current status and the health of VHI?  I was giving this some thought recently.  The single biggest catastrophe that could happen to the public health system would be if anything were to happen to VHI that resulted in a large movement of insured patients <Col N="622"/>back on to the waiting lists for the public system.  I supported the new Government parties when they were still in opposition on the notion that they would reform the health system to a single tier, insurance-based mixture of private and social insurance, which is the synthesis of the Fine Gael and Labour Party documents.  It is the same as the German model, not the Dutch model, and that is how they will get their reform.  Germany has the best large country health system in the world.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I have previously expressed a little disquiet that the plan is for this not to happen until after another election.  It is incumbent on all of us to advance that agenda because all the problems, pathologies and difficulties in the health system currently are not fixable in a most fundamental way until the inconsistencies at the heart of the system are addressed.  Pending that reform, the financial health of VHI, in which the Minister is the sole shareholder, is of critical importance and I would be grateful if he could give us a report indicating what his assessment and international expert opinions are about the current level of support for the company and, in particular, if there is a possibility that it is unusually sensitive to decreases in acute flow to meet its ability to pay for the services of its contracted members.  Most other commercial insurance companies have endowment and investment to support them.  I do not speak with authority on this and that is why I ask the question.  Does VHI have that or is it dependent on current revenues to fund the expenses it has incurred from past memberships?  If that is the case, as the economy contracts, one could imagine a vulnerability in this regard.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I asked a few quick questions of the Ministers of State at the Department of Health recently.  Will the Minister of State with responsibility for disability, equality and mental health, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, get back to us regarding the number of psychiatrists in Ireland and how that compares to the UK and the rest of Europe as we attempt to make this great move from inpatient psychiatric care to community-based care?</P>
        <P>Since I spoke on the issue of banning smoking in cars with children last week, I have experienced a tidal wave of support for an amendment.  There is no necessity to sway public opinion on this in advance of legislation.  A modest amendment to one paragraph of the 2002 Act could change this immediately and cost neutrally without debate.  It would involve adding one minor amendment to the section that empowers the Minister to ban smoking in various places.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Will the Leader ask the Minister about VHI and renew my questions about the other two issues?  I urge him to consider an amendment to ban smoking in cars in which children are travelling sooner rather than later.  There is no reason to delay that.  Every month we delay means more children will be exposed needlessly to cigarette smoke in cars.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaulCoghlan"><NameTxt>Senator Paul Coghlan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I support the remarks of Senators Quinn, Mullins and Conway regarding the takeover of the Superquinn group by the Musgrave group.  Superquinn is an important network of stores and it is good it will continue in Irish ownership.  Its commitment to Irish goods, produce and business is very important.</P>
        <P>The code of conduct proposed by the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, between large multiples and suppliers will be important.  If it is at all possible before the recess, will the Leader invite the Minister to explain what he envisages will be contained in the code?  From anecdotal evidence, we know the larger operations have used much browbeating and bullying tactics towards their suppliers.  It is important Musgraves has become involved in Superquinn and the jobs in the company secured.  I hope there will be a renewed commitment to supporting Irish suppliers and produce.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I second the proposal to amend the Order of Business to consider my motion on accident and emergency services at Roscommon County Hospital.  I am anxious <Col N="623"/>the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, attends the House to explain his allegations regarding mortality rates at the hospital.  Senator Crown has outlined his concerns about the Minister&rsquo;s figures.  An outgoing physician, Dr. Pat McHugh, was in touch with me about this matter to explain the hospital staff were upset by the allegations.  The figures the Minister gave for mortality rates at the hospital were inaccurate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I am proposing an amendment to the Order of Business in order that the Minister for Health will attend the House to explain his allegations about a 21% mortality rate at Roscommon County hospital when it was actually 5%.</P>
        <P>When does the Leader expect the House to debate the Cloyne report?  Will it be next week?  It must be debated before the House goes into the summer recess.  Otherwise, when the House returns the issue will have moved on.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I commend the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, for his actions regarding the serious sexual abuse case in Donegal heard in the courts yesterday.  I commend those courageous young men who went public to ensure the person responsible was outed.  When I heard them on the radio, I was impressed by the decision they made.  The 2001 legislation covering the sex offenders&rsquo; register must be reviewed considering it proved inadequate in the Donegal case.  It is remarkable that someone found guilty of sexual offences was subsequently allowed to continue as a caretaker in a school and re-offend.  The Minister has demanded reports on the Garda&rsquo;s role from the Garda Commissioner and from the staff and management of the school involved.  This case deserves an immediate and detailed investigation.</P>
        <P>I was impressed by Senator John Kelly&rsquo;s call for investigations into alleged social welfare fraud.  I was in awe of his alleged generosity when he was a community welfare officer in the Ballaghaderreen area&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">That is irrelevant to the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>&mdash;&mdash;particularly when it came to the 2009 local elections.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">That is irrelevant and inappropriate to the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I found it very hard to canvass in his area then.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Leyden should withdraw that comment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Those remarks should be withdrawn.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I said, &ldquo;I am in awe.&rdquo;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>That is a personal claim that an individual abused his position during a local election.  Those types of comments should not be allowed in the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>The Leader of the House has asked Senator Leyden to withdraw those remarks.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>If they have caused any offence.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Those comments were personal and inappropriate to the Order of Business.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I said, &ldquo;I am in awe of the alleged situation.&rdquo;</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="624"/>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Leyden referred to personal matters about the Senator&rsquo;s work which is inappropriate.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I withdraw the comments.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate the Senator&rsquo;s withdrawal.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TerryLeyden"><NameTxt>Senator Terry Leyden</NameTxt>
	<P>I made no allegation whatsoever.  The Leader of the House is adding to it actually.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>I accept the Senator&rsquo;s withdrawal.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="TomSheahan"><NameTxt>Senator Tom Sheahan</NameTxt>
	<P>I ask the Leader to request the Minister for Finance to come before the House to explain in a clear, concise manner the ramifications for ordinary account holders in the banks of the &euro;2.7 billion fund which must be set aside in the Central Bank by 2020 to guarantee the bank guarantee scheme.  The Central Bank must set aside &euro;300 million per annum in the period from 2011 until 2020 for this purpose.  The ramifications of this requirement for ordinary account holders include interest rate increases, further bank charges, etc.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to the House to explain the position as I do not believe members of the public are aware of the fund, even if they will have noticed that interest rates are increasing virtually weekly.  One hears about debt forgiveness and the pressure people are under to make their mortgage repayments but the elephant in the room is the bank charges which will hit every person who holds a bank account.  One must bear in mind that we have only three banks and many more banks were operating in this State when the &euro;2.7 billion fund was announced.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarcMacSharry"><NameTxt>Senator Marc MacSharry</NameTxt>
	<P>I join other speakers in calling for a debate on health.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, should come to the House to discuss a wide variety of issues which have arisen.  Notwithstanding that the Ministers of State, Deputies Shortall and Lynch, have come to the House to discuss specific issues, the senior Minister must make himself available to Senators.</P>
        <P>Media reports at the weekend indicated that the Health Service Executive overspent by &euro;170 million to the end of May.  This will place additional pressures on the exemptions to the moratorium on recruiting staff.  As a result, specialist ambulance personnel may not be replaced, which would have major implications for the health service in the context of accident and emergency services being wound down or reconfigured nationwide.  I would appreciate if the Leader could arrange such a debate as a matter of urgency.</P>
        <P>I ask the Leader to make time available to have the Minister for Finance come before the House to discuss the implications of the summit of European leaders which will take place later in the week.  It is interesting that the gravity of the situation is absent from many of the media reports on this issue.  Not since the Second World War has Europe, in this case the Single Market and European Union, been under such threat.  It is important that the House debate the issue as it could, in a small way, produce some solutions which could be listened to.  It is evident that a coherent approach is absent in Europe.  In the absence of debt forgiveness by the large European banks, whether French or German institutions, the only option will be quantitative easing on a massive scale.  Essentially, this means printing money to try to inflate our way out of the current economic problems.  This would complement the good work governments, including the Irish Government, are trying to do by introducing austerity measures.  In our case, it will ensure the &euro;18 billion deficit is reduced.  The position is serious.</P>
        <P>Under the previous Administration the House had a weekly opportunity to debate economic issues.  While I accept the Order of Business afforded some opportunity in that regard, irrespec<Col N="625"/>tive of whether the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, or another Minister comes before the House, we must have a specific debate focused on solutions rather than political point scoring.  Given that next week is the final week of the session and the D&aacute;il will rise this week, the Seanad should comment on developments that will take place later this week.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MarkDaly"><NameTxt>Senator Mark Daly</NameTxt>
	<P>I support Senator Mac Conghail&rsquo;s call to invite former President Robinson to the House to give her views on her visit to Africa.  The Horn of Africa is facing its worst famine in 60 years.  A total of 10 million people in Somalia, Ethiopia, Uganda and Kenya face starvation.  Given our own history, the view of Africa from this side of the world is probably similar to the view the Victorians had of the Irish, namely, that we deserved what we got.  When Lord Trevelyan closed the famine relief efforts and soup kitchens, he said the situation in Ireland shall be left to the operation of natural causes.  I am sure there are elements in the World Bank looking at the situation in the Horn of Africa who have a similar Victorian-type view.</P>
        <P>Dr. Nally, who is publishing a book on the Famine, <i>Political Violence and the Great Irish Famine</i>, spoke about the structural violence in terms of the Famine.  There was an institutional arrangement that made society vulnerable to famine.  It made us dependent on our near neighbour without us being able to realise our potential.  The same situation applies in Africa today.  The notion that science can provide a solution to famine is not true because famine is a human phenomenon.  It can be solved through politics.  In the same way as ships were leaving this country during the Famine laden with food for ports in other countries while relief ships were on the way, Africa, which has an abundance of resources in ores, diamonds and gold has all its resources leaving its land while people are starving at the same time.</P>
        <P>I look forward to the debate in the House, which I hope will take place next week, on Palestinian statehood.  The debate must happen now before the House reconvenes in September because the United Nations General Assembly will have voted on the resolution by then.  The parallels between this country in 1918 and Palestine of today are similar in that no one wanted to recognise Irish independence.  Palestinians are not looking for recognition of all of their lands, as the 1967 borders represents only 22% of what was formerly Palestine.  They are not asking for the world; they are not even asking for their own share of it, they are only asking for one fifth of it.  If our learned colleagues opposite do not put forward a resolution to be agreed by all Members of the House, then we will table one.  We would be very interested to see how members of the Labour Party would vote on the issue given the fact that the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade stated today that he wants to be there to recognise Palestinian statehood.  Let us see and test his mettle.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMWhite"><NameTxt>Senator Mary M. White</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I have spoken privately to the Leader of the Seanad, Senator Maurice Cummins, about how anxious I and all my colleagues on this side of the House are to get the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, to come to the House.  The most serious crisis in the country is the provision of jobs for the 450,000 people who are unemployed.  I inquired last week about how we are going to get the increasing number of long-term unemployed engaged in jobs.</P>
        <P>Two issues require the Minister&rsquo;s urgent attention.  The first is cashflow to small businesses.  Bank credit has plummeted from an annual expansion of approximately 30% in the boom years to zero in recent times.  Cash and liquidity have dried up.  The larger firms in particular are increasingly stretching out the number of days credit they expect from suppliers, especially SME companies.  Many firms are caught up in the pincer movement as banks restrict or will not increase overdraft facilities.  The net result is that many firms have collapsed or are in jeopardy.</P><Col N="626"/>
        <P Just="Left">The Minister seems to be basking in the glory of the increase in exports among multinational companies.  With all due respect, that has nothing to do with Fine Gael or the Labour Party.  It was under the watch of Fianna F&aacute;il that exports grew in indigenous and multinational companies.  I want the Minister to come to the House.  The jobs initiative makes a commitment that &euro;20 billion of new lending would be available from AIB and Bank of Ireland in the next three years.  The Minister will have to ensure the Department provides transparency and informs us as to whether this money is getting to small and medium-sized domestic companies.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Fianna F&aacute;il Members in the D&aacute;il, through Deputy Willie O&rsquo;Dea, are introducing a motion on Private Members&rsquo; business tonight dealing with the decision of Mr. Justice Kevin Feeney in the High Court last week that JLCs are unconstitutional.  My view about the attitudes of employers is not as cynical as that of Deputy O&rsquo;Dea.  I do not expect them to be rapacious in cutting back the wages of staff, particularly in lower wage industries such as catering.  However, I would like the Minister, Deputy Bruton, to come to the House and allay the fears of people in the sectors covered by the 13 JLCs by assuring them, bearing in mind last week&rsquo;s decision, that salaries will be maintained.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I express my disgust at the fact that the French boat <i>Dignit&eacute;</i> was attacked by Israeli commandos at noon, Irish time, today.  I hope that all parties support the attempts by the leader of the Seanad on this side to table a cross-party motion condemning the military action of the Israeli commandos, in order to emphasise Ireland&rsquo;s renewed stance in our attempt to bring about Palestinian rights to aid, trade and statehood.  I hope all parties and Members of this House, and indeed the D&aacute;il, will support this effort.</P>
        <P Just="Left">When the issue of hospital care was discussed here, I was unfortunately detained at a committee meeting but I would like to refer to it.  I met a voluntary community group yesterday evening to discuss its valid concerns, which are emerging on a daily basis, about our local hospital in Donegal, Letterkenny General Hospital.  The budgetary constraints placed upon the hospital management were touched on by the Taoiseach last Friday when he said it was up to management in every hospital to live within their budgets &mdash; in other words, they must cut services if they cannot meet demand.  That is an unreasonable stance for the Taoiseach to take.  He is almost condemning the management practices being adopted within our regional hospitals.  The general manager of Letterkenny General Hospital, Sean Murphy, and his team are doing their utmost to live within the constraints to which they are subject.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I hope the Leader will accede to the request for the debate we are seeking.  I ask that as part of it we discuss the issue of the moratorium on recruitment and the straitjacket placed upon HSE management at local level, which cannot send on requests to the Department of Health for the provision of essential services.  We are asking for the moratorium to be lifted for certain aspects of hospital care.  I hope that sense will prevail and that we can have this debate.  I also hope that, for the first time in the life of this new Seanad, the Minister will not shirk his responsibilities and will come to the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator O&rsquo;Brien and other Senators spoke about the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, and I thank them for their comments in that regard.  We need to change the way in which we do business and this is another step in the right direction.  With regard to the Palestinian motion, I hope that after the Order of Business we will be able to reach agreement on an all-party motion.  We have a wording we would like to use and I hope we can agree on the motion today.</P><Col N="627"/>
        <P Just="Left">Committee and Report Stages of the Electoral (Amendment) Bill will be dealt with on Thursday.  I had a meeting with the party leaders last week in which I outlined the position on this Bill, and there was no objection at that stage to having Committee and Report Stages on that day, with a break in between.  We will do our best to help everybody on this.  We are not trying to steamroll it through.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>On a point of order, I am the Whip of the Independent group and I would like at least to be informed of these matters.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator&rsquo;s leader did not inform him, I am afraid.  He or she should have informed the Senator.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not have a leader.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Whoever represents the Senator was at that meeting.  The Senator must have somebody representing him.  Ample time is being afforded to Senators to discuss the Electoral (Amendment) Bill.</P>
        <P>With regard to the request for the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, to come before the House, we will try to have him in early in September.  We have had the Ministers of State, Deputies Kathleen Lynch and R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall, who are excellent junior Ministers in the Department and quite capable of taking any matter with regard to health.  I compliment them on their performances in the House and the amount of time they have given to the Seanad.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Bacik spoke about strengthening the powers of committees, and about media ownership and the fallout of the telephone hacking scandal in the UK.  This is certainly something that needs attention here, and we can arrange a debate on the issue some time in the autumn.  </P><P Just="Left">Senators van Turnhout, Mullins and others called for a debate on the safety and welfare of children. The Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, has agreed to come to the House to discuss the recommendations of the Murphy report and others. I am sure we can arrange that at an early opportunity. The Minister will be coming to the House tomorrow after 7 p.m. to discuss the Child Care (Amendment) Bill. She will be here for a considerable time and I am sure there are many items with regard to the Bill that Senators would like to raise with her. </P>
        <P>Senators Quinn, Conway, Coghlan and others spoke about the takeover of Superquinn by the Musgrave group.  I am sure we all welcome the fact that more than 2,500 jobs will be protected as a result of this takeover.  Senator Quinn has raised in the House on several occasions the issue of the purchasing policies of retailers.  I accept his concerns about the Minister&rsquo;s intentions in that regard and I hope the Minister will address these matters.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senators Burke and Walsh spoke about the cost of tribunals and the amount of time they take.  I hope the increased powers for committees that are envisaged by the Oireachtas will negate the necessity for tribunals in the future.  The expense is, from my point of view, totally immoral.  I agree with Senator Walsh that waste will need to be tackled across all Departments; this is taking place, and I hope we have support from the other side of the House in this regard.</P>
        <P>Senator Healy Eames spoke about the extension of the remit of pharmacists to administer &lsquo;flu vaccinations and wondered whether this could be extended further to include the BCG vaccine.  She should contact the Minister in this regard.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I agree that we should have a further debate on tourism, particularly with regard to the home market.  Of course, the Galway Races is a big event and if Members wish to go to them, they will have four days next week to do so.  As we hope to finish our business on either Tuesday <Col N="628"/>or Wednesday next week, there will be another four days of racing if they wish to travel to Galway.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="BrianODomhnaill"><NameTxt>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</NameTxt>
	<P>A Fine Gael fund-raiser.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>Four days will be more than enough to lose money.</P>
        <P>Senator Norris raised the Residential Institutions Redress (Amendment) Bill.  The other House took approximately one and half hours to complete all Stages of that Bill.  I am allocating two and a half hours for the debate on it.  If that is not sufficient, we can look at it again but I hope we will be able to complete our business in two and a half hours, given that the Lower House spent less than an hour and a half on it.  I take on board his question regarding the involuntary use of ECT.  I will check the status of the Bill.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senators Mac Conghail and Daly referred to a matter raised by Senator Quinn last week, the famine in the Horn of Africa.  It is a dreadful situation.  Mary Robinson is travelling to the region, and the suggestion that we invite her to address the House is excellent.  We currently have requests for approximately ten people to address the House and we will try to deal with that in the next session.  Two of the people who have been asked to address the House are former Senators, Mary Robinson and Maurice Manning, who can speak on human rights.  I am sure they will accede to our requests.  It would be excellent to have them in the House to address Members on their experiences on those issues.</P>
        <P>Senator Cullinane referred to the remarks of the Minister for Social Protection.  The Minister, Deputy Burton, has clarified the matter.  She was referring to less than 2% of the people on social welfare.  She is an excellent Minister for Social Protection.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">4 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
<P>Senator Mullins asked that contact be made with the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food.  I remind Members that tomorrow the House will see a new departure with questions and answers on agriculture, rather than statements.  The Minister will spend an hour and a half dealing with agriculture and an hour on fisheries.  He will address the House for ten minutes on agriculture and for another ten minutes on fisheries.  That will be followed by a question and answer session, similar to what takes place on the Order of Business.  I hope there will be almost full attendance in the House.  It is what we envisage for such question and answer sessions.  If a Minister is prepared to come to the House and take questions and answer them, there should be a good attendance.  It might be a way in which we could change the way the House conducts its business.  I believe it should be the way for the future.</P>
        <P>In response to Senator Byrne and the press reports, I did not receive a letter from the Minister for Justice and Equality on that matter, as was reported.  With regard to the Minister for Social Protection coming to the House to clarify matters, she was in the House to deal with the Social Welfare and Pensions Bill.  She is an excellent Minister and I have full confidence in her abilities.  I have already addressed the question about health and the Ministers of State coming to the House.</P>
        <P>Senator Kelly referred to social welfare fraud.  The Minister is tackling that problem and I am sure we will see the result by the end of the year.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Mooney spoke about money for essential services.  Undoubtedly, that matter will be addressed in the budget but as I have said on a previous occasion, we are spending &euro;18 billion more than our income.  That problem must and will be addressed by the Government.  There will be painful decisions as a result but they must be taken as they are necessary.</P><Col N="629"/>
        <P>Senator Conway spoke about a buy Irish campaign and supporting Irish business.  I would not be anti-Tesco in any way.  The Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food will inform the House tomorrow that Tesco spends well over &euro;1 billion on Irish produce, thus supporting Irish producers.  We all hope they will support us even more.  They have created thousands of jobs.  I am sure the Minister for Agriculture, Fisheries and Food will address the question of food supply, producers and so on tomorrow and that the relevant questions will be asked of him.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator John Crown raised the financial health of VHI and its vulnerability or otherwise.  It is something I will address to the Minister along with his advice, like that of Senator Sean Barrett, that we advance the agenda of reform and universal health insurance.  I am sure the Minister would like to advance it but it will be difficult.  The Minister is totally committed to advancing the issue of universal health insurance.  I will address the questions asked in regard to the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, on the number of psychiatrists and on an amendment in regard to smoking in cars in which children are present.</P>
        <P>Senator Terry Leyden raised the dreadful Donegal case about which we read in the newspapers and heard on the news.  I share the concerns expressed by the judge in that case.  I also welcome the fact the Senator withdrew remarks in regard to Senator John Kelly.</P>
        <P>Senator Tom Sheahan raised the bank guarantee scheme.  Senator Mark MacSharry called for a solution-focused debate on financial matters next week.  The Minister for Finance will be in the House for the next two hours to deal with the Finance (No. 3) Bill, and it will not be the first time he will have been in this House.</P>
        <P>Senator Mark Daly raised the Palestine situation.  I hope we will agree on an all-party motion today which we will put to the House.  Senator Mary White raised the issue of jobs and small business.  The Minister for Finance has written to the banks in regard to releasing credit for small and medium-sized enterprises and business in general.  I hope the banks will act on the letter from the Minister.  I agree with Senator Mary White in regard to Deputy O&rsquo;Dea.  He has a cynical view of many issues.</P>
        <P>Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill raised the issue of budgets in hospitals.  As I said, we are spending &euro;18 billion more than we are taking in.  Householders are expected to balance their books from one week to the next and hospitals are being asked to do the same.  That is not a big thing to ask of hospitals.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Senator Norris proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: &ldquo;That only Second Stage of the Residential Institutions Redress (Amendment) Bill 2011 be taken today.&rdquo;  Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>In light of the Leader&rsquo;s helpful and co-operative answer, I am happy to withdraw the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Senator Thomas Byrne has also proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: &ldquo;That a debate with the Minister for Health to discuss the issue of local hospital services be taken today.&rdquo;  Is the amendment being pressed?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DarraghOBrien"><NameTxt>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien</NameTxt>
	<P>Absolutely.</P>
      
      </Speaker>
        <P Just="Left">Amendment put.</P>
      <Vote>
        <Result><Col N="630"/>The Seanad divided: T&aacute;, 18; N&iacute;l, 28.</Result>
        <YHeading>T&aacute;</YHeading>
        <YesVote pid="SeanDBarrett">Barrett, Sean D.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="ThomasByrne">Byrne, Thomas.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JohnCrown">Crown, John.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DavidCullinane">Cullinane, David.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarkDaly">Daly, Mark.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="TerryLeyden">Leyden, Terry.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MarcMacSharry">MacSharry, Marc.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="PaschalMooney">Mooney, Paschal.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DavidNorris">Norris, David.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="BrianODomhnaill">&Oacute; Domhnaill, Brian.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DarraghOBrien">O&rsquo;Brien, Darragh.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="NedOSullivan">O'Sullivan, Ned.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="AverilPower">Power, Averil.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="FergalQuinn">Quinn, Feargal.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="KathrynReilly">Reilly, Kathryn.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="JimWalsh">Walsh, Jim.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="MaryMWhite">White, Mary M.</YesVote>
        <YesVote pid="DiarmuidWilson">Wilson, Diarmuid.</YesVote>
        <NHeading>N&iacute;l</NHeading>
        <NoVote pid="IvanaBacik">Bacik, Ivana.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulBradford">Bradford, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TerryBrennan">Brennan, Terry.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="DeirdreClune">Clune, Deirdre.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="EamonnCoghlan">Coghlan, Eamonn.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PaulCoghlan">Coghlan, Paul.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelComiskey">Comiskey, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MartinConway">Conway, Martin.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MauriceCummins">Cummins, Maurice.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JimDarcy">D&rsquo;Arcy, Jim.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelWDArcy">D&rsquo;Arcy, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnGilroy">Gilroy, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FidelmaHealyEames">Healy Eames, Fidelma.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JamesHeffernan">Heffernan, James.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="LorraineHiggins">Higgins, Lorraine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CaitKeane">Keane, C&aacute;it.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="FiachMacConghail">Mac Conghail, Fiach.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MarieMoloney">Moloney, Marie.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MaryMoran">Moran, Mary.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TonyMulcahy">Mulcahy, Tony.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="MichaelMullins">Mullins, Michael.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="CatherineNoone">Noone, Catherine.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="SusanOKeeffe">O&rsquo;Keeffe, Susan.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="PatONeill">O&rsquo;Neill, Pat.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="TomSheahan">Sheahan, Tom.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JillianVanTurnhout">van Turnhout, Jillian.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="JohnWhelan">Whelan, John.</NoVote>
        <NoVote pid="KatherineZappone">Zappone, Katherine.</NoVote>
        <Tellers>Tellers: T&aacute;, Senators Ned O&rsquo;Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson; N&iacute;l, Senators Paul Coghlan and Susan O&rsquo;Keeffe.</Tellers>
        <Decision>Amendment declared lost.</Decision>
      </Vote>
        <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Standing Order" RHead="57: Motion"> 
    <Title>Standing Order 57: Motion</Title>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That, notwithstanding anything in Standing Orders, with effect from the 20th July, 2011 and until further notice in the 24th Seanad, Standing Order 57 of the Standing Orders of Seanad &Eacute;ireann relative to Public Business is hereby amended by the addition of the following paragraph:</P>
        <P LI="2">&lsquo;(2) On the recommendation of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges and with the leave of the House, representatives and persons in public and civic life may attend and be heard in the Seanad.&rsquo;.&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P FLI="0">Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Seanad Public Petitions" RHead="Committee: Motion"> 
    <Title>Seanad Public Petitions Committee: Motion</Title>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P>I move:</P>
        <P LI="1">That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the adoption of the following terms of reference for the Seanad Public Petitions Committee (SPPC), established under Standing Orders 92-95 and in <Col N="631"/>accordance with the Report of the Sub-Committee of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges on the Establishment of a Public Petitions Committee:</P>
        <P LI="2">1. The SPPC shall have the same membership as the Seanad Committee of Selection.</P>
        <P LI="2">2. The Leas-Chathaoirleach of the Seanad shall be <i>ex officio </i>Chairperson of the SPPC.  The quorum of the SPPC shall be five.</P>
        <P LI="2">3. The SPPC shall specify and publicise a particular area related to the legislative powers of the Seanad or to an issue of public policy on which petitions will be invited in each sitting term of the Seanad.</P>
        <P LI="2">4. A deadline for the submission of petitions to the SPPC shall also be specified and publicised in each sitting term.</P>
        <P LI="2">5. The SPPC shall sit in private in the first instance to decide upon the particular area upon which it will invite the submission of petitions.</P>
        <P LI="2">6. Once petitions have been submitted, the SPPC shall again sit in private to consider whether petitions submitted are admissible and to consider further what action to take in relation to admissible petitions.</P>
        <P LI="2">7. Private sittings of the SPPC shall take place in one of the Committee Rooms.</P>
        <P LI="2">8. Where the SPPC considers it appropriate to hear from a petitioner or petitioners directly in respect of a petition submitted to it, it shall arrange for the holding of a public session.</P>
        <P LI="2">9. Such public sessions, which one or more petitioners may be invited to address, and which members of the public may attend, may be held in the Seanad chamber outside of sitting times and may be televised.</P>
        <P LI="2">10. These terms of reference to be read in conjunction with Seanad Standing Orders 92-95.&rsquo;&rsquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P FLI="0">Question put and agreed to.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance (No. 3) Bill 2011 [Certified Money" RHead="Bill]: Committee and Remaining Stages"> 
    <Title>Finance (No. 3) Bill 2011 [Certified Money Bill]: Committee and Remaining Stages</Title>
        <P Just="Center">SECTION 1</P>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P>I move recommendation No. 1:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 4, to delete lines 4 to 7 and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;(2) A civil partner shall be treated for income tax purposes as living with his or her civil partner unless they are in fact separated and in such circumstances that the separation is likely to be permanent.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0" Just="Left">The general intention of this recommendation is the same as the other recommendations I, along with my colleagues, have proposed &mdash; to ensure the Bill provides the same tax treatment for civil partners as that of married couples under all tax categories and that the children of civil partners are afforded the same treatment as children of a married couple.  On Committee Stage, the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, said that registered civil partners will receive the same tax treatment as married couples in respect of income tax, stamp duty, capital acquis<Col N="632"/>itions tax, capital gains tax and VAT.  The Oireachtas Library and Research Service Bills Digest states this Bill gives civil partners an equal treatment to married couples regarding tax, that the Bill amends tax legislation to provide that civil partners will be treated with equal status to married partners in tax affairs and that a child of civil partners is given equivalent tax treatment to a child of a married couple.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In light of comments by Senators on the Bill, the Minister of State emphatically declared that civil partnership is not marriage because it cannot be marriage, a point with which I am wholeheartedly in agreement.  My recommendations do not seek to push the institution of civil partnership any closer to marriage.  On Committee Stage, I expressed the view that the institution of civil partnership will never represent equality for same-sex couples; therefore, there is no need to fix it in this regard.</P>
        <P>By way of a tangential point to my recommendation, I wish to respond to the declarations by the Minister of State on Committee Stage.  He stated three times during the debate that the only way marriage can be changed under our constitutional architecture is by constitutional referendum.  In the first instance of declaring this he referred to the case of Zappone and Gilligan <i>v</i> Revenue Commissioners, which is still before the courts.  I am that Zappone.  An appeal was lodged to the Supreme Court in early 2007 and we are still awaiting a date.  In light of the fact that there will ultimately be a Supreme Court judgment on the case, it is too soon to argue that the only way marriage will be extended to same-sex couples is through a constitutional referendum of the people.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I note, too, that on Second Stage a majority of Senators were in agreement with the comments I made and concerns I raised and the need to amend the Bill in certain instances, which is what is behind the recommendations I am putting forward, along with my colleagues.  Those recommendations focus solely on the Taxes Consolidation Act to ensure equal protection for registered civil partners and their children when that civil partnership breaks down.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I note also the comments of Senator Mullen on Committee Stage and offer him the same respect he offers me.  It is the only way to do our business here.  My views are also rooted in an ethical concern for the good of the common and that the common is good when it affirms the diversity of human identity in its entirety.</P>
        <P>The more specific intention of the first recommendation is to bring the definition of &ldquo;civil partners&rdquo; living together and separated in line with that of married couples.  If this recommendation is accepted or if the Minister considers it, it will mean that civil partners, like married couples, may be separated, thereby considered separated for tax purposes, but still living under the same roof.  As I outlined on Second Stage, there may be instances whereby, in light of difficult financial circumstances, civil partners whose relationship has broken down cannot maintain two separate dwellings and are effectively forced to live together.</P>
        <P>I note that tax law must follow general law &mdash; the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, referred to that in his response to me &mdash; and therefore this Bill must not go against the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act.  It is correct to note that the civil partnership Act does not expressly provide for a judicial separation.  It only provides for dissolution and annulment.  However, having read the Act again there does not appear to be anything within that Act that prevents a deed of separation or a separation agreement between civil partners.  There is an implicit recognition in the Act that civil partners can be separate.  Section 127(3) of the Act requires the court to have regard to separation agreements in considering the making of a post-dissolution order.  I am arguing, therefore, that there seems to be no impediment in the Act that couples are recognised as separated for taxation purposes. <Col N="633"/> In this recommendation they can be recognised as separated for taxation purposes while still living under the same roof as married couples.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P>I consider that we are very lucky to have someone of the standing of Senator Zappone to make the detailed, considered, thoughtful and authoritative statement on this matter.  I support every word she said and amplify it slightly.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The first point is with regard to constitutionality.  That is simply a ruse, and everybody knows it.  The Law Reform Commission took advice on that and it was advised by eminent counsel that there was no difficulty about introducing the full range of marriage unless the new institutions, right up to the level of marriage, purported to give greater rights.  Giving equal rights did not; that was the opinion of learned counsel.</P>
        <P>Second, the Minister&rsquo;s own late distinguished colleague, Declan Costello, pointed out in 1967 that the wording of the Constitution clearly left it open to the introduction of marriage between persons of the same sex.  I am quoting one of the most eminent members of the Minister&rsquo;s own party on that.  Those two references on their own should at least open up a discussion on this matter.</P>
        <P>With regard to the undermining of marriage, it was a laughable argument because surely the best allies that marriage could possibly have are people who want to commit themselves.  I refer the Minister to what I said during the debate on the civil partnership Bill, and it was not just uninformed opinion of my own but reports of various governments in the Scandinavian region, particularly the Swedish Parliament, which commissioned academic research into this area.  It discovered that this was a helpful direction in which to go.  It was unusually conservative at the beginning.  In the aftermath of the measures it passed in the Parliament, it was discovered there was actually an increase in marriage.  This is because heterosexual couples within a certain social circle who saw their same-sex couple friends getting married actually believed it would be a good idea to get married themselves.  Not only does same-sex marriage not undermine marriage, it actually supports it and leads to an increase in the incidence thereof.  These are not my opinions but facts, and they should be treated as such.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The civil partnership Bill was a considerable advance and for that reason I reluctantly supported it, despite its deeply offensive and most unhelpful language.  For example, in references to the domestic arrangements of people in civil partnerships, a distinction was drawn between persons of different sexes and persons of the same sex in references to the place in which they lived.  In the case of same-sex couples, the residence was described merely as a shared home or shared accommodation whereas it was described as the family home in reference to people of opposite sexes, even those in civil partnerships.  That is grossly offensive to gay people.  No consideration whatever was given to the welfare of children.  I would have believed, given the history of child abuse by both the religious and State institutions, that any Government would be very careful not to continue the abuse of children achieved by the legislation.  I looked to the Government to amend it.</P>
        <P>There seems to be a block with regard to retrospection.  I raised this on many occasions in this House.  In this regard, consider the circumstances of people I know who are now in recognised civil partnerships or at least in partly recognised civil partnerships &mdash; there seems to be a lot of confusion about this.  One couple got married in the British embassy in Dublin but there appears to be no retrospection in terms of their pension arrangements.  This is an unjust discrimination.</P>
        <P>Let me draw attention again to the remarkable and wonderful words made by M&aacute;ire Geoghegan-Quinn as Minister for Justice when mean-minded amendments were introduced by the then Opposition in order to humiliate gay people and put in place a discriminatory age of <Col N="634"/>consent.  She said &mdash; this is the golden mean &mdash; that she would require clear, factual and cogent reasons to introduce any measure of discrimination against an Irish citizen, and that since none had been provided, she would not accept the amendments.  That is a very important statement because it relates not only to the infringement of the rights of gay citizens in this country, but also to every area of discrimination.  No Irish Minister should accept a measure of discrimination unless clear, cogent and factual reasons have been produced.  I do not refer to financial reasons, moral objections of one kind or another or personal ideas but to clear, cogent and factual reasons.  For that reason, I have great pleasure in supporting the recommendation tabled by Senator Zappone.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister, Deputy Michael Noonan, to the House.  We all very much welcome this Bill.  It was very evident on Second Stage how much support there is for it across the floor of the House.  It is clearly designed to give effect to the commitments in the programme for Government following from the passing of the civil partnership legislation.  We all very much welcome that.  On Second Stage Senator Zappone put forward some very constructive and useful proposals as to how relatively minor amendments might be made.</P>
        <P>This recommendation is one that may deserve further consideration given that it would, if accepted, make very little change to section 1.  It simply proposes to change &ldquo;in fact living separately and apart&rdquo; to &ldquo;in fact separated&rdquo;.  Has the Minister had an opportunity to review that and consider whether the current wording is the best means of describing what is intended?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><TitleTxt>Minister for Finance</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senators for their contributions and very cogent arguments.  This is text legislation that is consequent on the primary legislation introduced by my predecessor, namely, the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010.  It is not possible for me to accept the recommendation because I cannot go beyond the scope of the original legislation.  If I understand the recommendation correctly, it seeks to define the status of separation for civil partners within the tax law.  The Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010 does not provide for a status of separation in the same manner as exists for married couples.  The tax legislation cannot make provision for something that is not in the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010 and as such cannot create the status of a separated civil partner.</P>
        <P>The legislation before the House already provides that a civil partner shall be treated for income tax purposes as living with his or her civil partner unless they are living separately and apart in circumstances where reconciliation is unlikely.  The recommendation, as proposed, relies on a civil partner being of the status of separated.  As we have established, this status does not exist for civil partners in the general law.  As such, I do not see that this recommendation could be implemented and therefore cannot accept it.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for his response.  In the recommendation I was trying to put forward two items.  The first is the suggestion that in the civil partnership legislation there is no absolute negation of the possibility of a voluntary agreement between civil partners for separation.  It does not seem to be contained in the Act.  It is true to state there is no allowance for judicial separation but this is not to state there is no possibility of implicit recognition of some form of voluntary or deed of separation.  On this basis, I am trying to argue that perhaps this recommendation could be accepted.</P>
        <P>The second is that if the recommendation is not accepted, should partnerships break down and partners separate prior to the time that must pass for the partnership to be dissolved or annulled but because of financial circumstances they are required to live together, they will not <Col N="635"/>be enabled to have the same favourable tax treatment as married couples as the law stands.  It is sad to state this because we are only beginning to witness a number of couples registering civil partnerships.  If the recommendation is not accepted it is important to note that in this instance there will not be the same treatment for civil partners as for married couples.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P Just="Left">Question, &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand,&rdquo; put and declared carried.</P>
        <P>Recommendation declared lost.</P>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P>I move recommendation No. 2:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 16, to delete lines 16 to 20 and substitute the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo; &lsquo;maintenance arrangement&rsquo; means an order of a court under Part 5 or 12 of the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010, a rule of court, deed of separation, trust, covenant, agreement, arrangement or any other act giving rise to a legally enforceable obligation and made or done so in consideration or in consequence of (<i>a</i>) the dissolution or annulment of a civil partnership, or (<i>b</i>) such separation of the parties to a civil partnership as is referred to in section 1013A(2), and a maintenance arrangement relates to the civil partnership in consideration or in consequence of the dissolution or annulment of which, or of the separation of the parties to which, the maintenance arrangement was made or arises;&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I thank the Minister for his patience.  This is my first experience of proposing recommendations and I am learning as I go.  I also appreciate the context.</P>
        <P>The intention of the recommendation is to extend the definition of maintenance arrangements for civil partners covered by the Bill.  In the proposed section 1013 J to be inserted in the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 which is contained in the Bill as it stands, &ldquo;maintenance arrangement&rdquo; means an order of the court giving rise to a legally enforceable obligation.  The maintenance arrangement refers only to that which is contained in an order of the court.  The proposed recommendation extends the definition to include a maintenance arrangement that comes about by a deed of separation or a separation agreement between civil partners.  I am putting forward a similar argument that the definition needs be extended to include a deed of separation to ensure equal treatment between civil partners and a married couple.  As I pointed out on Second Stage, maintenance payments for a spouse in marriage attract tax relief at the time of a deed of separation or a judicial separation.  In the case of civil partners, tax relief is not a possibility on maintenance payments until a statutory dissolution or an annulment.  This takes considerably longer than the time it takes for a deed or an agreement of separation.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There is in the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights of Cohabitants Act 2010 an implicit recognition that civil partners can be separate.  I acknowledge the Minister&rsquo;s comments in this regard but I still believe, on the basis of advice I have received, that this may be the case and, therefore, it would seem there is no impediment within the Act to extend the definition of a &ldquo;maintenance arrangement&rdquo; to include that which arises by deed of separation and that these arrangements are legally enforceable.</P>
        <P>An agreement providing for separation of married couples is typically enforceable.  There is no reason to believe that a court would fail to enforce such an agreement between civil partners.  In particular, there is no obvious public policy ground for the non-enforcement of such an agreement.  Section 47 of the civil partnership Act allows the maintenance provision of such a separation agreement to be adopted as a rule of court.  This allows the provisions of that agreement relating to maintenance to be enforced as if they were orders made by the court itself.</P><Col N="636"/>
        <P>I ask the Minister to consider this recommendation in order that civil partners may avail of tax relief on maintenance payments for a civil partner at the time of separation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CaitKeane"><NameTxt>Senator C&aacute;it Keane</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Minister provide further clarification?  The Bill, as drafted, could be flawed in that it does not define &ldquo;living separately&rdquo; and &ldquo;separated&rdquo;.  If a provision for a separation or civil partnership can be made, surely there must be facility if a case ever went to the courts to grant a separation for a civil partnership.  Would it be possible to amend this legislation without affecting the civil partnership Act, given this deals with the financial aspect?  It is how the citizens are treated that matters in the context of equality rather than the terminology and definitions of &ldquo;living separately&rdquo; and &ldquo;separated&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I refer to the Minister&rsquo;s response to the previous recommendation and his point, clearly correct in law, that the status of separation does not exist for civil partners.  Senator Zappone is correct to point out that this means there is no parity between civil partners and spouses.  However, is judicial separation a desirable process?  That we have such a developed law on judicial separation is a consequence of the fact that we did not have divorce in this country for so long and separation was seen as filling a gap that would have been unnecessary had divorce been introduced earlier than 1995 following a referendum.  Like Senator Zappone, I feel we should give effect to same sex marriage and the civil partnership Act did not go far enough.  I rehearsed the argument when we debated the legislation in the House and, while I welcomed it, it does not provide for full equality.</P>
        <P>I wonder whether separation is an equality principle that is desirable to seek, given married couples can still seek judicial separation.  Is it necessary for us to provide this for civil partners?  I acknowledge what Senator Zappone is trying to do with these recommendations.  I am not sure it would be a positive gain in practice for civil partners to have a mechanism inserted into the civil partnership Act that would allow for separation for civil partners along the same lines as that available for married couples.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senators for their contributions and, in particular, Senator Zappone for her cogent arguments.  She is on better ground with this recommendation than on the previous one.  She may have identified a measure in tax law available to married couples but which has not been extended to persons in civil partnerships.</P>
        <P>This recommendation seeks to extend the definition of maintenance agreements for tax purposes beyond those made by court order or on the dissolution of a civil partnership.  More specifically, the recommendation seeks to have maintenance agreements made as part of a legally binding contract between two civil partners recognised for tax purposes.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I see what Senator Zappone is trying to achieve with this recommendation.  There will be a period between the breakdown of a relationship and the legal dissolution of a civil partnership.  Solutions often need to be put in place during that time to protect both partners.  Civil partners can offer a maintenance order from the courts during the period before dissolution.  This option is perfectly suitable in most cases.</P>
        <P>However, in marriages, there is also the option of a deed of separation.  Both sides can sign up to it and the maintenance agreements which may form this deed are recognised in tax law.  Senator Zappone has identified the disparity of treatment in that civil partners have the option to enter into a similar agreement but the maintenance payments are not recognised in tax law unless the agreement is made a rule of court.</P>
        <P>This Bill is complex and crosses several areas of existing law.  For this reason, I am reluctant to rush to amend the legislation without further assessing all possible consequences.  It is for <Col N="637"/>that reason I cannot accept the recommendation today.  I will instruct my officials, however, to engage with the Revenue Commissioners, the Office of the Attorney General and the Department of Justice and Equality to examine the issues identified by the Senator.  If they find this is an issue which can only be rectified by amending legislation, I will consider it in the next finance Bill</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate the Minister&rsquo;s response.  At a personal level,  for those who have to go through the angst and grave disappointment of a relationship breakdown, it must be difficult to know their arrangements are not recognised in the same way as those in marriage are.  I accept Senator Bacik&rsquo;s point it may be necessary to examine the legislation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>The Minister has identified Senator Zappone&rsquo;s issue.  Equality is not always happiness; sometimes there can be unhappiness.  I was shocked by Senator Bacik&rsquo;s remarks that we should not provide for separation because it would not be a good story on equality.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I was referring to judicial separation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>This recommendation refers to deeds of separation trusts, etc. as well.  If the Department has recognised Senator Zappone has raised a legitimate issue and she has provided the wording to an amendment, then it is the job of the Seanad to amend the legislation accordingly.  If this amendment will provide equality to civil partners in this area, why can it not be accepted now?  It has been made in good faith and has been identified by the Department as necessary.  We must now wait until the next finance Bill.  Senator Zappone may not be aware that the Bill gives effect to the budget and will not be introduced until February or March 2012.  If that is the case, we have to wait that long for equality.  I urge the Minister to accept the recommendation and, failing that, I urge Senator Zappone to press it. </P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I pay tribute to Senator Zappone.  It is welcome that the Minister has accepted that the recommendation raises an issue which needs to be addressed.  I apologise for going off on a tangent about the judicial separation regime, which is a different issue, albeit one which I always considered to be a feature of the absence of divorce in this country.  It is important that we ensure individuals are covered in the period where there has not, as yet, been a formal dissolution of the civil partnership under the 2010 Act.  This important principle is at issue in the recommendation proposed by Senator Zappone.  It would be useful if the recommendation were adopted or at least reviewed with a view to adoption before December.  I await the Minister&rsquo;s comments on the matter.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CaitKeane"><NameTxt>Senator C&aacute;it Keane</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for his response given that he is in theory accepting Senator Zappone&rsquo;s argument.  I share other Senators&rsquo; view that the devil can be in the detail of legislation.  I would like to have the recommendations of the Attorney General, Department of Finance, Taxing Master and others before making a final decision on the matter.  As I stated previously, the tax element should be separated and the Minister&rsquo;s decision is a wise one.  I do not want to return to the civil partnership Act.  How soon will the next finance Bill be introduced?  Will it be in December?  When one considers for how many years equality has been denied, December is not too far down the road.  While I would welcome a decision to act more speedily in the matter, the Minister is taking a sensible route.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FiachMacConghail"><NameTxt>Senator Fiach Mac Conghail</NameTxt>
	<P>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire go dt&iacute; an Teach agus t&aacute; s&uacute;il agam go n-&eacute;ireoidh leis ina chuid oibre.  I seek clarification regarding the timescale.  The Minister indicated he would seek the advice of his Department, the Office of the Attorney General and the Department of Justice and Equality.  Will this take two months, six months or longer?  Is it <Col N="638"/>possible the advice may not be available before the next finance Bill is introduced?  Senators need clarification before we can consider the Minister&rsquo;s response to the recommendation.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>My position is that Senator Zappone has made a cogent argument and identified an issue which requires examination.  I am not 100% sure whether she is absolutely correct in law but it appears that if married couples can go to their solicitor and obtain a non-judicial separation by agreement and receive certain tax benefits from such an arrangement, the same should apply to persons who are separated and have been in a legal civil partnership.  Two issues run from this.  There is the principal issue of parity, which is the one I would like to deal with and should be dealt with as soon as we can properly do so, having received the best of advice, and the issue of whether any practical implication arises from this for any separated couple who were in a civil partnership.  As yet, this does not appear to be the case although such practical implications may arise in future.</P>
        <P>In terms of dealing with the particular problem of individuals we do not have to proceed in haste because we are not correcting anything in the lives of citizens.  However, in terms of parity we obviously want everything that was in the primary legislation to be reflected in the consequential tax legislation.  There is considerable merit in the arguments made by Senator Zappone and while I am not 100% sure whether she is fully correct, the matter requires further examination by the Office of the Attorney General.  If her office concludes that Senator Zappone has identified a provision that makes persons in civil partnerships who separate different in tax law from married couples, I will move to amend the provision in the finance Bill.  The finance Bill is a natural consequence of the budget.  It will be published next February and will be enacted in the following five or six weeks.  If there were a practical example of people suffering consequences as a result of this measure we could think of moving sooner, but I am not 100% certain whether the arguments are fully correct.  It seems that they are.  There is certainly sufficient merit in the Senator&rsquo;s argument for me to instruct the Attorney General to examine it and to reference it to the other relevant Departments.  I will proceed on that basis if that is acceptable.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>Is Senator Zappone pressing the recommendation?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P>I appreciate the comments made by Senators Byrne, Keane and Mac Conghail.  The Minister&rsquo;s response is sufficient, especially in terms of clarifying the matter from Senator Mac Conghail&rsquo;s perspective.  In practice, there are not civil partners currently that this will affect because they are just registering their partnerships and we do not have any such partnerships that are breaking down.  I appreciate the Minister&rsquo;s willingness to instruct the Attorney General.  We will wait in hope for a positive resolution in that regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Recommendation, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Recommendations Nos. 3 to 5, inclusive, are grouped together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P>I move recommendation No. 3:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 16, between lines 22 and 23, to insert the following:</P>
        <P LI="2">&ldquo;a reference to a child of a person includes a child in respect of whom the person was at any time before the making of the maintenance arrangement concerned entitled to relief under section 465(1).&rdquo;.</P><Col N="639"/>
        <P FLI="0">That is a great idea.  There are a lot of words and I have received support and advice in putting the recommendations to the Minister.  Effectively, the intention behind all three recommendations is to include reference to the children of civil partners with respect to maintenance arrangements for taxation purposes.  That is as simply as I can put it.  There is no reference to children in the Bill when maintenance arrangements are being defined for taxation purposes.</P>
        <P>Recommendation No. 3 is a technical provision which attempts to mirror an equivalent provision for married couples.  It provides for certain dependent children to be taken into account where a tax credit is claimed in that regard under section 465 but where they may not be the person&rsquo;s child.  For example, they may be acting as a guardian of the child.  Effectively, if they were entitled to tax relief for the child prior to the maintenance arrangements for the child then they are still entitled to the relief after maintenance arrangements.  That is what the amendment seeks to do.</P>
        <P>Recommendations Nos. 4 and 5 again seek to include express reference to payments made in respect of children within the context of maintenance arrangements, and that these give rise to legally enforceable obligations.  In recommendation No. 4 specifically the words we propose include reference to payments made to children.  The intention of the recommendation is simply to mirror equivalence between how maintenance payments for children of married couples and children of civil partners are treated for taxation purposes.  The intention is to mirror the language in the tax code.</P>
        <P Just="Left">On Committee Stage I noted that the civil partnership Act does not place an obligation on civil partners to maintain the child or children of their civil partner in the case of a breakdown.  Theoretically, that means that a civil partnership may be dissolved in circumstances where a child of either party may be financially disadvantaged as a result.  The absence of recognition of rights and responsibilities for children of civil partners was noted as a prime lacuna of the civil partnership Act by Senator Bacik in her comments on Committee Stage and also the historical debates on the civil partnership Bill itself.  I just bring that to the fore again.  However, after the breakdown of a civil partnership happens and if there are maintenance arrangements for children that become part of a voluntary commitment on separation or could become part of a legally binding agreement made in court then should that not be enforceable within taxation law?  The recommendation seeks to provide for the same taxation treatment for maintenance arrangements for children of civil partners as applies to children of married couples.</P>
        <P>Recommendation No. 5 proposes the insertion of a new section in order to mirror the tax treatment of payments for the maintenance of children of civil partners to that of children of married couples.  Maintenance payments to children of married couples are disregarded for tax purposes.  The intention of the recommendation is to include a provision in taxation legislation that maintenance payments to children of civil partners are also disregarded for taxation purposes.  The recommendation is lengthy, mirroring the length of the provisions within the income tax code legislation on this issue.  Whatever the rationale was behind those provisions, I am simply proposing that the same rationale be applied in respect of the children of civilpartners.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>I am grateful to Senator Katherine Zappone for raising this issue.  The absence of protections for children in the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010 was raised by me, Senator Norris and others in this and the other House during the debate on that legislation.  The Ombudsman for Children published a robust critique of the absence of protection for children in the civil partnership code.  There were only two references to children in the Act.</P>
        <P>The recommendations put forward by Senator Zappone address a gap in protection for children and highlight that the provisions in the civil partnership code do not go far enough. <Col N="640"/> Section 73 of the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010 provides for certain succession rights of children of a civil partner, while section 129 allows a court to have regard, on the dissolution of a partnership, to a child to whom either civil partner owes an obligation of support.  However, there is nothing in the legislation to address the gap identified by Senator Zappone in terms of the lack of parity in the treatment of maintenance payments to children of married couples following divorce as against the children of civil partnerships following dissolution.</P>
        <P>I urge the Minister to consider how this gap can be addressed.  I said on Second Stage in the debate on this Bill that further legislation is necessary in any case to deal more broadly with the rights and responsibilities of civil partners <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i> the children of their families.  This was an issue identified by many people during the debate on the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010.  There are broader issues to address apart from the issue raised in Senator Zappone&rsquo;s recommendations.  It will require further legislation to equate the position of children of civil partners with those of married couples.  Senator Zappone would accept that her recommendations will not achieve parity between children of gay couples and children of married couples.  However, the recommendations do address a particular disparity in treatment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not accept there is a disparity between the treatment of children of civil partners and the children of married couples.  Under law, people are obliged to look after their children, which includes providing financial support for them, regardless of whether the marriage is intact or has ended.  That is why there is no tax incentive to pay maintenance to one&rsquo;s partner in respect of the maintenance of one&rsquo;s children.  Maintenance payments are paid from after-tax income, which is the crucial difference.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Recommendations Nos. 3 to 5, inclusive, relate to the taxation treatment of maintenance payments to children of a civil partnership.  The Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010 did not provide for court-ordered maintenance payments from an individual in respect of the child of his or her former civil partner.  As this type of arrangement does not apply in the general law, it is not provided for in this tax law.  Furthermore, there is no tax relief for maintenance payments in respect of children in general.  Individuals are expected to support their children from their after-tax income. </P>
      
        
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">5 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
<P>Recommendation No. 3 appears to seek to define a child in the case of maintenance payments in civil partnerships as also a child defined under section 465 of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997, which deals with the incapacitated child tax credits.  Section 465 of that Act relies on the definition of a claimant for an incapacitated child tax credit as one who has the custody of, and maintains, the child at his or her own expense.  There is no mention in this section of marriage or spouse or any other term that would need to be amended to give equal treatment to civil partners.  That is the reason this section of the Taxes Consolidation Act is not amended in this Bill.  An individual has an entitlement to a tax credit in respect of an incapacitated child and this credit will continue to be available after that party has entered a civil partnership provided the adult continues to satisfy the qualifying criteria.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In the context of maintenance payments for children, payments made for the benefit of a child do not qualify for tax relief.  However, a payment made for the support of an incapacitated child may give the payer an entitlement to all or part of the incapacitated child tax credit.  This is a similar treatment for married couples and civil partners.  As I do not see a disparity of treatment here, I cannot accept that recommendation.</P><Col N="641"/>
        <P Just="Left">Recommendation No. 4 appears to indicate that there could be maintenance orders ordered to be paid by one civil partner for the benefit of his or her civil partner&rsquo;s child.  As I said previously, the civil partnership Act does not provide for this and this Bill does not, and cannot, change the rights of children in order that they have a right to be maintained by their parent&rsquo;s civil partner or former civil partner.  These are family law issues which go beyond the scope of tax legislation.  As this recommendation goes beyond the scope of the Bill and crosses into the area of family law, which is a matter for the Minister for Justice and Equality in the first instance, I cannot accept it.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Recommendation No. 5 replicates section 1025(4) of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997.  The purpose of that section is to confirm that there is no tax relief available for maintenance payments for children.  I understand from Senator Zappone&rsquo;s comments on Second Stage that her intention is for tax relief to be available for maintenance payments for children of civil partners.  As this recommendation does not achieve this, I cannot accept it.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Overall, the Finance (No. 3) Bill was drafted to provide for tax changes that are necessary as a consequence of the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Act 2010.  The tax law can only follow the general law in this matter, a point the Senator understands quite well because she referred to remarks made by the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, to this effect.  I am not willing to jeopardise this Bill by making changes which provide entitlements, rights or obligations above and beyond those afforded in the civil partnership legislation or the Constitution.  I am committed to this legislation and I do not wish to place it at risk of challenge in any way.  Consequently, I am not in a position to accept the recommendations.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P>I respect the reasons the Minister put forward.  I also accept that there ought not to be tax relief and that parents ought to look after their children.  With regard to the Minister&rsquo;s response, let it go forth from this Chamber that there is no express reference to children in this Bill in the context of maintenance arrangements.  That is effectively what the Minister said.  I understand the reasons for that, and I am sorry for those reasons.  That is what the Minister said, that there is no reference to children in this Bill in terms of maintenance orders.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">It is clear that the flaw lies with the original Bill and the absence of a reference to children there.  This is a tax measure and I accept the Minister&rsquo;s point that perhaps the changes proposed to provide for parity between children of civil partners and children of married couples go beyond the scope of a tax Bill.  That is in line with the general principle, but it is disappointing that provision cannot be made to a greater extent for children of civil partners.  As I said, we need general, standalone legislation, not tax legislation, presumably from the Department of Justice and Equality, to provide for parity of treatment for children of civil partners generally.  That is the legislation for which we should strive, and we will do that as best we can.  That is probably the answer to this.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CaitKeane"><NameTxt>Senator C&aacute;it Keane</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I listened to Senator Zappone but it is not today that it went forth from this Chamber that children of civil partners were treated differently, but the day the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Bill was passed.  As we are dealing with a finance Bill today, the Minister&rsquo;s hands are tied.  Rather than this Minister putting out a new message, it is an old message that Senator Zappone is enunciating today.  It was a flaw in the previous Bill.  The recommendation refers to a civil partner pursuant to a maintenance arrangement.  It is a good recommendation but, as the Minister has outlined, it is not possible to amend the Finance Act because of the civil partnership legislation.  The avenue <Col N="642"/>that should be examined is the amendment of the civil partnership legislation.  Perhaps that could be considered before the finance Bill next February.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Let it go forth from this Chamber that the purpose of this legislation is to provide equality of treatment under the law for persons who are in civil partnership and their children.  There is no tax relief for the payment of maintenance for children when marriages break down.  There is tax relief in respect of incapacitated children, and that tax relief is being applied equally to the children of civil partners and the children of married couples.  There is no tax relief for other maintenance payments in either circumstance.  I do not see where there is inequality.  I accept there are several other issues but it is not fair, in declaratory statements, to import the other issues into tax legislation which everybody knows must be confined by the primary legislation.  What I am pledged to do is to mirror every rule across the tax code which applies to married couples in the treatment of persons who have entered into civil partnership and to their children.  I do not see where there is discrimination against children in this.  If there is, I would be grateful if it was pointed out to me.</P>
        <P>There is no provision in tax law for receiving a tax break for maintenance payments for children.  There is a provision for a tax break for incapacitated children, but we are legislating to apply that to a child in a civil partnership in the same way as it applies to a child in a marriage.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KatherineZappone"><NameTxt>Senator Katherine Zappone</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I appreciate what the Minister is saying.  He is right &mdash; it is a question of fairness, and that is where my arguments originate.  Second, I understand the points made by the Minister.  There is no taxation implication and there is no tax relief.  If there is not and it is not that big a deal, why can we not include it in a Bill when there is not that implication in terms of public expenditure?  Even if there were, I would argue that it ought to be there.  However, as I respect the Minister&rsquo;s points, I will withdraw the recommendations.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Recommendation, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
        <P>Recommendations Nos. 4 and 5 not moved.</P>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 1 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>This section deals with the taxation treatment of civil partnerships, in particular, Chapter 1, Part 44A, which deals with income tax.  I invite the Minister to repeat the Government&rsquo;s commitment not to raise income tax rates in the budget, in particular for civil partnerships.  However, I presume that will apply to everybody in terms of equality of treatment.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator is lowering the debate by introducing a party political issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>I am making a very important point about tax rates and certainty surrounding them, which is of concern to many thousands of people.  I ask the Minister to give that certainty again.  It relates to this section on income tax.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P>It is not an appropriate occasion.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">The Minister has refused to do so.  This party contributed very constructively to this debate and I agreed with, and spoke to, a number the amendments Senator Zappone tabled.  The Minister has refused to restate the Government&rsquo;s commitment not to increase income tax rates.  We are dealing with a section on income tax.  I have asked the <Col N="643"/>Minister to repeat that commitment but he has refused to do so and one can only draw conclusions from that.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="IvanaBacik"><NameTxt>Senator Ivana Bacik</NameTxt>
	<P>The Senator should confine himself to the section at issue.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="ThomasByrne"><NameTxt>Senator Thomas Byrne</NameTxt>
	<P>The seventh word in the section is &ldquo;income&rdquo; and the eighth word is &ldquo;tax&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="CaitKeane"><NameTxt>Senator C&aacute;it Keane</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">On a point of order, we are dealing with a Bill on civil partnerships, not the broad issue of tax.  I would welcome a debate on the broad issue of tax on another day but not today because that is not on the agenda.  This Bill concerns civil partnerships and how the children of civil partners are treated.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MichaelNoonan"><NameTxt>Deputy Michael Noonan</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">We are debating something that is quite sensitive for many people and it should not be used as a vehicle for a party political point.  However, since Senator Byrne raised it and since he will dig his heels in, I will say that the Taoiseach has spoken for the Government.  The Senator can refer to his statement and what he said about income tax.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
        <P>Sections 2 to 5, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
        <P>Schedules 1 to 4 inclusive, agreed to.</P>
        <P>Title agreed to.</P>
        <P>Bill reported without recommendation, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Residential Institutions" RHead="Redress (Amendment) Bill 2011: Second Stage"> 
    <Title>Residential Institutions Redress (Amendment) Bill 2011: Second Stage</Title>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn"><TitleTxt>Minister for Education and Skills</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>This Bill removes the power of the Residential Institutions Redress Board to consider applications made on or after 17 September 2011.  It also requires the board to advertise this fact at least six weeks before the effective date in <i>Iris Oifigi&uacute;il</i>, two Irish daily newspapers and two UK daily newspapers.</P>
        <P>The redress board was established under the Residential Institutions Redress Act 2002 to make financial awards to assist in the recovery of certain persons who as children were abused while resident in certain institutions in the State and who have or have had injuries that are consistent with that abuse.  The original closing date for the receipt of applications was 15 December 2005, that is, three years after the establishment of the board.  However, subsection 8(2) of the 2002 Act allows the board to extend the period for receipt of an application in exceptional circumstances, while subsection 8(3) requires the board to extend the period when it is satisfied that an applicant was under a legal disability.</P>
        <P>It is now over eight and half years since the board was established and five and half years after the initial closing date.  The 2002 Act provides that when the Minister is satisfied, after consultation with the chairman of the redress board, that the board has completed the performance of its functions, he can make an order to dissolve the board, following a positive motion by each House of the Oireachtas.  It is necessary to amend the 2002 legislation to provide for a final date for the receipt of late applications, to facilitate the winding-up of the redress board.</P>
        <P>The work of the redress board is a cornerstone of the response to the appalling and shocking reality of abuse suffered by so many of our citizens who as children were resident in the scheduled residential institutions.  The establishment of the board afforded the abuse victims an opportunity <Col N="644"/>to receive fair and reasonable financial compensation for the abuses they suffered as children, without recourse to the courts system.  Making awards on an <i>ex gratia</i> basis, involving no finding of fault or declaration of liability, the redress board requires a much lower burden of proof than would have been required in court.  The arrangements put in place reflected the moral and societal duty to pay compensation to those injured.  The procedures adopted by the board reflect its duty to ensure that hearings are conducted as informally as is possible having regard to all the circumstances.</P>
        <P Just="Left">To qualify for an award, an applicant must prove his or her identity and establish to the board&rsquo;s satisfaction that he or she was resident in a scheduled institution while under 18 and that he or she was injured while so resident and the injury is consistent with any abuse that is alleged to have occurred while so resident.  The redress board commenced making awards in May 2003 and has processed over 14,600 cases, resulting in over 13,700 awards to date.  Awards are made by the board in accordance with the framework set out in Towards Redress and Recovery, the report of the independent compensation advisory committee which advised on the appropriate levels of compensation.  Awards are determined by the board having regard to the severity of the abuse and the severity of physical and psychological injury and loss of opportunity resulting from the abuse.  The resultant weightings produce an overall assessment which the board reviews to ensure that it is reasonable in all the circumstances for the particular applicant. The amount of redress payable is then determined according to the redress bands.</P>
        <P>The redress board is chaired by Mr. Justice Esmond Smyth and its other ten members are drawn from the legal and medical professions.  The board is wholly independent in the performance of its functions.  Independent legal advice is available to applicants and the vast majority chose to avail of this.  It is open to each applicant to accept or reject an award made by the board and the review committee provides an appeal mechanism by which an applicant can seek to have his-her award reviewed. The review committee, which is chaired by the Honourable Mr. Justice Frank Murphy, can uphold, increase or decrease the amount of the award.</P>
        <P>Of the 13,720 awards made to date, 78% were made following settlements with a further 19% made following hearings.  The remaining 3% were made following reviews by the residential institutions review committee under the independent appeals mechanism, to which I have just referred.  Applicants may reject awards.  To date 13 people out of over 13,700 have rejected their awards.  Where an applicant does not accept an award, they retain the option to pursue any legal avenue which may be open to them.</P>
        <P>The Government is satisfied that every reasonable effort has been made to advise potential applicants of their right to redress and that it is now time to move towards winding up the board.  By the end of June 2011, the board had received a total of 15,173 applications and had finalised 14,645 cases.  Of these, 13,720 have resulted in awards being made by the board, with the remaining 925 either being refused, withdrawn or resulting in no award.  In terms of the late applications, that is, those received after 15 December 2005, a total of 1,540 have been received by the board at the end of June 2011.  Of these 725 have been allowed and the board has a further 559 to adjudicate on. In all, between original and late applications, the board has just over 1,000 applications to finalise.  By stipulating a final cut-off for receipt of late applications of 16 September 2011, it will be possible to finalise the workload remaining for the board and to plan its orderly wind-down.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The redress board has fulfilled its functions.  It has operated independently and with certainty for applicants. In keeping with its statutory duty, the board undertook an extensive advertising campaign up to the end of 2005.  It utilised press advertising as well as television and radio advertising and held information days and distributed leaflets and pamphlets to the network of Irish societies in the UK.  In total, the board placed 1,492 advertisements since it was established.</P><Col N="645"/>
        <P>This Bill requires the board to undertake further press advertising to advise the public of the closing date for receipt of late applications.  In tandem with this, the survivor group network, the Irish societies and the embassies are being asked to alert any relevant contacts known to them.  The publication of the Ryan report in 2009 and the Murphy commission reports, most recently on the Cloyne Diocese, have also ensured that the redress board retains a high public profile.</P>
        <P>The overall cost of the redress scheme had been estimated to reach &euro;l.l billion and actual expenditure on the scheme and associated litigation reached &euro;1.05 billion at the end of 2010.  This figure includes some &euro;836 million in awards made by the board and &euro;158 million in associated medical and legal costs.  The average value of the awards made is some &euro;63,000.  As the end of 2010, some 36% of awards made attracted awards of up to &euro;50,000, 49% attracted awards of between &euro;50,000 and &euro;100,000, 13% attracted awards of between &euro;100,000 and &euro;150,000  while the remaining 2% of awards attracted awards of between &euro;150,000 and &euro;300,000.</P>
        <P>The response to residential institutional abuse also involved the establishment of the Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse which was tasked with investigating the causes, nature and extent of the abuse.  The publication of the Ryan report in 2009, as I said at the time, &ldquo;shocked a nation that thought it had got beyond being shocked&rdquo;. The litany and scale of the abuse recounted by anguished voices caused us all, as a people, to be ashamed and to apologise to those whose childhoods were stolen and who in many instances, could not live full lives as adults.</P>
        <P>The commission&rsquo;s conclusions were unequivocal and damning, detailing the failures of those who managed the institutions and the failure of the State to protect its vulnerable children. Its report justified the decision to establish the Residential Institutions Redress Board to compensate survivors outside of the court system. The report&rsquo;s findings are an indictment on us all and it is our duty to ensure that the lessons of the past are learned and that such abuse is never repeated.</P>
        <P>There is a need for all involved to accept their role and responsibility.  It is in this context that the Government has called on the congregations to meet the costs of the response to residential institutional abuse on an equal basis with the taxpayer.  This is a fair and reasonable approach.  The final cost of the response is estimated to be approximately &euro;1.36 billion.  However, the offers from the 18 congregations to date have fallen far short of the approximately &euro;680 million needed to meet half of these costs.   The Government believes that the transfer of school property currently owned by the congregations offers an opportunity to reach this target.  I have invited the congregations to meet me later this week to discuss these matters.  The management bodies of other institutions included within the redress scheme have also been approached to make a contribution towards the costs involved.  Their potential to similarly transfer school infrastructure will be explored.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Government is continuing to address the needs of survivors of institutional abuse.  Increased funding has been provided for the Health Service Executive for the national counselling service set up to help victims cope with their experiences.  My Department is continuing to fund the Origins family tracing service, operated by Barnardos, which assists former residents wishing to trace their families of origin.</P>
        <P>I recently announced that the Government is proceeding with legislation to provide for the establishment of the residential institutions statutory fund to support the needs of survivors of residential institutional abuse.  Such a fund was unanimously endorsed by this House in the period following the publication of the Ryan report.  The fund will utilise &euro;110 million of the contributions &mdash; essentially the cash element &mdash; offered by the congregations and will target support at survivors&rsquo; needs, such as counselling services, psychological support services and mental health services, and such health and personal social services, educational services and housing services as the fund may determine.  The fund will also promote understanding of the effects of abuse on former residents among service providers and will evaluate the effectiveness of the approved services in meeting the <Col N="646"/>needs of former residents. To date, &euro;21.05 million of the contributions pledged have been received and lodged in a special interest bearing account in the Central Bank pending the establishment of the statutory fund.  I hope to return to the House in the autumn in respect of the residential institutions fund Bill.</P>
        <P>I take this opportunity to acknowledge the work of all those involved in the operation of the Residential Institutions Redress Board and I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergalQuinn"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Feargal Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>Senator Power was due to speak next but she wishes to delay her contribution until later.  I will, therefore, call Senator Jim D&rsquo;Arcy to make his contribution now.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimDarcy"><NameTxt>Senator Jim D&rsquo;Arcy</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister and thank him for introducing this Bill.  As he stated, it facilitates the winding up of the Residential Institutions Redress Board.  It also removes the board&rsquo;s power to consider applications made on or after 17 September 2011.  I welcome the fact that Bill requires that the board must advertise this fact at least six weeks prior to 17 September next.  Since the original closing date of 15 December 2005, some 1,260 applications have been made.  This is out of an overall total of 15,173 applications with which the board has dealt.  Is the Minister convinced that all of the people entitled to submit applications for redress have done so?</P>
        <P Just="Left">On &ldquo;The Pat Kenny Show&rdquo; yesterday, a woman described the time she spent in a residential institution.  She referred to how residents were stripped of their personalities and indicated that the default position was for people to put what had happened out of their minds when they left the institution.  In such circumstances, could there be others who have suffered deep psychological traumas who have yet to come forward?  What right to redress, if any, will these individuals have after 17 September?  Could the residential institutions statutory fund Bill, which will be brought forward in the near future, be used to provide special advice and counselling for those to whom I refer if they came forward in the future?</P>
        <P Just="Left">By the end of June this year, the board had finalised 14,645 cases out of the overall total of 15,173.  It made some 13,720 awards and paid out &euro;836 million in respect of these.  The legal costs involved amounted to &euro;158 million.  Therefore, the grand total was &euro;1.05 billion.  Is it possible to indicate the percentage of former residents who were still alive in 1999 to which this figure relates?  Would that information be available from any source?</P>
        <P>The report by the compensation advisory committee, Towards Redress and Recovery &mdash; more commonly known as the Ryan report &mdash; states that no amount of money can truly compensate those who have been abused.  This is true.  The horrors suffered by children who were resident in industrial schools, reformatory schools, orphanages, children&rsquo;s homes and special schools can only be imagined.  Monetary compensation is but a small consolation in the context of lives that were seriously damaged or, in some cases, utterly destroyed.  Mr. Justice Esmond Smyth and the Residential Institutions Redress Board must be thanked for the compassionate and understanding way in which they have gone about their business.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Ryan report also states that the making of financial redress to individual survivors is only one of the measures necessary.  In this context, I welcome the fact that the proposed residential institutions statutory fund Bill will soon be brought forward.  This legislation will provide continued support for the victims of residential institutional child abuse.  Such support will include counselling services and psychological support.  When will be Bill be introduced?  I welcome the fact that the religious congregations are to contribute &euro;110 million to the fund.  The final cost relating to this matter is currently estimated at &euro;1.36 billion.  The Minister indicated that even in light of discussions on a 50:50 sharing of the costs involved, there will still be a shortfall of &euro;200 million on the part of the congregations.  If ever there was a time for a gesture to be made, this is it.  I appeal to the <Col N="647"/>congregations to discuss with the Minister, in a spirit of change and renewal and in an open and positive way, how matters might be progressed.  There is a need for such change and renewal in this country.  The State also bears responsibility for what occurred.  If we deny that responsibility, then the abuse could happen again.</P>
        <P>It is continually stated that the majority of abuse occurs in the home.  There is a need, therefore, to welcome and support the Private Members&rsquo; motion relating to the social, personal and health education, SPHE, programme &mdash; incorporating relationships and sexuality education, RSE &mdash; in the senior cycle in post-primary schools.  This programme is mandatory in primary schools and in the junior cycle in post-primary schools.  I do not want to pre-empt the debate on the motion tabled by some of the Independent Members but I ask the Minister to take cognisance of what will be said in order that he might take the action that is required.  I congratulate the Minister on his efforts in this regard.  As the Ryan report states in its concluding remarks, this abuse must never happen again.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidNorris"><NameTxt>Senator David Norris</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister to the House.  I regard him as an old friend and colleague and somebody with a compassionate heart and interest in these matters.  I have had an amendment to the Bill disallowed on the grounds that it would cause a charge on the Exchequer.  It undoubtedly would do so, but this is something that should be encompassed in reform of the Seanad.  It is completely ridiculous that these types of serious amendments are routinely ruled out.  My amendment clearly infringes the rules, but there have been many others where that ruling is marginal.  The cost of printing an amendment was used on one occasion in this House to rule it out on the grounds of a charge on the Exchequer.  If we take this to extremes, we will get no business done in the House.  This bar should we be removed and we should at least be allowed to make recommendations.  We are allowed to do so in respect of certified money Bills &mdash; a rather Jesuitical arrangement &mdash; and I have had three pages included in the Finance Bill in the past.  What is the difference in allowing us to table recommendations for any legislation where the proposals involve a charge on the Exchequer?  We are also precluded from sitting on select committees.  I was a founder of the foreign affairs committee and the only Member who is there since its establishment, yet I cannot even attend, let alone speak, at meetings of the select committee.  This is a side issue, but I ask the Minister to consider it at Cabinet.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Minister has indicated that a notice regarding the closing date for applications to the redress board of 17 September 2011 will be published in <i>Iris Oifigi&uacute;il</i>.  While this is a necessity, I doubt very much that many survivors of abuse read that publication.  The Minister also indicated that notices would be published in two Irish daily newspapers and two British daily newspapers.  I welcome the inclusion of the latter given that many survivors are in exile, partly because of their savage treatment by institutions of both church and State in this jurisdiction.  Will the Minister indicate the two Irish daily newspapers in which it is proposed to publish the notice?  There are at least three broadsheet newspapers of record, namely, <i>The Irish Times</i>, the <i>Irish Independent</i> and the <i>Irish Examiner</i>.  The latter is a very fine newspaper which has published detailed investigative analysis in areas not far removed from this issue.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I accept that a broader scope of publication would involve an expense, and I cannot, therefore, table an amendment, but it is important that we reach as many people as possible.  On the day on which Rupert Murdoch received a custard pie &mdash; I hesitate to gloat about it or to make any remarks about the lower end of the media &mdash; we must acknowledge that, regrettably or not, many people read those publications.  It may well be that survivors of abuse, because they have had less opportunity for educational attainment, are more likely to read some of the more popular newspapers.  The Minister indicated that a total of 1,540 applications had been received by the board at the end of June 2011, while the number of advertisements published was 1,492.  In other words, there is approximately one application per advertisement.  This shows the significance of advertising as <Col N="648"/>widely as possible.  This may not be a realistic proposition, but I am interested in the Minister&rsquo;s thinking on the matter.</P>
        <P Just="Left">While I usually seek not to personalise issues, I take the opportunity to acknowledge that I know the person appointed chairman of the redress board since university debating days.  I have also had experience of his wisdom in the Irish courts.  He is an eminent and most suitable person.  The ten members are not named but are drawn from various sectors of society.  However, I notice there is no provision to appoint a representative of survivors.  I understand this might be difficult given that survivors are not all in the same camp, having different interests and being members of different groups.  I accept that such a move might be impractical and lead to dissension among the various groups.  However, I ask the Minister to comment on this omission.  I hope to be here for his response, although I have other business of a different political nature to attend to.  As I expect the Bill to go through quite quickly, I may well be in the Chamber until the end of the debate.  I do not intend the slightest discourtesy to the Minister if I am obliged to leave and, in that case, I will read his comments.</P>
        <P>The explanatory memorandum to this short Bill is not very interesting, simply setting out the contents therein, which we know from reading the Bill.  It is something of a waste of paper, but at least no Senator can be held responsible for that charge on the Exchequer.  I would have liked the explanatory memorandum to give a reason for the introduction of the legislation, that is, to set out that this is being done because of X, Y and Z.  I do not wish to criticise the Minister&rsquo;s advisers and officials, but it is my experience that an explanatory memorandum will usually include an explanation of why a particular Bill is being introduced, rather than merely setting out its contents.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I take the opportunity on Second Stage to raise a matter which I will be precluded from raising by way of amendment.  I am confident there is no bar on my raising it because it is a matter of general principle and suitable for Second Stage discussion.  I assure the Minister that I am not making any subversive attempt to push the amendment into the discussion.  The issue I raise is the exclusion of the Bethany Home from the provisions of the legislation.  It is remarkable that the advice of the Department of Health and the urgent plea of the Church of Ireland, in the person of the Archbishop of Dublin, Dr. John Neill, were apparently completely ignored by the previous Government.  That would not have happened had it been a Roman Catholic prelate making a similar plea.  The situation of the Bethany Home in Rathgar, which operated between 1921 and 1972, is exactly analogous to that of the Magdalene laundries.  I attended a service some time ago at the burial place of 200 children in unmarked graves.  The naming of those children was marked with a ceremony.</P>
        <P>In 1939, the State&rsquo;s inspectors reported serious cases of medical neglect at the Bethany Home.  The State deflected that concern and publicly instructed Roman Catholic children not to be admitted.  This was a sectarian response and people are now being penalised simply for being Protestant victims.  It is quite astonishing.  An eminent appointment to this House, Senator Martin McAleese, has been charged with examining the State&rsquo;s relationship with the Roman Catholic Magdalene laundries and other institutions of that type.  Is it not possible for Senator McAleese to be permitted to extend the remit of his investigation to take into account the interactions between the State and the Bethany Home?  The survivors are entitled to justice.  They should not be neglected simply because they are not of the Roman Catholic persuasion.  I take this opportunity to pay tribute to a gentleman called Mr. Derek Leinster in this regard.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JillianVanTurnhout"><NameTxt>Senator Jillian van Turnhout</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for his presentation.  I also thank Senator Jim D&rsquo;Arcy for his early support of our motion tomorrow evening.  This debate is extremely timely given that the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, is, as we speak, launching the second progress report on the recommendations arising from the Ryan report.</P><Col N="649"/>
        <P>In considering the legislation before us, I take the opportunity to acknowledge the substantial work carried out by the redress board since its inception in 2002.  However, behind all the facts and figures lies the suffering of thousands of children who were entitled to be cared for, cherished and loved at a time when they could not have been more vulnerable.  Instead, as we learned from the Ryan report, physical and emotional abuse and neglect were features of the institutions in which these children were detained.  Sexual abuse occurred in many, particularly boys&rsquo; institutions.  A climate of fear created by pervasive, excessive and arbitrary punishment permeated most of the institutions.  Children lived with the daily terror of not knowing where the next beating would come from.  Seeing or hearing other children being beaten was a frightening experience that stayed with many survivors for all of their lives.  Children who ran away were severely beaten, often publicly, and were often humiliated in public and had their heads shaven.  Prolonged, excessive beatings with implements intended to cause maximum pain occurred with the knowledge of staff and management.</P>
        <P>In a week where the Ombudsman for Children, Emily Logan, reminded us of her concern that a hierarchy of abuse was being drawn up by social workers today, with neglect often placed at the bottom, let us not forget what the Ryan report said about the neglect of children.  Children were frequently hungry and food was inadequate, inedible and badly prepared in many schools.  Survivors spoke of scavenging for food in waste bins and animal feed.  Inspectors found that malnourishment was a serious problem in schools run by the nuns in the late 1940s and, although improvements were made, food was meagre and basic.  Sanitary provision was primitive, hygiene facilities were poor and sanitary protection for girls in menstruation was generally inadequate.  Emotional abuse was suffered and the redress board heard cases of witnesses being belittled and ridiculed.  Humiliating practices of underwear inspections and displaying soiled or wet sheets were conducted throughout the industrial schools system.  Private matters such as bodily functions and personal hygiene were used as opportunities for degradation and humiliation.  There was constant criticism and verbal abuse and children were told they were worthless.</P>
        <P>It is important we remember this because when we consider the work of the redress board and review the legislation, we should be mindful of the experiences of so many young children that prompted the need for it in the first place.  It is unfortunate to learn from many of the organisations supporting survivors that, in some cases, their experience of the redress board caused additional distress.  Many were upset when told that they could not discuss their financial awards publicly.  They took this to mean they could not talk publicly about the redress and that there was blanket secrecy, which added to the whole feeling of secrecy and humiliation.  Once they accepted a settlement, they believed they could not speak about their childhood experiences, which reinforced the feeling of secrecy and the point about their reputation.  This hurt them badly.</P>
        <P>As Senator Norris said, it is regrettable that the Government has repeatedly refused to allow Bethany Home &mdash; a combined detention centre, children&rsquo;s home and maternity home in Dublin &mdash; to be included on the list of qualifying institutions for the residential institutions redress scheme.  This deprived survivors of the opportunity to present their cases to the redress board and seek some semblance of justice and compensation for abuse suffered as children there.  The passing of this legislation is a timely reminder that survivors of Bethany Home have not had justice and redress.  At this late stage, I urge the Government to find a way to address the needs of Bethany Home survivors, for an inquiry into the activities there and for the survivors to be allowed to access some form of reasonable redress.</P>
        <P>As this legislation is before the House at a time when there is public debate about the overall cost of redress and specifically by whom the cost should be met, I fully support the Minister in his efforts to ensure the taxpayer is not left to pay a disproportionate amount of the cost of redress.  There are clearly others who should pay their fair share, giving the role they played in causing so much harm to so many.</P>
      </Speaker><Col N="650"/>
      <Speaker pid="MaryMoran"><NameTxt>Senator Mary Moran</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister to the House and the opportunity to speak to the Residential Institutions Redress (Amendment) Bill, which facilitates the winding up of the Residential Institutions Redress Board.  The opportunity for claims under the residential redress scheme has been available since 2002.  The closing date for applications was originally December 2005.  However it made provision for late applications in exceptional circumstances.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, announced earlier this month that no further applications can be received after 16 September 2011.  I agree the deadline must be upheld in order to wind up the redress board in a fair and timely fashion.  I commend the redress board on its advertising campaign and on the notices that will be placed in daily newspapers six weeks before the deadline.</P>
        <P>At the end of June 2011, the board had received 15,173 applications, of which 14,645 had been finalised, leading to 13,720 awards.  This was a far greater number of claims than was originally anticipated by the previous Government.  By the end of 2010, the overall expenditure on the redress scheme and associated litigation was &euro;1.05 billion, including &euro;836 million in awards made by the board and &euro;158 million in associated medical and legal costs.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I express my disappointment at the level of contributions offered by the religious congregations to meet the costs of residential institutional child abuse.  Only 12 of the properties offered by the religious congregations have been identified as being of potential benefit to the State and only two of the 18 congregations have agreed to make up the shortfall of &euro;200 million.  While I understand the concerns of the proposers of this amendment, it is now impossible to include Bethany Home claims in this redress bill.  I appreciate the fact that they have raised the issue but I now hope and anticipate that the Government will take positive alternative steps to ensure a mechanism is put in place to acknowledge the suffering of the Bethany Home residents.</P>
        <P Just="Left">With all of the Labour Party Senators, I am very hopeful an alternative mechanism for recognition of the Bethany Home residents will be found.  I would like to pay a personal tribute to Derek Leinster, who has tirelessly worked on behalf of all Bethany Home survivors to bring their plight to public attention.  I would also like to pay tribute to the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, and Deputy Joe Costello who have campaigned endlessly of behalf of the Bethany Home residents since 2002.  I welcome the establishment of the review committee on the Magdalene laundries survivors chaired by Senator Martin McAleese to examine the role of the State in these laundries and to bring the religious orders and State together to provide a clear picture on their involvement in the Magdalene laundries.  I ask the Minister to consider the cases of the Bethany Home survivors in this review with the Magdalene survivors in order that the terrible scandals and dreadful legacy of abuse victims in our institutions may finally be resolved.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AverilPower"><NameTxt>Senator Averil Power</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for his opening remarks.  Fianna F&aacute;il acknowledges the need for a deadline to be set.  The board has been working for nearly nine years.  We welcome the fact that advertisements will be placed for six weeks prior to the closing date.  I wish to record thanks to the members of the board, particularly Mr. Justice Smyth, for the work carried out.  I thank the victims because, in coming forward and recounting the horrendous abuse they were subjected to as children, they have done us all a major service.  It cannot have been easy for them and we should all be grateful for the fact they were willing to do it.</P>
        <P>Child abuse in residential institutions and elsewhere in this country is a severe scar on our national consciousness.  For a long time, we refused to talk about it as a society.  I find it difficult to look at interviews with these people in documentaries.  I remember seeing one a few years ago where a girl talked about being abused in a day school.  She went home and told her parents but they did not believe her and brought her back to the same school the next morning.</P><Col N="651"/>
        <P>I find that incredible but I hope it would not happen in the current environment where we talk about these issues.  Society has moved on in that regard.  That is the reality of the lives many children led in this country and it is to the shame of all of us that it was allowed happen.</P>
        
      <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">6 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt><P>The Residential Institutions Redress Board stems from the apology of the then Taoiseach, former Deputy Bertie Ahern, in May 1999 when he stated on behalf of the State that the Government wished to make a sincere and long overdue apology to the victims of child abuse.  He stated that too many children had been denied the love, care and security to which they were entitled.  He also stated that abuse had ruined their childhood and had been an ever-present part of their adult lives.  He emphasised that the Government believed those people were gravely wronged by the State and stated that it was incumbent on the State to act now and do its best to compensate them.  As other Members have said, no amount of financial compensation can in any way make up for the torture those victims endured as children but it was a small token of recognition from the State.</P>
        <P Just="Left">It is wrong that the institutions did not commit to a 50:50 split from the outset but the Government was right to proceed and set up the redress board.  Many of the victims were elderly.  At the time the Government was considering setting up the board there were concerns that some of them might pass away by the time their cases had been heard.  The Government was right to set up the board while constantly seeking to get a fairer contribution from the institutions.</P>
        <P>The Minister will be aware that in April 2010 the then Government published a detailed breakdown of the financial assets of the congregations and a little over a year ago the then Taoiseach called on them to pay their final half of the bill.  I am very glad the Minister, Deputy Quinn, is pursuing that and I genuinely respect his perseverance in ensuring that they finally pay their fair share.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I was appalled to read in one of the newspapers today or yesterday that only two of the congregations had confirmed they would attend the meeting with the Minister on Friday.  That is a disgrace.  They appear to have no idea what ordinary members of society feel&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn"><NameTxt>Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">On a point of information, two have stated they are unable to attend but the majority of them will attend.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="AverilPower"><NameTxt>Senator Averil Power</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome that because the report I read quoted only two of them as stating they would attend and that the others had not replied.  I welcome that because there is no doubt that society in general, and also people who are religious, believe it is a disgrace that it has taken so long for the institutions to put up their hands, so to speak.  The Government published reports on their assets and, therefore, there is no reason for them to do anything but come forward and do the right thing at this stage.</P>
        <P>On the legislation before the House, first, I welcome the fact that the Minister will run advertisements in the remaining few weeks before it concludes.  I am sure he will also take advantage of the networks the different advocacy groups have across the world that have been working for victims and try to get them to disseminate the information.  I am sure that is something on which the Department is working.</P>
        <P>Second, on the point Deputy Smith raised in the D&aacute;il debate on behalf of Fianna F&aacute;il, we accept there is a need for a general deadline but we propose that when that legislation is being brought forward, the Minister might consider whether it would be appropriate to include some provision whereby in very exceptional circumstances people might be able to get redress.  I am formally restating that proposal.</P>
        <P>Third, I am aware that concerns have been expressed by some about the records of the board.  Some of the cases were horrendous and it would be important to ensure that the records are disposed of in a confidential way.</P><Col N="652"/>
        <P>We must ensure in the future that the highest standards of child protection operate across every institution, be they people charged with the care of children in a residential sense such as that covered by the Residential Institutions Redress Board but also anybody who has access to children.  I agree with the call for children to be educated about being safe.  The Minister might correct me if I am wrong but the Stay Safe programme is now being operated by all schools.  I am aware there was a gap in that regard, although I never understood the reason some schools and boards of management would refuse to make children aware of basic measures to keep them safe.  If some are not operating the programme, I would support naming and shaming those schools and letting their communities come forward in that regard because the programme is acceptable to approximately 98% of schools throughout the country.  It is important for children to know how to defend themselves and identify whether an approach is inappropriate.</P>
        <P>With regard to vetting, much work has been done in recent years in ensuring that people are properly vetted.  Deputy Simon Harris from Fine Gael raised the issue today.  The diocese has overall responsibility but I understand that whether it is a youth group or organisation that group or organisation is responsible for making sure their members are vetted and putting in the applications to the vetting board.</P>
        <P>Deputy Harris raised the question as to whether any priests have refused to be vetted.  I would like to know that also because in terms of the residential institutions we are talking about relatively distant abuse in most cases but the Cloyne report was frighteningly up to date.  The same applies to the Ryan report and other reports about more recent abuse throughout the country.  We must be sure that anybody who has access to children is being vetted and does not have a way of escaping the net in that respect.</P>
        <P>The Cloyne report provides an account of what happened in one area, and we have had reports about other dioceses, but there is a need to listen to the stories from people throughout the country.  When one considers the extent of the abuse revealed in both the Cloyne and the Ryan reports, it is obvious that serious incidents of abuse were taking place.  There are stories to be told by people living in other areas of the country.  The Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, was reported as saying she would not rule out having a widespread inquiry to establish what happened in other areas of the country.  I hope that is something the Government will examine.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I supported most of the legislation that has come before the House from the Government.  I would have had concerns about some aspects of those Bills, the Medical Practitioners Bill being one example, but I saw it as a means to an end and supported it.  I cannot support this Bill, however, on the grounds that there are many people in this State who are suffering as a result of the consequences of abuse, be it mental, physical or sexual.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senators mentioned some of the television documentaries.  I recall watching the &ldquo;States of Fear&rdquo; documentary.  It was one of the first documentaries to expose what was happening and caused shock across the State.  I am in my 30s and I see this as one of the worst chapters in the history of the State in that vulnerable children people who should have been protected by the State were treated in this way.  In an attempt to try to get my head around these issues, so to speak, when watching those programmes I often tried to put myself in the shoes of the victims in those institutions who lived in fear of the people who operated them and who felt that the State was letting them down.  One can imagine the fear they had to endure and their belief that there was no place for them to go.  Those institutions were the place where they should have been protected, yet they were the places they were abused.  For that reason I cannot support the Bill which puts a timeframe <Col N="653"/>on the redress board because many victims have not had an opportunity to use it.  I will deal with some of these issues shortly.</P>
        <P>The setting up of the redress board was more than a means of compensation.  It was about the State acknowledging the failure in terms of its responsibilities.  It was also motivated by compassion and concern for the victims.  This State cannot do enough to compensate those victims not just financially, but to ensure they get the justice they deserve.  There is nothing we can do that would be seen as too much and if anything, it would be too little because of the failures.  We cannot make up for the failures of previous generations but we can certainly ensure this generation does the right thing.  We can certainly ensure it is the generation that ensures the abuses do not happen again, that robust mechanisms, procedures and laws are put in place to prevent child abuse taking place in any institution or home and that victims are given every opportunity to seek redress.</P>
        <P>From the outset, my view and that of my party was that the redress scheme was fundamentally flawed.  Many found it overly complicated and, more often than not, it involved a traumatic experience that succeeded in reopening the emotional scars of the past.</P>
        <P>The recent Cloyne report makes it clear that clerical abuse is still a major issue.  That the report covers the period up to 2009 shows the Catholic Church has not learned from its mistakes.  I referred to this in another debate recently.  I welcome the move by the Minister to amend the law so the withholding of information on serious offences against a child will be a criminal offence.  This is very important and my party and I support it.</P>
        <P>It is interesting that in response to the findings of the Cloyne report Bishop Gerard Clifford, the auxiliary bishop of the archdiocese of Armagh, said the church&rsquo;s standing was prioritised over the victims of abuse and that this was a great disappointment.  This is a gross understatement; it was much more than a disappointment.</P>
        <P>Let me refer briefly to some of the specifics.  The redress scheme is still processing a backlog of more than 1,000 applications.  However, the applicants can only apply for compensation if they can prove their circumstances are exceptional.  This usually means physical and mental illness prevented them from applying earlier.  It is wrong that the avenue of redress will be closed to them if this Bill is passed.</P>
        <P>When the Ryan report was published in 2009, Irish centres in Britain were inundated with inquiries from people who wanted to apply for redress.  Many who have lost all contact with Ireland knew nothing about the Residential Institutions Redress Board and were unaware they had a right to apply for compensation for the hurt they suffered.  A number of independent reports have shown that many of the tens of thousands of children who were abused left the country and ended up in the United States.  Every opportunity should be given to those victims to ensure they are aware of the redress board and that compensation is available to them.</P>
        <P>Members have made reference to the timeframe.  It is ironic that while it took ten years to produce the Ryan report given the wealth of knowledge and experience and legal backup made available to those compiling it, we are putting a deadline on the timeframe in which victims will be able to obtain redress.  There is something grossly wrong with this.  Many survivors will see something wrong with it also.  One cannot impose a deadline or put a price on child abuse.</P>
        <P>While I have difficulties with the Bill and my party will oppose it, I welcome the view expressed recently by the Minister that every step will be taken by the Government to ensure the lessons of the past will be learned, that the Catholic Church will be taken on, as it should be, that anybody connected with that institution will be subject to the laws of this land, and that children will be protected.  Nobody should have to go through the trauma that abused children experienced in the past.  As a father of two young children, I would be horrified if I knew that, somewhere in this country tonight, children were being abused while in State care or in the home, or being abused by any member of the clergy.  Every step must be taken to prevent this.  I welcome the fact that <Col N="654"/>some positive steps are being taken but my party cannot support the deadline established in this Bill for the reasons I have outlined.  I will deal with some of these reasons in greater detail on Subsequent Stages.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JohnCrown"><NameTxt>Senator John Crown</NameTxt>
	<P>I do not want to sound corny but believe it is a great pleasure to have the opportunity to serve in the same Oireachtas as the Minister, Deputy Quinn.  I have regarded him for some time as the perfect model of the modern social democrat and have great confidence in his ability to implement an important agenda.  I hope he will not think me unduly personal in saying the skill and great energy he has brought to his new portfolio make me more convinced than ever that my campaign to end mandatory retirement at the age of 65 in the public service can be justified.  I have not noticed any particular diminution in the Minister&rsquo;s output since his previous term in government.  I base my remarks on what I have read in Wikipedia being correct.   Were the Minister working as a doctor in the health service, he would be transformed from being a highly productive worker, carer and researcher into being involuntarily dependent on a bankrupt state.</P>
        <P>Let us consider the specifics of this legislation.  I echo the words of my colleague, Senator Cullinane, in that I wonder whether this is the right week or point in history for us to even begin to give the appearance of putting a time limit on the activities of a very necessary social function.  The disclosure in the Cloyne report that was probably most surprising to those of us who observed the unfolding tragedy of various forms of organised abuse of children by those in whom we would have been expected to have greater trust over the years was that some of the abuses occurred very recently.  One wonders whether there are still people harbouring awful memories of terrible things that happened to them but who perhaps lack the courage, motivation and confidence to come forward.  Are we giving the right message by appearing to be drawing a line under the scheme right now?</P>
        <P>I have been a great admirer of the energy that the Minister has brought to the task of attempting to assemble the wherewithal to fund redress through a fair-minded but somewhat more focused challenge regarding the assets of the organisations that bore the greatest responsibility.  Without intending any disrespect, I no longer get the impression there is a game of football taking place between the religious orders and the Government in which both sides are kicking from the same goal, as appeared to be the case in the past.</P>
        <P>It is important in looking at this matter that one consider carefully the portfolio of assets that some of the religious organisations had.  Has attention been paid to the circumstances of and motivation for changes in ownership of non-academic, non-scholastic major religious-owned facilities, some of which, at corporate level, bore considerable responsibility for some of the worst abuses that occurred although they may have been staffed in many cases by very fine people?  Without being too coded about the matter, one wonders about the exact circumstances pertaining to the changes of ownership of certain hospitals and health care facilities and whether they should be examined.  I am not making any charges because I do not know the facts.</P>
        <P>It always struck me as somewhat telling that there appeared to be major changes in the management and ownership structures of certain institutions just when they might have been regarded as potential assets on a balance sheet.  Is it possible for the Minister, as the person responsible for this matter, to ask, perhaps on foot of consultation with his Cabinet colleagues, whether there was any questionable motivation?  One wonders whether, in redress of this, we could have for the first time in this country a different kind of ownership of certain health care facilities, perhaps through the proxy of the publicly funded universities.  The hospitals would be funded by the State, held for the public good and run by professionals appointed by universities.  This is a model that has resulted in some of the finest hospitals in the world.  I refer to the Harvard-run hospitals, the University of California-run hospitals and those run by institutions as diverse as Mount Sinai and Cornell, which <Col N="655"/>exist for the care they provide in the context of academic medicine.  Has the Minister had the chance to investigate some of the changes of ownership?  Are some of the facilities in question ones that should be considered to be on the balance sheet?  I will probably make myself very unpopular in my own hospital for making these remarks but believe they need to be made.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="SeanDBarrett"><NameTxt>Senator Sean D. Barrett</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Quinn, to the House.  I have had the pleasure of knowing him for many years.  Like Senator Cullinane, I fear so much of this is still unresolved that we may find ourselves back here again because even more scandals will have been unearthed.  Like Senator Crown, I appreciate the Minister is seeking to draw a line under this but we do not know what lurks around the corner.  Only yesterday, we saw in a court case with regard to County Donegal that nobody in the Garda or education seemed to be alert to what had been going on over many years.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Judge Yvonne Murphy submitted her report on Cloyne on 23 December last, and on page 88 of that report she found the Office of the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs claimed legal privilege over advice the Child Care Act was not limited to cases of intra-familial abuse.  The former Minister of State with responsibility for children and youth affairs claimed privilege over this advice and refused to provide it for the commission.  This seems like people looking the other way or finding excuses or legal loopholes and not putting children first, as I know the Minister does so staunchly.</P>
        <P Just="Left">We face failures of governance rather than government, and this is also why the country had to be rescued on 1 December last.  No Minister ever came to the House to condone what was going on in these institutions but many other people must have known.  Page 307 of the Murphy report on the Cloyne diocese states the commission was very concerned that the Department of Education and Science could have misunderstood the terms of reference in the manner described.  I am afraid many adult members of society are still covering up.  What will happen when the next diocese report is published?  Raphoe and Derry have been mentioned in this context.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The report on the Cloyne diocese refers to boarding schools which seem to come within the definition of &ldquo;residential institutions&rdquo;.  Most unsavoury incidents have been reported from boarding schools in the Cloyne diocese in Judge Murphy&rsquo;s report.  What will we find when we go to other dioceses which also have boarding schools?  I presume the victims were somewhat older than the people on whose behalf the Minister has been working in the legislation.</P>
        <P>Yet again the call must go out, with the Minister taking the lead and Parliament supporting him, that we must stop the nods and winks and condoning behaviour which we all condemn at moments such as this but which happens again.  I do not know how to get the message to all educational institutions, Departments and Garda divisions in the country that we have had enough of this and that we do not want find out yet again in a court case or a report that it is continuing to the present day.</P>
        <P>The fact that the Cloyne report was presented to the Minister last December is what makes me wary about putting a deadline on this.  I support the Minister personally in what he is trying to do.  It is a mark of shame on an adult society that we keep unearthing these appalling situations where people have not put children first but put legal loopholes first or stated it is not their job to work on it and meanwhile children suffer.  This cannot be allowed to persist.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn"><TitleTxt>Minister for Education and Skills</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank the Senators for their contributions and I will try to respond to the various points made.  Senator Jim D&rsquo;Arcy began by questioning the timeframe for this legislation.  The original Bill did not provide for a clear mechanism whereby this temporary body could be deemed to have completed its work or to put a closing date on it.  This very short Bill is necessary in the first instance.  Societies such as ours are very good at starting organisations but any organisation seems to have an extraordinary reluctance to state it <Col N="656"/>has done its job and will finish.  Conducting the termination in the orderly manner set out by the Bill does not mean we will close the door forever on any subsequent responses to new revelations made.  I heard what Senator Cullinane of Sinn F&eacute;in stated on his party&rsquo;s contribution.  There is a broad degree of consensus on this issue.</P>
        <P>This body was established in 2002 and was to have a window of three years after which it would close its doors for applications in 2005.  We now propose with a precise legal mechanism to close its doors for new applications after 16 September.  The publicity that has been generated in recent years has been substantial and was sadly compounded by the revelations about the Cloyne diocese and speculation about the approximately 30 other dioceses.  Who knows what happens to be there.</P>
        <P>This is a specific response to a specific set of happenings in which the State was complicit in that it subcontracted out to organisations, in this instance 18 congregations and others, to take people into incarcerated care by way of punishment or by way of society&rsquo;s response to people deemed to have misbehaved.  It is a complex area and is horrible from the perspective of 2011.  One only has to read the literature to get into the background of the way society treated itself and how we behaved as a people 50 years ago.  In a number of residential institutions, people were involuntarily incarcerated by the State which contracted out the incarceration to institutions which clearly misbehaved according to the reports we have discussed.</P>
        <P>It is necessary to bring this operation to a close.  Publicity has been generated in recent days.  Senator Power referred to the Government acting on this.  In response to Senator Norris, it is the redress board which will decide what newspapers will be selected for advertisement, when the advertisements will be placed and how they will be run because it is an independent body.  Out of the horror of the recent revelations will be a highlighted consciousness of what has happened.</P>
        <P>Senator Cullinane made reference to the fact that once again people will be reminded they have an opportunity to make an appeal, if they wish.  Last week, I attended educational conferences in Chicago and I took the opportunity to visit an Irish heritage centre in north-west Chicago.  Generations of people emigrated from this country over many years.  Some of the people affected may have gravitated towards the network of Irish societies and through it they will be informed of the possibility of redress.  Sadly, some people were so traumatised and damaged that they left this country with hatred in their hearts and never mixed again with Irish people.  They wanted to go and never have any connection.  Inevitably, some will not have heard, or will not want to hear, of this opportunity.  We cannot compel people to avail of it but we must bring it to an orderly conclusion.  This is what I am doing and I will move on the termination date of 16 September.  I will ask the redress board to ensure the advertisements they run are as effective as possible.</P>
        <P>Senator Norris and others referred to Bethany Home.  This Bill does not close the door to an appropriate response to the survivors of Bethany Home and the Magdalen laundries.  A Member of the House has accepted an invitation from the Government through the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, to chair the body that will examine this situation.  I do not want to prejudice its outcome.  However, by voting to terminate the work of this redress board, we will not close down any response to whatsoever else might happen and, specifically, the body to which Senator McAleese will respond.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Senator Norris and others also asked about the number of countries to which people travelled.  The board has received applications from more than 30 countries, including Great Britain, Australia, USA, Canada, Spain, New Zealand, the Netherlands, Germany and the Channel Islands and relatively obscure places in the context of the history of this issue such as Morocco, Nigeria, Norway, the Republic of Panama, Sri Lanka, the Philippines and the United Arab Emirates.  The total number of applications was just under 14,500.  It is not clear whether there will be many more <Col N="657"/>applicants but we will try to ensure anybody who can demonstrate he or she has a legitimate case will be properly heard.</P>
        <P>I would like to turn to the issues raised about compensation and our discussions with the religious congregations.  The previous Taoiseach, Brian Cowen, and former Minister for Education and Skills, Batt O&rsquo;Keeffe, met the congregations following the publication of the Ryan report and subsequent debate in the D&aacute;il and they suggested that the congregations would be expected to come up to the plate in the context of a 50:50 contribution.  A number of newspaper reports were inaccurate in that while that was said by the Taoiseach and the Minister, the congregations did not agree to it.  It is my hope that when I meet them on Friday to reopen discussions that we can get some agreement on what their contribution will be.</P>
        <P>When everything is finalised, this will have cost the taxpayer approximately &euro;1.36 billion.  Most of that money has been paid out on behalf of the taxpayer at a time the country has lost its economic sovereignty and faces extraordinary difficulties.  It is hoped the shortfall of approximately &euro;200 million on the &euro;680 million contribution that one could have expected from the congregations will be found but I do not wish to prejudice the outcome of our discussions.  I am strongly empowered by the sentiments expressed in the House to pursue them.  As Senator Power said, this is not a matter of who is religious or non-religious.  That has nothing to do with it.  The issue is people taking responsibility to make a fair contribution to the cost of something that was jointly shared by the State and the congregations and it is in that spirit I intend to approach it.</P>
        <P>I accept what Senator Crown said about not necessarily confining assets to buildings and properties used for educational purposes.  We will certainly examine the possibility he has opened up.  During the previous D&aacute;il, I said this could be done by simply handing over the legal ownership of educational properties.  This would mean the congregations making a contribution towards the 50:50 share and, as far as I was concerned, as the Labour Party spokesperson in opposition, they would continue to use the buildings as schools under their current form of patronage until they indicated they wanted to change it.  My concern was twofold, and I wanted to ensure the taxpayer would see a fair response from the congregations.  I have no intention, nor is it the Government&rsquo;s intention, to attempt to bankrupt these congregations, which have the responsibility of looking after their aging members.  That is not my agenda or the Government&rsquo;s agenda.  We are trying to ask them to make a fair contribution that does not bankrupt them while, at the same, time, recognises they have an obligation and, in return, the education infrastructure will continue as they choose it to continue until they wish to change it.  That was the spirit in which I made those comments and that will be the spirit in which I propose to continue the discussions.</P>
        <P>The shortfall was &euro;200 million on the basis of the offers made following the publication of the Ryan report.  However, following the Government&rsquo;s consideration of the properties, only 12 of them with a value of &euro;60 million are of immediate interest and that is why we have arrived at the current position.</P>
        <P>Other points could be made but there seems to be a broad consensus to maximise the 50:50 contribution and to make sure there is a final opportunity for those who may have been victims to respond.  Given the publicity that has been generated across the airwaves in Ireland, Great Britain and elsewhere and the fact that 30 countries have been accessed so far, we can in all reasonableness bring this scheme to a close on 16 September for new applications.  It will take the board some time to process the 1,000 incomplete applications and whatever new applications are received between now and 16 September.  I thank the House for its support.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed.</P>
      </MainHeading>
      <Col N="658"/><MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Residential Institutions Redress (Amendment)" RHead="Bill 2011: Committee and Remaining Stages"><Title>Residential Institutions Redress (Amendment) Bill 2011: Committee and Remaining Stages</Title>
	<P Just="Center">SECTION  1</P>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 are related and may be discussed together.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 3, line 15, to delete &ldquo;17 September 2011&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;17 September 2013&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">I oppose the deadline of 17 September.  It should in no way be seen as my view or that of my party that the Minister and the Government are trying to sweep this issue under the carpet.  They have been forthright in ensuring that child abuse issues are properly dealt with.  We do not want to give the impression that not enough is being done by the Government on behalf of survivors of abuse.  I welcome the Minister&rsquo;s comments on the Bethany Homes and the Magdalene laundries.  When the investigations are completed, there will be a need to ensure similar mechanisms are established to make sure the victims in those institutions have access to redress as well.</P>
        <TimeSt down="4" idown="4">7 o&rsquo;clock</TimeSt>
<P>Senator Crown and I both referred to the timing not being good.  Timing is everything, given the Cloyne report and given people do not believe that we have satisfactorily dealt with these issues.  I accept the Minister&rsquo;s statement that the redress board was established for a specific purpose to deal with a specific issue but, in the context of where we are now following the latest report, it may be seen as rash and premature to close the scheme and, for that reason, we are seeking that the board be allowed to remain in place until September 2013 at which point we can re-examine where we are.  Despite the fact that the board has proven to be fundamentally flawed, it is, nevertheless, wrong for the Government to introduce legislation that from 16 September will prevent people from pursing this avenue in their quest for compensation.  The Ryan report brought us up to 2009, which is only two years ago.  This led to Irish centres in Britain being inundated with inquiries from people wanting to apply for redress.  Many people who had lost all contact with Ireland knew nothing about the redress board and were unaware they had the right to apply for compensation for the hurt they suffered.  As my wife&rsquo;s family is from America, I travel there frequently.  Once I met an Irishman living there who disassociated himself entirely from this State because of what happened to him in a residential institution.  While I accept the Minister is correct that it is not possible to compel people to come forward, this amendment aims to ensure every opportunity is given to those affected.  Due to the recent revelations in the Cloyne report, the closing of the scheme this September may not be timely.</P>
        <P>I am concerned that we may be too rash in closing this avenue for redress.  I am seeking to extend the closing date to September 2013.  I echo the calls of survivors&rsquo; groups made in 2009 when the Ryan report was finally released to the public.  According to Right of Place, at least 150,000 children and teenagers went through orphanages.  It is estimated up to 100,000 of these left Ireland afterwards with at least half travelling to the United States.  There has, however, not been a significant take-up of applications to the redress board from the US community.</P>
        <P Just="Left">It took ten years to produce the Ryan report but the survivors of abuse have been given a much shorter timeframe in which to make an application to the redress board.  In essence, highly paid experts, including judges, barristers and solicitors along with Government and health care professions, are allowed unlimited time to conclude their reports into the abuse that occurred in State institutions.  The victims, however, regardless of their trauma, must work to a rigid timescale and deadline.  One woman referred to in the Cloyne report stated it took her 40 years to report her abuse.  Many of these victims feel abandoned by the State.  I empathise with those who are reluctant to come forward because they fear they will reopen old wounds and do not trust the State to give them the redress they deserve.</P><Col N="659"/>
        <P>If the Cloyne report motivates more victims of abuse to come forward, then the deadline for applications must be extended.  I accept the Government does not want to deny victims of abuse a right to redress and the Minister&rsquo;s bona fides in his explanation as to why the September 2011 deadline is appropriate.  However, there may be victims who, years after the abuse, may take up the opportunity to right the wrong.  Accordingly, a deadline until 2013 is important.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn"><TitleTxt>Minister for Education and Skills</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I was referring to 17 September, not 16 September.</P>
        <P>I cannot accept this amendment because the Government believes sufficient time has been given for applications and every reasonable effort has been made to alert potential applicants to the arrangements of the redress board.  A three-year period for the receipt of applications wasoriginally provided for in the legislation and late applications can be considered in exceptional circumstances.</P>
        <P>We have now reached a point where the bulk of the original applications through the redress board has been dealt with.  While the board continues to receive late applications, it is necessary to provide a cut-off for the receipt of late applications so that the redress board can be wound down.  Over 15,000 applications have been received from over 30 countries.  Extensive advertising campaigns have been undertaken and the redress board will again be placing further press advertisements in advance of the 17 September deadline so as to encourage people to submit applications.</P>
        <P>We need to prepare now for the board&rsquo;s closure.  This Bill will set a date after which it will no longer be possible to receive applications.  Closure of the board will be needed at some point and I believe now is the right time.  Inevitably, the publicity surrounding abuse in the dioceses of Cloyne and Donegal will highlight the newsworthiness of this particular point.  I hope the media makes a connection between this legislation and what has sadly been revealed in the Cloyne report.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P Just="Left">Question, &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand,&rdquo; put and declared carried.</P>
        <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 2:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 3, line 19, to delete &ldquo;17 September 2011&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;17 September 2013&rdquo;.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P FLI="0">Question put: &ldquo;That the words proposed to be deleted stand.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>Vot&aacute;il.</P>
      
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P>Will the Senators claiming a division please rise?</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P><i>Senators Sean Barrett, John Crown, David Cullinane and Jillian van Turnhout rose.</i></P>
      <Speaker pid="DennisODonovan"><NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">As fewer than five Members have risen, I declare the question carried.  In accordance with Standing Order 61, the names of the Senators dissenting will be recorded in the Journal of the Proceedings of the Seanad.</P>
<P>Question declared carried.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
        <P>Section 1 agreed to.</P><Col N="660"/>
        <P Just="Center">NEW SECTION</P>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>I move amendment No. 3:</P>
        <P LI="1">In page 3, before section 2, to insert the following new section:</P>
        <P LI="2">2.&mdash;The Residential Institutions Redress Act 2002 is amended in section 13, by the insertion of the following subsection:</P>
        <P LI="3" Just="Left">&ldquo;(4A) Where the applicant believes the Board failed to deliver appropriate levels of compensation, the applicant may appeal the decision to the High Court.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</P>
        <P FLI="0">The purpose of the amendment is to ensure clarity and provide that those who wish to claim redress have the fullest entitlement to appeal the decision where the redress board has not delivered suitable redress and compensation.  This is an important proposal given the considerable confusion surrounding this issue.  People must be made aware of their rights in this regard and the amendment will be helpful to those victims who are still confused about the issue.  We must ensure the courts are open to the victims of abuse to the fullest possible extent.  The methodology used to calculate appropriate compensation was recognised by many individuals with a legal background as containing a number of flaws.  Compensation was delivered under a points system as opposed to one based on the principles relating to the calculation of damages applied daily in the High Court.  By accepting this amendment the House would send a message that a mechanism will be in place to allow people to take cases to the courts.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn"><NameTxt>Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I am afraid I cannot accept the amendment as it is unnecessary.  The framework under which the redress board makes awards is based on a report entitled, Towards Redress and Recovery, published in January 2002 by the independent compensation advisory committee chaired by Mr. Se&aacute;n Ryan, then a senior counsel.  The report advised on appropriate levels of compensation for injuries related to childhood abuse.  The committee reviewed international precedents and concluded that the best guidance as regards the amounts of awards was to be obtained from within the State by reference to the level of awards made by the Irish courts for pain, suffering and the loss of amenities arising from serious personal injuries.  The committee devised a two stage process for the board to follow in determining any redress award.  First, the board assesses the weight to be attached to the different elements which make up the experiences of victims of abuse.  The weightings then produce an overall assessment which the board reviews to ensure it is reasonable in all circumstances for the applicant in question.</P>
        <P>It is open to all applicants to the redress board to avail of independent legal advice and I understand 97% of applicants have chosen to avail of such advice.  Some 75% of the 13,720 awards made by the board were made following settlements, while a further 19% were made following hearings.  The remaining 3% were made following reviews by the independent residential institutions review committee under the statutory appeals mechanism provided for by the 2002 Act.  Only a handful of applicants have rejected their awards.  Where an applicant does not accept an award, he or she retains the option to pursue any legal avenue which may be open to him or her.  For all of these reasons, specifically the statistic showing that only 3% of applicants appealed their awards to the independent committee, I do not propose to accept the amendment.  If the level of rejections or appeals were high, the case the Senator makes would have some strength.  In all honesty, however, his case does not have strength and, therefore, I cannot accept the amendment.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 have been ruled out of order as they give rise to a potential charge on Revenue.</P><Col N="661"/>
        <P>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 not moved.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Section 2 agreed to.</P>
        <P>Title agreed to.</P>
        <P>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</P>
        <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill do now pass.&rdquo;</P>
      <Speaker pid="RuairiQuinn"><TitleTxt>Minister for Education and Skills</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank Senators for their co-operation in moving on this measure.  This is my first visit to the Seanad since my appointment and I am grateful for the welcome I have received.  I hope to accede to a request from the Leader of the House to participate in a debate on the Government&rsquo;s priorities in education.  The date of the debate is to be fixed by the Seanad.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="JimDarcy"><NameTxt>Senator Jim D&rsquo;Arcy</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister for introducing the Bill and explaining its provisions in such detail.  He has made a great start in his role as Minister for Education and Skills.  I look forward, all being well, to a busy couple of years for his Department.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><TitleTxt>Acting Chairman</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P>When is it proposed to sit again?</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MauriceCummins"><NameTxt>Senator Maurice Cummins</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Ar 10.30 maidin am&aacute;rach.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adjournment" RHead="Matters"> 
    <Title>Adjournment Matters</Title>
    <Sect LHead="Community" RHead="Development"> 
      <sTitle>Community Development</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, back to the House.  The wording of the matter is self-explanatory.  It arises from a briefing For&oacute;ige made to Members of the Oireachtas in the past week in which it highlighted the important work of the Big Brothers Big Sisters of Ireland project.  Of more fundamental concern is that funding for the project, which has been mainly based on philanthropic sources in recent years, is ending in the current year.  As a result For&oacute;ige has a major problem in continuing the project.</P>
        <P>The Minister of State will be aware of the project.  The Big Brothers Big Sisters project is essentially a mentoring project which is aimed largely but not exclusively at siblings in dysfunctional families or where there are difficult social or environmental conditions.  It is a simple concept where an older mentor takes on the role of mentoring a younger person.  It has been established in excess of 30 countries across the world.  It began in this country in the 1990s in the former Western Health Board area in Galway.  It was then extended as a pilot scheme to a number of western and midland counties and has since been rolled out nationally.</P>
        <P>Listening to some of the case histories that were explained to Members of the Oireachtas last week, I was very much taken by the project.  I could see where it would have positive benefits for those, for example, suffering from lack of self-esteem, those subjected to bullying, be it in the home or elsewhere, or those subject to neglect.  Some of the case histories that were outlined to us were very heart warming and they were producing results.</P>
        <P>I appreciate that in the current economic climate facing the Government it will be extremely difficult if not impossible to cater for all of the various financial demands on it.  However, as has <Col N="662"/>been said in the Chamber since she assumed her post, the Minister of State has a great deal of empathy with many of the causes and cases of social and economic disadvantage.  This matter fits into that category.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The wording of the matter is self-explanatory.  Essentially, it is to highlight the wonderful job For&oacute;ige is doing through the Big Brothers Big Sisters of Ireland project and to see what is the attitude and position of the Government in terms of supporting it financially.  I am keen to establish what the thinking is within the Department of Children and Youth Affairs on the issue, what its proposals are or how it intends to be supportive in other ways if not financially.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenLynch"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Health</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</NameTxt>
	<P>I am replying to this Adjournment matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald.  I thank the Senator for raising the matter.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I have been advised that the vision of the Big Brothers Big Sisters, BBBS, programme is to help children around the world realise their potential, create a better future for themselves, their countries and the global community.  BBBS was developed in the United States as a mentoring programme that matches an adult volunteer to a young person, typically ten to 18 years old.  It consists of two types of programmes &mdash; a community-based programme and a school-based programme.  The community-based programme matches an adult volunteer with a young person in need of support and friendship.  The basic idea is that a friendship will form between the young person and adult volunteer that will promote the positive development of the young person and will act as an early intervention mechanism, helping prevent future difficulties and supporting the young person in dealing with adversity in their lives. The programme involves the young person and adult volunteer meeting once a week for a minimum of one year, under supervision.</P>
        <P>The school-based programme aims to ease the transition of primary school students to secondary school by facilitating friendships between first year secondary school students and older students in their schools.  The programme is aimed at young participants that may be at risk of cultural or economic disadvantage.  They may also have poor social skills, early signs of anti-social behaviour or underachievement in school.  The Department of Children and Youth Affairs recognises that many such innovative programmes have an important role in improving outcomes for children and young people.</P>
        <P>For&oacute;ige is to be congratulated on its initiative in respect of BBBS.  In line with the BBBS programme, I have been advised that For&oacute;ige is employing a rigorous approach to initial assessment, ongoing supervision and support for young people and adults involved in the matches, in addition to a detailed evaluation of the programme itself.  The research-focused approach is in keeping with that of the Department of Children and Youth Affairs, which seeks to evaluate in a rigorous and robust fashion new and innovative ways of working with children and young people.  The aim of such research is to seek to answer the deceptively simple questions of &ldquo;What works?&rdquo; and &ldquo;Why does this work?&rdquo;  Ultimately, I see programme evaluations of this type becoming the norm and being utilised to promote a process of continuous improvement in service delivery.  Such an approach will also be of significant benefit in the development of new policy.</P>
        <P>The learning emerging from all such research will help inform policy and service development and delivery into the future.  I understand that the research findings from the For&oacute;ige initiative with BBBS indicate that the programme leads to improved emotional well-being; improved social support and relationships; improved decision-making to combat risk behaviour; and an improvement in young people&rsquo;s attitude to education.</P>
        <P Just="Left">For&oacute;ige&rsquo;s commitment to proven models of intervention, in line with international best practice, is an approach I warmly welcome.  The Department of Children and Youth Affairs has not funded the Big Brothers Big Sisters of Ireland programme.  The House will be aware that the 2011 budget <Col N="663"/>allocation for the youth affairs unit of that Department is &euro;60.154 million on current expenditure and &euro;800,000 on capital expenditure.  This funding supports the delivery of a range of youth work programmes and services for all young people, including those from disadvantaged communities through grant-in-aid.  For&oacute;ige is currently in receipt of &euro;6.037 million from the youth affairs unit of the Department for projects run under a number of schemes, including the youth service grants scheme, the special projects for youth scheme, four youth information centres and a number of projects under the young people&rsquo;s facilities and services fund, rounds 1 and 2.</P>
        <P>As Senator Mooney correctly pointed out, having regard to the current fiscal environment, the reductions in public expenditure that must be achieved by Departments and State agencies and the limited funding available and in light of further budgetary constraints in 2012, it is highly unlikely that it will be possible to consider any new applications for funding in 2012.  I sincerely regret that.  I know well the programme to which he refers.  It is an exceptionally worthy one.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I would be grateful if the Minister of State would convey to the line Minister my thanks for the detail into which her Department has gone on the matter.  I also thank the Minister of State for her personal commitment to it.  It is rather sad but it is due to the economic circumstances in which we find ourselves.  I note that a sum of over &euro;6 million is being provided for projects under the youth affairs unit of the Department.  Am I right to assume that these projects are all ring-fenced, in the sense that the money is given to For&oacute;ige and it then spends it on whatever it considers to be its priorities?  I presume there is detailed negotiation with the organisation, as would occur with any organisation, and the money is then specified for a particular area of expenditure.</P>
        <P Just="Left">In light of the review of expenditure under way, perhaps it might be possible when deciding on the 2012 budget allocations to find a way of moving around some of the money that has already been allocated, in consultation with For&oacute;ige, although I am not speaking for For&oacute;ige and I might even be speaking out of line.  That might help to address the obvious forthcoming shortfall in the Big Brothers Big Sisters of Ireland programme.  It is a little like Mom and apple pie in that everybody is in favour of the programme because it is so good.  I hope the Minister of State will convey those sentiments to the Minister.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenLynch"><NameTxt>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</NameTxt>
	<P>I will do that.  The system as it is currently structured, with the grant having to be directed to a particular unit, is not productive.  We will have to examine how to give funding to people and allow them to decide their priorities, provided&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="PaschalMooney"><NameTxt>Senator Paschal Mooney</NameTxt>
	<P>A little flexibility.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenLynch"><NameTxt>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</NameTxt>
	<P>Yes.  However, that is on condition that when they return to the Department, they can justify the funding.  That type of flexibility is essential.</P>
      </Speaker>
    </Sect>
  
  <Sect LHead="Child Welfare" RHead="and Protection"> 
    <sTitle>Child Welfare and Protection</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister back to the House.  She is here so often she is gaining many frequent visitor points, unlike some of her colleagues.</P>
        <P>I was taken aback to discover that this country does not have a missing children&rsquo;s hotline.  I welcome the fact that 13 European countries have already adopted the 116000 number which has been allocated as a hotline for missing children throughout Europe.  The purpose of having a pan-European hotline is to give and extract as much information as possible within the Community.  It will be an enormous resource to the police, in the first instance, and families with missing children for gathering information and will, in time, become an instantly recognisable number, just as 999 and 911 are.</P><Col N="664"/>
        <P>It is most regrettable that if one dials 116000 in this country, one only hears the tone which indicates that the number is out of service.  We have spoken extensively in this House about what has happened to children in terms of abuse in residential settings, children in care and so forth.  It is only right that redress is made properly and openly and that proper compensation is put in place.</P>
        <P>However, we must look to the future.  The establishment of a full Cabinet Minister for Children and Youth Affairs is most welcome.  The commitment that the children&rsquo;s referendum will take place in 2012 is also most welcome, as is the fact that we will use the material that was so successfully put together by the inter-party committee of the last Oireachtas.  This issue is not, and should not be, about party politics.  The Government should strive to ensure that the wording is agreed by as many parties as possible within the House.</P>
        <P Just="Left">What I am proposing is very necessary.  The cost will not be prohibitive.  My colleague, Senator Crown, suggested that a golf classic organised by the Oireachtas Golf Society be used to collect some money.  Given that neither he nor I plays golf perhaps we are being a little cheeky making that suggestion but this hotline is necessary.  I hope the response from the Minister is positive.  We have a responsibility in this regard.  A total of 13 EU member states have already engaged in this process and gone live with the 116000 number.  A &ldquo;No&rdquo; is not good enough; it also is not good enough to kick the matter to touch.  It must be done as a matter of absolute urgency.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenLynch"><NameTxt>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</NameTxt>
	<P>I am replying on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, and I appreciate the Senator&rsquo;s interest in this area.</P>
        <P>I am glad to have the opportunity to address the House on the matter of the 116 000 hotline for missing children.  The establishment of this hotline is a cross-departmental issue and the Minister intends to ensure that every effort is made to have this hotline up and running as soon as possible.  Under revised EU telecommunications rules agreed in 2009, and in particular Article 27a of the universal service directive, member states were required to &ldquo;make every effort to ensure that citizens have access to a service operating a hotline to report cases of missing children. The hotline shall be available on the number 116 000&rdquo;.  The same directive also requires member states to &ldquo;ensure that citizens are adequately informed of the existence and use of services provided under the 116 numbering range, in particular through initiatives specifically targeting persons travelling between Member States&rdquo;.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources is responsible for transposing this directive into national law.  In essence, the purpose of the 116000 telephone number is to provide a contact number to families if children go missing.  The allocation of specific numbers in the 116 number range in Ireland is managed by the Commission for Communications Regulation, ComReg.  Currently ComReg has designated the following numbers: 116111 is assigned to Childline; 116006 is assigned to the crime victims helpline; 116000 was assigned to missing children; 116117 is assigned to non-emergency medical on-call services;  and 116123 is assigned to emotional support helplines and after a pilot period will be operated by Samaritans.</P>
        <P Just="Left">To date, 18 member states have assigned the 116000 number, 15 of which are functional and operational.  The Department of Children and Youth Affairs has in recent months met other Departments regarding the establishment of the hotline.  The process to date has involved the Department of Children and Youth Affairs, the Department of Health, the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, the Department of Justice and Equality, the HSE and ComReg.  To progress this matter, it is intended to co-ordinate the activities of these Departments and ensure that the 116000 hotline is established.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Minister has recently met NGOs which are eager to assist in the establishment of the hotline and she is grateful for the work they have already put into this process.  The Minister will examine <Col N="665"/>the proposals made in this regard with a view to moving this matter forward as quickly as possible.  The Garda and HSE take every incident of missing children extremely seriously and are committed to ensuring that any vulnerable children are not exploited or ill-treated as part of their responsibility to provide care for any children in the State who are deemed not to have appropriate or satisfactory care arrangements.  This includes separated children seeking asylum.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The input of the Garda is central to the issue of missing children and the Garda has ultimate responsibility for the investigation of these matters.  The Garda and the HSE have worked closely on this matter in recent years.  The HSE, as the major statutory child care authority in Ireland, recognises the value of an EU common freefone hotline for missing children.  Access to a hotline telephone number can be of great assistance to parents when a child goes missing from home or while travelling or on holiday in another European country.</P>
        <P>The HSE operates a joint &ldquo;Missing in Care&rdquo; protocol with An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na which sets out an agreed procedure between the Health Service Executive and the Garda, and clarifies the roles and requirements of both agencies in relation to all children missing from their care placements, as set out in the Child Care Act 1991.  A missing child from care is one whose whereabouts are unknown and the circumstances of their disappearance are such that the Health Service Executive, or its agents, risk assess the absence as high risk.</P>
        <P Just="Left">While the introduction of a missing children&rsquo;s hotline involves many Departments, the notification of a missing child is particularly a matter for the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Accordingly, the Minister is in contact with the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, in seeking to jointly achieve the establishment of this service.  Different costings for such a service have been calculated, including by NGOs interested in providing the service.  Obviously, in the current financial climate, it is essential that the most economic approach possible is taken to providing any service.  The Minister would hope a partnership approach could achieve a cost-effective solution to the implementation of this important initiative.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Given my responsibility in the area of suicide, I wrote to the three mobile phone providers because up to this point, the Samaritans line was funded, in the main, by Eircom as it is a land line service.  The Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Pat Rabbitte, and I wrote to the three mobile phone providers to ask if they would consider providing the same type of service which Eircom delivered in recent years and they came back with a positive response.  If the three mobile phone providers come on board, the 116000 number becomes far more viable.</P>
        <P Just="Left">Most emergency calls, not only 999 calls but also calls from people who are feeling suicidal and calls in regard to missing children, are made from mobile phones.  It is important to get the mobile phone providers on board in order that we can roll this out efficiency.  It will do what the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, hopes it will do, that is, it will give us a unique service from all the mobile phone providers for a minimal cost.  I appreciate very much for what the Senator is calling.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="MartinConway"><NameTxt>Senator Martin Conway</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Minister of State, who might thank the Minister for Children, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, for a most comprehensive response.  I am glad the Minister of State corrected me.  My figure was 13 but 18 member states have complied with this which probably makes the scenario here even worse.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I agree with the Minister of State&rsquo;s comments that the mobile phone providers will play an integral part.  I am sure they operate in the other 18 countries.  Even if people are out of credit or their SIM cards disappear, it is essential the 116000 number can be accessed.  I am disappointed that we have not been given a date.  The idea behind setting up a Ministry for children and creating a full Cabinet position was that all Departments would be pulled together and that the Minister would ensure things happened quickly.</P><Col N="666"/>
        <P Just="Left">We have been very compliant Europeans in areas that are not as critical and I hope the Government will be an exceptionally compliant European in bringing in the 116000 number.  I will raise this matter again in a number of months but I hope we will see action.  If the will is there, this could be done in a couple of months.  I hope this emergency service will be in place in 2012.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I commend the Minister of State and the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Rabbitte, for their initiative in regard to the mobile phone providers and Samaritans.  A close friend of mine does much voluntary work for Samaritans.  Its work is well recognised but much of the time, the work of the volunteers is not given the proper recognition.  They are the real heroes in our society.  I commend the Minister of State for what she has done.  Her work as Minister of State so far has been outstanding.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="KathleenLynch"><NameTxt>Deputy Kathleen Lynch</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I thank the Senator.  Having watched it at close quarters, trying to a create a new Department is a feat in itself.  Dragging things from other Departments is quite difficult.  I reassure the Senator that I, the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Pat Rabbitte, and, I am sure, the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, will meet the three mobile phone providers in the near future.</P>
      </Speaker>
  </Sect>
  <Sect LHead="Electricity" RHead="Transmission Network"> 
    <sTitle>Electricity Transmission Network</sTitle>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy O&rsquo;Dowd.  The ESB has played a significant role in the State&rsquo;s development since its foundation.  The Ardnacrusha dam was one of the most significant moments in the early development of this State.  The ESB is a sizeable company, which employs thousands of people.  It is also a profitable company and contributes to the Exchequer.  The ESB operates independently and successfully and provides an essential service.</P>
        <P>The Fianna F&aacute;il and the Green Party 2007 White Paper on Energy advised on the need to unbundle the ESB&rsquo;s transmission and distribution assets &mdash; in other words, to break up the ESB as we know it.  In 2009, the then Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Eamon Ryan, appointed Fergus Cahill, the former chief executive of the Irish National Petroleum Corporation, to chair a review of the implications of splitting up the company.  Frontier Economics was selected to complete the report.  The Cahill-Frontier Economics report was presented to the current Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Pat Rabbitte, earlier this year.</P>
        <P>The report makes a strong economic argument against the Government&rsquo;s intention to unbundle the ESB&rsquo;s transmission and distribution assets, a move that could cost the State a whopping &euro;1.6 billion.  The programme for Government commits to transferring the ESB transmission assets to Eirgrid or Smart Grid.  The Government&rsquo;s current legislative programme includes the Electricity Transmission Assets Bill 2011, which allows for the unbundling of the transmission system and to establish Eirgrid in primary legislation.</P>
        <P Just="Left">There is also the matter of the EU electricity directive, which will also result in unbundling unless the Government seeks and obtains a derogation.  The Cahill-Frontier Economics report sets out ways and mechanisms in which this could be achieved.  It is worth noting that the deadline for seeking a derogation is the autumn of this year; therefore, there is a time imperative in that regard.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The McCarthy report on the sale of State assets recommended the break up of the ESB.  I suppose that is the genesis of this and of the previous Government&rsquo;s commitment to unbundle and break up the company.  It would seem that is the intention of this Government as well as the transfer of the transmission grid, including the high voltage system in the North of Ireland to Eirgrid.</P>
        <P>The McCarthy report, published by the previous Government, calls for the break up of the ESB.  The report more or less supported what the previous Government called for and what the new <Col N="667"/>Government seems to be supporting.  However, the Cahill-Frontier Economics report calls for something contrary to both the Government&rsquo;s stated intention in terms of policy and the programme for Government.  Therefore, we must pose the question as to why a report, which is supportive of what the previous and the current Governments called for in terms of the future of the ESB, is published but a report which calls for something that is at variance to what the Government proposes is not published?  That is a very real worry for the trade unions and those who want to see the ESB remain as a single entity, a company which has done so well for Ireland and which is so profitable.</P>
        <P>We believe the Cahill-Frontier report must be published immediately.  Week after week, Sinn F&eacute;in has called for this.  Deputy Mary Lou McDonald has called <i>ad nauseam</i> in the D&aacute;il for the report to be published.  It has been sitting on the Minister&rsquo;s desk for a number of months.  The Taoiseach, in response to a question from Deputy Gerry Adams, recently confirmed that the report has not even been brought to Cabinet.  I find this incredible.  The programme for Government has been published and the Minister has stated that he has not yet made a decision as to what the Government will do or even with regard to commitments made by the previous Government.  We still await publication of an independent report commissioned by the Government.  The report should be published.</P>
        <P>I ask the Minister of State, Deputy Fergus O&rsquo;Dowd, to bring this matter to the attention of the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Rabbitte, and impress on him the strong view of my party that the report should be published.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG"><TitleTxt>Minister of State at the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources</TitleTxt><NameTxt>Deputy Fergus O&rsquo;Dowd</NameTxt>
	<P>The report by Cahill-Frontier Economics was undertaken under a process overseen by Mr. Fergus Cahill as independent chairperson.  The report contains an assessment of costs, benefits and regulatory impact of the options for unbundling the electricity transmission assets set in the context of EU third package and the all-island single electricity market.  Frontier was asked to examine all the options available to ensure Ireland&rsquo;s compliance with the EU third energy package, comparing each of the other scenarios allowed for under the directive.</P>
        <P>The three primary options under the directive are the full ownership unbundling, independent system operator and independent transmission operator.  The directive also contains a provision which allows that where a member state considers that there were arrangements in place on 3 September 2009 which guarantee a more effective independence of the transmission system operator than the ITO regime, and the member state permits this option, then the asset owner, in this case the ESB, is required to make the case to retain the system.  This provision requires the asset owner to apply for an exemption under Article 9(9) of the directive and for the national energy regulator, CER, and the Commission to certify and approve the arrangements.</P>
        <P>The Frontier process involved input from the direct stakeholders and other stakeholders.  The direct stakeholders were the management and the unions of ESB and EirGrid and the ESB employee share ownership trust.  The direct stakeholders were provided with a copy of the draft conclusions of the Frontier report and the opportunity to comment on those conclusions.</P>
        <P>Both EirGrid and ESB have vital roles to play in delivering our national electricity infrastructure.  The unbundling of the transmission assets involves the resolution of complex technical, financial and operational issues as well as the possible development of legislation.  Both companies were given a copy of the final report on a confidential, redacted basis and have submitted observations on it.  The Minister will be bringing proposals to Government shortly with a recommendation on the next steps with regard to the electricity transmission assets.</P>
        <P>The Frontier report contains significant and detailed commercially sensitive information. The report will be published shortly but will redact the commercially sensitive information which it <Col N="668"/>contains.  Publication will take place after the conclusion of Government consideration of the transmission assets issue.</P>
        <P>With regard to the future of ESB, there are no proposals at present to sell the ESB or any of the State&rsquo;s energy assets.  I note that ESB&rsquo;s status as a vertically integrated utility would remain unaltered irrespective of any future arrangements decided upon in relation to the transmission assets, having regard to the programme for Government statement in the matter.  Any energy utility which owns distribution networks and power generation and supply is a vertically integrated utility under EU law.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The report of the review group on State assets and liabilities has been submitted to the Government and published.  The Government has stated that the recommendations of that report will be considered and that consultations will take place with the stakeholders.  Proposals are also being developed for the Government&rsquo;s consideration on the formal establishment of the NewERA, overseen by the Cabinet sub-committee on economic infrastructure.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="DavidCullinane"><NameTxt>Senator David Cullinane</NameTxt>
	<P Just="Left">I do not accept the Minister of State&rsquo;s response.  There are no proposals to sell the ESB but there are proposals to break it up.  Once the company is unbundled and its distribution assets transferred to EirGrid, its power base will be, effectively, taken away.</P>
        <P>We must be conscious of the negative effect of the threat of unbundling on the future of the company.  The ESB has been self-financing since its inception and has been the source of billions of euro for the Exchequer.  The ESB has a very ambitious plan to invest in Ireland by improving its distribution mechanism.  The company was able to borrow money on the bond markets to invest in the country and create jobs.  This project is under threat.  This corporate plan meant the company could borrow money, which the State cannot do.  It is ahead of the State in this regard because it is a profitable company.  The ESB has an ambitious plan and wants to invest in the economy.  That will be put at risk if the unbundling goes ahead.</P>
        <P Just="Left">The Minister of State has said the report will be published shortly.  We have been given the same answer for a long time.  Like the previous Government, he hides behind the facade of sensitive information.  Every report contains a level of sensitive information.  This is a smokescreen.  The Minister of State should publish the report.  If it contains sensitive information, that can be dealt with very quickly.  We call on the Government to publish the report immediately.</P>
        <P Just="Left">I welcome the Minister of State&rsquo;s promise to publish the report shortly.  However, we are not convinced by this promise.  He has given no timeframe for when this might happen.</P>
      </Speaker>
      <Speaker pid="FergusODowdFG"><NameTxt>Deputy Fergus O&rsquo;Dowd</NameTxt>
	<P>I thank the Senator for his views.  This is a matter of concern to everybody.  In line with the EU directive, the report lays out three options and examines each fully.  Every country in Europe, with the exception of Ireland, Scotland, Latvia and Greece, has unbundled its transmission assets.  There are different views, but the programme for Government is also clear on the matter.</P>
        <P Just="Left">As soon as the Minister is in a position to publish the report that will be done.  This will be when the Government has considered the outcome of the report.  I expect it to be very soon.</P>
      </Speaker>
        <adjournment>The Seanad adjourned at 7.50 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 20 July 2011.</adjournment>
    </Sect>
<HtmlBk SectId="0" />
  </MainHeading><!--Fix-->
</Debate><!--Fix-->
