<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="7" Month="May" Year="1930" Vol="13" No="19" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 7 Bealtaine 1930" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 7 May 1930" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1005">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1005" /> Do chuaidh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar a 3 p.m.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Cork Harbour" RHead="Bill, 1927&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Cork Harbour Bill, 1927&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. Dowdall Mr. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That, in view of the fact that the Ports and Harbours Tribunal has not yet reported, the Second Stage of the Cork Harbour Bill, 1927, be further postponed until the 22nd October, 1930, or, if the Seanad be not sitting on that day, until the next day thereafter on which the Seanad shall sit.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnCounihan" hpid="Mr. Counihan Mr. Counihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Counihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the motion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Waterford and Bishop Foy Endowed" RHead="Schools (Amendment) Bill, 1928&mdash;Report Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Waterford and Bishop Foy Endowed Schools (Amendment) Bill, 1928&mdash;Report Stage.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDuffy" hpid="Mr. Duffy Mr. Duffy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Duffy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That the Bill be considered on Report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to know something about this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Do you object to the Report Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I do, until I know something about it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Bill must therefore stand over until the next sitting.</P>
      <P>Report Stage adjourned until next sitting.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Censorship of Films" RHead="(Amendment) Bill, 1930&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Censorship of Films (Amendment) Bill, 1930&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Col N="1006" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney) James Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney)</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a short Bill amending the existing Act for the censorship of films.  The reason why a Bill of this nature has become necessary is that, as I am sure all Senators are aware, a new kind of film has come into existence, that is, the talking film.  As things are, there is not in the Censorship Board power to censor talking films.  The only thing which the Censorship Board can do at present is to censor the picture and not the words.  In consequence, it is quite possible that undesirable pictures might get through, because I think it will be readily understood that the picture might look all right, but that it might be associated with unpleasant words which would put a different meaning on the picture altogether. In consequence of the growth of these talking films and the necessity of dealing with them, I set up a small committee which went into the matter fully, and this Bill carries out their recommendations.  The chairman of that Committee was Senator O'Farrell, who is also chairman of the Censorship Board.  One of the principal difficulties which the Committee had, I think I may say, was the selection of suitable apparatus. Senator O'Farrell and Mr. Montgomery, the film censor, went over to England and inspected various apparatus there, and they finally recommended one.  After the Bill becomes law, we hope that in a very short time, say, two or three weeks, the necessary apparatus will have been installed and that talking films will be properly censored.  In consequence, I would ask the Seanad to pass this Bill, as I think it would be the general view of everybody that talking films should be properly censored.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I am entirely in favour of this measure and I think most of us will be, but I should like to take this opportunity of expressing an opinion on the present censorship as regards films generally.  I think a great deal still remains to be done with regard to censorship from <Col N="1007" /> what we can see of some films in this country.  On investigating the matter, I was informed&mdash;I do not know how far it is true&mdash;that in many cases the Appeals Board actually permitted films to be shown that had already been turned down by the censor.  I think when we are dealing with a big issue like this, that may be a great menace to the future development of the youth of the country as there has been very serious criticism with regard to certain films which have been allowed to go through.  I do not think I am unduly puritanical, but I think it is a matter that requires the closest attention.  I understand that in some cases the Appeals Board have permitted films to be shown which the censor did not approve of.  I do not know how far that is true, but I have it on reasonably good authority.</P>
      <P>There is another matter which I ought to mention, and that is, that I believe very old films are being shown through the small towns that really have never been through the censor's hands.  I have knowledge of two particular instances where such films were shown in small towns and I am satisfied from what I have heard of these films that they were certainly never shown before the censor.  I should like to draw the Minister's attention to these two or three points, so that we may ensure that such films in the hands of travelling showmen shall not be displayed in the small country towns or anywhere else and that the censorship shall be effectively applied.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>With regard to Senator Connolly's point that certain films that have been rejected by the censor have been passed by the Board, I would ask him what is the object of having a Board at all except for the purpose of considering appeals and, if necessary, reversing or modifying the decisions of the censor.  It is a big responsibility to put on any one man to say in every single case whether a picture is fit to be shown or otherwise and what cuts, if any, should be effected. It is in order to relieve the official <Col N="1008" /> censor of this responsibility that it was decided under the Act of 1923 to set up a Board of Appeal and that Board has been functioning in accordance with the Act ever since. I think on the whole its decisions have not been adverse to public opinion because the number of complaints received has been negligible. It is true, since the talking film came into vogue, that the sound portion of the film, the dialogue portion, could not be, and has not been censored. In the first place, the Act did not cover the spoken word and, secondly, there was no apparatus by which the censor could hear the spoken word in order to censor it.  Looking at a talking film in a visual way, merely seeing the action does not even give an indication as to what the theme of the picture itself may be and it is possibly true that pictures have been passed after merely a visual observation which were objectionable and that would not have been passed if the apparatus were there and the dialogue could be understood, but the number of pictures rejected <i>in toto</i> by the film censor but passed by the Board is absolutely negligible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Really what happens is: The censor agrees to issue a certificate provided certain cuts which he indicates are made.  The renter, if he objects to the cuts or portion of them has a right to appeal to the Board.  That appeal is then heard <i>de novo</i> as if the film had been rejected.  The Board is then at liberty itself to indicate cuts which will be insisted upon if a certificate is to be issued and these may coincide with the censor's cuts or they may not.  They may be a little more or they may be a little less and the renter either accepts the decision of the Board merely or he rejects it.  But of course, unless the Board has power to do things of that kind, or to act in that way, it would be meaningless altogether to have a Board.  It is difficult to lay down any hard and fast rule.  It is hard to say what type of mentality one should take as a standard.  It is said you may pass certain things for cities which you <Col N="1009" /> cannot pass for a simple country population, but against that is the argument: are you to take the simplest mentality of the whole country as a standard upon which you should base your judgment in all cases?</P>
    <P>The same principle will arise in regard to the censorship of publications. The Board, as made up, is composed of clergymen of different denominations, representatives of the universities and the medical profession and the general public.  On the whole, where you find this board of nine, or as many of them as may be present, arguing that a certain picture is unobjectionable in the main you may take it that there is not very much wrong.  There are certain types of vulgarity in pictures which cannot be said to be obscene or immoral, and it is pretty hard under existing legislation to turn down pictures in this respect. But I think you may take it that gross vulgarity is not tolerated. There are certain pictures that one would like to reject as positively worthless and a fraud upon the public, but which you cannot reject for these reasons alone.  We must make up our minds that we cannot look upon the film as merely an instructive medium, something which is going to elevate, to educate, and so forth.  It is not intended for that. It is merely a source of amusement and a source of profit, and as such it would be impossible, I think, in any legislation which might be devised to make the film purely and simply an educative or an elevating medium in any sense of the word.</P>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>I strongly support the Minister in his desire to censor talkies, but I think if he had the courage of what is the conviction of many people who dealt with censorship, he ought to abolish them utterly out of the country.  We take to ourselves a great deal of credit for being purists as a nation, and at the same time we allow this cosmopolitan form of attacking the emotional nature of the country to go unchecked.  I was a member of the Board, and the only objection <Col N="1010" /> I had was when the chairman happened to be fooled by the subtlety of the propaganda.  When they allowed the Life and Passion of Our Lord to appear on the films the subtle Semitics who composed this pious picture had it preceded by a scene which was sufficiently objectionable to satisfy the cutting of the censors.  It was promptly cut and a ten times more dangerous form of immorality was permitted to pass, and that was the position where Christ was put as a colleague of Charlie Chaplin, and presented to the minds of 12-year-old children in this country.  This film went round the barns and music halls and other places in Ireland, and there is nothing to prevent a child who sees a religious picture associating in his mind the sentiments which appertain to the ordinary general bulk of picture of the cinema&mdash;pictures that cannot help being vulgar, because they must pass the frontiers of the world, and they must appeal with the three appeals only tolerable to the mass of humanity, that is sex, blood and murder.  That is the reiterated and unchanged theme of every cinema picture.</P>
      <P>The talkies are another affair. They are presumably made up in Hollywood.  They never use the English language, as it is used by the English.  They use a cosmopolitan lingo which is always degrading, and which is distracting the English speaking nations from the source of the language and from its own centre.  It is a form of making national sentiment eccentric, and I think that without drawing on that vision of our self-righteousness we ought to abolish talkies utterly. Apart from the fact that these cinemas are drawing out of the country £250,000 per year through the renters&mdash;the fact that the penny a foot tax brings that in through the renters&mdash;you will see the people queueing up all through the city and our best sites in this city are ruined by cinema palaces.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>National assets!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>How are they assets?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1011" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>We were told that by a high authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>A national asset obstructing O'Connell Street with cinema palaces, in the general cosmopolitan taste.  A suction of money from this country cannot be afforded. I think we have got it on very good authority that there is a quarter of a million of money going out of the country and none of it for educative purposes.  If we allow talkies&mdash;this international lingo of vulgarity to be added to the cinema palaces we will do the country an incalculable harm, because, in my opinion, what is most precious to the nation is that the emotional nature of the nation be kept within its own confines.  We have children with their minds thrown to the ends of the earth, where the eyes of the fool are supposed to be and nothing is censored. There is nothing educational because they cannot afford to be educational. The highest claim that a cinema producer makes is that it is a new work. It is neither drama nor rhetoric.  It is a photograph that moves.  It is a new vulgarity and centres across everybody's frontier invading in a new way the integrity of each nation it touches.  As I say they are bound to these three things.  They are bound to the appeal in its lowest terms and therefore the censors have, to a certain extent, to consider the mentality of the people who see it in its very lowest terms.  They have to imagine the fool because it is to those people with uncontrolled emotions that the cinema constructors are appealing.  As I once said we would require no censorship board if you projected on the screen the faces of the renters.  You could see an international gang of people who have less character than anybody who ever came out of the Levant.  That in itself would be an excellent censorship.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The talkie is a far more dangerous thing super-added to the picture, and I think the simplest way is to say in Ireland you will get as much cinema, or I suppose it is called kinema as you wish, but you will not have any of this cosmopolitan slang. <Col N="1012" /> It is not grammar.  It certainly is not English, and it is in every case disastrous to those who listen to it, because it shakes the very foundations of education in the primary and secondary schools, and it adds to unrest in terms which are never satiable.</P>
    <P>You can never supply education to the people who are made restless with the cosmopólitan appeal of these pictures.  The children who see them do not realise how they are composed. They are composed in a little room and have nothing at all to say to the scenery, which can be rented or hired separately altogether from the subject.  There are well-known things like the profile of camels crossing a desert which can be handed out as a background to any film.  When it comes to the talkies you will never censor the talkies, because it is impossible with the change of language to know to what extent the vulgarity can affect the country inasmuch as it is always eccentric, always over the frontier, always outside our own business and our own ideas.  It would be no loss to this country but in every way a gain, and a re-gaining of the position of which, as I say, we are justly or unjustly proud of dictating to the people, if not morals at least good taste.  I think the censorship ought to simplify itself by saying that no talkies will be censored, that we will not have talkies, that we will not have any international slang, which is never uplifting.  I have never seen a picture (except on two or three occasions when we had a German representation of Goethe's Faust) with any definite signs of artistic selection.  These are the only cinema things which, I think, a child should see.  If not directly, at least the association of ideas in the background of everything else was the level of Charlie Chaplin, who, by the way, is not in favour of the talkies. I do really ask the censor to simplify the thing by saying: &ldquo;We will have no censorship at all of the talkies, but get rid of them.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I have never <Col N="1013" /> listened to such&mdash;I do not like to use it&mdash;high-brow balderdash.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="OliverGogarty" hpid="Dr. Gogarty Dr. Gogarty">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Gogarty</NameTxt>
      <P>Another example of the talkies.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I presume that Senator Gogarty, speaking of the talkies, refers to all sound pictures. I can only infer from the Senator's remarks that he very rarely, if ever, visits the places where the talking picture is exhibited.  I make no apology for saying that I very frequently attend cinema shows and I never found either my ethical, my moral sense, or my sense of sanity sapped as the Senator seems to think happens.  One of the best talking or sound pictures that has been shown in Dublin, I think, since the matter became a practical proposition was a talking picture of the Emancipation Centenary Celebrations.  One of the finest examples of the development of that science or art was the representation of the Archbishop of Dublin addressing the people.  If what Senator Gogarty said is to be taken in its applied sense that would be all censored as the very fact that it is a talking picture would be sapping the morals of those who attended it.</P>
      <P>I can only gather one thing from the Senator's observation, that is his apprehension of the damage that this is going to do to the English language.  I am quite sure that if it was suggested the talkies in the future should use compulsory Irish the Senator would put a barricade in front of every cinema house in the city.  In my impression from what I have seen of the development of the talking picture I think there are tremendous possibilities before us both from the point of view of entertainment and instruction and I think it is retrograde to have the idea that Senator Gogarty gives expression to broadcasted.  It is because I do not want those ideas to go without some expression of dissent that I have intervened in the discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse-Power Mrs. Wyse-Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse-Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to point out to the Seanad that this very short Bill has nothing to do <Col N="1014" /> with the general Censorship Bill that the Censor and the Board works.  It is particularly short for the reason that the necessity of having a censorship of the talkies is so great.  That is the reason if there is really nothing else why this particular Bill takes power to censor the talkies.  Whether we agree with films being in Ireland or not, or whether we agree to other powers being given to the Censor or the Board has nothing to do with this, and I would appeal to the Seanad generally to pass this Bill as quickly as possible, because anyone who has gone to the talking pictures will realise that if the words were heard by either the Censor or the Board very many of them would not be allowed.  You can only censor at present what you see, and you have no idea what the characters are saying each to the other.  You do not know what the woman's position is in the case.  She may be the wife or she may be the mistress.  If we had machinery, and if we had the power, a great deal of unpleasantness would disappear, and I can only ask the Seanad to pass this Bill as quickly as possible, because the need is very great.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to refer in a personal way to a matter that Senator Gogarty mentioned.  He said that the chairman on a certain occasion allowed himself to be fooled by propaganda.  The person to whom he referred is not here, and is not in a position to defend himself, and I want to say, as a member of the Board at that time, that the statement is not justified and really should not have been made.  As a matter of fact, as regards the particular picture concerned, the Board, I think, very largely defers to clerical opinion on the Board, and on that occasion they were guided by it so that there is no justification for the statement.  As regards talking pictures, parrot disease develops very rapidly, and that may account for some of the statements made.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say that I agree with what Senator Gogarty <Col N="1015" /> has said.  I do not often agree with him; perhaps I have never agreed with him before, but on this occasion I do agree with him.  If we pass this Bill we practically give our sanction to the introduction of these talkies, which, I think, are a great nuisance. I am inclined to vote against the Bill altogether simply as a protest against talkies being introduced into this country.  Later perhaps we will get a ban against them altogether.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask the Minister in his reply to say what would be the effect upon talkies of not passing the Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>At the present moment talking pictures are coming into this country and they are practically uncensored.  If this Bill is rejected the pictures will still continue to come in and still continue to go uncensored.  As far as what Senator Colonel Moore and Senator Gogarty have stated about talking pictures, I do not intend to express any opinion.  It might possibly be that the world would be better if the moving picture had never been invented, and the world might be a better place if the talking picture had never been developed out of the simple, silent moving picture. That may be the case, but we cannot put our heads in the sand. We must recognise that there are such things as cinemas and that there are such things as talking pictures, and we must deal with them in a sensible, rational way, recognising their existence.  The sensible, rational way of dealing with them is by seeing that they are properly censored and that they are not harmful to the morals of the people of this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There were a couple of other matters mentioned which are hardly germane to this present Bill.  One of them was mentioned by Senator Connolly. He said that there were some films in some country towns that had never been passed by the Censor.  I would like very much if he would send me particulars of the towns, the <Col N="1016" /> films, and the producers of these films.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse-Power Mrs. Wyse-Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse-Power</NameTxt>
      <P>The name of the film.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JosephConnolly" hpid="Mr. Connolly Mr. Connolly">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Connolly</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be glad to supply the particulars.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>It surprised me very much to hear that a film would last for seven years.  I certainly understood that the life of a film is extremely short.  Though it has nothing to do with this particular Bill, if the Senator furnishes me with particulars I will make inquiries. I do not think there is anything further I need say.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time&rdquo;&mdash;put and declared carried.</P>
      <P>Committee ordered for next Wednesday.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Illegitimate Children" RHead="(Affiliation Orders) Bill, 1929&mdash;Report">
    <Title>Public Business. - Illegitimate Children (Affiliation Orders) Bill, 1929&mdash;Report.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to suggest to the House that in view of the number of amendments to Section 3 and the difficulty of discussing these amendments in accordance with the rules for Report Stage and also because of the possibility that when an amendment is carried it might need some revision, we refer Section 3 back to Committee for consideration of the amendments.  It would mean that the Report Stage could be taken next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I was going to suggest that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>It seems to me that in the working out of this Bill the amendments to Section 2 will be quite as important as the amendments to Section 3.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>They will get ample discussion on Report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there any precedent for recommitting any one section of the Bill when a request has been made to recommit another section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>There is.  I formally second Senator Douglas's motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1017" /> Ordered: That Section 3 of the Bill be re-committed.</P>
    <P>The Seanad went into Committee on Section 3 of the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask each Senator to move his amendment, and when they are debated I will put the original question: &ldquo;That sub-section (5) stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
      <P>(1)  On the hearing by the District Court of a summons issued under this Act the Justice, if he is satisfied in accordance with this section that the alleged father of the illegitimate child (whether born alive or still-born) to whom such summons relates is the father of such child may make an order (in this Act called an affiliation order) adjudging such alleged father to be the putative father of such child and ordering such putative father to pay the expenses, as measured by the Justice, incidental to the birth of such child, and, where such child was born alive, such of the following moneys as may be appropriate, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  if such child has died before the making of such order, the funeral expenses, as measured by the Justice, of such child to an amount not exceeding five pounds, or</P>
      <P>(b)  such weekly sum not exceeding twenty shillings as the Justice shall fix for the maintenance and education of such child, or</P>
      <P>(c)  where the putative father so consents, a lump sum of such amount as shall be fixed by the Justice in commutation of any weekly sum which might otherwise be payable under this Act by such putative father in respect of such child.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(2)  No Justice of the District Court shall be satisfied that a person is the putative father of an illegitimate child without hearing <Col N="1018" /> the evidence of the mother of such child and also evidence corroborative in some material particular or particulars of the evidence of such mother.</P>
    <P>(3)  Where a Justice of a District Court by an affiliation order orders the putative father of an illegitimate child to pay a weekly sum in respect of such child he may attach such conditions as he shall think proper to the payment or to the receipt of such weekly sum.</P>
    <P>(4)  The provisions of this Act relating to the fixing of the amount of a lump sum paid in commutation of a weekly sum payable under an affiliation order and the payment, administration, and application of such lump sum shall apply to the fixing, payment, administration and application of a lump sum made payable by an affiliation order in commutation of any weekly sum which might otherwise be payable.</P>
    <P>(5)  All applications to the District Court and all cases under this Act shall be heard <i>in camera.</i></P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>On behalf of Senator Farren I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 3, sub-section (5).  To delete the sub-section and to substitute the following new subsections therefor:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(5)  On the hearing in the District Court, or in the Circuit Court on appeal therefrom, of a case under this Act, the Judge shall direct all persons to be excluded from the Court other than the officers of the Court, the parties and their counsel and solicitors, the witnesses and the mother or other female relative or female friend of the applicant.</P>
      <P>(6)  It shall not be lawful to print or publish or cause or procure to be printed or published any report, statement, commentary or other matter of or in relation to the judical proceedings in any case under this Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1019" /> (7)  Nothing in the last preceding sub-section shall apply&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  to the printing or publishing of any order, notice or report in pursuance of the direction of the Court, or</P>
    <P>(b)  to the printing or publishing of any matter in any separate volume or part of any bona fide series of law reports which does not form part of any other publication and consists solely of reports of proceedings in courts of law, or in any publication of a technical character <i>bona fide</i> intended for circulation among members of the legal profession.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The effect of this amendment would really be to put in practical working form the amendment that was carried on the Committee Stage. That amendment provided only that the cases would be heard <i>in camera;</i> this amendment makes provision for the clearing of the court, with the exception only of the persons who are parties to the suit, their counsel or solicitors, the mother or other female relative or female friend of the applicant, the officers of the court, witnesses, and so on.  It prohibits the publication in the form of a newspaper report or in any other similar form of anything in connection with the proceedings, but it does not prohibit the printing or publishing of any order, notice or report in pursuance of a direction of the court, or the printing in any separate volume of part of any <i>bona fide</i> series of law reports which does not form part of any other publication and which is published merely for the information of the court and of lawyers.  There is nothing new in principle in this except to the extent that it definitely prohibits publication, retaining, of course, as it does, the principle of the hearing of the case <i>in camera.</i>  There is a subsequent amendment which imposes a definite penalty in the event of publication.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We will come to that later.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1020" />
    <Speaker pid="JohnOFarrell" hpid="Mr. O'Farrell Mr. O'Farrell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Farrell</NameTxt>
      <P>I just mention that now.  This merely amplifies or puts into legal form the principle adopted on the Committee Stage through the amendment that was then agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>Section 3, sub-section (5).  To delete the sub-section and to substitute the following new subsections therefor:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(5)  Where in his opinion the ends of justice may be defeated owing to the difficulty of obtaining the necessary evidence from witnesses in open court, it shall be within the power of a District Justice, or, on appeal, of a Circuit Court Judge to order the exclusion of all persons not being members or officers of the Court or parties to the application, their counsel or solicitors, the necessary witnesses and a female relative or friend of the applicant, and the <i>bona fide</i> representatives of a newspaper or news agency from the hearing of any application under this Act.</P>
      <P>(6)  It shall not be lawful to print or publish or cause or procure to be printed or published any report, statement, commentary or other matter of or in relation to any judicial proceedings for the grant of an affiliation order save and except all or any of the following particulars of such proceedings, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  The names of the parties,</P>
      <P>(b)  the court in which and the Judge before whom the proceedings were tried and the names of the solicitors and counsel professionally engaged in the proceedings,</P>
      <P>(c)  a concise statement of the charges, defences and counter-charges in support of which evidence was given,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>(d)  particulars of any point <Col N="1021" /> of law raised and discussed in the proceedings and the decision of the Court thereon,</P>
    <P>(e)  the decision of the Court and the observations of the Judge when pronouncing his decision.</P>
    <P>Nothing in this section shall apply&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  to the printing of any pleading, transcript of evidence or other document for use in connection with any judicial proceedings, or the communication thereof to persons concerned in the proceedings, or</P>
    <P>(b)  to the printing and publishing of any order, notice or report in pursuance of the directions of the Court, or</P>
    <P>(c)  to the printing or publishing of any matter in any separate volume or part of any <i>bona fide</i> series of law reports which does not form part of any other publication and consists solely of reports of proceedings in courts of law, or in any publication of a technical character <i>bona fide</i> intended for circulation among members of the legal profession or medical profession.</P>
    <P>(7) (a)  If any person being the proprietor, editor or publisher of any book or periodical publication, or being a master printer engaged in the printing of such book or publication, prints or publishes or causes, procures or permits to be printed or published therein in contravention of any of the provisions of this section any matter, details or particulars in relation to any judical proceedings, such person shall be guilty of an offence under this section and shall be liable on summary conviction thereof to a fine not exceeding five hundred pounds or at the discretion of the court to imprisonment with or without hard labour for any term not exceeding six months or to both such fine and such imprisonment.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1022" /> (b)  Every prosecution for an offence under this section shall be brought at the suit and in the name of the Attorney-General.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>My amendment, only the first portion of which I will deal with now, is meant to give some amount of limited discretion to the judge who deals with the case.  I have listened with interest to the debates in this House on the subject, and I have studied the debates in the Dáil. They bring out, as far as I can see, only one point, and that is that it is only sentiment which justifies a departure from the accepted principles which we have used in our courts for some time, and that main point is that any person who has a serious charge brought against him is entitled to a public investigation.</P>
    <P>The main object of this Bill is to impose on the father of a child born out of wedlock the burden of its maintenance; and the secondary object is to relieve the public of the burden of maintenance.  But in Section 14 you see that the final responsibility still rests with the mother.  I think our natural desire is to ensure that the father and the mother join in maintaining their child, but in attempting to do so we must be very careful as a criticising assembly that we do not sanction sentimental legislation or create ill-considered precedents, possibly precedents which will be very far-reaching indeed.</P>
    <P>The main advantages which are claimed for hearing cases <i>in camera</i> here are that applications will be made by girls who would not otherwise face the open court, and on the other side, that the male defendants will be less open to blackmail.  The disadvantages are that the force of public opinion is absent and that the defendant is at the mercy, behind closed doors, of possibly a biassed justice or judge.  I have given every consideration to the views expressed by Senator Mrs. Wyse-Power in this House, and I have read very carefully the account of her work on the Commission for the Relief of the Sick Poor, but neither she nor any other speaker, in this or in the other <Col N="1023" /> House, has given us one single statistic in support of their contentions. Figures are an immense help in examining most arguments, and it is my experience that their absence implies, as a rule, that an argument is based on a few individual cases which have come to the knowledge of the person concerned.</P>
    <P>In this connection, I wonder if there is anybody in the House to-day who could give us the number of illegitimate births in the Saorstát in 1928 or 1929?  I ascertained that the figure for 1928 was 1,788, and that for 1929, which are not yet quite complete, amounted to 1,850. I think we are legislating for rather outside cases.  If there was only one type of case to be dealt with, the question whether it was to be <i>in camera</i> or not would be very simple, but the debates, both in this House and in the Dáil, have disclosed a very large number of different kinds of persons who will be involved.  On the female side, for instance, we have the innocent girl who has been wronged; the girl who is well aware of what she was doing, but who made a mistake; the older woman who is alarmed at the poor prospect of matrimony except by guile of some kind; the hopeless case, who has been referred to by the Commission on the Relief of the Sick Poor, the girl who had two or more children, of which there is a considerable number; the dangerous woman whom, it is suggested, will make a living out of affiliation orders; and the blackmailer.  On the male side, you have several cases.  You have the simple boy who is led away by sexual instincts and who is probably not as much to blame as the girl; the marauder, the man who goes from town to town and leaves his mark; the innocent victim of blackmail; and finally, the selected one out of several sinners, who is selected because he has a long purse and is the most likely to be able to pay.  All these cases are different, and that being so it seems to me that they should be differently treated.  If <Col N="1024" /> you combine some of these cases, it would be evident that the hearing <i>in camera</i> would be to the advantage of one party and to the disadvantage of the other, and very probably to the disadvantage of the public as well.  I suggest that no general rule can apply, and that a limited discretion in the terms of my amendment, which indicates the reasons why, should be left to the District Justice or the Circuit Judge.</P>
    <P>The laws on which the conduct of our courts of justice are based hold that the only occasions on which cases should be heard otherwise than in open court are when the public mind may be unnecessarily contaminated, or when it is reasonably clear that justice cannot be done except by hearing <i>in camera.</i>  Except to make it clear and prevent legal argument there is really no reason to mention this matter in the Bill.  I think when there is a very even balance of advantage and disadvantage in any problem the House should hesitate before committing itself to radical change in a procedure which has had centuries of practice behind it.  In the Dáil 119 Deputies voted on the amendment, but only 13 took part in the debate. I wonder whether all these votes were recorded after consideration of the working of the principles which brought, and which still maintain the justice of our courts at their present high level.  The majority for the clause on a free vote of the House was nine, and it seems to me that there might have been at least that number who did not give it the serious consideration which a question like this deserves.  I think moreover, that there was a certain lack of moral responsibility on the part of the Executive itself, evidently against the advice of the Minister for Justice, in leaving a question of this nature to an open vote, because it is one that affects the well-being of the people under the Constitution for which they are responsible.  Finally I think the House will recollect that it was Eve that originally made Adam pluck the apple from the tree. <Col N="1025" /> I think it is the old Adam you have before you to-day and it is the old Eve who accuses him and I think the House should at any rate give him the benefit of accepted principles.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 3, sub-section (5).  To delete the sub-section and to substitute the following new sub-section therefor:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(5) On the hearing of any case under this Act in the District Court or on appeal in the Circuit Court, the Judge shall order the exclusion from the Court of all persons other than the parties, their Counsel or solicitors, the mother or other female relative or friend of the applicant, the officers of the Court, the witnesses in the case and any bona fide representatives of a newspaper or news agency.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I wish to make it clear to the House that the amendment which stands in my name is No. 8 on the Order Paper.  My name was in the original draft, but the printers evidently were so much impressed by <i>in camera</i> that they thought I wanted to move it <i>in camera</i> and my name was removed. Perhaps I can explain my amendment best by telling the House how I came to put it down.  I was very much impressed, particularly by the speech of Senator Mrs. Wyse-Power, with reference to the difficulty of persuading girls who were believed to have a perfectly good case, but who were unable to support the illegitimate child, to go into open court, and although I have a good deal of sympathy with some of the arguments used by Senator The McGillycuddy I cannot help feeling that a strong case has been made, by persons who have studied the question, against having more persons in the court than are absolutely necessary.  In this House I think we are without exception strongly in favour of the principle of the Bill, and that the Bill itself meets with general approval.  We are equally desirous to see that as <Col N="1026" /> far as it can possibly be assured, where there is a genuine and clear case, a maintenance order will be made, and that the girl will get what we might roughly call justice.  We are equally anxious, as far as it can be prevented, that there shall not be blackmail.  I think we also want a situation, as far as it can be achieved, that there shall be a fair measure of uniformity in dealing with cases of this kind.</P>
    <P>Since this Bill came before the House first, I have had conversation with a number of persons accustomed to the practice of the courts&mdash; judges, barristers and others, and I found an absolutely uniform opinion that if you are going to get justice and general uniformity, you must have an open court as far as the Press is concerned, that if you leave it, as has been suggested by Senator The McGillycuddy, to the judges, you will find one judge will almost always hear cases <i>in camera</i> without the Press, while another judge will nearly always admit the Press. We are not now discussing the second part of the amendment, but that argument possibly applies even stronger there.  The amendment provides definitely that the Press may be present, and that they may report cases within the limits provided under the Censorship Act, but it provides that no one else other than persons connected with the case, and the mother or other female friend, shall be present.  That means, for the sake of argument, that if a board of guardians want to get a girl to apply for an order, if the case is <i>in camera</i> they will be in the position of assuring her that no one outside those actually connected with the case, and her own friends, will be present.  Under the amendment of Senator The McGillycuddy, that might be the case, but there would not be a definite assurance.  In a nutshell, my amendment provides for the presence of the Press, because I believe it is necessary to justice, but it also provides that no busybody or mischievous person, or persons who might be there purely for curiosity, <Col N="1027" /> should be present when cases of the kind are heard.  I have, somewhat reluctantly, come definitely to the conclusion that while I would prefer Senator Farren's amendment to the Bill as it stands, nevertheless I am not prepared to support complete and absolute secrecy.  I would much prefer it to the Bill as it stands or as it came from the Dáil, as I believe it would be much more workable.  I would prefer the amendment of Senator The McGillycuddy to that of Senator Farren for the reasons stated, but I prefer my own to either, because I think mine assures a secret court, a court in which it would be much easier for the girl to appear.  It also provides the necessary publicity which I honestly believe is desirable if you are to have uniformity and equal justice for both the girl and the man, who may virtually be the accused in these cases.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We will now take Senator Comyn's amendment.  The Senator, while leaving the sub-section as amended in the Committee Stage stand, wishes to add an addendum to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment 12:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 3, sub-section (5).  To add at the end of the sub-section the words:&mdash;&ldquo;But this sub-section shall not be construed as excluding from the District Court or, on appeal, from the Circuit Court any persons being members or officers of the Court or parties to the case, their Counsel or solicitors, or persons otherwise directly concerned in the case.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As you, sir, have pointed out to the Seanad the amendments in my name accept the decision already arrived at by the Seanad.  The three sets of amendments proposed by Senator The McGillycuddy, Senator Douglas and Senator Farren propose to reverse that decision.  If I were to decide as between the three sets <Col N="1028" /> of amendments I would certainly be in favour of the amendments proposed on behalf of Senator Farren. Speaking for myself, I would say that Senator Farren's amendments, which appear as No. 9 on the Order Paper, are very carefully drawn and probably meet the case, but I still prefer the amendments that are in my own name.</P>
    <P>Like all lawyers, I have a prejudice in favour of the open court. The practice has been to insist on the open court in all cases except where the higher interests of justice require that the court should not be open.  There are already in our law two examples of that: matters relating to persons who might be temporarily deranged in mind.  These matters are heard and decided in private, because it is considered not desirable to expose the infirmities of people who may, and frequently do, recover from their illness.  There are many cases in which officers administering that very important branch of the law find themselves in social relations&mdash;sometimes at a bridge party&mdash;with people who may have been at some other time under their care. Now it is highly desirable, from the public point of view, that proceedings of that nature should be heard <i>in camera</i> and so they are.  There is another class of litigation which is also held in private.  It is litigation relating to the fortunes of wards of court.  That is to prevent the fortune-hunter from finding out how much a young girl has.  These matters are always heard in private, and for a sufficient public purpose.  Now so far as I know these are the only two matters of a civil kind that are discussed in private.</P>
    <P>When this Bill came before the Seanad I was in favour of the open court, because in my experience I did not find that many girls were deterred from giving evidence in seduction actions brought by their fathers.  Perhaps I may have been wrong in that, but I must say that I changed my mind on hearing what Senator O'Farrell had to say on the question of publicity in these particular cases.  I was thinking of the <Col N="1029" /> position of the girl, but I think it was Senator O'Farrell or Senator Farren who suggested the case of the man.  Suppose there is a man against whom an affiliation order is sought and suppose an order is made against him, because of the fact that the order is published he may lose his employment and may not be able to pay the money awarded against him.  That, I think, is a very serious consideration.  I would say that this new law&mdash;because it is a new law providing that a father shall make provision for his illegitimate child&mdash; comes into the same category as the other two classes of litigation that I have spoken about, and that the ends of justice would best be served by having as little publicity as possible.</P>
    <P>Senator The McGillycuddy said, and also Senator Douglas, that it was highly desirable that the Press should be admitted.  Now we all know that the Press is conducted by gentlemen of the highest honour and of great discretion, but sometimes it happens that cases of this kind are reported in country districts without any regard for any other consideration except the circulation of the local little paper.  We had an example of that some four or five months ago in the South of Ireland where the entire details of a case of this character were fully reported in one newspaper.  The newspaper was, of course, bought up.  There was not a copy of it to be had for love or money.  It was a great success from the point of view of the circulation of the particular little periodical, but certainly it was not a success from the public point of view.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Senator say how much the proprietor of it was fined?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very glad to know that the Minister considers that the fine was adequate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse-Power Mrs. Wyse-Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse-Power</NameTxt>
      <P>The harm was done, and what good was the fine then?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1030" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The harm was done, as Senator Mrs. Wyse-Power says.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>It certainly did not pay him.  He lost very, very heavily over it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>He may have lost very heavily, but the prospect of losing heavily did not prevent him from being guilty of the offence and the same thing may apply again.  I do not say that it would apply in the case of journals of wide circulation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>It was the first case under the Censorship of Publications Act.  The case could not be dealt with except under that Act, and there has been no case since.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The feeling of the Seanad was that for the protection of the girl and the protection of the man these cases should be heard <i>in camera.</i>  Now if they are to be held in secret, so far as the actual hearing in the court is concerned, is it not absurd that once the hearing is over the whole thing may be published broadcast through the country, not merely to the 20 or 30 people who may come into court to hear what is going on, but to all the people with libidinous minds who may be inclined to read and gloat over reports of this character.  I think, therefore, that the amendment proposed by Senator The McGillycuddy ought not to be accepted by the House.  I would also ask the House not to accept the amendment proposed by Senator Douglas, and for the reason that it provides for the admission of the Press.  Senator Douglas's amendment&mdash;No.8 on the Order Paper&mdash;down to the last line of it is, I think, unobjectionable. The words in the last line are: &ldquo;Any <i>bona fide</i> representatives of a newspaper, or news agency.&rdquo;  That last clause in my judgment is one to which the Seanad ought not to give its approval.  A <i>bona fide</i> representative of a newspaper or of a news agency has no concern whatever with the paltry details of an affiliation order by a poor servant <Col N="1031" /> girl or a person of that class against a man in the same walk of life. Therefore, I think that as the amendments of Senator Douglas have to be taken as a whole that they ought not to be accepted, because really this particular clause would be closing the window and opening the door. The section of the Bill as it stands is: &ldquo;That all applications to the District Court and all cases under this Act shall be held <i>in camera.</i>&rdquo; That is how it stands as a result of Senator O'Farrell's amendment. What I proposed to do was to define as clearly as I can what <i>in camera</i> means, and it is not my own invention.  It is what I have culled from various sections of Acts of Parliament passed in other countries, and is defined in the amendment.  I think my amendment is a fair explanation to give of the words <i>in camera.</i>  I merely repeat them, as they speak for themselves. As I have already occupied too much of your time I will only just ask you to pass your judgment on them, but I would submit that what we have already done should stand, that is, on Senator O'Farrell's amendment we voted and we left the section as I have read it to you and we ought to abide by that decision. I am bound to say that in one respect Senator Farren's amendment is superior to mine because it provides for publication in the official law reports, but I think we will be able to get over that difficulty and there will be no necessity for legislation on that particular point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>May I ask what is the particular section of the Bill we are debating?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>In Committee we altered sub-section (5) to read in this way: &ldquo;All applications to the District Court and all cases under this Act shall be heard <i>in camera.</i>&rdquo; That is how it stands now.  There are three amendments to delete that and to substitute other words.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I have had a great deal of difficulty in making up my mind as to how one ought to approach these amendments, and I <Col N="1032" /> am sure a number of members of this House had a similar difficulty.  I would, therefore, like to say how I have made up my mind and made my choice between these amendments. The cardinal difference between the four amendments is whether you are to admit the members of the Press or not on the hearing of a case.  The first thing that any of us who has to make up his or her mind on this question has to ask is: Ought the Press to be admitted on hearing, even though the rest of the attendance in court is strictly limited?  Now, that is really the main question we have to discuss, and when we have made up our minds on the question of the exclusion or non-exclusion of the Press we have solved the difficulty.  Senator O'Farrell's amendment definitely and admittedly excludes the Press. Then we would have to choose be tween the amendments by Senator Douglas and Senator The McGillycuddy of the Reeks.  Senator Douglas's amendment is one that admits the Press without any limitation or restriction as to what they can publish, except under the restrictions of the Censorship Act. The amendment of Senator The McGillycuddy of the Reeks is one that leaves it in the discretion of the judge.  The main question, therefore, is, are we going to have a court in which a limited number of persons only are to be admitted but from which the Press is to be excluded?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Comyn has stated that he as a lawyer has a prejudice in favour of an open court.  Every lawyer has, I think, more than a prejudice in favour of an open court.  It is a principle with lawyers that there ought to be an open court, and the only excuse for not having an open court is that in some particular cases there are arguments sufficiently weighty to induce legislation to provide that there should not be an open court.  The case that is made against an open court under this Bill is that if you have an open court you will prevent the mother very often from facing the ordeal of an open court, and we must all recognise that to <Col N="1033" /> some extent at least, and probably to a very considerable extent in some cases, it would prevent a modest girl from taking advantage of this legislation, but the real objection is not to the Press itself but to the busybody and the gossip amongst the people amongst whom she lives.  The real objection is that if you exclude that kind of public from the court and admit the Press you will still have, as far as you can possibly have, the advantage of the open court, for the Press is there and everything is done as it ought to be done and will be reported.  You will have the Press there, and all the protection that a mother making an application in cases of this kind requires. I have made up my mind on the amendments.  I would be strongly in favour of the amendment by Senator Douglas which admits the Press, subject only to whatever limitations are put upon them by the censorship law.  My objection to Senator The McGillycuddy's amendment is that it leaves it to the judge to say whether a case is absolutely to be heard <i>in camera</i>, or whether the Press is to be there or not, for you will have one judge deciding one way and another judge another way, and there is nothing worse in the administration of law than want of uniformity.  I will, therefor, vote against all the amendments except Senator Douglas's.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse-Power Mrs. Wyse-Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse-Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I was following very closely the remarks made by Senator Brown with regard to the question of the Press being there.  What does the Press there mean?  Does it mean that the Press have a right to publish or does it mean that the Press is limited in any way by the power of the judge?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Mrs. Wyse-Power's point is that if Senator Douglas's amendment is passed what will be the result of allowing the representatives of the Press to be present?  The result would be absolutely free publication subject only to the censorship regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We have further amendments which will limit the power of the Press.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1034" />
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>If they are adopted. If the House so desires, this can be added.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There are further amendments which seek to curtail the power of the Press.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse-Power Mrs. Wyse-Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse-Power</NameTxt>
      <P>I am against the Press, because the whole feeling underlying this hearing <i>in camera</i> is that a girl would be induced to give her evidence in open court without people looking and gaping at her and that she would know her evidence would not be reported in the local papers.  Speaking of the girl, one must also speak of the man, and I think for the sake of the man as well as for the sake of the girl there should not be publication. If you let the Press in you are running a great risk.  When Abraham Lincoln began life, he wrote a paper on this very question, and he wound up by saying: &ldquo;There never was a woman went astray but there was a man to help her.&rdquo;  We ought to think of that in our contentions over the Bill; we ought to think of the two sides of the question.  When Senator Farren suggested that it should be made clear that the man's name would not be published, I was quite in favour of it because I think it would be very unfair, if it was decided that the girl's name should not be published, that the man should not have the same advantage, although I think he is the greatest sinner.  For those reasons I could not vote for Senator Douglas's amendment. The MacGillycuddy referred to the proportion of second and third cases.  That has been very seriously thought out, but the number of first cases is so much in excess of anything else that it is really the first cases we ought to consider and not the second and third.  If the Senator excludes the second and third cases perhaps I would be with him. The first cases are really the ones under consideration, and if the Senator thinks the second and third cases should be treated differently, perhaps I am with him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1035" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>It appears to me that Senator Comyn has made a case for my amendment.  There seems to be considerable doubt, even amongst the members of the legal profession, with regard to the exact meaning of the words <i>in camera.</i>  Accordingly, we have submitted an amendment which clarifies the whole matter. The House has decided on the principle that cases under this section shall be heard <i>in camera.</i>  We go further and we define what we mean by <i>in camera.</i>  We take out the words <i>in camera</i> altogether and we substitute something that will be easily understood by everybody; we indicate that certain people named in the amendment will be permitted to attend the court.  We do propose that the Press be excluded, because we think there is no sense in admitting them once we have decided that the case shall be heard <i>in camera.</i> Otherwise the position would be that busybodies who had come to listen to the details of these unfortunate cases would be excluded from the court, but the whole countryside would be informed through the reporters who would be present. There is no sense in the House agreeing to have these particular cases heard <i>in camera</i> if the Press reporters are permitted to be present and if the proceedings are published.  No doubt the details of these cases will not be published, but we do know that sufficient of the details can be published for the whole countryside to know all the circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>As Senator Comyn has stated, I remarked on a previous occasion that in justice to all concerned there ought not to be publicity of any kind from the point of view of the girl and from the point of view of the man, but more particularly from the point of view of the illegitimate child, in whose interest the whole Bill is introduced.  As Senator Comyn has said, I already have made the point that if these proceedings are made public and an order has been obtained against the man and that man is in a small way of business or is a working man, it is quite probable that he will clear out <Col N="1036" /> of the neighbourhood.  I do not say that he would be driven out with stones, but there was a time when he would be.  Anyway, he will not be able to earn a livelihood in the locality and he will not be in a position to meet the order made against him.  That is the whole point in regard to publication.  Under all the circumstances there is no necessity for the Press to be present.  I do not understand Senator Douglas's point of view, and I do not see the benefit that is to be gained by his suggestion. If the man is imprisoned by order of the court, that would be well known without publication in the papers.  I assume what Senator Douglas has in mind is if the man's character is clear.  It may be argued that in many cases it makes little difference whether or not there is publication, because there are people in this country who strongly hold the view that there is seldom smoke without fire.  We have put forward a particular amendment and, in view of the House agreeing to the principle that these cases should be heard <i>in camera</i>, we hold that our amendment meets the situation.  I think the Seanad ought to accept the amendment.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I have felt very great difficulty indeed as to what should be our attitude on this question. During the last two or three weeks I had the privilege of discussing this matter with an eminent lawyer, and I have been impressed with the practical unanimity and&mdash;I think that somebody spoke of uniformity&mdash;with the uniformity of legal opinion in favour of an open court.  I am not easily moved from the view that the principle which has been generally accepted and practised for many generations has something very valuable behind it.  It has been suggested to me on high authority that Article 64 of our Constitution might well make this proposal invalid.  That article states that judicial power in the Irish Free State shall be exercised and justice administered in the public courts.  I am not going to express any view as to what that implies.  But it has <Col N="1037" /> been raised as a matter of serious doubt.  I put it that supposing 20 or 30 cases had been tried <i>in camera</i> and that the 21st case or the 31st case was such that it was brought into the Supreme Court for a decision as to whether this provision was <i>ultra vires</i>, and suppose it did turn out that the decision was that the Constitution prohibited <i>camera</i> proceedings, what would be the effect upon the women in the particular cases that had already been decided?  It seems to me that that is a risk that those concerned with the protection of women ought to be a little slow to take, if there is a risk in that matter, because the decided cases would probably be of no effect in aid of the women; the orders made would have no validity, and quite probably some of the cases would have to be retried in public.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>They could not be in the circumstances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I will leave out the question as to whether they could be re-tried in public.  I am not putting that forward with any strong confidence because it is a matter of doubt as to the legal interpretation of the Constitution.  I am, as I said, strongly impressed with the almost unanimous responsible legal view that it is desirable as a matter of legal principle to have cases of this kind tried in public court.  I think it is not primarily for the benefit of the plaintiff or the defendant, the prosecutor or the prosecuted, but I think it is very important from the point of view of the judge that he should feel that there is a public criticism directed to his actions.  If the judge can go on from year to year trying this kind of case with the knowledge that whatever he decides is not to be made public; that there is no public opinion, not even legal opinion directed towards him, it is bad for the administration of justice. When I say legal opinion I mean lawyer's criticism which undoubtedly must have its effect upon the action of the judges in the courts.  Under such conditions of closed courts <Col N="1038" /> there is sure to be some fault and some public damage done.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to point out that the amendment we are dealing with arranges for some form of closed courts and the Senator is assuming something different.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am just coming to that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is not in order to deal with the public courts when they are not in the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am going to argue that the court would not be a closed court if there were representatives of the press present.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It would not be a public court at all if any people were excluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I dissent from your view in that.  I think it would be a public court if the press were allowed to be present by law.  I have every desire to meet the case made by those in favour of <i>camera</i> proceedings.  I think that Senator Douglas's proposal <i>plus</i> the provision regarding the limitation of reports of such cases to the barest details, such as are stated in Senator The McGillycuddy's amendment, or some such thing would meet the case that has been made.  That is to say, it would be possible to assure the woman concerned that she can give evidence without any fear of large numbers of people being present, and she can be assured that details of any case that have been made are not going to be set forth in the public Press.  I think you will have substantial justice and consideration for the woman concerned, while maintaining the principle of the public court which is established under the Constitution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>I have already expressed very strongly in this House, and very strongly in the Dáil, my views upon the general proposition as to whether there should be a hearing of this class of case in open court or <i>in camera.</i>  I <Col N="1039" /> have expressed my views strongly and I do not now propose to put again to the Seanad the arguments which I put before you on a very recent occasion.  But to me, strongly as I am against the exclusion from the court of any person and strongly convinced as I am that if the court were open to everybody it would not prevent one single action being brought; convinced as I am of that, I recognise now that the Seanad has decided that there would be some restriction upon the public entering the court, and turning my attention to those various amendments which are before the Seanad, I would venture to suggest that the Seanad would do what Senator Johnson suggested a moment ago&mdash;that they might substitute the amendment of Senator Douglas for the first paragraph of the amendment of Senator The McGillycuddy.  I think that if that were done it would go a very long way indeed, if it did not go the complete way, to satisfy the great protagonist of secrecy, Senator Mrs. Wyse-Power.  As far as Senator Farren's amendment is concerned, I do not see any substantial difference between it and the amendment down under the name of Senator Comyn's beyond this, that Senator Farren's amendment allows one thing that Senator Comyn's amendment does not allow.  It would allow the girl who is the plaintiff in the case to have her mother or some woman friend with her.  Senator Comyn's amendment would not allow that, and therefore it appears to be the substantial difference between the two of them.  Senator Farren also says that there might be reports in the law papers.  It has been alluded to already.  There might be a <i>bona fide</i> report in the law papers, but under this amendment there could not be, because if you could not have reporters there could be no report.  These cases are heard and there would be no law reporters there.  Quite possibly counsel or solicitors would send in reports to the &ldquo;Law Journal&rdquo; or the &ldquo;Law Times.&rdquo;  That, however, is never done.  Reports are in fact <Col N="1040" /> made by reporters who are not themselves barristers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>What about the reports in existence?  Senator Farren's amendment provides for the publication for professional purposes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>A report to be quoted in the court must be a particular kind of report.  A report made by an ordinary newspaper would be of no value, because a report, to be quoted, must be a report by a trained barrister.  An ordinary newspaper report will not be quoted as an authority.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>This amendment can be modified on report so as to allow the official reporters to present such a report, as is done in nullity cases, which are also heard <i>in camera.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichardWilson" hpid="Mr. Wilson Mr. Wilson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Wilson</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no official reporter in the District Court.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>There would be decisions, and a decision in the District Court or Circuit Court might be reported.  I agree with the Senator that they seldom are reported, and that really goes to show that it is not of very much importance. I will tell the Senator, however, what does happen.  A considerable number of cases will come up, and there will be the question of corroboration of the girl's story.  It will be very helpful&mdash;that is what precedents are for&mdash;when one District Justice knows what another District Justice has decided.  It would be very helpful to know what is the meaning given to the word &ldquo;corroboration.&rdquo;  He will see that in the newspaper report, although it may not be binding on him or quoted to him as an authority.  He will know that such a case came before the Circuit Judge or the District Justice, and that it was decided in a particular way.  All the light of public criticism that ought to beat on the judicial bench cannot beat if you do not allow the Press to be present. I would ask the Seanad, although this does not go as far as I would personally like, to accept the amendment of Senator Douglas <Col N="1041" /> when it is amalgamated with that of Senator The McGillycuddy.  I heard an argument put forward to-day against publication in the interests of the defendant.  If that were driven to its logical conclusion you would have every single court in the country sitting <i>in camera.</i>  A man might lose his position if a decree were made against him in this class of case.  Suppose a decree were made against a business man, not in a very large way, say, in a running down case for two or three thousand pounds.  A report in such a case might do a terrific amount of harm.  It might drive him into bankruptcy.  You would have his creditors coming down on him like a ton of bricks.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no parallel.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>An absolute parallel.  It might do a considerable amount of harm if a verdict for any amount was given against him and published.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>A legal verdict is different to a moral verdict.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>If you would not allow any proceedings to be published, your argument would apply as well to all criminal proceedings.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse-Power Mrs. Wyse-Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse-Power</NameTxt>
      <P>It would not apply.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>The arguments you put forward that it would damage the defendant would apply just as much to criminal cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse-Power Mrs. Wyse-Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse-Power</NameTxt>
      <P>They are two different cases.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>To clear up any misapprehension there may be in the minds of Senators with regard to the term &ldquo;official reporter,&rdquo; I should explain that when I say &ldquo;official reporter&rdquo; I mean the reporter who is appointed by the Bar Council or whoever is responsible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1042" /> I do not know the body who is responsible but in a certain class of cases, if the legal profession or the Bar thinks it necessary, a barrister is appointed to report these particular cases.  I say that the term in my amendment &ldquo;officer of the court&rdquo; refers to that particular individual.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be in order to withdraw my amendment in favour of Senator Farren's?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I will put the original question that the sub-section stands, that is, that all cases be heard <i>in camera.</i>  If that is beaten then your amendment is beaten.  You cannot move your amendment in that event because there would be no section to which that would be added.  If the original motion which I will put is carried then all your amendments go.  If the original is not carried I will put Senator Farren's amendment which excludes the Press.  If that is defeated then we will go to Senator The McGillycuddy's amendment, which is permissive for the judge,, and if that is defeated I will put Senator Douglas's amendment which compels the judge.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the matter goes to a division I should like to state that I did not deal with the second part of Senator The McGillycuddy's amendment, because at that time it was not before the House.  As it has been dealt with by a number of speakers I would like to say, as far as I am concerned, that I am strongly in favour of adding the second part of his amendment to the one which I have moved, should it be carried.  I am just as much opposed as Senator Mrs. Wyse-Power to mischievous details being published in any newspaper, in so far as it is possible to prevent it.  I would point out to the Seanad that the second portion of Senator The McGillycuddy's amendment allows the names of the parties the court. <Col N="1043" /> the judge, the name of the counsel acting professionally in the matter, a concise statement of the charges, defence, and countercharges, any point of law, and the actual decision of the court to be published.  The real issue, to my mind, is this: If that is added to my amendment there will be, admittedly, no details published, but there will be the effectual publication of the facts.  I believe that complete secrecy without publication of any kind, and very little means of knowing what each judge has done, will not lead to uniformity and justice in these cases.  I believe that the minimum amount of publicity is necessary to uniformity and justice generally.</P>
      <P>I do not want to say anything that could in any circumstances be regarded as a reflection on the justices who tried the cases, but I do believe that there are some who, if acting <i>in camera,</i> would have a tendency almost always to acquit a man because their sympathies are in that direction. There are others possibly who would act in the opposite way, and public knowledge of the actual decision should be there if you are really going to get justice.  Senator Mrs. Wyse-Power dealt with my amendment in a very friendly way.  I feel that the issue is small, but it is important. According to her speech, she is not prepared to have even the smallest details published.  That is clear.  She is opposed to that because she thinks it might prevent girls coming forward, and it might create a difficulty for them.  I believe that the small amount of difficulty that would be created, if only the essential points were published, is nothing like as important as the great danger of injustice which would occur if you had complete secrecy all over the country in every case.  I honestly believe, from the point of view of the girl, leaving out the man for the moment, that she would have far more to lose by that secrecy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1044" />
    <Speaker pid="JanePower" hpid="Mrs. Wyse-Power Mrs. Wyse-Power">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Wyse-Power</NameTxt>
      <P>Leave the man in.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I will first put to the House the question that sub-section (5), which proposes that all applications under this Act should be heard <i>in camera</i>, stand part of the section.  If that is carried no amendment that has been proposed will be permissible except the amendment of Senator Comyn, which proposes to make an addition.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That sub-section (5) stand part of the section&rdquo;&mdash;put and negatived.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I will now put Senator Farren's amendment, and, if it passes, the amendments of Senators The McGillycuddy and Douglas go.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>Are we to understand that we are only dealing with paragraph 5?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>And we may vote for that and vote against the latter part of the section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>It is clear that in voting for that you are definitely voting against Senator The McGillycuddy's amendment or mine.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  If you decide in favour of this amendment the amendments of Senator The McGillycuddy and Senator Douglas go.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>What was troubling my mind was that I did not notice at first that this excludes the Press.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HonJameson" hpid="Mr. Jameson Mr. Jameson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Jameson</NameTxt>
      <P>If we vote for this amendment we are voting for not allowing the Press to be present?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>That is so.</P>
      <P>Amendment put.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1045" />
      <Col N="1046" /> The Committee divided: Tá, 19; Níl, 24.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Miss Kathleen Browne.<br />Caitlín Bean Uí Chléirigh.<br />Michael Comyn, K.C.<br />Joseph Connolly.<br />Mrs. Costello.<br />William Cummins.<br />J.C. Dowdall.<br />Michael Duffy.<br />Sir Thomas Grattan Esmonde.<br />Thomas Farren.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Henry S. Guinness.<br />Major-General Sir William Hickie.<br />Seán E. MacEllin.<br />Colonel Moore.<br />Joseph O'Doherty.<br />John T. O'Farrell.<br />L. O'Neill.<br />Siobhán Bean an Phaoraigh.<br />Séumas Robinson.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">John Bagwell.<br />William Barrington.<br />Sir Edward Coey Bigger.<br />Samuel L. Brown, K.C.<br />Alfred Byrne.<br />John C. Counihan.<br />The Countess of Desart.<br />James G. Douglas.<br />Michael Fanning.<br />Sir John Purser Griffith.<br />P. J. Hooper.<br />Right Hon. Andrew Jameson.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Thomas Johnson.<br />Cornelius Kennedy.<br />The McGillycuddy of the Reeks.<br />James MacKean.<br />John MacLoughlin.<br />Seán Milroy.<br />William John Molloy.<br />James Moran.<br />Joseph O'Connor.<br />M. F. O'Hanlon.<br />Thomas Toal.<br />Richard Wilson.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I will now put the amendment of Senator The McGillycuddy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to withdraw the first portion of my amendment in favour of Senator Douglas's amendment.</P>
      <P>Portion of amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I now put the following amendment accordingly:&mdash;</P>
      <P>Section 3, sub-section (5).  To delete the sub-section and to substitute the following new sub-section therefor:&mdash;</P>
      <P>&ldquo;(5) On the hearing of any case under this Act in the District Court or on appeal in the Circuit Court, the judge shall order the exclusion from the court of all persons other than the parties, their counsel or solicitors, the mother or other female relative or friend of the applicant, the officers of the court, the witnesses in the case and any <i>bona fide</i> representatives of a newspaper or news agency.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>We now come to the portion of the Bill dealing with the question of publication, and I would ask Senator The McGillycuddy to move as an amendment sub-sections (6) and (7) of amendment 7.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="McGillycuddyReeks" hpid="The McGillycuddy of the Reeks The McGillycuddy of the Reeks">
      <NameTxt>The McGillycuddy of the Reeks</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(6) It shall not be lawful to print or publish or cause or procure to be printed or published any report, statement, commentary or other matter of or in relation to any judicial proceedings for the grant of an affiliation order save and except all or any of the following particulars of such proceedings, that is to say:&mdash;</P>
      <P>(a)  the names of the parties,</P>
      <P>(b)  the court in which and the judge before whom the proceedings were tried and the names of the solicitors and counsel professionally engaged in the proceedings,</P>
      <P>(c)  a concise statement of the charges, defences and counter-charges in support of which evidence was given,</P>
      <P>(d)  particulars of any point of law raised and discussed in the proceedings and the decision of the court thereon,</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1047" /> (e)  the decision of the court and the observations of the judge when pronouncing his decision.</P>
    <P>Nothing in this section shall apply&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a)  to the printing of any pleading, transcript of evidence or other document for use in connection with any judicial proceedings, or the communication thereof to persons concerned in the proceedings, or</P>
    <P>(b)  to the printing or publishing of any order, notice or report in pursuance of the directions of the Court, or</P>
    <P>(c)  to the printing or publishing of any matter in any separate volume or part of any <i>bona fide</i> series of law reports which does not form part of any other publication and consists solely of reports of proceedings in courts of law, or in any publication of a technical character <i>bona fide</i> intended for circulation among members of the legal profession or medical profession.</P>
    <P>(7.) (a)  If any person being the proprietor, editor or publisher of any book or periodical publication, or being a master printer engaged in the printing of such book or publication, prints or publishes or causes, procures or permits to be printed or published therein in contravention of any of the provisions of this section any matter, details or particulars in relation to any judicial proceedings, such person shall be guilty of an offence under this section and shall be liable on summary conviction thereof to a fine not exceeding five hundred pounds or at the discretion of the court to imprisonment with or without hard labour for any term not exceeding six months or to both such fine and such imprisonment.</P>
    <P>(b)  Every prosecution for an <Col N="1048" /> offence under this section shall be brought at the suit and in the name of the Attorney-General.</P>
    <P>Sub-section (6) is similar to a section in the Censorship of Publications Act of which the House has already approved.  I think there must be some publicity in the interests of the public.  For instance, there may be in future some delicate-minded parents who would prefer that their daughter should not contract matrimony with a man who has been burdened with one or more affiliation orders.  Again, there will be people who would not care to welcome such a grandchild into the family, but without some publication these people have no means of finding this out.  Then there will be occasions when an ill-founded rumour will be circulated with regard to some individual.  It should be possible for parents to have a search made through their solicitor and no difficulty should be made in the circumstances. With regard to the publication of the proceedings in limited form, it cannot be of assistance to the judge.  Counsel up to now have been able to look up the whole of our law in order to argue their cases and without precedents I think that the legal profession will find themselves at a considerable disadvantage. Therefore, I think, a section such as this is essential to the Bill.  With regard to sub-section (7), it is similar to one in the Censorship of Publications Act and it is only necessary in order to ensure obedience to the law.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to explain that the amendment which we have just passed permits the Press to attend the hearing of a case.  The effect of the two amendments now moved by Senator The McGillycuddy is that the Press will only be allowed a limited form of publication.  That ought to be distinctly understood.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>And the penalty is attached.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be possible to put these amendments separately, <Col N="1049" /> because there may be Senators in favour of this limited publication provided for in sub-section (6)?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Sub-section (7) provides the penalty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Sub-section (7) provides the penalty by way of a fine, and it also provides, in paragraph (b) that &ldquo;Every prosecution for an offence under this section shall be brought at the suit and in the name of the Attorney-General.&rdquo;  Some of us might be in favour of sub-section (6), but we might not be in favour of limiting sub-section (7) in the way it is limited there.  I suggest therefore, that they be put separately.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>Sub-section (6) and sub-section (7) presumably will be put separately, as they are separate sub-sections, but I should like to suggest to Senator Comyn that he should not vote against sub-section (7), which provides the penalty, because of his objection to the Attorney-General, in view of the fact that on the Report Stage next week he can propose to alter or exclude that. It would be a great pity to lose the effective penalty, as otherwise, I think, this would be of very little use.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="WilliamBarrington" hpid="Mr. Barrington Mr. Barrington">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Barrington</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Minister whether this amendment as now drafted falls in with his views expressed a few moments ago.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>The suggestion had been made already by Senator Johnson, and I followed out that suggestion, that these two amendments of Senator Douglas and Senator The McGillycuddy should be joined together, paragraph 5 being taken out of Senator Douglas's and the other one from Senator The McGillycuddy's.  It is a compromise on the whole business, but possibly in this sort of question a compromise works out the wisest in the long run.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Would Senator <Col N="1050" /> Farren wish to argue his amendment?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>It would not apply to this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I might withdraw mine now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Farren's amendment excludes the Press completely.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is quite a different matter, and I shall allow Senator Farren to move his amendment if he so desires.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasFarren" hpid="Mr. Farren Mr. Farren">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Farren</NameTxt>
      <P>There is no sense in moving it now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall now put sub-section (6) of Senator The McGillycuddy's amendment.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall now allow a discussion on sub-section (7).</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>This particular amendment provides that if a newspaper contravenes the provisions of the Act the proprietor and publisher shall be liable to prosecution and it provides a fine of £500 or imprisonment. It also provides that no person shall be competent to take any proceedings against the newspaper except the Attorney-General.  I would much prefer that the rights of the parties were left to the ordinary law.  Under the ordinary law it would be competent for a person who has been injured to sue for criminal libel whether what was published were true or false.  I think I am right in that.  It would also be competent for a person under the ordinary law to bring a civil action in case a report was unfair, and it would be also open to him to bring an action for an injunction.  If these three remedies of the ordinary individual are to be taken away&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>They are not taken away.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1051" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to know from the Minister whether the penalty here is an exclusive remedy or not.  If it is an exclusive remedy I certainly shall vote against the amendment; if it is only an additional remedy I have not much to say one way or the other except this: that I would be opposed to limiting the rights to the Attorney-General. I think the right of proceeding for a penalty ought to be given both to the Attorney-General and to the person injured.  If it is open to me on Report Stage, as Senator Douglas has suggested, to bring in an amendment if necessary to delete this paragraph (b) I shall do so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to say that it is not arguable that this sub-section, which provides a penalty and a prosecution in the name of the Attorney-General, takes away anything. It does not take away the civil remedy against a newspaper, it only gives an additional penalty.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>Does it take away the criminal remedy against the newspaper which the individual has?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>It undoubtedly does not&mdash;not even the criminal remedy in the shape of criminal prosecution for criminal libel.  So far as the Attorney-General being the proper person and the only person to prosecute, that is all entirely in favour of the person who is protected against this kind of wrongful publication. Poor people cannot go to the expense of such a prosecution. The Attorney-General is the proper person to prosecute at the expense of the country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelComynKC" hpid="Mr. Comyn Mr. Comyn">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Comyn</NameTxt>
      <P>The Attorney-General is not bound to bring the prosecution.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Comyn knows perfectly well that there never are prosecutions brought by anyone else except by the Attorney-General.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>Or by his leave.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesFitzgeraldKenne" hpid="Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Fitzgerald-Kenney</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, in his name.  I cannot see how having the <Col N="1052" /> Attorney-General in here does the slightest harm.  I think it is the proper thing to do.  I know that in all these cases of criminal libel it is necessary to get the fiat of the Attorney-General before you can go on.</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that practically covers all the amendments in the paper.  There is an amendment, No. 14, in the name of Senator Farren, but I think that he does not propose to move it.  I now put the section.</P>
      <P>Question&mdash;&ldquo;That Section 3, as amended, stand part of the Bill&rdquo;&mdash; put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Seanad went out of Committee.</P>
      <P>Section reported.</P>
      <P>Bill ordered for consideration on report, Wednesday, 14th May, 1930.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Shop Hours (Drapery Trades, Dublin" RHead="and Districts) Bill, 1930&mdash;Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Public Business. - Shop Hours (Drapery Trades, Dublin and Districts) Bill, 1930&mdash;Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Fourth Stage agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;&ldquo;That the Standing Orders be suspended for the purpose of enabling the remaining stage of the Shop Hours (Drapery Trades, Dublin and Districts) Bill, 1930, to be taken today.&rdquo;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SamuelBrownKC" hpid="Mr. Brown Mr. Brown">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brown</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second the motion.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDouglas" hpid="Mr. Douglas Mr. Douglas">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Douglas</NameTxt>
      <P>I move that the Bill do now pass.  The only thing I want to say is that a circular was sent to members of this House in regard to this Bill which was liable to be misleading. I do not think it misled any Senators, but it might mislead people outside.  The circular said that this Bill which was being extended was a Bill previously introduced by me and very much objected to.  That is not the case at all.  This Bill which <Col N="1053" /> is being extended is a Bill that was introduced in the Dáil and was the result of a considerable amount of compromise.  I only want to make that clear, because otherwise people might have been misled in regard to it.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Permanent" RHead="Court of International Justice">
    <Title>Public Business. - Permanent Court of International Justice.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:&mdash;</P>
      <P>That Seanad Eireann approves of the Declaration accepting as compulsory the jurisdiction of the Permanent Court of International Justice signed at Geneva on the 14th day of September, 1929, a copy of which was laid on the Table of the Seanad on the 26th day of February, 1930, and recommends the Executive Council to take the necessary steps for its ratification.</P>
      <P>I do not know that it is necessary for me to say anything to commend this motion for the acceptance of the Seanad.  The declaration accepting the jurisdiction of this Court was laid on the Table of the Seanad on last February.  The jurisdiction of that Court was accepted without reservation on behalf of Saorstát Eireann.  The whole matter was discussed in the other House of the Oireachtas at very considerable length.  A very full statement was made by the Minister and a similar motion to this was passed unanimously by the Dáil after a discussion. I believe that there is general agreement with the action taken on behalf of the Saorstát by the Minister. There is general endorsement of his action and I think that it is unnecessary therefore to enter upon any exhaustive argument in moving the adoption of this motion.  If there are any questions to be asked bearing on the matter the Minister is here to deal with them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasToal" hpid="Mr. Toal Mr. Toal">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Toal</NameTxt>
      <P>I beg to second the motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that it is right that the Minister and the <Col N="1054" /> Ministry should be congratulated on the action they took in signing this optional clause as it is called and signing it without reservation.  The act was an indication on the face of it that so far as this State is concerned we are prepared in all matters of a justiciable character to accept the rule of law and to submit the case in dispute to a court of arbitral justice.</P>
      <P>A statement was made in this House by the Minister in July last showing us that that was the policy that the Ministry intended to follow out and they have fulfilled that promise to the letter.  So far as the practical effect is concerned it has been made much less valuable by the refusal of the British Government and other governments of the British Commonwealth to accept the clause without reservation.  I think to conform fairly and in spirit to the Covenant of the League it would have been right and proper for all these States to have signed a clause without reservations of the kind that were stated and reciprocally.  The likelihood of dispute as between the Free State and nations outside the British Commonwealth is not very great.  There are possibilities of dispute between States so closely allied as those of the British Commonwealth and the fact that all but one have signed this clause with the reservation that they will not allow <i>ipso facto</i> without question disputes between these several States to go to the Court makes of little practical effect the signature of the Free State.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It would have seemed to me on the face of it that that paragraph of the reservation which excludes &ldquo;disputes in regard to which the parties to the dispute have agreed or shall agree to have recourse to some other method of peaceful settlement&rdquo; would have been entirely satisfactory and quite sufficient to make possible an agreement, as between the States of the British Commonwealth, to adopt some other method of settling disputes.  I think it would have been fairly easy to arrive at an agreement of that kind.  In addition to that reservation we have <Col N="1055" /> included &ldquo;disputes with the Government of any other member of the League which is a member of the British Commonwealth of Nations all of which disputes shall be settled in such manner as the parties have agreed or shall agree.&rdquo;  While that seems to be almost a repetition I think it has other implications which are unfortunate.  One cannot blind oneself to the fact that ever since 1924 when an objection was lodged by the British Government in the League to the registration by the League of the Anglo-Irish Treaty there has been a pretty persistent struggle between two ideas: one that inter Commonwealth questions are not subject to international decision and are not within the region of international law and that is was the intention to treat inter-Commonwealth matters as more or less domestic, the other idea being the tendency towards full recognition as international entities of the States of the British Commonwealth, at least those which are recognised by the League of Nations as capable of being members of that League and of entering into international covenants.</P>
    <P>One must take note of the tenacity with which the various British Governments of all colours cling to the imperialist conception of the position of Britain as related to the States which were once colonies, and any other unit of the King's dominions.  I note, for instance, in the White Paper which was circulated by the British Government on this matter a very interesting paragraph dealing with the Imperial Conference resolution of 1926 concerning the optional clause.  The paragraph reads: &ldquo;This new agreement among His Majesty's Governments concerning the vital question of international arbitration marks a further step in the acceptance of common principles for the conduct of foreign policy.&rdquo;  It may be very desirable that there should be agreement amongst as many States as possible; in fact all, if possible, on principles which guide foreign policy.  This is an evidence of the <Col N="1056" /> persistence and almost, I say, in some respects the success of the British policy to bring these Commonwealth questions into unity.  That is to say, there may be equality of status among the States of the British Commonwealth in relation to each other, but when dealing with non-British States it is something different. The question of equality of status does not arise.  That has not yet been fully recognised and the tendency seems to be to make it as difficult as possible to have that recognised.</P>
    <P>I am not forgetting the statement of Mr. Henderson at Geneva on the occasion of the signing of this clause.  He said:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;Disputes with other members of the British Commonwealth of Nations are excluded because members of the British Commonwealth, though international units individually in the fullest sense of the term, are united by their common allegiance to the Crown.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>In that parenthetical way he said &ldquo;though international units individually in the fullest sense of the term.&rdquo;  That, though valuable in so far as it goes, is not of so very much importance as compared with his reservation that the agreement should not apply as between States of the British Commonwealth.  I am anxious that the Irish Free State and other States of the British Commonwealth should press forward steadily to the point where international lawyers of other States will have no hesitation or question as to their status vis-a-vis other States not in the British Commonwealth, that they shall be recognised as international units by these other authorities in the fullest sense of the term.  I think a very long step in that direction would have been made if the British Government and the other States of the Commonwealth had signed this clause without this particular reservation.</P>
    <P>I am entirely at a loss to understand why it should have been put in, unless it were part of that pressure which is being steadily applied to prevent this international recognition <Col N="1057" /> in the fullest sense of the term which Mr. Henderson referred to. It is of note that a protagonist of the older British view in international legal affairs, Mr. Berridale Keith, very recently wrote on this question in these terms:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The motive, unquestionably, of this action (that is, of the Irish Free State Government) was to establish the independence of the Free State within the League.  But after all that freedom had not been denied in essentials, and it was negatived by the action of the other Dominions and the United Kingdom as regards one point of importance to the State, the desire to have relations with the United Kingdom put on the basis of international law.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That desire, in his view, was negatived by this reservation signed by all the other States of the British Commonwealth.  He goes on:&mdash;</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The doctrine that disputes between members of the Empire are not within the province of the Court as a matter of international law was, however, apparently opposed by the Union of South Africa, which agreed to the actual reservation on the score of expediency, but it is satisfactory that no change has taken place in the views of the British Government.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I am afraid there is too much truth in that last statement, and whatever general view may be taken regarding international relations that there is persistence in the older imperialist view that States of the British Commonwealth, notwithstanding the equality of status promulgated, are still within the orbit, so far as foreign relations are concerned, of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland.</P>
    <P>While I have no evidence at all on the matter, I have no doubt that before the Minister on behalf of the Free State signed the optional clause without reservation, that there was a considerable amount of discussion and a considerable amount of argument directed to showing him how <Col N="1058" /> unnecessary and undesirable it was that such a sign of difference between the Free State view and the British view, the Canadian and the South African view, should be exhibited, and, imagining the strength of that pressure, I think his action is doubly commendable and he deserves the hearty congratulation of this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Minister for External Affairs (Mr. McGilligan) Patrick McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for External Affairs (Mr. McGilligan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I desire to reply to Senator Johnson on one or two points.  I have very little to dispute as regards what the Senator has said, particularly in regard to the details. I would frame any objection I have merely in this way, that I would not like to have it understood when he speaks of the persistence of the older imperialistic view that because the British do give evidence of persistence in that point of view that it is accepted.  It is quite right that there is a school which dislikes intensely all the movements that have taken place since the war in regard to the independence of the Dominions.  I think the signature to the optional clause, although the Senator is quite right in saying that it is of less value than if the British had not made Reservation I, and had signed unreservedly, nevertheless, has marked a step forward, because, remember, if it had to be considered at any time that there was an Irish Free State point of view, and an older British point of view, the odds, on material considerations, would be rather in favour of the British point of view. But South Africa has as strong a national viewpoint as we ourselves have, and the Dominion of Canada, although its origins are different, in the position in which it now is, has as strong a national point of view and as independent a point of view as we have, and we must take that point of view into consideration in regard to the signing of the optional clause.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I count as a gain that from that discussion at Geneva we got, first of all, the declaration from the British Foreign Secretary that members of the Commonwealth were &ldquo;international <Col N="1059" /> units individually in the fullest sense of the term,&rdquo; and further we get these two statements, one from Canada and one from South Africa.  The South African delegates expressed themselves in this way:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;With regard to the reservation as to disputes between members of the British Commonwealth of Nations, I wish to state that, although in the view of my Government such disputes are justiciable by the International Court of Justice, my Government prefers to settle them by other means&mdash;hence the reservation.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>That is a clear and distinct statement by the Government of South Africa, that disputes arising between the South African Government and the Government of Great Britain are regarded not as domestic quarrels but as international matters.  On that South Africa and ourselves have the same point of view, but the occasion of signing the optional clause was the first time that a declaration was made indicating that attitude on the part of South Africa, and I count it a gain, that it was made and made so explicitly.</P>
    <P>The representative of Canada made the following statement:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;The Dominion of Canada has excluded from the purview of the Court legal disputes with other members of the British Commonwealth for the sole reason that it is its expressed policy to settle these matters by some other methods....&rdquo;</P>
    <P>I want to pause at that.  That declaration was made just after the South African declaration; it was the last declaration made, and it was made after full consideration of what our attitude had been and expressed in public to be, and after the consideration of what South Africa had expressed as to their viewpoint.  They followed up the South African statement by saying that Canada excluded certain matters &ldquo;for the sole reason that it <Col N="1060" /> is its expressed policy to settle these matters by some other methods.&rdquo; If the Seanad will refer back to the context and go into the whole circumstances of last September it will be quite clear that that Canadian declaration has to have read into it the exact words of the South African Government, and hence equally clearly that they regard disputes as between the Dominion of Canada and the Government of Great Britain as justiciable by the International Court of Justice.  They made the reservation regarding certain disputes for the sole reason that they preferred to settle them by some other means.</P>
    <P>The Dominion of Canada went on to make a further point:&mdash;</P>
    <P>and it has deemed opportune to include its will as a reservation, although a doubt may exist as to such reservation being consistent with Article 36 of the Statute of the Court.</P>
    <P>The last phrase throws doubt upon the whole reservation, a reservation which I thought at the time, being so advised at the time, and which I now consider, having been more recently and more deliberately advised, to be not merely out of accord with the spirit of the optional clause but to be illegal, to be definitely null and void.  As a valid reservation it may have to be tested, and if it does come to be tested its validity will be tested by the International Court itself.</P>
    <P>So too with regard to the White Paper, if the circumstances are taken into consideration I claim that it is in our favour.  The White Paper referred to by Senator Johnson was published on behalf of the British Government only.  It is a British Stationery Office paper.  It says: &ldquo;This new agreement among His Majesty's Governments concerning the vital question of international arbitration marks a further step in the acceptance of common principles for the conduct of foreign policy.&rdquo; Remember that this quotation is from the last page of a pamphlet which has gone through the whole circumstances of the optional clause and <Col N="1061" /> has referred to the fact that we signed without reservation and that the other two States made certain statements, and in the end it says &ldquo;This new agreement among His Majesty's Governments concerning the vital question of international arbitration marks a further step in the acceptance of common principles for the conduct of foreign policy.&rdquo; What is the agreement?  The agreement was this, and this only&mdash;that the optional clause should be signed. There was no agreement on the incidents of signature for we signed without reservation, and Canada and South Africa, while agreeing to the British reservation, refuted the principles on which the British based their reservation and accepted the reservation only on grounds of expediency and policy.  On one point was there common agreement, that the optional clause should be signed, in other words, we shared the view that there should not be recourse to war to settle disputes that seem to be capable of being settled by arbitration or by some judicial method.  And it is of no little importance and value that the British Government should come to that point.  If the British Government had not advanced so far the optional clause would not have received so many signatures as it did last year and as it has received since.  In so far as that White Paper has been brought in in evidence&mdash;and I am not sure I regard it as a good thing that it has been brought in evidence at all on this matter, because it indicates a tendency to accept evidence from what might be a biassed source&mdash;but in so far as it has been brought in it tells rather in my favour than against any of my contentions.  It says that there was agreement concerning the vital question of international arbitration, as there was&mdash;to the extent I have explained&mdash;and that this marked a further step in the acceptance of common principles for the conduct of foreign policy.  The common principle accepted is that there should not be a resort to war but a resort to the International Court.</P>
    <P>With regard to Prof. Berriedale <Col N="1062" /> Keith, I only hope that Professor Berriedale Keith will continue to write as he has written heretofore. He has a knack of finding out small points of procedure which have come down from antiquity, and it is a good thing to have these brought forward and exposed so that we can take the earliest opportunity of having them changed.  I think one of the best ways of finding what progress has been made in Dominion affairs is to take some of the older works of Prof. Berriedale Keith and some of his later editions and see how his theories and explanations have had to change, even despite his evident desire and his stubborn fight to keep alive the older imperialistic ideas.  It is to be hoped that Professor Berriedale Keith will continue to write and will unearth more relies, if there be any, on which Imperialists might rely to prove that the old Imperial system still continues.  Even our own research might fail to discover these, and it is better that they should be discovered so that we may take them up and have them harmonised with the new order of things.  The optional clause at the moment has either been signed and ratified or signed and some progress made towards ratification on the part of forty States out of fifty-four. There has been progress in this matter ever since I stated in the Dáil that 25 countries had definitely bound themselves to the optional clause.  We hope to be the next to be added to that list.</P>
    <P>The British Government's attitude to us as an international unit has been raised in this discussion. I am not at all sure that it can be properly related to the persistence of the old imperialistic ideas.  I think it might better be related to that portion of the reservation which envisages other methods being found for the settlement of disputes arising between members of the Commonwealth of Nations.  On that I spoke previously and in case there should be any doubt arising from my previous statement I would like to cover the <Col N="1063" /> point again.  Recognising a definite and special relationship between ourselves and the other States members of the Commonwealth, we would like to see established any means of securing the settlement of disputes between members of that Commonwealth of Nations rather than the method of war.  We would even accept something other than the Permanent Court, but we do believe that we are entitled to have the Permanent Court to fall back upon and as good members of the League we feel that we should be favourably disposed towards the Permanent Court unless and until some special circumstances establish a claim for some other tribunal.  We know nothing in practice of the details of that Court, who the judges would be, what law they will administer, or what legal conventions they will follow when decisions are being taken, and it may be that in an actual trial before that Court we may regret the step which we have taken.  But at the moment there is a case for the Permanent Court, though as between the States of the Commonwealth something other than the Permanent International Court may be found acceptable.  If there are suggested any other methods of resolving disputes as between ourselves and the other members of the British Commonwealth of Nations, and if we believe that these other methods will give us an impartial tribunal we will not hesitate to consider the suggestions and try out that other tribunal, but we believe that the Permanent Court should be there in the last resort. In the meantime, until such other tribunal is approved by us, we stand by the Permanent Court.</P>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>Has this motion been accepted by the Dáil?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMcGilligan" hpid="Mr. McGilligan Mr. McGilligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGilligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="HenryGuinness2" hpid="Mr. Guinness Mr. Guinness">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Guinness</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to congratulate the Minister on his last words, that before going to the Permanent Court the Irish Free State <Col N="1064" /> is prepared to negotiate its differences with the parties with whom it may have differences.</P>
      <P>Motion put and declared carried.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - Civil Service (Transferred Officers)" RHead="Compensation (Amendment) Bill, 1930&mdash;Second Stage">
    <Title>Public Business. - Civil Service (Transferred Officers) Compensation (Amendment) Bill, 1930&mdash;Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MauriceMoore" hpid="Colonel Moore Colonel Moore">
      <NameTxt>Colonel Moore</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like the Minister for Finance to tell us how this Bill affects us and whether the sums of money that will be paid by us will be refunded to us by the British or not.  I do not understand how the matter stands.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasJohnson" hpid="Mr. Johnson Mr. Johnson">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Johnson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like the Minister to tell us what this means. There are technical terms in it, and on the face of it it means nothing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ErnestBlythe" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. Blythe) Ernest Blythe">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. Blythe)</NameTxt>
      <P>It means, in fact, very little.  The position is that in regard to the cases that came before the Civil Service Compensation Tribunal the date fixed for retirement had to be not more than four months after the passage of the original Act. That meant that the court had to fix the date of retirement at not later than the 17th April.  The court found itself unable to dispose of about twenty of the cases before that date.  The result would be that if we did not amend the legislation the court could not deal with these cases at all.  This merely extends the period for two months in order to enable the court to dispose of this small number of cases.  It gives no additional right to any civil servant and it does not admit anybody who did not claim before.  It merely extends the time in which we thought it would be possible for the court to complete its work.  The court has gone on hearing cases since the 17th April but it has not been able to come to decisions.  When this Bill has been passed it will be able to do so.  The point which Senator Colonel Moore raised was explained when the Principal Act was going <Col N="1065" /> through, namely, that any extra payment that arises as a result of the Principal Act is refunded by the British Government.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, May 14th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Public Business. - The" RHead="Marketing of Butter">
    <Title>Public Business. - The Marketing of Butter.</Title>
    <P>The following motion stood on the Paper in the name of Senator O'Hanlon:&mdash;</P>
    <P>That it is expedient that a Tribunal be established for inquiring into a definite matter of urgent public importance, that is to say:</P>
    <P>(1)  the marketing of butter produced in Saorstát Eireann during the five years ended 31st December, 1929, with special reference to the effect of combined marketing on the demand for and price of butter produced in cooperative creameries, and</P>
    <P>(2)  the method of marketing butter in future which would conduce most effectively to increase the demand for butter produced in Saorstát Eireann and the price obtainable for such butter relative to the prices obtainable for other butters, without adding unduly to the cost of marketing.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. Dowdall Mr. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very important motion on which I would like to say something.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have an amendment handed in by you, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. Dowdall Mr. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it would be far more satisfactory if the Minister were here to explain to the House&mdash;he need not explain it to me &mdash;the important and the importance of this motion.  I have consulted Senator O'Hanlon, who does not see his way to accept the amendment which I put down, but I think if the Minister were here he would accept it.  Under these circumstances I ask that this matter be deferred until our next meeting.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1066" />
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Your amendment came in rather late.  I am afraid that the Tribunals of Inquiry Act, 1929, would seem to require an identical resolution in both Houses.  I am not quite sure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. Dowdall Mr. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that, but the importance of the amendment is such that a very trivial alteration would be necessary, and it would be very well worth the trouble of the Minister to move in the Dáil that the motion be rescinded and to move another motion with my amendment incorporated.  It would involve no expense and no appreciable time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is the wish of the House I will adjourn this matter for the attendance of the Minister.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelOHanlon" hpid="Mr. O'Hanlon Mr. O'Hanlon">
      <NameTxt>Mr. O'Hanlon</NameTxt>
      <P>If it is the wish of the House I will not oppose the adjournment, but after all this motion comes before the House as a matter of public importance, and it is scarcely fair to have it adjourned now.  If Senator Dowdall feels that if the Minister for Agriculture were present he would be inclined to accept the amendment which I am not inclined to accept and would oppose, if he feels that he is labouring under any difficulty I would not take advantage of the position created by the Minister's absence.  It is only on that ground that I would be prepared to have consideration of the matter adjourned.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="Cathaoirleach Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think I could accept the amendment now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDowdall" hpid="Mr. Dowdall Mr. Dowdall">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dowdall</NameTxt>
      <P>I think if the Minister for Agriculture were here he would accept my amendment.  I really speak with an extensive and peculiar knowledge of the subject, because I have experience of these matters.  I think it would be worth while, if this tribunal is to be effective, that the amendment I suggest should be incorporated in the motion.  Under these circumstances I would ask that the sense of the House be taken.  The adjournment <Col N="1067" /> would be only for a week.  This is not such an urgently important matter that it could not be deferred for a week.  If deferring the matter would secure a very much better report, and very much better results, I think it would be well worth while doing so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanMilroy" hpid="Mr. Milroy Mr. Milroy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Milroy</NameTxt>
      <P>The position of most Senators is that they do not know <Col N="1068" /> what is contained in Senator Dowdall's amendment, and therefore they are not in a position to say whether it is of sufficient importance to warrant a postponement or not. I presume if the motion is postponed the amendment will appear on the Order Paper for the next meeting.</P>
      <P>Adjournment agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 6 p.m. until Wednesday, May 14th.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>