<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="27" Month="Jun" Year="1974" Vol="78" No="9" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 27 Meitheamh 1974" DateEnglish="Thursday, 27 June 1974" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="635">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="635" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1 and 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance (Taxation of Profits of Certain Mines) Bill," RHead="1974 (Certified Money Bill): Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Finance (Taxation of Profits of Certain Mines) Bill, 1974    (Certified Money Bill)  : Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>As I indicated when speaking on this Bill last night, I welcome it as a limited measure in that it does repeal the tax exemption for profits arising from the mining of the scheduled materials which had been granted by the Income Tax Act, 1967.  However I was arguing that it is only a very limited measure and does not at all indicate the radical new approach which I would argue is imperative if we are to benefit from the natural resources which we find in this country.</P>
      <P>It is important if we are to cope with the extraordinary and quite different new problems which challenge this country and other countries both in Western Europe and the world. Last night I said that the balance of power in the world has changed as a result of what was called the energy crisis and as a result of the steep rise in oil prices with the consequent serious balance of payments problem for countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That particular problem is not unrelated to this subject of mining and mineral wealth in this country, because precisely the same situation can and, to some extent, is occurring in relation to exploitation of mineral wealth.  Developing countries with <Col N="636" /> mineral resources are beginning to adopt a similar attitude to the OPEC countries&mdash;the oil-producing countries. I believe that this will continue and that they will adopt a similar attitude.  They will say: &ldquo;We want much higher prices for our materials; we want to nationalise&rdquo;&mdash;this is happening to a very large degree&mdash;&ldquo;we want to control the degree to which our resources are being exploited; we want to process and benefit substantially from our own resources.&rdquo;</P>
    <P>The result will be that a shortage of base metals will become more acute and the need for alternative development will become still more critical. We, in Ireland, are in danger of not being equipped to cope with our own situation or to benefit to the greatest degree that we can from the mineral wealth which is in our country, so that we can use it in a positive way to cope with the vast problems of the balance of payments deficits which we will be meeting as a result of the increased oil prices.  We must cope with the tensions and the distress generated by galloping double-figure inflation in this country. This measure does not show even an indication of a governmental awareness of the degree to which we must harness the resources we have to meet a radically changed situation.  Therefore I should like to see more indication that the Government are trying to adjust to these new circumstances.</P>
    <P>As I said last night, the Minister in his opening speech talked about an inter-departmental committee set up in 1971.  I re-affirm here that this is not at all a sufficient basis on which to introduce either this legislation or any such legislation in 1974.  We must re-examine the whole situation of our natural resources in the light of the last three months, six months, and the last year, with a knowledge of how much the situation has changed and what a very different problem will face us over the next three to five years.  We must do it by making available the expert information which we need and the technological experience and the backup which we can now demand because we have the resources of which the world is becoming critically scarce.  For that reason I do not agree either with the intimidation in the Minister's <Col N="637" /> speech or in the speeches of some other Senators that we are a small country and that we do not have the capability or the potential to develop our own resources.</P>
    <P>We now have sufficient leverage to call a very substantial tune in this area. The Government can argue for and develop a governmental participation in the assessment and exploitation of our natural resources and their processing, and formulate an overall policy of the extent to which and at what speed we develop our mineral resources.  We must be aware that these are a wasting asset.  We must know, not only in relation to this country but in global terms, what the asset is and to what degree it ought to be conserved or exploited.  We would be extremely foolish not to have a radically different and accelerated approach to this problem.</P>
    <P>I should like therefore to put to the Minister some rather more specific questions in this area.  I appreciate that this Bill is to tax profits arising out of mining.  The Minister may not wish, or may not be in a position to answer the questions either because they do not relate to his specific area of responsibility or because they have not been examined at a sufficiently developed stage at governmental level. I would put it to the Minister that if they have not been examined they should be in the forefront of Cabinet thinking and that he, as a very senior member of the Cabinet, ought to be in a position to give an indication of the degree to which the Government are aware of and are equipped to cope with both the radical new dimension of problems and the completely new position in which we find ourselves in relation to both the energy crisis and the exploitation of natural resources.</P>
    <P>The more specific questions I should like to put to the Minister are, first of all, to what extent is this Bill a limited first step in relation to mining and the development of mineral wealth in the country?  To what extent will it be followed by much more radical and substantial measures which are part of a Government intent and strategy to participate in and to have a substantial control over <Col N="638" /> the exploitation of mineral wealth and its processing?</P>
    <P>Secondly, to what extent is this Bill a first step in a realistic appraisal of the extent of the mineral resources in the country and of the necessity to have a coherent policy which takes into account the radically changed and still evolving circumstances?  To what extent are we aware that what happens in some faraway developing country with similar resources which adopts a radical policy, affects the level and the value of our mineral resources?  To what extent are we flexible enough to introduce sufficient Government control of exploitation of our natural resources to allow us to adapt to this dimension of problem?</P>
    <P>More specifically, to what degree has the feasibility of Government participation in exploitation and processing of our mineral resources been examined in the new context of having sufficient leverage and of having the ability to demand that those multi-national companies who wish to exploit mineral resources in this country must do so in Irish terms with sufficient participation by the Irish Government?  This must be done in a way which will allow the Irish Government to have overall control of conservation of this wasting asset, and the degree to which it will be processed within this country with the spin-off benefits which that would have for the Irish people and with the capacity that would give us to cope with the very severe problems which we will face in relation to balance of payments, inflation and so on.</P>
    <P>In the light of Government policy in this area, to what extent have we already invited, or are we prepared to invite into our country the expertise in a technological and economic sense which will protect us from being used by multi-national companies?  These companies know very well how to compensate for their difficult experiences elsewhere by exploiting a small, perhaps insufficiently aware, country like Ireland.  Unless we have a global perspective in relation to our own mineral resources and unless we go <Col N="639" /> significantly further than the terms of this out-of-date measure in relation to the taxing of the mineral wealth of this country, we will be exploited.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>We welcome the present Bill because it changes the previous incentive of the 20-year tax exemption.  The 20-year incentive was necessary at the beginning but it was not necessary when the Tynagh mines were found to be so productive.  It is high time for the change to be made. I am pleased that the change was made after prolonged consultations and that the policies proposed here are in line with those operating elsewhere. We are, we hope, at the start of mineral development.  The Navan mines, with their tremendous possibilities, should be followed by similar discoveries in other places.  Therefore it is proper that the Government should be wholly involved and concerned with monitoring the development as it progresses.</P>
      <P>The present Bill does not offer any prospect of immediate tax return to the Exchequer.  That is understandable because we must allow for the expenses incurred in exploration before true profits can be computed.  Therefore the return to the country is in the long-term.  The figure of £125 million over some long period is a highly speculative one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>Peanuts.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>The return to the country will be much more in the creation of employment.  It is really the shin-off of the secondary effects that hold out the greatest hope in this area.  We hope the smelter project will become a viable one.  There are many areas which would be much more suitable than Cork harbour.  This type of industry should be located in a very remote area where it would not create a nuisance.  When this smelter project is reactivated again, I hope the Government and not the company concerned will call the tune.  We know smelter companies would like to set up in the most favourable location, irrespective of the consequences.  The Government should ensure that this does not happen.  They should have <Col N="640" /> a very definite zoning policy regarding the location of such potentially dangerous and dirty industries.</P>
      <P>I mentioned the great pay-off we expect from the high employment involved in the mining industry.  That is something which needs to be guided and developed.  On the one hand we must ensure that the environmental control is at the highest practicable level.  We do not want eyesores such as disfigure many other countries.  We want the Government to exercise real control over the activities of the companies in this regard.  This should be a continuing control and should have ever-increasing standards.  It is only now countries are becoming conscious of the environmental problem associated with many industries, but especially with mining.  Countries are putting increasing pressures on the mining companies.  Because mining companies are international companies they are exceedingly difficult to control.  We should not delude ourselves that we can control them better than others.  Other countries will succeed in the years ahead in compelling those mining companies to contribute towards the preservation of the environment.  That battle will be a continuing one.  We will be able to impose conditions on them in five years' time that we just could not attempt today.  In ten years' time I hope we will be able to impose still higher standards.  These should be the standards that more powerful countries have been able to impose on those national giants.</P>
      <P>With regard to the question of employment, we must learn as rapidly as we can from other countries.  People should be encouraged to be thrifty. Otherwise we may be faced with a position such as confronts parts of Norway at present, where wage-earners as a result of affluence squander their money at weekends on drink and so on.  When the assets are gone people would be in a worse condition than at the start.  There is a real educational problem.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We are fortunate in that we are only at the beginning of this.  We should make a real effort to ensure that what happened elsewhere is not repeated <Col N="641" /> here.  That applies not merely to mining industry but also to offshore gas and oil.  They will create the same problems of affluence for a small group who work very hard and put up with difficult conditions whether in mines or on rigs in the ocean.  People must be advised on how to cope with this problem for the benefit of their families and the community in which they live.  These are the real problems. The amount of the tax yield is insignificant compared with facing those problems in a proper way.  We must succeed in leaving our country better for having found these resources than we were without them.</P>
    <P>I wonder if more teeth could be put into the Bill to encourage continued exploration.  If we are going to create a mining group within the country people whose way of life is mining should be assured that their livelihood continues and that when one mine runs out others are coming into production. The only way to ensure that is by continued exploration.  While I know there is the permissive clause here that costs incurred against exploration can be written off against profits, I should like them to qualify for certain of the reliefs here&mdash;being able to allow past profits to be written off against profits. However, there should be some commitment that a certain percentage of the profits in any one year have to be put into exploration in that year.  In other words, we want to avoid the company deciding that they would just mine out what they wish and then leave the country after that.  Would it be possible to introduce an amendment to that effect, or would the Minister have any idea how we might put the pressure on to ensure that exploration is a continuing process for those who are operating the existing mines?</P>
    <P>We should also need to expand very rapidly our own geological services and corresponding departments in our universities and technical colleges so as to ensure that we were not relying merely on these companies for advice and for knowledge as to where the most likely further finds would be or indeed for the evaluation of anything that might be found.  We should at this stage have a commitment to <Col N="642" /> developing our resources.  We should be prepared to expand, as rapidly as we can get technical staff, into creating independent centres of geological and mineral exploration, acting either through the universities or through the various State offices co-ordinated in some way.  We should strengthen considerably our own efforts and potential in this field.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill as far as it goes. I realise fully the difficulties that face a small country in trying to grapple with and control these international giants and I only hope that in the years ahead our control will move step by step with the control we see other and more powerful nations being able to impose on those companies especially in the field of environment and in the field of community and labour development.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AlexisFitzgerald" hpid="Mr. Alexis FitzGerald Mr. Alexis FitzGerald">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Alexis FitzGerald</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to speak at excessive length this morning on what is obviously a subject of very great importance.  I had some doubt as to whether I should speak at all because, though of a different nature to his, I would have to make a like declaration of interest to that made by Senator Russell last evening, in that my professional firm advise the chief company whose happy, fruitful discovery has led to this legislation to combat the evils that are thought to flow from their happy, fruitful discovery.  I thought about this because it is right that we should declare an interest.  I am sure that my colleagues in the Seanad will know that it does not at all affect the views I express, which would not be the views of that company.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have had no discussions relative to what I want to say here today.  It did not seem to me that merely because my firm took instructions from this company I should be forever silenced from making a contribution to a matter which had interested me long before I received the instructions from them.  Indeed I should say with regard to that that I acted for a very large number of the firms which engaged in prospecting work in this country including one in particular which incurred considerable <Col N="643" /> expenditure long before even the first tax holiday was introduced in 1956.  Some knowledge of the subject should not silence me. Perhaps it will become clear that what I say really relates to the generality of the situation and I hardly refer to the detail of the matter with regard to any interested party.  Should I do so, it would be merely incidental.</P>
    <P>I understand the problems the Government were faced with in reaching the decisions enshrined in this Bill, From most of the contributions which have been made I gather that, if there is a public criticism, it is on the whole, a criticism that this legislation, which withdraws a tax holiday and introduces a new set of allowances, does not go far enough in the withdrawal but goes too far in the allowances proposed to be made.  My view is completely different.  It is possible that the Government, as a pragmatic matter in producing legislation which would allay public feeling with regard to this, had little option but to introduce legislation of this kind.  If I had been a member of the Government I could not have persuaded myself that I was entitled to withdraw a concession on the footing of which very large sums of money had been invested by many people, a great majority of whom were resident in Ireland.  I could not have persuaded myself that it was right to withdraw a concession in so far as that withdrawal would affect existing companies which had outlayed their moneys on the understanding and had made their calculations on the basis that a particular type of legislation would be there for the benefit of the companies who were raising the money.</P>
    <P>However, I can see why people could reach a different conclusion. For instance, there was the outcry, based on the idea that a group of people, a foreign company, were sitting on scarce exhaustible Irish resources which they could take away for their own personal advantage. Public enlightenment was such with regard to this that I do not think we could have begun to have a rational discussion on this matter until we got that particular thing out of the way. <Col N="644" /> Why have the Government introduced this legislation?  Why were the committee established in 1971 to consider the possible changes in tax as well as in relation to royalties?  Why has this all happened?  It is possible to say, although there is a degree of hindsight of course involved in this, that the concessions made in 1967 were excessively generous.  A concession, incidentally, was being sought and I believe was being required when the concession of 1967 was made.  In other words, the four-year tax holiday followed by the second four-year period of the 1956 legislation was not, in fact, fully satisfying the interested parties.</P>
    <P>The reason for all of this is a complete failure to grasp the problems involved in relation to this.  It is funny that we are debating this issue.  There has been a Departmental committee. I know that the rubrics of it do not require the Department or the Government to publish their report, but it would be such a help to us all if we knew, for example, whether everybody agreed with the recommendations. What was the other point of view?  What degree of information did these people have?  On foot of what set of facts did they reach their decision? Was the statement of the facts disputable or not?  Do we all agree with it?  It would be useful to know if the Government at the end of the day reached a decision on foot of an argument which was satisfying to us who are outside the Government as well as to those in the Cabinet who had the duty to do what they have done.  I think that is unfortunate.</P>
    <P>To go back, I think that probably one must expect that there is a general feeling that the concessions given in 1967 were over-generous.  This has led to a consideration within the Department with regard to this.  I wonder how much real study has been made by the Departments concerned regarding the whole question of mineral resources, the whole question of the relationship&mdash;forget about Ireland for the moment&mdash;of modern industrial developments to the availability of resources.  How much examination have they made of the whole structure of the business of starting off with <Col N="645" /> the discovery and then the development of that discovery?  There seems to be an assumption that we go over to a tap in the corner, turn it on and take a glass of water; that that is our water and why should we let somebody else come in here, walk over to the tap, turn it on and take a glass of water.</P>
    <P>It is not as simple as that of course. There is no doubt that the whole situation would be utterly outrageous that we should be allowing foreigners&mdash; let us assume for a moment that this was an entirely foreign company; this is disputable and I think inexact in relation to the beneficial ownership of the shares anyhow&mdash;let us assume, which is not true, that the companies here were multi-national corporations and were coming in here with their great resources and just running away with what we have.  That is not true either.  In fact, no multi-national has been involved in the discoveries.  If I am correct I think four relatively small companies have been making these discoveries. These are Northgate, Tara, Silver-mines and Avoca.  To go back to my simile of the glass of water, the mining position is not quite like that.  It is much more like the situation of somebody in a desert who is extremely anxious to find water and there happens to be a well somewhere which, with the expenditure of very scarce resources available to the people in the desert, can be discovered by somebody with pertinacity and the flair and determination to take all the risks and on the basis that he and his family are going to get a good chunk of the water in the well if they do actually get it but with the risk that they will expire in the process.</P>
    <P>There is no mine actually existing in an economically significant sense until it is discovered.  It is assumed that it is all there and that everybody knows all about it and that there are, say, seven people down in the Geological Survey Office who, if they only took time off, would discover all the resources everywhere and then it would be a simple question of the Minister for Finance going over to London and getting the necessary cash.  This is not the situation.  We <Col N="646" /> shall be in serious trouble unless as a country we learn to face facts and to examine the clichés that are thrown at us and to remember that things said often enough do not become true by the fact of their being said often enough.</P>
    <P>The public are pushing the Government towards a kind of legislation, towards a kind of policy which is wrong, based upon a misconception of reality.  We as public men have a very serious duty to inform the public so that they understand what they are talking about.  There are vast areas of the world which are still unexplored.  Let us forget for a moment about the club of Rome.  Let us assume that they are wrong and that the whole world can sail along in its present kind of conduct, that on this matter the socialists and capitalists agree.  It would be very interesting for the Seanad to engage in a debate as to whether we should not all be wearing hairshirts or whatever you wear when you are cutting back and whether we should not all be giving an example to the world of the kind of life that men will have to live when we use up all these resources, but that would not be right for this particular debate.  Let us assume that the world wishes to continue to do what it is doing at the moment.  If it is to be able to continue to do what it is doing at the moment it will have to make enormous discoveries of new resources all over the world.</P>
    <P>At this point in time there are vast areas of the world unexplored, and from the national point of view as distinct from an international point of view.  There are people here who are very concerned about the underdeveloped areas, as I hope I am myself. We are going to help them by making discoveries, although in the short term it may have a bad effect on the Zambian metal prices.  However, in the long term the more discoveries that are made the more help we are going to be able to give to the world.  If that is so we must encourage people to go about the business of discovery.</P>
    <P>A mine is not there until it is discovered. It is no good, for example having a factory on the Aran Islands <Col N="647" /> producing marvellous things to satisfy everyone in the world if these goods cannot reach the mainland.  They are only there when they are obtainable. A mine is not discovered without great difficulty.  It is not discovered without great risk or without great cost.  We must recognise that these operations are costly and risky and that few people are prepared to pursue them.  We must frame our policy in this light and get rid of this curious blockage, which is partly anti-foreign, partly anti-landlord&mdash;this curious syndrome in which there is an element of envy, an ordinary natural envy, this feeling that these people have got a wonderful thing which we all could have got.</P>
    <P>These people have discovered for Ireland a marvellous thing which without their discovery would not be in Ireland in the economic sense of being in Ireland because it is only in Ireland when it is known to be there. I am not a geologist and I have no idea of geological time but let us call it geological time&mdash;ages and ages.  It might have been lying there for another set of ages.</P>
    <P>On that particular point it is perhaps worth knowing that one of the very big international companies had a licence to explore this particular area and gave it up.  Then these people took their prospecting licence, went on and made their discovery.  It is impossible to talk about mining in Ireland at the moment without referring to this very great mine.</P>
    <P>Could we look at some actual facts with regard to the cost of discovery. In the Canadian Mining Journal of April, 1973 Cranston and Martin worked out that in terms of cost and dollars, we can forget about inflation, every discovery in the period 1946 to 1950 cost $2 million.  This is the average cost of what must be spent before a discovery is made.  In the 1966-1970 period that cost had increased to $15 million.  This is one of the side effects of technology.</P>
    <P>Technology has been referred to in this debate as if it now got rid of the necessity for the prospectual flair, the individual skill.  This is not true. <Col N="648" /> Technology has increased the range of ability to discover but it has also increased the cost of discovery.  These are facts worth considering and I should like to be assured that they were considered by the inter-departmental committee.  There are many sides to this argument and many countries to be surveyed which are at different stages of economic development, which have different social systems and different political traditions. If changes are taking place in one country, is it right to assume that these changes are in the right direction even for that country?  In 1971 the average cost of one Canadian ore discovery was $27 million.</P>
    <P>A calculation was made by the Australian mining industry, taking the period of ten years to 1971-72 and this again confirms the Canadian estimate where the Australian average, relating significant mineral discoveries to mineral exploration expenses, worked out at $20 million.  That does not guarantee a major discovery. There might be no Navan in that.  If there had not been a Navan we would not be having this debate.  We would still be wondering if we could further improve the holiday to get somebody to go around and continue to search. What about the prospects of success?</P>
    <P>The United States Government's strategic minerals development programme surveyed the period for 1939-49.  During that period there were 10,071 prospecting licences granted.  Of these 1,342 were worked and abandoned and one successful mine emerged.  The odds were 10,000 to one in the range covered by that particular case.  This is in relation to the grabbing of what is not there until it is discovered.</P>
    <P>In Canada a company called Caminco which has some interests here now had surveyed its own operations during a period of 42 years&mdash; 1927-1969.  One thousand properties were examined and 78 of these were found worthy of major exploration expense, that is, exploration expense of $100,000 a go, and seven of them became operable mines.  A prospector's financial ability to pursue the prospect must be looked at by the <Col N="649" /> Department before he is given the right to go ahead.  If one's expenditure does not result in producing something, all is lost.  It is completely at risk.  Hard work has been put into the project but there is no return. There are no second prizes.  There is no place money in this business.  You win or you lose.  If you lose you lose all.  Do those people who are arguing that the Irish people are being robbed of their resources state to the Minister that he should take millions of pounds from the taxpayer or that he should persuade some financier to give him millions for this operation, to engage in the risk involved in this type of exercise?  This kind of money is only available for this kind of operation in a free society to the people who can spare it for that kind of activity and who are prepared to take that risk.  Are we to take money from people who do not wish to engage in this kind of risk?  Are we to tax them down?  Are we to force their savings? This is the bit in the puzzle that none of the people against international capital will face up to.  Are we to replace international capital, talking generally, by a development dependent upon our own savings?  I should like to see any of you facing the hustings on that basis.  Are there to be compulsory savings?  That would mean a reduction in the standard of living.  It would mean a cutting back in the accelerating social programme that we are all so keen to further.</P>
    <P>Unless we can establish and develop our industry on the basis of a stable community, generating revenue, these programmes which the Government wish to maintain would have to be cut back.  We should look at what is the actual situation here.</P>
    <P>From 1956 there were 2,090 prospecting licences issued.  There were 90 companies involved.  As a result of that operation, there were three economic ore bodies and two marginal ones established.  Of these four are in production.  That is a rate per operation of .25 per cent.  From 1961 £38 million was spent to bring four companies into production.  To the most recent date I have seen £3,500,000 was paid to the shareholders.  The £38 <Col N="650" /> million had not been recouped in earnings.  That does not take into account the £6 million of totally abortive expenditure engaged by the various companies involved.</P>
    <P>There is a distinction which is generally made and one which the Minister and one of his colleagues have made also.  There seems to be an assumption that in some way mining at the end of the day leaves merely a hole in the ground whereas investment in industry other than mining is on a longer continuing basis, in other words that when one particular hole is exhausted that is the end of the mining industry.  There are a lot of holes in the ground in Canada but at this moment after 100 years of mining industry in Canada with all these holes left behind their exports of minerals is in the order of £2,000 million.  The assumption is that once a company has organised itself with suitable finance it will bale out.  Of course, its funds are committed for prospecting and exploration.</P>
    <P>There is something to be said, arising out of what Senator Quinlan said, for examining the kind of inducements we should offer to ensure that the moneys made out of mining activity go back into prospecting here because, of course, international companies will be free to prospect everywhere.  In fact, one hole in the ground leads to another; that is the history of the mining industry.  The funds become committed to this kind of activity; the people's minds run in this direction.  They are mining men; they are miners.  George Orwell called the miner a sort of grimy caryatid upon whose shoulders nearly everything that is not grimy is supported. I take that Orwellian sentence as a fairly sound proposition to account for the whole of modern industry. The miner's activities lie at the foundation of the whole of modern development.  Without these resources, because of the threat to their existence, because of the possibility of their scarcity, all modern development is cast into doubt as to how long a life it may have.</P>
    <P>These activities are of supreme importance to the whole world.  That is true whatever view you take of the <Col N="651" /> nature of the social organisation there ought to be.  They are in this thing; they like the business; it is risky but they are men who take these risks and, in fact, tend to go on doing so and have done so. This may sound surprising but the Canadian example is not a bad one. When resources in a particular area are used up the funds seek them elsewhere. What has happened in Ireland? This is proven already and arises by implication from what the Minister said in his opening speech in the Dáil. This happened in Ireland.  Tynagh mines is not yet a hole in the ground; it is on its way to becoming one, but in the course of the using up the Tynagh mines the very same people, admittedly with another company, went off and found Navan.  The very same people who found Navan may go off and find another mine and so on.  It is of enormous importance that the Government and the people engaged in public life should look at the realities and should rethink their whole view of the mining industry.  If we do not have a right view of it then we have no proper policy about it and we do not have right legislation.</P>
    <P>There is a feeling that it is a less worthy activity, less useful a contribution to the economy.  We can dispose of the hole-in-the-ground argument on the basis that one hole in the ground is replaced by a potential further hole in the ground by the people who found what was in the first and will find what is in the second hole.  When this discovery is made it has an enormously beneficial effect on the economy.  Look at the Canadian export figure of £2,000 million a year.  I am just taking a recent figure; I have not checked it. The figure here is £20 million at present.  That could be, and I hope will be very much more but there is a very low import content involved in making these exports which is not true of many exports.  The multiple effect of incomes generated in mining is notably high. The release of the economic forces made by mineral discoveries, I believe, can be seen to enable new countries to develop and stride forward into the circle of developed nations.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="652" /> Take the Canadian position.  It is an industry now 100 years old and it is worth knowing&mdash;I am not going to go into details but the Minister will probably concede&mdash;that the concessions in these new sets of allowances are not as good as even the existing set of Canadian allowances.  They are certainly not as good as the allowances which existed in Canada before the change and they are certainly not as good as those that existed before the tax holiday was introduced in 1956.</P>
    <P>During a period of favourable tax treatment in Canada a fine and considerable industry grew up.  As a consequence manufacturing industry has been established to supply the services needed by the mining industry, to take the profits of the mining industry.  It generates industry both in relation to what is leading into and what is to come out of the activity.  I think we must face the facts with regard to this.  It seems to be infinitely more important that we have a fine exploration programme going forward here. Getting that launched is much more important than the question of who is going to launch it, who is going to be the beneficiary of the discoveries which are made.  The community is the major beneficiary because the final income which remains behind is, in any case, insignificant in comparison with the overall benefits to the community in terms of employment, services and so on.</P>
    <P>In Canada there has developed also in the universities tremendous skills which are available for the industry and which are required by the industry. That kind of demand for professional skill, even for solicitors, is beneficial to those on whom the demand is made.  I would like to see the kind of sober assessment, which was difficult to make in the situation we had last year, being made of the benefits to the community of mining activities.</P>
    <P>In the course of his speech in the Dáil the Minister referred to the fiscal changes taking place in various countries.  I think this should be said so often that people would wish we would stop saying it in relation to all our industrial and commercial activities, <Col N="653" /> other than those where we had this export tax concession.  When they talk about nationalisation of this, that and the other thing they should really be brought back to the fact that the State is a partner as to 50 per cent in all commercial and industrial activities in the sense that&mdash;it may be a sleeping partner&mdash;it gets one half of the profits.  This seems to be a fairly good position to be in.  It is not going to be 50 per cent here with the adjustments to be made in the light of the concessions.</P>
    <P>There seemed to be a suggestion that we are making a move which all other wise countries, such as the Philippines, are making and that we are right in doing that but one of these sober countries is Canada. Another is Australia.  What has been the effect of the Australian fiscal changes?  Canada's situation is enormously different from ours.  It has established a vast mining industry which has had 100 years of favourable tax treatment during which it was built up.  But let us look at Australia. According to the statistics on mineral exploration published by the Board of Census in Australia, the money being spent on exploration in 1968-69 was 73 million dollars; in 1968/69 it was 118 million dollars; in 1970-71 it was 161 million dollars; in 1971-72 it was down to 117 million dollars; in 1972-73 it was down to 90 million dollars.  Its prospect for 1973-74 is 65 million dollars.  As a result of these brilliant tax changes the amount of money being spent on exploration in Australia, which is cited to us as an example to follow, has been reduced by 62 per cent.</P>
    <P>I am asking the House to assume that it is a good thing that money be spent on exploration, that it is a good thing to continue to be looking for resources that are urgently needed by modern industry if modern industry is to go on.  I ask you to forget about ecology for the moment.  There are other ways of dealing with that.</P>
    <P>We can assume that argument to have been completed.  In mid-1971&mdash; this, I gather, is one of the great tests of activity in this field&mdash;there were 280 diamond drilling rigs in Australia. <Col N="654" /> Two years later this had fallen to 100. Drilling contractors were seeking work overseas; the smaller exploring companies had disappeared and this is one of the features of the situation. They were all small men, men who had gathered together their pence from the Canadian Exchange and who were having a fling and hoping to God they would find something; none of them were &ldquo;big cheese&rdquo;.</P>
    <P>All these companies in Australia have disappeared because of the tax changes&mdash;it is no longer interesting for them.  Australian-trained drillers are moving overseas.  If it is as easy as all that for foreigners to come in to take our scarce resources, why are not we busy taking these somewhere else? Why do we not ring up a number and go off and pick up a zinc mine somewhere? Is it as easy as all that?  If it is, these extraordinarily selfish, cruel and avaricious capitalists of Ireland are blind, and dull as ditch water. What is the reason for it?  If they are foreigners with us, why are we not foreigners with them?</P>
    <P>I do not think it is as easy as all that.  There is a great deal of preparedness required, willingness to spend money and to pursue that money with hard work and a good deal of knowledge.  We are talking about the lifeline of the modern industrial world; discoveries make possible a reassessment of the degree of scarcity of these resources.  I am quite optimistic about this because of the extent to which exploration has not taken place over vast areas of the world.  That activity should be encouraged. If I were one of these fellows I would not be seen dead in Ireland at the moment, where the climate of opinion has forced the Government to do this kind of thing.  I do not think there is hostility from the Government or from the Revenue Commissioners. This has been forced upon them by an unenlightened public opinion, which is unfriendly and not welcoming.  Their line is: &ldquo;You find and we shall grab&rdquo;.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>It is always interesting to hear Senator FitzGerald even where he fails to put his own individual point of view.  It is certainly <Col N="655" /> stimulating and instructive to get lists of facts and figures and to be able to make some comparisons of our situation, in quantitative terms, with the situation in other countries.</P>
      <P>I would like to emphasise particularly one remark he made.  It is the fact that an advisory committee have been sitting for some time.  Presumably, they have given their report of deliberations to the Government.  We should be able to read this report; it should be made public and we should debate it in the Seanad.  Then we would know what is at the basis of Government thinking in drawing up legislation for our mining industry and for the whole of the oil and gas industry which we hope will develop around our shores.  We should be working towards the framing of some sort of overall policy.</P>
      <P>Certainly, the Bill that is before us now gives very little indication of an overall policy that the Government should be preparing and working on and to which we should be contributing. Most people agree that 20-year tax holiday was too generous in its original conception.  As Senator FitzGerald pointed out, this was drawn up in an era when the common belief of most Irish people was that we were a poor country as far as mineral resources were concerned.  I can recall my geography classes where all the Irish textbooks spelled out the fact that Ireland had few mineral resources&mdash;just a couple of coalmines that were not going to last much longer and a few small deposits of other minerals.  It was within that context that the tax legislation on mines, which we are repealing, was drawn up.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The 20-year tax holiday was designed to encourage people to risk their money and to risk their capital in an effort to discover mineral wealth.  Whether we like it or not, it certainly had the effect of inviting exploration and prospecting.  The companies involved may be basically Irish but, of course, in this situation we had to draw on foreign expertise. Therefore, the 20-year tax holiday has produced results and there is no question <Col N="656" /> that it has totally changed our view of our mineral resources.  It is not just the view of what has been discovered, but there is a widely held view&mdash;one reads it in newspaper reports by serious correspondents and in other magazines dealing with economics, finance and industry&mdash;that there are good prospects of further discoveries of minerals and of oil and gas off our shores.</P>
    <P>Therefore the context in which we are working has changed and we now realise that the view which was held about ten years ago was not a true one.  The work of the explorers and of the prospectors has made us more aware of the mineral wealth which we now know exists in certain quantities. It is not unreasonable that we should alter our legislation.  The problem is to find a balance to ensure that a sufficient proportion of this wealth remains in the country, and, as Senator Quinlan has said, that sufficient proportion is reinvested in further exploration and at the same time that the legislation which is drawn up does not discourage further discovery or further prospecting.  In fact, this must be encouraged.</P>
    <P>It is not simple.  Members who have spoken, saying that this legislation does not go far enough, have a very strong point and wish to see a more vigorous Government attitude to mining, to exploration and to the total mineral resources of this country. They wish to see clear indications of Government policy.</P>
    <P>Apart from the two measures which have been mentioned, the ending of the 20-year tax holiday and the awarding of certain allowances in this Bill, there is no general indication of Government policy.  I should like the Minister to give a clearer indication of over-all Government policy.  As Senator FitzGerald and myself have stated, we should like to see the inter-departmental committee's report published and have it debated in this House in a realistic way.  This debate has been a good one.  We could contribute to policy and we would fulfil our duty as Members of the Oireachtas if we debated a possible White Paper and were able to make suggestions <Col N="657" /> about the policy the Government should follow in this area.</P>
    <P>There are two ways in which the Government can influence the operations of mining or prospecting companies. One way is through the legislation we have before us, that is by taxation, and the other is by the Government being more vigorously involved in the running of the companies, by having Government nominees on the boards.  The Government should act on this suggestion.  It would ensure benefits all round. Senator FitzGerald has eloquently made the case for being careful that we do not tax prospecting and mining companies out of existence.  This would be short-sighted.  When the time came to establish our own industry to continue the work, if it was a totally nationalised industry, we would have financial problems and difficulties in obtaining expertise from abroad.  The <i>entrepreneur</i> has an important role to play in this area.  The Government should enact legislation to have Government nominees appointed to the boards of prospecting companies.  This is one of the ways in which we can ensure that the Government view is put forward to the companies.  One cannot view just one particular aspect in isolation: there must be a general policy.  Again, as Senator FitzGerald has pointed out, the mining industry generates further industrial activity at both ends.  There is a processing industry, when the mine is developed and when there is a sufficient level of mining activity; there is the ancillary industry, the pre-mining industry which provides equipment for prospecting and mining.</P>
    <P>One of the dangers in a small country like this is that these ancillary industries at both ends of the mining spectrum would not be based in Ireland, if for example, all the equipment were imported and the ore exported unprocessed.  We are neigh-bours to Britain and the Continent with their large industrial bases, their smelters and their own mining industries of various types.  Government nominees on the boards of mining companies could do a great deal to ensure that the ancillary industries <Col N="658" /> were developed in suitable places in Ireland.  There is no doubt that there are environmental problems.  There are problems, for example, in the siting of smelters.  Certain smelters create few problems for the environment. Depending on the ore being smelted, there can be considerable devastation.  One has only to go to some of the areas of the Ruhr in Germany where smelters have been in operation for ten to 15 years to see the devastation of the countryside. Ireland is a small country and cannot afford to make mistakes of this kind.</P>
    <P>There has been much talk of putting a particularly noisesome smelter in a very scenic part of Cork harbour.  This could very well destroy a wonderful amenity and an area which is of great tourist attraction. This is the type of problem which could be solved expeditiously if the Government had nominees on the boards of mining companies.  The important liaison work which could be done in the development of the industry is something which I hope the Minister will consider.</P>
    <P>The Norwegian Government, for example, have produced legislation in this connection, particularly in dealing with the problem of off-shore exploration.  The Norwegian Government have a stake in all the exploratory work and also in the actual extraction of the oil or gas.  We should be prepared to take a stake in the companies, if only by appointing Government nominees to the boards.</P>
    <P>I should also like to see further encouragement for Irish-based companies. If the company is Irish-based, there is no reason why there should not be a bias in its favour in the tax laws and in the legislation governing the regulation of the industry.  What we want to ensure, and this will keep the wealth in Ireland, is that Irish people are encouraged to take risks, invest money and become generally involved in the mining industry to a greater extent.  We should not cavil at giving specially favourable conditions to Irish-based mining industries. As Senator Russell has said, why should we not also encourage Irish people who wish to prospect abroad? <Col N="659" /> There is something to be done in that area too.  Perhaps these Irish people prospecting abroad could be facilitated in their taxation problems when they return to the country with their money.  Every encouragement should be given to them to work abroad if they so wish.  If a mining industry develops here, as we hope it will&mdash;it has already begun to a considerable degree&mdash;we should encourage our people, if they find suitable conditions, to prospect outside Ireland.  There is something to be said for giving them special treatment just as I feel we should give Irish-based mining companies specially favourable treatment for their operations in this country.</P>
    <P>Senator FitzGerald pointed out that there has been a change in the tide of public opinion here.  Of course this is natural.  Ten years ago people here were under the impression that there were not any minerals in this country.  In the sense that Senator FitzGerald talked about, there were not&mdash;in a sense they are not there until they have been discovered.  We hope that there will be further discoveries and that there will be incentives for people to continue these discoveries. The fact that public opinion has changed in that the view is held that what wealth is there should be used for the benefit of this country.  This is not an unnatural feeling provided it expresses itself in a way which is constructive and unconstrictive.  Then, there is nothing wrong with this feeling. It is one of the feelings the Government will have to respond to.</P>
    <P>It is the Government's job to find the right balance in drawing up legislation for dealing with the companies which will work in Ireland, but I think there are considerable dangers if large multinational corporations come in, because they have such efficient ways of compensating themselves for any losses they incur in any other area of operations.  They certainly are expert at exploiting countries which are not aware of their own potential.  We have got to be careful when these multinational corporations start operations.  They <Col N="660" /> need not be discouraged but they must be carefully supervised.  There definitely is a need for Government nominees on the boards of all corporations involved in the mining industry, particularly in the actual mining side of the industry in Ireland.  I hope that when the Minister replies to the debate he will be able to give us some further indication of overall policy and particularly of the advice he is getting from the inter-departmental committee which are keeping a watching brief in this area.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyMcAuliffe" hpid="Mr. McAuliffe Mr. McAuliffe">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McAuliffe</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill. It is a clear indication that the Minister is serious about reform in the income tax code.  This is something which no Minister has done in the history of this country.  We have got our own Parliament.  It took some considerable time to start reform of the income tax code.  This Bill proposes to embrace in the tax code an extra £125 million income in 20 years, otherwise 6.5 millions per annum, which I think is hardly a figure with which I could agree.  The people of the country were expecting to get much more from taxing of the mines than what the Minister estimates.</P>
      <P>I know that mining companies will be quite satisfied with the Bill that is presented by the Minister.  They will have no objection whatsoever to paying that amount of tax per annum. They are serious about developing mining in this country.  They have given hefty scholarships to have mining technicians trained in the Regional Technical College in Athlone.  That is a clear indication that they intend to stay here and develop the mines.  It is only natural that the State and the community would benefit as a result of wealth accruing from these mines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think any sane person could justify giving a 20-year tax exemption.  I think Senator Hanafin was embarrassed in his opening speech when trying to make a case that the present Government should not have done anything about the 20-years tax exemption.  If they had been allowed to do that it would have been full speed ahead and the companies involved in these operations <Col N="661" /> would have completed the work and exhausted the mines before the period elapsed, leaving nothing except holes in the ground filled with rubble and water.</P>
    <P>It is extraordinary that it is where the good land is that these mines have been found.  We are losing a natural amenity when the mines are exhausted.  I do not think it will be possible to redevelop the land or reclaim it when the mining has come to an end.  Many people who invested in these mines became rich overnight. As Senator Noel Browne said, some became millionaires.  Had the Government not moved, there might have been a very serious situation created for the over taxed workers of this country.  The first sign of that had been the formation of an organisation called NITRO.  They certainly are looking for reform.  We know that reform will have to come slowly.  It will not happen overnight.  I am satisfied this Bill provides concessions which we never got before.  Something will have to be done to give greater relief to people who are overtaxed at the present time.  This is one of the countries where the people who have most of the wealth are not taxed.  I refer to mining companies, land speculators and, to a lesser extent, big farmers.  The Minister has done something about all these matters.  It is very welcome as far as the workers of the country, and I, are concerned.</P>
    <P>The Bill is a move in the right direction.  If the Revenue Commissioners were as ruthless with the mining companies as they are with the ordinary taxpayer, the Minister's conservative figure would be exceeded, and the mines would become a greater source of wealth which would help the economic and social development of this country.</P>
    <P>Senator Noel Browne made use of the occasion to attack the Labour Party, and the Ministers in particular. He is still a member of the Labour Party.  If he had any sense of honour he would resign from the party and not go around creating a situation where there is character assassination. He uses every single occasion possible to attack members of the Labour <Col N="662" /> Party.  He probably expects to be a martyr and to be expelled.  I doubt if he will get the opportunity to become a martyr.  I was hurt by Senator Browne's remarks about Ministers who were not here to defend themselves. The Minister for Finance escaped fairly well, possibly because he was present.  When we are dealing with such an important matter as the Bill before the House it should be dealt with in a serious manner.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHalligan" hpid="Mr. Halligan Mr. Halligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Halligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have just heard from Senator McAuliffe the best argument I have heard for not joining the Labour Party.  Earlier, I very much enjoyed the contribution of Senator FitzGerald, although I must admit that I did not agree with one word of his conclusions.  As a callow youth I had the great pleasure and, indeed, also the great benefit, of sitting at his feet on many a fine morning and listening to him lecture.  I admired then the range of his erudition, humour and his great humanism.  That admiration has increased since then through listening to some of his contributions here in this Chamber.  He was one of those who helped to inculcate in me that attitude of scepticism which is the hallmark of academic training and it is ironic that I am not in the least bit convinced by his comprehensive reporting to us of the difficulties that face the mining industry in terms of exploration costs, the size of investment finance and the return on capital.</P>
      <P>He recognised that in economics, which pretends to be a science but which is based to a great extent on eighteenth century philosophy, the basic justification for profits is an ethical one.  Profits are a reward for risk.  There has latterly arisen in economics the problem of trying to justify profits in a non-risk situation, particularly in the field of the multinational corporation and the integrated firm.  If profits are based upon risk and if profits are in a sense commensurate with the degree of risk, then one cannot plead a special case that because risk is high in a particular form of economic activity it must have particular types of protection.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In a capitalist society risk taking <Col N="663" /> and earning profits are synonomous. Profits are the motor power of the economy.  If there is no profit in a particular form of economic activity or enterprise it follows rationally from the system that there will be no investment within it and, for that reason, one requires social forms of investment if that economic activity is to be pursued.</P>
    <P>There is not an industry that could not fail to put up the type of argument and special pleading that Senator FitzGerald so eloquently presented to us here today.  For example, one would not find the great advances in medical science if there was not such a high degree of financial return on pharmaceuticals. The pharmaceutical industry is notorious in terms of the risks involved and in terms of the huge expenditure required in fundamental research.  That research is not carried out for the good that these companies can do man in terms of helping his health.  Rather is it carried out in order that there can be an economic return on capital invested.</P>
    <P>There is no argument, therefore, in saying that because an enterprise is a high risk one we should not impose social controls or social constraints on its activities and there is no justification for giving it special consideration.</P>
    <P>In terms of a national policy in relation to national resources I welcome this Bill for what it is.  In my view, it is nothing more than a beginning. In so doing, I have to declare my own interest and say that my philosophical attitude on this would be the one shared by members of my party and that is a socialist one in relation to the use of national resources and their control.  Quite clearly and obviously my remarks will be biased because of that particular basis.</P>
    <P>The Bill, in itself, should never have been necessary, irrespective of the very eloquent defence put forward by Senator FitzGerald for the risks involved in mining, because these concessions should not, in the first instance, ever have been given.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="664" /> Senator FitzGerald asked: are Irish capitalists different from their ilk in other countries?  I indicated that they are.  That difference, I believe, is part of our national character, which is too lethargic.  In our school days we were told that this was a country in which there were no natural resources, except peat, and that if there were natural resources we did not, in any event, have the capability, the capacity, the energy, the drive or the money to exploit them.  It was a craven and cringing attitude.  As a result, exploration licences for land and sea were sold for a song particularly in the palmy days of the Department of Industry and Commerce in the late 1950s.</P>
    <P>Yet one can go back into the last century and find, for example, in the publications of the RDS that there was common belief that there existed at least the possibility of mineral resources in this country.  One can also refer, for example, to the IBEC Report in the 1940s.  Yet there was not a child, I am sure, up to 1960 that was not informed in his geography lessons that this country was one which was devoid and denuded of mineral wealth.</P>
    <P>Having said that, it would in my view be a continuation of the craven policy of the past if we did not regard this Bill other than as a beginning of a national policy covering the development of our natural resources, whether it be base metals, oil or gas. We should see this Bill as a foundation upon which we will build State participation in metal extraction, in smelting and indeed in process industries based upon the smelting processes.</P>
    <P>In the past this country has remained poor because its exploitation of its other great natural resource&mdash; grass&mdash;has not been carried to the highest form of economic processing. We exported the product of that particular resource at an unfinished stage &mdash;cattle on the hoof&mdash;the &ldquo;value-added&rdquo; was carried out in another economy.  Irish capital was exported to that economy in pursuit of our export and Irishmen went to that economy too in pursuit of Irish capital. <Col N="665" /> It was, and is, a ridiculous situation. National income is, in itself, simply an aggregation of &ldquo;value added&rdquo;.  If we export the possibilities of the &ldquo;value added&rdquo; naturally we depress our national income.  There would simply be a repetition of that disastrous policy in respect of one great natural resource if we were not now to insist that &ldquo;value added&rdquo; to the maximum will occur within the confines of our economy with regard to base metals mined in Ireland.  For that reason I am saying that this Bill no more than constitutes the beginnings of a policy on resources.  We have now, for the first time, the possibilities of using a resource which will give us the central core to the economy which we have lacked for so long, and that is in metals and medium scale engineering.</P>
    <P>One can use an analogy in respect of the optimum utilisation of this resource by referring to oil, which is affecting us all very considerably throughout the western world at the moment.  The Arabs have long been exploited by outside companies.  Their product has been exported in its most unprocessed form.  But they have now realised what has been happening to them and they recognise their great power.  They have taken steps to redress the economic balance between them and the companies.</P>
    <P>Other countries too, such as the Norwegians, have learned in the oil area.  Unfortunately, other countries, such as Britain, have never learned. It is an economic rule of thumb that whatever the British do economically is automatically wrong.  We should not imitate them.  Senator Alexis FitzGerald referred to another country which is now beginning to exert some national muscle over the use of its natural resources, namely, Australia.  He criticised the impact of their tax policy and by reference to that he showed a graph that went downwards in terms of investment in exploration.  That is mainly true, but one would have to look at a cost benefit analysis from the Australian national point of view and ask what is the relationship between output and consumption.  What use does the <Col N="666" /> Australian Government have in mind for the exploration and utilisation of those resources?  Perhaps a slow down in extraction is to their national advantage.</P>
    <P>We have now the possibilities presented to us, through this Bill and through other measures which I hope will follow it, of developing a metals industry and, upon it, medium scale engineering.  If that can be effected within a period of about 15 years it will change the technological face of this country.  It will not only do that by giving us a truly integrated and comprehensive industrial structure, but it will also have financial benefits of which the Minister for Finance is aware and to which he referred in his speech.  I am making reference, of course, to the impact which a national mining and metals industry will have on the balance of payments.</P>
    <P>My party's policy has been referred to during the course of this debate.  It is this.  The natural resources of our country should be developed to the maximum benefit of the Irish people as a whole, in other words, spelling it out institutionally, there should be maximum State involvement, within the constraints imposed by capital available and political factors.  I understand, and Senator McAuliffe made reference to it, that Senator Browne criticised the Labour Minister who is involved in this area, namely, the Minister for Industry and Commerce.  I should like to make one comment on that. In a public debate at our own party conference last year between the Minister and the Senator it was the advice of the Minister that was taken by the party.  That explains, to a great extent, the chagrin of the Senator and his attacks on the Minister.</P>
    <P>As I said at the beginning, my personal approach to this whole Bill is from the point of view of a socialist but it is one which is shared now by others who do not share that ideology. It is shared by the Arab community. It is shared by the emerging peoples of Africa, for example, Zambia.  It is shared by the Australians.  It is <Col N="667" /> shared by the South Americans.  That is to say, that where a resource exists it must be exploited in such a fashion that there is a balance between those who are given the right to exploit that resource and the people in whose country that resource exists. We have got to establish the principle, particularly in relation to exploration costs, that if private enterprise discovers these resources, then it does not have an absolute right to exploit them without social controls, and that any exploitation can only be carried out in conjunction with the social partner of the State.</P>
    <P>However, the last speaker referred to one very important point in terms of national attitudes on this matter which appeared to disconcert Senator FitzGerald.  It is one to which the Minister very wisely referred in his speech.  The people do not wish to see a situation in which a very great resource of theirs is exploited in such a fashion that only the very few benefit while ordinary people have got to shoulder a burden of taxation, which many of them regard as being beyond their ability to pay.  They wish to see the taxation burden spread equitably.  Essentially then I regard this Bill as being part of the over-all taxation reform which has been begun by the Minister in a most imaginative and encouraging manner.  One might also say, a most courageous manner.</P>
    <P>Finally, I regard it as a foundation upon which this Government will construct a policy in relation to all natural resources so that we will have, in this country, a proper balance between private enterprise and social involvement in the exploitation of our mineral resources which will bring us the benefit of outside expertise and outside capital while at the same time ensuring for the people of our country an adequate financial return on the resources which are theirs as of right.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>The title of the Bill seems to limit the observations one can make on it.  It is a Finance Bill and it seems to me that we have to confine ourselves as to whether or not in the circumstances of finance and tax a good job has been done.  As mentioned <Col N="668" /> by Senator Halligan, it was on the basis of the advice of the Minister for Industry and Commerce that the Labour Party's attitude to the mines was changed.  In changing their minds they realised that they were not saying to him that the social order is unchangeable.  What they were saying to him was: &ldquo;You have got a job to do.  There is a way of getting at some money that would be beneficial to the community.&rdquo;  The question arose as to whether to compromise at the particular time and in the particular circumstances how much the compromise and how to compromise.  Having heard the observations of my own party and having looked at the Bill, I am satisfied that if the Minister had adopted an intransigent attitude I frankly do not think we would even have got this far on the question of dealing with the mines and we would not have the more effective type of taxation that we have now.  Like Senator Halligan, I see this as a beginning.  Because of the circumstances in which we found ourselves and the factors that were placed before us having regard to how other nations tackled the problem, I felt that there was room for compromise and the thing to do under the circumstances was to compromise. There was a question of procrastination in trying to get your needs.  For that reason it would have been everything or nothing at this time.  There were a large number of choices but I am quite sure that the Minister having regard to the fact that it was difficult to satisfy the needs of all the people and after consultation did deal with the strength that he had.  Having read through the Bill, I am satisfied that the speculators have not been allowed to oversell their ideas.  I can see promise within the Bill of further things to come.  I am not speaking about the smelter because I do not think it is relevant to this particular Bill.  It is a Finance Bill and we are discussing how to get money in the interests of the people of the country in general.  The Minister, in my opinion, did a fair job of getting this money without losing sight of the objective.  I hope the objective is still <Col N="669" /> there.  We should get a great deal more out of the full potential.</P>
      <P>The Minister had to look at the needs of each side in dealing with the introduction of taxation.  He probably had to revise his strategy to some extent based on consultation and the views offered by the various interests throughout the country.  When dealing with mines it must be noted that not only do they run out but they become smaller.  Electronics and plastics are involved.  There are large areas of employment in these fields.  If enough cannot be got out of the mines and other industries take their place, those changes affect the lives of hundreds of people.  On the basis of the proposed taxation when mining starts to go down these other industries can grow.</P>
      <P>It does not appear that £125 million will be got out of this project, nor is that the full exploitation of what is available.  As a realist, I recognise that each side can exercise a certain amount of power on the other.  The Government will not get their way all the time.  The Government and industry do not always hit it off so well nor do the Government and employees.  There is some power with the investors and they exercise this power to some degree.  If I were to speak on a basis other than that of finance and taxation, I would not make the same observation. I am dealing with this matter in a pragmatic manner.</P>
      <P>This is a finance Bill, a development of the taxation system.  It introduces some improvements in regard to taxation. There was only a three year exemption in Canada, for example. They had already got away with seven years here.  There is scope for further development.  I do not like using the word &ldquo;exploitation&rdquo; having regard to my belief in socialism.  It could give the impression, wrongly, that everyone's possessions would be taken over without regard to their rights.  The Minister has held council with his associates including the Minister for Industry and Commerce.  He had to evaluate how the other countries got the most out of it. On the question of mining, neither the investors nor the State could get sufficient out of it without putting in a certain amount.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="670" /> To become intransigent about the question of applying the taxation in the manner in which it was done would show an eagerness to get away from dealing with the problem.  If taxation had not been introduced we would have some of the community arguing that there was a fear of criticism on the part of the responsible Ministers. This would be a sign of defeat.  I do not make my criticisms on the basis of disparaging the Bill.  I welcome it as a beginning.  I do not accept that this is the whole situation.  There is a great area between everything and nothing. Based on accumulated experience any experiment and research should be taxed in a short time to show the public that the problem was being tackled. Reading through the Bill, I feel that the Minister was over-cautious in dealing with the problem.  He could not be accused of procrastinating.</P>
    <P>It is said that treasures of the heart and soul are riches.  That is not much use to a man who is without a bean. He is looking for employment.  If this Bill allowed people to pursue their interests in a way which would help the employment situation and would not push it back from the point to which it had reached and the potential it showed, the unemployed should be satisfied to see this type of development, apart from the taxation which will be introduced.  They can recognise that if the mines decline, that effects only one aspect of the economy.  Other industries can grow and develop as those who have money to invest will not be satisfied with putting money into mines for 20 years.  When they become money-orientated they will put money into other side issues.  If the mines are not paying, they will move out of the area.</P>
    <P>Senator FitzGerald stated that Irish people should have a look at prospectors in other countries.  They are not looked upon as foreigners.  In any event, we appreciate the money which is coming in and the expertise and the scientific knowledge these people bring to the country.  However, this does not establish their full right to exploit to an excessive degree the mineral wealth of the country.  This can only be done on the basis of what is good for the people.  Whether Irishmen go out and <Col N="671" /> do so in any other country or not the same argument holds.</P>
    <P>I will wind up by saying that I hope this is a beginning of much better things to come.  Before there are any other major developments, such as those we read about in the paper the other night regarding natural oil and gas, I hope there will be a coming together of the minds within Government, and not in their own separate ways, as to what is the best way to tackle the problem from here on.  The people should assert themselves in a way that will, in the long run, be to their advantage.  In deciding that policy perhaps one or two people with money will get hurt but many people could get hurt if we did not make up our minds to go the whole hog and follow it up.</P>
    <P>Having examined the matter jointly and having had the benefit of all points of view including the attitudes of the people who feel that the mines should be nationalised, and so on I would say as an individual&mdash;and I think I could speak for some of my fellow party members&mdash;that if we found all the facts were against us and that there was only a certain limit to which we could go we should come to terms with the facts.  At least before anything is done there is a need to get together.  I say that openly and without reservations.</P>
    <P>There is a difference of opinion with regard to the question of the development of our natural resources. That problem should be resolved not so much on the basis of one side being dominant over the other but on the basis of a full examination based on our present experience and our acquisition of knowledge.  Any further dealings we have about the granting of licences or dealing with people who are making attempts at mining, who are in the field or are looking to get into the field, should be on a very deep, inquisitorial basis.  We must look right into every aspect of it before we finally come to a decision, and this should be done jointly.</P>
    <P>Finally, I should like to say to the Minister&mdash;in the circumstances he is not the happiest man in the place having regard to the power that each <Col N="672" /> could exercise on the other at a particular time and having regard to the position which developed&mdash;that I should like to welcome the Bill and hope that some of the observations I made will be helpful.  I hope also that this will be the beginning of better things to come.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Ryan) Richie Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to Senators for the manner in which they received this Bill.  Everybody in the House without exception gave it a welcome, although in some cases the welcome was spelled with a small &ldquo;w&rdquo;.  Some aspersions were cast on the value of the Bill.  My principal congratulatory prize must go to Senator Hanafin who, with tongue in cheek, criticised the Bill as being a piece of window-dressing and then assured us that Fianna Fáil believed in getting the greatest possible return to the community from the mines.  The Senator then criticised the Bill because he said it was so Draconian it might discourage investors.  He then told us that when Fianna Fáil were in power they had provided incentives to encourage mines and when they were put out of power they were about to extract maximum benefits.  That is not bad for a person who did not tell us in what way they had succeeded in getting a return from the industry or how they were going to go about extracting the maximum benefit in a way which would not have discouraged investors. He seemed to think this Bill was going to do that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesHanafin" hpid="Mr. Hanafin Mr. Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>May I interrupt?  I was dealing at that stage with new mines.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I see.  Senator Hanafin did not tell us what he considered to be a new mine.  For instance, would he like to tell us whether he would regard Tara as being a new mine or an old mine? Would he consider that Tara should be exempt from the provisions of this Bill?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesHanafin" hpid="Mr. Hanafin Mr. Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>I had in mind new explorations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>In other words, he would not apply this Bill to Tara.  If that be so it would mean that the <Col N="673" /> estimated £125 million, which I emphasised was in 1973 figures, would in fact be something in the region of only about £50 million.  In other words, the lion's share of the benefit which he said Fianna Fáil believed in getting for the community could not be obtained if the Tara mine was to be excluded.  I am afraid Senator Hanafin in the long run has disclosed something material because his own speech was a perfect piece of evasion. We now have, on his disclosure at this stage, obtained a clear indication that his thinkinig, and presumably the thinking of his party, is that the profits in Tara would not be available to the Irish people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesHanafin" hpid="Mr. Hanafin Mr. Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>If I was evasive in what I said the Minister is much more so.  I did not mention the Tara mines at any stage.  Is that the one to which the Minister referred?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I asked Senator Hanafin if he was considering that the Navan mine was a new mine or an old one and I understood him to say that in his view a new one would be one that had yet to be explored.  The Navan mine is already discovered.  It is ripe for development.  If I understood the Senator correctly he said that the Mining Taxation Bill should not apply to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesHanafin" hpid="Mr. Hanafin Mr. Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>I was dealing with new applications for licences for mining.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, in other words it would not apply&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Despite the politeness of the interchange between the Minister and Senator Hanafin I would ask the Minister to desist from these invitations to Senator Hanafin to intervene.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very sorry but I wanted to clarify with Senator Hanafin some matter that was in doubt.  What is not in doubt is the purpose of this Bill.  Under this Bill the Government on behalf of the people will acquire a half-interest in Irish mines.  The Government will be partners and will obtain through the system of taxation 50 per cent of the profits of the mines. I think that is a very significant step forward.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There has been criticism of the Bill <Col N="674" /> that it does not spell out conditions which the Government would attach to mining leases and so forth.  Of course that is a matter for the Minister for Industry and Commerce.  It is a matter not for legislation but for inserting in the leases as they may be issued.  This Bill is a finance Bill and is therefore, limited in its scope to deal with matters affecting taxation.  There has been disappointment expressed by several Senators about the £125 million estimated taxation over the next 20 years.  I would like to emphasise, as I said at the beginning, that that is based on 1973 figures and is itself open to a number of considerations which cannot yet be accurately estimated.  For instance, while there have been published figures relating to estimated ore reserves many of these published figures have not indicated the grades of ore or the percentage of metal content.  There is very little information about metal ratios, the rate of throughput, the percentage rate of extraction, capital outlay and operating costs and royalties payable. Of course, we do not know what will be the behaviour of world prices of metals over the next two decades. There are other matters, such as transport costs, which cannot be precisely measured.</P>
    <P>It is reasonable to anticipate that in accordance with their very best traditions the Revenue Commissioners have been conservative in their estimate.  Indeed, some figures which have been bandied about since the estimates were made would lead one at this stage to say that perhaps the estimate could have been increased to something in the region of £150 to £160 million, on the basis of present knowledge.  But, as I emphasise, with increasing knowledge one might well find that that should be further increased. I doubt very much that it would decrease.</P>
    <P>Again, it is important to emphasise that this estimate is based upon what we know about mineral resources.  It is related to discoveries already made and does not relate at all to anything at all which may be discovered over the next 20 years.</P>
    <P>Reference has been made by several Senators to the desirability of <Col N="675" /> bringing offshore resources, such as gas and oil, within tax liability.  I should like to remind Senators that I took the steps to bring profits from such development within the tax net in the Finance Act last year.  If profits are made from offshore gas or oil, then the benefit will flow to the Irish taxpayer as well as to the users of the commodities because of the action we took last year.  That is not to say that it might not be necessary to introduce a Bill to take account of the particular problems and difficulties of the oil and gas industries, particularly in relation to offshore development.  That will be a matter for a Bill which, like this, will deal with the peculiar problems of offshore drilling and development.  We shall face that whenever the need arises, which I think will be fairly soon.</P>
    <P>Because of the limited time available, I do not want to deal with all the points raised in the debate, but I will deal with some of them.</P>
    <P>Senator Hanafin referred to the mining activity in the Republic and contrasted it with the comparative lack of a mining industry in the North.  He suggested that this was a consequence of the 1967 prodigal incentive of a 20-year tax holiday.  It is important to recall once again that there is no company engaged in mining in the Republic of Ireland which was not engaged in exploration before 1967.</P>
    <P>Senator Alexis FitzGerald referred to the undesirability of a Government going back on promises or undertakings.  If somebody acts on foot of those undertakings, I accept that that is an undesirable thing.  Very fortunately for us, it is not a consideration that we have to bear in mind in relation to the taxation of mines.  No company has operated on foot of the 1967 bonanza.  They were all in Ireland and active in Ireland before the 1967 unnecessary tax holiday was given to them.</P>
    <P>Fortunately, there has been no breach of faith and we are right to be acting now before somebody is in a position to say: &ldquo;Well, we have <Col N="676" /> only come into Ireland after 1967 and, therefore, it would be a breach of faith to go back on what we understood to be the position in Ireland&rdquo;. The activity in Ireland has mainly stemmed in recent times from the 1956 legislation, introduced by my predecessor, the late Deputy Gerard Sweetman.</P>
    <P>There were others&mdash;a minority in Ireland&mdash;such as Senator Ted Russell, who had faith in the mining possibilities of Ireland when the rest of us were still influenced by Eleanor Butler's geological findings about there being no mineral resources in Ireland.  We do not blame Eleanor Butler.  She was only as wise as the state of man's knowledge then.  However, there are people like Senator Ted Russell who had the foresight, courage and patience to be involved. They were very, very few and perhaps it is fortunate that Ireland has had such people and still has them.  They have had the foresight and the courage and were ready to take risks where other people were too cautious to move.</P>
    <P>Senator Hanafin referred to the possibility that this legislation might discourage investment in Ireland.  This has been mentioned by the Fianna Fáil Party for several months past.  It is about time they stopped it.  They did it when we first announced our intention to bring this tax holiday to an end.  The people who shouted loudest about it were some people who, naturally enough, were disappointed that they were going to lose the freedom from taxation.  I and my colleagues have been criticised because, as we have spoken about mining taxation, we have also emphasised from time to time that there was no possibility whatsoever of withdrawing the exemption from income tax which was enjoyed by exported manufactured goods.  We had to do this because no matter what is suggested to the contrary, or whatever might have been said by the Opposition or by any politicians, the facts are that the inquiries which the IDA are receiving from people interested in setting up manufacturing industry in this country are on the increase.  Inquiries have increased substantially since the <Col N="677" /> announcement about the ending of the mining taxation holiday.  I hope that we will hear no more about this, because it is certainly most damaging to the interests of Irish workers and the people as a whole.</P>
    <P>We had only one advocate of nationalisation of mines in this debate. That is not surprising because our people realise that nationalisation is not a panacea; it is something that cannot be done without paying for it. We already have considerable difficulty in acquiring sufficient funds to invest in agriculture, manufacturing industry, housing and other very necessary social investments.  It would be entirely wrong, as Senator Alexis FitzGerald said, if the State were to deprive some of those essential investment needs of the funds that they require, in order to become directly and solely involved in the highly risky occupation of mining.  It could not, by any sensible test, be justified.</P>
    <P>The only other way in which nationalisation, referred to by Senator Browne, could be implemented, would be to start printing money to try to pay for it with devalued currency. That would have a most damaging effect upon the whole economy, even more damaging than the other method I previously mentioned.  It was because the Labour Party conference realised the folly of confiscation and nationalisation that they accepted the advice of my colleague, the Minister for Industry and Commerce, that the right thing was to achieve a compromise of conflicting interests.  That is what we have done in this legislation.</P>
    <P>We, in Government, are hopeful that the State will participate in a very active way in the mining industry. The Seanad are bringing in an amendment on Committee Stage.  This will provide that the various tax allowances in respect of exploration will be available to developing mining companies if they are wholly-owned subsidiaries of the company which explored and discovered the mine. These incentives will be available even though there might be State participation.  We want to ensure that there is no avoidance.  That is why we are granting this concession only <Col N="678" /> where the developer is the explorer or is a wholly-owned subsidiary of the explorer.  In order to facilitate the the participation by the State in the mining industry we will provide in this amendment that the incentives will be there even though the State may be involved.</P>
    <P>Several Senators including Senators Browne, Robinson and Russell referred to the desirability of having a smelter.  The Government are actively engaged in encouraging people already in the mining industry in Ireland to establish a smelter.  I do not wish to say too much about it at present because the negotiations are at a sensitive and very constructive stage. We can look forward with confidence to the possibility of having a smelter in Ireland in the foreseeable future. The smelter is now an economically sound proposition because of the quantity of ore which we now know exists and which is about to be developed. With a little bit of luck we will be able to supply all the requirements of the smelter for a considerable time to come.  There is a certain amount of spare smelter capacity in the world.  It is a very costly business to establish a smelter.  Notwithstanding all these considerations, the time has come for the smelter and we will see it emerge very soon.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not on Little Island, though.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Quinlan very properly raised this question of the location of dirty industries.  We are surveying the whole country at the moment in order to consider the most suitable locations for dirty industries but the most suitable location is always in somebody else's back yard or nearer somebody else's property rather than one's own.  It will not be easy for the Government to make recommendations in this field.  They are bound to be resented by somebody or other.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrosnan" hpid="Mr. Brosnan Mr. Brosnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brosnan</NameTxt>
      <P>Like the itinerants.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.  The dirty industries are like the itinerants.  We are all for them so long as somebody else <Col N="679" /> carries the cost and the disadvantages. Mines have been placed by nature.  The mine must be developed wherever it exists.  The same does not apply in relation to a smelter.  There are of course certain constraints.  The principal constraint is the desirability of having the smelter as near as possible to the principal source of the ore.  If Senator Quinlan considers that factor he would realise that Cork Harbour would not qualify at the present time for that particular industry, whatever qualifications it might have for other industries.</P>
      <P>I trust that this short survey of the points made in the debate will suffice. If, on my further consideration of the matter.  I think that any particular points raised by Senators require further comment, I shall communicate directly with them.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>When is it intended to take the Committee Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>Today, if possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesHanafin" hpid="Mr. Hanafin Mr. Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>The Minister may not be aware that a number of our Front Bench Members are in Brussels.  It is likely that they would wish to have an opportunity of dealing with the Committee and Report Stages.  The Minister can be assured of the fact that we should like to facilitate him, but since there was no notice of an intention to complete the Bill today I do not think I am being unreasonable in requesting the next Stage to be taken next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>In that case I have no wish to create any difficulty for anybody.  I would not object to it being left over.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a request from the Minister for it to be taken immediately and a proposition from Senator Hanafin that it be taken next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>The only point I should like to make, and we should certainly like to facilitate Senator Hanafin and the Opposition generally, is that this Bill passed through all the Stages in <Col N="680" /> the Dáil with an assurance from the Minister that he would introduce an amendment to cover a point made by Deputy Colley.  Otherwise the Bill was passed unanimously.  The Minister is now introducing that amendment.  I wish to make that point clear in case there are any doubts about possible further amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesHanafin" hpid="Mr. Hanafin Mr. Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>I would not wish in any way to be unreasonable.  In that case, perhaps we could proceed today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHalligan" hpid="Mr. Halligan Mr. Halligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Halligan</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the very heavy burden which would be put on the Minister with the Finance Bill and also that this amendment is coming in by virtue of a request from his own party, Senator Hanafin might consider allowing the remaining Stages to be taken today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="DesHanafin" hpid="Mr. Hanafin Mr. Hanafin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Hanafin</NameTxt>
      <P>I am agreeable.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to Senator Hanafin.  However, I should not like to mislead him.  There were criticisms of different sections of the Bill in the Dáil but I have given an undertaking to Deputy Colley to consider a point that he made and this amendment certainly meets that point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is a matter for the House to decide whether it is agreeable to take Committee Stage now and further that it agrees to take the recommendations, without notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I can see no useful purpose being served by delaying the next Stage to this day week.</P>
      <P>I have no desire to make any contribution to this debate but I have been associated for the past 50 years with mining, I happen to be a very near friend of Mr. Hughes who, incidentally, is an Armagh man.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I think the Senator is making the wrong contribution at the wrong time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>People who speak most on matters are very often those who know least about them.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Finance (Taxation of Profits of Certain Mines) Bill," RHead="1974 (Certified Money Bill): Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Finance (Taxation of Profits of Certain Mines) Bill, 1974    (Certified Money Bill):    Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="681" /> Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Government recommendation No. 1:</P>
    <P>In page 4, subsection (3), to delete line 57 and to substitute the following:</P>
    <P>expenditure incurred prior to the date of the change in ownership:</P>
    <P>Provided that in any case where part of the ordinary share capital of any body corporate is acquired by a Minister of State, such acquisition shall be disregarded in determining whether or not there was or is such a change in ownership as aforesaid.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Ryan) Richie Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>As I said in reply to the Second Stage, the purpose of this recommendation is to provide that if the State acquires an interest in a mine, which it might by purchase or gift by the mining industry, the right to set off exploration expenses against tax liability will not as a consequence be lost.  We are not allowing this right to be enjoyed by anybody unless the person who seeks to enjoy the right has explored the mine.  That is to stop anybody going round the country and buying up holes&mdash;dead holes or unsuccessful development. This would mean that the State could go in and the benefits would still be there.  I think the recommendation, from what I gathered in the debate, will meet the wishes of all Senators.</P>
      <P>Recommendation agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 3 agreed to with recommendation.</P>
      <P Just="Center">SECTION 4.</P>
      <P>Government recommendation No. 2:</P>
      <P>In page 5, subsection (2), to delete line 54 and to substitute the following:</P>
      <P>through another body corporate or other bodies corporate:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="682" /> Provided that where part of the ordinary share capital of anybody corporate is held by a Minister of State and the remainder of the ordinary share capital of that body corporate is held by another body corporate, the first-mentioned body corporate shall be deemed, for purposes of subsection (1), to be a wholly-owned subsidiary of the last-mentioned body corporate.</P>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is similar to the previous one and is for the same purpose.</P>
      <P>Recommendation agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 4 agreed to with recommendation.</P>
      <P>Sections 5 to 18, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported with recommendations, received for final consideration and ordered to be returned to the Dáil.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at</i> 1.15 <i>p.m. and resumed at</i> 2.30 <i>p.m.</i></P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Maintenance Orders Bill, 1974:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Maintenance Orders Bill, 1974: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney) Patrick M. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney)</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill, which makes provision for the reciprocal enforcement of maintenance orders as between ourselves and Britain and Northern Ireland, is a measure of social legislation for which there is at present an urgent need.  As such it has been welcomed by the public generally and members of all parties.  It was dealt with sympathetically and constructively by the Dáil and I know that Senators, too, will approach it on the basis that it endeavours to deal in a positive and practical way with one of the many problems in the field of family law. This is a branch of the law which is of special concern to me as Minister for Justice and I consider it to be one of my main tasks to effect substantial and overdue improvements in it during my term of office.  In this connection I have arranged that the 19th interim report of the Committee on Court <Col N="683" /> Practice and Procedure, on the subject of desertion and maintenance, will be examined as a matter of urgency by the various Departments concerned with a view to submitting the various recommendations in the Report to the Government and the preparation of legislation on the basis of the Government's decisions.</P>
      <P>The Bill is confined to the particular problem of making the necessary provision to enable effect to be given in the State to a proposed Agreement for the reciprocal enforcement of maintenance and affiliation orders as between the State and Britain and Northern Ireland.  It does not propose to make any changes in the law other than those necessary to implement that Agreement.  I decided at an early stage that to try to go any further would inevitably delay the preparation and, possibly, the passage of the Bill through the Oireachtas.  I would have liked to have seen, for example, a provision for attachment of wages in the Bill.  Such a provision would have to apply generally and it must and will, be considered in a broader context.</P>
      <P>The proposed Agreement is intended to be an interim one pending the accession of the new member States to the EEC Convention on Jurisdiction and the Enforcement of Judgments in Civil and Commercial Matters.  This Convention, which applies to maintenance and affiliation orders, as well as other civil and commercial judgments, came into force between the six original member States of the EEC on February 1, 1973. Negotiations for the accession of the new member States are at present proceeding but it is not expected that accession can take place before 1976.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Agreement will follow closely the recognition and enforcement provisions of the EEC Convention, and thus provide an opportunity to see how the Convention will operate in practice between the State and Britain and Northern Ireland in relation to maintenance orders.  For the same reason, the text of the Bill also follows these provisions of the Convention, as far as practicable and appropriate. <Col N="684" /> For ease of reference, the Bill contains marginal references to the relevant Articles of the Convention. In addition, an English translation of these Articles has been given in the Appendix to the explanatory memorandum circulated with the Bill when it was introduced in the Dáil.  I trust that Senators will find this helpful in their consideration of the Bill.</P>
    <P>In regard to the proposed Agreement, the negotiations are progressing very satisfactorily and I hope that they can be finalised at the next meeting due to be held towards the end of July. I expect that, if the Bill is passed by the Oireachtas before the Adjournment, it should be possible to have the Agreement signed during the Recess. The enforcement arrangements would then be brought into operation on a date agreed between the two Governments following the making of a commencement order under section 2 of the Bill and, on the British side, an Order in Council applying their Maintenance Orders (Reciprocal Enforcement) Act, 1972, with the necessary adaptations, to maintenance orders made in the State.</P>
    <P>The operative provisions of the Bill are contained in Part II.  First, provision is made for the recognition and enforcement in the State of British and Northern Ireland maintenance orders.  That is in sections 6 to 16. Secondly, jurisdiction is conferred on our courts to hear and determine maintenance and affiliation proceedings against a defendant residing in Britain or Northern Ireland and provision is made for transmitting our maintenance orders there for enforcement. These provisions are in sections 17 to 19.  The remaining sections of the Bill relate to mutual co-operation between courts in obtaining evidence for the purposes of maintenance or enforcement proceedings in the respective jurisdictions and provide for the admissibility as evidence in our courts of certain documents and statements.</P>
    <P>I shall deal first with the procedure for the recognition and enforcement in the State of British and Northern Ireland maintenance orders.  This procedure has been made as simple and <Col N="685" /> informal as possible, but with full regard to the need to respect the basic rights of both parties.  A request for enforcement, together with the necessary supporting documents, will be received by the Master of the High Court from the appropriate authority in the reciprocating jurisdiction concerned, that is to say, from the Secretary of State.  The Master will consider the documents privately and, on the basis of such consideration, he will decide whether or not to order the enforcement in the State of the maintenance order concerned.</P>
    <P>He can only refuse enforcement if it appears to him, from the documents or from his own knowledge, that recognition and enforcement would be prohibited on the grounds specified in section 9.  Those grounds are that recognition or enforcement would be contrary to public policy; that, where the maintenance order was made in default of appearance, the defendant was not served with notice of the institution of the proceedings in sufficient time to enable him to arrange for his defence, and, finally, that the order is irreconcilable with a judgment given in a dispute between the same parties in the State. These are taken from Article 27 of the EEC Convention.</P>
    <P>Where the Master decides to grant enforcement, he will make an enforcement order.  That order will, as it were, &ldquo;naturalise&rdquo; the maintenance order concerned.  It will then be treated for enforcement purposes as if it had been made in desertion or affiliation proceedings, as the case may be, in the District Court.  The maintenance debtor&mdash;the husband or putative father, as the case may be&mdash; must be served with a notice of the making of the enforcement order.  The notice must include a statement of his right of appeal against the enforcement order, and other relevant information. The Master must notify the maintenance creditor of his decision, whether or not he decides to enforce the order.</P>
    <P>Both debtor and creditor are given a right to appeal to the High Court. There may be a further appeal to the Supreme Court, but only on a point of <Col N="686" /> law.  Senators will observe that there is no requirement that the maintenance debtor be notified of the receipt by the Master of the request for enforcement and that the debtor will not, in fact, be entitled to make any submissions on the request at that stage.  This is in accordance with the procedure laid down in the EEC Convention. Substantial safeguards are, however, built into the system to ensure protection of the debtor's rights.  He will, in the first instance, have been served with notice of the original proceedings taken in the other jurisdiction.  These notices will be received by the Master of the High Court from the appropriate authority and the Master will have them served through the local district court clerk.  The maintenance debtor will, thus, have had an opportunity to defend the British or Northern Ireland proceedings in person, or to representations or submit evidence to the court.  If a maintenance order is made, the debtor will be notified directly by the district court clerk by registered post.  It will be then open to him to appeal against it in the ordinary way in the jurisdiction concerned. Finally, where the Master makes an enforcement order, the debtor will have one month after he has received notice of it to appeal to the High Court.</P>
    <P>The actual enforcement of the enforceable maintenance order will be effected by the District Court in the same manner as it would enforce a maintenance or affiliation order made by itself.  However, in order to strengthen the effectiveness of the enforcement machinery two innovations have been introduced.  First, the Bill requires that all payments due under these maintenance orders must be made to the local district court clerk for transmission to the maintenance creditor.  Secondly, the district court clerk is being empowered to initiate enforcement proceedings at the request of the maintenance creditor.</P>
    <P>I now turn to what is, perhaps, from our point of view a more important aspect of the proposed agreement namely, the enforcement in Britain and Northern Ireland of maintenance <Col N="687" /> orders made in the State.  The legal basis for this will be, as I have said, the British Maintenance Orders (Reciprocal Enforcement) Act, 1972, as it will be adapted by an order in council. What the Bill does in this respect is to confer jurisdiction on our courts to make maintenance orders where the defendants are in Britain or Northern Ireland, and also to provide machinery for the transmission of these orders to the appropriate authorities there for enforcement in accordance with the provisions of the 1972 Act.</P>
    <P>The procedure to be adopted by a deserted wife whose husband has gone to England will be as follows.  She will go to the local district court clerk and apply for a maintenance order in the ordinary way.  Notice of the institution of the proceedings will then be sent by the clerk to the Master of the High Court under section 17 (3).  The Master will transmit the notice to the appropriate authority for service on the defendant.  The court here will in due course hear the case and, if it makes a maintenance order, it will be sent for enforcement through the same channels.  The proceedings will, therefore, be as simple and as inexpensive for the wife as they would be if the husband were within the jurisdiction.  Incidentally, there appears to be some doubt as to whether the Bill applies to maintenance orders made by the High Court in desertion and affiliation cases.  I can assure the House that it applies to all such orders whether made by the High Court or by the District Court.</P>
    <P>Finally, the Bill contains some provisions in relation to evidence.  These deal with obtaining evidence from a person residing in Britain or Northern Ireland for the purposes of court proceedings in the State under the Bill, and the taking of evidence in the State for the purpose of British or Northern Ireland proceedings.  These provisions will enable the courts concerned to have the evidence of persons who cannot, or will not, travel to attend the court proceedings but who are prepared to give evidence at a local venue.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="688" /> Provision is also made, in section 22, for the admissibility in court proceedings here of the various documents which must be submitted in connection with the recognition and enforcement of maintenance orders in the State, of evidence taken in Britain and Northern Ireland at the request of courts in the State and of statements contained in documents of a kind likely to be produced in maintenance or enforcement proceedings under the Bill.  This section endeavours to face up realistically to the problems that would arise if the rules of evidence appropriate to circumstances where both parties live within the jurisdiction were to be applied to maintenance proceedings where one of the parties is living and working in another jurisdiction and may not be able to attend the proceedings here.  I believe it succeeds in this and that the admission of these statements and documents, subject to the various safeguards provided, will help in enabling the court to ensure that justice is done to both parties in each particular case.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I should like to emphasise that I am presenting the Bill as a measure containing the technical legal provisions necessary to authorise machinery to be established on our side for the reciprocal enforcement of maintenance orders. While I am sure that Senators are in sympathy with the general aim of the Bill, they may, perhaps, wish to make suggestions for its improvement.  I can assure them in advance that I shall consider any such suggestions very carefully.  No measure of this kind can provide a perfect solution to the problems it is designed to deal with but I think I can reasonably claim that it will assist in a worthwhile way the deserted wives and unmarried mothers who at present have no means of enforcing their rights against men who have gone to Britain and the North and that its enactment will be a deterrent to those men who may feel tempted to ignore their responsibilities in this regard.</P>
    <P>I commend the Bill to the House on this basis and ask that it be given a Second Reading.</P>
    <Col N="689" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrosnan" hpid="Mr. Brosnan Mr. Brosnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brosnan</NameTxt>
      <P>As the Minister stated, this is important social legislation and it is not alone urgent and desirable but it is also necessary in view of our accession to the EEC.  Of course the real and the practical aim of the Bill is a worthy one and one which commends itself to everybody in this House and, in fact, to all members of the community and that is to set up legal machinery to compel deserting husbands and putative fathers who have fled from the jurisdiction to carry out their legal and moral obligations to the people whom they have wronged, namely, the deserted wives or the illegitimate children, by providing for them the support and maintenance to which they are legally and I submit morally entitled.</P>
      <P>However, I have grave reservations about the ability of this measure and the machinery which the Minister proposes to set up under this Bill to deal adequately with these problems which we are all anxious to have solved.  This expression of doubt on my part is no reflection on the Minister, his advisers or his Department.  It arises from the nature and the difficulties of the problem which this Bill sets out to resolve. I agree that some measure of co-operation and reciprocity is essential if these difficult problems are to be tackled at all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>To some extent this Bill and the legal machinery which it is proposed to set up under it are unique and largely experimental.  The Minister is attempting to legislate to deal with a social and human problem.  For that reason the reciprocity sought under this measure is essential.  It is difficult to establish this co-operation, this mutual co-ordination between the courts of this country and the courts of Britain and Northern Ireland.  Some degree of co-operation does at present exist between the courts of these three countries in other fields such as criminal law and as between the revenue departments and the social justice departments.  The machinery governing these areas is highly complicated and highly technical.  The difficulty of obtaining a large measure of co-operation of this nature has <Col N="690" /> been exemplified and demonstrated recently in the failure of the legal experts of this State and Great Britain when they met to discuss the area of common law enforcement.  They failed to agree on what practical steps could be taken to deal with this problem. The success of the Bill depends on the effectiveness of the machinery to trace the culprits, the deserting husband or the putative father, in order to make them amenable to the provisions of this Bill and to enforce maintenance orders against them.</P>
    <P>The maintenance order in itself is useless unless it can be enforced.  As the Minister is aware from his practical experience as a solicitor even when one gets a maintenance order or any other order of our courts against a person residing in our own jurisdiction, it is difficult and sometimes impossible to enforce that order. Many Senators are aware that Garda barracks throughout the country have sheafs of execution orders which they do not or cannot execute.</P>
    <P>The enforcement of a maintenance order against the type of person who comes under this Bill is more difficult as these persons are usually will-of-the-wisps, having injured their wives in the case of deserting husbands or another woman in the case of a putative father, and usually abscond out of the jurisdiction of this country. They are to be found in the ghettos of London, Birmingham or Manchester or some other large centre in Great Britain.  They make a point of remaining anonymous.  They often commit the same offences against other females and that further actuates them to conceal their identities.  They become adept at escaping the law and evading any inquiries from either their wives at home or the female whom they got into trouble or the relatives of that female.  They become artful dodgers.  Some Irish labourers who go abroad are expert at dodging the revenue commissioners there.  When income tax becomes due in one job they leave and take up another job.  This can go on apparently for years.  Much the same applies to the type of person the Minister hopes to catch and to make amenable to the law under this Bill.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="691" /> When a maintenance order is made against these people and enforced they usually do make a number of payments. Then the payments cease and they disappear and this complex procedure has to be gone through once more.  Even with the full co-operation of the gardaí, the employers, the revenue authorities, labour exchanges, social workers and other voluntary bodies working in England it is doubtful if their combined efforts would be adequate to deal with this type of person and bring them to justice.</P>
    <P>This legislation is not intended to come fully into force in relation to the EEC until 1976.  Legislation of this nature did come into force in the six member countries of the Common Market in February, 1973.  I should like the Minister to inform us how this legislation is working in those countries, and if it was effective enough to deal with these problems. Perhaps when replying he would inform us.</P>
    <P>Turning to the text of the Bill, as the Minister stated in his speech, the provisions are informal and flexible. This is expected in a Bill which is, to a large extent, novel and experimental. Many of the provisions particularly those dealing with the functions and powers of the Master of the High Court and of the clerk of the District Court are new and so are the provisions dealing with the obtaining and the admissibility of evidence and, in particular, the admissibility of documentary evidence.  This fresh, informal approach is welcome if it helps to achieve the worthy objectives of this measure.</P>
    <P>I should like to make some tangible comments on a number of the sections. In section 4 I note that this Bill, when it becomes an Act, will not have effect in relation to arrears accrued before the commencement of the operation of the Act.  That seems to me to be strange.  I fail to appreciate why that should be so.  I would suggest to the Minister that under this Bill when it is enacted creditors should be entitled to seek arrears for a period of six years as in the Contracts Act.  In section 9&mdash;<Col N="692" /> and part of this is inexplicable&mdash;we read:</P>
    <P>A maintenance order made in a reciprocating jurisdiction shall not be recognised or enforcable if, but only if&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a) recognition or enforcement would be contrary to public policy.</P>
    <P>I should be grateful to the Minister if, when replying, he would inform me what situation is envisaged under section 9 (a).  How could the attempt by a maintenance creditor to obtain a maintenance order and the enforcement of that order be contrary to public policy?  Section 9 (b) I understand and appreciate but I have some doubts about section 9 (c) which states that this order cannot be recognised or enforced if</P>
    <P>it is irreconcilable with a judgment given in a dispute between the same parties in the State.</P>
    <P>I should like the Minister to enlighten me on what is intended by these two subsections:</P>
    <P>In section 14 (8) (a) we read:</P>
    <P>Any sum payable by virtue of an enforceable maintenance order shall, notwithstanding anything to the contrary therein, be paid by the maintenance debtor to the district court clerk for the district court area in which the debtor for the time being resides for transmission...</P>
    <P>There is no time limit on the obligation on the district court clerk to pay or to transmit any payment he receives to the maintenance creditor.  I wonder if the Minister would consider putting in a time limit because sometimes District Court clerks, like ourselves can take things easy while the unfortunate maintenance creditor may be badly in need of the money which is being held on her behalf.</P>
    <P>I welcome the flexibility in relation to the obtaining and the admissibility of evidence.  However, one thing did occur to me and it is a suggestion which I would make to the Minister; that is that in paternity suits evidence of blood tests and other medical evidence be admissible in order to establish the paternity of an illegitimate child.  I <Col N="693" /> understand that this is now common practice and medical opinion is that in most cases this evidence is conclusive.  I would ask the Minister to consider that point.</P>
    <P>As I said at the outset I have serious reservations about the success of this Bill and about its workability. However, as the Minister has stated in his opening speech, it may be a deterrent to errant husbands and prospective putative fathers of illegitimate children and it may be of some consolation to deserted wives and illegitimate children to know that there is some machinery now on the Statute Book to which they could resort in circumstances which might prove successful in a small number of cases.  However, I look with hope and with confidence to the success of the Bill and I wish it well.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to extend a welcome to this Bill as a limited but constructive step in trying to reform our family law and bring it into line with the demands of social justice and the aspirations of the less privileged people in the country.  It has to be a qualified welcome, however.  Although this Bill has solved one of the intractable problems of recent times, it is of very limited application.  Paradoxically, it very largely depends on English law and it puts an English deserted wife in a better position than her Irish counterpart.  I will elaborate on that later, because there are a number of paradoxes which arise from the fact that the Minister has settled for this more limited measure.  His reason for so doing is in order to get the Bill through at this stage to allow the agreement between this country and Britain on recognition and enforcement of maintenance orders to be finalised, hopefully in July.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In view of the Minister's Second Reading speech, which was more detailed and open than other speeches that are sometimes made in introducing Bills to this House, I do not want to appear to be carping or to be criticising irritably a measure which tries to improve the position relating to family law.  Any comments that I <Col N="694" /> make are an attempt to be constructive and to improve the Bill itself&mdash;if that is necessary or possible&mdash;and to put whatever pressure can be put on the Minister and public opinion generally for a vastly accelerated attempt by us, as a country, to meet the urgent social problems in this whole area of family law.  I note that the Minister made reference in the first paragraph of his speech to the recommendations of the Committee on Court Practice and Procedure in its 19th interim report.  He did so in somewhat general terms and I should like, if he is amenable to it, to seek more specific answers.  He said:</P>
    <P>I have arranged that the 19th Interim report of the Committee on Court Practice and Procedure, on the subject of desertion and maintenance, will be examined as a matter of urgency by the various Departments concerned with a view to submitting the various recommendations in the Report to the Government and the preparation of legislation on the basis of the Government's decisions.</P>
    <P>With respect to the Minister, I would hope that he can comment in more specific terms on the recommendations of this report.</P>
    <P>We must approach this subject with a knowledge of the reality of Irish family life at the moment.  One way in which we can assess this reality is by way of careful studies such as the exploratory study which was made by Kathleen O'Higgins on behalf of the Economic and Social Research Institute entitled <i>Marital Desertion in Dublin.</i>  It makes very sad reading, particularly Section V, headed &ldquo;Marriage Breakdown and the Law in Ireland.&rdquo;  On page 123 she states:</P>
    <P>Legislation in the area of marriage breakdown in Ireland have done almost nothing in the past 70 years.</P>
    <P>She goes on to give a survey of the position.  At a later stage in that same chapter, at page 126, she analyses one of the most crucial problems in marital desertion, namely, the lack of proper legal safeguards and processes <Col N="695" /> to resolve the hardships in this area. She emphasises the need to resolve one of the most serious problems which is totally outside the present scope of this Bill:</P>
    <P>Another aspect of desertion cases which requires some legal intervention is the right of the husband to reappear at any time.  Some women live in dread of this event when the husband will temporarily resume his role as head of the household as his legal right.  He more than likely will also continue his previous behaviour pattern, possibly of drunkenness and violence. The jurisdiction of the court is based on The Married Women (Maintenance in case of Desertion) Act, 1886, as amended by section 18 of the Courts Act, 1971.  The court under that Act cannot properly protect a wife who has been the victim of physical cruelty as the Act was originally designed to deal with desertion only.</P>
    <P>I hope that the Minister would agree that it is this need for protection of the spouse&mdash;protection from physical or mental cruelty, from actual beating, from the drunken behaviour of a husband either returning after a desertion or even when it has been what might be termed technical desertion that poses one of the most serious problems.  We must be faulted very seriously for not having provided the necessary legal mechanisms and in particular a jurisdiction in the district court to protect the deserted wife.</P>
    <P>Therefore, I should like to ask the Minister for some more specific indications of the extent to which he has accepted the specific recommendations of the Committee on Court Practice and Procedure and the sort of time scale he envisages for getting a Governmental decision to implement the necessary legislation?  For example, Paragraph 44 of the 19th interim report of the Committee on Court Practice and Procedure reads:</P>
    <P>The existing law should be amended to provide that the spouse may be ordered to pay to the other <Col N="696" /> spouse by means of maintenance order for the support of that spouse and the dependent children such sum as the court may order when it is satisfied that there has been a family default on the part of the spouse against whom the order is sought.  Family default should be defined as</P>
    <P>(a)  actually abandonment of the family home, the other spouse and the dependent children and failure to maintain them or</P>
    <P>(b)  such ill-treatment, physical or mental, or other misconduct on the part of one spouse as would reasonably justify the other in leaving the family home and a failure by the spouse in the family home to maintain the other or</P>
    <P>(c)  such ill-treatment, physical or mental, or other misconduct on the part of one spouse as would reasonably justify the other in leaving the family home although she or he does not do so and a failure by the spouse who earns to maintain the other or</P>
    <P>(d)  failure of the spouse who is responsible for the support of the family to provide a reasonable standard of living for them having regard to the means and earnings of that spouse.</P>
    <P>The important factor here is that the proposed extension of jurisdiction to award maintenance orders would put the Irish deserted wife more on a parity with the English wife who has been deserted.  One of the points I was making earlier is that, paradoxically, because of the far better system of English law allowing much broader grounds for awarding maintenance orders, the English deserted wife who can get those orders enforced here&mdash; and they will be enforced without inquiry on the grounds on which the order was made by the English or Northern Ireland court&mdash;is in a better position than her Irish counterpart. There is no equality of treatment between the Irish deserted wife and the English deserted wife because our domestic law prescribes only a very narrow, limited basis for allowing maintenance to be awarded.  It may <Col N="697" /> only be awarded on the grounds of desertion, a concept which has been extended by judicial interpretation of the motion of constructive desertion.</P>
    <P>We must as a priority face up to our legislative responsibility and lay down broader bases on which maintenance orders may be given.  A commendable way to do this would be to accept the idea of family default&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>For the information of the Senator, I have already indicated that that report is acceptable in principle.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to the Minister for this assurance.  It will shorten to some extent this part of my contribution.  If he has accepted the recommendations in principle, will he go further and indicate in what sort of time span they may be reduced into actual legislation?  Although I can see the necessity for co-operation with other Departments the overall responsibility and jurisdiction is very squarely in the Minister's Department and I should like some guideline&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>Again, for the information of the Senator, I indicated some time ago that it is my hope the legislation to implement that report will be introduced in the Michaelmas Term, to use a legal phrase.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful to the Minister for this information.  I often feel that though this information is available elsewhere, it is sometimes hard to check out, and one of the values of a debate of this nature is to try to get a fairly coherent overall picture of the Government's, and particularly the Department of Justice's, policy in relation to the subject.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It was announced in the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I was not suggesting it had been announced at a dinner or on some such occasion.  It is very useful to have a statement of intent on Government policy in specific terms in relation to this area.  Given the response of the Minister on that question, I should like to comment on the framework of this Bill and then <Col N="698" /> make some more specific comments on different sections.</P>
      <P>First of all, as to the overall framework: the Minister has said that it is a rather technical Bill for the purpose of concluding an agreement for the reciprocal enforcement of maintenance orders between Britain and this country.  It has been introduced in anticipation of our ratifying the EEC Convention on the Jurisdiction and Enforcement of Civil and Commercial Judgments.</P>
      <P>Accepting that this is the technical context, I should like to ask the Minister why it was not thought desirable to introduce a general statutory framework not just relating to the reciprocating jurisdiction as defined in the interpretation section, section 3 of the Bill, namely, Northern Ireland, England, Wales or Scotland?  Why was it not thought desirable to have a more general framework which could then be expended by a Ministerial Order or other appropriate mechanism to any country?  I fully accept the position that we hope to ratify the European Convention despite some problems in adopting it for the three new member states, but what about other countries which are outside this scope?  for example, countries like Spain, the United States or Australia?  Would it not have been an opportunity to have a framework to allow us when the occasion arose to enter into bilateral arrangements with other countries? The need may not seem so urgent because there are fewer husbands who would desert to these other countries, but there are certainly some.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I could see us participating in a private international law convention, for example, the Hague Convention, in which the effect would be that we would be extending this sort of enforcement arrangement to a larger number of countries.  Outside that framework we might want to extend it still further and a more general statutory authority might make it easier for us to ratify and to enforce in our internal law the obligations of such a multilateral convention.  That is the first question: why a policy decision was taken to confine this Bill <Col N="699" /> merely to the reciprocating countries which are, I admit, the main countries in which the deserting party goes? This is in contrast to the English structure where their Act can be extended and will be extended to Ireland by an Order in Council.  It seems to be a more flexible overall formula.</P>
    <P>Looking at the sections of the Bill, first of all in the interpretation section, section 3, I have a comment to make: this may seem a rather small point but it is perhaps more useful to make it now if it is felt that it requires some amendment in that there is a difficulty of citation.  For example, if I am citing section 3 (1) (a) there are in effect two paragraphs (a) which qualify.  There is a need for some different sub-grouping so that we do not have two sets of (a), (b) and (c) under subsection (1).  However, this is a small point and there are more important comments which I should like to make on the text of the Bill.</P>
    <P>On section 3 (1) (b) at the top of page 4, I wonder whether the provision is broad enough to include payments of lump sums.  It reads:</P>
    <P>an affiliation order or an order consequent thereon, being an order which provides for the payment by a person adjudged, found or declared to be a child's father or expenses incidental to the birth of the child or, were the child has died, of the funeral expenses,</P>
    <P>In the Illegitimate Children (Affiliation Orders) Act, 1930, there is provision for payment of a lump sum instead of periodic payments over a certain period.  Looking at the definition of &ldquo;maintenance order&rdquo;, in paragraphs (a) and (b) of section 3, I am in some doubt as to whether this would cover either affiliation proceedings which result in the payment of a lump sum under the 1930 Act or whether it would cover the practice in England where there is power to award maintenance by means of a lump sum.</P>
    <P>Under subsection (2) of section 3, there is the curious phrase, in a sense: &ldquo;For the avoidance of doubt, a maintenance <Col N="700" /> order includes&mdash;&rdquo;.  This is the area in which I have maximum doubt about the doubt that it is hoped to avoid, and I would appreciate some clarification by the Minister.  Subsection (2) states:</P>
    <P>For the avoidance of doubt, a maintenance order includes&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a) such an order which is incidental to a decision as to the status of natural persons,</P>
    <P>I would welcome clarification from the Minister as to what is intended by that.  Specifically, does it include maintenance orders arising out of divorce proceedings?</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It does.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am very pleased to have that doubt laid to rest.  Again, and it is on the same subject, I should welcome some clarification on a point in relation to section 9 (a).  Section 9 provides:</P>
      <P>A maintenance order made in a reciprocating jurisdiction shall not be recognised or enforceable if, but only if&mdash;&mdash;</P>
      <P>Then paragraph (a) goes on:</P>
      <P>recognition or enforcement would be contrary to public policy.</P>
      <P>This paragraph would seem to raise the question of whether, although we have included in the definition of &ldquo;maintenance orders&rdquo; maintenance orders arising out of divorce proceedings whether the enforceability of these very maintenance orders might come within section 9 (a) and be treated as in conflict with public policy?  I would welcome some clarification from the Minister on this.  The reason is that I believe that in this area public policy must undoubtedly be something stated and set out by the legislature to guide the judiciary and not left so vague that it may be subject to different interpretation by individual judges, without any overall policy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Looking at section 13 (1) (d), I wonder why there was reference there &ldquo;where appropriate&rdquo; to a document showing that the maintenance creditor is receiving legal aid in that jurisdiction. Unhappily this could not apply to a person applying for maintenance <Col N="701" /> in this country, since we have not extended legal aid to cover applications for maintenance, but it would almost always cover an application for maintenance in the other reciprocating jurisdictions.  What I really wondered was, seeing that it has been included specifically here, is this in order that we may more rapidly introduce legal aid in the application for maintenance orders in this country so that this would result in the same documentation being exchanged? More specifically, has this relevance to the terms of the Convention on Jurisdiction and the Enforcement of Civil and Commercial Judgments where there are very interesting provisions relating to legal aid and where, if I understand them, the position indeed is that if a person has been receiving legal aid in the country where the application for a maintenance order is made, that person must also receive legal aid in the country where the order is being enforced?</P>
    <P>Again, it would heighten the paradoxes that are there already, if we were to put the English wife in a more advantageous position by qualifying her for legal aid in pursuing enforcement here, whereas we did not allow the Irish deserted wife who has made an application for maintenance to have legal aid in bringing her application to this country.  These remarks are made in an attempt to emphasise yet again the vital urgency of extending legal aid to cover maintenance orders and family law in general.  I know the Minister is about to intervene and tell me about the committee that has been set up on this.  Of that, at least, I am aware.  I hope that this committee will recommend with appropriate speed, and that its recommendations in this area will be implemented as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>I return to my original observation on this Bill, that because it is essentially a Bill which recognises and enforces maintenance orders made either in England, Scotland, Wales or Northern Ireland, it highlights the far better position in which the deserted wife who lives in Wales, Scotland, Northern Ireland, or England finds <Col N="702" /> herself&mdash;a far better position under the domestic law which obtains in those countries.  This must be an incentive to us to put the Irish deserted wife on a position of equality and parity with the deserted wives in these other jurisdictions.  For example, in section 14 (7) (d), there is a role for the district court clerk in that the payment will be made to the district court clerk and if the payment is not being made there will be the possibility for the said district court clerk to take the initiative for enforcement proceedings, enforcing the maintenance order for the wife living outside the jurisdiction; whereas, the Irish wife who has been deserted by her husband who is still living in this country must initiate her own enforcement proceedings.  It would be most welcome to see the district court clerk fulfilling the same role for the Irish wife deserted by her husband who continues to live in this jurisdiction, in order to put her in the same position as the English wife whose husband has deserted and come to live in this jurisdiction.  The English wife who is having the maintenance order enforced under this Bill is already in a remarkably better position than her Irish counterpart because of the much broader basis for seeking that maintenance order in the first place and because of the broader ways in which it can be enforced.  I note that the Minister said in his opening speech:</P>
    <P>&ldquo;I would like to have seen for example, provision for attachment of wages in this Bill.&rdquo;  This is another paradox, that the English wife who got her maintenance order in England to be enforced here can have an order for attachment of earnings.  That can be enforced against a deserted husband living here, but the Irish woman cannot have a similar order made to be enforced against her husband either in a completely domestic context or enforcement by the British courts, because under our domestic law, we do not have attachment of earnings. We do have a provision for this in the Illegitimate Children (Affiliation Proceedings) Act, 1930.</P>
    <P>It is rather depressing to see that&mdash; in so far as my limited researches have <Col N="703" /> gone in any case&mdash;there appears to be no instance of this procedure having been used.  That is a sad reflection on the absence of proper legal advice and the absence of the possibility of getting the knowledge and technical expertise by the single mothers, in this case, who might have got an affiliation order, but would not know how to go about attaching earnings in order to enforce it against the putative father.</P>
    <P>I see this Bill as a very sharp incentive to us here in Ireland to improve rapidly and urgently the position of deserted wives living in this country.  This can only be done by improving the domestic law under which we operate.  We must improve it in relation to the different cases for awarding maintenance orders; the protection which the law offers to the deserted wife; the realistic nature of the remedy by affording her both legal aid, and by introducing a similar role for the district court clerk in taking the initiative in relation to the enforcement of the maintenance orders where there is a failure to pay under these orders.  If we can bring about this sort of reform in our internal law, then I believe that there will be a fair balance in the operation of this Bill.  At the moment I think it is a Bill which highlights the substantially inferior position of the deserted wife in Ireland.</P>
    <P>Section 17 is a very welcome provision in that it gives jurisdiction to the Irish courts where the spouse who has deserted is living outside the jurisdiction.  I think, however, that there is need for much better tracing techniques between the two jurisdictions. I am not sure whether these are matters about which there is need for specific legislation or just need for more real co-operation in the administration of such tracing techniques and resources in this area.</P>
    <P>Those are most of the comments which I wished to make on the terms of this Bill.  I come back to the original framework in which the Minister placed it.  I welcome the fact that he did place it in the context of our general family law and pledged that reform of family law itself is one of <Col N="704" /> the main tasks to be undertaken during his term of office.  I hope that this will be possible, and that it will not be delayed unnecessarily in a very difficult time for the Minister's Department, a time when there must be a very substantial preoccupation with security and with the problems relating to the situation in which we find ourselves.  Emphasis must be placed on the urgent need for family law reform so that the many recommendations will be translated into legislation in a very short time in order to redress what Kathleen O'Higgins, in her study called 70 years of neglect by legislators in this country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to begin by welcoming the Bill and welcoming it precisely in the terms that the Minister presented it.  Again he has presented it as a limited Bill.  He has shown himself aware of its limitation and has declared himself sensitive to the large over-reaching area of family law into which it must ultimately fit.</P>
      <P>I think it will have two immediate advantages, in the sense that it will at least begin to bring some degree of justice and responsibility to bear on deserting husbands and illegitimate fathers.  I am always amused by the use of the rather grandiose and euphemistic word given to fathers, whereas you speak about the illegitimate child&mdash;the one innocent party to the entire arrangement has the pejorative word attached to him or her.  Yet it seems to me that if there is any bastard in the case it is the bastard who gets the girl into trouble and runs out on his responsibilities. This phrase &ldquo;illegitimate child&rdquo; is so caught up in our law and so woven into the whole terminology of legislation that it is almost inextricable from it.  It is a phrase that always offends me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Apart from this, the Bill in itself is useful in that, at least, it reverses the situation that existed.  That escape route to England, as long as it was open, could be seen not only as a refuge but a kind of encouragement to irresponsibility on the part of Irish husbands. The fact that it was lying there openly <Col N="705" /> at their disposal actually encouraged irresponsibility, and the degree of irresponsibility among Irish men is particularly high.  I would say it is well above the international average.  The availability of that route was an incentive, almost, to that kind of irresponsibility. Even if the tracing processes are not brilliant and perfect at least the moral position is now made utterly clear and, of course, the enforcement devices will inevitably improve as the years go on.  So it closes a gap and in a sense, of course, in contemplating it, one is aware of the enormous gaps that loom on every side.</P>
    <P>The 70 years of neglect that Senator Robinson has spoken of are obviously there the minute we look at this, the minute we look forward to next week when we take the Adoption Bill.  The fact is that our family law has been a rather piecemeal affair and in many ways it has been based continuously on archaic premises.  For instance, on the social scene, there is the recent strenuous and salutary work on the part of voluntary societies who suddenly mushroomed in this particular area, of late, in response to an increasing acute situation&mdash;organisations like ALLY, AIM and CONCERN who, with the help of the media have drawn our horrified attention to the degree to which one finds within society battered wives, battered children, children and wives abused, starved, neglected, and humiliated in all kinds of ways, the extraordinary degree of hidden and silent cruelty and suffering that goes on behind the respectable facade of our society.</P>
    <P>It is not just the reticence of the past that answers the problem.  It is not just that now people are beginning to speak out.  There is a correlation between the outcry and the reality. The degree of responsibility among Irishmen in particular is decreasing, and I do not think that education, as we call it, and sophistication and affluence have had a corresponding advance and parallel advance in terms of delicacy, humanity, tenderness, the ability to love, to cherish, to take responsibility for one's wife and <Col N="706" /> family.  In fact, within our affluent society there is a new kind of a swaggering arrogance on the part of the male as he comes lurching home in his Mercedes and his mohair suit or goes lurching out to his golf club later after dinner.  This does inflict a degree of suffering, probably far greater than the cruder and more direct approaches that traditionally have been ascribed to what are known as the working classes, or the unemployed or the labourers.  I noticed that in Senator Brosnan's speech, an excellent speech in its way, he concentrated almost completely on the migrant labourers who go to England, the will o' the wisps, the fly by nights.</P>
    <P>Nearly everybody who knows a situation of an unhappy marriage in this country where the whole area of separation proceedings comes up, knows the extraordinary handicap under which the wife has to operate, if she wants to proceed towards a separation, the fact that she cannot easily lay her hands on the family purse of which half should rightly be hers.  The majority of solicitors do not want to know her particularly well.  In order to get proper redress she has to go to the High Court which is an extraordinarily costly affair.  Most women, at the beginning are disheartened by the very prospect of the process they have to go through in this area.  In the area of the enforcement of this particular measure I am not sure myself&mdash;I am not a lawyer&mdash;as to the degree to which a woman will have to cope with those particular kinds of difficulties, but I am sure the Minister will take into account the difficulties that occur in the whole area of this family law and enact his Bill in such a way as to alleviate that to the furthest degree.</P>
    <P>Behind this is what Brian Faulkner would have spoken about&mdash;the men on the ground or the troops in the the field.  It is one thing to have an enactment on the Statute Book, but we all know that many of the difficulties in our society have nothing at all to do with the law.  The law has to be right, but the means by which the law can be translated from the Statute Book into the fabric of our living situation is even more crucial and, here, I am thinking particularly of the whole area of social <Col N="707" /> service and the social worker.  We have not nearly enough of these in our society.  Everybody knows that.  I know we cannot afford everything we need in every particular area but we certainly need a large increase in the number of social workers&mdash;we have marvellously well-trained and well-motivated ones just waiting to be asked&mdash;within the whole area of family advice and family life.  We should, indeed, ultimately strive towards courts which would specifically deal with family situations. This, I think, is essential.  The problems of loneliness and isolation on the part of the deserted or battered wife makes her feel helpless, defenceless in the face of a society even if she has the law to work on her side.  If she can make contact with somebody who knows the law well, who has the contacts with the legal profession and who knows how to go about getting even the very basic benefits to which she is already entitled, it is of enormous importance.</P>
    <P>I would urge again that this aspect, the whole question of the practical implementation of a law and the making of that law fruitful within the fabric of a human situation, should be taken strenuously into account.  The Minister said in his opening speech that he is very interested in bringing in the attachment of earnings.  He assures the House that maintenance orders can be made to the High Court on desertion and he would take into account the necessity for this.  I should like to know whether, in fact, this is a firm commitment.  Will there be attachment of earnings in future legislation because that would be the teeth which would make this Bill absolutely effective?  It is grossly unjust, obviously clearly unjust and ludicrous that for so many centuries the earnings of the husband have been regarded as his property while the wife is at home rearing his children, cooking his meals, doing all kinds of work 24 hours of the day but somehow or other, his earnings are more or less sacrosanct when the crunch comes.  He can walk away with his earnings and leave her there with the children and let them starve.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="708" /> The question of attachment of earnings is, I think, an open and shut case.  The morality of it certainly seems to me to be open and shut.  I think the quicker we can get the legality of the situation adjusted the better.  I should like to know from the Minister how firm is his confidence that that will become very soon a feature of legislation following on this Bill.  I should like to see, in other words, the greatest possible haste on the part of the Minister towards the objectives which he is clearly cognisant of and to which he is clearly committed&mdash;that is, a more philosophic concern about family life as a whole area of law requiring a particular delicacy of legislation, on the one hand, and a very strong backup in terms of social services on the other.  Much of the difficulty here would be prevented, in fact, if we had proper social services.  These irresponsible young men who run away from their family often run away out of fear, out of guilt, because they have not enough money, because they drank it down at the local.  The wife and the husband are not caught in a kind of web of benign social service to which they can turn in that state of guilt and fear and difficulty, turn to somebody within the society, someone close to them, for aid.</P>
    <P>For too long we have left this kind of family advice in the hands of the churches.  The churches can do a great deal.  The last place the man I am talking about would go is to the church.  The clergyman is the last person he would go to when caught in a state of panic.  The trouble is that, if he runs away, the chances are he will fall into bad habits and he will not come back.  It is, in fact, more important to keep him at home, to advise him, to try to get him to adjust and to make service and direction available before the crime has taken place and before an unfortunate tendency has been allowed to develop in, perhaps, an irreversible way.  It is with these reservations, which are not reservations about the Bill really and, in the strict sense, are not reservations at all, these thoughts <Col N="709" /> and hopes in the larger context of consideration for family law that I very, very heartily welcome the Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney) Patrick M. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to thank the Senators who intervened in the debate for their contributions and for the general welcome they have given to the Bill.  As I pointed out in my opening speech, and this was recognised, this is a limited technical measure to provide the structure within which these orders may be enforced.  It does not get into details of how the absconding husband or father is to be traced.</P>
      <P>Senator Brosnan, and Senator Martin to a lesser extent, made the point about the effectiveness of the Bill in relation to the measures that can be devised administratively to trace the missing people.  This is not something that can be provided for in a statute.  It has to be a matter for administrative co-operation between the jurisdictions concerned.  This point was raised in the other House in the context that it should be a police function.  This is a delicate area.  I do not think it should be a police function.  Other agencies would possibly be better equipped for dealing with this problem.  Maybe, and I will just emphasise maybe, in some way voluntary agencies, such as the Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children, could assist.  But this is not something that can be provided for legislatively.  It is something that has to be worked out administratively.  Indeed, in tracing these people there must be a considerable reliance on what I would call grapevine information. Irish people in Britain&mdash;we will speak of it in this context because this is where the problem is for us&mdash;tend to congregate in certain areas and word very often filters back as to the whereabouts of a particular person.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Some, of course, would be notorious for going underground and would be quite prepared to move from community to community, from city to city, from suburb to suburb, in an effort to ensure that they would never be caught for the purpose of enforcement under this legislation.  They are already expert at it for the purpose of avoiding <Col N="710" /> liability to the British Exchequer. I have no doubt that a person who seriously wants to go underground in a large urban society, such as that which exists in the United Kingdom, can do so and can escape.  This is a reality we have to face and accept. Nevertheless, for those who are not that callous about their obligations and for those who desert but are prepared to wait to be caught, this legislation improves the position.  The fact that there is machinery for going after him may bring him face to face with reality and will, I hope, ensure that many deserting husbands will realise their responsibilities.  It is in that context that I deal with the point raised by Senator Brosnan and his disappointment that the Bill does not provide for arrears of instalment orders.  These arrears arise in the case where a wife in this country has been able to obtain a maintenance order against her husband prior to his leaving the jurisdiction. Up to now that is the only type of order that could be obtained.  He had to be here for service of the proceedings. A considerable amount of arrears might have accrued.  He is now, we will say, in the United Kingdom and he is traceable.  Senator Brosnan asked why should he be allowed avoid those arrears when there is both a moral and a legal obligation on him to pay them.  The question of what to do about this gave us considerable difficulty and, for a number of reasons, we decided to exclude arrears and have the Bill start just from the commencement date so that any such orders would be enforced only as from the commencement date of the Bill.  The reasons are a mixture of the legal and the practical. One legal reason is that we intend to ratify the Hague Convention on the enforcement of maintenance obligations and this Convention imposes an obligation not to have any element of retrospection in the matter of arrears which might have accrued under maintenance orders before the Convention comes into force between the countries concerned.  We should be careful, in domestic legislation being enacted prior to that ratification, to take account of the terms of the Convention and not be in conflict with it when we eventually <Col N="711" /> ratify it.  That is a legal reason.</P>
    <P>There is a domestic legal reason which goes half way towards Senator Brosnan's point.  It is the fact that the Enforcement of Court Orders Act, 1940, dealing with the enforcement of affiliation and maintenance cases, only allows arrears of up to six months to be enforced. There is already a recognition in our domestic legislation that it may not always be practical or desirable to go back to the start and look for the arrears.</P>
    <P>The amount of arrears, even in the days when the weekly order could be for a maximum of £4 only, could have amounted to a considerable sum.  At £4 per week, £208 per year, four years' arrears could amount to more than £800, and in five years it would be coming up to £1,000.  If there was provision for enforcing the payment of these arrears, and they were sought to be enforced against a husband who went to England, I would be afraid that the thought of a burden of that magnitude would drive him underground and put him out of circulation completely.</P>
    <P>The realistic position is to try and enforce, as from now, a weekly payment which is reasonably certain to be paid.  It was my experience, and I am sure the experience of any lawyer who had to take a debt collection action, that many of these cases were not contested.  When it came to the stage of asking the District Court to make an instalment order, in practice we found ourselves asking for an order that we knew would be realistic even though it might be very small in relation to the debt, and even though the proceedings were not defended.  The court would grant whatever order was asked for.  In practice the dictates of reality ensured that we would only ask for a realistic order having regard to the circumstances of the debtor.  In this case it would be unrealistic to allow him be pursued for arrears even though they might be limited to a number of months or years.  Anything that would tend to drive him underground would make the last state of a deserted wife worse than her first. For that mixture of practical and legal <Col N="712" /> reasons, the decision was taken not to include accrued arrears.</P>
    <P>The ultimate sanction to enforce payment of maintenance orders is imprisonment.  Bearing in mind that this Act will be mainly of use to us in the United Kingdom jurisdiction, if there was provision for enforcement of arrears, and arrears were not paid through obstinacy, the British authorities would have the burden of imprisoning the absconding debtor in possibly a large number of cases.  This is not a burden they would be willing to accept.  In any case, imprisonment would be self-defeating because if he were in jail there would be no hope of getting anything.  For these reasons we decided not to bring in the arrears. I sympathise with the humanity of the plea to put them in, but that has to be balanced against the practical realities of the situation.</P>
    <P>Senator Brosnan wanted to know what was the experience in the EEC regarding the tracing of absconding debtors.  As I have stated, this Bill anticipates our accession to the EEC Convention.  It is an interim bilateral arrangement to obviate the delay which accession to the Convention necessarily involves.  Senator Brosnan was wondering if the experience in EEC countries has been of any assistance. It has not, because the EEC Convention is only in operation for just over one year and as far as I know, there has not yet been any survey as to how it is operated within the Six.  I do not know if the same social problems of the deserting husband exist in a fashion analogous to the pattern as between here and the United Kingdom.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson and Senator Brosnan raised the question of what is public policy in the sense in which it is used in the Bill, that is, as one of the grounds for not enforcing a maintenance order in this jurisdiction when sent from the other jurisdiction for enforcement.  Before I deal with that specific point, I should state that the exclusions on these grounds are taken from the EEC Convention. There is the exclusion on the grounds of public policy, where the foreign <Col N="713" /> judgment cannot be reconciled with a judgment in a dispute in the State between the same parties, and where the defaulting party had not sufficient notice of the proceedings against him. These three exclusions are repeated in this legislation.</P>
    <P>What public policy would be in a particular case would be a matter for the courts to decide.  <i>Prima facie</i> it would appear in our situation to arise in the context of the enforcement of maintenance orders arising from divorce proceedings.  Our Constitution prohibits divorce and there are two judgments of the superior courts which give an indication of what the attitude of the courts would be. Unfortunately, the two judgments are not complementary to each other.  I would hesitate to guess, and it would not be appropriate for me to speculate, as to what the courts might find in defining public policy in this area.  That is a matter which is reserved by the Constitution to them. I would not agree with Senator Robinson's point of view that the Legislature should in a Statute endeavour to deal with an area such as this.  It is essentially interpretative and that is what the courts are for.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>But the courts interpret what the Legislature has stated.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>The basic law&mdash;the Constitution&mdash;states that divorce is illegal.  It is a matter for the courts to continue to interpret the Constitution in the light of a maintenance order being sought to be enforced here consequent on divorce or separation proceedings in the other jurisdiction.  This Bill could not attempt to intervene in that area.  This is an area where the division of powers has to be respected and it would be improper for me to attempt to say any more on that subject.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Brosnan raised the other exclusion in paragraph (c) of section 9 which provides that a maintenance order will not be enforced if it is irreconcilable with a judgment given in a dispute between the same parties in the State.  There could be an order <Col N="714" /> in a UK court consequent on divorce proceedings and it is possible to envisage that in this country there could be similar matrimonial proceedings between the parties leading to an order.  Prior to the proceedings in England their might be an order for maintenance here consequent on a desertion.  If these two situations were irreconcilable the order from the other jurisdiction would not be enforced here.  The order made in the domestic courts would have precedence and that is in effect what it means.</P>
    <P>The question of the time limit within which the district court clerk would transmit payments to the maintenance creditor was raised by Senator Brosnan in relation to section 14.  He was worried that there might be delay on this.  My experience of the district court clerk service is that they are universally&mdash;and I use the word advisedly&mdash;an efficient body of men and I would anticipate no delay in that area.  In any event, district court rules will have to be introduced to regulate procedure under this Act.  Those rules are at the present time being drawn up. This is something to which I shall draw the attention of the President of the District Court who is instrumental in drawing up these rules&mdash;and very, very valuably instrumental if I may say so.  I will draw his attention to the point whether there is any necessity to place a time limit on the court in regard to transmitting fees collected.</P>
    <P>With regard to the burden of proof in paternity suits and the admission of medical evidence, this is not a matter for this particular Bill.  I do not propose to go into the merits or demerits of that question.  That would be a matter for an amendment of the affiliation Orders Act if and when that comes to be amended.</P>
    <P>On the question of legal aid, as Senators are aware&mdash;I thank Senator Martin for his gust of wind into my sails; the Minister for Finance has to see the full gale in due course&mdash;the committee to advise on this matter has had its first meeting.  I took the opportunity of indicating to them our general anxiety to see a system of legal aid in <Col N="715" /> operation here.  In anticipation of that, the provision was included in section 13 (1) (d) that one of the documents to be sent to the Master would be a document showing that the maintenance credit was receiving legal aid in the other jurisdiction.  This would be an indication to the courts here that the person's means were such as to entitle him to legal aid, so that if and when we have our system of legal aid in civil cases it would be clear that that party would be entitled to legal aid in our courts.</P>
    <P>I quite agree that legal aid in this whole field of family law is important so that people would have access to the High Court, which is the appropriate court at the moment in cases of separation.  I am conscious of the fact that hardship is caused by reason of the expense of such proceedings.  That is one of the factors which I took into account in trying to expedite the introduction of legal aid.  It is a by-product of our accession to the EEC&mdash;a good by-product&mdash;that legal aid will be forced upon us because the Convention to which we hope to accede provides that the same legal assistance should be available in the differing countries.  In order to comply with our requirements under the Convention we will have to have legal aid.  All these things constitute a full gale blowing in the direction of the Minister for Finance in due course.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson raised the point that it was a pity that this Bill was bilateral and, therefore, somewhat narrow in its operation.  I do not deny that this is a narrow Bill.  It is intended merely to deal with an immediate problem&mdash;our biggest problem in this area is the absconding husband or father going to the United Kingdom. If we had attempted to do all the preliminary work that would be necessary in relation to other jurisdictions for the purpose of including them in this Bill, the legislation would have been delayed for a long time.  There would have had to be an examination of their legal systems to see that reciprocity would be available to us and whether the conclusion of a bilateral agreement with the country <Col N="716" /> concerned would be possible.  We will have to have an international agreement with the United Kingdom before this Bill can come into operation.  I think the best way to approach the task of extending the remedy here to a wider number of countries is via whatever international conventions are available such as The Hague Convention. I think there is a United Nations (New York) Convention which would enable us to have mutual enforceability in this area with a great many other countries.</P>
    <P>The problem we want to solve is essentially that between Ireland and the United Kingdom.  That is why this Bill was kept narrow in scope.  While we were preparing an omnibus piece of legislation to deal with that problem, and the whole field of family law, and introducing all the desirable reforms, such as the attachment of wages, expanding the concept of family default, reforming the marriage laws, many people would continue to suffer.  I have taken the policy decision that the best way, because of the urgency of this particular problem, is to tackle it piecemeal, even though I recognise the word &ldquo;piecemeal&rdquo; can be open to objection and criticism.  Nevertheless, it is bringing ease in cases of hardship and that justifies the piecemeal element.  That is part of that policy being implemented.</P>
    <P>We have to face facts and the hard fact is that the British authorities will have the main burden of enforcement because the traffic is very largely weighted in one direction.  I want to pay tribute to them for the co-operation they have given in all the negotiations and consultations which have taken place at official level in order to produce this Bill.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson asked for clarification of the definition section and whether lump sums are covered.  It is not intended to have this Bill apply to lump sums, with the exception of sums incidental to the birth or to the funeral expenses of the illegitimate child.  If a lump sum should be awarded it can always be enforced in Britain at the moment by suing on the judgment.  To that extent lump sums are already covered.  However, that is getting into a matter of interpretation. <Col N="717" /> As to whether a maintenance order consequent on an instalment order made in connection with the enforcement of a lump sum judgment would be a maintenance order under this Bill, I would not be prepared to hazard a guess, but it would seem to me to be.  I should like to have a closer look at it.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson mentioned a number of paradoxes and she instanced one in connection with the attachment of wages.  But the paradox works in our favour.  The English wife seeking to enforce an English maintenance order in this country would not have the benefit of attachment of wages because we do not have it as part of our domestic law whereas the Irish wife seeking to enforce the order in England would have. This is contrary to the position as expressed by the Senator because the effect of this Bill is to naturalise in our jurisdiction, in our law, the order coming from the other jurisdiction and <i>vice versa.</i>  If an order comes from the other jurisdiction into the State it will be enforced in accordance with our laws of enforcement and <i>vice versa.</i>  It is a paradox but it works in our favour.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I take it the Minister did not really mean that!</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is the reverse as the Senator expressed it.  She expressed it wrongly, if I might say so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is in nobody's favour because it is to our shame, if you like, that our situation as such is to permit it.  I am very conscious of that.  As I have already indicated, in the 19th interim report, which has been accepted in principle, there are matters of detail which have to be examined.  There is no point in rushing into a piece of legislation which turns out to be ineffective, or to have a consequence never dreamt of, so as to demand amending legislation and possibly greater disappointment.  It is being examined as a matter of urgency.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Senator put a finger on a personal problem which I have, namely, <Col N="718" /> that the demands of the Department of Justice are unusual in these times. Nevertheless, I am hopeful that this legislation, which will expand the concept of family default and allow attachment of wages and various other desirable reforms in this field, will be before the legislature in the next session.  I am hopeful of that but I cannot promise it.  If we can get that legislation through, our position here will have improved considerably.  The whole area of family law is under examination by this committee.  This was an interim report, and indeed the whole area of marriage law will have to be tackled sooner rather than later. That raises very large legal implications and opens up a huge legal field, but nevertheless it is something that will have to be tackled in this context.</P>
    <P>I think I have covered the points raised by Senators.  In conclusion I repeat my thanks to Senators for their welcome for the Bill.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>As I pointed out, the interpretation section does not stand up to citation.  For example there are two subsections (1) (a) (b) and (c) in section 3.  I would welcome an opportunity to reflect on what the Minister said on the possibility of bringing in an amendment next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not want to rush the Seanad.  I have the difficulty that I am anxious that this Bill be law before the summer recess, to enable the agreement to be concluded between the two countries during the recess, so as to pave the way for its coming into operation as soon as possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrosnan" hpid="Mr. Brosnan Mr. Brosnan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brosnan</NameTxt>
      <P>I am handicapped by the absence of most of my colleagues from the Front Bench, who are in Europe.  I do not know what their attitude is towards it but I am sure they will be as helpful as possible.  I should prefer if they were here.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 3rd July, 1974.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 4.30 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 3rd July, 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>