<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Tue" Date="28" Month="May" Year="1974" Vol="78" No="4" DateIrish="Dé Máirt, 28 Bealtaine 1974" DateEnglish="Tuesday, 28 May 1974" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="257">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="257" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 3 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Dublin and Monaghan Bombings:" RHead="Expression of Sympathy">
    <Title>Dublin and Monaghan Bombings: Expression of Sympathy.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>This is the first meeting of the Seanad since the tragic events in Dublin and Monaghan recently when four car bombs were exploded with such fatal results.  I feel sure that every Member of the Seanad would desire that we should place on record here today &mdash;the first opportunity we have had &mdash;our very sincere sympathy with the relatives and friends of those who were killed and those who were maimed in those deplorable events.  The other House of the Oireachtas has already recorded the views of everybody there when, at a recent meeting of the Dáil, the spokesmen for the various parties referred to this matter.  I do not wish to make a speech about it.  I know we would all like to record our sympathy.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I feel we would also like to go on record&mdash;and I think it is up to all of us to say this&mdash;as condemning in the strongest possible terms the deplorable events which led to the carnage in the city of Dublin and in Monaghan.  I do not see, and I do not think any of us can see, how happenings of this kind can advance the cause of any section of the Irish people, North or South.  Until all of us see these events in their proper light as callous murders we are in danger of witnessing further events of the same sort.  On the other hand, so far as the people in this part of the country are concerned&mdash;and I am sure this is true also of the vast majority of the people in the North&mdash;<Col N="258" /> happenings of this kind will only steel the determination of the people to try to rid our society, North and South, of violence, hatred and division. I would like again to express to the relatives and friends of those who were killed, injured and maimed the sincere sympathy of this House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to be associated with the remarks made by the Leader of the House in this respect and on behalf of my group also to convey our very sincere sympathy to the relatives of the people who were killed and our good wishes for the recovery of those people who were maimed and injured.  It is important to recognise in this happening a symptom of the violence which has bedevilled society in the whole of our island in recent years.  A condemnation of the acts that occurred in Dublin and Monaghan should be linked with equal condemnation of all acts of violence on the part of people who wish to pursue political objectives in this manner.  We can succeed in achieving political objectives by adopting legitimate means.  Now more than ever before, it is necessary to emphasise this and to condemn in no ambiguous fashion but to condemn unambiguously the pursuit of political objectives by methods such as those which outraged our people and caused such suffering and havoc in the city of Dublin and the town of Monaghan in recent weeks.  We cannot pursue our political objectives in this manner but we can pursue them in a civilised, political manner despite what has been happening in this island in recent days.  Men who feel that political objectives can be achieved in a civilised way must not be deterred and must continue along that path.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Members rose in their places.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1, 2 and 3, in that order.  If not already reached, it is proposed that we interrupt business at 7 o'clock to take Nos. 2 and 3.  It might be of assistance if I indicated that it is proposed to sit tomorrow <Col N="259" /> at 3 p.m.  If the Anti-Discrimination Bill comes from the Dáil it is proposed to have the Second Stage debate and also to continue the discussion on Motion No. 5.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Senator resumes his seat might I remind him there is a meeting of the Committee of Procedure and Privileges at 6 o'clock?  He might, therefore, like to say 7.30 p.m. rather than 7 o'clock.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>That is agreeable to me, if it is to the Senators opposite.  I hope this will not arise, as we may have reached it.  If we do not reach No. 2 shall we say 7.30 p.m. instead of 7 p.m.?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>What is the element of urgency about the Anti-Discrimination Bill that it has to be taken in this manner?  I would refer to Standing Order No. 74, paragraph 1, which refers to a Bill that comes to the Seanad from Dáil Éireann.  It says:</P>
      <P>... save in the case of a Certified Money Bill, and a Bill the time for the consideration of which by the Seanad shall have been abridged under Article 24 of the Constitution, shall not be considered, unless the Seanad otherwise orders, before the expiration of three clear days after it has been received from the Dáil by the Clerk.</P>
      <P>I accept that under Standing Orders the Seanad can order that a Bill be taken less than three days after it reaches the Seanad, but it is clearly the normal and accepted fact that three days should be given.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I suggest that we might leave that until tomorrow's Order of Business.  I was merely giving an indication to the Seanad of what was intended.  It is not ordered for today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>In all fairness I should give an indication now that our group could not agree to the taking of a Bill of this importance, this magnitude and this complexity at this kind of notice.  It is not simply a question <Col N="260" /> of niggling about the exact wording of Standing Orders.  The provision of three clear days has been put down for a very good reason.  It is to provide adequate time for people to prepare their position on a Bill of this importance.  It would be quite wrong and contrary to ordinary parliamentary practice to ask us to take it at that kind of notice.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to ask the Leader of the House to take steps to allow time in the near future to allow a debate on Motion No. 11:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann notes the critical situation in Northern Ireland and requests the Government to outline its policy of reconciliation and the steps it intends to take towards a political solution.</P>
      <P>This was put down in my name and in the names of Senators Browne, Robinson, Quinlan and Brosnahan. Shortly after this motion was tabled the Senators who signed it requested that a debate in the Seanad be held at the earliest possible opportunity to discuss the situation in Northern Ireland.  That was the time at which the delicate Sunningdale negotiations were going on and we were asked not to press this request.  We took a perfectly responsible attitude and did not press our request to have this motion because of the delicate negotiations which were proceeding at that time.  This House is not fulfilling its duty if in the near future it does not have a debate on the situation in Northern Ireland.  We are elected representatives.  We are paid to put our views forthrightly and fearlessly to the people.  Surely our views on the situation in Northern Ireland should be debated in a straightforward manner as soon as possible?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>When we made our request previously the argument presented to us was that the situation in the North was too grave to warrant discussion and that we might in some sense rock the boat.  It is clear that the situation in the North&mdash;and perhaps in this part of the country&mdash;will be grave for a long time to come.  That argument therefore would preclude debate taking place for many years. <Col N="261" /> It is our duty not to step away from a discussion of this nature.  We can only do good in the long term and in general by having a debate on this motion.</P>
    <P>The Lower House discussed the situation in the North on various occasions. It is of the utmost importance that we assert our right&mdash;more than our right; our duty&mdash;to discuss the Northern political situation.  We can only do good by expressing our fears and our hopes, by putting forward policies and asking the Government to make a statement of their policy.</P>
    <P>I hope the Leader of the House will see his way to accede to this request in the near future.  This is a matter of extreme urgency which we should not put off any longer.  We should not accept the excuse that because the situation is grave the Seanad are therefore not to discuss it.  That is treating the Seanad as if it were not a political forum.  We are the body to discuss such deep and serious problems. It is our responsibility.  That is what we are elected to do.  I should like the Leader of the House to take these views into consideration and to arrange a debate on this motion as a matter of urgency.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support Senator West in asking for an early debate on the situation in Northern Ireland.  It may seem strange in years to come, in view of the events which have taken place here over the past 12 months, if there is no attempt to have a debate in this House.  The delicacy of the situation is evident to all.  Rather than being an excuse to avoid having a debate in this House, this ought to be an incentive to try to clarify issues&mdash;to try to have an expression of the views of the Government and of the various representatives in this House on the record of the Seanad at this time.  If we are talking about the whole idea of Parliament being relevant to what is happening in the country, if we are talking about the idea of the Seanad being able to encompass the events which occur in the nation at a particular point in time, we must, as responsible Senators, be afforded the opportunity of a debate of this nature.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="262" /> In a sense it must be seriously regretted that we did not have an opportunity to debate the Sunningdale Agreement shortly after its conclusion. It would have been invaluable to have had the views of the Seanad on that agreement.  More and more there is a need for a public expression of views and for putting opinions on record.  It is not necessary to have opinions that are completely uniform.  There is a value in encouraging people to express their political viewpoints, to put them on the records of the House, and to have a responsive answer from the particular Government of the time.</P>
    <P>Therefore I endorse completely the arguments put forward by Senator West and join with him in asking the Leader of the House if we will be afforded this opportunity in the very near future.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>As regards Senator Yeats's point, we could discuss that on tomorrow's Order of Business.  As he very properly pointed out, it will be necessary to have an Order of the House, which would be made on the Order of Business, if we are to take the Second Stage of the Anti-Discrimination Bill at shorter notice than provided for in Standing Orders.  I was trying to be helpful to the House in mentioning what we have in mind.</P>
      <P>With regard to Motion No. 11, Senator West may be right in his recollection of the arguments advanced, if they were advanced, against taking this particular motion when it was put down previously.  I honestly do not recall having ever argued that this House should not discuss this particular motion because of the grave situation in the North.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>On a point of information and to help the Leader of the House, the arguments on the previous occasion would not be on the record of the House, because the discussions were held in private.  We did not press to have the motion discussed. Senator O'Higgins is therefore correct when he says that this is not on the record of the House.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="263" />
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not recall having ever argued that case either in public or in private, because it is not a point of view I hold.  However, while I have not argued it, there is manifestly good reason at times to take that particular point of view. Sunningdale may have been one of those occasions.  If it was justified in the case of Sunningdale my personal view would be that it is far more justified now.  As Senators will appreciate, this is not a decision which will rest with me.  The particular motion is worded in a way which calls necessarily for a statement of Government policy.  According to the arrangements made in connection with such motions, it will be necessary to have a Minister in attendance for the discussion and it would be very much a matter for the Government in these extremely tense times to decide if it would be appropriate to have a discussion just at this juncture.</P>
      <P>It is fair to say that a similar motion in the other House was postponed at the request of the Opposition because of the tense circumstances which surround the whole situation at the moment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1, 2 and 3 and if No. 2 is not reached by 7.30 p.m. to take it at that time.</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Food Standards Bill, 1974:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Food Standards Bill, 1974: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MarkAClinton" hpid="Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. Clinton) Mark A. Clinton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. Clinton)</NameTxt>
      <P>My purpose in this Bill is to provide the statutory framework for a code of standards which will when fully developed guarantee the quality and wholesomeness of our whole range of human foods right up to the point where they reach the consumer.  The Ministers for Industry and Commerce and Health are associated with me in this Bill since aspects of it fall within their competence.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The process of building a food standards code will take time, but we will not have to start off from scratch. <Col N="264" /> We can of course draw up standards of our own where a special need is seen and where no suitable model exists.  In the main however we will be concerned with the adoption and implementation of existing Codex Alimentarius standards and with the implementation of EEC directives in the food standardisation field.</P>
    <P>The Codex Alimentarius is a commission sponsored jointly by two United Nations bodies&mdash;the Food and Agriculture Organisation and the World Health Organisation.  After some years of preparation it has now brought about 60 standards covering a wide range of foods to the point where it can recommend them to member governments for acceptance. Many more standards are in the course of preparation.</P>
    <P>The business of drawing up a Codex Alimentarius standard is a long and painstaking process of drafting, consultation, discussion, redrafting and so on.  Member governments can, and do, offer their views at several stages of the procedure.  We have participated fully in this work from the beginning, and the officials involved have had the valuable assistance, in framing their comments, of our National Codex Committee, an expert advisory body which represents consumers and the various sectors of the food trade in addition to Government Departments and research bodies.  This Bill has the full support of the National Codex Committee.</P>
    <P>All the EEC countries are members of the Codex Alimentarius Commission and take an active part in its work.  The Community is itself engaged on a programme of food standardisation but it cannot look on its own position in isolation, since the world-wide Codex standards directly concern the Community's trade with third countries.  The Community therefore keeps as close as practicable to Codex standards and the member governments adopt a common approach to the acceptance of those standards.  For example, the Council Directive of 11th December, 1973, concerning certain sugars intended for human consumption, prescribes standards which are close to the recommended <Col N="265" /> Codex standards for sugar and will enable the members of the Community to accept and implement the Codex standards.</P>
    <P>When a government accepts a Codex standard it undertakes that a product which complies with that standard may be freely distributed within the country and that a product which does not comply with the standard may not be distributed.  When I say &ldquo;freely distributed&rdquo; I do not mean that the normal economic controls do not apply&mdash;I mean simply that governments cannot use their domestic quality standards as an excuse to keep products out.  Codex standards are likely to be an important factor in world trade in the future and the Government regard it as essential that we should be in a position to accept and implement them where appropriate.  This will be necessary both to protect ourselves in export markets and to ensure that other countries do not dump substandard food here.</P>
    <P>These then, are the reasons why we need the Bill.  I should now like to refer briefly to its provisions.  The Bill is largely taken up with the power to make regulations&mdash;and the delimitation of that power&mdash;but, as was acknowledged on all sides in the Dáil, there is no practical alternative to delegated legislation in these circumstances. Regulations will, in the course of time, have to be made for a wide range of commodities, and these regulations will have to be constantly changed as international standards change and improve.</P>
    <P>Section 1 defines &ldquo;food&rdquo; and &ldquo;sell&rdquo; for the purposes of this Bill.</P>
    <P>Section 2 provides the power to prescribe food standards and gives an indication of the principal matters with which such standards would deal and of the obligations which they could impose.  It also provides that the Minister concerned must consult with organisations who have a legitimate interest before he makes regulations. As a further safeguard, section 3 provides that a Minister must in each case publish a notice of his intention to make regulations.</P>
    <P>Section 4 is concerned with enforcement. <Col N="266" /> It may appear from subsection (1) that there would be a large corps of inspectors involved, but this is not the case.  We envisage that most of the work would fall to be carried out by health inspectors, who are already responsible for the Food Hygiene Regulations made under the Health Acts.  There may be need, in respect of certain foods or certain premises, to have others&mdash;such as veterinary inspectors&mdash;involved but there is no danger of a horde of inspectors harrying the individual food manufacturer or retailer.  Every officer exercising powers under this legislation would have to be specifically authorised for that purpose and would have to carry an official certificate of his authority. The section also sets out the things which an inspecting officer is entitled to do and these I consider to be the minimum necessary for effective enforcement. Subsection (4) makes it an offence for a person who has obtained information in the course of an inspection to reveal it other than in the line of duty.  This will protect confidential trade information.</P>
    <P>Section 5 deals with food seized by an enforcing officer.  I should like to say here that there would have to be something seriously wrong before this course was resorted to, since there are adequate powers elsewhere in the Bill to deal with any minor infringements of the regulations.  However, where food is seized it can only be destroyed by an order of the District Court. There is provision for compensation where the court considers that the food should not have been seized.</P>
    <P>Section 6 contains a number of presumptions without which a successful prosecution under this legislation would be almost impossible.  It also provides a defence for two types of person who might otherwise be open to prosecution.  The first of these protects any person who has innocently dealt in substandard food provided he has a warranty that the food complied with the regulations.  The second, which I included in response to suggestions in the Dail, protects a person who transports or stores food for hire unless he does so in a manner prohibited by the regulations.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="267" /> The remaining sections of the Bill are self explanatory.</P>
    <P>I hope that the House will agree with the provisions of this Bill and with the objectives which it is designed to achieve.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very necessary Bill.  We will have some suggestions in the form of amendments on Committee Stage.  This is largely a Committee Stage Bill.  For that reason we will not be in a position to give the Committee Stage today.  We want to take Committee Stage on another occasion in order to consider the Bill in detail and put down the necessary amendments.</P>
      <P>I accept the basic principle put forward by the Minister that it is necessary to adopt these standards for two very good reasons: &ldquo;to protect ourselves in export markets and to ensure that other countries do not dump substandard food here&rdquo;.  There is a general movement, not just in the European Economic Community but throughout the world, towards common standards in food production, wholesaling, retailing and consumption.</P>
      <P>One may from a legal point of view object to the fact that it is almost entirely delegated legislation. I accept that in an area of enforcement such as this, where one has to comply with a growing body of international regulations or a growing code of international behaviour and enforcement in regard to food distribution, it is imperative to have delegated facilities available to the enforcement authority.  It is a flexible area.  It is important as far as we are concerned, both in regard to food coming to our markets from abroad and to our exports, that we have standards in common with those throughout the world, and in particular with those in the EEC countries.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In section 6 there is a question in regard to prosecution, where a number of presumptions are written in in statute form.  Again the onus of proof is shifted here.  In classical legal terms it could be argued to be wrong, but I feel it is necessary in an important <Col N="268" /> matter of this kind, vitally affecting our most important industry and basic values in regard to consumption, advertising, production, distribution and so on.</P>
    <P>I will conclude by saying that the Bill is acceptable in broad outline as far as we are concerned.  It is necessary both from the social point of view at home and from the point of view of our international position as a trading country.  There are a number of technical aspects that could be improved.  The Seanad should be enabled to have a very close look at the Bill between now and the Committee Stage when amendments can be put down that could be of a constructive nature to improve the Bill in its application.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say a few words on the Bill.  First of all, I should like to welcome it.  It is very important in a country such as ours, which is not only an agricultural country producing food for consumption within its own shores but, even more important, producing agricultural produce of all kinds for export abroad.  It would be a serious reflection on us if we were not to welcome this Bill wholeheartedly.  If the Bill can be improved on the Committee Stage, as Senator Lenihan suggests, we should not hesitate to incorporate amendments in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister made it quite clear at the outset of his speech that this Bill is intended to provide the statutory framework for a code of standards which will when fully developed guarantee the quality and wholesomeness of our whole range of human foods up to the point where they reach the consumer.  In other words, this Bill is not intended to be the ultimate in legislation for the protection of the consumer.  Reading through the Bill and listening to the Minister's speech it struck me that further legislation is obviously going to be necessary in the years ahead. We in this country are becoming largely an urban society.  The days have long passed for most of the people living in this country when food was either reared on two or <Col N="269" /> four feet or produced from the land in the form of vegetables and cooked in the home farm or very close to where it was grown or reared.  Those days are long gone.  Some of us will probably still remember them.  We are living in a very different world, where the consumer is daily bombarded through TV, radio or newspaper advertisements enticing him or her to purchase all sorts of exotic foods in tins or packets of one kind or another.</P>
    <P>Therefore, it is obviously vitally necessary that the consumer is protected and is in a position to judge whether, in fact, the product advertised&mdash;in some instances at a colossal cost&mdash;is of a certain minimum quality and has a certain degree of wholesomeness.  Unfortunately it is easy nowadays to make even synthetic foods tempting by additives of all kinds.  I wonder whether the words &ldquo;quality&rdquo; and &ldquo;wholesomeness&rdquo; cover all the requirements for the protection of the consumer.  I suggest that they do not.  It will be found that further requirements will have to be added to the requirements in this Bill.  It is not unusual in the process of manufacture to add elements that may be injurious if they exceed a certain minimum content in a product.  This does not appear to be covered in the Bill.  Perhaps I am wrong.  An article or product can be said to be of a minimum standard and certainly can be wholesome if it appeals to the palate of the consumer but that does not necessarily ensure that the consumer is protected in every sense.</P>
    <P>A day may come when we will have minimum requirements in regard to protein and other similar standards branded on packets and tins of food. It is now becoming more usual for manufacturers of animal feeds to have to do this.  Farmers are aware of the necessity of knowing what is inside the bag of compound or feeding stuffs.  I suggest that the human consumer will need to be protected to a similar degree in the years ahead. We should now be making preparation for this type of protection to ensure that not only will the packet contain something that looks wholesome <Col N="270" /> and is of a minimum standard, but also that it will be free from any additives that could prove detrimental to the consumer.</P>
    <P>I am not quite certain whether this Bill covers travelling shops, ice cream vans and similar types of movable shops.  Perhaps it does.  The Bill certainly has a very wide application. In his reply the Minister might confirm that it does in fact cover these shops because they are a growing means of trade.  There is nothing wrong with that.  They provide a very useful service in certain areas, particularly at hurling and football matches.  They should also be subject to the same stringent regulations as the ordinary shopkeeper whose premises are wide open to inspectors from any of the three Departments referred to.</P>
    <P>In connection with the inspection of certain foods, I should mention that the distribution of milk is now divided between the Minister's own Department and the Department of Health.  Some form of co-operation, co-ordination or rationalisation of this system is desirable.  The regional health boards are obvious bodies to look after this in a co-ordinated form.  In the case of milk or other animal products all processes, from the production to the bottling or distribution to the ultimate consumer, should come under one Department.  The responsibility should not be divided.  We are told that the National Codex Committee:</P>
    <P>... are an expert advisory body which represent consumers and the various sectors of the food trade in addition to Government Departments and research bodies.</P>
    <P>I do not know whether manufacturers <i>per se</i> are represented on that committee. If they are not, they should be.  The conditions under which food is produced can have a vital effect on the ultimate product.  Take, for example, the use of artificial fertilisers. Standards must be laid down to ensure that the food which reaches the consumer will not be contaminated from the beginning.  The days when wheat and such products were grown with the use of organic <Col N="271" /> manures is gone.  We live in a more sophisticated age so far as the use of fertilisers, manufacture and distribution are concerned.</P>
    <P>There should be some control on the advertising of foods.  The bigger the company the more they have to spend on advertising.  The success for their products is assured.  Some household products, which I do not wish to mention in the House, are so well-known and backed by such advertising strength that no competitor could hope to rival them.  All of us are conversant with some prominent, international brand names.  Any effort at competition can be either bought out or put out of business quickly.  Where a product is advertised with a background of pop music and plenty of noise it does not necessarily mean it is the best product.  An opportunity should be given for adequate competition in the food trade in all its aspects.  This does not come within the Minister's ambit but it should be taken into consideration when talking about the protection of the consumer. The consumer can be protected by what is in the tin, but he or she is not protected from exploitation, price-wise or otherwise, under the terms of this Bill.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill.  It establishes the framework.  An agricultural food-producing country should welcome it wholeheartedly.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is necessary if we are to survive as a food-packaging country.  The Bill does not cover sufficiently the question of meat packaging.  The main part of the Bill is concerned with the power to make regulations.  Section 2 provides the power to prescribe food standards.  I accept that would be the main strength of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In his speech the Minister said the implementation of the Bill would be left to veterinary officers and health inspectors.  The Minister and his Department are aware that veterinary officers and health inspectors already have a backlog of work.  The health inspector is already overburdened with housing needs, and so on.  Those <Col N="272" /> who come from rural areas know that the veterinary officer is greatly overworked.</P>
    <P>The Department have trained veterinary officers with knowledge of the packaging of food.  Nevertheless the machinery of government through this channel is too weak and slow.  We are a long way behind in these matters. The Minister and his Department must accept this.  It is to be hoped that we can provide the machinery to implement the Bill and that we will not be forced to seek help from veterinary officers or health inspectors who are already overburdened.</P>
    <P>There is a great need for this Bill. The regulations should provide for special attention to the packaging of sausage meat.  Sometime ago I had occasion to visit two establishments which produce sausage meat in Dublin city.  I was surprised to note that no meat whatsoever was included in the products sold as sausages.  They were made from meal and water.  I was accompanied by a qualified butcher. He was amazed at how the preservative was applied to the food, if it could be called food.  It was applied to the food by sprinkling with the hand.  One drop of that preservative, which was added in such a sloppy, careless manner, would burn the toe out of a shoe.  I wrote to the Minister for Health to express my alarm after seeing this.  In the second establishment I visited the lungs of cattle were being used.  I do not know if this is permissible.  I have not a palate for that type of food.  No regulations were displayed.  If the public could see how those sausages were manufactured they would be horrified.  I have not eaten any sausages since then.  These new measures should cover and eliminate this.</P>
    <P>In these days a quick snack on the road and pub grub are commonplace. There are people travelling from place to place in vans who call into the lounges or pubs and sell frozen pies or ready-cooked food.  There should be a proper description on the wrappers, giving the weight, date and food content.  This should be attended to under this Bill immediately and <Col N="273" /> treated as urgent.  There is no control at the moment.  I welcome the Bill.  If it means the introduction of Codex standards it can only do good.</P>
    <P>There is one other aspect of food packaging and selling which might escape the regulations made under the Bill.  We import large quantities of canned fish.  It is possible to buy a tin of salmon which came from Japan or the Argentine.  It may not be fair to mention particular countries.  We have little control over what is sold in such tins.  This fish is packed by very big multinational companies.  I do not know how we can control the contents of those tins.  Secondly, the food varies.  In some instances although it may be called tinned salmon it tastes very unlike salmon.  I would hope that we have some control over the type of food marketed here, whether it comes from Hong Kong or from Killybegs.  We should have standards that are not easily overlooked by the big companies who have massive marketing and advertising agencies. We should have the machinery to administer this Bill.  It is too weak to tackle these giants.  I hope we will deal with these problems now because the public are entitled an assurance that what is being packeted and what is being sold in the shops is safe to eat.</P>
    <P>I welcome the Bill.  I certainly hope that the Minister does not depend on the veterinary officers and the health inspectors for its implementation.  I am satisfied that those two sets of officers have not the time to implement the Bill.  I cannot see any value in introducing it if that is the only way the Minister has of implementing it.  I hope he will find some other way of enforcing the regulations.  This Bill is overdue.  It can only do good.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MarkAClinton" hpid="Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. Clinton) Mark A. Clinton">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. Clinton)</NameTxt>
      <P>I want to thank the Members of the Seanad for the way in which they have dealt with this Bill.  It is fair to say that the attitude is one of general welcome for the Bill and what it contains.  That was also the attitude in the Dáil.  There was a feeling that we had to have legislation of this sort and that the very existence of such legislation would provide a <Col N="274" /> safeguard against the various dangers that have been expressed by the Members who have spoken.</P>
      <P>The question of the importance of doing something about advertising was raised again.  This is something which, in fact, is not in the Bill.  The question of advertising gave rise to comment also in the Dáil.  It was mentioned that there was no provision in the Bill to deal with advertising which was regarded generally as being deceitful and over-pushful, particularly in an age when food has become much more complicated.  This is the age of the readymix and instant foods.  The feeling generally was that as long as you had straight foods you had fairly safe foods.  Now with all the readymix products that are available and all the dressed-up products that exist&mdash; dressed-up for colour, dressed-up for preservation and so on&mdash;perhaps there may be many quite unsafe products around.</P>
      <P>In relation to the advertising aspect, which is not covered in this Bill, the Minister for Industry and Commerce proposes to introduce legislation before the end of the year to take care of advertising.  The feeling was that it would be wrong to deal with advertising in a piecemeal way.  It was felt that it would be much better that all types of advertising should be covered comprehensively in one Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Russell raised the point that there should be information on the packet concerning the quality, nutritive value and safety of the product. This is fully covered in section 2 of the Bill where all the points are outlined that may be covered by regulation such as the names of the food, the description, composition and quality of the food, the methods of manufacture and preparation of the food, the additives used in the manufacture and preparation&mdash;many people are concerned about additives these days&mdash;the contaminants, including pesticide residues, in food, hygiene in relation to food, time limits for consumption of food, packaging, labelling and presentation, transportation, storage and distribution, weights and measures and matters consequential <Col N="275" /> on or ancillary, incidental or supplementary to any of the foregoing matters.</P>
    <P>Section 2 covers comprehensively any aspect of food preparation, presentation and transportation.  Anything that might affect the general quality of the food is fully covered in this section.</P>
    <P>Senator McGowan expressed his concern about a couple of firms in Dublin who were producing very inferior-quality sausages with no meat content whatever.  It is quite obvious that if there is not a regulation in existence at the moment covering this point it is quite easy to provide such a regulation.  I am aware, however, that most institutions which buy sausages have requirements in regard to meat-content of a certain percentage, and this is a pretty high percentage. It is quite surprising that any firm could get away with producing sausages with only meal and no meat, and hope to sell them.  This is quite surprising to me.  It is fair to say that on the whole our food standards in this country are very high.  It would be wrong to give the impression, simply and solely because we are bringing in this legislation to protect food standards in the future and to be in line with the other EEC countries in regard to food standards, that the standards we have at the moment are in any way inferior to the standards in those countries.  We have very high standards in this country and we can be very proud of them.  Of course, there will always be the occasional small organisation trying to make &ldquo;a quick buck&rdquo;.  I do not think any large organisation that is serious about selling its product in any quantity over a period will have recourse to low standards.  Such an organisation will ensure for their own sake, if not for anything else, that the quality is likely to be good.</P>
    <P>Senator McGowan also spoke about imported tinned fish.  He had certain doubts about it.  This, of course, is fully covered.  If fish is imported in this way nobody can be expected to open the tins and be certain of the <Col N="276" /> quality.  The importer is held responsible. If he has a warranty he is safe enough, but he must be responsible for that warranty.  There must be somebody within the country who is responsible for the quality of food imported. That is the reason for insisting on the warranty.</P>
    <P>I think I have covered all the points raised.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Next Stage?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MarkAClinton" hpid="Mr. Clinton Mr. Clinton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Clinton</NameTxt>
      <P>I had hoped that because it was not a controversial Bill we might be able to take all Stages today but Senator Lenihan expressed the view that perhaps he might be putting down amendments on the Committee Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>I think that a Bill of this kind, which is more a Committee Stage Bill than a Second Stage Bill, ought to be left over to consider whether we should put down amendments.</P>
      <P>Committee Stage ordered for Wednesday, 5th June, 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prisons Bill, 1974:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Prisons Bill, 1974: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney) Patrick M. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to apologise to the House for my absence when the matter was first called; it came unexpectedly.</P>
      <P>This short Bill proposes to extend, for three years, section 2 of the Prisons Act, 1972, which makes provision for the transfer of prisoners from the civil prisons to military custody and for related matters.</P>
      <P>The 1972 Act was passed immediately after the riot which occurred in Mountjoy prison in May, 1972.  The destruction caused in the riot so reduced prison accommodation that it was essential to transfer some prisoners and the only place they could be transferred to was military custody. Those transferred were persons requiring a high degree of security.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Since then however factors have existed in the overall situation which <Col N="277" /> make it essential to continue the present arrangements.  If we are to have a prison system geared to rehabilitation then there must be peace in our prisons; an absence of agitation and tension.  This, in my opinion, can only be achieved by the careful segregation of prisoners into suitable categories or groups.  It might be helpful to Senators if I were to give some details of prison accommodation available for male offenders and how the accommodation is being used.</P>
    <P>The largest prison is Mountjoy, which can house about 450 male prisoners. It is the principle committal prison in the State and at the moment takes all what I might describe as ordinary long-term prisoners, together with all other prisoners from outside the areas served by Limerick and Cork prisons.  It is an old building which requires radical adaptation and restructuring to make it well-serviced, with an increased emphasis on rehabilitation, and at the same time, secure.  Although this long-term work has started, it will soon be necessary to reduce the population in Mountjoy considerably to enable the major part of the work to commence.  This will be possible as soon as the new accommodation for the training of selected prisoners now nearing completion beside Mountjoy, and the renovated Arbour Hill prison are brought into operation.  The new training unit will be able to accommodate 96 prisoners but, of course, it will be essential to build up its population very gradually so that a satisfactory regime may be established by stages to enable full value to be obtained from the very advanced educational and training facilities being provided in it. The renovated Arbour Hill prison will accommodate about 100 prisoners and will cater mainly for a category of prisoners who are likely to respond to the particular training in industrial skills which the prison will be specially equipped to provide.  It will not be a high security prison and the prisoners sent there will not be of a kind that need high security.</P>
    <P>Also in Dublin there is St. Patrick's Institution, which is a place of detention for young male adult offenders. <Col N="278" /> I should say that St. Patrick's has at the moment a near capacity population.</P>
    <P>Outside Dublin we have Limerick, Cork and Portlaoise prisons and three &ldquo;open&rdquo; institutions: Shanganagh Castle, Loughan House and Shelton Abbey.  Limerick prison can accommodate about 100 male prisoners and is a committal prison for the South West.  It works constantly to full capacity.  It cannot be described as a highly secure prison and adequate educational and work facilities have yet to be provided in it.</P>
    <P>Cork prison, which is the former military detention barracks, is being extensively renovated and added to. In effect it serves the counties of Cork and Waterford.  The conditions there for its present population of about 65 are barely adequate.  It may shortly be necessary to vacate the prison altogether to allow the reconstruction work to be completed.  When completed early next year Cork will be a modern well-serviced prison for about 100 prisoners but it will not be a high security prison.</P>
    <P>Portlaoise Prison is the only place where reasonable, but not ideal, conditions of security obtain and since last November it is being used to house offenders who are a homogeneous group of subversive criminals and have to be accommodated in a secure prison.</P>
    <P>There are 32 prisoners in the Military Detention Barracks at the Curragh. I do not wish, for obvious reasons, to comment in any detail on the individual prisoners there. Suffice it to say that they are considered to represent a threat to the security and good order of the prisons. The difficulty with them is that when mixed with ordinary-type prisoners they can foment such disorder as to make the prison unworkable and make normal rehabilitative work impossible. They require a high degree of security.</P>
    <P>Straightaway therefore Mountjoy, Limerick, Cork and Arbour Hill prisons, the &ldquo;open&rdquo; centres and the new accommodation near Mountjoy can be ruled out as suitable places for <Col N="279" /> them.  Portlaoise prison might be suitable but it is not possible to place them in Portlaoise in the company of the other group of high-risk prisoners without endangernig security there.  Military custody is the only alternative.</P>
    <P>I have decided in fact that the best long-term solution is to build a special unit to house prisoners of this type. This unit will be one of maximum security capable of housing up to 30 high risk prisoners and it will be located in the Portlaoise prison complex. Preliminary work has started on it but it may take up to three years to complete it.  It may not be readily understood why a maximum security unit should take so long to complete. The fact is that a structure of this sort is completely different in nearly every possible way from structures of any other kind.  Careful consideration has to be given to even the minutest details of lay-out and equipment and to the materials which are used.  As well as that the new unit must be integrated into an ongoing prison complex, the security of which has to be maintained throughout and this in its own way does not make it any easier to get work done expeditiously.  While it may be possible to dispense with military custody for civilians before then I am afraid that it is essential to provide for the possibility of military custody for that three years.</P>
    <P>An alternative to military custody might seem to be the transfer of the Curragh Military Detention Barracks to civilian control to be operated as a civilian prison.  I am satisfied that this is not possible.  Apart from the basic objection to having a civilian controlled enclave in the heart of a military complex, there are not adequate staff resources in the prison service to run the Curragh Military Detention Barracks and at the same time meet current and prospective commitments in the civil prisons.  The task of operating military custody must be an unwelcome burden to the Defence Forces at the present time and I regret that it should be necessary to prolong it.  I shall do all I can to relieve them of it as quickly as possible.  In the <Col N="280" /> meantime I know the Defence Forces are doing everything possible to provide as good a regime as possible for prisoners in military custody.  For example, in liaison with my Department educational classes are being provided in the Curragh Military Detention Barracks by two teachers made available by the County Kildare Vocational Educational Committee. Recreation facilities to the maximum feasible extent have been provided. The possibility of extending and augmenting these facilities is being kept under review.</P>
    <P>I regret the necessity for this Bill.  I also wish to apologise for the fact that the Bill has been introduced at this late stage.  I was in fact considering whether the prisoners in question could be accommodated otherwise than in military custody and, as I have said, it is with reluctance that I have come to the conclusion that they cannot.</P>
    <P>I will conclude by saying that I am fully satisfied that the security of our prison system makes the continuation of military custody essential, and I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to make a preliminary point which we have made on other legislation that has come before this House in recent weeks.  It relates to the incompetence of the Government in rushing legislation through both Houses of the Oireachtas.  We have had it from the Minister for Local Government in regard to two measures, the Electoral Bill and the Local Government Bill. We now have it here from the Minister for Justice in regard to the Prisons Bill.  This Bill is, quite simply, a continuation of the existing Prisons Act of 1972, a simple two-section Bill continuing that Act in operation.  It was rushed into the Dáil last week and is now brought before the Seanad today with a special motion for early signing by the President in order to secure its enactment, which must be secured if the Bill is to be effective before 31st May, 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Here again, as in the case of the Minister for Local Government, is an <Col N="281" /> example of legislation being hustled through the Oireachtas.  It is bad for parliamentary institutions&mdash;and I want to repeat this point again&mdash;that business should be conducted in this way.  I regard it as fundamental for a Government in a democratic society, if they have any respect for the institutions of democratic society, to organise their business through the Houses so as to enable responsible debate to take place.  It certainly is not helping matters to hustle a Bill into the Dáil last week, to hustle it into the Seanad this week and to have a motion for early signature allied to it, all on the basis of having it enacted before the 31st of this month, which will be in a few days' time. Surely it was quite obvious to the Minister for the past nine months, in view of the mounting seriousness of the security situation in the island as a whole, that the extension of the Prisons Act of 1972 was basic to the security of the State.  I do not see what sort of waffling, or second thoughts or other thoughts, a responsible Government or a responsible Minister for Justice could have had in regard to this matter for the past nine months.  It must have been quite obvious to him, to his officials and to the Government that this Bill would have to be accepted for three years.</P>
    <P>The Act was introduced in 1972 and was severely criticised.  I do not intend to follow up what I would regard as the rather sterile debate of 1972.  I do not believe in debates of that kind.  I shall not quote from the extensive criticism that was offered in the Dáil and Seanad in regard to the Prisons Bill, 1972, when it was going through the Oireachtas.  At that time we had a serious security situation which was nothing like the situation we have now, in which the whole problem of the security of this island has escalated into one of very serious proportions.  It is quite obvious that it is necessary to continue an important measure of this kind.  It is essential that provision be made for the transfer of prisoners from civil prisons to military custody, particularly in the case of high security risk prisoners.  That is basic.  Unfortunately, in the context of the current <Col N="282" /> problems with which we live, this situation will continue.</P>
    <P>Why should it be necessary to come here at the very last minute and in a very apologetic way suggest a measure that quite obviously must be introduced?  We support the measure fully, for the reasons I have mentioned, on the basis that we are a responsible Opposition.  When, in far less dangerous situations we had the time, the perspicacity and the wisdom to see the necessity for this measure, it was violently opposed on the basis that it was unnecessary, illiberal and that we were being arrogant.</P>
    <P>Legislation of this kind is essential in the present context.  The Minister himself has set out very clearly why it is necessary.  To put it bluntly, it is essential to have in military custody people who foment riot or who have the mentality for fomenting riot, trouble and terrorism in prisons.  Unfortunately, in the situation in which we now find ourselves, we are likely to have more men of violence of that kind from every side.  That is a fact of life and there is no point in running away from it in view of the two extremes that exist in this island.  We had an example of this violence, unfortunately, in Monaghan and Dublin recently.</P>
    <P>Therefore the need for this Bill is unquestionable, but I question the seriousness of a Government in doing their business when it was quite obvious for the past 12 months that this Bill needed to be introduced.  It is essential&mdash;I agree with the Minister on this&mdash;that people of this kind should be separated from the ordinary run-of-the-mill lawbreaker, who can, perhaps, be induced to change his habits by training methods, by psychological help, or by advice.  Many excellent reforms have been introduced into our prison system and are applicable to the ordinary type of lawbreaker who happens to make mistakes and who should be properly treated.  Training facilities, as stated by the Minister, are available in our civil prisons for that category.  I do not see why there should be any consideration or any question in the Government's mind, short of not having <Col N="283" /> guts, in facing up to the fact that the other type of security prisoner is best suited to military custody.</P>
    <P>The Minister stated that he was considering if the prisoners in question could be accommodated otherwise than in military custody.  It was with reluctance he said that he came to the conclusion that they cannot.  Of course, they cannot.  There is no need for reluctance or consideration about it.  It is a fact that military custody is the appropriate custody for this particular type of prisoner.  The whole argument presented by the Minister in his introductory speech leads one inescapably to that conclusion that you do not mix the two types of prisoner.  If you are going to have prisoners who are concerned about overthrowing the institutions of the State, be they of the extreme Orange or the extreme Green kind, it is quite obvious that they should not be accommodated with the normal civil prisoners.</P>
    <P>I cannot see why this Bill is being introduced at such a late stage, after much doubt and with apologies to the House.  As far as the Minister is concerned, there is no need to apologise to this side of the House.  We support him fully in the implementation of this measure.  What we do not support is the prevarication of the Government in regard to it, the lack of consistency and the attitude of mind that appears to be unable to face up to responsibilities.  Any attempt to deal responsibly with problems that affect the basic security of the State will have the full approval of this side of the House.  We shall agree completely with any Government measure in that regard, but the Government will meet severe criticism of any inability to face up to their responsibilities or of any attitude that suggests&mdash;as their handling of this measure does&mdash;a dilatory attitude, an attitude of prevarication or apology in regard to people of this kind.  This matter can only be dealt with as was proposed in the Prisons Bill, 1972, now the Prisons Act, 1972.</P>
    <P>This extension is necessary also to deal with the problem which, unfortunately, may escalate.  We suggest to <Col N="284" /> the Minister and the Government that there is no need to have massive reservations in matters of this kind.  We, as a Government, took immediate action at all stages when the essential security of the State was threatened. We did so in regard to the passing of this legislation; we did so in regard to the Offences Against the State Act in December, 1972.  On each occasions we were opposed, as we were in regard to other legislation of this kind. We now find that legislation adopted <i>in toto</i> by the Government and continued, as in the case of the present legislation.</P>
    <P>We welcome the conversion of the two parties comprising the present Government to our sane and responsible attitude.  The criticism I have is that after 18 months in Government they should realise that there is no need to be pussyfooting about this Bill.  There is no need to come here at a very late stage, with apologies, with a Bill that is essentially necessary.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to compliment the Minister on the spirit in which he has introduced the Bill into the House.  Unlike Senator Lenihan, I think the Minister's attitude is a very proper one.  We would all agree, no matter how determined we are in relation to violence and to matters of security, that if it were at all possible to do so the proper way to treat criminals in our jurisdiction is under the civil jurisdiction, in the custody of the civil authorities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It was only with reluctance and because of a particular situation which had arisen in Mountjoy in May, 1972, causing a certain amount of destruction and devastation of the premises which left accommodation short, that the then Fianna Fáil Government felt they had no alternative in the circumstances but to introduce the Prisons Bill, which it is now proposed should be extended.  It was only in exceptional circumstances that the Fianna Fáil Government&mdash;and I hope I am not doing them any injustices when I say this&mdash;a civilian Government of a democratic country, felt it was proper that civilian prisoners should be allowed to be transferred to military custody.  The Minister's attitude <Col N="285" /> is precisely the same.  However, the Minister had the good grace to tell the House that he was considering if there was any way out or if he would be forced to continue an Act which must be regarded in any democratic country as an exceptional Act. After that consideration, in the interests of security and having regard to the lack of accommodation at the moment, he felt reluctantly compelled to propose to both Houses of the Oireachtas a continuation of the provisions of this Act.  I regard that as a very proper, democratic and open attitude on his part.  I am disappointed at the attitude adopted by Senator Lenihan, as indicated in his speech.</P>
    <P>There is another danger about transferring prisoners of a particular category to military custody.  The transfer of these prisoners to military custody may elevate their position in the eyes of subversives.  They might claim they are not, and should not, be treated as criminals and that this is recognised by the Government.  This is a risk which the Minister and Government undertake by continuing this measure.  This risk existed from the time the Act was first introduced as a Bill by the Fianna Fáil Government.</P>
    <P>My recollection of the discussion on that Bill was that it was very detailed and searching and not obstructive. The necessity and the exceptional circumstances, as outlined by the Minister at the time, were accepted.  Examination was given to the Bill as it stood, because in our particular democratic process the Bill was unusual and exceptional.  People in both Houses were concerned to ensure that the powers being given to the Minister would be used only in the particular circumstances for which they were required by the then Government and now by this Government.</P>
    <P>The Bill has been in operation for over two years.  Any fears which anyone had, under either Government, that there might have been an abuse of the powers provided in the Act, have been completely dispelled, both by the present Minister and his predecessor. But it is right that the Minister should adopt an attitude of <Col N="286" /> reluctance to the continuance of this Bill.  It is my hope, and the Minister's also, that the necessary structural alterations in the physical buildings of our prisons will be undertaken and completed as speedily as possible. Then we can depart from this measure and return to the ordinary process of having these prisoners in civilian custody.</P>
    <P>The Minister mentioned that because of the particular programme of work to be undertaken, the minute attention to detail required in connection with the high security block of the Portlaoise prison complex, the building work will be slow moving and will take time.  Three years is the projected timetable for the work.  On that account the Minister finds it necessary to get an extension of three years.  However if the time is less, the retransfer of such prisoners to civilian custody will take place.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senator Lenihan has already said, we support the provisions of this Bill.  In spite of what the Leader of the House suggested, we welcome the fact that the Minister, and the Coalition parties, have considerably changed the attitude they held at the time the original Bill was put through by the former Government. It is worth referring to the fact that at the time the Prisons Bill was put through there was an emergency situation because Mountjoy Prison had been to a considerable extent destroyed by a riot.  The fact that there was an obvious and continuing emergency in the Prison Service did not preserve the then Fianna Fáil Government from very considerable criticism from the Opposition and from suggestions that this was another example of the generally dictatorial attitude allegedly adopted by Fianna Fáil Ministers.  However times, circumstances and Governments change. Now the Minister comes in not merely with the continuing Bill, but a Bill which extends for three years, in totally different circumstances, the provisions of the original Prisons Act.  The emergency is now over but nonetheless the Minister has decided to continue the provisions of the Act. <Col N="287" /> We accept his reasons and are prepared to support them.</P>
      <P>The Minister apologised in the second last paragraph of his opening statement for being so late in bringing in the Bill.  We accept the apology, but we are entitled to query if it was necessary to spend well over a year in taking this decision.  I accept that it is with reluctance that the Minister came to the conclusion that these provisions must be continued. We understand, in view of his former attitude, that it was a difficult decision for him to take.  However, the Minister had a year in which to make the decision.</P>
      <P>The Minister and his fellow-Ministers must understand that one of the difficulties about being in Government is that decisions must be made, and in particular difficult decisions. The fact that they are difficult does not mean that they will by themselves go away.  Problems remain and have to be decided.  To leave a problem of this kind until the very last moment, to introduce a Bill in the Dáil precisely ten days before it must become law, with only ten days for all Stages to go through the Dáil and Seanad, is simply incompetent administration. We can be in no doubt about that. One could forgive an individual instance of this kind, where for some reason or other a Minister had refrained from taking a decision in time.  But the Minister is one of a long line of Ministers who are behaving like this.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>We had the ludicrous situation a few weeks ago where the House was called to deal with a Bill which the Dáil was supposed to pass the night before for the Minister for Local Government.  The Dáil did not pass the Bill, so we had no business.  The following week the same Minister brought in a Bill relating to the local elections.  It, too, had a time limit.  He had had over a year to consider that Bill and again it had been left to the last minute.  He told us that we had three hours to pass it through all Stages.  Now this Minister tells us this Bill must be in force by Friday next. <Col N="288" /> Therefore, we must take all Stages and again, as last time, support a motion for earlier signature by the President.  Again we were told today by the Leader of the House that a very big, important and complex Bill, the Anti-Discrimination (Pay) Bill, which has not even yet been passed by the Dáil, is supposed to be taken by this House tomorrow.</P>
    <P>This is another example of utterly incompetent and dilatory administration. Have the members of this Government any interest in the democratic process?  Have they any conception of what the parliamentary process means?  Legislation is brought before both Houses of the Oireachtas and debated through the various Stages in order to give interested parties an opportunity of making their feelings known.  Have the members of this Government any conception of what all this means?  Do they look upon the parliamentary process as a nuisance?  The Bills are drafted in their Departments.  The Ministers say: &ldquo;This is grand.  Let us get it through Parliament as quickly as possible.&rdquo;  I have been a Senator for a long time.  I have never seen anything like the succession of Ministers coming in here over the last few weeks looking for all Stages of their Bills within hours and suggesting we meet on particular days in the hope that the Dáil would perhaps have passed the Bill the night before.  This is a ludicrous way of doing business and suggests that the members of this Government have not an adequate grasp of their own business and certainly have no adequate respect for democratic traditions.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose to oppose this Bill.  Perhaps I shall be the only Senator to go so far as to oppose it.  I do so in full awareness of the very grave and serious circumstances in this island at this point in time.  The fact that the situation is grave and that there are serious threats to democracy, is reason for being all the more concerned to protect and reinforce the institutions of the State and the democratic process.  I oppose this Bill, because I believe it constitutes an abuse of the parliamentary process.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="289" /> I join with Senators Lenihan and Yeats in their criticism of the short time within which this Bill was introduced, but I propose to return to that later.  I differ from them in my criticism of the actual abuse of the parliamentary process which it constitutes.  The Prisons Bill, 1972, was brought into the House as an urgent measure to meet a particular circumstance.  It had a very difficult passage through both Houses of the Oireachtas.  It was criticised because, as was conceded at the time, it went against the basic principles of penology in allowing civilians to be transferred to military custody. It was argued and justified on the grounds of the emergency circumstances which existed at that time. There had been riots in Mountjoy Jail in May, 1972, and it could no longer accommodate prisoners.  There was no other available accommodation and it was necessary, as an urgent measure, to secure a place for them.  Military custody was secured for them in the Curragh.  It is now proposed to change the whole structure of this emergency Act by an amending Bill two years later and by extending the time limit for a completely new reason.  This, in my view, should not be conceded. I am sorry the Opposition party have conceded that principle so lightly.</P>
    <P>If it is proposed to build a high security prison to hold particular persons that should be planned for and discussed in the normal way.  The Minister for Justice has an opportunity, when the Estimates for the Department of Justice are being discussed, to make known plans and proposals to that effect.  If it is proposed to bring in legislation in relation to our prisons, then this should be done in a comprehensive and planned way, with sufficient time for discussion.  To use the Prisons Act, 1972, which was brought in for a particular emergency and to which a time limit had been introduced, to meet an entirely new situation and to extend it for a further three years in the light of that situation, is not, in my view, the proper use of the parliamentary process.  I take strong exception to that and I will elaborate on my reasons for that.  It is the most basic reason for my opposition to this present Bill.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="290" /> This Bill was introduced in the Dáil on 21st May, 1974.  It passed through all Stages on that day.  It has now been brought into the Seanad and, it would appear, will pass all Stages here today. There is also a motion for earlier signature by the President.  Therefore this will be law within a fortnight of being introduced into the Houses of the Oireachtas.  I join with Senators Lenihan and Yeats in querying the reason for this sudden emergency.  Why could the Houses not have had an indication of the likelihood that this step might have had to be taken?  This indication could have been given either in a debate on the Estimates for the Department of Justice or in the course of some other measure when the Minister for Justice was before either House.  No such indication was given and one is led to believe, rather cynically, that it may have been much less planned than was stated.</P>
    <P>This Bill purports to continue what I regard as a most unwelcome departure from the normal principles of penology, the basic principles which ought to underline our prison system, the safeguards which a society can take to protect itself, and the maintenance of proper standards and protection for the individuals concerned in our prison system.  It is not therefore a small or an irrelevant matter. It is a very fundamental principle for our society that we surround any prison system with the most careful safeguards, with the most scrupulous monitoring, and that we do not, as is happening in this case, introduce or extend military custody by a back door, by a last minute extension of an emergency Bill which was brought in for a totally different situation.</P>
    <P>The disadvantage of a Bill of this sort, which consists effectively of one section extending the time of operation of the Prison Act, 1972, is that it applies a particularly narrow focus to our prison system.  This is doubly regrettable at this point in time because of the very gravity of the situation in which we find ourselves. It is difficult to have a comprehensive discussion about our prison system on the focus of a Bill such as this.  This is distorting the original purpose of <Col N="291" /> the Act and extending the time limit to cover another eventuality.</P>
    <P>The basic principle remains the same, which is that we should be very slow and hesitant to introduce into our system of prisons the principle that civilians can be transferred from civil to military custody on the order of the Minister for Justice.  We all must agree that military custody is a much less suitable manner of retaining civilians than any other form of custody that the State could devise.  As we understand from the Minister's speech in the other House and his Second Reading speech in this House, the particular emergency which is the foundation of the Prisons Act, 1972, has been met and Mountjoy has been rebuilt.  These very critical circumstances do not exist for this distortion of the original intention of the Prisons Act by extending it for a further three years.  They do not exist in the critical form which would be necessary if the House were to consent to the extension of the Bill in this form.  If this Prisons Bill was not passed and if the three-year time limit was not introduced, nothing of sufficient urgency would happen as a result.  The 32 prisoners mentioned by the Minister could be accommodated in Portlaoise or elsewhere without the extension of military custody. Even if this were not so, the Minister had adequate time to take other measures to provide other accommodation for the particular individuals involved.  We have conceded an important principle in a one-section Bill amending an earlier Act which had nothing to do with this particular question.  We must be aware of what we are doing in this Bill and must not be deceived by the manner in which it comes before us.</P>
    <P>Another extraordinary feature of this question is that the last few years have been a time of discontent and to some extent of disruption in the prisons.  But there also has been a questioning of our whole system of custodial care, and of our prisons.  It is an undermining of the real meaning of democracy that the way in which we discuss this extremely <Col N="292" /> important subject is by the narrow and distorted focus of a Bill such as this.  There has been as much serious questioning of the prison system in this country as there has been serious questioning in other western European countries, in particular the Scandinavian countries, and in the United States and other so-called civilised countries about custodial care, about confining persons to prison who are not regarded as dangerous either to themselves or to other citizens of their country.</P>
    <P>We are here consenting in a backdoor manner to extending military custody for a further three years.  In other countries they have given serious thought and consideration to extending all possible forms of non-custodial care so that people are not confined to prisons.  We should examine our consciences in this respect.  It is my firm view that we will look back on the 1970s and the decades up to this as barbaric, to the extent that we have locked away human beings for a number of years, the justification on the part of society being to prevent them from being at large.  They are prohibited from exercising the normal relationships of a human being and this is justified as a deterrent to their physically carrying out further activities.  This can hardly be called rehabilitating those persons since the process of rehabilitation has been so little a feature of the prison system in this country.  Let us be clear that we are seriously out of line with advanced thinking in other countries if this is our approach to prisons in 1974 and if this is the way in which we intend to debate the questions of our prison population, of the new prisons being built and of the way in which citizens are distributed as between prisons.</P>
    <P>In his Second Reading speech the Minister has given an account of the male adult prisons in this country and a very limited idea of the policy of the Department of Justice in this sphere.  That is to be regretted.  The Minister conceded that the idea of transferring civilians to military custody is contrary to every concept of penology.  Towards the end of his <Col N="293" /> speech in this House the Minister made reference to the fact that some attempt is being made to provide educational facilities.</P>
    <P>I quote from the Minister's speech:</P>
    <P>For example, in liaison with my Department, educational classes are being provided in the Curragh Military Detention Barracks by two teachers made available by the County Kildare Vocational Educational Committee.  Recreation facilities to the maximum feasible extent have been provided.  The possibility of extending and augmenting these facilities is being kept under review</P>
    <P>The whole context in which this is being done is unreal.  In military custody there cannot be any genuine attempt at rehabilitation.  Rehabilitation is preparing a person to adapt to a normal and civilised life.  Therefore, although one may introduce some relaxation in the strictest application of military custody, it would be wrong to concede that this was a genuine attempt at rehabilitation. The underlying assumption of the Minister's speech is that there is not any other serious problem in regard to prisons other than the critical points mentioned in regard to the need for a high security prison.</P>
    <P>This Bill is introduced in a year when discontent has been so widespread and dissatisfaction with the prison system has been so great that the Minister took the unusual step of bringing journalists on a public relations visit of the prisons.  I am in favour of constant visiting, not just by the established visiting committee, but by Members of the Houses of the Oireachtas and by journalists so that as a society we can monitor the way in which we get rid of certain individuals because we say they have committed crimes against our society and that therefore they must be locked up for a period.</P>
    <P>This is a dangerous principle to concede in its simple form.  If we examine the concept of society wishing to protect itself against certain actions, of how that can best be done, then first, the whole prison system <Col N="294" /> would be the last resort, and secondly, our prison population would diminish considerably.  As a result the Minister would have ample space in which to cater for high-security prisoners within the existing prisons.  It is a retrograde step, like building very large cathedrals, to want to start building large prisons and conceding that we want to augment our prison population; whereas the whole bias should be strongly in favour of trying to examine the ways in which we can devise a system of non-custodial care, and a system of retribution to society for acts done which society regards as anti-social but a system which does not involve the locking-away of a human being.  We should exercise all our ingenuity and all our powers in order to reduce the prison population to its absolute minimum.  Within that minimum we should devise the security necessary from time to time particularly in a troubled time in a country.</P>
    <P>It is part of the argument for a high-risk security prison that one must examine the whole basis for the prison system in the country and do so in the terms of enlightened modern attitudes towards penology and not in the way in which the Minister approached it in his Second Reading speech where he has merely counted the existing prisons for adults and their populations. Therefore the Minister must extend an Act which was brought in for another emergency to meet this now recognised emergency.  There is no other option open to him.</P>
    <P>It is necessary in talking about this Prisons Bill in the terms in which the Minister justifies it to look even briefly at the process by which civilians, who are high-risk prisoners, may be sent to military custody.  It would appear that the most likely route for persons to military custody would be by way of trial before the Special Criminal Court.  It is relevant in a debate of this sort to note the structure and to assess in some measure the operation of the Special Criminal Court.  In another capacity, as a professor in Trinity College, I did a recent study of the operation of the Special <Col N="295" /> Criminal Court over the last two years.  In this appraisal I was greatly helped&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator is now going wide of the Bill. This Bill is a continuance Bill.  The Senator is certainly in order in discussing alternative ways of achieving what the Minister hopes to achieve by this particular amending Bill, but in my opinion the discussion of the operation of the Special Criminal Court would be outside the scope of such a measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that.  A long discussion on the operation of the court was not my intention.  My intention, if I may explain&mdash;and I will accept the ruling of the Chair on this&mdash;is to make&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>As long as it is brief.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes, I will make it brief.  The contention which I made as a result of this study is that there are persons being tried and convicted before the Special Criminal Court who have not been linked with any subversive organisation, who have not been either charged with such activities nor has it been alleged that they have furthered the activities of any unlawful organisation.  Yet they have then been committed to prisons.  It is possible that these persons could under the present law, be transferred to military custody.  The purpose of that argument is to show the extent to which we in this part of Ireland at the moment are eroding what we would all regard as the fundamental principles of justice and of the rule of law.  We are eroding the concept of trial by jury for criminal offences subject to the exception in Article 38 of the Constitution.  Here, today, we are eroding the concept of civilian custody in our prisons.  We are eroding it by allowing an extension for another three years of the concept of military custody.  This Bill, in the straitjacket of the time-limit in which we are committed to debate it, will justify this extension of military custody.  We need to be very well aware of this because sometimes we get quite self-congratulatory <Col N="296" /> and sanctimonious about the degree to which we protect democracy and democratic institutions in this part of the island.  I would maintain that there are very serious inroads on the very democratic institutions and the process of democracy which we proclaim from time to time. As well as this aspect of how the persons may get ultimately to military custody under the prolongation of this provision&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must again intervene to say that we are concerned here with the administrative actions of the Minister for Justice in transferring people to military custody.  Anything prior to that does not come within the scope of the original Bill and does not come within the scope of the continuance Bill which we are now discussing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>The Cathaoirleach has confirmed me in my view that this is a very narrow focus indeed to discuss what I regard as a very important social issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very narrow Bill, Senator.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I appreciate that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>You are bound by that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>The social issue concerning our prison system and modern concepts of penology cannot, as is evident from the degree to which I am being hauled up by the Chair, be discussed on this Bill, whose purpose is the extension of the concept of military custody for civilians who have been sentenced by our Special Criminal Court.  It is my contention, in summary, that prison itself should be the last resort and the last option of society in judging the punishment for anti-social acts.  We need a great deal more study and assessment of other alternatives of non-custodial care.  My serious objection to this Bill, and my reason for opposing it, is that military custody being contrary to all the fundamental ideas of penology should not be conceded by the Houses of the Oireachtas in an extension of an Act which was enforced for a limited period of two <Col N="297" /> years and which had nothing whatsoever to do with the present subject matter.  Therefore we are extending an Act whose very purpose is now distorted. The purpose was not debated at the time when the Bill itself was enacted with difficulty through the Houses of the Oireachtas in May, 1972.</P>
      <P>Finally I should like to ask the Minister whether there is or is intended to be a proper assessment of the prison facilities in this country.  Is there to be a proper examination of custodial care and the other options open to society? Is this particular notion of transferring from civilian to military custody one on which the Minister will undertake to make full disclosure to the House? Will he tell the House of the times when this becomes necessary and and allow the Houses of the Oireachtas to monitor the operation of the exercise of power which will be given to him, if the Prison Act, 1972, is continued for another three years until May, 1977?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHalligan" hpid="Mr. Halligan Mr. Halligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Halligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Those of us on this side of the House exercise a sort of self-imposed silence for reasons that Members of the Opposition will understand. There comes a time when one has even got to try the patience of colleagues by adding to the time that they have to remain in this House and when one must say what one has to say.  In particular in view of the attitude that has been taken on this Bill by major Opposition spokesmen, I feel impelled to make two simple points.  First of all, the parties on this side of the House support the Bill because the key consideration at the moment, particularly on this very grave day, is the suppression of terror and the control of terrorists.  The people of this country will not forgive the Government for failing in their duty in that regard nor will they forgive this Parliament for preventing them from carrying out their duty, based upon some naive appreciation of human nature.  The security issue is the key and important issue of today. It is my regret that we do not have a high-security prison which would be capable of maintaining within civil custody those who are convicted of subversive acts or of belonging to illegal organisations.  That <Col N="298" /> defect goes back for quite some considerable time.  The blame for it can be apportioned right across the floor of the House.</P>
      <P>However human history has interludes of peace and calm and also periods of grave and deep distress when men do to each other things that in normal times would appear to be unimaginable.  Regrettably, we live in such times; and I am wondering whether or not the Minister is too sanguine in his analysis and whether a high-security unit, which will be added to Portlaoise prison, will be sufficient when it will house 30 prisoners only.  I understand, for the reasons he has advanced by implication at the end of the second paragraph, that there are other matters which the Minister, for security reasons, does not wish to go into and which any responsible public representative understands without the necessity for the Minister to have it spelled out in black and white in large type.</P>
      <P>I welcome the Government's commitment to return the prison system in its entirety to civilian control as soon as possible.  I believe that those who have been convicted by the Special Criminal Court should be housed under civilian control; I believe this to be a fundamental principle of the rule of law.  If there is to be military custody then those who are put into military custody must come there by a different avenue.  I support the point made by the Leader of the Government here.  That point was made by the then Minister for Justice in 1972.  I was shocked by Senator Lenihan's apparent disagreement with that principle and by his departure from it here when he appeared to advance the principle of military custody as a valid principle in itself.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>In the situation&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHalligan" hpid="Mr. Halligan Mr. Halligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Halligan</NameTxt>
      <P>Not in the present situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I hope so.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHalligan" hpid="Mr. Halligan Mr. Halligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Halligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the Minister's analysis of the present prison accommodation as outlined in his speech.  I accept too his conclusion that high-risk security prisoners cannot <Col N="299" /> be housed for the moment in ordinary prison custody and must be conveyed for a temporary period to military custody.  I regret the fact that this has to be so.  I do accept, as I hope all of us do who accept the necessity for maintaining democracy, the consequences that flow from the Minister's analysis, and I do so too without any apology.  Any person who values democracy in this country on this particular day at this particular time and who willingly accepts the necessity for defending it, however difficult that might be, will also accept the principles of this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I intend to be extremely brief in my comments.  I agree very much with what Senator Halligan has said in that we are all concerned with the suppression of terror.  Indeed more than that we are positively concerned with the elimination of terror.  Senator Halligan's rebuke for Senator Lenihan is quite well taken.  Senator Lenihan apparently accepted&mdash;at least as I understood his speech&mdash;the principle of military detention when he made his intervention during Senator Halligan's speech.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>We are talking about the House.  I am not bringing in the Bill.  The Minister is bringing in the Bill, and I agree with him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Fine, but I think in discussing this Bill that it is an insufficient reaction to simply say: &ldquo;We were right some time ago. Now you have realised such necessity and, therefore you can be right today&rdquo;.  This, to my mind, is an insufficient and careless reaction to a Bill of this kind.  It is in contrast with the contribution Senator Robinson made and the comments she made on the prison system as referred to in the Minister's speech.  I should like to refer specifically to the third paragraph of the Minister's introductory speech on the Second Stage:</P>
      <P>If we are to have a prison system geared to rehabilitation then there must be peace in our prisons; an absence of agitation and tension.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="300" /> At the present time, it is true to say that there has been a serious revaluation at a professional level of the extent and constitution of crime in our society.  There has also been a revaluation of the effects of punishment itself.  It is welcome that Senator Robinson has asked these questions of the Minister at the conclusion of her speech.  She asked that he would at an early date indicate his intentions for the reform of the penal code.  In the second page of his speech the Minister has listed the structural changes that are taking place at different institutions.  This can hardly be regarded as in any way sufficient.  In fact I would regard it as almost a dangerous commitment to a narrow and dated view of criminology in view of the changes that have taken place in terms of politics, philosophy and research in crime.  I refer here particularly to an article in the current issue of <i>The Economic and Social Review</i> by Professor Eyenon on this subject.</P>
    <P>In conclusion I should simply like to say that I join with Senator Halligan in saying that those of us on this side agree that the suppression of terror and the elimination of fear in our society are of primary importance at the present time.  In these circumstances, which can hardly be pleasant circumstances for any member of our society, reaction, if it goes beyond that simple statement, should be directed towards the more general question of the adequacy of our prison system.  This arises on the Prisons Bill, 1974, on the Second Reading, in so far as the removal of people to military custody from civilian control inevitably raises the question of the circumstances of those who are in civilian control at the present time.</P>
    <P>If in future the Opposition wish to comment on a Bill of this kind I should like if they would not suggest that we are abandoning fundamental principles of law for principles of expediency.  To suggest that a situation has repeated itself and therefore, prevention is necessary is, to my mind, not only an inadequate response, <Col N="301" /> but is a dangerous response in so far as it does not seek to elicit any positive policy directions for the future.  I wholeheartedly support the necessity of Senator Robinson pressing for some kind of indication by the Minister as to future policy in the area she has highlighted.  Obviously, these are difficult times for the Minister.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney) Patrick M. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney)</NameTxt>
      <P>I am obliged to Senators for their welcome for this Bill and to Members of the Opposition for their agreement to its being passed.  Again I regret the time limit that was imposed on its introduction.  I cannot blame Senator Lenihan and Senator Yeats for taking advantage of this to have something to say by way of chastisement.  As I did attempt to indicate, it was with some reluctance that I introduced this Bill at all.  There was a considerable examination in depth to see if the necessity for it could be avoided. Reluctantly I could not find any way in which to avoid it because the feelings which I have about it, and which I expressed when the parent Bill was being debated originally in the other House, I still retain.  I think those feelings are echoed by most people in this House: that military custody <i>per se</i> is undesirable, that we should strive at all times to have civilian prisoners detained in civil prisons and subject to the normal regime which would operate in those prisons.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Senator Robinson made the point that we are now seeking this extension for different reasons than those advanced by my predecessor when the original Bill was introduced in 1972. To some extent this is correct.  The immediate reason for the Bill in 1972 was the fact that Mountjoy Prison was well-nigh uninhabitable following a large-scale riot and accommodation had to be found for some of the prisoners.  The prisoners picked were those who were regarded as being dangerous to the security of the prison. Mountjoy Prison has been largely restored but there still remains the problem that there are a certain number of prisoners whose presence in any of our prisons tends to give rise to agitation and disturbance and <Col N="302" /> tends to defeat the work of the prison officers in introducing and implementing rehabilitative measures.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson made the point that the prison system has been a focus for discontent and unrest.  If she examines our prisons and casts her mind over the last six months she might notice that the position happily has improved drastically when compared with that of the previous six months.  I am glad to say that we have had a comparatively peaceful time within our prisons.  The reason for this is that we have been able to have a careful segregation of prisoners into homogenous groups between our prisons.  It was our experience that a wrong mix produced agitation and unrest and worse.  This is what has to be avoided.  In order to have full segregation it is necessary to continue to use the facilities in the Curragh.</P>
    <P>I do not agree that military custody &mdash;Senator Lenihan mentioned this but possibly he did not mean it in the particular context here&mdash;is the appropriate type of custody for the prisoners who are in the Curragh at the moment.  They are prisoners who are suitable for civilian custody, provided we are able to segregate them from other prisoners within our civil prisons.  It is not possible to do that at present.  That is the only reason they are in military custody.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson seemed to feel that prisoners could be accommodated elsewhere.  I want to show the House that if this were so they would be accommodated elsewhere.  There is no other venue within our prison system where these prisoners can be detained without running a grave risk of the disruption and the riots which marked the prison system of this country until about six months ago.  The Senator made the point that if there was no other place for them I should have provided one.  One cannot build prisons very quickly.  The type of unit that is necessary is a high-security unit.  I thought I had made the point in my opening speech that the provision of a high-security unit is a long-term process. Even the briefing of architects is a slow and detailed business because the architect has to be briefed in the most minute detail.  If you are building <Col N="303" /> a hotel or any other type of structure the architect can be given a general outline of his brief, but for a high-security prison the briefing has to get down to even indicating to him the type of catch that would not be acceptable on the window in a cell. Literally, the briefing of an architect is very long.  The planning is equally long and careful.  The building must be extremely carefully done and must be to an extremely high quality.  The position is further complicated by the fact that the site chosen for the high-security unit is within the Portlaoise complex.  Security has to be maintained in Portlaoise while this is going on.  This will necessarily slow up the building operations.</P>
    <P>It is for these reasons that I am asking the House to agree to an extension up to 1977, hoping of course that we will be able to terminate military custody at an earlier date, but to be realistic we had to take an end date of 1977.  Things are not as simple as Senator Robinson seems to think&mdash;that if we have not got the accommodation we could have provided it.  I am in the position, as I indicated in the other House, that no plans for this type of accommodation had been made.  I came to the conclusion that this type of accommodation would have to be provided.  Until such time as we would have it it would be impossible to have effective segregation as between prisoners. Without effective segregation as between prisoners we could not have peace within our prisons, and without peace within our prisons we cannot have effective rehabilitation.  I know this from a visit I made to Portlaoise shortly after I was appointed during the course of which I met many prisoners.  At that time Portlaoise had a history of agitation and unrest.  Many of the prisoners I spoke to resented the efforts of a group within that prison to form an association or a union as they called it.  This led to aggravation between the prisoners and confrontation situations.  There was a continuing tension which the prisoners found unpleasant and which considerably impeded any efforts on the part of the staff to rehabilitate prisoners.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="304" /> The first essential to a rehabilitative process is peace and the first essential to that is proper segregation.  This is why we need the facilities in the Curragh for some time to come.  I hope I have made that point clear.  I am making that point in the context of saying that I regret that it is necessary that we have been left with the situation in which we had not got the facilities to avoid it.  I do not like the idea of military custody for civil prisoners. I am not defending the principle, but it is purely a matter of expediency that we have to accept it for the moment.</P>
    <P>For that reason I am grateful to the Opposition for their agreement to this Bill.  Our prison system could be in serious jeopardy if we did not have these facilities.  If our prison system is in serious jeopardy our very democracy is in serious jeopardy because the security of the State and the security of the community demands that some people have to be kept in custody.  The community would not tolerate a large number of people who are now in custody roaming the streets at large. Unfortunately the only place in which they can be kept in custody is in prison.</P>
    <P>I sympathise with Senator Robinson's ambition to see all our prisons well-nigh empty.  This would be everybody's ambition but it is closing one's eyes to reality to hope that this is an achievable target, because the community would not tolerate at large those who had terrorised them or of whom they were frightened.  That is not to say the prisons themselves could not be improved and that the aim within the prisons should not be to rehabilitate such persons.  This is the aim.</P>
    <P>I would refer Senator Robinson and Senator Higgins to the Estimate speech which I made in the Dáil some months ago in which I indicated in some detail the work that has been taking place in reforming our prisons. I indicated my views on what was still needed in our prisons.  I indicated the fact that I have initiated studies in order to look at alternatives to jail.  I also indicated the large extent to which the parole system is being used. If Senators had taken the trouble of <Col N="305" /> reading what has been said in this area we might not have the implications in speeches here today that there had been no movement whatever in this area.  I reject that suggestion: there has been considerable movement in improving our prison service to provide a rehabilitative regime.</P>
    <P>I want to put on record our gratitude to the military authorities for the way they have shouldered a burden which is not properly theirs and the patience with which they have continued to deal with it.  It is heartening that without any cavil whatever they are prepared to continue with that burden until such time as they can be relieved of it.  It is important that the officers and NCOs who are running this military prison in the Curragh should know that their efforts are appreciated and are crucial to the well-being of the State in these difficult times and I want to thank them.</P>
    <P>I wish to make the point that this is a temporary measure and is not to be taken as any indication that the Government and myself are in favour of military custody for civilian prisoners irrespective of what court they have been sentenced by.</P>
    <P>In the parent Act, section 2 (6) provides that the Oireachtas shall be informed of any directions given for the transfer of persons to military custody. That answers another point raised by Senator Robinson: that the Oireachtas should know of these things.  Provision is made in the Act for giving this information to the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>Senator Yeats made the point that he welcomed the change of attitude by the parties that were in Opposition when the 1972 Act was passed.  I made it clear that essentially there is no change of attitude by the then Opposition, and no change of attitude on our part in Government.  I do not like the idea of military custody for civilian prisoners.  It is forced on us because of the inadequacies of the prison buildings which I inherited. Steps have been taken to improve these, but it will take three years to carry out the improvements.</P>
    <P>I am grateful to the House for giving us this time.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="306" /> Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prisons Bill, 1974:" RHead="Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Prisons Bill, 1974: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 1 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the effects of this section is to extend the Act for a further three years without any other safeguards, would it be appropriate to write in certain safeguards?  The reason for this is that when the Bill was passed in 1972 the idea was to meet the emergency of needing further accommodation.  However it is admitted that the extension is for a different reason: to deal with what are known as subversive or difficult prisoners, where strict security is needed.  They will be held in military custody while a high-risk prison is being built.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>First I find the word &ldquo;subversive&rdquo; a very dangerous one.  There are certain people who might call me &ldquo;subversive&rdquo; and might call me even more subversive after my contribution here this afternoon.  It has that very loose connotation and it would be preferable to use a more precise description of the persons concerned.  It is my fear that in allowing an extension of this Act for another three years we are not writing in a sufficient safeguard. We are allowing the transfer from civil to military custody.  Under the Bill the Minister does make a statement about persons and about reasons for the conviction, etc., but there is not sufficient control of the exercise of his discretion.  The particular danger that could be foreseen would be that if a person held in a prison was objecting to conditions in the prison and to the way he was confined within the prison, objecting in a way which was immediately categorised as &ldquo;subversive&rdquo;, that person could either be threatened with or be transferred to military custody without any further scrutiny or any need for any objective process at all.  Without wishing to cast any aspersions on the particular Minister for Justice at <Col N="307" /> any time, as a Parliament we ought to be cautious about giving&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is now discussing the sections of the original Bill.  What is before us is a section of the amending Bill which seeks to extend.  The principle of extension has been agreed by the Bill being read a Second Time.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I agree that the principle of extension has been agreed but I do not agree that it is not open to say, since the meaning and the whole purpose of the Bill is being changed, that there ought to be safeguards written into this extension which were not in the original Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I fail to see any point in this since no amendment to insert anything in the section, other than an amendment in relation to time, would be in order on a continuation Bill.  It is not possible to insert an amendment into section 1.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I would be astonished if the Minister himself has conceded that the purpose of the original Bill has changed and that this is an extension to it&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>No, I have not.  I should like to clarify that.  All I said was that the immediate cause for the original Bill was the riot in Mountjoy, which was caused in turn by a certain type of destructive prisoner. The necessity then arose to transfer those prisoners.  That necessity still remains.</P>
      <P>As regards the other point, I am surprised that the Senator, who has displayed a keen interest in penology, has not read the Prisons Act, 1972, where section 2 (3) clearly provides the conditions under which the prisoners can be transferred.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="308" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I have that particular Act in my hand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>It is clear that there are safeguards in it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is concerned with the relevance to the discussion on section 1.  The continuance has been agreed by passing the Second Reading and section 1 provides for continuance until a particular date.  Section 1, embodying that date, is before the House at the moment.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Section 2 agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Prisons Bill, 1974:" RHead="Motion for Earlier Signature">
    <Title>Prisons Bill, 1974: Motion for Earlier Signature.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That, pursuant to subsection 2º of section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad Éireann concur with the Government in a request to the President to sign the Prisons Bill, 1974, on a date which is earlier than the fifth day after the date on which the Bill shall have been presented to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelYeats" hpid="Mr. Yeats Mr. Yeats">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Yeats</NameTxt>
      <P>We are obviously agreeing to this motion, because we agree with the principle of the Bill and we accept that it must be enforced by Friday next.  However we should reiterate that we agree to this motion under protest.  We look on it as an example of incompetent government.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 5.40 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 29th May, 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>