<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Thu" Date="18" Month="Jul" Year="1974" Vol="78" No="15" DateIrish="Déardaoin, 18 Iúil 1974" DateEnglish="Thursday, 18 July 1974" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1189">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P>
      <Col N="1189" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10.30 a.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Death of Member:" RHead="Expression of Sympathy">
    <Title>Death of Member: Expression of Sympathy.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senators will have heard this morning with the deepest regret the death of our colleague Senator Bob Aylward.  Senator Aylward although a Member of the Seanad for a relatively short time had a life-long involvement in public life and was noted for his tireless devotion to the service of the people he represented in the county of Kilkenny.  He was for 25 years a member of the county council and was foremost among those involved in the work of many committees, notably the committee of agriculture, the health committee and the hospitals committee.  Senator Aylward, in his earlier days, was an outstanding G.A.A. player and subsequently continued his activities in this field as an administrator.  He held the offices of vice-president of the Association and as chairman of the Leinster council.</P>
      <P>As an outstanding farmer it was fitting he should have been elected a Senator last May on the Agricultural Panel.  He was, as we all know, a very kind and courteous man and his deep convictions and concern for the public welfare were manifest in his contributions to the debates in this House during the past year.  On your behalf and on my own I shall convey to his widow and family our sympathy and appreciation.  Solas Dé ar a anam.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Members rose in their places.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Order of" RHead="Business">
    <Title>Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 1 and 2 and to take No. 2 <Col N="1190" /> at 12.30 and, if necessary, interrupt discussion on No. 1 if it has not concluded and, at the conclusion of No. 2, to revert to No. 1 if it is still continuing.  As regards No. 3, I am in some difficulty.  I understand that the Minister for Finance is moving a similar motion in the Dáil and he would wish to move it in the Dáil first. I would ask in these circumstances, as we cannot be quite certain whether he will be able to move it here or not before we conclude, that we might order No. 3 provisionally.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take No. 1 and to take No. 2 at 12.30 and to take No. 3 if it has been passed by the Dáil before the conclusion of Business.  Is that agreed?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, since it does appear we may not have a full day's work before us, might I suggest that we add to the Order of Business Items No. 6 on which I feel I am becoming now monotonous &mdash;the Illegitimate Children (Maintenance and Succession) Bill, 1974.  I do not want to be in the position of dividing the House or, worse still, failing to divide the House each time we meet by trying to add this item. If the Leader of the House would give me an assurance that he will try to have this taken perhaps, next week, and that it would be given a Second Reading then I shall not divide the House on it but I think I will have to ask for some undertaking in relation to this item.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I explained to the Senator yesterday that I am not in the position to give an undertaking. The fact that her request for an undertaking has been repeated does not alter my position.  I am not in a position to give an undertaking.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I find it very difficult to understand the attitude of the Leader of the House in relation to this Bill.  It had been on the Order Paper for a long number of weeks and as I said, we have already debated and are taking the Report Stage of the Adoption Bill, a subject matter very closely linked with this Bill and I find that for some curious reason the Leader of the House <Col N="1191" /> is less willing to take any steps to have time given to this Bill than he has been in relation to motions and other items. I suggest that this is an important social matter; it is a problem to which this House ought to give time and I find his attitude very disappointing.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would ask the Leader of the House to facilitate Senator Robinson in this regard.  I can appreciate that it is not &ldquo;on&rdquo; to have this matter discussed today but surely some assurance could be given as to when it can be taken.  It is an important social matter and I feel that the rights of Independent Senators in this House should be respected and appreciated. We have two weeks of sittings&mdash;next week and the following week&mdash;surely this Bill can be accommodated in either of those two weeks in some measure or some indication can be given by the Leader of the House that this item can be taken.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before the Leader of the House concludes the discussion, does any other Senator wish to contribute?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>All I can do is express my view on this.  I pointed out more than once that it is a matter for this House to fix the Order of Business. It is not fixed by the Government; it is not fixed by me.  It is a matter for the House to fix it.  When Senator Lenihan refers to finding time to accommodate discussion on this Bill it is not for me to find time.  The House is entirely free to come to its own decision with regard to it.  It is open to Senator Lenihan, as it is open to Senator Mary Robinson, to propose an amendment to the Order of Business at any time and let the House take a decision on it. From the Government's point of view, this is the third or fourth occasion on which the matter has been raised.  On the first occasion, I made it clear to Senator Robinson that it was unlikely that it would be proposed&mdash;if the proposal is being left to me as Leader of the House&mdash;for inclusion in the Order of Business this side of the summer recess.  That still remains to be the position.  Possibly I should have said <Col N="1192" /> earlier to Senator Robinson that I understand the Government have in preparation legislation dealing with this subject.  It seems proper that whatever legislation is introduced should be introduced after the Governmental scrutiny and preparation that the topic warrants.  The Government, I understand, will be introducing legislation. I am not in a position to indicate when that legislation will be ready.  In those circumstances there are reasonable grounds for arguing against taking it now.  If Senator Robinson or Senator Lenihan want to obtain the views of the House and the decision of the House on it, there is procedure for doing that. It does not rest with me.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Leader of the House has given me no option but to move the amendment to include Item No. 6.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It is your right.  It is not an option I am presenting to you.  It is your right to do it if you want.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I suggest that although I welcome the hint or indication by the Leader of the House that the Government are considering this matter and may be bringing in legislation this, to me, is all the more reason to have a Second Reading debate on this Bill so the Minister can give us an indication of Government thinking on it.  I fail to see why he cannot give the time to a discussion on this very important subject especially if the Government have a policy on it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I have concluded the discussion on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is capable of controlling the proceedings. The Senator is not entitled at this stage to move an amendment but I am prepared to say that an amendment was implicit on her original contribution. Accordingly, I am prepared to accept an amendment that item No. 6 be added to the Order of Business provided it is seconded.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I would like to make a remark on this.  We are doing this on <Col N="1193" /> the Order of Business regularly here in the Seanad.  It is not doing anybody any good.  It is all very well for the Leader of the House to say: &ldquo;Right, we will have a vote&rdquo; and a vote takes place and time is wasted.  Let us be mature about this.  This is a very important matter.  Surely it can be included in two weeks sitting time which we have next week and the following week.  Surely there should be some &ldquo;give&rdquo;, as it were, in a matter of this kind which has been raised on numerous occasions by Senator Robinson, rather than adopt the crude device of voting in this manner on the Order of Business.  I sincerely think it is bringing the whole proceedings here into disrepute to have repetitive votes on the Order of Business.  I just want to make that last appeal.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would suggest to the Senator that perhaps these views could be expressed more effectively outside the House and that consultation might take place.  The Question is: &ldquo;That Item No. 6 be added to the Order of Business.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>Amendment put and declared lost.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The original question is that the Order of Business consists of Items Nos. 1, 2 and 3.  Is that agreed?</P>
      <P>Order of Business agreed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Agricultural (Amendment) Bill, 1974:" RHead="Second Stage">
    <Title>Agricultural (Amendment) Bill, 1974: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. M.P. Murphy) Michael Pat Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. M.P. Murphy)</NameTxt>
      <P>The committees of agriculture are financed each year by means of contributions from their respective county councils together with State grants related to these contributions.  The State grant normally approximates to the local rates contribution but in the case of the 12 committees of agriculture in the small farm areas of the west and north of the country further State assistance is granted by way of a contribution of 75 per cent instead of the normal 50 per cent.  The purpose of this extra contribution is to assist these particular <Col N="1194" /> counties in employing adequate numbers of advisory staff.</P>
      <P>The existing statutory ceiling of county council contributions, which has been in operation since 1st April, 1972, is a sum not exceeding 15 times the produce of a rate of 1p in the £ in the area consisting of the county, exclusive of any urban areas therein and the immediate purpose of this short Bill is to enable county councils to give increased contributions where necessary towards the financing of county committees of agriculture in the local financial year commencing 1st January, 1975.</P>
      <P>Under section 1 subsection (1) of the bill, it is proposed to increase the ceiling to 40p in the £ with effect from 1st January 1975.  This maximum does not, of course, make it mandatory on county councils to reach it or indeed to meet the demands of committees of agriculture for increased funds, unless they see fit.  Section 1 subsection (2) would enable county councils to make any necessary preliminary arrangements during the current financial year with a view to adopting a suitable rate contribution, within the proposed new maximum, in respect of the coming financial year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>In recent years there has been a considerable expansion in the staff of the agricultural advisory services&mdash;it now numbers some 650 officers.  There is still a need, however, to further strengthen these services in most counties.  In recent times I have approved of the creation by each of the twenty-seven committees of agriculture of a post of deputy chief agricultural officer with special responsibility for educational matters.  In addition there will now be over 70 posts of senior instructor the holders of which will supervise, under the CAO, the work of all advisers in a particular advisory district.  A significant development in recent years has been the provision of much-needed headquarters for committees of agriculture, and also the provision of new agricultural education centres.  To date, 16 such centres have been provided at a total cost of some £415,000, and my Department has paid a total of £183,000 in grants towards the centres.  A further seven centres are <Col N="1195" /> under construction.  I have recently increased the maximum grant towards the cost of each approved centre from £15,000 to £20,000.</P>
    <P>In the year 1973-74 ten committees were on a rate between 14.5p and 15p (maximum) in the £, while a further ten committees were in receipt of the produce of a rate of between 12p and 14p in the £.  In addition to increased expenses generally, increased salaries have contributed to the deterioration in the finances of all committees, whose staff, in addition to having secured increased remuneration under conciliation and arbitration proceedings, have been granted the benefits of the national wage agreements.</P>
    <P>This Bill is required, and is, in fact, essential to ensure that those committees which in the immediate future cannot carry out their statutory functions on their present incomes, will be permitted to seek sufficient funds to enable them to do so.  Some committees either now have, or will have substantial deficits on 31st December next and unless action is taken now the position will deteriorate further.</P>
    <P>I would see an advantage in having the statutory upper limit abolished entirely, if only with a view to avoiding an over-frequent resort to amending legislation which is inevitable in present circumstances of undue restriction on the necessary contribution from the rates.  I am advised, however, that the abolition of a maximum rate contribution as it exists would not be feasible unless it were substituted by other statutory amendments which would confer new powers on me thus limiting the activities and finances of the individual committees of agriculture. Because of the administrative and other difficulties this would involve and more particularly as it would remove from the committees and from the county councils a responsibility which desirably they should have, I consider that the present system should continue, but that the maximum rate contribution should be fixed at a sufficiently high level to permit committees of agriculture to perform their functions without an undue pre-occupation with trying to avoid deficits.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1196" /> In the circumstances, I consider that the existing maximum rate contribution of 15p in the £ should be increased to 40p in the £.  As I have already indicated it will not be mandatory on county councils to meet demands of committees of agriculture for increased funds unless they see fit.  Contributions from the Department will, of course, continue to be made on the same <i>pro rata</i> basis as hitherto.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanKeegan" hpid="Mr. Keegan Mr. Keegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome an opportunity to express an opinion on this Bill. I am disappointed that the Bill does not go far enough to meet the changes and the challenges which face the agricultural industry and the agricultural community at the present time.  Agriculture is our greatest industry.  It is our greatest exporting industry because of the fact that the basic raw materials are produced in this country and, therefore, it is the industry which contributes most to our balance of payments.  I am sorry and disappointed that the Parliamentary Secretary in his opening speech did not make any reference to the changing role of the committees in a changing agricultural industry.  I can see the point that the Bill is designed solely to increase the powers of local authorities to make a greater amount of money available to each county committee of agriculture, to expand their existing services and to cater for increases in salaries to the officers employed by the various committees.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill does not take into consideration the changes which are taking place since we became members of the European Economic Community. Therefore, the Bill does not go far enough because of the fact that our agricultural officers have been called upon to implement the new farm modernisation scheme.  The work of the local officers will increase while the work of the land project officers will decrease, to a certain extent.  Here was an opportunity for the Parliamentary Secretary and his Minister to initiate changes because changes must take place in view of our role as members of that Community.  With the introduction of the farm modernisation scheme and all the administrative work involved <Col N="1197" /> some changes should have taken place. Here was an opportunity to do it because this Bill seals with the county committees of agriculture and the method of financing those committees.</P>
    <P>Therefore, I am disappointed but the Minister, or his Parliamentary Secretary, may still have an opportunity to rectify the matter.  There is an urgent need to bring about those changes and to have the services geared to give the greatest benefits to those in need, namely, the small farmers in every county.  An air of despondency and despair has set in amongst those people because of the depression in the agricultural industry.  Some means of uplifting the industry is necessary if we are to restore confidence and induce farmers to plan for the future and remain in agriculture.  Therefore, the role of the county committees and their officers is important.  It now will be more important than ever because of the changes that are taking place in Europe, with which we are associated, because of the air of uncertainty which exists at present.</P>
    <P>New approaches must be made: new schemes must be devised to enable the farmer to secure the greatest possible income from his holding and to guarantee him a future in that industry. I am disappointed, also, that it is the county councils that will foot any increase which will be passed on in the future.</P>
    <P>I would have hoped that the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries would have announced an increase in the grants to committees of agriculture to enable them to foot the bill.  After all, every farmer is a ratepayer.  If he finds that his income is declining he will find it difficult to understand how he is expected to foot further increases.  This is an important piece of legislation; it is something that is above politics.  The livelihood of our farmers should be the concern of everybody both Government and Opposition.  Therefore, a great deal of new thinking is required at the present time to restore confidence in the farming community.  The Minister or his Parliamentary Secretary should have announced an increase in Government spending on increased subsidy for <Col N="1198" /> the various county committees of agriculture.</P>
    <P>There should have been some mention in the Bill with regard to channelling all the services associated with agriculture into the one local department.  As I mentioned the new farm modernisation scheme and the land project are similar except that their implementation and administration will be slightly different. Something should have been done to bring those two groups together and have their services governed by one section of one Department.  The same applies to the veterinary services and the brucellosis eradication scheme and all the other schemes that are associated with county committees of agriculture and with the farming community in general.</P>
    <P>I would have been pleased if the Minister and his Parliamentary Secretary had made some effort at channelling the activities of all those different spheres under the one heading and have them responsible to one officer.  In that way you would create greater efficiency and reduce costs.  This Bill is all about costs and money.  That is one way in which it could be done because in the long run the activities of all the various sections of the Department are all dealing with the one section of the community&mdash;the farmers.  Therefore, this Bill does not go far enough in promoting harmony among the various officers.  I should mention the long drawn out industrial dispute which took place with the agricultural officers and the Department of Agriculture with the result that thousands of applications under the Farm Modernisation Scheme are still awaiting attention.  First, they were with the Department and now, as a result of the resolving of the dispute they are with the various county committees of agriculture.</P>
    <P>Any effort that can be made to broaden the activities of the county committees of agriculture is to be welcomed.  It is disappointing that any further increase in expenditure must be borne by the ratepayers.  I can tell you that the ratepayers will not take too kindly to this bill this year because of the diminishing income of thousands of our farmers.  It will be said that those engaged in non-farming activities will <Col N="1199" /> also have to contribute to the cost.  All ratepayers will be making their contribution towards the increase in costs of this new piece of legislation.</P>
    <P>A great deal more needs to be done. As I said before possibly the Minister or his Parliamentary Secretary may have some new thinking in the pipeline for the various agricultural committees throughout the country but now is the time to advance this new thinking and have the schemes implemented.  We must concentrate the efforts of all the county committees on the small farmer because his survival seems to be at stake.  His future is in doubt.  Confidence must be restored to the small farming community.  It can be done through the schemes of the county committees of agriculture and it can be done by initiating the best possible marketing which can be made available to the farmer.</P>
    <P>I mentioned that the pig industry and the schemes operated by the county committees of agriculture are now inadequate in order to induce the small farmer to continue in pig production. Drastic remedies need to be implemented in order to put that industry back on a sound footing and in order to induce the small farmer to get back into the pig industry.  By and large over the years the pig industry enabled the small farmers to continue in farming. The various schemes which have been in operation by the county committees of agriculture need to be further extended and strengthened in an effort to keep the small farmer in production.</P>
    <P>The same position prevails in the cattle industry.  The man who is producing the store cattle needs further advice on how to get the best possible return in the shortest possible time. Those were the duties and functions of our agricultural advisers.  I am inclined to query the role of the land project officer and the agricultural officer with regard to all these new schemes which are embodied in the new farm modernisation scheme.  Every aspect of our agricultural industry is embodied in the farm modernisation scheme.  Greater education is necessary in order to keep our farmers fully informed in regard to all the changes which are taking place.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1200" /> Much more is necessary in the field of farm education.  A great deal of research must be done in the field of marketing and the farming community must be assured that there is a market for what they produce.  They must be assured that never again will they have to face a period of depression.  Never again will they be allowed to drift and float from day to day or from week to week.</P>
    <P>I was pleased when I read in the newspapers this morning that we are to have a beef sales promotion campaign. That is very welcome and is something in which our county committees of agriculture could actively be engaged.  This kind of promotion is very necessary in order to induce people to purchase our beef.  Last year and the year before you had this hardening of attitudes against the purchase of beef because people were saying that it was too dear.  It happened in this country; it happened in the European countries and in America.  That was detrimental to the cattle industry in general and played a part in a fall-off in the consumption of beef.  I am convinced that in present day living costs beef is value for money.  It never was such value for money as it is at present.  Our people at home should be encouraged to purchase beef.  It is discouraging indeed when we hear the uproar that is created when beef prices increase but the glass of brandy could go up to £1 per glass and it would still be purchased and there would not be a word about it.  It is imported from France mainly&mdash;a country which refused our lamb and mutton last week.  While I am wandering from the contents of the Bill I hope the Chair will bear with me for the moment.  I feel the strongest form of protest should have been registered against the attitude of the French last week in closing the markets to our mutton.  The sheep farmer was doing reasonably well this year.  It is a pity the market was closed to him because of the action of the French.  Some form of action should have been taken by our Government.  After all, the Italians did the same some months ago.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator knows he should not continue too long.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="1201" />
    <Speaker pid="SeanKeegan" hpid="Mr. Keegan Mr. Keegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Chair for allowing me to broaden the scope of the debate.  In dealing with an industry of such vast significance as agriculture it can be difficult to keep rigidly to the terms of the Bill, as the Chair can well understand.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator has been excellent up to now.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeanKeegan" hpid="Mr. Keegan Mr. Keegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will get back to the Bill.  Knowing the Parliamentary Secretary's associations with agriculture, I hope he will give the House a guarantee that there will be new thinking in an effort to save our greatest industry and instil confidence into the farming community once again.  While any measure to increase the spending powers of the committees of agriculture is welcome, it is disappointing that the ratepayers will have to foot the cost. As I said before, the work of the officers is becoming increasingly urgent as a result of the introduction of the farm modernisation scheme.  Therefore, I was a bit disappointed that all those new activities were not mentioned in the Minister's Bill or in the Parliamentary Secretary's speech.  I am confident that they will give the House and the Irish people an assurance that more will be done in future to stabilise the agricultural industry and to try and get it back on a secure footing once again.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JoeJMcCartin" hpid="Mr. McCartin Mr. McCartin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCartin</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is very necessary.  We are aware of the circumstances that brought it about.  We know that many of our committees were seriously in the red, as was stated by the Parliamentary Secretary in his opening remarks.  The question of a further burden on the ratepayers of the different counties has come up for discussion both here and in the other House in relation to this Bill.  As far as this new legislation is concerned, there is nothing compulsory about it.  It just means that committees of agriculture may ask county councils for a sum in excess of 15p if they wish.  In reports brought out two years ago, committees of agriculture recommedned to the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries that they should have the right to make up their own minds with regard to the amount of money <Col N="1202" /> required to run their services in their counties.  Having done so, it ought to be mandatory on the county councils to pay the amount of money required. It is not a very important point because I do not know of cases where committees of agriculture sought the particular amount within the limits of the legislation and were refused by the county council concerned.</P>
      <P>We have democratic local administration working properly: a situation where the local authority can sit back and make plans, ask itself how much the service is worth and, having done so, decide whether it can levy a certain amount of money against the ratepayers. At the moment there is quite a generous subsidy being paid.  Arguments have been entered into again and again about this question of increasing the rates.  A subsidy of 50 per cent is being given all over the country and 75 per cent in the 12 western counties. Everybody, I think, will agree that it is a generous subsidy.</P>
      <P>Senator Keegan said he would have liked to see increased subsidisation from from central funds.  Of course, it is obvious that increased spending requires increased subsidisation from central funds.  If the county committees of agriculture increase their spending in the western areas, it will mean an increase in the 75 per cent; in the rest it will mean an increase in the 50 per cent.  Those of us who believe in the democratic system based on the county councils as we have seen it in the past and who believe in the development and strengthening of this system, seriously could not expect the central authority to go much further in subsidising the activities of the county committees of agriculture, without calling to question and further reducing the power of the local authority.  This is a very important point.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I do not think any of us who are involved in local government can honestly say that we would like to see a situation in which we, the local authority, would merely spend the money handed down to us by central government.  This would be a very hollow and make-belief sort of situation for a local authority.  To have any power they must decide, to some extent, the <Col N="1203" /> extent of the services they will give. Having done so, they must be in a position to levy some form of local taxation in support of their activities. If we did not have some form of local taxation the very nature of local authority and local government would be called into question.  I would not like to see that situation come about.</P>
    <P>Reference was made to old age pensioners and people who have difficulty in paying rates.  There is provision where any county council can remit rates or part of the rates of any person who is in great need.  Local authorities must avail themselves of this provision to protect people who are not in a position to pay rates.  That is the way to get around that difficulty.</P>
    <P>If we take money from central funds it means there is going to be less money for old age pensions.  We should not worry about asking the ratepayers to provide more money for this service. The advisory services have made a bigger contribution towards the development, expansion and increasing the standard of living of those engaged in the agricultural industry than any other service provided by the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries.  The competent, qualified adviser within the reach of everybody engaged in the agricultural industry is the greatest guarantee we have of keeping the farming community up-to-date, and of raising the standard of living of those who are dependent on agriculture.</P>
    <P>During the debates on the farm modernisation scheme, I quoted figures for a pilot area with which I am familiar in my own county.  I used those figures to prove that direct subsidisation in the form of grants for building, drainage and so on are not as great a stimulant to increased production as is generally believed.  In the particular area about which I spoke, I mentioned the explosive increase in the amount of stock.  There was an improvement in the quality of the stock and an increased standard of living for the people engaged in agriculture in that area.  I pointed out that the amounts of capital imput by the Government by way of grants for farm buildings and drainage were relatively small.  I am making the <Col N="1204" /> case now that the most important factor in that increased production, to my mind, was the intensification and the quality of the advisory service provided in that area.  From my own experience as a farmer and from watching trends in agriculture over the past number of years, I believe that the agricultural adviser has the greatest single contribution to make on behalf of farmers.</P>
    <P>I believe in a good strong, basic training for the young farmer, the type of training that is provided in the agricultural colleges through scholarships by the county committees of agriculture.  Some farmers can obtain this training privately.  It can also be obtained in winter schools, and at night classes.  All the activities carried on by the committees are very important. It is regrettable that so many of the young people who were awarded county committee of agricultural scholarships and attended the agri-agricultural training colleges have not returned to farming.  Nevertheless the benefits of this training have not been lost to the farming community.</P>
    <P>The one way we can ensure that education in farm modernisation and development is brought to the farmer is through the agricultural instructor. Labour has become very scarce and very precious in rural areas.  Farmers, particularly those engaged in mixed farming, cannot find the time to attend winter farm schools.  Young men may not realise sufficiently the importance of the education which is being provided for them.  The young married man is very anxious to obtain whatever education is available in modernisation and development, but he may not be able to attend winter farm schools or night classes.  The way to provide that man with the sort of service he wants is through the agricultural adviser.  These advisers have had a basic training and have time to study.  They are in contact with the Agricultural Institute and with other sources of research and development from abroad.  They can fit all this knowledge to the particular circumstances and needs of the locality and can bring it to the farmers.  This is the most important service we can give to the agricultural community.</P>
    <P>The advisory service has fallen down <Col N="1205" /> slightly in some fields.  I have the greatest respect for the advisory service and I owe a lot to the various instructors with whom I have been in contact.  This was first noticeable in the poultry industry where the poultry instructresses seemed to fall behind in so far as the giving of advice to the more intensive and more modernised poultry units was concerned.  They tended to help the small, less-efficient, less-important producer.  It was a pity that this occurred down through the years.  The high-powered adviser employed by business interests and sometimes by co-operatives took over the work of the poultry instructresses.  I can see the same thing happening in the intensification of the pig industry.  I should like to see the local instructor in the forefront of the developments that are taking place. Many members of the agricultural community will look to research institutions abroad rather than to the local agricultural adviser.  This is bad for the morale of the service.  I should like to see the local agricultural instructor being the most efficient, the most competent and the best equipped man available to deal with the problems of all farmers, however progressive they might be.  This happened in the poultry industry; it seems to be happening to some extent in the pig industry.  As beef production becomes more intensified I would not like to see this trend occur. It is very important that we should take good care of our advisory service.</P>
    <P>The question of specialisation should be seriously considered by the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries. Instructors in the various counties should have the opportunity to spend more time to study research institutions at home and abroad.  They should be enabled to travel abroad not just to become aware of what is most modern and most efficient but to see what are the most efficient means in similar situations in any part of the world.  We should have a number of instructors who have the time and the ability to do this sort of work and who can come back to their counties and make their knowledge available to the ordinary instructor so that they can give this special advice in cases where it is needed.  There is a great deal of work to be done for the man who is not a <Col N="1206" /> specialist, who carries on mixed farming as most of us know it, but who has at his disposal the advice and guidance of the specialised instructor.  This idea should receive more consideration.</P>
    <P>I welcome the appointment of senior instructors.  In the past we had perhaps too many young graduates with the necessary qualifications but with very little experience in giving the sort of advice needed by the farmer who was in difficulties, but whose knowledge and experience was a little more sophisticated than this young instructor expected. Senior instructors can work with these young graduates in their first years in which they will gain their own experience and knowledge.  The appointing of senior instructors should be welcomed by the advisory service.  The present Minister has done a lot to improve prospects of promotion and opportunities for them.  For too long agricultural instructors employed by the committees of agriculture were more or less in a <i>cul-de-sac</i> compared with the men who joined the Agricultural Institute and the Department and even with the men who were employed by private enterprise.  The man employed by the committees of agriculture found himself with very little promotional opportunities and very little chance to develop his talents for anything except direct advice in the field.  A young man embarking on his career should have the opportunity, if he has the ability, to go ahead fairly rapidly.  I welcome the new opportunities for promotion.</P>
    <P>The changing role of the adviser has been mentioned in relation to the new farm modernisation scheme.  This change was long overdue.  I would not like to see the number of officers engaged on land reclamation or rehabilitation reduced in any way.  I can see more work in the future for people engaged on land reclamation.</P>
    <P>We hear talk about the depressed state of agriculture at present.  It is very depressed in the west of Ireland, where farmers are engaged mainly on the production of store cattle.  These men have been hardest hit and the hardest hit of all is the man who depended for his living on a cow for the production of a calf which was sold either as a calf or a store bullock or heifer.  The man <Col N="1207" /> who sits down with his agricultural adviser, makes his plans for four or five or six years ahead, decides what money he wishes to invest and what return he expects to get out of it and stays with that plan through the good year and the bad, that is the man who in ten or 20 years will be the successful farmer.</P>
    <P>There will always be situations in which farmers may find they are in the wrong line because there is not a good future for this particular line.  Farmers who jump into calves one day, milk the next day, and then sugar beet, or wheat or barley will find, in the long run, that they will not be successful farmers.  The agricultural adviser could have a very stabilising influence on farmers with whom he is in contact and this contact should be promoted through conferences and discussions.  He should try in the bad periods to maintain the confidence of the farmer in the particular line he chooses to follow.  Nobody has to justify the role of the local adviser to anybody.  The Minister does not have to justify it.  The county councillors do not have to justify it to the ratepayers because everybody knows the important function the agricultural adviser performs.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MarkKillileaJnr" hpid="Mr. Killilea Mr. Killilea">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Killilea</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is certainly needed.  The contribution to the west is reasonably satisfactory.  I would point out that this is not the first time the contribution has been raised for the west but there is a reason for that.  The rate in the £ in the west is much higher than it is in the rest of the country. The west is, therefore, entitled to a bigger slice of the cake.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The reason why the Bill is necessary now is because last year the Government received on our entry into Europe £30 million which they did not reinvest in agriculture.  That was a mistake.  It would have been a good reinvestment because a better all-round situation would now prevail in agriculture. Senator McCartin tried to put good face on agriculture despite the appealling conditions which prevail in agriculture. The situation is unparalleled.  Certainly my generation have never seen such a depression.  That fact must be faced <Col N="1208" /> because, if it is not, we are only codding ourselves.</P>
    <P>The county committee of agriculture is a very important body.  It has always been so.  It is a body which distributes information on agricultural matters. There is a great need for that kind of information particularly in the west. The ratepayers are asked to pay, but the ratepayers do not mind paying provided that the net result is an improvement in our agricultural economy and a consequential improvement in incomes.  For the remaining part of this year ratepayers, particularly farmers, will find it desperately hard to meet their commitments due to the situation that prevails in agriculture.  My county is already at its maximum.  Indeed, we are in the &ldquo;red&rdquo; so this contribution is absolutely necessary.</P>
    <P>County committees of agriculture have always played an important role but they will have to play an even greater role now.  They will have to expand.  We have always in our committee tried to explain to our farmers exactly what is going on in agriculture. We hold night classes.  We hold field days to show why can be done.  We have tried to explain what should be done in sheep because we carry one-fifth of all the sheep in the country.  Our money, to date, has been well spent.</P>
    <P>There is a great deal of respect in our county for the county committee of agriculture and for the officials and staff who work so diligently for an improved agriculture.  The same can be said for most committees of agriculture in the west.  They have worked very hard in difficult circumstances.  The going has been hard but they have succeeded in disseminating a wealth of knowledge.  The fact that we have to go to our ratepayers is sad but we must get the money.  As I said, some of the EEC money last year could have been reinvested in agriculture.  We have lost out from entry into the EEC.  Regional policy seems to be at a dead end. Britain, in her typical role of either wanting to command or to break, has adversely affected us by stopping EEC regional policy.  Agriculture has lost out.  There is need for a big injection of money, particularly for the small farmer for whom the regional policy was really <Col N="1209" /> designed.  However, the ratepayer is asked to pay, he will pay, but I can assure the Parliamentary Secretary that he will find it desperately hard to pay.</P>
    <P>The sheep situation is acute at the moment.  We all know why.  The French market is closed.  This is an embarrassment to us.  Cattle are in a very bad state also.  We see what is happening with milk and one can foresee a situation two or three years hence when we will have a great surplus of milk.  The cost of the rising input in milk is about the only salvation at the moment for the farmer because other forms of agriculture are so depressed.  I am not blaming the Minister for that but more could and should be done.</P>
    <P>I put down a motion in this House concerning the Farm Modernisation Scheme and I remember saying it would be very hard to implement it.  It will be even harder now because the calculations made last January or February and sent in to the Minister, as he requested that time, are now hopelessly out of date.  Something was obviously slipped across on us.  I asked then that the directive be re-negotiated and my arguments then have been borne out. Despite all that has been said in favour of the farm organisation scheme, the onerous task that falls on the agricultural advisers and the small farmers to become viable is too great a burden. Forecasts can be quite crazy and a situation may prevail in six months time that cannot now be foreseen, much less forecast.  There is not a Senator who could forecast what the price of cattle will be next October.  Neither could he forecast the price of sheep or potatoes next October.  Yet, we were asked to make that forecast.  It is most unfair. In the prevailing situation the county committees of agriculture should now be asked to review the situation.  The Department should also review the situation with regard to the farm modernisation schemes.</P>
    <P>The advisory service needs to the strengthened.  In my county we need ten new advisers.  There are long delays but they cannot help that because they cannot be everywhere at the same time.  In a county so thickly populated with small farms the demand on advisers is very great.  We are losing <Col N="1210" /> out because some avenues of agriculture are neglected owing to the total absorption of the agricultural advisers on farm modernisation.  In the past we had field days dealing with sheep, wheat, beet, potatoes, particularly certified seed potatoes.  These have been dropped.  Why?  Because our agricultural advisers simply do not have the time for this very important work.</P>
    <P>I have great faith in the Agricultural Institute but they seem to specialise on a narrow aspect of farming and the broad spectrum of agriculture is left in abeyance.  The advisory service needs reorganisation and new thinking.  It needs a broadening in scope.  The ruination of agriculture is that one year a farmer specialises in cattle, the next year in beet, two years later in milk, and two years later he switches all over again.  There is no levelling off.  Trends here are vastly different from trends in Europe.</P>
    <P>It is our duty, and particularly the duty of the Government, to instruct county committees of agriculture which in turn should instruct the farmers in a new positive approach.  Chopping and changing has played too big a part in agriculture for the past 50 years.  This must cease and, to bring an end to it, it is absolutely necessary to reorganise the whole advisory service.</P>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary said that the staff of the agricultural advisory service now numbers 650 officers.  He referred to the new deputy chief agricultural officer who will have responsibility for educational matters. Education is half the battle; if a man is educated he has some chance but, if he is not educated, he has no chance Agricultural education is very important. There are ways and means of achieving that education but the county committees of agriculture have a responsibility where less well-off farmers are concerned who may not be able to get a proper agricultural education. This could be done in a variety of ways. Indeed, some of that £30 million should have been invested in this aspect of agriculture.</P>
    <P>One must admire the advisory services for their refusal to implement the farm modernisation scheme.  It was not, as has been suggested, a strike.  It was a <Col N="1211" /> refusal to implement a particular scheme to draw attention to certain existing defects.  The Parliamentary Secretary glossed over the situation.  He said that there was a considerable expansion in staff.  He pointed out they were making a new post of deputy chief agricultural officer.  I do not think this post was part of the bargain to put an end to the dispute between the advisory service and the Department.  It is not fair to say the Department in their forward-thinking way would have found this solution without the pressure brought to bear by the advisory service.</P>
    <P>I read an article in the Official Journal of the EEC which stated that the intensification of store cattle and beef should be furthered and nurtured.  The Department should not have allowed a situation to develop in which we are totally dependent on agriculture.  Our dependence is much greater than that of any other country in the EEC, with the exception of Italy.  We are definitely in &ldquo;slumpland&rdquo; where beef is concerned and there does not seem to be any way out.  Yet, only 16 months ago, Brussels told us&mdash;we accepted it as fact&mdash;that we should intensify our beef and store cattle production.  The results of that intensification can be seen today.  We really must be on our toes to ensure that these situations are not allowed to develop in the future.</P>
    <P>Senator Keegan rightly said that it was a public disgrace that the door to the French market for our lamb should be closed in our faces, the windows shut up and we shot out when, in fact, we are a good supporter of French produce. A protest is not good enough.  Something positive and concrete should be done to let the French know that we have a greater dependence on agriculture than they have.  That should be done and I would certainly lend my support to some way in which both the French and the other members of the EEC could be shown that our dependence on agriculture is very important.</P>
    <P>Coming back again to the last paragraph where the Parliamentary Secretary said he could see an advantage in having the statutory upper limit abolished entirely, even though this sounds daring, I do not think it is the answer. <Col N="1212" /> He is wise in not doing this.  The county committees of agriculture must be protected.  The only way they can be protected is by legislation in the two Houses of the Oireachtas.  County committees of agriculture all their lives have played an important role and they have an even more important role to play. Therefore, they are entitled to protection from the Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>We have seen the rise and fall of many organisations which, at the outset, were classified as great agricultural organisations. We have seen them lead and mislead. The one outstanding organisation that has stood all the tests of time has been the county committee of agriculture. I certainly would uphold those committees.  It was suggested that there would be an advantage in having the statutory upper limit abolished entirely. I do not agree.  This would be losing sight of the principles for which the county committees of agriculture stand.</P>
    <P>So, with a half-hearted welcome&mdash;I think that is the word&mdash;one has to accept this situation, one has to accept this Bill.  It does not go far enough.  It is not without mistakes.  Enough is not being done in agriculture and, in particular, in this field of agriculture.  A reorganisation of the advisory services should be looked into immediately.  The scope of the county committees of agriculture should be investigated.  It should be broadened.  They should be given a far more important role. Definitely, a greater slice of the national cake should be given to the county committees of agriculture.  The ratepayer is now certainly being asked to pay.  These committees have a great job to do and they need money to do it. This money should be forthcoming willingly from the Government of the day.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PierceButler" hpid="Mr. Butler Mr. Butler">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Butler</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the Bill.  Most people will congratulate the county committees of agriculture on the work they have done over the past number of years.  This Bill allows contributions of up to 40p in the £ by the county council to be made to meet demands by the county committees of agriculture.  It allows it but it does not state that from 1st January, 1975, every county committee of agriculture can demand 40p in the £ from county councils.  A case will <Col N="1213" /> have to be made for each demand and, if we look at the figures given in the statement, we see that up to now only 12 counties in this State have looked for and obtained the maximum of 14.5p to 15p in the £.  If 40p in the £ is to be demanded from 1st January, thereby increasing the rates, this cannot be substantiated.  I feel sorry for those county committees of agriculture who have obtained only 12p to 14p in the £ in ten counties.  In seven counties they have not even looked for 12p in the £ for the county committees of agriculture and for the working of those committees. I do not know how those seven counties could have a rate as low as or lower than 12p in the £.  Surely in those counties the same interest in agriculture should prevail.  I would advise all county committees of agriculture to examine their claims in the county council for extra incentives for agriculture. We all realise that agriculture is our principal industry.  It is the industry which this country has survived on and will survive on for many years to come. I should like to see more interest taken in the investment side of the business by the county committees of agriculture.</P>
      <P>It was stated by some Senators that there would be a substantial increase in the rates because of extra demands.  I would like to point out that in the western counties the State provides £3 for every £1 demanded.  The State subscribes 75 per cent and the county councils subscribe 25 per cent to the county committees of agriculture.  If I were in that position I would be looking for more and more to help the farmers in those counties to get proper advice. If the State pays £3 for every £1 I cannot understand why Senators from the west of Ireland are not encouraging their county committees of agriculture to look for more so that that investment could be put to the betterment of the small farmers in the west of Ireland.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Advice is needed and training must be given to those people in the advisory service.  They must be kept up to date in their knowledge.  There is a falling down in this respect.  When an agricultural instructor is appointed by a county committee of agriculture he does not get the opportunity to keep himself informed.  He works full-time with the county committee of agriculture.  He <Col N="1214" /> works day and night on their behalf, visiting farmers during the day and giving instruction to farmers at night. It would be advisable for county committees of agriculture to allow instructors at least two weeks for an educational tour or to go back to school to keep up to date.  Advice is necessary in a progressive State.  Up-to-date advice is always readily available and can be obtained if sought.  I advise the county committees of agriculture to look for this advice from their agricultural officers.</P>
    <P>Ten years ago we had only 354 agricultural officers attached to the county committees of agriculture and now we have 654, an increase of 300 over ten years.  It is not quite enough. We still need, over a period of four or five years, another substantial increase in the number of agricultural advisers to the county committees of agriculture because we are now in a situation where intensive development is necessary for every acre of land and where advice must be given to every farmer even if he does not look for it.  That is why I would like to see each county committee of agriculture appointing one officer who would be trained in socio-economics, especially in the counties where there is a number of small farmers.  This is necessary because some of those farmers are living in impoverished conditions. It would be better for them if they were out of farming, receiving a pension, leasing the land and living a happier life.</P>
    <P>I visit some of those farmers very often, especially in my own area, because I am involved with farmers. Every day I meet them and visit their holdings.  In my area it is not too bad. I can imagine areas especially in the west of Ireland where the average farms are much smaller than in my area.  Some of those farmers and their wives must be living in a situation which nobody else would tolerate.  If we had a person who was trained in socio-economics, a person who would be able to go to those people, a recognised agricultural adviser and sit down with them at the fire and talk to them we would get better results.  He could walk around the farm and point out faults here and there and advise them on the best way <Col N="1215" /> to spend their future years in happiness and contentment.  The only way some of them could do that is to retire from farming.  When the county committees of agriculture are increasing their advisory services at least one officer should be trained in the field I have already mentioned.</P>
    <P>Another thing that is very important in the agricultural field and in the education of the farmers is financial methods.  It is all right for a farmer to buy a beast for a certain figure and after a few months sell that beast at an increased price.  The farmer may think that he has gained fairly well.  If the agricultural adviser educated the farmers&mdash;many of them are educated, I admit, but there are some who are slow to learn and slow to accept advice&mdash;by getting across to them the importance of keeping expense accounts, then he would be doing not only the farmers but the State and the county a service.  It is necessary now more than at any other time that farmers should be business people.  They should be trained as business people as well as farmers.  The only way in which they can be trained is by advice given by the people whom they accept, the agricultural officers.</P>
    <P>Most of the increased demand on the county committees of agriculture, as the Parliamentary Secretary stated, arises as a result of the increase in salaries and expenses.  Seventy per cent of the demand is for salaries and expenses of agricultural advisers.  I am glad that they have got those increases.  They are entitled to them in the same way as everybody else.  Over the years the national wage agreement has allowed a percentage increase to all workers.  The agricultural adviser is also entitled to those increases and entitled to the increases for expenses that he incurs. There should be no hesitation about it. Every time there is a national wage agreement the agricultural officer should get it without even looking for it.  I do not think anybody should now go along and demand that they should be entitled to this, that or the other thing. They should get it there and then.</P>
    <P>I should also like to congratulate the Minister for Agriculture who stated that he is now appointing to each <Col N="1216" /> county committee of agriculture a deputy chief agricultural officer for educational matters because education is now all-important.  The chief agricultural officer will have to delegate his authority to the other officers.  My feeling is that the main job of the chief agricultural officer will be to educate the junior agricultural instructors.  Most of his time will be spent advising those on the up-to-date educational facilities that are available and the up-to-date knowledge he has received.  Because the statement has been made that a deputy chief agricultural officer will be appointed, many of the agricultural organisations will be demanding that that officer should come to this area and that area.  There will be such a demand for that one person that it cannot work, unless it is accepted that his advice be given to the other officers who will convey it to the farmers.</P>
    <P>I also congratulate the Minister on appointing 70 senior instructors.  One thing that has been disturbing the agricultural instructor appointed by the county committees of agriculture was that there was no promotion opportunity. There was a chief agricultural officer, then a deputy chief probably and after that the agricultural officer.  Now, there is an opportunity for promotion. Seventy senior instructors will allow at least two chief agricultural instructors in each county.  You will have a deputy chief agricultural officer and a chief agricultural officer, so that instead of one opportunity there will be four. This, in my opinion, is a very great advantage to the agricultural officers in the county.  At the moment the education of farmers is essential more than anything else.  The opportunity is being given to farmers to receive that education from the newly appointed officers. They should look for it because it will pay them very well.</P>
    <P>I should like to refer to scholarships to the agricultural colleges.  Up to very recently in every county agricultural scholarships were given.  Notices were published inviting applications for those agricultural scholarships.  Very little interest was taken and in fact many counties were not able to fill the number of places they held in those agricultural colleges.</P>
    <P>There is a demand for education by <Col N="1217" /> the agricultural organisations such as the IFA and the ICMSA, Macra na Feirme and Muintir na Tíre.  Here is an opportunity for some member to get first-class education in an agricultural college.  I know the type of education given in agricultural colleges because I spent 12 months in one of these colleges myself.  It was the best year of my life in every way.  I was educated in how to handle young people and discuss problems with them.  There were other things which we had to do in the agricultural colleges which probably gave us very little extra knowledge; we had to help the workers there.  I would advise young farmers to take the opportunity, if there are scholarships available in their counties to apply for those scholarships and work hard to get those scholarships because they will benefit eventually.</P>
    <P>There are many openings for people who have gone to agricultural colleges. Recently I saw an advertisement by the Department notifying vacancies.  One of the necessary qualifications was that applicants should have spent a year in an agricultural college.  This is very welcome.</P>
    <P>I should like to ask what influence the county committees of agriculture have with the colleges themselves.  I should think that some organisation such as the General Council of County Councils should have an influence with the colleges to see that the students are properly cared for and properly advised. We hear from time to time that this is not so in some colleges.  In the college I was in we got a very satisfactory education.  In other areas I believe this is not so.  From time to time members of the committees of agriculture should visit those colleges, see what is going on and have consultation with the headmasters. By consultations between members of the county committees of agriculture and officers in charge of the agricultural colleges a greater flow of the right type of information and education will be achieved.  This is advisable.</P>
    <P>Again I welcome the Parliamentary Secretary and I warmly welcome the Bill now before us.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I join with previous speakers in welcoming the Bill <Col N="1218" /> and at the outset I wish to avail of the opportunity to pay a sincere tribute to work done by the agricultural officers in the various advisory teams.  Despite the many difficulties they have encountered in past years their enthusiasm remains unabated and the results are there for all to see.  It is good to see that provision is made here to enable counties to make a substantial increase in the contribution from the rates to this work.  It is vital work and indeed it was never more vital than it is in the present months when we have a depressed situation in agriculture.</P>
      <P>With the euphoria of the last two years suddenly gone we realise that the situation is a highly competitive one. In this situation the main role of the agricultural advisory services appears as a service designed to cut costs; to show the farmers the most efficient ways of doing it and to counter the salesmen whose function is to lure the farmers deeper into debt with new-fangled ways of approaching various farmyard tasks. What is wrong in many sectors is not so much the price of the products but the fact that costs have risen so enormously that the resultant margin is indeed a slim one.  This is very important because we have an exceedingly threatening balance of payments situation&mdash;£150 million deficit for the current year.  It is on agriculture that we depend to reduce this: it is on the advice of the agricultural officers that we rely to spearhead this.  A primary consideration in tackling this problem is that our agricultural grass-based enterprises account for 91 per cent of our output as compared with 37 per cent in the EEC in general.  In other words, we are a completely grass-based economy.  The agricultural officers have the dominant role today in ensuring that the maximum use is made of that grass.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the conservation side they have been doing very valuable work: we must improve substantially in that respect.  Figures show that we are not sufficiently conserving food supplies. We cannot depend for profitable agriculture on imported foodstuffs.  We must minimise that dependence.  Likewise, a very close eye has to be kept on the level of fertiliser consumption in view of the greatly increased costs.  The <Col N="1219" /> agricultural officers have a vital role to play in that regard ensuring an economical use of artificial fertilisers and endeavouring by every means possible to promote a greater utilisation of farmyard refuse.  The crisis shows that their role has developed enormously. There is a slight hint in the Bill of structural change as a result of the recent agreement with the agricultural officers association: it needs to go much further than that.</P>
    <P>The provision of a post of senior instructor within the county is very useful and valuable.  It always struck me as the height of folly to have officers transferred to another part of the country on promotion.  I can recall excellent instructors stationed in Limerick being transferred on promotion to some place with a completely different farming set-up, in the midlands or elsewhere.  There is a grave loss in that. The aim should be to have promotional opportunities within the county for experienced officers.  The post of chief agricultural officer or deputy chief agricultural officer may be an exception. This is a post more related to administration and leadership.  Intimate knowledge of the local advisory scene is something which cannot be transferred and it takes a long time for a new officer to acquire it.</P>
    <P>I support very strongly all the excellent suggestions made by Senator Butler but especially the one suggesting opportunities for agricultural officers to study.  I suggest that one month every year be devoted to that because, by pooling ideas and getting together, a sound, commonsense approach to agricultural problems based on hard economics can be achieved.  That is precisely what we want today.</P>
    <P>I would like to see the ambit of the chief agricultural officer extended to all services within the county; we should foster the existing co-operation with the Agricultural Institute.  Various creamery groups, such as Mitchelstown and Golden Vale are developing their own special advisory services.  These are playing a vital role in a specialised area of quality milk production.  They should be assisted and encouraged by every means possible by the county committees <Col N="1220" /> of agriculture and the agricultural advisory service.  The State might well empower the county committees to make certain contributions to those services at least from the point of view of getting them going in areas where they are not functioning at present.</P>
    <P>I would like to see the pioneering work done by some of our excellent societies such as those I have mentioned become the standard pattern all over the country.  We also have the rise of agricultural contracting services as a very necessary and vital part of the modern farm organisation.  These would merit having at least one officer in each county assigned to their co-ordination and development.  From rather casual observation of them I can see very often while the execution of the work is first-class the business associated with it is appalling.  I saw a most excellent and hard-working contractor recently whose only fault was that his bills for last year had not been sent out and could not be extracted from him. Obviously, you cannot survive with that type of business approach.  It is essential that people such as he should be brought to see the faults of their organisation on the business side.</P>
    <P>There is also the very special problem of relief and seasonal workers in agriculture.  That is something which should be approached along similar lines.  Possibly the county committees of agriculture, in association with the Agricultural Institute, could have special training schemes at the beginning of the summer for relief and seasonal workers. The whole system should be catered for ranging from education aspects to the ordinary work on the farm.  The premium is on leadership.  We are looking to these agricultural advisers for leadership.  Above all, there is the question of the temporary agricultural officer who has great difficulty in becoming permanent.  Surely, when he serves a minimum of three or four years in an area it is in everybody's interest that he be given permanency: cut the red tape and let them get on with the work.  The work is such that an officer need do nothing or he could do a grand job: it completely depends on the initiative of the person concerned. Where that is the case we should recognise initiative and reward it and <Col N="1221" /> free it from as much of the trammels of red tape as possible.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Adoption Bill, 1974:" RHead="Report and Final Stages">
    <Title>Adoption Bill, 1974: Report and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I move amendment No. 1:</P>
      <P>In page 3, between lines 29 and 30, to insert a new section as follows:</P>
      <P>&ldquo;Section 16 of the Principal Act is hereby amended by the insertion before &lsquo;(<i>c</i>)&rsquo; in subsection (1) of &lsquo;<i>(bb)</i>) the natural father of the child&rsquo;.&rdquo;</P>
      <P>I shall not delay the House on this amendment because it has already been before the House on Committee Stage. I have given my reasons why I think the amendment should be accepted but I would like to make one comment.  The Minister quoted from the Nicolaou case in the Supreme Court and he pointed out that the court held that the father had no natural right to be heard.  This arose from the question of whether the Act was in breach of the Constitution; whether the father had a natural right which would make it unconstitutional not to give him that right.  They were not dealing with the practical right as to whether it would be reasonable or equitable that he should be heard.  I would like to point out that in section 16 of the people who are entitled to be heard, and there is quite a list of them, few, if any of them, with the exception of the mother, could be regarded as people who have a natural right or a constitutional right to be heard.  They are merely people who should be heard from a practical point of view and from a common-sense point of view, and from an equitable point of view to ensure that justice was done to everybody concerned in the application.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney) Patrick M. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Justice (Mr. Cooney)</NameTxt>
      <P>As Senators are aware, when this matter was originally raised on Second Stage I indicated when I was replying that I was against the point of view advanced by Senator Ryan and Senator Horgan in relation to giving rights to the natural father to be heard by the Adoption Board.  I indicated I was moving away <Col N="1222" /> from that point of view and asked time for further consideration.  On further consideration I am satisfied that for a number of reasons my initial reaction was the correct one.</P>
      <P>There has been no problem in this area.  There has been no case where a natural father has sought to be heard by the Adoption Board and has been excluded.  There is no grievance to be remedied by this amendment.  No actual case has arisen and not only is there no widespread grievance but there is no grievance at all.  That is the first point.</P>
      <P>The second point is that the natural father is not excluded by the 1952 Act. He does not have a right to demand to be heard by the Adoption Board but the board may hear him, if they so decide.  My initial reaction was that he should not be put on a par with the mother and allowed a hearing as of right.  I felt that the position of the two parties did not permit of an equality of approach.  I thought the mother was in a superior position because of the fact of the illegitimacy of the birth and that her superior position should be preserved through the entire area, and that it would be wrong to give the natural father equal rights, because, as I indicated, in many cases he might be an unworthy person and would not, because of that unworthiness, deserve equality of right.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is a further difficulty.  In a situation where a case is pending before the Adoption Board if the father had a right to come in to be heard co-equal with the right of the mother we could have a situation where there could be a conflict of interests between the father and the mother.  If we give him an equal status the board would be in a difficult position.  The direction and emphasis in the legislation is that the good of the child is the paramount consideration.  Nevertheless, the board could be in a difficulty.  It could be further complicated by the fact that the person purporting to be the natural father might find this fact being denied by the mother because there would not have been any finding of paternity.  But you might find the mother, in order to deny the claim of the natural father, taking the line that there is no proof that he is the natural father and she might deny the paternity alleged.  There <Col N="1223" /> might be uncertainty of knowledge on the part of both parties.  One could, unhappily, visualise such a situation arising.  I am sure the Senator would agree that would be a most undesirable situation, where you would have a tug-of-war between the two parties and the mother, in order to try to resolve it, denying the paternity of the person alleging that he is the natural father. This would be most undesirable.</P>
    <P>Again, if the man had a right to come and be heard before the Adoption Board, and bearing in mind that a right carries with it a corelative duty, the question arises then that the board might see themselves as being under a duty in all cases to seek out the natural father for the purpose of hearing him before making their decision on an adoption.  This is inconsistent with the nature of the case.  The mother is the person who has to be considered; the father's status at that stage is ancillary and should not be co-equal with that of the mother.</P>
    <P>The legal position of the natural father is such that, apart from an affiliation order proceedings, he has no status in our law.  The Nicolaou case confirmed this and this has been the legal position in regard to natural fathers.  They do not have any legal status by reason of their paternity and I think it would be introducing a novel legal principle if we were to admit the amendment in the context of this Bill. This question, however, is something that is being examined in the whole context of family law which is under examination at the moment.  The Committee on Court Practice and Procedure are looking at family law and, in addition, studies are being undertaken in my Department.  The rights and the position and legal status of the natural father can properly be determined in the context of family law generally.  An aspect of the matter will come up for debate in due course when Senator Robinson's private Bill, in due course, comes up for debate.  It would be better to leave this question of the position of the natural father for a more wide reaching debate rather than to admit new legal principles here in the comparatively narrow and specialised field <Col N="1224" /> of adoption.  For these reasons I would suggest to the House that the amendments are not desirable.  I sympathise with the humanity behind the amendments&mdash;the desire to see that justice is done by all parties involved&mdash;but for the reasons I have given we might be unwittingly doing an injustice to what I think are the principal parties, the mother and the child, the child, of course, is the principal, the mother is next.</P>
    <P>We could import into our law a novel legal principle without having fully considered all the consequences that might flow from it generally, particularly in the adoption world.  If these amendments were to be accepted the board might find themselves compelled in all cases to look for the natural father. There could be a tug of war between the natural father and the mother and there could be this very awkward situation where in order to defend her position the mother might deny the paternity of the person alleged to be the father.  All this would be undesirable and it would bring the Adoption Board into an area of controversy that, at present, does not exist.  It would bring the adoption procedure slightly into danger and it would be an added burden in a sensitive area.  I would ask Senators not to press the amendments for these reasons and on the understanding that the principle behind the amendments is in the course of examination.</P>
    <Speaker pid="EoinRyan2" hpid="Mr. E. Ryan Mr. E. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. E. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>I cannot understand why the Minister says that there is no case of this kind because the Nicolaou case was one where the father was unable to put his views before the board and where the board refused to exercise their discretion.  So there is at least one case where the father wanted to and was unable to put his view to the board. There may be many other cases which we do not know of where the father wanted to exercise his right or the right which he felt he had to give his views on the question of adoption.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Minister has said at this Stage and on a number of times on the previous Stage that he was reluctant to give the father equal rights with the mother.  It is quite clear that this does not propose to give the father equal rights.  First of all, the mother's views <Col N="1225" /> would be given far more weight than those of the father.  Secondly, the mother, under section 14 has a right which is not given to the father and which I do not propose should be given to the father.  So, both from the legal point of view and from the practical point of view it is not proposed to give equal rights to the father and I do not suggest for one moment, that the Adoption Board should regard the father as being a person who has equal rights or that his point of view should be given equal weight with that of the mother.  It is not a question of equal rights, it is a question of giving the father minimal rights and that is, to express a point of view.</P>
    <P>The question of whether the paternity of the father might be in doubt is of course a practical problem but not one which I think is insurmountable.  I think the Adoption Board would be quite right in refusing to hear somebody who merely said he was the father unless they were satisfied that he was in fact the father.  Again, in the case which I mentioned there was no doubt that the father in that case was the natural father.  The mother did not deny it, there was no question about it.  I am merely dealing with the kind of case where there is no doubt about that aspect of the matter and if the board were in any doubt I think they would be right not to hear the person who purported to be the father.  Again, this is a practical problem which I am sure that the board would be well able to deal with in a practical way.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1226" /> Finally, the Minister has put forward the objection which I do not think is a valid one and that is that if this was included, the board would have to seek out the father in every case.  Surely that cannot be a valid objection because there are, in section 16, eight or nine categories of people who are entitled to be heard.  I think it is most unlikely that the Adoption Board consider themselves obliged to seek out every one of these categories and ask them if they want to be heard before a decision is made.  Certain people are entitled to be heard if they want to be heard.  The board do not seek them out and the board would not have to seek out the natural father if he was included under this amendment.  I do not think that that was a valid objection to the amendment.  I feel that far from giving equal rights, far from introducing a system which would be in any way dangerous or create any real difficulties this is merely giving minimal rights to a person who may, now and again, and I willingly admit it is not a situation that will exist very often, wish to be heard. There is nothing to be lost by making the kind of provision that this amendment provides for.  There will be, in my view, an occasional situation where justice will not be done if this amendment is not accepted.  I feel the objections he has made to it are not sufficiently weighty to justify him refusing to accept the amendment and, therefore, I must press it.</P>
    <P>Amendment put.</P>
    <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 13; Níl, 19.</P>
    <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Browne, Patrick (Fad).<br />Cowen, Bernard.<br />Eachthéirn, Cáit Uí.<br />Garrett, Jack.<br />Hanafin, Des.<br />Keegan, Seán.<br />Lenihan, Brian.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">McGlinchey, Bernard.<br />McGowan, Patrick.<br />Robinson, Mary.<br />Ryan, Eoin.<br />Ryan, William.<br />Yeats, Michael B.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Blennerhassett, John.<br />Boland, John.<br />Butler, Pierce.<br />Deasy, Austin.<br />Farrelly, Denis.<br />Fitzgerald, Jack.<br />Halligan, Brendan.<br />Kerrigan, Patrick.<br />Kilbride, Thomas.<br />Lyons, Michael Dalgan.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">McAuliffe, Timothy.<br />McCartin, John Joseph.<br />Markey, Bernard.<br />O'Brien, Andy.<br />O'Brien, William.<br />O'Toole, Patrick.<br />Owens, Evelyn.<br />Russell, George Edward.<br />Sanfey, James W.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators W. Ryan and Hanafin; Níl, Senators Sanfey and Halligan.</P>
    <P>Amendment declared lost.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1227" /> Amendments Nos. 2 and 3 not moved.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickMarkCooney" hpid="Mr. Cooney Mr. Cooney">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cooney</NameTxt>
      <P>With the permission of the House I would like to raise a matter to which the attention of the House was drawn yesterday by Senator Yeats.  As a result of careful scrutiny, the Senator detected what is a drafting error in section 4, subsection (3).  Consequently, I wish to rectify the situation by way of amendment.</P>
      <P>Government amendment No. 3.</P>
      <P>In page 2, line 39, to delete &ldquo;(1)&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;(2)&rdquo;.</P>
      <P>Amendment agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
      <P>
        <i>Business suspended at 1.05 p.m. and resumed at 2.30 p.m.</i>
      </P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Agricultural (Amendment) Bill, 1974: Second" RHead="Stage (Resumed) and Subsequent Stages">
    <Title>Agricultural (Amendment) Bill, 1974: Second Stage (Resumed) and Subsequent Stages.</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cowen</NameTxt>
      <P>When concluding the debate on this Bill in the Dáil the Minister declared his appreciation of the Deputies' contributions on, as he described it, this short Bill.  I do not know why the Bill should be so short when it is so vitally important to the economy, so important that the Bill should be a very, very long one entailing a whole new structure for farming development and the activities and functions of our agricultural committees. This is what this Bill should entail.  What the Bill does is tell us that agricultural committees need more money to carry out their functions and it tells the committees to increase their demands on the parent body, the county council, from the present maximum of 15p in the £ to a maximum of 40p in the £.  The Bill then tells them to find this money in that particular way.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Parliamentary Secretary in the other House made much of the fact that the composition of the committees of agriculture are closely aligned to the various committees of county councils. <Col N="1228" /> He sees this as a safeguard either against the maximum of 40p being reached quickly or the present lower maximum of 15p not being significantly increased.  Is what the Minister is now doing not burdening county committees of agriculture with the job of fund raising?  Their principal function is servicing and maintaining agricultural, educational, instructional and development schemes of all sorts and the other various projects county committees of agriculture have to put into effect.  I believe, when the Parliamentary Secretary made this comparison, he was leaning towards the argument that because there are so many county councillors involved in committees of agriculture an even balance would be kept.  If that is the Government's approach towards promoting agriculture it is a very poor one indeed.</P>
    <P>When I said that I expected this Bill to be a long and important one I meant the Minister should have got down to the kernel of the problem.  Agriculture, as we all realise, is our basic industry. It is our bread and butter.  Progress on all agricultural fronts must always be maintained and we must always be seen to be accelerating the rate of progress. Agriculture has become a very sophisticated business particularly since our involvement in the EEC.  The vast increase in technical know-how and agricultural education requires adequate finance.  At the moment we need more finance.  This finance should, of course, be obtained through a more sophisticated system than that of rates.  The present inequitable and out-moded ratepaying system is one that we should now leave behind us.  It is not a system we should have in mind when talking and promoting agriculture.</P>
    <P>We, on this side of the House, look to the Minister to provide in this Bill the vast amount of money needed from the Central Fund.  Basically, the Central Fund is the most important source of national spending and investment; it is also the most fruitful one from the point of view of raising money.</P>
    <P>I would imagine that any committee of agriculture, while diligent in promoting its advisory services for the betterment of agriculture in general, would be very slow to ask ratepayers to increase their contributions to finance an expansion <Col N="1229" /> of advisory services.  In the past, when county committees of agriculture were financed through the rates, there was not this vast involvement in advisory services that we have today. Advisory services today have a very far-reaching and important role to play in promoting our agricultural economy. Agriculture and the advisory services are of paramount national importance and struggling committees of agriculture should not be encumbered with the burden of deciding to raise money through the ratepaying system in order to develop the advisory services.  That is why we think that the Minister could have done a great deal more in this Bill.  He could have broadened its scope to ensure that money would be made available from the Central Fund rather than trying to raise it, as will be the case, through the relevant local authorities. That is what this Bill involves.  It will depend totally on the county councils as to what increased moneys will be made available for the agricultural advisory services.</P>
    <P>I would like to know if the Minister for Agriculture has made any effort to pinpoint the Irish farmers' case in his consultations with his counterparts in Europe in regard to the implementation of the farm modernisation scheme. Those of us who are involved on agricultural committees are well aware of the vast financial involvement necessary in the implementation of this modernisation scheme to ensure that the ordinary Irish farmer will benefit from it.  We are also well aware that, for the implementation of this farm modernisation scheme, the number of advisory instructors necessary to ensure its effectiveness will be almost double. The ratio before this scheme came into effect was one adviser to 500 farmers. I believe the ratio, following the implementation of this scheme, will be one instructor to something in the region of 300 farmers.  Here we have evidence of the enormous cost of implementing this scheme.  I doubt very much, even if every county concerned increased its contribution to the maximum envisaged in the Bill of 40p in the £, if the money that this would bring in would give full effect to this farm modernisation scheme.  That is why I wonder if the Minister and his Parliamentary <Col N="1230" /> Secretary realise the enormous amount of money necessary effectively to put this scheme into operation.  That is why I believe the Minister may have fallen down in his consultations with his counterparts in Europe in not pressing the Irish case.  European funds should be available to implement such a very important new scheme.  Had the Minister made the cost known to his counterparts in Europe I imagine EEC funds would have been made available. This particular scheme is as a result of EEC Directive 159.  I have pointed out that the volume of work on the agricultural committees, on the agricultural advisers and their helpers will be enormously increased.  The point is more and more funds will be needed effectively to put the scheme into operation.</P>
    <P>It was suggested recently that the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries slipped up to some extent in not informing fishermen of the availability of grants for boats and fishing equipment in general from EEC funds.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Mr. M.P. Murphy Mr. M.P. Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.P. Murphy</NameTxt>
      <P>That is nonsense.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>It is irrelevant on this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cowen</NameTxt>
      <P>It was quoted in the papers, and not as being nonsense.  If that is the case, it is quite possible that money could be made available from EEC funds effectively to put into operation the farm modernisation scheme.  The fishermen were not told of the availability of grants towards boat-building and fishing equipment and that leads one to believe that the Minister may not be striking a hard enough bargain in the EEC to ensure that all the benefits that could accrue to Irish farmers do accrue.  No EEC funds should be considered as a pittance or a charity.  When funds are needed they must be sought and it is up to the Minister to seek them in a positive way, showing the future constructive contribution which would result from any desirable spread of investment from the EEC in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Europeans realise that what is good for Irish agriculture is good for Europe. This should be firmly stressed and emphasised in all negotiations.  We are no mere cog in the EEC as far as <Col N="1231" /> agriculture is concerned.  We are a very big wheel and many of the EEC countries realise this.  The Minister and his Department need not, therefore, be worried when negotiating on any particular aspect of agriculture.</P>
    <P>The present depressed state of Irish farming needs a stimulant and an injection now more than ever.  I doubt if the Minister and his Parliamentary Secretary are doing enough to ensure that that injection is forthcoming.  The best example of this depressed state is the cattle trade.  The Minister and his Department have failed to promote a store cattle trade to the EEC countries. We seem to be exporting only a limited supply of store cattle to these countries. This is an area in which the Minister and his Department could involve themselves to ensure a store cattle trade is built up.  This is one aspect of the cattle trade which has been totally and utterly neglected.  We are still depending on our neighbours across the water to absorb 80 per cent of our store cattle.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator has wandered somewhat from the Bill.  I would be glad if he would relate his remarks to the operation of the committees and the advisers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cowen</NameTxt>
      <P>Now that we are involved in the EEC we must appreciate the need for agricultural education and training. For instance, the farm modernisation scheme obviously entails detailed and informed instruction as a result of information obtained in Brussels.  What is happening in Brussels?  It is becoming more and more difficult to keep track of various complicated changes in legislation.  Committees of agriculture need more finance to set up a link with this source of information in Brussels. These committees and their advisers should have some sort of representation in Brussels so that they could bring their own unique problems for solution there. As well as that, Brussels would become aware of unique and important difficulties and developments in particular areas and different associations connected with agriculture would become involved with this link-up with European agriculture.  There is not a proper <Col N="1232" /> link-up to keep us informed of the varying trends in European agriculture and the Department could do more to ensure that the committees and their advisers get this sort of information.  Is it not just and right that our advisory services should benefit from EEC funds?</P>
      <P>The greatest need in Irish agriculture has always been the need for education in agriculture.  Much has been done by the agricultural advisers over the years. I want to join with previous speakers, both here and in the Dáil, to pay tribute to those men for their exalted interest in enlightening the farming community with very limited financial backing.  They have done a wonderful job and the younger generation of agricultural advisers are still doing a wonderful job.  They put in many hours which their pay packets may not reflect after their month's work.  I know of many young agricultural instructors who do a great deal of overtime helping to meet the needs of the Irish farmer in general and they do not rush back to their offices at 5 o'clock or 5.30 or whatever the closing time may be.</P>
      <P>The need for education is even more acute today than it ever has been.  In education, it is wrong to compartmentalise. The Department of Education are primarily concerned with education, but every Department must be concerned with education in some way or another. The Department of Agriculture and Fisheries are very concerned with education. Agricultural advisers are not just instructors; they are also advocates and educators working in a rural agricultural environment and they cannot be divorced from the general education scheme because they deal with the youth who are earning a livelihood by farming.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I believe that the Department of Agriculture and the Department of Education should work more closely together.  I have seen prospectuses from technical schools and regional technical colleges and from higher institutions of education with many courses on their programmes in which there should be a link up between both Departments. Agricultural advisers could avail themselves of some of these courses if there was a link-up between the Departments concerned.  There are other subjects on <Col N="1233" /> the curricula of these colleges by which young farmers could improve themselves from an educational point of view.  I ask the Minister to examine the possibility of a link-up between the two Departments.  In the programmes of technical schools and regional technical colleges there are basic aspects of education which are essential to the farming community at this time.  Many people from the farming community attend these schools and obtain their leaving certificates.  A study of business methods and accountancy would be useful for those with an agricultural background.</P>
    <P>There should be more emphasis on aspects of farming education in agricultural colleges.  There should be some sort of European study course and more emphasis on book-keeping and accountancy in recognised agricultural colleges.  Business methods are so important now that the farmer needs to be a very able businessman if he is to survive.</P>
    <P>While recognising the need for, and the good intentions of this Bill my main objection to it is that it is a short Bill in every sense of the word&mdash;short in what should have been its primary objective, the raising of sufficient finance.  It is a Bill which should be more involved and more radical.  Because it is too short, it is also too simple. If the Minister wants county committees of agriculture to increase their rate collection figures, will the contribution from the Department of Agriculture not increase at the same rate?  There is no indication in this Bill that the Minister and his Department are recognising the grave financial needs of advisory committees.  In Offaly there are no signs whatever of the initiation of plans to erect offices for the county, to provide the advisory personnel with proper accommodation.  There is a large number of office staff in the county involved with advisory committees and they are all confined to one room in the county council building in Tullamore. This is a major financial problem.  If we are to develop our advisory services by increasing taxation by the rates system I doubt very much if we can develop to the extent needed at the present time.</P>
    <P>The problem in regard to office <Col N="1234" /> accommodation is not confined to Offaly.  There are similar problems in most counties in Ireland.  The lack of proper facilities is not improving the situation and I am sure our counterparts in Europe recognise this.</P>
    <P>This is why, as I said at the outset, a great deal of money is needed to put our agriculture development into proper gear.  This is why I am against the Minister and his attitude towards raising this money.  Supplying proper facilities for our agricultural advisers is a national project and has European connotations also.  I maintain that the finances to provide proper office facilities in Offaly or in any other county should be forthcoming from central and European funds.  Unless there is a new approach the present position will remain for many years because the finance involved is enormous and, as I pointed out earlier, this is why I think this Bill does not meet the requirements of the agricultural committees and advisory services.</P>
    <P>Agriculture will earn money in proportion to the effort and money invested in it.  Agricultural committees are basically engaged in agricultural education. So money must be increasingly invested in agriculture and agricultural education. We need more relevant agricultural advice through the Department from the general source in Brussels and we need increasingly informed education in agriculture.  If the Departments concerned, Education and Agriculture, would get together the situation could be vastly improved through our technical schools and through our regional colleges.</P>
    <P>Irrespective of whether we like it or not rates are a form of taxation.  If we are to advance our agricultural programme and promote it to its fullest extent, let us avail ourselves of this money from the Government and from Europe.  Do not let us ask the ordinary, already over-taxed ratepayer to subscribe and develop our advisory services. I would ask the Minister, through the Parliamentary Secretary, to ensure that when we need money at any particular time to promote agriculture in this country we do not go back to the farmer himself and to the ordinary taxpayer for it.  Let us find it in the national &ldquo;kitty&rdquo;.  If we project the agricultural <Col N="1235" /> end of our identity in the EEC context I feel that the EEC funds will be made available through some source to put agriculture in this country at its proper level.  We want it taken out of its present depressed position and promoted to what it can be and should be, a really good industry, and let the farmers see that both Houses of the Oireachtas are behind their efforts to develop their way of living.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKilbride" hpid="Mr. Kilbride Mr. Kilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>This Bill is welcome.  If there were no consideration of foreign organisation it would be necessary for the Government to bring in this Bill to make provision for inflation due to the loss of the value of money.  In my time, as a member of a committee of agriculture, over a period of 20 years, I have seen when four pence in the pound in old money was the maximum the county council might subscribe.  It was felt at that stage that some sort of a climax would be reached.  The then Minister for Agriculture, either Dr. Ryan or his successor, increased the figure to seven old pence and it was later increased to 11 pence.  In real terms this was much more than the 15 new pence which is the maximum today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The Bill is welcome because it includes provision for implementing the Government scheme for modernisation of farms.  It includes provision for an extension of education.  Education is more than ever essential in 1974 even though the farmers are much more educated than many of the Senators opposite seem to think.  I doubt if there are any farmers today stupid enough to believe that if they are to have an advanced system of education they should not have to pay something towards it.  There is none so foolish as to believe, as is implied by Senators opposite, that all the money raised in consequence of this Bill would come exclusively from the rates.  They know well that the Government, in the ordinary course of events, help to meet the costs of agricultural committees by a subvention of at least 50 per cent and, in the western counties, by a subvention of 75 per cent.  The ordinary grants that are paid in subsidies are not paid from the rates and it is naïve for somebody to suggest that this is the only effort the <Col N="1236" /> Government are making towards aiding agriculture and that this is the sum total of the effort of the Department of Agriculture in this year of 1974.  The cost of administration is considerable and for that reason I think the scheme should be utilised more effectively.  The agricultural instructors should be in a position to afford the best possible opportunity to farmers to take advantage of the services provided.</P>
    <P>The construction, improvement or replacement of agricultural centres was envisaged in the past six or seven years. The Department offered a grant of £15,000 towards the centres.  That was four years ago.  At that time the cost per square foot of the construction of the centre was approximately £4.  It is now £6.  Does the Minister think an increase of £20,000 is adequate?  In my county we have been campaigning for an agricultural centre but so far without success.  Money will be a vital factor when it comes to implementing whatever plans we finally decide on.  I would respectfully submit to the Parliamentary Secretary that a grant of £25,000 for such a centre would be appropriate and would correspond to the £15,000 originally allocated.</P>
    <P>Some county agricultural instructors have had very lofty notions about what a centre should contain.  Because the Department have not put out a standard accommodation plan for committees of agriculture many committees are placed at a disadvantage if a particular individual closely associated with the Administration looks for something extraordinary.  In one county, somebody associated with the Administration wanted additional office accommodation and it was left to the Department of Lands to facilitate other services, brucellosis testing, tuberculosis schemes and anything else connected or linked to agriculture.  That is not correct.  The Minister should put his foot down and say, according to the number of instructors in a particular county, here is what is wanted per instructor; here is what is wanted for a lecture hall and here is what you should have.  Foolish notions should not impede or hold up for years the opportunities afforded to committees of agriculture to avail of these schemes and grants which are now being offered and which I welcome.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1237" /> An agricultural instructor in 1974 differs in regard he what he has to do and whom he has to see and the manner in which he deals with business from an agricultural instructor in 1954.  A certain amount of enlightenment is needed to keep up with developments, particularly since our entry into the EEC.  Courses should be held every year to enable agricultural instructors to keep alert.  An agricultural instructor from, say County Offaly, who is appointed to Cavan or Leitrim or Mayo or Longford and who is not acquainted with the area, should get an opportunity of studying the area for at least six months before appointment. He would thus know the special needs of the county to which he was assigned.  There is not much point in appointing somebody who has been acquainted with the growing of grain, barley and oats to a place like north Cavan, north Longford or north Leitrim.  It has been said already today that instructors should not be transferred to areas very far distant.  I agree entirely with that.  If he is due for promotion he should be given an area that is akin to the particular one in which he is at present working.</P>
    <P>The people who get instruction, the people in whom we all profess to be keenly interested, the farmers and farmers' sons, should be educated in the trend of events in Europe with which this country is so much involved at present.  They should be educated as to what to expect in the years ahead.  We would not then have a situation where somebody is led to believe&mdash;it has happened, I will refer to it later&mdash;that there is a future in beef and when he has switched his thoughts to the production of beef he finds that there is nothing in it.  That is one instance. Farmers should be made aware of what developments are likely to take place in the future, what competition will be like in the EEC, and to what extent can we be guaranteed tariff protection.</P>
    <P>The pity is that farmers are not told these things.  They are told how to produce more pigs, grain and beef. They are offered incentives to stop producing milk and to switch over to beef production.  We have had this going on over the last six or seven years. But we have never been told of what the effect of competition in the European <Col N="1238" /> market would be on our profits.  In the past the farmer has been ignored when he said: &ldquo;What am I going to get out of this?&rdquo; Was he not as much entitled to ask that question as the labourer who went out to work and to give his services for a week?  A great many people feel farmers have no right to demand special treatment.  I agree with that.  But the fact is that society is so structured here that the price of what the farmer has to offer goes up or down without any relationship to the producer's costs.  The farmer is being placed in the position of having to produce something for society and very often get little out of it.</P>
    <P>Agriculture in this country has been made the plaything of politicians down the years.  Now we have farmers being told they should not have to pay rates. They are being told that what it costs to help them become better farmers is an imposition.  We are told that because of our association with the EEC circumstances now should be better than they actually are.  We are told that if the farmer was much more enlightened than he is considered to be he would have been in revolution long ago.</P>
    <P>The Minister is being blamed for not having a marketing system and for not putting our produce on the European market to the best advantage.  Anybody making that statement should read of the revolt of farmers in Belgium and in France this week to see what the real position is, if they are so stupid as not to see it already.  Such people are trying to hoodwink us that our difficulties are in consequence of our entry to the EEC three years ago and that these difficulties are of the making of the Minister and of the Government.</P>
    <P>The Minister is facing up to a very difficult task in Europe.  He has challenged all comers and has asserted the rights of Irish farmers.  He is actively promoting a development scheme for this country.  The most vehement opponents of the Government&mdash;at least those of them who are honest&mdash;would not dare to say that the present Minister is not playing a man's part in Europe. He is to be commended and I should like that he be commended from these benches today.</P>
    <P>Grants are being paid by committees of agriculture as incentives to farmers, <Col N="1239" /> to educate them and to make them aware of the advantages of the use of certain implements.  At present it is impossible to get fertilisers at an economic price.  Many small farmers find it impossible to finance a fertiliser scheme, except with the help of the Agricultural Credit Corporation. Grants should be paid to farmers who would provide slurry tanks in the vicinity of pig production centres.  We have complaints of pollution in various rivers and various lakes in the country&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like the Senator to relate these remarks to the advisory services, which are the subject of the Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasKilbride" hpid="Mr. Kilbride Mr. Kilbride">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kilbride</NameTxt>
      <P>The services of the agricultural instructors are financed by the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries and in that sense I relate my remarks.</P>
      <P>We are told that pig slurry is a very effective replacement for fertilisers.  This is what has been polluting many of the rivers.  The Department should make regulations for enabling slurry to be sold to farmers for spreading on the land. Slurry tanks should be subsidised.  These were being subsidised by the Department but they recently stopped doing so.  They subsidised a small number in some counties, including my own county.  Slurry is immediately available and at very little cost.  I would urge the Minister to aid small farmers by giving more and adequate grants for slurry tanks.  This fertiliser is one of the best we could have for the land.  It is cheaper than the phosphates and nitrates that are imported at great cost.</P>
      <P>Because of the economic circumstances prevailing there the 12 western counties have an advantage in that the cost of agricultural services there are met, to the extent of 75 per cent by subvention from the Department.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The cost of agricultural centres in the 12 western counties should also be met to the extent of 75 per cent irrespective of the value of the holdings.  If that were done, if we made a beginning in regard to incentives and gave effect to what has been proposed in that scheme three or four years ago, people would <Col N="1240" /> have appreciated that agricultural education was something that had the same standard of dignity and importance from the administrative point of view and its effectiveness would have been fully appreciated by the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries.  At present there are areas where classes are held and instructions are given that do not have any relationship to the standard of education that should and, I hope, will normally apply to these centres.</P>
    <P>A farmer must have more than a specialised notion about a particular sphere of activity.  He is not somebody who knows all about a horse and nothing about a cow or a sow.  He must know all about the horse, the cow, the sow and the plough.  He must know about the production of grain and about diseases associated with animals.  He must know everything associated with the multiplicity of activities that go on on a mixed farm.  He must, if he is to succeed, be somebody well versed by experience and by technical education and this is where the good agricultural instructor comes in.  He should be well versed in everything that is going to affect him, in the particular spheres of activity on the farm in which he is engaged.</P>
    <P>To my mind the agricultural instructor can help farmers by imparting the knowledge he has, almost as much by the manner in which he imparts it and by the approach he has and how he is able to fit in with the company of farmers and farmers' sons.  I think it should be accepted by everyone that an agricultural instructor who comes out and sets himself up with a cigar, a pair of long stockings, plus-fours or a pair of drainpipe pants and very long hair, will not fit into the farming life.  These fellows are not able to get the confidence of the farmers.  If they can get the farmer to accept what they have to say they must be as one of them.  These are some of the things that I have noticed have made certain instructors in certain areas far more successful than others.</P>
    <P>Confidence in an instructor is three parts of education.  If you feel that somebody is coming out to talk to you about a matter about which you are anxious, you would like him to be the same as yourself.  You would like him <Col N="1241" /> to be prepared to talk to you about the farm and the stock on it.  If he comes out prepared to talk about this you are going to welcome him and look forward to him coming.  But if he comes out to you with a notion that he is just that little bit above you and wants to talk down to you, and if he will not give an answer that is easily understood, you will not want him, no matter how decent a fellow he is.  This is one of the areas to which education in the agricultural sphere should apply.  Kindergarten study should be followed when training people who are expected to impart knowledge to farmers' sons or daughters. They should realise that the manner of presentation associated with farming in different areas may be very important from the point of view of the extent to which their instructions and lectures will be successful or otherwise.</P>
    <P>The Minister deserves well of the people.  As far as farmers are concerned, their relationship with the Minister is good.  He has their confidence, irrespective of the sphere from which their organised activities are coming.  The real test is how far the people can see that the Government and the Minister are genuinely and sincerely facing up to their responsibilities.  I am glad to see the Minister is facing up to them.  I hope when he has negotiated a development scheme, whether in conjunction with Northern Ireland or not, it will be as successful as his determination indicates. I hope that this extension of the right of committees of agriculture to get the finance they require, will be operated and applied in a way that will bring satisfaction to the farmers and to the people.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBrennan" hpid="Mr. Brennan Mr. Brennan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Brennan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have no desire to delay the House very long because everything that could usefully be said about this Bill has been said.  I congratulate Senator Kilbride on his detailed speech.  I sympathise with the Minister and his Parliamentary Secretary because they were left with a legacy which is likely to remain with us for some time.  I would like the committees to ask them to come down from their lofty perch.  I would describe most of the speeches I heard today as &ldquo;roamin' in the gloamin' &rdquo; to use a Scottish phrase.  I have a fair idea of <Col N="1242" /> the Republic from north to south. The one thing, if I judge rightly, that is besetting the farmer today is how he will feed his stock for the next 12 months.</P>
      <P>I will not go into the merits or demerits of the people who went before the Parliamentary Secretary or the Minister.  One need not be a Bachelor in Agricultural Science to know as any farmer could tell, that the more cattle one breeds the better one's chance of controlling not only the financial structure in one's own State but also one's entry to the EEC.</P>
      <P>These are the facts.  No provision, however humble, was made to feed that particular stock.  Now we find ourselves in the unhappy position that we cannot hope to feed them.  I am afraid, Parliamentary Secretary, that what I am saying is unfortunately only too true.</P>
      <P>The vast majority of our cattle are underfed at the moment.  This is the time of the year when we should have the best grass&mdash;after the 12th of July is the peak time in Northern Ireland. Agricultural instructors led one to believe that no beast could be fed out of anything but a polythene bag.  The compounders, as the people and the Parliamentary Secretary must be aware, know that for hundreds of years&mdash;if not a thousand&mdash;cattle were fed not out of polythene bags but from the natural resources of the country&mdash;the grain, oats, barley, <i>et cetera.</i>  They told us this was all wrong.  They must have a balanced diet which consisted of a certain amount of barley and oats with a handful of grass meal thrown in for good measure.</P>
      <P>I am glad the Parliamentary Secretary's advisers are amused, but these are the facts, whether they like them or not. How did the stocks survive down through the centuries?  I, being a historian, found that one of the generals at the Battle of Clontibret was fined 500 cattle for cowardice.  If there were 500 cattle taken out of the parish of Contibret where I come from there would be very few left.  Senator Kilbride went to great lengths about the advisory service.  I have every respect for the advisory services but they have their limits and will continue to have their limits.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1243" /> The pig industry, as far as I can see, has vanished.  What is the Department's redress for this?  Have they made any real contribution towards saving the pig industry?  Have they anything in mind? I would like the Parliamentary Secretary when he is replying to answer my queries, although I have grave doubts that he can do so.  If I am to judge rightly the farmers are in an unfortunate and unhappy position today. They are in a much more unhappy position than when they were sitting over on the east side of this House when a certain former Minister for Agriculture was then in charge.  I see no market today nor I hear no intention of any market.  I wonder why?  This is a matter for themselves of course, but that is one of the things they are entitled to have.</P>
    <P>Seanad Éireann is supposed to be a vocational body, yet it seems strange that there are only four Members present to debate this Bill.  If we were looking for Seanad votes there would be more here.  Maybe I am too critical and I confess to my faults.  Be that as it may. I am on more than nodding terms with the agricultural community because I live in an agricultural community in my native county of Monaghan.  I am on nodding terms with most counties in Ireland.  I was in Cork at the end of February or the 1st of March and I came from Bandon in Cork into Limerick, from Limerick to Tipperary. I watched from the train as I travelled from Nenagh to Dublin at that particular time and counted only two herds of cattle being fed on my side of the train.  I give credit that the same would happen on the other side.  Cattle cannot be put in one's pocket.  The Department's experts should have ensured that if there was an increase in cattle numbers there should also have been an increase in seeds to sustain these cattle.  That was and still is a source of worry to me.  It is as prevalent today as it was last March.</P>
    <P>I have every sympathy with the Minister.  I believe he is doing his best and I wish him well.  I have no desire to delay the House any longer.  I would like the Parliamentary Secretary when he is replying to tell us if he has any solution for the pig industry.  I come from an area where the pig industry <Col N="1244" /> was very remunerative.  We are a community of small farmers.  Believe it or not, I did not know that we are blessed or cursed, if you like, with so many hills.  On the journey from Nenagh to Dublin I found that the hilly country was much more acceptable than flat, because the flat country will flood much more quickly than the hilly country.</P>
    <P>I would like the Parliamentary Secretary to let us know when he is replying what he has in mind for the pig industry.  Can he give an assurance that grain will be provided?  Will he advise the farmers to grow more grain, oats and barley.  In other words, will he give them a balanced diet?  If the Cathaoirleach will permit me to do so I would like to tell a joke.  I knew a young man who was doing his final examination for the position of agricultural instructor.  One of the questions was to give instructions for the preparation of a balanced diet for a bonham two days old but the young man shied away from the question because he was afraid to attempt it.  On one occasion I happened to be visiting a friend who is in the veterinary profession.  We called to a farmhouse in County Limerick where we spoke to an old lady.  There was one sow across the street, another in the yard and still another elsewhere, I said: &ldquo;Oh, I see you have a lot of pigs here&rdquo;.  She said: &ldquo;I have another litter over here but the sow died&rdquo;.  I asked her how she reared them and she replied: &ldquo;Come over here, son, and I will show you&rdquo;. I went over and saw her prepare a balanced diet which consisted of a certain amount of milk, glucose and water.</P>
    <P>What I am trying to convey to the Minister, Parliamentary Secretary and the Department is that they should get down from their lofty perches and not be lead away by the nonsense we hear too much of.  There was an abundance of pigs, poultry and cattle in this country hundreds of years ago.  Now we find ourselves in the unhappy position that we have more cattle than we can feed.  I hope the Minister will do everything possible to alleviate that problem.</P>
    <Col N="1245" />
    <Speaker pid="WilliamRyan" hpid="Mr. W. Ryan Mr. W. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. W. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>At the outset we were told that this was a short Bill.  I am afraid the debate on it proved a rather lengthy affair.  Therefore I intend to be very brief.  I have to be because it would be difficult for me to find something to say which has not already been said.  I am not entirely happy about this Bill.  It is the third Bill of this nature which I have seen come to this House during my time here.  On all other occasions the Bills were welcomed and passed because we were assured that the money which they were making available was being spent on for the improvement of the advisory services thereby increasing production and the farmers' income.  That happened.</P>
      <P>On this occasion it is a little different. We are asking the ratepayers to pay 40p in the £ on the rates for agriculture. I do not see any hope of getting any return for that money such as we got in the past.  The farmers' incomes at the moment are lower than they were last year.  This should not be.  All other sections of the community have increased their incomes.  We were told by economic experts some years ago that once we got into the EEC rates on agricultural land would be abolished. The farmers were very happy about that and it happened the farmers would not be grumbling today about having to pay income tax.  It seems rates on agricultural land in this country will continue to exist although that is not the case in a number of European countries.  While this situation exists it is grossly unfair to ask farmers to pay income tax.</P>
      <P>In the Bill it states that the western counties will only pay 25 per cent of the rates, that 75 per cent will be borne by the Department.  I see no reason why this should not be applied to the whole country.  We, in Tipperary as well as people in other counties, find it as difficult to pay rates as do the people in the western counties.  We have very high valuations and the rates are pretty high.  If the Department cannot find EEC funds to relieve the rates of the 40p in the £ they should find some other way of helping the farmers in all counties, so that each county would only have to pay 25 per cent.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I have been a member of a committee of agriculture for 24 years.  We have always followed the advice we got from <Col N="1246" /> our CAO down through the years.  Any time he asked for increased staff or a sub-office he was facilitated because we believed that all this money was money well spent.  When I asked our CAO, a few days ago, about the cattle prices and pointed out that increased production had been the cause of the fall in prices he replied that it was not the adviser's job to provide a market. That is a job for the Department.  No doubt he was right.  I believe there should be closer liaison between the Department of Agriculture and Fisheries and the local advisers.  There is no use in the agricultural adviser recommending increased production when the bottom has fallen out of the market.</P>
    <P>I am pleased to know that the dispute between the Department and the local advisers has been settled.  It is up to the Department now to ensure that there is no further delay in the payment of grants.</P>
    <P>Farmers living in urban areas have not been mentioned.  Quite a number of farmers in County Tipperary reside in urban areas.  I am sure a similar situation applies to every county in Ireland.  They are excluded from the committees of agriculture.  They get no rebate on rates.  I do not understand why these farmers are classified differently from farmers living, one might say, across the ditch from them. It is time the Department did something about that.</P>
    <P>I am slightly worried about female staff working in committees, especially poultry instructresses and those engaged in home management.  Some time ago, a rule was introduced whereby married women can now retain their jobs.  This means that there are fewer jobs available for girls leaving colleges.  It is most unfair that those girls should find it so difficult to get a job.  I know girls who left college almost a year ago and who are still without jobs.  When a temporary job is advertised they have to go and canvass all the members of the committee in different counties to try to get the job. In most cases they are not successful. While it may be a good idea to allow married women to continue in their employment after marriage, in this field where the number of jobs is limited, <Col N="1247" /> they should never have been allowed to do so.</P>
    <P>Finally, I want to refer to the structure of our county committees of agriculture.  This structure is badly in need of change.  We were told a year ago that there would be a change and that rural organisations such as the IFA, the ICMSA, Macra na Feirme and others would be allotted a certain percentage&mdash;I think 25 per cent&mdash;of the membership of each committee of agriculture.  With the change of Government this did not happen and the committees have now been re-formed for the next five years.  I doubt if these organisations have got representation anywhere.  They did not get it in my own home county.</P>
    <P>As far as the committees are concerned, I do not want to blame any one of the three political parties more than the other.  I blame them all for the position in each county.  If Fianna Fáil have a majority in a county they give all the seats to Fianna Fáil members&mdash;or most of them, anyway.  If Labour and Fine Gael have a majority in a county&mdash; and they have that in a number of counties&mdash;they do the same.  This is not fair.  In South Tipperary we got 11 seats on the county council; we got only six seats on the committee of agriculture Labour got four seats on the county council and five seats on the committee of agriculture, which I think is not proper.  This is a difficult matter to solve but it is a matter in which the Minister and the Department should take a hand.  I understand that in one or two counties the method adopted is that you get so many seats for the number of votes you got at the county council election.  That is the fairest way but it will never be done if it is left to the committees.</P>
    <P>We talk a lot about power sharing and we advise others that power sharing is their salvation but when it comes to power sharing down here among the three political parties we forget all about it.  I want to make it clear that I am not blaming Fine Gael or Labour any more than I am blaming Fianna Fáil.  The same position exists in every county.  Whichever side get the majority on the council grab all the <Col N="1248" /> seats on the committee of agriculture, which is the most important committee in the county.  I would suggest to the Minister that he take note of this and perhaps in five years time we may see a change in the constitution of committees.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelPatMurphy" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. M.P. Murphy) Michael Pat Murphy">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Agriculture and Fisheries (Mr. M.P. Murphy)</NameTxt>
      <P>When introducing this short Bill in the Dáil the Minister prefaced his remarks by saying that the sole purpose of it is to enable county councils to give increased contributions, where necessary, towards the financing of the county committees of agriculture in the local financial year, commencing 1st January, 1975.  It was indicated by the Minister that the sole purpose of this measure is to enable county councils to give the increased contributions if councils so decide to grant such contributions.</P>
      <P>The original Agricultural Act was passed in 1931 and it set down that county councils must grant a minimum of 2d in the £ and a maximum of not more than 3d in the £ to county committees of agriculture.  That was varied in 1941, when councils were empowered to grant up to 4d in the £, in 1948, the rate was fixed at 7d; in 1955, 10d, in 1958, 15d, 1964, 21d, 1970, 27d and 1971, 15 new pence, so that this Act is similar in almost all respects to seven previous Agricultural (Amendment) Acts that were brought before both Houses of Parliament to enable committees of agriculture to get more financial assistance from county councils where councils decide to grant that additional help and assistance.</P>
      <P>I know that the House generally welcomes the necessity for this measure because I am sure all Senators appreciate that with the dwindling value of money more finances are needed by committees of agriculture to carry out their duties and functions.  I note here that for the year ended 31st March, 1974, the total expenditure of committees was £3,202,478.  Nine years ago that figure was £1,243,000.  The House will see that the expenditure of our 27 committees of agriculture is rising steeply from year to year.  Thus, there is a necessity for this measure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1249" /> It is made clear in the openning statement that a figure of 40p was desirable mainly by virtue of the fact that this is the eighth amending Act that is necessary and we have learned from experience that the amounts authorised by the previous Agriculture (Amending) Acts were inadequate and insufficient.  We thought it well to raise the figure from 15p to 40p.  That does not mean&mdash;as suggested by the last speaker, Senator Ryan&mdash;that it is mandatory on a county council to make available to a committee of agriculture 40p in the £.  The Bill does not ask the county councils to do any such thing. Neither does it do what Senator Cowen alleged&mdash;tells a committee of agriculture that it must demand 40p from a county council.  It does not tell a county council or it does not tell a county committee of agriculture to do anything. It lays down in simplified terms that in the case of a county committee of agriculture it is appropriate for them to make a demand on the county council of their area, their parent body, for a figure from local revenue of up to 40p in the £ or such sum as they in their wisdom consider to be necessary to measure up to their requirements.</P>
    <P>It is the sole right of the county council to say whether the demand is reasonable or whether it should be met.  I mentioned in the other House that seldom or ever did any friction arise between a county council and a committee of agriculture regarding demands made under the existing legislation. I gave as a reason for that, that to a large extent and this was referred to by Senator Ryan, committees of agriculture are made up mainly of county council members.  I instanced the case of my own county of Cork where the number on the committee is 28-26 of whom are members of the county council, so that in making demands to the parent body the committee of agriculture are to a great extent making a demand on themselves.</P>
    <P>I am satisfied from my experience as a member of a committee of agriculture and from what I have read and know of the discussions at other committees that there is no danger of any committee in Ireland making a demand on a county council for money from local rates unless, in the opinion of the <Col N="1250" /> committee, that money is necessary in order to advance their work in some way in which the committee would like to see it advance.</P>
    <P>Mention has been made of the different schemes that need development&mdash;improvement of offices and accommodation whether they be desirable improvements such as the extension of services unless indicated in the opening statement.  The main point of agricultural committees is the question of salaries.  The criticism was made here that it was unfair to bring a Bill like this into the House and ask the Houses of the Oireachtas to approve of a measure that is likely to impose additional taxation on our rural communities.</P>
    <P>The imposing of additional taxation is left to the local democratically elected members of county councils. I am a firm believer in democracy and a firm believer in having such local bodies&mdash;county councils and committees of agriculture&mdash;that are elected by the local people in their areas, that are elected by them through the ballot boxes and I hope that that system will long continue in this country.  Despite whatever disadvantages it might have the advantages far outweigh them because people have opportunities to remove members of councils if they so decide and if they consider not to be measuring up to their requirements.  It is much easier to remove the democratically elected member of a local authority than it is to remove an officer or an executive member of that authority.  If local bodies are to continue they must make some local contribution.  If the Minister were to bring in the Bill for the purpose of raising money to committees of agriculture and if he were to tell the Senators that he proposes to do away with this local contribution and would ask the Exchequer to bear all local costs for committees of agriculture, what would be the natural outcome? If central funds pay for the services provided by the committees the Department here, in my view, would be taking over and the committees would have no right to continue in existence any further because they were making no local contribution.</P>
    <P>Money does not fall from Heaven <Col N="1251" /> here in Ireland no more than it does in any other country.  Whether it comes from central funds or local revenue it comes out of the pocket of &ldquo;Johnny Citizen&rdquo;.  For national taxation it comes out of his right hand pocket and for local taxation it comes out of his left hand pocket.  It is the Government's duty to devise what in their opinion is a fair and equitable measure for extracting that money from our people be it through the avenue of national taxation or through rates.</P>
    <P>There is general agreement&mdash;and I have a somewhat similar term of membership of a committee of agriculture as has Senator Ryan&mdash;among committees of agriculture that the contributions made from central funds are fair and reasonable.  Most of the local councillors do not consider there is an obligation to find some of this money locally because if all the money was to be provided from Dublin what would be likely to happen? Some scheme might come up for consideration by a particular committee of agriculture and a councillor might say that all this money comes from Dublin and that they should gobble it up because if they do not Limerick or some other county will.  It gives a sense of responsibility to a committee that approve of a particular scheme within their county for they are obliged to ask the local people to pay part of the costs and this is fair and reasonable.</P>
    <P>The Government, mindful of the problems of the people in what is termed as the congested part of this country&mdash;the 12 western counties&mdash;are determined that they should get special consideration.  I think there is general agreement on that.  I would say to Senator Ryan that a farmer in my area of south west Cork is in a different position to a farmer in Senator Ryan's area of south Tipperary.  His land is rather different, to put it mildly.  It needs a great deal of nourishment and its productivity potential is nothing compared with the lands in most parts of this country.  That carries with it this obligation of nourishing it to a much greater extent.  We know how costly nourishment is at this time.  With the indifferent nature of the land, its low <Col N="1252" /> productivity content, which unfortunately is the position of the southern and western and north western part of this country, Governments here in their wisdom determined that such counties were entitled to some special consideration and they gave them this special consideration of making available in the case of county committees of agriculture grants of 75 per cent as against 25 per cent in the 14 counties which are deemed to be more favourably placed so far as agricultural development is concerned and so far as the productive content of the land, mainly in the four counties, is concerned.</P>
    <P>I could not comment&mdash;neither I nor anyone else here has that authority&mdash; on whether it is fair or just that that should be the case.  I merely offer a view.  There must be boundaries.  Unfortunately people do not like boundaries because of past history, but there must be boundaries.  There is justification for this dividing line and I say this as one who is familiar with every county in Ireland.  While Senator Ryan has every right to make a case for levelling off the grants I do not think it is well founded.  Perhaps it is because I come from a congested district that I hold that view.  I do not know the Minister's view, but I think he would agree with me.  This must be viewed on a national basis.  We must not be parochial in our approach.  These people, because of their handicaps, are entitled to this special consideration.</P>
    <P>In addition to getting this 75 per cent from Dublin&mdash;I use the term &ldquo;Dublin&rdquo; equating it with the Exchequer&mdash;many of the farmers who will benefit from this scheme, and that means probably the majority of them in the 12 western counties, because their land valuation is less than £20 are exempt from the payment of rates.  In actual fact the Exchequer, in bearing the full liability of paying rates for such farmers, is giving towards the development schemes operated by the committees of agriculture in these counties amounts far in excess of the 75 per cent.  The main purpose of the Bill is to ensure the availability of the money and the granting of certain powers to the committees of agriculture which, in turn, will ask the county councils to make available sums in excess of the <Col N="1253" /> 15p, the maximum at present, ranging between 15p and 40p.</P>
    <P>The need for the Bill is self-evident. At present ten committees are very near the maximum rate of 15p in the £.  Such committees cannot get any further finances locally.  This Bill will give them power and authority from 1st January next to request county councils to make extra funds available.  It has been suggested that, in this day and age, the State should carry more liability for local schemes and local authority services.  That view is held by Senators and others.  It is a view held also by the National Coalition Government who, in other fields of activity where moneys are collected from national and local revenue, have given, by virtue of a firm decision immense reliefs to the rate-paying public, particularly in the fields of health and local authority housing.  I do not like making general statements on matters like this, but I have here the actual figures to show how in other fields of public activity reliefs have been given.</P>
    <P>There was comment in the Dáil to the effect that the Government were putting additional burdens on local revenue instead of giving reliefs.  For the information of Senators who may not have the information, this is the record of the Government where relieving the burden of rates is concerned in the fields of health and local authority housing: they reduced the local burden on ratepayers from £43.2 million in 1972-73 to £32.4 million in 1973-74. The amount for such services in this relevant nine-months' period is £16.2 million.  The Government are aware that local rates should not be increased except where necessary and desirable and the reliefs granted to ratepayers of all classifications are immense.</P>
    <P>Reference was made by Senators to assistance from EEC funds.  By virtue of our membership of the Community, conditions so far as farming is concerned, have changed drastically.  There is an obligation on us to get anything that is going in the agricultural field and I can assure the House that the Minister and his Department are mindful of that.  Any funds that can be lawfully obtained by our Minister will be obtained during the transitional period up to 1st January, 1978.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="1254" /> Senator Cowen was worried as to whether the Minister was giving as much thought and attention to this matter as he should.  I can assure him the Minister is giving thought to and is concerned for all such matters.  The House is aware that the Minister spends almost half his time in Europe advancing the cause of the Irish farmer.  He does not want any bouquets for that.  He is doing a really good job and I am glad that that viewpoint was held even by someone not of the Minister's party, Senator Brennan.  He accepted the fact in the course of his contribution that the Minister was and is doing his best for our people.</P>
    <P>What we like to see happening&mdash;this is the aim of the Minister and something, I am sure, he would say himself were it possible for him to be here for this discussion today&mdash;is a unified effort.  We want to see co-operation between all groups interested in the development of our agricultural economy, stemming from the farmer, the man in the field, the man Senator Brennan knows in Monaghan, the man similar to the man in Schull, in Skibbereen and west Cork, with his few sows and his litters of bonhams who is trying to make a few pounds from them.  We want to see all these people participating with their organisation, whether it be the IFA, ICMSA, Macra na Fierme, or any other group, whether public or voluntary bodies, which have our agricultural interests at heart.  The fact was mentioned&mdash;I am sorry I cannot recollect the Senator who mentioned it&mdash;that, no matter where we are, whether here in Dublin or down the country, agriculture plays a part of our lives.  It is our main industry and everybody in this relatively small State, with a population of some 3,000,000 people, is dependent on it.  If agriculture is doing well, money is circulating and people are able to buy goods.  More money is generated through the whole circle of our population and that, in turn, creates more employment.  It is to everyone's advantage if agriculture is doing well.</P>
    <P>I was very pleased by the many constructive suggestions and criticisms. Senators naturally dealt at great length with the activities of the committees of agriculture.  In general, the majority, if <Col N="1255" /> not all the speakers, were reasonably satisfied with the activities of the committees of agriculture.  The advantages of providing an educational centre for our farming community, young and old, was emphasised again and again.  There was general approval of the new arrangement whereby there will be a deputy chief agricultural officer attached to each committee whose sole role will be to provide educational advice to and an educational service for farmers.  That was adverted to by several Senators.  We must try to get the confidence of the farmers.  I like the phrase used by Senator Kilbride in the course of his remarks because psychology plays some part in this: an instructor to discharge his duties efficiently and effectively, irrespective of what qualifications he may hold academically, must come down to what Senator Kilbride has described here as &ldquo;the level of the farmer&rdquo;.  He instanced some person&mdash; perhaps he was illustrating by relating to some non-existent person&mdash;in plus fours or Oxford bags, a long cigar and so on.  If such officers did exist, I would have to agree with Senator Kilbride that our farmers would not have too much time for discussing problems with them.  I agree with the viewpoint expressed by the majority of the speakers that our advisory services are giving sound advice and results are quite good; our farmers are much more inclined now, to avail of advice and help from these officers than they were in the not-too-distant past.  I made that point at the Cork Committee of Agriculture.  I am sure it would not be 20 years ago that it came to our notice that the services of the small number of instructors we had were being availed of by a very limited number of farmers.  It was, in fact, as low as 5 per cent in my own area.  There was a feeling then that the farmer himself knew as much about managing his farm as any instructor sent out to him by a committee or by the Department.  That has all changed. It was a mistaken belief held sincerely by many farmers.  Now the boot is on the other foot and there is so great a demand and so many requests for advice that it is very, very difficult for the number of instructors, large as it is, <Col N="1256" /> to be available to get to the farmer within a reasonable time following on the request from the farmer.</P>
    <P>I know the farm modernisation scheme will throw a big burden on committees of agriculture and I am not overlooking the part played by members. We had, rightly so, a great deal of comment on the part played by the advisory services, but we must not forget the part played by the members of those committees.  They have practical experience. They know what they are talking about and they have a great deal to offer.  The best place to go for advice is to the man who was brought up as a farmer.  Because of their long experience of agricultural life the members can make valuable suggestions at meetings and can offer valuable criticisms.</P>
    <P>I do not know if it is necessary to go into detail on the comments of the different speakers.  I will refer to them in a general way.  The activities of the committees were referred to.  Mention was made by Senator McCartin of enough agricultural scholarships not being availed of.  I took a special note of that.  Agricultural scholarships are made available annually by the 27 committees for boys and girls.  One Senator from the midlands complained they were not being availed of.  Apparently that is happening in other areas as well.  I am rather surprised at this.  The Minister is very anxious about this because he emphasises strongly the desirability of getting as many boys as we can into our agricultural schools, particularly boys who are returning to their own home farms.  Senator Butler spoke about the value he got from the 12 months he spent in an agricultural school.  Naturally it is desirable that these scholarships should be availed of. In the case of home management, which was also referred to, and where sex enters the question, home management is of vital importance.  Many successful farmers are successful because of the help and assistance they get from their better halves and wives need training in home management just as much as husbands do in agriculture.</P>
    <P>I will conclude by saying I am grateful for the constructive nature of the debate and the views offered by those Members who contributed to the discussion.  The Minister is naturally <Col N="1257" /> disappointed at not having been with Senators today to hear their views. All the views and all the statements will of course, be available to him through the Official Report.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages today.</P>
    <P>Bill put through Committee, reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Houses of the Oireachtas (Members)" RHead="Pensions Scheme: Motion">
    <Title>Houses of the Oireachtas (Members) Pensions Scheme: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="PierceButler" hpid="Mr. Butler Mr. Butler">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Butler</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That Seanad Éireann hereby approves of the amendment of the Houses of the Oireachtas (Members) Pensions Scheme made under section 6A of the Oireachtas (Allowances to Members) Act, 1938, by:</P>
      <P>(1) the substitution of &ldquo;Minister for the Public Service&rdquo; for &ldquo;Minister for Finance&rdquo; in clauses 2 (2), 3 (1), 3 (5), 4 (2) and 4 (3).</P>
      <P>(2) the addition to clause 1 (2) of &lsquo;save as provided in clause 2 (4) below&rsquo;, and the addition to clause 2 of the following sub-clause:</P>
      <P>&lsquo;(4) (a) Any references to a financial year in sub-clause (3) of this clause shall, in relation to after the 31st day of December, 1974, be construed and have effect as a reference to a period which is co-extensive with a calendar year.</P>
      <P>(b)  Where the reference in sub-clause (3) of this clause to each financial year includes, or may be construed as including, a reference to the period from the 1st day of April, 1974, to the 31st day of March, 1975, the reference shall be construed and have effect as a reference to the period from the 1st day of April, 1974, to the 31st day of December, 1974.&rsquo;,</P>
      <P>(3) the addition to clause 5 of the following sub-clauses:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="1258" />&lsquo;(14)  A pension awarded under this Scheme may be increased as if it were computed by reference to the rate of Parliamentary Allowance payable from time to time to a member of the Dáil or of Seanad Éireann, as the case may be.</P>
    <P>(15)  An increase in pension under sub-clause (14) of this clause shall apply only where&mdash;</P>
    <P>(a) the member has completed not less than 12 years' service as a member, or</P>
    <P>(b)  the member is 55 years of age or over, or</P>
    <P>(c)  the member is, in the opinion of the Trustees, precluded from earning a livelihood by reason of permanent disability, or</P>
    <P>(d)  the pension is payable to the widow of a member by virtue of her late husband's membership of either House of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>(16)  Increases in pensions under sub-clause (14) of this clause shall apply with effect from 1 October, 1973 or, where the conditions specified in sub-clause (15) are not fulfilled at the time of cesser of membership of either House of the Oireachtas, the date on which any of these conditions are fulfilled but any increase arising from changes in the rate of Parliamentary Allowance occurring after 1 October, 1973 shall apply with effect from the date (hereinafter referred to as the specified date) specified for the payment of increases in pensions (awarded under the Superannuation Acts, 1834 to 1963) in regulations made under section 29 of the Pensions (Increase) Act, 1964, for the year in which such changes occur, if these changes occur on or before the specified date in that year, but where they occur after the specified date in that year increases in pensions under sub-clause (14) of this clause shall apply with effect from such date <Col N="1259" /> as the Trustees unanimously decide.&rsquo;,</P>
    <P>(4)  the substitution for sub-clause (10) of clause 5 of the following:</P>
    <P>&lsquo;(10)  The Trustees may pay to a widow</P>
    <P>(a)  whose marriage to her husband took place before he ceased to be a member, and</P>
    <P>(b)  whose husband was</P>
    <P>(i)  in receipt of a pension under this scheme, or</P>
    <P>(ii)  a member after 1 December, 1960, and had not less than 5 years' service as a member</P>
    <P>a pension until her widowhood ceases not exceeding the greater of</P>
    <P>(a)  £250, or</P>
    <P>(b)  one-half of the pension payable to her husband under this Scheme or which would have been payable to him if he had ceased to be a member on the date of his death, or</P>
    <P>(c)  in case a pension under this Scheme was not payable to her husband on the date of his death, one-half of the pension which would have been payable to him under this Scheme on such date if he had had eight years' such service</P>
    <P>together with an addition to such pension of £75 for each child under the appropriate age subject to the total amount so payable not exceeding the greater of</P>
    <P>(a)  £250, or</P>
    <P>(b)  the pension payable to her husband under this Scheme or which would have been payable to him if he had ceased to be a member on the date of his death, or</P>
    <P>(c)  in case a pension under this Scheme was not payable <Col N="1260" /> to her husband on the date of his death, the pension which would have been payable to him under this Scheme on such date if he had had eight years' such service.&rsquo;,</P>
    <P>(5)  the substitution for sub-clause (13) of clause 5 of the following:</P>
    <P>&lsquo;(13)  The Trustees may pay to each orphan whose parent was</P>
    <P>(a)  in receipt of a pension under this Scheme, or</P>
    <P>(b)  a member after 1 December, 1960, and had not less than 5 years' service as a member</P>
    <P>a pension of £150 up to the appropriate age subject to the pensions payable to the orphans of such parent not exceeding the greater of</P>
    <P>(a)  £250, or</P>
    <P>(b)  one-half of the pension payable to such parent under this Scheme or which would have been payable to him if he had ceased to be a member on the date of his death, or</P>
    <P>(c)  in case a pension under this Scheme was not payable to such parent on the date of his death, one-half of the pension which would have been payable to him under this Scheme on such date if he had had eight years' such service</P>
    <P>and, where both parents have been members, the parent eligible for if he had ceased to be a member on the date of his death, or in receipt of, or if he had eight years' service as a member on such date would have been eligible for, the smaller pension shall be disregarded for the purposes of this sub-clause.&rsquo;, and</P>
    <P>(6)  clauses (4) and (5) of this resolution shall be deemed to have been passed on the 1st day of July, 1974.</P>
    <Col N="1261" />
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Ryan) Richie Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Finance (Mr. R. Ryan)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of this motion, which amends the Houses of the Oireachtas (Members) Pensions Scheme, is two-fold&mdash;(1) to provide pensions parity for certain categories of pensioners and (2) to broaden the area of eligibility for widows' pensions.  Representations on these matters have been received by me from the Committee on Procedure and Privileges and other quarters.</P>
      <P>At present pensions are based on the rates of parliamentary allowances which Members were receiving when their membership ceased and are not subject to revision.  I have decided that the pensions payable to persons, who had at least 12 years' service or who are over 55 years of age or who are precluded from earning a livelihood by reason of permanent disability or who are widows of Members, may be increased periodically as if they were calculated by reference to the rates of parliamentary allowance payable from time to time.  The operative date each year for these increases will be the same date as for public service pensioners generally, commencing on 1st October, 1973.</P>
      <P>I have also decided to reduce the qualifying period for widows' pensions from eight years to five years.  The actual rate of pension for a widow whose husband had not less than five but less than eight years' service as a Member of either House of the Oireachtas will be half the pension calculated as if the husband had had eight years' service subject to a minimum of £250 for the widow.  The addition which is made to a widow's pension in respect of each child is being increased from £50 to £75, and an orphans' pension is being increased from £100 to £150.  These amendments will take effect from 1st July, 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The motion also provides for technical changes in the Members' pensions scheme following on the transfer of responsibility for superannuation matters generally from the Minister for Finance to the Minister for the Public Service and the change-over of the <Col N="1262" /> present financial year to coincide with the calendar year.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>This is a very welcome motion.  There are just one or two points of clarification I would like to seek from the Minister.  In particular, in relation to widows of TDs and Senators&mdash;there are very few of them left&mdash;who became widows prior to the inauguration of the superannuation scheme for Oireachtas Members, I just want clarification as to whether or not they are included.  The Minister has stated the alternatives in regard to pensions payable.  Does the proposed Order include the widows or widowers&mdash;in my experience there are only widows involved&mdash;who were Members of the Oireachtas prior to the inauguration of the Oireachtas Superannuation Scheme of 1959?  To my knowledge, there are only four or five widows in this category.  I should like to know if they are included.  If they are not, they should be.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="RichieRyan" hpid="Mr. R. Ryan Mr. R. Ryan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. R. Ryan</NameTxt>
      <P>They are not catered for in this Order.  The position is that there is no formal scheme provided for them.  We did provide a sum of £5,000 in the Estimates for payment of <i>ex gratia</i> pensions to such people. Although there were very exhaustive inquiries conducted, in response to a request from my Department to the Whips of the different parties, nobody was then identified who would be a possible recipient.  However, one has recently come to light in the last few weeks and that application is at present being considered and I think an appropriate pension will be paid.  I propose to consult, as is customary, with an informal committee of the Houses so that the terms can be settled.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BrianLenihanSnr" hpid="Mr. Lenihan Mr. Lenihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lenihan</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you, Minister.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 5.05 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 24th July, 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>