<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE Debate SYSTEM "../Debate.dtd"[]>
<Debate DocTitle="Seanad Debate" Day="Wed" Date="13" Month="Feb" Year="1974" Vol="77" No="1" DateIrish="Dé Céadaoin, 13 Feabhra 1974" DateEnglish="Wednesday, 13 February 1974" House="S" CommitteeEng="" CommitteeIr="" SubNameEng="" cnum="1">
  <MainHeading Type="Prelude" LHead="" RHead="">
    <Title>
    </Title>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="1" /> Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gcean nas ar 3 p.m.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Paidir.</i>
    </P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <i>Prayer.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Death of Member:" RHead="Expression of Sympathy">
    <Title>Death of Member: Expression of Sympathy.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Since the last meeting Senators will have learned with deep regret of the death of our colleague, Senator Kevin O'Callaghan. The late Senator O'Callaghan was a member of a family long connected with the political life of this country and he himself from an early age took an active part in public affairs.</P>
      <P>He was first elected to this House at a by-election in 1970 and was re-elected on the Agricultural Panel at the general election last year.  When the Joint Committee on Secondary Legislation of the EEC was established recently Senator O'Callaghan was one of those Members of the House selected to serve on it.</P>
      <P>He was an extensive and progressive farmer and a member of several farming bodies.  He was a director of Erin Foods from 1965 to 1970.  Despite these many demands on his services he was extremely active in many charitable organisations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>His contributions to debates in the Seanad, noteworthy for pertinence and <Col N="2" /> conciseness, were invariably listened to with respect.  In personal relationships, his kindly and pleasant disposition made him popular with all Members. By his untimely death we have lost a valuable colleague.</P>
    <P>I have conveyed, on your behalf and on my own, our deepest sympathy to the widow and children of the late Senator.</P>
    <P>I bhFlaitheas Dé go raibh a anam.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Members rose in their places.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - The Leopardstown Park Hospital (Trust" RHead="Deed Amendment) Bill, 1972: Report Stage and Final Stages">
    <Title>Private Business. - The Leopardstown Park Hospital (Trust Deed Amendment) Bill, 1972: Report Stage and Final Stages.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the Bill be received for final consideration.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Agreed to take Fifth Stage today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the Standing Orders relative to Private <Col N="3" /> Business, the Fifth Stage of the Leopardstown Park Hospital (Trust Deed Amendment) Bill, 1972, shall be taken today.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="" hpid="An Leas-Chathaoirleach An Leas-Chathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Leas-Chathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the Bill do now pass.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Ordered: That the Bill be sent to the Dáil.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. -" RHead="Business of Seanad">
    <Title>Private Business. - Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I have received notice from Senator Robinson that, on the motion for the adjournment of the House tonight, she proposes to raise the following matter:</P>
      <P>The fact that the map collections of the National Library are not being made available to members of the public and particularly scholars.</P>
      <P>I am accepting that notice and the matter will be taken from 9.30 p.m. to 10 p.m. or earlier if the business ordered is concluded.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. -" RHead="Order of Business">
    <Title>Private Business. - Order of Business.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It is proposed to take Nos. 2, 3 and 4 in that order.  It might be appropriate to say that in view of the recent announcement regarding Government proposals for legislation, it is not proposed to take No. 7 today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, the Family Planning Bill, 1973, was ordered in November to be taken on the first sitting day after Christmas.  Therefore, to that extent, by not moving No. 7&mdash;the Family Planning Bill&mdash;today, the Seanad is varying that Order of Business.  I should like to make it clear that we fully accept that it is open to the Seanad to decide at the start of each day to order its business; it is open to Senators to put in amendments to that Order of Business; if necessary, to divide on it and vote on it.  We, the proposers of this Bill, do not intend to move the amendment of the Order of Business by asking that the Second Reading be given today, as had been arranged before Christmas.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="4" /> We have decided to wait a little longer in consideration of two factors. Firstly, in view of the fact that the Government came to a decision only last night that they were going to bring in their own Bill in the other House; and, secondly, because to move for a debate today would only result in wasting the time of the House, because the business which has been ordered, which is described as urgent, namely, the Transport Bill, will take a substantial amount of time. But we give notice that we do propose to either seek that the Leader of the House order the Family Planning Bill at the next sitting day of the Seanad, or else we shall order ourselves by amendment that it be taken.</P>
    <P>We do so because we seek an early debate in this House on the terms of the Bill which was given a First Reading by the Seanad.  We facilitated the Government by allowing the Christmas Recess to go by between the First Stage and Second Stage; we are facilitating them once more by not pressing for a Second Reading to be taken today.  But we give notice that we will be looking for a debate on the next sitting day.  Perhaps the most satisfactory contribution that this House could make on the whole question is to have a debate on the general principles and then adjourn the Second Reading without a vote.  This would be an opportunity for us, as proposers of this Bill, to outline and explain the framework of the Bill and its contents and to have a discussion on the record on it.  It would be an opportunity for those totally opposed to express their views.  It would be an opportunity for those who would like to see amendments to express their views on it; and it would be an opportunity for the Government to indicate why they prefer to bring in a Government Bill.  Hopefully at that stage they may be in a position to outline what the contents of that Bill would be.</P>
    <P>I want to make it very clear, because this is a very technical point, that it is not weakness or indecision or a lack of desire to go ahead with the Second Reading which motivates <Col N="5" /> us.  Nothing would please us more, as sponsors of the Bill, than that the Bill be given a Second Reading here today.  But we feel that we can accommodate the Government and accommodate the Seanad by not pressing for it today, on the understanding that we will be looking for a Second Reading at the next meeting of the Seanad, whether it be next week, or in a fortnight's time, or at whatever date the Seanad is adjourned to. At that stage we feel entitled to a debate.  We have put a lot of homework into this and have provided the text of a Bill.  The public, which has seen public money expended on the printing of the Bill, is entitled to see a debate on the terms of that Bill.</P>
    <P>We feel that the Seanad has a positive contribution to make as a forum for public opinion, especially in anticipation of a Government text, because the Government have not revealed what they intend to put in their Bill.  We do not have the text of it and we, as individual Senators, have unhappy memories of a previous Government promising to bring in a Bill, and of a Private Member's Bill being withdrawn in anticipation of such Government Bill which was never produced.</P>
    <P>Therefore, what we will be seeking at the next meeting day is a Second Reading debate on the principles.  The Oireachtas owes it to itself, as an important forum for airing controversial matters or important matters of this sort.  We must at this stage debate the principles of legalising family planning by providing for the sale and availability of contraceptives and the removal of the censorship restrictions on the subject matter.  We could then adjourn the Second Reading pending the First Reading in the Dáil of the Government measure showing the precise provisions of the Government text.  When we have seen these provisions of the Government text, we will be in a position to know whether we ought to withdraw entirely in favour of this Government Bill, or whether we would still like our text to be given further consideration and a vote by the Seanad as being, in our view, a preferable text.  That is still <Col N="6" /> an option which ought to be open to us at that stage, when a Government Bill has been published and is about to be debated in the Dáil.  Consequently, we are merely holding our fire for a very limited further time. We do not accept in any way that the Seanad has been displaced as a forum in which to discuss this issue by the promise on behalf of the Government to bring in a measure in the Dáil.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>On the Order of Business, I am wondering how useful the Seanad is and how useful a Member of the Seanad can be, when the Order of Business is selected in this way.</P>
      <P>Motion No. 12 in my name has been down for nine months.  This motion refers to a money matter not provided in the last budget.  I consider this of importance to the country at large.  If it cannot be dealt with in nine months and has to run its course and another budget is passed, any Member of the Seanad, whichever side of the House he is on, is entitled to ask himself what contribution can he make.  No. 12 is a very simple motion. Even the Government accepted it and supported it.  I do not think it would do the Government any harm.  I appeal to you, Sir, with respect, to ask the Leader of the House to allow time for this motion to be taken.  At least it would encourage Members to feel that they contribute something. If matters cannot be raised in this manner we are most restricted in the amount of business that we can transact here.  We cannot ask questions. I would appeal to you, Sir, to do something about this matter because many local authorities and organisations throughout the country have been left in a dilemma since last year. They have been left waiting for nine months.  It is unfair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would say to the Senator that the Order of Business is a matter for the House, not for the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to support Senator McGowan's plea on this, because the Motion No. 12 is a very important one.  I am not going to go <Col N="7" /> into the merits of it now, but it is tremendously important.  Things have changed immensely in this country within the last nine months.  Consequently, it is wrong of the Seanad to postpone this motion from one meeting to another.  An important motion such as that should be discussed. I would appeal to the House to discuss it today, if possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHorgan1977" hpid="Mr. Horgan Mr. Horgan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Horgan</NameTxt>
      <P>In proposing the Order of Business as he did, Senator M.J. O'Higgins gave as his reason for not including No. 7 the fact that the Government have already indicated their intention of introducing legislation in the same area.</P>
      <P>I agree with Senator Robinson that there is no particular necessity to press for a Second Reading today, because of the urgency of the Transport Bill.  I should like to reply to Senator M.J. O'Higgins and to suggest that the willingness or unwillingness of the Government to introduce legislation on any matter is not necessarily related at all to the way in which this House should order its business.  The House does not need reminding that legislation of this kind has been on the Order Paper in our names for the best part of four years.  The Government proposals are as yet not a week old and have not even been unveiled in all their details.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>On the particular matter in question I would obviously prefer&mdash;and no doubt Senator Robinson would prefer as well&mdash; that the Government should introduce an adequate measure and put it through both Houses of the Oireachtas.  We have as yet no assurance that any measure which they introduce will be adequate.  We have, as I said, a history of four years' waiting in this House for a reasonable, sensible discussion on a matter of some public importance.  The main reason why I would disagree with Senator O'Higgins when he says that we should not debate this measure because the Government are going to introduce proposals is that if we agree to this we are agreeing to something which I feel strikes at the heart of parliamentary democracy.  We are agreeing in <Col N="8" /> effect that the Government are above Parliament.  If we hold the other position&mdash;which I do&mdash;we believe in the principle that Parliament is superior to Government, not Government superior to Parliament.  We believe in the autonomy of Parliament.  We believe that Governments are ultimately answerable to Parliaments. Senator O'Higgins would no doubt add that they are answerable to the people as well.  I do not think I would disagree with him on that, but I would suggest that it is not a point at issue here.</P>
    <P>I am saying as strongly as I can that we must not allow it to go out from this House that the Seanad should not discuss this item just because the Government say they will do something.  It is not in the tradition of parliamentary democracy for any Parliament to jump like a rabbit when the Government fire a popgun. It is, on the contrary, a principle of parliamentary democracy and, indeed, of autonomy of the Oireachtas, that we have the right to discuss whatever we want to discuss, whenever we want to discuss it, irrespective of what the Government may happen to wish or proposed.  I agree with Senator Robinson that we would fail in our duty to the electorate who have elected us and to the taxpayers who pay us if we failed at this point to write into the record of the House our adherence to the principle that the supremacy of Parliament must never be in doubt.</P>
    <P>We must make clear our conviction that Parliament is not an offshoot or an extension of Government but that the situation is the other way round.  I would make that point very strongly.  I am not, for the very same reasons as Senator Robinson, pressing for a Second Stage debate today.  I believe with her, however, that an adjourned Second Stage debate at the first possible opportunity is essential and that it is the duty of all seriousthinking people in this House to support us when we press for it.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to raise two matters on the Order of Business.  The first one is that already raised by Senator Robinson and Senator <Col N="9" /> Horgan.  I must say I am not very happy with what has happened.  The Family Planning Bill&mdash;No. 7 on the Order Paper&mdash;was ordered at our last sitting to be taken today.  At the very last moment the Government have produced a tentative plan but no concrete Bill and we are left in the lurch. I feel that this is government by delay. I am distinctly unhappy because this sort of thing could go on for weeks and weeks, as it did under the last administration when such a Bill was on the Order Paper, and we could keep on being put off.  Things could continue on being postponed.  At the very least we should ask the Leader of the House for a concrete undertaking that on the next sitting day of this House the Family Planning Bill in the names of Senator Robinson, Senator Horgan and myself will be taken or that a Government Bill will be discussed, but it is absolutely essential that a Family Planning Bill should be taken.</P>
      <P>During the period of the last administration we suffered something similar over an Adoption Bill with which Senator Robinson, Senator Horgan and I were involved.  Senator Robinson introduced that Bill on 29th June, 1972, and the then Minister for Justice mentioned that he had a Bill of his own in preparation and he hoped to introduce it before Christmas, 1972.  He could not give a definite undertaking but he hoped that it would be possible.</P>
      <P>I know that the Minister's successor also has a commitment to introduce an Adoption Bill.  There are very serious anomalies in the present law concerning adoption.  It is now two months after Christmas, 1973, and there is no sign of an Adoption Bill. This is another example of what happens to Private Members' Bills in this House and, apparently, in the other House.  They are treated with a considerable amount of disdain by whatever administration is in power. This is not just good enough.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The second matter I wish to raise concerns the Transport Bill.  The proposal is that we take it first on the agenda.  Motion No. 15 on today's Order Paper, in the names of myself <Col N="10" /> and Senator William O'Brien, reads as follows:</P>
    <P>That Seanad Éireann takes note of the McKinsey Report on &ldquo;Defining the Role of Public Transport in a Changing Environment&rdquo; laid before the Seanad on 30th September, 1971.</P>
    <P>A motion has been on the Order Paper of the House for virtually two years concerning the McKinsey Report and, a Chathaoirleach, if I recall correctly you were a co-signatory with me for that motion in the last administration.  We now have a Transport Bill dealing with the finances of the national transport company, Córas Iompair Éireann, and we have a motion on the Order Paper to discuss the McKinsey Report, which is a report commissioned by the Government to discuss the finance of the transport company.  For some reason these two items cannot be taken together. I intend to ask the Seanad to amend the Order of Business and to propose an amendment so that the Bill and the motion can be taken together. It seems absolutely ridiculous that the McKinsey Report, which was laid before the House on 30th September, 1971, cannot now be discussed in conjunction with a Transport Bill which deals with the finances of our national transport company.  It is ludicrous.  It makes pie in the sky of our pious idea to discuss a motion per month in this House.  By my count we have had three motions since June and we have been sitting for almost nine months.</P>
    <P>Here is a unique opportunity to take two subjects which are very closely linked together.  I see absolutely no reason why the McKinsey Report should not be discussed along with the Transport Bill, 1974, and, therefore, I propose an amendment to the Order of Business that items No. 2 and 15 on the Order Paper be taken first and then items No. 3 and 4.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to associate myself with the view that this Bill should be discussed in the Seanad.  I am not challenging the Order of Business of today because to debate it in an atmosphere of urgency and <Col N="11" /> tension arising out of the urgency of the Transport Bill would obviously be the wrong sort of atmosphere in which to debate it.  The view that the Government are thinking out their own Bill at the moment and have a Bill to present to the Dáil and to the people cannot be submitted as a good reason why the Seanad should not discuss this Bill on Second Stage.</P>
      <P>In fact, I would argue the dead opposite.  If the Government are framing their policy and if they are serious about the parliamentary procedure, surely they should hear what this House has to say on this Bill before they form their policy.  I say that with a certain amount of annoyance almost because if the Government are serious about letting us debate it, fine, but if they are not I would find it a ground for very great annoyance.  I have put a lot of thought into this issue over the past few weeks and I am sure everybody in this House has and we assembled here to day on the grounds that it was to be taken.  Now all the thought we have put into it as parliamentarians will be lost just because a few superior intelligences in the Cabinet have decided &ldquo;No.  We do not need that Bill; we will do something much better ourselves&rdquo;.  Do the Government so disdain the collective intelligence of this House and the individual intelligences of its Members as to think that our debate, our contributions on this issue, could not shed any possible light in the framing of a Bill?  That would seem to be the implication if the Government do not allow us to debate this Bill on Second Stage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Therefore, while not challenging the Order of Business today, I should like to serve notice that there will be a great deal of annoyance, there will be divisions and a good deal of fractiousness on all sides if the Government treat in this way the people who have thought this Bill out so carefully. Indeed, I believe the entire House would like to see it brought before them and subjected to constructive critique.  However, that is to be brushed aside and a decision handed down from above.  That would seem&mdash; I would agee with Senator Horgan <Col N="12" /> here&mdash;to be a negation, a deliberate and perhaps a very cynical negation, of the whole parliamentary procedure.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>Would the Leader of the House indicate when he proposes ordering Motion No. 12?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not think anybody has any doubt as to what has happened here.  I could quote the phrase coined by a very distinguished predecessor of ours in the Seanad, Senator W.B. Yeats, &ldquo;You have disgraced yourselves again&rdquo;.  I think there is little doubt about that.  To quote another distinguished politician: &ldquo;The paltroons have won again&rdquo;.  As all of the Senators have said, there is no reason in the world why this Bill cannot be discussed in the Seanad.  It is most ideally suited for discussion in the first instance by Senators.  That cannot be said of many Bills, but it can be said of this Bill because of the varying connotations in which academic and professional expertise could be of help to the Dáil in the Bill discussed and passed here.</P>
      <P>I am surprised at the wonderful tolerance and patience of these three talented Senators&mdash;Senator Horgan, Senator Mary Robinson and Senator West&mdash;who have waited so long with such patience and put so much time into devising and introducing this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I can assure the Senator that our patience is running out.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am glad to hear it is running out.  They have waited four years, I think Senator Horgan says. We have all waited four years.  I think I have waited since 1947.  This started in 1947, in the 1947 Act.  People have been waiting for this kind of legislation. It started, I suppose, even in 1935.  How can the Government ask for our tolerance and patience, and particularly this Government, whose two components are committed in political terms to the introduction of this Bill over a matter of years through their two party conferences and by public declarations made by members of the present Cabinet?  There is no reason in the world why this Bill should not be discussed this afternoon.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="13" /> As Senator Robinson has said we were told it would be taken at the first meeting after Christmas.  The Government knew that.  That was a formal undertaking given here and on the records of the House.  Why should the Government be permitted to break that undertaking?  What grounds have been given to us which would justify us accepting the undertaking that it will be taken at some time in the unspecified future?  If, for instance, the Leader of the House would give us an undertaking that this Bill would be taken, say, next week, then that could be considered.  But unless a specific date is given, the Seanad should press for taking this Bill now.  There are medical reasons. This is not an academic discussion. There are very important human repercussions from the absence of this kind of legislation on our Statute Book in relation to the incidence of unwanted children, of unfortunate mothers who are having children they do not want.  I will not go into that in any length now but the Seanad knows that this is a Bill with very far reaching human implications throughout our society.</P>
    <P>There is a great urgency about this Bill.  We are one of the last countries in Europe without legislation of this kind.  Recently, in the Dáil we were told that there is so much other legislation coming up from this Government with all the talents they have, that they had to suspend Private Members' time.  So, what chance has a Bill of this kind in priority with all the other important legislation which these political geniuses are dreaming up for our delectation in the months ahead? Why not?  Surely this is an ideal opportunity for the Dáil and for the Cabinet to hand over to responsible people&mdash;I think it can be accepted that there is a majority of responsible people here&mdash;discussion of this Bill. The value of our opinion then would be available to those talking about the Bill in the Dáil.  We can ease the burden of the many demands on their time.</P>
    <P>They did not hear of this thing for the first time last week.  This is not the first time this has been heard of. <Col N="14" /> As Senator Horgan has stated it has been there for four years.  When it was rejected by Senator Ó Maoláin, as Leader of the House under the Fianna Fáil Government, there was a mixture of jubilation and indignation amongst the &ldquo;hawks&rdquo; who wanted to get this type of legislation to show that that was not a theocratic society. Fianna Fáil had it that way; but if these people had the opportunity to govern they would strip all these archaic and medieval statutes off the Statute Book and we would become a progressive, liberalised society.  They are there a year now.</P>
    <P>This excellent Bill was devised by Senator Mary Robinson after a great deal of thought and concern.  To my mind, it does not go far enough, and I propose to amend it when it is introduced.  However, it is an excellent Bill as an advance on what is already there.</P>
    <P>But something has tamed the hawks; something has clipped their wings. They are adopting much the same attitude, but in a more serious way, as Senator Ó Maoláin, who at least had the support of his party behind him. We now have the Leader of the House apparently differing from the general policy decision of his own party&mdash;an extraordinary position.  You remind me &mdash;I have to use that word&mdash;over the years I have been in public life you all remind me, successive political leaders here&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I would point out to the Senator that when he uses &ldquo;you&rdquo; he is addressing the Chair.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>Sorry.  I am talking about politicians generally.  I went on to define exactly whom I was talking about.  You remind me of children. When a child closes his eyes he thinks it is night-time.  The Dáil, the Seanad, year after year as you brought in this kind of loaded decision in the Oireachtas, have behaved as if nobody notices what is happening.  This goes way back to the 1935 Bill, which Senator Robinson is trying to amend.  It goes back to the 1937 Constitution.  It goes back to the famous mother and child scheme.  It goes back to adoption.  All the way through there is a strong <Col N="15" /> unbroken thread of subservience to an opinion outside this House and that is what is motivating the present decision of the Government in asking Senator Robinson to withdraw her Bill.</P>
      <P>This decision which is being taken is being watched very carefully.  It is not night-time in the North of Ireland. They are wide awake up there and are watching.  This decision is being taken in the context of Sunningdale, in the context of Faulkner fighting for his life, in the context of the Protestant unionists being further confirmed in his justified belief&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator has gone so far from the matter of the Order of Business that I must ask him to come back to it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The question is that Nos. 2, 3 and 4 be the Order of Business for today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>To use the phrase of Deputy O'Brien, Minister for Posts and Telegraphs, of December last, if the Family Planning Bill is not passed this is good evidence to show that we are ruled by Rome.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must point out to the Senator that he is now talking about the merits of the Bill and has departed from the question of whether it be debated today or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>Just a moment.  That is just what I was saying.  I am talking about Sunningdale.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Sunningdale is not on the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am talking about it in the context of people who are being assured by our Government that a State which would evolve from a Council of Ireland would be a State in which pluralist attitudes in regard to matters such as contraception, adoption, divorce, therapeutic legal abortion, homosexuality, censorship would all be possible.  This is being held forward to the Unionist Loyalists as likely eventualities&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="16" />
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must intervene to indicate to the Senator that the only question to be debated at the moment is the Order of Business today. It is not in order to enter into the merits of or to anticipate the debate which might take place today or on another occasion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>I am attempting to show that the decision not to allow this Bill to go forward is to support the illusion created by Mr. Faulkner in the North that the kind of society into which he is attempting to inveigle the dissenting Unionists at the present time, the third who do not want to come into a theocratic society.  This is an attempt to support the case he is putting forward that all is now changed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that, despite all the rephrasing the Senator is making, his speech has been for some time past outside the scope of the present discussion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>No case whatever has been made.  It has been suggested that we are a busy Seanad.  I sincerely hope this will not get into the Press, the radio or television.  It would be laughed out of court as a serious suggestion.  We have met today for the first time since before Christmas. It is being suggested there is a controversial Transport Bill but surely we will not pull one another's hair out about a Transport Bill and the fact that we might try to discuss a Bill on contraception at the same time. There is no reason why this Bill should not be discussed now unless we are given an undertaking by the Leader of the House that it will be taken next week.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>There is medical urgency for it. There is also legal urgency and I am surprised the Leader of the House is not concerned about this.  There is an unconstitutional law on the Statute Book at the moment.  There is also very important political urgency about it.  Let them allow Senator Robinson's Bill to be discussed.  Let them show the people in the North of Ireland what the Seanad feels about this.  Let them establish the case put <Col N="17" /> forward by Deputy O'Brien, the Minister for Posts and Telegraphs, that if this is turned down we are ruled by Rome.  Let us prove we are not ruled by Rome.  Let us debate this Bill, pass it and refute this.</P>
    <P>Could I ask the Leader of the House, could I ask the other Senators, would they mind reassembling tomorrow in order to discuss it?  If that agreement is given for even this day week, then I will withdraw my amendment to the Order of Business, which is that No. 7&mdash;the Family Planning Bill&mdash;be taken now since it is easily the most urgent matter on the Order of Business before the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>From a very much different standpoint to that of the previous Senator who has spoken, I would ask the Leader of the House to give us an opportunity as soon as possible to get this off the Order Paper.  Give us an opportunity to get the case, and a very compelling case, that is against many of the changes which Senator Dr. Browne so glibly hails as being progressive.  Let us get an opportunity of putting our case against that and then I, for one, will resist very strongly any idea that a Second Reading debate should be adjourned.  Let us go and nail our colours to the mast and I will be found there with those who will be, I am absolutely confident, the overwhelming majority of the Seanad who will vote&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is anticipating the debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Profesor Quinlan Profesor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Profesor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>I have a little more experience in politics and in this House than the junior Senator from Galway.  Also I came through an electorate; I did not have an easy passage like the junior Senator.  The quicker we have an opportunity of doing this, the better.  I would not like it to be delayed until the Government brought in the Bill, except that the Government have to bring in some amending legislation based on the Supreme Court decision.  Such an effort by the Government should be only after very serious and mature and prolonged consideration.  I do not <Col N="18" /> for one moment suggest that the Government should rush this.</P>
      <P>Senator Browne suggested that we in Parliament are subservient to an authority outside of Parliament.  We are subservient to an authority outside of Parliament.  We are subservient to the plain people of Ireland who appreciate the quality of life that has made Ireland a country we have been proud of.  These plain people will give the&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator Quinlan is following Senator Noel Browne into his irrelevancies.  I would ask him to come back to the Order of Business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>&mdash;&mdash;same answer as I know the plain people of Seanad Éireann and Dáil Éireann will give to this.  We can rely on them to take a commonsense and an overall approach to the problem that faces us today and not to be swayed in any way by the pressure groups that are having such an innings today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Using the vocative case correctly, a Chathaoirleach, as the junior Senator from Galway West I was considerably embarassed by confusion with the surname of the Leader of the House.  I want to say that I am one person on this side of the House who wants a debate as soon as possible on this issue.  It arises from the moving of the Order of Business.  I can put it in much fewer words than Senator Quinlan, even if I have not the benefit of his age and erudition.  It is necessary to have a debate soon so that the very many mistaken and stupid and ill-informed sociological comments which have been made will be put an end to once and for all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am a professional sociologist, whatever that might mean.  I teach this subject in the university.  I have seen one comment after another, one fact linked to another, blatant inaccuracies perpetrated by those who claim to teach in third level institutions. The most important reason why we welcome a quick debate is that this matter affects the young and particularly the poor young.  Who <Col N="19" /> are affected by it?  It is those whom we have told, whom previous Governments told cannot be guaranteed a house and we cannot guarantee them their rights.  We need to discuss their rights.  We need to discuss what kind of society we want.  We need to discuss the many documents put forward by the Irish Conservation Society and the documents put forward by many other brilliant people who have studied the subject.  We need to discuss these documents soon.</P>
    <P>I should like to pay tribute to Senator Robinson for making an attempt to introduce this legislation. She is making what I think is a reasonable request for an early debate on yet another human matter.  It has been her contribution not only to this Seanad&mdash;of which I am not an elected but a nominated Member, as I am reminded by my erudite third level colleague from Cork&mdash;but once again she has drawn our attention to something human, or rather inhuman.  She has put her name to a Bill which affects vulnerable people who are in need of a voice and who need our discussion.  The sooner the Bill is discussed the sooner it will give our colleagues in the Labour Party, who are united on this measure, satisfaction.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FintanKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely the important question at issue here is not when the present Family Planning Bill will be debated in this House.  That is not the important question.  The important question is the desirability of ensuring that whatever legislation should ultimately be enacted will be adequate, equitable and will meet the wishes of the majority of our people. That is the real issue.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I cannot remember exactly when the present Bill was placed on the Order Paper, but it was some time ago.  Since then the Government have had a full opportunity of considering all the pros and cons and are therefore in my opinion in a much better position to introduce the type of measure I have referred to.  It may well be that the Government will embody in their Bill the objections and the amendments which one Senator <Col N="20" /> has already given notice of intention to relate to the present Bill.</P>
    <P>Two Senators have expressed themselves on the Bill.  I think they were out of order.  One Senator has said that he will not accept it.  Another has said that he accepts it but he wants to make an amendment.  It may well be that the Government will embody all these objections and suit everybody and therefore expedite the matter instead of delaying it by this type of discussion.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Before I call on Senator Michael O'Higgins to reply to the debate there have been two variations in the Order of Business moved. Senator West has proposed to add No. 15 and Senator Noel Browne moved to add No. 7.  Are there seconders for those propositions?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>I second the amendment to add No. 15.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I propose to withdraw my amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Is there a seconder for the amendment to add No. 7?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>Can Senator Browne be given a firm undertaking that this matter will be debated, preferably tomorrow or, if not, next week?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Chair is concerned that any question which comes before the House will be properly before it.  This is the reason why seconders are sought; otherwise no decision could be taken on these points.  It is a further matter whether they are ultimately pressed or not.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>On that understanding&mdash;that the Leader of the House may give an indication when this Bill will be debated&mdash;I should like, for the purpose of having the motion put forward, to second Senator Browne's motion.  As I understand it, he will withdraw it if there is a firm indication that the Bill will be given time for a debate.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I call on Senator Michael O'Higgins to conclude the discussion on the proposal that the Order <Col N="21" /> of Business be Nos. 2, 3 and 4 to which amendments Nos. 7, 12 and 15 have been proposed.  There are three separate amendments.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I have not taken full notes of what has been said. Senators McGowan and Dolan raised the question of Motion No. 12.  I should like to tell them that as far as I am concerned that will be taken as early as we can arrange to have it taken. The only reason motions were not ordered for today was that, as every Member of the Seanad is aware, the notice we received for this meeting of the Seanad was very brief.  The Government Whip made an effort to arrange for the taking of the motion.  However, the Minister concerned was not available&mdash;he is abroad on duties connected with his office&mdash;and we were not able to get another motion arranged in time.</P>
      <P>It certainly is my purpose&mdash;and I have made this clear time and time again&mdash;to endeavour so far as the Government side of the House are concerned to adhere to the scheme which was agreed by the House that we would take a motion each month. That is all I can say in regard to Motion No. 12, but we will take it as soon as possible so far as this side of the House are concerned.</P>
      <P>With regard to Motion No. 15, which was raised by Senator West, I understand that it simply is not convenient for the Minister to deal with the Transport Bill and the McKensey Report at the same time.  Having regard to the views of the Minister on the subject, we are not suggesting that it should be taken with Motion No. 2.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Regarding the request made by Senator Robinson and others in connection with item no. 7, I am not in a position to give an undertaking in a concrete or definite form which was suggested, in the first instance, by Senator Robinson and then by Senator West.  I will certainly consider the request which has been made that a <Col N="22" /> Second Reading discussion on the Bill should take place in this House and possibly by agreement be adjourned. As I say, I am not in a position to give an undertaking.  In addition to consideration of that suggestion from a Government point of view, I think it is only fair that the political parties&mdash; Fianna Fáil, Fine Gael and Labour&mdash; should have an opportunity of considering it and letting us know what their views are so that the matter can be dealt with on that basis.</P>
    <P>Senator Browne, in his contribution, referred to evidence of my view differing from those of my party.  At least I would differ from only one party if that was so.  I have been in the same party all my political life and I am glad to say it is the only one that Senator Dr. Browne was never in.</P>
    <P>As regards Senator Higgins' embarrassment over a confusion of names, may I tell him that his embarrassment was nothing to mine when I received his income tax demand.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>I will accept the undertaking by the Leader of the House but I would ask that he try to get this in next week if possible.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator West?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I have got no reason whatever, a Chathaoirleach, why motion No. 15 cannot be taken except that it is just not convenient.  That is a perfect non-reason, so I intend to press the amendment.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Senator West is proposing that item No. 15 be added to the Order of Business.</P>
      <P>Question &ldquo;That No. 15 be added to the Order of Business&rdquo; put and declared negatived.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="NoelCBrowne" hpid="Dr. Browne Dr. Browne">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Browne</NameTxt>
      <P>We got no undertaking at all.  You can kick to touch until the end of this session, have us here till Christmas or even next year.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am putting the question: &ldquo;That No. 7 be added to the Order of Business.&rdquo;</P>
      <P Just="Center">The Seanad divided: Tá, 5; Níl, 43.</P>
      <P Just="Center">Tá</P>
    </Speaker>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Browne, Noel C.<br />Horgan, John S.<br />Martin, Augustine.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Robinson, Mary.<br />West, Timothy Trevor.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="23" />
      <Col N="24" /> Níl</P>
    <table pgwide="1">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" align="center">
        </colspec>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry rowsep="1">Aylward, Bob.<br />Barrett, Jack.<br />Blennerhassett, John.<br />Brennan, John J.<br />Brosnahan, Seán.<br />Browne, Patrick (Fad).<br />Burton, Philip.<br />Butler, Pierce.<br />Cowen, Bernard.<br />Deasy, Austin.<br />Dolan, Séamus.<br />Eachthéirn, Cáit Uí.<br />Farrelly, Denis.<br />FitzGerald, Alexis.<br />FitzGerald, Jack.<br />Fox, Billy.<br />Garrett, Jack.<br />Halligan, Brendan.<br />Hanafin, Des.<br />Harte, John.<br />Higgins, Michael D.<br />Keegan, Seán.</entry>
            <entry rowsep="1">Kennedy, Fintan.<br />Kerrigan, Patrick.<br />Lyons, Michael Dalgan.<br />McCartin, John Joseph.<br />McGlinchey, Bernard.<br />Mannion, John M.<br />Markey, Bernard.<br />Moynihan, Michael.<br />Mullen, Michael.<br />O'Brien, Andy.<br />O'Brien, William.<br />O'Higgins, Michael J.<br />O'Toole, Patrick.<br />Owens, Evelyn.<br />Quinlan, Patrick Michael.<br />Russell, George Edward.<br />Ryan, Eoin.<br />Ryan, William.<br />Sanfey, James W.<br />Walsh, Mary.<br />Whyte, Liam.<br /></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <P Just="Center">Tellers: Tá, Senators Browne and Robinson; Níl, Senators Sanfey and Halligan.</P>
    <P>Question declared lost.</P>
    <P>Order of Business agreed to.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BrendanHalligan" hpid="Mr. Halligan Mr. Halligan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Halligan</NameTxt>
      <P>I wish to indicate that the Labour Party supported the Order of Business today in the hope that the reasonable request made by Senator Robinson would be acceded to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Transport" RHead="Bill, 1974: Second Stage">
    <Title>Private Business. - Transport Bill, 1974: Second Stage.</Title>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. P. Barry) Peter Barry">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. P. Barry)</NameTxt>
      <P>The purpose of the Bill is to extend CIE's long-term borrowing powers for capital purposes and also to increase the limit on the board's temporary borrowing powers.</P>
      <P>Before dealing with the Bill itself I propose to review briefly the position of CIE in recent years.  As Senators are aware there has been a serious deterioration in CIE's financial position since 1969 when the amount of the board's statutory grant was fixed at £2.65 million per annum.  The board's losses have increased from over £3 million in 1969-70 to over £8 million in 1972-73 and there will be a further substantial increase in the current financial year.  The increased losses have been incurred mainly on the railway but the position has been aggravated by a decline into a loss-making situation of hitherto profitable road services.  Increases in rates and fares sought by the board in 1972 were postponed for almost a year pending completion of an investigation by the National Prices Commission and this, of course, has contributed significantly to the losses.</P>
      <P>The investigations carried out by McKinsey &amp; Co. in 1971 showed that CIE's increasing losses were due mainly to inflation and to growing competition from private transport. The consultants carried out a broad cost benefit analysis of railway operations and found that, even when given credit for all the social benefits which it could be deemed to render to the community, the railway still incurred substantial losses and, leaving aside transitional costs, could be replaced more economically by an all road system. However, the inclusion of unavoidable transitional costs, mainly costs of redundancy, altered the position and the consultants found that from a community standpoint the best course of action was to retain the railway but to selectively modify and develop it so as to bring social costs and benefits more closely into line.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>CIE, on the basis of the general recommendations of the consultants, have been developing specific plans for the rationalisation of mainline railway operations and improvements in operating practices which will involve, <Col N="25" /><i>inter alia,</i> increased capital investment in modernising terminals, rolling stock, track and signalling. These plans are at present under examination and I hope to secure the early approval of the Government for CIE to proceed on the lines proposed. Because the costs of the railway consist so largely of labour costs any financial improvement will involve some redundancy but it is envisaged that this can largely be met by natural wastage.  The whole plan will in any case be discussed by CIE with the trade unions.</P>
    <P>By the use of imaginative marketing and promotional campaigns CIE have achieved a considerable increase in the number of passengers travelling by rail.  Almost 12 million were carried in 1972-73 which represents an increase of 8 per cent over 1971-72, which itself had shown an increase of 6½ per cent over the previous year. The introduction of the new air-conditioned super trains which brought a new standard of passenger comfort, speed and convenience was also a contributory factor.  Dublin suburban commuter rail traffic also continued to expand in 1972-73, showing a growth of 7½ per cent on the previous year.  New push/pull train units were introduced to improve these services.</P>
    <P>Rail freight tonnage at 3.65 million tons was marginally higher in 1972-73 than in the previous year.  The liner train concept was further developed and the remand for unit load/container conveyance and for further extensions of pallets continued to grow.</P>
    <P>There was also an expansion in CIE's road services.  Dublin city buses carried 210 million passengers in 1972-73, an increase of 9.5 million on the previous year.  A total of 62 million passengers were carried on the board's provincial long distance and city bus services, excluding special school services, in 1972-73, an increase of 2 million over the previous year.  A major bus passenger survey has recently been carried out by CIE and the information obtained will form the basis of a new overall provincial bus policy plan which is being formulated. In the road freight section the <Col N="26" /> total tonnage carried in 1972-73 was 5.7 million tons which was 2 per cent higher than in the previous year.  CIE's shipping and air freight services, which are conducted through Irish Ferry-ways and Aerlód Teoranta, showed larger turnover and increased profitability in spite of the severe competition in sea and air freight.</P>
    <P>Unfortunately, as I have already indicated, these improvements have not been sufficient to counteract the prevailing economic forces and the board's deficits still continue to grow. The railway deficit in 1972-73 was £7.695 million, an increase of £980,000 on the deficit in 1971-72.  Notwithstanding the increase in the number of passengers carried, a loss of £360,000 was incurred on the Dublin city bus services compared with a profit of £185,000 in 1971-72.  The provincial bus services showed a decline in profits from £550,000 in 1971-72 to £319,000 in 1972-73.  Road freight services, however, showed a small profit of £22,000 compared with a loss of £134,000 in 1971-72.</P>
    <P>The existing blanket type subvention paid to CIE will no longer be appropriate under EEC regulations and proposals for a new subvention structure to meet EEC requirements are at present nearing completion.</P>
    <P>The immediate need for the present Bill is to enable CIE to take up a loan of £4m. which has been approved by the European Investment Bank for a term of 20 years at a proposed rate of interest of 8¾ per cent.  At present CIE's long-term capital borrowing powers are confined to borrowing from the Minister for Finance and it is necessary therefore to extend these powers so as to enable the board to take up the proposed loan from the EIB and also to avail of any other sources of finance which might be found attractive.  It is expected however, that the Exchequer will still remain the main source of loan finance for CIE's capital expenditure.  Borrowing from sources other than the Exchequer will be subject to my prior consent and the approval of the Minister for Finance, who will be empowered to guarantee such borrowings.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="27" /> The EIB loan is related to the board's railway investment programme and will contribute in particular to improvements in passenger train services, wagon load freight services, terminal facilities and the signalling system.  These improvements will enable the provision of faster and more frequent passenger trains with modern carriages and the concentration of freight traffic on fully fitted block trains.  We would hope that these measures will lead to a significant increase in traffic by rail.  By granting the loan of £4 million, the European Investment Bank is helping the railway to remain an essential part of Ireland's transport system and to play its part in the programme of the Irish economy.</P>
    <P>The limit on the board's capital borrowing powers and on Exchequer capital advances to CIE was increased from £6 million to £17 million under the Transport Act, 1969.  The £17 million provision is now almost exhausted and it is proposed to extend the limit to £55 million, that is an increase of £38 million.  This sum, together with the board's depreciation provisions, will be available to meet future capital expenditure by the board.  It will enable the board to continue with its policy of modenising its services and improving standards.</P>
    <P>In addition to the proposals already mentioned for modernising mainline railway operations, CIE are also preparing plans for the improvement of the Dublin rail commuter services.  As Senators are aware, the Government recently approved in principle of the development of these services to play the maximum role possible in helping to relieve the city's present congestion problems.</P>
    <P>Provision is also being made in the Bill for an increase from £2 million to £5 million in CIE's temporary borrowing powers.  The existing limit of £2 million was fixed in 1958 and is now an inadequate safeguard against possible short-term cash difficulties. This has been evident in recent years when Supplementary Estimates have had to be introduced at short notice to ensure that the board would have <Col N="28" /> sufficient cash to meet its current requirements.</P>
    <P>The contract for the European Investment Bank loan cannot be concluded pending the enactment of legislation, as provided for in this Bill, to extend the scope of CIE's borrowing powers.  The next meeting of the board of the European Investment Bank will take place on 19th February and to avoid the possibility of the interest rate on the proposed loan being increased the intention is that, provided the Bill has been enacted, the contract will be concluded by that date.</P>
    <P>I should, therefore, greatly appreciate it if the House would agree to give a quick passage to the Bill.  I commend the Bill to the House.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>We on this side of the House welcome this Bill because we believe that as a result of it CIE may be in a position to provide the necessary improvements in their service to benefit more people than are benefiting at the moment.  Coming from a county that knows little about CIE or their operations, I should like to hear from the Minister the future policy of CIE as far as the west of Ireland and the Ulster counties are concerned.  I note from his speech that on the basis of the general recommendations of the consultants, CIE have been developing specific plans for the rationalisation of mainline railway operations.  Later on in his speech he told us that the EIB loan is related to the board's ran-way investment programme and will contribute in particular to improvements in the passenger train service, wagon load freight services, terminal facilities and the signalling system.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I feel that the people in the west and north-west of Ireland have a right to ask are their interests being taken into consideration in these plans.  They have a right to ask will any of this EIB loan be used to give them the service to which they are entitled and which they have never got.  When one studies the railway system in the country one admits that apart from this city to the Minister's city and to <Col N="29" /> Galway, the train service in Ireland is practically non-existent.</P>
    <P>I come from a county that, as a result of Partition, is virtually cut off from the rest of the Republic, a county that has suffered, not alone politically but economically as a result of the Partition of this country.  I have always felt that because of the political situation bodies such as CIE should have given it more consideration. CIE's contribution to the transport services in Donegal amounts to this: a bus leaves Letterkenny at 9 a.m. and 3 p.m.  A bus leaves Donegal town once a day and that is the sum total of CIE's transport operations in a country of 100,000 people.</P>
    <P>As a result of the regionalisation of the health services and the tourist services it is necessary for many people in my county to travel to the Regional Hospital in Galway and to University College Galway, and this is considered a tremendous hardship because of the failure of CIE to provide proper services.  Up to a few years ago, a train service operated from Strabane, County Tyrone, to Dublin but with the eclipse of the Great Northern Railway and as a result of the closure of the Portadown line, this service ceased, thus cutting off 100,000 people from the capital of this country.</P>
    <P>Any plans which CIE have to develop the railway system in Ireland must recognise the imbalance in railway services as far as the province of Connacht and County Donegal are concerned.  There have been many pleas in recent years calling for a special subsidy on manufactured goods transport.  One of the reasons why it is found difficult to encourage industrialists to this part of the country is the heavy and crippling burden of transport costs.</P>
    <P>We in our part of the country&mdash; from Donegal to Kerry or to Clare&mdash; believe that we have as much right to these necessary services as our neighbours on the east and southern coasts. Now that CIE are being given powers to raise so much money, now that they are benefiting from the European loans and now that the whole transport system in this country will be reviewed, the special position of <Col N="30" /> Connacht and Donegal should be given priority consideration.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, am quite happy with this Bill which allows CIE to borrow money at a very attractive rate of interest.  I suppose it is only fair to admit that CIE have had a difficult task assigned to them over the years because they have endeavoured to provide systems of communication in all parts of the country.  It is fair to say that in the sparsely and thinly populated areas of the country, I am sure from the very beginning, it was more or less assumed that there would be a loss on these services in such areas.</P>
      <P>I should like to draw the attention of the Minister to the fact that, like my colleague beside me, as an Ulster-man we have lost the Great Northern Railway and because of that a great deal of articulated traffic has come on to the roads.  While in some cases we have got better grants there, we have not, in any shape or form, benefited to the extent necessary to bring our roads up to a standard which would enable them to carry the articulated type of traffic that they are asked to carry now, especially with juggernauts and various other trucks coming from the EEC and using our roads.  It should be possible to allot part of this money to such areas.</P>
      <P>Rail services are a tremendous advantage in any particular area.  We, unfortunately, in the north-west have not any such services now.  It amuses me to see CIE advertising nightly on television about &ldquo;The Great Train Robbery&rdquo; and the great facilities that are available to children and adults to travel by CIE, but it is rather frustrating to find that none of the people in my area can avail of these services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is true that to attract industry into an area you must have decent communications. The Minister would be well advised, in looking over these railways and where they are situated, to have a look at the main road that leads from my constituency in County Cavan to Dublin city and to notice that, no matter how we strive to get industrialists in&mdash;and we have quite a few of them&mdash;they either have to get their <Col N="31" /> manufactured products for export out through the ports of Drogheda, Dundalk or Dublin, or up to Greenore. When you try to get into Dublin city from Clonee or Mulhuddart the road there is practically as narrow and as twisty as it is in County Cavan.  We may have an excuse for twisty roads because of the number of lakes in our county but there is not any excuse that I know of, and I do not think there should be any financial reason either, why the people living in the north-west of our country should be penalised in that way.  Having gained time getting towards the port, especially to Dublin, they spend practically the same length of time on the journey from Clonee into Dublin city as they would from leaving Cavan town to get to Mulhuddart.  That certainly should be taken into consideration.</P>
    <P>We in our end of the country do not benefit a lot from CIE hotels.  We have an abundance of lovely lakes and forests and everything that should attract tourists and that would be pleasing to the eye of those who wished to enjoy the beauties of nature.  There is plenty of that in our area and yet CIE never during their existence contemplated putting a decent hotel in that area.  If one travels down south you will find hotels all over the place.  I do not think it fair that the money has been allotted on such a biased fashion&mdash; the whole north-western area has been neglected so far as decent roads and hotels are concerned.  Both of these come under the Department of Transport and Power.</P>
    <P>There have been some complaints, I do not know how valid they are, regarding bus services.  We have no train services in our area.  In the Minister's speech today we read of the efforts that will be made to improve trains and make them more luxurious.  I wonder if the same standard, or something similar, could be applied to improving the standard of our buses. Perhaps the roads may not be able to take them but there are things that would need to be seen to, in particular this matter of toilets.  These are necessary on trains and I do not see why <Col N="32" /> they should not be provided on buses also.  Some way should be devised whereby they could provide them on buses.</P>
    <P>CIE have done an excellent job in providing school transport services. Here, again, I should say that it should be the responsibility of CIE or the people responsible for the buses to ensure that no damage is done to them by any of the students or the people travelling on them.  Some prefect or some responsible individual should be in charge.  I do not think any type of bad conduct or any type of vandalism should be tolerated on our buses or trains.  It is wrong that people should not be checked and punished when they commit vandalism. It is a type of training that is very necessary.</P>
    <P>I wish to compliment CIE on having the Irish words &ldquo;Bus Scoile&rdquo; and the names in Irish on their vehicles. Through a Bill here in the Seanad some time ago we legalised this form through the log-ainmneacha legislation. It is good that CIE have continued to do it and I wish them luck in the years ahead.  I am glad to see that they are being given this chance in this Bill.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to join the other Members in assuring the Minister of a speedy passage of this Bill.  It is necessary that it be passed through the House this afternoon.  I think the Minister can be assured of our co-operation in that regard.</P>
      <P>It is disappointing, and I am sure the Minister takes no pleasure in coming to this House to point it out, that despite the very energetic marketing and promotional efforts of CIE&mdash; and I think they are to be very strongly commended for their efforts in recent years&mdash;heavy losses continue in all sections of the system, both road and rail. When one contemplates the fact that the loss has increased from £3 million in 1969-70 to £8 million in 1972-73 it is a fair indication of the serious situation that faces the railways not only in this country&mdash;let us be fair about it &mdash;but in every country in Europe today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>What is encouraging&mdash;and I think is <Col N="33" /> an indication of the hard work and drive that has been put into the promotional campaign&mdash;is that under all headings, both in road traffic and in passenger traffic there have been substantial increases.  Normally in a commercial or industrial concern, one would expect improved results to flow from such successful promotional or marketing efforts.  In the case of CIE we must heavily subsidise our national transport system if we wish to retain it. Nobody in this House or outside would wish it otherwise.</P>
    <P>In 1956 or 1957 the late Seán Lemass, then Minister for Industry and Commerce, introduced a Bill in the Dáil to provide a subsidy of not more than £500,000 for CIE, and hopefully stated on the occasion that after a few years CIE would become a viable proposition.  At the time I did not share his optimism and my views have been proved only too true.  The main object of this Bill, as the Minister pointed out, is to take advantage of the European Investment Bank loan, which is very attractive at present-day terms, of £4 million over a 20 year period at 8 per cent.  If I could express a wish in that regard it would be that instead of £4 million it would be £40 million.  That sort of money is not easily raised today.  We should grab this without delay.</P>
    <P>Secondly, the proposal to increase the board's capital borrowing powers from £17 million to £55 million is an indication of the sort of capital expenditure that will be needed not only to maintain the system on the rails and on the roads but also to increase its efficiency and its comfort for the passengers and the facilities for the freight carried.  Finally, there is the proposal to increase CIE's temporary borrowing powers from £2 million to £5 million.  All these are necessary expenditures.</P>
    <P>We regret CIE must continue to face losses but we must be realists in the matter.  The recent fuel emergency proved how vitally necessary our national transport system is.  There was panic in regard to fuel and all of us who had become used to travelling by car to our places of business and <Col N="34" /> so on, suddenly found the only reliable mode of transport was CIE.</P>
    <P>We should not forget that, even though there are apparent losses from the point of view of accountancy, there are rewards for the very heavy investment which the country has made in CIE over many years.  They are the biggest single employers in the country with more than 20,000 employees drawing a salary and wage bill of some £34 million.  All these employees pay rates and taxes, purchase goods and services and give indirect employment to others.  If a balance sheet were to be made out on a social rather than on a purely accountancy system we might find that CIE were paying their way nationally through the taxes and other income which the State gets from the employees.</P>
    <P>There is no substitute for CIE as a long haul carrier.  Even the juggernauts which are becoming a great nuisance on our roads&mdash;it is almost impossible to get through country towns and villages if one of these gigantic vehicles happens to be passing through&mdash;could not compete with them.  We obviously will have to spend vast sums of money on our roads in the near future.  We must contemplate providing motorways as they have done in Northern Ireland and Great Britain and other European countries. This will run into millions of pounds.</P>
    <P>The time has come when the Minister should seriously consider setting up a national transport system to coordinate all forms of surface transport to ensure that resources of energy-consuming fuels, personnel and all that goes towards making a roadway or a railway are utilised to the best and most efficient degree.  When I put this forward some years ago in the Seanad the then Minister did not think it worth his while to consider it. I should like to bring it up again for the benefit of the present Minister. Fuels and all forms of energy will become more and more expensive as time goes on.  This was brought before us vividly in recent months and we must ensure that we, who have to import almost all our energy requirements, use our fuel in the best possible <Col N="35" /> economic and most efficient manner. The best way of ensuring that economic use is made of the various forms of energy such as fuels is a co-ordinated national transport system.  I should like to put that forward for the Minister's consideration.  He can be assured of a quick passage for this Bill and the absolute appreciation of this House that the money is urgently required.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Mr. Moynihan rose.</i>
    </P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanBrosnahan" hpid="Acting Chairman (Mr. Brosnahan) Acting Chairman (Mr. Brosnahan)">
      <NameTxt>Acting Chairman (Mr. Brosnahan)</NameTxt>
      <P>We have had two speakers from the Opposition side and only one from the Government side.  To keep the balance I now call on Senator Moynihan.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelMoynihanKerry" hpid="Mr. Moynihan Mr. Moynihan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Moynihan</NameTxt>
      <P>I merely want to say that we in the Labour Party congratulate the Minister for bringing forward this financial requirement for the running of CIE.  In doing so there are some remarks I should like to make.  Over the years the financial losses of CIE have been a worry for the different Departments, for the board and the different Governments, but still the dance goes merrily on. Numerous inquiries and investigations have been set up and quite recently consultants have been brought in.  As a trade unionist, I wish to say that one of the worrying aspects of each inquiry was the implications that labour costs must be cut at a particular level, which is the labour wage generally.</P>
      <P>We saw in the late fifties and the early sixties substantial segments of the railway lines being closed down. Not only that, but the major blunder was made of tearing up the lines, thus ending for all time any possibility of restoring them as transport channels. We now realise they could be usefully restored for the benefit of the community.</P>
      <P>On page 2 of the Minister's document it is stated:</P>
      <P>CIE on the basis of the general recommendations of the consultants have been developing specific plans for the rationalisation of main line railway operations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="36" /> The word &ldquo;rationalisation&rdquo; aggravates the ordinary work force in industry. It usually ends up with another word, &ldquo;redundancy&rdquo;.  This word is used here. It states:</P>
    <P>Because the cost of the railway consists so largely of labour costs any financial improvement will involve some redundancy, but it is envisaged that this can be largely met by national wastage.</P>
    <P>I am glad the whole plan will be discussed by CIE with the trade unions.</P>
    <P>Over all the years in which these investigations have been proceeding in all the different inquiries that have been held, over all the rationalisation and redundancy plans that have been implemented, it is alleged, I think with good authority, that at managerial, at sub-managerial and at supervisory level there has been major expansion by CIE and their employees.  I ask the Minister today, when he is seeking this money, to ensure that this expansion at that level will have the desired effect of efficiency and economy for which it was originally intended rather than the creation of posts which have served no useful purpose in the administration of this very important company.  Although we have had drastic reductions at the labour level, it is unrealistic to think that a concern that has been losing for so long and so heavily should expand the top level managerial and salaried posts with their extra costs if they do not show clearly that the company are gaining the efficiency and economy intended.</P>
    <P>We accept that CIE must remain as an integral part of our transport services.  I think that they are giving a reasonable service within their limitations, financial and otherwise.</P>
    <P>One aspect of efficiency comes immediately to mind.  It is regrettable for any of us&mdash;and certainly for the Minister and the board of CIE&mdash;to see bus crews refusing to take out defective buses.  That is something which should not happen in a company like CIE. Every bus offered to a crew to go into service should be roadworthy.  That is something to which the Minister should draw the pansion by CIE and its employees.  I <Col N="37" /> CIE are the largest employers in the country.  There is a massive State investment in the company.  Relations with the trade unions are an integral part of the company's functions. There is another human aspect I did mention in the pre-Christmas debate. It refers to those employees who have served the company well and are now retired.  They have been badly treated. No company can hope to survive unless they treat their employees reasonably while in their employment.  When such employees leave after having given many long years of service to the company, the company still has a responsibility to them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>We can all welcome the present measure because there is no other option but to keep and modernise CIE as our main public transport system.  It cannot be done any other way.  Any recommendation of any board of consultants that we could afford to put all that traffic on an all-road system is just so much nonsense.  I do not think that could ever be realised.</P>
      <P>We have had every three or four years a CIE Bill coming before Seanad Éireann.  About eight years ago we legislated CIE into solvency and laid a solemn obligation on them from the Oireachtas that henceforth they were to pay their way.  Again, that was an approach that many of us who spoke at that stage pointed out was just nonsense.  It has proved to be so.  We can be conscious, looking qualitatively at CIE, that great strides have been made.  Certainly the train service has improved considerably. The emergency over the last two months must have resulted in a very considerable increase in traffic for CIE.  It could very well have altered the profitability position.  The emergency, even in its short period, changed airlines quickly from a loss to a profit situation because they were able to cut redundant services.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It is suggested that in the future we might have faster and more frequent services.  We have too many services on the main line from Cork to Dublin. There is no call for any increase in that service.  Obviously we must have <Col N="38" /> a full public transport system within our cities.  Having seen the effect of the drastic cut-down in the number of automobiles going through the cities in the last few months because of the petrol shortage we are delighted to see that cities can be brought to life again.  The public have had an experiment and they can see that public transport can be used.  It is vital to get down now to a drastic cutdown on the number of cars going into the cities, with a consequent improvement in the usage of public transport.  People are conditioned to it now.  It is in the interest of everyone that this should be done.  I would go so far as to say that we might even have a toll system for cars going into our major cities in the future. Automobile drivers could be charged a toll, with a possibility of a reduction for every passenger carried.  The real culpability lies in the use of the car for just one passenger, taking up the very valuable space on the roads and streets of our cities.</P>
    <P>Now is the time to tackle that problem. I hope that this modernisation plan of CIE will start by having a critical and constructive look at what has happened during the past two months.  Things are possible now that would not have been thought of two months ago.  Two months ago the public would not have accepted some of the limitations on the use of private transport that are accepted now.  With the increase in petrol prices that have occurred and the prospect of more to come there is an opportunity for a more profitable public transport system. The tide has turned.  All factors combine to indicate that now is the time to tackle the job.</P>
    <P>In the past those of us listening here protested again and again at the senseless policy of closing down branch lines.  Now we can see the folly of that policy.  We remember the West Cork railroad from Cork to Bantry that has now been demolished and remember that those engaged on demolition could not get out fast enough to ensure that the railway could not be utilised ever again.  That is something we bitterly regret.  With the developments that are foreshadowed <Col N="39" /> in the south-west area and other places we may well find that we have got to put back, at tremendous cost, the rail link between Cork and Bantry.</P>
    <P>On the other side we see the vandalism that got rid of the West Clare railroad, the Percy French railroad.</P>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>I could not agree more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Surely if there was any single railway that was capable of being a tourist attraction it was this railroad.  There could have been a halfway policy of at least leaving it and letting it be used when the appropriate time came.  It was demolished and every step taken to ensure that it could never be used again.  I hear that the single-gauge railroad is puffing its way somewhere in Africa today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="GeorgeERussell" hpid="Mr. Russell Mr. Russell">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Russell</NameTxt>
      <P>Through darkest Africa.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>These are some of the mistakes made in the past which should not have been made.  If we have faith and confidence in our future we will not make such mistakes again. Therefore, our approach to CIE and their development at this stage is really a barometer of our confidence in the future.  While experts can advise.  I do not think there is any need to remind a businessman like the Minister that they are fallible.  This cost-benefit analysis is the greatest bit of jiggery-pokery that can be engaged in.  If one knows what one wants to prove one can always fiddle the cost and the advantages around in such a way that the answer comes up.</P>
      <P>I commend the Bill and I look forward to a really exciting time in the development of public transport in the next few years.  The time is ripe.  Let us face the problems involved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="AndyOBrien" hpid="Mr. A. O'Brien Mr. A. O'Brien">
      <NameTxt>Mr. A. O'Brien</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to join with the other Senators who have congratulated the Minister on the introduction of this Bill.  I hope the money that has to be borrowed will be used by CIE to develop a more efficient transport service, not just for one section of the country but for the whole country.  It is worthy of note too that the money is borrowed at a reasonably low rate of interest.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="40" /> It is unfortunate that the operations of CIE result in a loss every year.  It would be even more unfortunate if the fact that the loss is met every year by the taxpayer were to result in those who control the fortunes of CIE reaching a frame of mind where they felt that the taxpayer would foot the bill irrespective of how CIE do their business.  I do not say that that attitude exists, but it would be unfortunate if a constant succession of payments by the taxpayer were to meet a constant succession of losses by a company.  It would be unfortunate if that kind of thinking were to develop among those who administer the CIE service.</P>
    <P>The emphasis in the advertising of the new &ldquo;Supertrain&rdquo; is on more comfort and greater speed, which is to be welcomed.  The bus service also could have more comfort and certainly more speed.  However, with the improvements in the main arterial roads this should come.  A bus journey from Cavan to Dublin, of 70 miles, takes three hours, which is far too long.  I should add that this is not the express bus, but the ordinary service bus and it has several stops on the journey.  The delays when the bus stops to pick up passengers or let them off are too long.  This journey has taken three hours each time for the last 20 years even though the road has been improved.  CIE do not appear to realise that the people's time is valuable and that a person will think twice before spending three hours on a bus for a 70-mile journey.  That is one reason why CIE lose patronage.</P>
    <P>I travelled on a bus recently and there was a breakdown.  That is not the cause of my complaint because breakdowns are not common on CIE buses.  There was a delay of three-quarters of an hour while the bus was being repaired.  It never ocurred to the driver to explain to the passengers what was wrong, how long they were likely to be delayed, or if they were likely to get out of the place at all.  It should be a matter of common courtesy for officials operating these buses to be helpful and courteous to passengers and not to take it for granted that 30 persons on a bus under repair <Col N="41" /> are willing to spend half an hour on the road without an explanation. Thirty people should not be delayed like that without any explanation or apology whatever.</P>
    <P>Senator Dolan mentioned earlier the bus tours organised to places of tourist interest, and that they have been very successful.  I have been at Busaras several times during the summer season and I saw buses going to different places of well-known scenic attraction.  But little or nothing has been done by CIE to develop the desire on the part of visitors to travel to places that are equally beautiful but not as well-known.  CIE have that obligation to the part of the country that is not well known overseas.  They must try to get people to visit places of scenic attraction in different parts of the country.  It is not right to go on the well-worn roads all the time and to give the impression that places of scenic beauty are confined to one area.  I should like if more attention were given to this point.</P>
    <P>People should not have to spend so much time queueing for tickets in the Busaras during the rush hour.  There should be some allocation of staff for the rush hours.  Sometimes there is only one person in the ticket office and perhaps 400 or 500 persons waiting to get tickets.  It should be possible to have two or three persons in the ticket office during the rush hours and not have people queueing so long to get a ticket.</P>
    <P>With regard to the excursion rates to Dublin from different parts of the country served by trains, I believe CIE owe the same concession to the parts of the country not served by trains.  If it has been found economic to give cheap fares to areas served by train, such cheap fares should also be available to people who are not served by trains.  There should be cheap fares on the buses during the week or at times when these buses are running half-empty.  CIE should give some thought to this.  With regard to these cheap fares on trains I think the &ldquo;Great Train Robbery&rdquo; slogan was a most unhappy choice.  I do not think it displayed any great taste to perpetuate in a slogan like that the <Col N="42" /> memory of one of the greatest train robberies that took place in these islands in the last 100 years.  Anybody with any proper taste would not have let that slogan through.</P>
    <P>I should like to refer to the opening page in the Minister's statement which says that:</P>
    <P>Increases in rates and fares sought by the board in 1972 were postponed for almost a year pending completion of an investigation by the National Prices Commission and this, of course, has contributed significantly to the losses.</P>
    <P>If CIE were a private company I believe that the trend towards losses would have been foreseen and a case could have been made to the National Prices Commission.  It should not have been necessary for the company to operate at a loss for a long period of time pending an investigation of the claim.  A private concern could not run its affairs like that.  I do not believe it would have been done in CIE were those responsible not aware of the fact that, no matter how things ended up, the taxpayer would eventually foot the bill.</P>
    <P>It is most satisfactory to hear that the road freight services showed a profit.  The profit was small but in previous years road freight services showed a very significant loss.  One of the strongest contributing factors to the decline of the railways was a most unsatisfactory freight service.  There were inordinate delays and losses shown and that contributed to a very large degree to the failure of the railroad system.  For that reason it is significant that the road freight service has shown a profit following a year when there was quite a sizeable loss.</P>
    <P>The provincial bus services have shown a decline in profit.  Something might come out of the point I made earlier on about speeding up the buses. The most annoying point in the whole statement is the losses incurred in Dublin city.  Notwithstanding the increase in the number of passengers carried a loss of £360,000 was incurred by the Dublin city service compared with a profit of £185,000 in <Col N="43" /> 1971-72.  That is the most significant factor in the whole of the Minister's speech.  It is something which calls for close and critical examination.  In Dublin city a huge number of people wish to travel at fixed times.  A large number of people are willing to travel outside of peak hours.  It is a certain market.  The people are always there. Their journeys are always the same. The distances they travel are very short and the bus fares are very high. A critical examination is necessary to determine why the returns from the Dublin city bus services have fallen as such a degree in one year.  If CIE were providing an efficient service, with parking presenting such a problem in most areas in Dublin at the present time, people would leave their cars at home and avail themselves of the bus services.  With the present energy crisis it is more than likely that people will find it better and more economical to use the public transport service.  If they do, they will expect efficiency and a good service.  The returns would indicate that this type of service is not forthcoming in Dublin to the extent we should like to see.  I would not wish to be hypercritical.  I am quite aware that in many aspects CIE are doing a very good job, but this is something that calls for immediate attention.</P>
    <P>Finally, I should like to say that CIE did not give sufficient attention to a new development that has taken place in recent years.  Large numbers of people from rural Ireland are anxious to go home for the week-ends.  In some instances private companies foresaw this development and provided buses to take people home to the provinces from Dublin city on Friday evening or Saturday evening and to bring them back on Sunday.  CIE should have foreseen this trend.  This service should have been provided to people from rural areas working in the city who were anxious to maintain their contacts with home.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanKeegan" hpid="Mr. Keegan Mr. Keegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome the opportunity of making a few remarks on this Bill.  All of us have come to realise that CIE are more of a social amenity than a huge business concern.  The Irish taxpayers <Col N="44" /> have been conditioned into the belief that in order for CIE to survive they must receive State subsidies.  We must also bear in mind that the livelihood of some 14,000 to 16,000 people is at stake.  It is probably cheaper to continue to subsidise the activities of CIE than to have those people on the unemployment register.  I do not see any alternative to the present system of subsidising the activities of CIE.  The duty of CIE is to make their services more attractive and to enable them to operate as competitively as possible. The difficulty is that CIE are such a vast organisation that their activities cannot be geared on the same lines as those of a private transport company. There is no use blaming any particular section of CIE or any particular Minister because they fail to make a profit each year.  CIE are bound by law to give a service.  They have to comply with regulations and they must give a service despite the fact that this service may not be a paying proposition.</P>
      <P>It is a pity that our rail system cannot be organised to cater for the meat trade and the cattle industry.  CIE lost the bulk of the cattle transportation service because they did not have suitable trains and because many of the marts were built in locations not suitable for CIE rail haulage.  The result was that CIE put on cattle trucks, but these trucks did not secure the business because the private haulier was in a position to give a quicker and more economic service.  It was a pity that CIE did not move in and try to maintain that wedge in the haulage business. It would have enabled them to carry more tonnage and to attract a business which was a profitable one.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>That situation cannot be altered now because of the changes that took place in recent years.  The marts have been located away from the stations. I know of only one or two marts which have been located beside the railway stations.  The buyers who come to those marts are not availing of the services which CIE are in a position to provide for them.  The cattle trucks go direct to the boats or meat factories.  CIE would be well advised to examine the possibility of attracting back some of that business. <Col N="45" /> The fuel crisis which we have all heard so much about may in the long run prove a blessing in disguise in so far as CIE are concerned.  The Irish motorist will begin to do some costings to see whether it is more profitable to avail of the rail services or to use his private car.  I am convinced that if CIE can make it more attractive for the motorist to use the rail system he will leave his car at home. Of course, we must bear in mind that any increase in fuel costs will also affect CIE, but they should make a special effort to induce more people to use their system.  People will use the system if it is more economical to do so.  Therefore, the rail service should be in a better position to do it than the bus service, because of the new super trains which have been mentioned and because of the time factor involved in getting from one place to another.</P>
    <P>From Mullingar, near where I live, it is possible to get to Dublin by rail in an hour.  If one travels by road it may take an hour and a half.  The fuel crisis has created a great deal of new thinking and rethinking about the whole CIE network.  If petrol prices continue to rise and if the world shortage of oil continues, motorists will be compelled for economic reasons to think of using this network.  CIE should therefore do everything possible to exploit the situation.</P>
    <P>Another aspect of the activities of CIE which I feel could be exploited further is the school transport service. It is a very controversial service in rural Ireland.  In one area you will have a minibus loaded to capacity passing children on the road who are prepared to pay their fare on the bus. But, unfortunately, because of the regulations the bus cannot carry them. In another area, two townlands away, you will have a full-size CIE bus transporting from 12 to 14 children.  That is all the children there for that bus to carry.  The parents are prepared to pay the fares of their children in order to have them transported to and from school in safety, but they cannot do so because CIE cannot provide a bigger bus.  There could be a greater <Col N="46" /> amount of co-ordination so as to make that service a more viable proposition. It could be carried out by the staff of CIE in conjunction with the school authorities and the school managers throughout the country.</P>
    <P>You cannot blame people for becoming discontented and disillusioned with the service when they realise that a full-size bus may have only 14 children on it and a minibus in another area may be packed to capacity.  That is something worthy of the attention of the administrators in CIE.  If this were properly organised they could earn more revenue and also satisfy the parents of children who are at present being denied a transport service, who would be assured that their children were travelling in safety and would return home to the rural area in daylight. I am sure CIE and the Department of Education could come together to work out a more acceptable and equitable solution to that problem.</P>
    <P>Another problem that always seems to cause contention is communication between the various staffs of CIE and the management.  Because of the fear of redundancy every member of CIE is concerned for the future of that organisation.  From time to time they are prepared to make suggestions as to how CIE could operate more economically and be made more attractive to the people.  They are always disillusioned because of the fact that their suggestions are never asked for or if they are asked for, they are never considered or acted upon.  I know from my own experience and my contacts with the various staffs of CIE, both in Athlone and Mullingar, that their concern is for their own jobs, first of all, and for the future of Córas Iompair Éireann.  CIE would be well advised to have greater consultation with the staff because they can put forward opinions and views and make recommendations which would enable CIE to become a more profitable organisation.</P>
    <P>At present CIE have a complete monopoly of the transport of lime from the limeworks throughout the country to the farmyards.  Whenever CIE have a breakdown or a strike that service comes to a standstill.  The farmers become anxious.  They fail to <Col N="47" /> have the lime delivered or spread at a given time, and there is only one particular season for it.  Many people believe that if CIE are not able to give the service they should allow the use of private trucks to deliver lime to the farmers throughout the country. Again, that is something worthy of consideration.  It is something that can be rectified if there is proper cooperation between the management of CIE, the supervisors and the truck drivers.  All those people are involved and it will require greater communication and understanding on the part of those people to ensure that a workable service can be provided.</P>
    <P>We are all anxious to see CIE becoming a viable proposition.  Crisis or no crisis, I am still convinced CIE will never become a viable proposition unless we can condition ourselves to the fact that the Irish taxpayer will have to continue to subsidise the activities of that organisation.  There is one problem we should all try and have eliminated with regard to CIE and that is vandalism.  Most Senators will recall that when CIE started mystery tours some years ago the hooligan element availed of the opportunity to travel by train and that they wrecked those trains before they reached their home destination.  That is something that we all must condemn in the strongest possible words.  We cannot blame CIE for discontinuing those tours.  It proved a costly exercise for them because of this vandalism.  As I said before, CIE can only continue with the support of those capital sums which are granted to them occasionally.  Therefore, I hope the fuel crisis may prove a blessing in disguise as far as CIE are concerned.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>We have for long now been accustomed to hearing the worst of news as regards the CIE rail services, and it is no surprise that the Minister has come once again before us looking for a loan this time of £4 million.  But to me the disquieting side of his report is the position of the road services.  We should spend a moment or two on them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="48" /> It is alarming to find that notwithstanding an increase of 5 per cent in the city road passenger services, there is an actual loss in money terms in the Dublin city services and even a fall in profit on the provincial road services.</P>
    <P>We are no longer surprised at continuing loss on the rail services; indeed we expect to put in the money as it is required.  But we are now in the position that something even worse than a break-even position is beginning to apply in regard to the road services.  That seems very strange to me.  To find that in the city of Dublin, where the greatest density of population exists, a natural loss has been incurred is somewhat alarming.</P>
    <P>One point in the Minister's statement is encouraging: we are now seeing an end to the existing blanket type subvention given to cover the weaknesses which exist in CIE.  This blanket-type of assistance to any organisation can sometimes be merely a camouflage to cover up weaknesses which have been inherent in that organisation for a long time past.  It is good to realise that we must now come up with new suggestions to meet EEC regulations in this regard.  We hope that, whatever these regulations throw up, they will provide for a far tighter scrutiny of what the subvention will go towards in future.</P>
    <P>I suppose hindsight is a wonderful thing.  Looking back to the late fifties, when we started closing down the commuter lines around Dublin, we can see the mistake made.  I suppose, again with hindsight we can take encouragement from the fact that McKinsey's Report in 1971 has not been adopted.  He at that time saw difficulty in the transitional costs involved in closing down the rail services altogether, transitional in the sense of redundancy payments and so on.  I am sure if the same people were looking at the situation now other factors would have come to the surface which would have encouraged them to continue with the system we have at the moment.</P>
    <P>We are in a situation where we have no option but to hand over the money as it is required.  The Minister, <Col N="49" /> in asking for this £4 million to meet modernisation in railways, expresses a hope that this modernisation will lead to a greater increase in traffic by rail. Perhaps it will.  But I would ask the Minister to look closely in future at the road situation because no doubt we are heading into serious difficulty when we find ourselves not even at a break-even position at the moment in that respect.</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>The atmosphere in the House indicates the place CIE hold in the affections of the Irish people, because we are managing to spend an enormous sum of money in a short time and so far there have been no complaints, nobody saying this is too much money.  Everybody is reflecting what is a national opinion&mdash;that CIE are essential to the country, that they have a very important social role as well as an economic one and that we are now used to Ministers for Transport and Power coming in and asking us for ever larger subventions. On the other hand this is an enormous sum of money the Minister is asking for and he is giving CIE three blank cheques: one of £4 million, £38 million and then a short-term increase of £3 million.  From the point of view of the legislator it would be pleasant if we had some more concrete idea of how this money has been spent.  From CIE's point of view they just want blank cheques.  The Minister has given us some ideas of the possible ways in which the money is being spent but there is very little concrete costing. We have very little to go on.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>My basic philosophy is to support CIE because of their essential place in our whole economic and social life. Like the previous speakers I think that the company has an opportunity, now that the price of petrol has been increased so markedly over the last few days.  It will undoubtedly increase again.  Many people will be turning to public transport&mdash;buses, trains, freight and all the forms of public transport.  It is up to the company to take the ball on the hop.  Things are going for them now.  They are obviously going to have to pay increased charges on their fuel, but I think that they are going to have <Col N="50" /> increased passenger numbers.  The CIE management has shown imagination in the past.  I feel sometimes that the imaginative people in CIE leave the top structure of the company too early.  I hope that CIE recognise the opportunity they have at the moment because of the fuel crisis and that they press on with increasing the passenger load, increasing the freight load and generally using the money we are voting for them to modernise in a way which will make CIE more attractive to the shipper and to the passenger.</P>
    <P>I wish to make some specific comments. Clearly, as the McKinsey Report says, the actual method of paying money over to CIE is going to have to change.  The Minister did mention that this was being reviewed, not so much the sums but the headings under which the money is to be paid.  The National Prices Commission's Occasional Paper No. 10 sets this out clearly in section 6 when it talks about transport policy in the EEC.  It says on page 118 that:</P>
    <P>It would seem very unlikely that the present &ldquo;block grant&rdquo; to CIE would be permissible under present EEC regulations.  On the other hand, grants could be given to a great many individual services including....</P>
    <P>It goes on to mention the commuter railway in Dublin, passenger and freight services on some sections of the main line, unremunerative provincial bus services and unremunerative road freight services.  It points out that the EEC directives&mdash;regulations 1191/69, 1192/69 and 1107/70&mdash;take into account the social benefits of the services involved and therefore make allowances for the very important role CIE plays in the less well-off areas of the country.  I hope that the company will continue to maintain services to these areas.  I think it is essential that they continue to develop services to the west, south and north, as Senators have asked.  There is no question that this is one of the company's most important roles in the whole Irish economic and social situation.</P>
    <P>Since CIE were formed in 1944, in spite of considerable modernisation, there have been recurring deficits.  As <Col N="51" /> I said, we are now in a position where we are attuned to expect CIE to run it at a deficit because we realise the social advantage.  The McKinsey Report has done some cost-benefit analysis on the sort of problem that would occur if the rail system were closed down.  In 1971, when the McKinsey Report was published, it said that:</P>
    <P>The cost of redundancy compensation under current railway schemes is estimated to be £7 million per annum.  A net present value calculation over 20 years estimates the cost of this proposal to be around £70 million.</P>
    <P>That gives us some idea of the problem we would be faced with if the purely economic view was taken and CIE were cut down, a purely economic view of dealing with the current costs.  Although the McKinsey Report has been criticised severely by economists, who say its cost-benefit analyses were not sufficiently tight and sufficiently accurate, I would say to the Minister much the same as Senator Quinlan has already said: that even the most sophisticated cost benefit analyses do not really give the true picture.  Just because somebody now has a more sophisticated approach does not mean it is the right one.  The people as a whole support CIE and realised that there are many services which it is essential to run, many services which must be maintained and must be maintained by subsidies from the taxpayer, by loans from the European Bank, by raising finance in the way in which the Minister suggests in his Bill.</P>
    <P>I should like to talk a bit about the railways.  The railways are really the main loss-making side of CIE. Any railway system has fixed costs&mdash; the cost inherent in putting down the permanent way and buying the initial rolling stock&mdash;and then, of course, it has operating costs, wages and so on. One of the ways in which the money has been spent recently is in purchasing new rolling stock for long distance trains.  Clearly, the new rolling stock is a success and CIE are to be commended on their choice of stock.  I <Col N="52" /> should like the Minister to say something in his reply about the modernisation of the permanent way.  There are certain trial pieces of continuous rail down&mdash;certainly on the Cork-Dublin line, they are so obvious you can feel them&mdash;but what is CIE policy on continuous welded rails?</P>
    <P>Their policy on coloured light signalling has been made clear.  Basically, they intend replacing semaphore signalling with coloured light signalling. However, I should like to know what the policy is on continuous welded rail.  There is a great deal of expense involved but ultimately there is no question that the continuous welded rail is the thing.</P>
    <P>The company are to be commended on their efforts to get more people to travel on long distances by rail.  The operation that went under the hideous name of &ldquo;The Great Train Robbery,&rdquo; as Senator O'Brien said, with the mad men from the wild west jumping out of your television screen at you, was a success.  It increased the numbers of passengers travelling, although I do not think it increased revenue a great deal.  But it is essential that a transport company which receive a subsidy should be running full trains.  We had the educational tours, the cheap midweek fares, the experiment that was tried a year or two ago of a £2 late night return fare from Dublin to Cork, which was a success.  I should like to know what the company policy is about repeating these late nightearly morning operations because they are worth trying.  Experiments of that kind should be encouraged.  It gives one the idea that the top management of CIE are making an effort to sell their product to the people.</P>
    <P>In some ways the Northern Ireland Railways, who looked as if they were going to go through a bad spell under the Unionist administration, have got a great fillup and are ahead of CIE in many ways.  They got new rolling stock before we did and they have done a great deal of modernisation on the rail.  They are revamping the link between Lisburn and Antrim which is going to cut hours off the Dublin-Derry time.  They have already announced their plans for a central <Col N="53" /> station in the Markets area in Belfast. They intend to close down the three existing stations.</P>
    <P>One thing that the Northern Ireland Railways can be complimented on is the fact that they never sold their permanent way.  We made a terrible mistake when we disposed of the permanent way.  I do not know about the Bantry line, but I know the problem on the Harcourt Street line.  If you dispose of any part of your permanent way you are in trouble.  Whatever you do about pulling up the line, keep the land, because when the suburbs of Dublin develop, as they have done&mdash; and it is clear that a Harcourt Street to Bray line would be of tremendous benefit&mdash;the land is not there.  Do not sell the permanent way.</P>
    <P>In speaking about the North&mdash;I travel up to the North a good deal&mdash; I should like to pay a tribute to the crews, both of Northern Ireland Railways and CIE, who take trains and buses up to the North under very trying conditions.  They are working under great difficulties and they deserve every credit.  I am happy to pay a tribute to them and get it on the Seanad record.  They are often in considerable danger but they stick to their job.  They deserve our best thanks for the work they have continued to do under very difficult circumstances.</P>
    <P>To move on to the commuter rail services, as McKinsey points out, they are totally uneconomic.  In 1971 Dublin commuter rail services showed a £300,000 operating loss, but McKinsey did some calculations.  I am not really clear how rigorous the basis of their calculations was, but if you estimated the social cost of closing down these suburban rail services and of trying to put everybody back on to the roads in cars and buses, then the total additional time spent by commuters would be 1:8 million hours. They estimated the cost as £540,000 at 30p per man per hour and £900,000 at 50p per man per hour.  There was a net credit balance in favour of retaining commuter services.</P>
    <P>The Minister has indicated that some of this money we are voting today is going to be spent on updating <Col N="54" /> commuter services.  We are going to get, we hope, completely new rolling stock.  Sliding doors are needed, more standing room and less seating so that people can get on and off quickly at the stations and so that you can put more people into the trains for the short haul through the city from Lansdowne Road to say Raheny or Kilbarrack.  You also need trains which have a higher acceleration and this will allow greater frequency.  The old push-and-pull units with the diesel at one end or at the other have not really got the acceleration required. We need completely new units there.</P>
    <P>I hope CIE are studying the problems and the solutions adopted in other cities.  In Hamburg for instance, they have commuter tickets which can be got on a giro system through the bank.  All the services are interlocked &mdash;the underground service, the above ground train service, the bus services. All the timetables are issued together so as to familiarise people with the interchanges.  The Hamburg HVV, the company which run the three services, issue puzzles and special card games with the major lines depicted on these. These are puzzles involving train times, bus times, routes and route numbers, so that the kids in Hambourg can learn of the rather complicated system in a pleasant and interesting way.  They have eliminated all bus conductors, turnstiles and ticket collections.  All ticket collection is done on an honour code system, spot checks with a very stiff fine of £50 if you are caught riding without a ticket.  That seems to be worth looking at, too.  We should look at the various modern ideas in suburban transportation.</P>
    <P>I have one here which was developed by an Irish, in fact a Cork, planning expert who has been working in Motherwell in Lanarkshire.  He won second prize in a competition which CIE ran for Cork traffic planning a couple of years ago.  His basic plan was to cut down offstreet parking in the cities, meter all the streets in the city centre, put up the parking fee to a realistic figure: say, 50p per hour in the city centre, decreasing as you go out further.  Then use the revenue from <Col N="55" /> the parking meters to provide a virtually free bus service.  Because the parking meters would be expensive and cut down city centre parking this would allow the bus service to the city centre to flow more easily.  The frequency of the service could be increased with a smaller number of buses because of the ease of traffic flow.  This plan would be well worth looking at and I should like to see the company's reaction to it.</P>
    <P>There have been, as stated by the Minister, considerable developments in the container traffic.  The container depots, the idea of bulk trains, liner trains, container services, the mineral ore traffic, the cement traffic, the Guinness trains and the container trains in conjunction with B &amp; I&mdash;all these are welcome developments in CIE.  It is clear that this is the way freight traffic will go.  The wagon load traffic, the small separates and the parcel traffic must be phased out over a time except where it is absolutely essential.  These should not be carried by rail.  There is the idea of major centres with frequent fast goods trains and road haulage distribution from container depots.  There have been many improvements made in the services.  The passenger express buses are a considerable improvement. The coach services are very good and serve areas which do not have rail services, particularly from Dublin to the north-west and along the west coast. These should be increased.</P>
    <P>Debate adjourned.</P>
    <P>
      <i>Business suspended at 6 p.m. and resumed at 7 p.m.</i>
    </P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. -" RHead="Business of Seanad">
    <Title>Private Business. - Business of Seanad.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the provisions which allow us to raise a matter of special urgency, I was hoping that at this recommencement of business I might be able to draw attention to&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is now raising a matter of urgency without informing the Chair beforehand. This can be done only on notice at the commencement of public business.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="56" />
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>I have in mind the urgent situation which has arisen in relation to Ireland because of the action of the Soviet Union against Alexander Solzhenitsyn and it seems to me that&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I must inform the Senator on this point.  There is provision in the Standing Orders for raising matters of urgent public importance.  A certain procedure is laid down in regard to that.  The Senator must follow that procedure if he wants to take advantage of those Standing Orders.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>In view of the fact that we do not know when the Seanad will sit again and that this matter of grave human importance arises at a time when we are negotiating with the Soviet Union&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I must say to the Senator that he is not in order in accordance with the Standing Orders and accordingly I cannot allow him to pursue the matter.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>In other words, the Standing Orders of the House are so rigid that such a matter of great human importance as the persecution of a great writer&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is now arguing the substance of the matter. The position is that the Standing Orders are clear.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>Well, I admit to being inexperienced in the procedure of the House so I was, in a way, looking for clarification as to whether in a matter as urgent as that involving Solzhenitsyn and in view of our ambition to have diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union, I would have the right to raise it.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator can consult me privately in regard to the operation of Standing Orders, but it is certainly not in order to raise such a matter now.  Neither is it in order to discuss in detail the matter.  I have given my ruling.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>I apologise for my importunity in the matter.  Of course I will not pursue it at the moment, but <Col N="57" /> I hope to raise it the next time the Seanad meets, because it seems to me to be a matter of such grave importance to us all.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>There is a notice of motion handed in by the Senator in this regard and he could consult the Leader of the House in regard to the taking of this at an early date if he wishes.  That course is certainly open to him.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>Thank you very much.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Transport Bill," RHead="1974: Second Stage (Resumed)">
    <Title>Private Business. - Transport Bill, 1974: Second Stage (Resumed).</Title>
    <P>Question again proposed: &ldquo;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I just have a few more remarks to make and they concern mainly our urban transport.  As someone who has spent a great deal of time in the US&mdash;too much perhaps&mdash; I realise the problems which the dominance of the car has brought to that society.  The lack of provision for any proper urban transport has now run the US into tremendous problems. Here is a situation where the economists have been proved wrong. The economists subscribed some years ago to the abolition, the obliteration or the allowing to fall into disuse of the urban transport systems in the US.  Now they are making dreadful and desperate efforts to resuscitate them and they are not having a great deal of success.  At this stage in the development of American cities the expenditure required to buy any land for development of urban motorways or urban trackways is colossal and is causing great problems.</P>
      <P>I should like to quote from the <i>OECD Observer</i> of October, 1972, an article entitled <i>The Future of European Intercity Transport</i>.  It was an article which came from deliberations of the nine OECD members, including this country, and it is a discussion of some of the problems that occur when one tries to build urban motorways. I quote:</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Moreover, the building of highways, particularly in heavily populated regions, meets with increasing <Col N="58" /> opposition from the public on the grounds of pollution, noise, displacement of people and disruption of neighbourhoods.  The current controversies in London, Zurich and Paris and the cancellation of highway projects in Toronto and in a number of United States cities testify to the growing public concern about urban highway construction and to the strength of citizens' protest.</P>
    <P>We can be absolutely sure that any big urban motorway plan in this country would bring a similar outcry. In fact, it is now going on in Belfast where there is a great deal of pressure being put on the new Executive and particularly on Mr. Bradford, the Minister for the Environment, to stop Phase 2&mdash;I think that is the phase it has got to&mdash; and further stages of the big urban motorway development.</P>
    <P>I should like to ask the Minister to say at what stage are our plans, particularly in the cities of Dublin and Cork, for developments of urban transport.  I have here the very interesting Heanue Report on Transportation in the Dublin area.  It is full of ideas.  I do not intend to go through them in detail but one in particular interests me and that is the development of an underground system which, on page 28 of the Heanue Report, would start at Lansdowne Road, go through Merrion Square, Grafton Street with a central terminal somewhere in Westmoreland Street with branches to Broadstone Station. They envisage a bus lane or trains running from Broadstone again and then another branch through Parnell Square, the North Circular Road and Fairview.  That is one of the many interesting ideas which are set out in great detail in the Heanue Report and he makes it fairly clear that it is not possible in the Dublin area to do great suburban motorway development, certainly in the centre of the city.  There are some ring roads proposed but certainly in the centre of the city the ideal form of transport is the underground and we have been very slow in thinking of development of an underground transport system <Col N="59" /> in this city.  I should like to hear what the Minister has to say about our plans for a Dublin underground.</P>
    <P>There are a few other minor points. Out city bus services have an upper limit to their efficiency which is caused by the traffic density in the city.  That is the main precluding factor.  If one could cut down the traffic density by some means or other, specifically by the Richardson plan which I mentioned earlier, then one would help to solve this.  Sooner or later we will have to tackle the problem, also mentioned in the Heanue Report, of cutting down traffic coming into city centres.</P>
    <P>Heanue also envisages the designation of more streets as pedestrian ways.  It is a great pity that the Grafton Street experiment was ceased, and there was one in Henry Street as well.  Heanue makes it clear that if life is going to be worth living in city centres then there must be more streets for pedestrians only.  Inevitably there will have to be a curtailment of traffic coming into city centres.  That is one of the things we have to face.</P>
    <P>Another problem CIE might face is the problem of pollution from the diesel exhaust fumes of the buses.  I should like to see CIE in a civic-spirited way taking the lead and fitting these&mdash;I am not sure of the technical term&mdash;back burners or bafflers or whatever you put on exhausts.  They are standard in many American States.  They ensure that the emission from the exhaust is circulated again, and therefore comes out much less dangerous to the ordinary person. Anybody who comes into Dublin now, particularly from Holyhead on the mail boat to Dún Laoghaire on a clear morning, will see this pall of black gaseous material hanging over the city, and it is mainly fumes from cars, buses and of course household smoke. Anything that could be done to cut down the fumes from our buses would be a very important gesture by CIE. We should see that the national transport company is the first to make that gesture before legislation is brought in making these back burners compulsory.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="60" /> Finally, I should like to ask the Minister about a service in which I have a special interest, having travelled on it very often, that is, the CIE service to the Aran Islands.  The <i>Naomh Eanna</i> must be getting close to its replacement date.  I know there is an air service to the islands now but it is essential that the shipping service to Aran Islands be maintained and it is CIE's responsibility to bear the loss. In other words, the taxpayer pays for it.  It is an essential subsidy to make life on the islands more attractive, and perhaps the Minister would say something about that.</P>
    <P>As I conclude, I would urge, somewhat in the same way as I started, that the accounts for this very large sum of money which we are voting to CIE, when the money is spent, be made available to the public representatives and to the media and that some sort of planned programmed budgeting system be used so that it is pretty clear whether the money is being well spent or whether it is being wasted. With such large sums of money it is very important that the public who are paying the piper should at least know the tune.</P>
    <P>I am glad to see that over the last few years CIE's public relations have improved a great deal.  It is very important from the point of view of public relations that the money is accounted for in a way in which the public can understand how its subsidy is being spent and where it goes.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to speak for long because the Minister has been delayed here quite a long time, and I believe the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare is outside and has important business to do.  Anyway, if I spoke for as long as I had originally proposed, it would to a great extent be a duplication of a number of things that have been said.</P>
      <P>What worries me is that there should be any concern at all about spending of money, particularly when we see from the Minister's statement the way the money will be dealt with, what the projections for the future of CIE are and what it is liable to throw up to the benefit of society as a whole.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="61" /> I see society having an obligation to supply a railway system, even if it means a heavy increase in taxation. It is a social system and it is based on collective social endeavour.  Consequently if you have that type of system and you need that type of system, it has to be paid for and there should not be any bellyaching about the amount.  Admittedly, when you are living in a private enterprise society the question of social systems and a social ideal cannot run on its own; it must also run to some extent with desirable economic aims; on the other hand, if you go too far with the economic objectives there is always the possibility that if by any miracle the undertaking performs well we may have a gallant bid for it to be handed over to private enterprise.  I do not think that is a danger but nevertheless it is a point worth making to support the fact that any social system based on collective social endeavour must be tolerated to a great extent in the sense of paying for the cost of it.</P>
    <P>I am in sympathy with the views that were expressed about the areas that were cut off from a railway service. I am not going to go over the decisions made by the manager of CIE many years ago about the branch lines and the inadequacies of the substitution. However, if we speak about it on the basis of its being a social system and a collective endeavour, there is an obligation to have a look at those areas again and see if after an examination it is a practicable and realisable thing and not too costly to provide the service again.  Despite the fact that decisions have been taken in regard to branch lines there is no reason why those same areas cannot be looked at again.  This could meet the problem of the Senator from Donegal and the Senator from Cavan who find that the bus services that were provided to replace the train services available at one time, particularly freight trains, are inadequate.</P>
    <P>I hope nobody from the private enterprise sector thinks I am trying to take work from them, but what I am about to suggest has happened in Guinnesses to a great extent.  They have <Col N="62" /> allowed a system to run in tandem with their own transport system whereby they have give very substantial contracts to CIE and created a great deal of necessary revenue, particularly in the light of the fact that they are a great source of employment and have a major wage bill to meet. Some inducement should be offered to other big enterprises&mdash;provided of course that it will not upset employment in one particular area&mdash;to operate on a social basis.</P>
    <P>In conclusion, I should like to ask the Minister if he could explain to us how there was a change from a substantial profit to a marginal loss on the Dublin buses.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PaddyMcGowan" hpid="Mr. McGowan Mr. McGowan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGowan</NameTxt>
      <P>During the debate on the approval of the borrowing by CIE of £38 million, I think Senators are entitled to comment on and to offer criticism of the way that CIE has been run and how the money should be spent.  It is a duty of Senators to come here and by their presence to give support and approval to the passage of this Bill.  There is an obligation on them to comment.  If I were asked to say simply and briefly why I thought CIE were losing so much money.  I could do so very easily, because on my way to this House I saw two very good reasons.  Number one, I saw that all the large container and truck service was all Euro-traffic.  There were no CIE vehicles at all.  I have not seen, on my journey to this House today, one single CIE vehicle, while I saw between 40 to 50 very heavy Eurolorries carrying heavy traffic.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I hope that the provision of this money will put CIE into that type of business.  They have missed the boat here.  I do not think they are aggressive enough.  Their sales ability is not adequate.  I hope the provision of this money will put them into this field and that they will compete.  The carriers in Northern Ireland and the carriers in England and Germany are very prominently involved in the transport of goods to and from this country.  Raw materials coming in here are being delivered and manufactured goods collected, and CIE are not active enough in this type of traffic.  I blame the outdated <Col N="63" /> policy of that company.  I hope there will be a major change in policy towards road freight and a greater participation by CIE in that lucrative business.  The cream of the haulage business now is in Euro-traffic.  I hope CIE will take notice and will spend some of this money in getting into and getting a share of the business.</P>
    <P>Another thing you can notice on your way to this House is the bumper to bumper traffic.  Anyone with average IQ would understand that if you drive through the city you will see a few hundred buses, bumper to bumper, all using fuel and all making very little progress.  Any one of us who sits behind them in the evening trying to make his way through the city would ask: how could that company not be losing a stack of money?  The Government will have to tackle the traffic problem at the same time as they sanction the money for CIE.  This is complete waste of money.  The cost of the buses doing unproductive work, sitting there wasting fuel, wasting drivers' time and cluttering up the centre of the city, are obvious reasons why CIE cannot make money.  They are obvious to the man in the street without studying a report of any kind.  I should like to see the Government making progress on the traffic problem with this money being provided for CIE.</P>
    <P>Another aspect I should like to speak about, even though it has been mentioned before, is school transport. On the experience I have had of the way they handle this transport, I can only be critical.  There is a complete lack of policy here.  In some cases in rural areas, CIE hire a minibus service and those people who hire minibuses to CIE have no straightforward policy, no hiring rates, no security. The arrangement is on a day-to-day basis&mdash;a sort of fair day arrangement, whereby you can get one man to drive for 7p a mile and other for 8p a mile. It is a makeshift arrangement.  One area is completely out of step with another.  This results in very poor transport being provided for children in rural areas.  It does not affect city areas so much.  I would ask the Minister <Col N="64" /> to take a very active interest in CIE's policy for the provision of school transport.</P>
    <P>We appreciate that we are still working with a very inadequate school transport system but CIE's approach to it makes it much more difficult. Their lack of policy, their lack of a proper uniform rate for the minibus service that is being provided on hire to CIE, results in a big number of problems and shortcomings in the school transport service.  This ground has been partly covered by previous speakers.  I would hope that the Minister would see to it in providing this money that sets of conditions are attached.  I would hope that the Minister would ensure that we would have a more streamlined school transport policy from CIE and that it will not be put on a makeshift arrangement depending on an official in the area. That is not good enough.  The rural areas are not given a fair deal.  I would urge the Minister to ensure that there is an improvement.</P>
    <P>CIE lack policy even in the handling of goods on their rail services, This was brought home to me forcibly not too long ago when I attended an auction of lost goods held by CIE.  I saw an item of goods valued at £100 sold for £1.  I regard this as slackness.  The item of goods in question was a valve for a waterworks mains.  That was something which would be difficult to lose. I do not for the life of me know how it could be mislaid because a limited number of people would manufacture this valve and a limited number of people would buy it.  I felt this was very strong evidence of slack handling. This leads to a lack of confidence by the public.</P>
    <P>Now is the time for the Government to insist on sets of conditions when money is being provided.  I say this in the knowledge that my county can benefit very little from the £38 million that is being provided for CIE. We have a right to be concerned. Only recently my county applied for sanction to the Government for a small sum of money in comparison to this.  The sum was around £50,000 to buy land for the provision of an airstrip. In the absence of a proper rail <Col N="65" /> system in County Donegal I would have thought that our county council would have had no difficulty in getting Government approval for the raising of a loan to purchase land and provide an airstrip.  The Government refused sanction to the Donegal County Council to raise a loan for the purchase of that land.  Representatives from County Donegal are asked to come in here and support the raising of this money.  We are entitled to be concerned and ask questions as to how it is going to be spent.</P>
    <P>It is a pity that a greater proportion of this money than £4 million cannot be raised from the European Investment Bank.  The raising of £38 million for CIE will restrict the general public in their borrowings.  God knows, the public's borrowings powers are restricted enough at the moment. I would ask the Minister for clarification on that point.  I only hope that the banks, when they decide to restrict lending, will not say they have lent up the maximum allowed by the Government and that this item of £38 million will go against the public borrowing powers.  I sincerely hope the Government will give more thought to this.  If they are given targets, incentives and directives from the Government they will do a better job.  CIE need the money.  I only hope we will see a healthier transport system as a result of the money being provided.</P>
    <Speaker pid="AustinDeasy" hpid="Mr. Deasy Mr. Deasy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Deasy</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not detain the House but I should like to add my support for this Bill.  In doing so I should like to ask a few questions and make a few observations.  The loss of £8 million in 1972-73 is quite colossal. I note from the Minister's brief that he expects it to be substantially higher in 1973-74.  This must cause considerable concern to the taxpayer. The loss of more than £7½ million on the rail system alone is staggering.  As an ordinary citizen I would never have believed that the whole rail system would have cost £7½ million to run.  I should like if the Minister could outline briefly how we fell into such arrears.  I know that not so many years ago British Railways admitted <Col N="66" /> publicly that they had lost a train&mdash; engine, rolling stock, guards van and so on.  Luckily enough it was not a passenger train.  In their complex system, such a thing is likely to happen. For our small railway system, reduced as it has been in the past six or seven years by cutting off uneconomical lines, to lose £7½ million takes some believing.</P>
      <P>The Government should at this stage seriously consider a provision whereby heavy traffic would by law be taken from the roads and put on the railways, especially container traffic.  The taxpayer is being mulcted on the double.  This heavy traffic is causing serious damage to our main network of roadways.  On the other hand we have trains travelling with a very small amount of goods.  Surely the stage has been reached when this traffic should be compulsorily diverted from the roads to the railways especially because of the staggering losses which I have mentioned. If this cannot be done I feel the public will not tolerate this type of loss on the rail system, and it will increase: £7½ million is bad enough for one year but if it is to increase they just will not tolerate it.  In the event of not being able to channel what is at present going on the roads on to the rails, I feel that we should consider handing back our rail system and CIE generally to private enterprise, of course, putting in clauses to safeguard jobs and also making sure that the essential services are maintained.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to approach this Bill from two stand-points&mdash;first, considering the more limited contents of the Bill, and, secondly, considering it from a more general standpoint: standing back from the Bill itself and analysing it, in a sense, in an institutional context.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>First of all, on the more limited standpoint of the contents of the Bill and what it asks of this House, I should like to ask the Minister why this Bill has developed its own urgency, why it is now needed urgently?  As I understand it, the application made by CIE to the European Investment Bank was one of the first applications made by <Col N="67" /> Ireland to the European Investment Bank.  If I am wrong, I should like the Minister to state when this application was first made by CIE.  At the time the application was made, was it not realised that CIE would require statutory authority to borrow from the European Investment Bank, and was there not a considerable period of time during which statutory authority to borrow from the European Investment Bank might have been requested?</P>
    <P>Has there, therefore, not been considerable negligence in this particular area, in that at the last minute, when the European Investment Bank have made it clear that they will make £4 million available on a long-term loan over the next 20 years, that we scramble together a piece of legislation to give CIE the necessary authority to avail of this loan?  Is this really a very good way of going about this type of activity?</P>
    <P>Secondly&mdash;and this is still on the limited terms of the Bill itself&mdash;this Bill, as Senator West has said, has a considerable financial significance for the State.  It asks that a very large amount of public moneys be available to be borrowed by CIE by raising the ceiling of their borrowing power.  This provision, extending so substantially the borrowing power of CIE, has come before the Dáil and the Seanad with an aura of urgency, and therefore, I would maintain, is not being given the sort of consideration it merits.</P>
    <P>I have been present for some of the debate this afternoon, not all of it, and I have listened with great interest to the contributions of my colleagues. I have in particular been impressed with the detailed contribution of Senator West, who has obviously done a lot of homework on this Bill.  I seconded his motion earlier this afternoon that the motion on the McKinsey Report be taken in conjunction with this Bill.  I was&mdash;and I put it deliberately in this language&mdash;horrified that the excuse given by the Leader of the House for not taking the McKinsey Report motion was that the Minister did not consider it to be &ldquo;convenient&rdquo;. That was the phrase used&mdash;it was not &ldquo;convenient for the Minister&rdquo;<Col N="68" /> to take the McKinsey Report motion with this Bill.  Yet the Minister himself in his Second Reading speech on this Bill referred to and argued from the McKinsey Report. He maintains, in fact, that part of the reason for this Bill is because CIE are implementing some of the recommendations of the McKinsey Report.</P>
    <P>Then why was it not convenient for the Seanad to have this motion taken with the Transport Bill and so discuss the merits of the McKinsey Report directly rather than in a general sense on the Second Reading of the Bill? I think it is not satisfactory that the Minister would deem it inconvenient and that the House would be satisfied that it was inconvenient to the Minister, when the Minister himself is pleading the McKinsey Report as part of the agreement for the Bill itself!</P>
    <P>As I say, Senators have addressed themselves to the merits of this Transport Bill and in doing so have commented on the role of CIE and on their position in the State.  Their comments have been wide-ranging and very interesting.  They have ranged from economic assessments to the sort of social assessment by Senator Harte, including localised comments on the role of CIE.  I would maintain that this has been interesting from an academic point of view but not very useful.  The role of the Seanad has been extremely limited in relation to this particular Bill and to Bills of this sort.</P>
    <P>The Bill, if it is to be meaningfully discussed at all, would require some knowledge on our part of the criteria by which we should judge CIE.  This brings me to the second standpoint with which I view this Bill&mdash;from the institutional standpoint.  We do not know by what criteria to judge CIE because the criteria have never been set out by which we will judge any of the State-sponsored bodies, including CIE.  We do not know whether CIE should try to make a profit.  I would agree with Senator Deasy: it seems appalling that CIE can amass such a substantial loss&mdash;over £7 million&mdash;but have we ever required them to make a profit?  Do we want CIE to run at a profit or do we want them to provide <Col N="69" /> a social service?  Do we see it as a service to the community, to run at a loss in providing such service with the State subsidising them and authorising them to borrow from the European Investment Bank or other sources in order to provide this widespread service at that loss, which we have costed in community terms?</P>
    <P>This is the sort of debate which cannot at the moment get off the ground because the criteria by which we ought to judge this particular State-sponsored body and State-sponsored bodies in general have not been determined by us as a State in any way.  We have allowed a very important section of our economic and social life to be controlled and run by these State-sponsored bodies.  I do not think this is a good thing in terms of the Irish economy.  It is a bad thing that there is no overall long-term thinking on this, that these State-sponsored bodies have been created in a haphazard fashion from time to time when it suited the particular industry, or a particular sector of Irish life.  The composition of these State-sponsored bodies varies from one to the other.  The way in which they are controlled varies from one to the other and, as I say, we have no criteria by which to judge them, or no long-term attitude of the State towards these public enterprises.</P>
    <P>Following on this institutional argument, it is, in my view, not worthwhile as an exercise for the Seanad to debate in a subjective, off-the-cuff manner a Bill like this Transport Bill. It is not adequate, not satisfactory. What we must press for, if we are to fulfil a parliamentary function, is for the implementation rapidly of this promised committee on State-sponsored bodies.  It would make a great difference to how the Seanad ultimately considered this Bill if we had a report from a committee on State-sponsored bodies, which committee could have examined it in detail without any aura of urgency.  As I have tried to maintain, the aura of urgency is in any case artificial.  I await the Minister's explanation as to why this Bill has come so late in the day and why, as I say, it is therefore being <Col N="70" /> described as one which must be passed quickly by the two Houses of the Oireachtas.</P>
    <P>This Bill could have been submitted to a committee on State-sponsored bodies if we had such a committee. That committee could have called for independent expertise, could have determined what should be the criteria by which we judge the performance of CIE, could have reported in detail to both Houses of the Oireachtas.  Then we as Members of the Seanad would have had the benefit of that analysis, of that information, the benefit of the expertise of individual members of the committee, some of whom would be from the Seanad, and we could have a much more constructive debate as a consequence.</P>
    <P>That institutional apparatus is extremely urgent when we see that the pattern of Bills which come up in relation to State-sponsored bodies is that they simply ask for more money as a grant, or for more potential money in the sense of more borrowing capacity. This is the sort of Bill which has come up again and again before the Seanad in the last session and now in this session, in relation to this and other state enterprises.</P>
    <P>On a second footing this Bill is entirely unsatisfactory from our point of view because it stems from the fact that, quoting from the Minister's Second Reading Speech:</P>
    <P>The immediate need for the present Bill is to enable CIE to take up a loan of £4 million which has been approved by the European Investment Bank for a term of 20 years at a proposed rate of interest of 8¾ per cent.</P>
    <P>In order to assess the implications of that we would really want to know what other applications have been made by Ireland to the European Investment Bank, who had decided on the priority of these applications, what moneys could be available from the European Investment Bank&mdash;this sort of information.</P>
    <P>If this Bill had been considered as having a European dimension by the fact that an application had been made by CIE, and that it was now looking <Col N="71" /> for statutory authority to borrow from the European Investment Bank, then the Bill could have been referred to the Joint Committee on European Affairs.  That committee could examine this European dimension; that committee could look at the role of the European Investment Bank about which I am going to speak in a moment; that committee could draw the attention of both Houses of the Oireachtas to this whole aspect of applying for long-term loans to the European Investment Bank and of the potential there for Ireland.  It could be a source of real regional development apart altogether from the European Community agreeing on a regional policy and a regional development fund.</P>
    <P>This European Investment Bank has enormous potential for Ireland.  It has an enormous potential for applications by public enterprises and by private enterprise.  It is at the moment almost unknown to Members of the Oireachtas.  It is a body about which we must do long-term thinking and long-term planning.  I would submit we must do it in the Joint Committee on European Affairs and in the open forum of both Houses of the Parliament; because the nature of applications to the European Investment Bank and the types of applications are very broad.  We must determine what are our own priorities.  This point will become clearer when I outline the applications that have been made and granted to Ireland already during 1973, and in the light of the fact that during 1974 a substantially larger fund of money will be available.  Still more would be available if we had appropriate applications to the European Investment Bank for further loans. We have never really considered this from the viewpoint of establishing our policy.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am sorry to intervene here.  There is no question that the particular loan being sought from the European Investment Bank is relevant to the discussion on this Bill on Second Stage, but to go into detail about other possible applications <Col N="72" /> or other actual applications would be to go beyond the scope of the Bill.  It would be wrong to do other than make a passing reference to them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not propose to go into great detail, in fact it would take me&mdash;&mdash;</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator has already gone into some detail.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I can make my point relevant to the terms of the Bill.  It is that before we pass this Bill, and before we authorise CIE to accept this loan from the European Investment Bank, we ought to know the framework in which it is being done, whether this is a loan which ought to get priority from Ireland.  In other words, the question is whether we should approve this particular Transport Bill with the provision in it which authorises CIE to borrow specifically that £4 million from the European Investment Bank and giving general power to borrow in a European currency.  If the Cathaoirleach will bear with me&mdash;I do not intend to be very long on this&mdash;I am trying to make the point that if we are to consider this aspect of the Transport Bill meaningfully, we can only do it in terms of the types of applications which have been made and authorised from Ireland&mdash;the list is brief&mdash;and whether we want to see CIE included in this way in that list, and what our overall policy on that is.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>For example, during the year 1973 the bank has already awarded roughly £12 million to Ireland.  It is revelant to see in what way these loans, because they are all long-term loans, have been distributed.  The first loan was to the Sugar Company, another State-sponsored body, for £2.8 million to modernise their factories.  The second loan was to the Department of Posts and Telegraphs, of the larger sum of £7.5 million, for modernisation of our telephone system; and the third loan was to the Agricultural Credit Corporation, of £800,000 in order to relend that sum to the Irish <Col N="73" /> Agricultural Wholesalers' Society to establish a factory in Cork for the manufacture of protein concentrates.</P>
    <P>As the Cathaoirleach has pointed out, these matters are not strictly relevant to this particular application except in so far as they illustrate that these are the types of application which Ireland is making at the moment to the European Investment Bank.  It is a similar application which CIE, under the authority of this Transport Bill, want to avail of since it has been approved by the European Investment Bank.  We, as a House of the Oireachtas, are not in a position to have the information for an overall view of whether we approve of these four public enterprises getting this particular money in preference to other possible applicants.  At the moment the applicants can come from these public enterprises or indeed from private industry and they are channelled through the Department of Finance so that there is that sort of governmental co-ordination of applications.  But they should also be a matter of policy which would be assessed and reviewed in Parliament. It is an area which Members of the Oireachtas ought to have considered in depth.  In my view they could not do this unless preliminary homework is done in committee session, with the possibility of getting expert information on it; with the possibility of interviewing various members of these bodies and the officials concerned in the making of these applications in order to determine what should be our priorities.</P>
    <P>Should the priority be, in this case, to enable CIE to get &ldquo;Supertrains&rdquo;, or should it be some other project like the development of small industries in the west of Ireland to boil it down to that?  Is it appropriate to make an application to the European Investment Bank for the modernisation of CIE?  I think that when we are faced with this type of Bill, which simply requests greater borrowing power and allows the Government to increase the amount by which it will guarantee loans to CIE, and when the Bill is considered in a single day in each House of the Oireachtas because of its &ldquo;urgency&rdquo;, <Col N="74" /> we reduce our parliamentary process to its most inadequate point.  We reduce it to subjective, ill-informed comments by individual Senators on how they feel that CIE may or may not be operating, without any criteria by which to judge it properly because these criteria have never been set out or accepted.  The debate takes place without adequate back-up information to assess both the role of CIE, as a State-sponsored body and the implications of this application to the European Investment Bank and the priorities we should have set out in that.</P>
    <P>This to me is a rather depressing exercise.  I hope that it is an exercise that we will not carry on much longer in our parliamentary life.  I hope that we will evolve the sort of institutional control that will make Parliament more relevant to considering this type of Bill and which will make the type of questions asked when the Bill comes for debate on the floor of the House much more searching.  We are not asking sufficiently searching questions because we do not have the back-up information to do it.  It is not enough to speak off the cuff and to express a view on it.  This is not adequate.  It is not scientific.  It is not constructive.  It is not worth the time spent, and the whole amount of administrative machinery which is involved in a parliamentary process.  I urge those Members, especially on the Government side of the House, who are in a position to do so, to have the committee on State-sponsored bodies established at the earliest possible opportunity and also I would urge the Minister, when he has a Bill of this nature to be prepared.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I must intervene again.  The Senator is arguing for a change in procedure when dealing with a matter under the current procedure which is laid down. The House is obliged to deal with this Bill according to the procedure which is laid down.  It is not appropriate to discuss changes in that procedure while we are dealing with this Bill.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the Cathaoirleach's ruling on that point.  I <Col N="75" /> have, in fact, made the point that I wanted to make within the limits&mdash; and sometimes obvious straying outside the limits&mdash;of a Second Reading debate.  I end by referring to the specific question which I asked, and on which I should like a specific answer from the Minister, as to when the original application by CIE was made to the European Investment Bank and how long they might have had to seek this statutory authority to borrow?  In other words, whether, in fact, there was a necessity for this to become a rather urgent matter rather than one that could have been taken at more leisure in the parliamentary process.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>I have some sympathy for the Minister who comes in with a simple Bill to ask the Seanad to give him the authority to borrow from the European Investment Bank.  The reason I have sympathy for him is this.  In my opinion, Senator Robinson has been completely out of order over the last quarter-of-an-hour.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator is casting a reflection on the Chair's handling of the procedure.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>This is not casting any reflection on the Cathaoirleach; it is merely pointing out the fact that he is too much of a gentleman to take the lady to task over what she has said in the last half-hour.  I want to say that Senator Robinson is a very charming lady with a magnificent brain.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>However, the &ldquo;cloud cuckooland&rdquo; that she has been exploring over the last half-hour has nothing at all to do with this simple Bill before us.  If we are going to relate borrowing for CIE to borrowing for every other little thing for which the Government seek money, and if everybody here in this chamber is going to speak at length on these matters, the Minister will not get his Bill in a month, never mind getting it in one evening.  While as an academic discussion it might be useful, we have not time to listen to it <Col N="76" /> and its relevance at this particular time is nil.</P>
    <P>I am in agreement with the provisions of the Bill as proposed by the Minister.  I could spend a long time here telling the Minister about the deficiencies of the service provided by CIE.  I could talk for a long time about the type of train that goes to Mayo, and the times and the delays and all the other things that go with it, but I am not going to bore the people here this evening with the long recital of the many bizarre events that happened over a considerable time. Some people have mentioned the fact that the heavy traffic must be put off the roads and on to the rails.  I agree entirely with this because if we are going to have the juggernauts that we see coming in from Europe at the moment carried on our road system, we will not have a road system in the foreseeable future.  Compared to the amount of money that would be needed to give us a road system capable of carrying this type of traffic, the sum the Minister is seeking on behalf of CIE is a mere bagatelle.</P>
    <P>The CIE rail services are so necessary that they must be brought to the highest possible level in the shortest possible time.  This is something about which the Minister should concern himself.  Otherwise, as I said earlier, the roads will not be able to carry the traffic in the future.  I was listening attentively to Senator MacGowan talking about the deficiencies in the services to Donegal and other places.  I want to tell Senator MacGowan&mdash;I do not know if he is here at the moment&mdash;that it was a Fianna Fáil Government that closed down the rail services, not alone in Donegal but everywhere else throughout the country.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JackGarrett" hpid="Mr. Garrett Mr. Garrett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garrett</NameTxt>
      <P>That is because they were in so long.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>They were in too long. One of the reasons why they are out now is because they closed them.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JackGarrett" hpid="Mr. Garrett Mr. Garrett">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Garrett</NameTxt>
      <P>Do not worry.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDLyons" hpid="Mr. Lyons Mr. Lyons">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Lyons</NameTxt>
      <P>However, this is a fact of life.  Maybe, on the advice they had at the time and in the circumstances at that time, this appeared to be the <Col N="77" /> proper thing to do.  Forward planning is necessary at this stage, because we have arrived at a situation now where we have something imposed on us.  The oil crisis has opened our eyes at every level, from Government level right down to the man in the street, to the dangers of having all our eggs in one basket and the dangers that exist if we do not have a diversified transport system.  Maybe it is the best thing that ever happened.  Everybody will now be concerned about the future.  As Senator Robinson pointed out in her speech, various studies may be necessary to evaluate what type of transport is necessary in the short term and what the targets should be for the long term. In the long term we are going to be faced with situations of which we have no cognisance at this point in time. There should be a study made&mdash;I agree with Senator Robinson thus far&mdash;of the complete picture of transport now and 20 years hence.  The time to do that is now.</P>
      <P>I do not know whether it is possible to get other loans or EEC grants for the study of transport problems.  If it is possible, now is the time to do it. Asking the Minister, who is just about a year in office, to suddenly evolve a new system of transport, when the existing system has been running down for years and to solve all our problems is asking for too much.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I believe that if we could get the type of &ldquo;super-eggheads&rdquo; who would evaluate the whole situation, as Senator Robinson envisaged, we would not be able to pay them enough.  I know the Minister wants to get away and I do not wish to delay him.  I shall be writing to him about the situation <i>vis-á-vis</i> rail transport for west Mayo&mdash;the delays, the carriages that are put on the trains as apart from the &ldquo;Supertrains,&rdquo;&mdash;the fact that up to a very short time ago it was possible to get a train at Westland Row to travel to the west of Ireland at 8.10 p.m. in the evening. This was a mail train with one or two passenger coaches attached if necessary.  That mail train still travels to the west of Ireland but there is no passenger coach on it.  Some other <Col N="78" /> Members of the Oireachtas and I who often miss the first train would like to know that this late train was available.</P>
    <P>I would also refer to the difficulty of getting from the centre of the city to Heuston Station.  If there are road repairs going on&mdash;and they are nearly always going on&mdash;along the quays anybody who tries to get a bus to take him to the station on time will find that he is delayed.</P>
    <P>It is imperative&mdash;I am sorry to say this because it might sound parochial to other Senators&mdash;that when a mail train travels to the west of Ireland on a particular evening there should be no great problem in putting on a passenger coach or two.  I hope this will be done as soon as possible.</P>
    <P>The Seanad are prepared to give the Minister the Bill.  We hope that in the final analysis CIE will break even, or make a profit, but in the present circumstances, as we see it at the moment with the cost of fuel escalating beyond anything ever thought of a few months ago this is certainly not possible.  Any money that is expended over and above that which is necessary to make CIE break even is good social spending and very necessary in giving to the people in outlying areas a service which they need and to which they are entitled.  Roads are already overcrowded and unable to take the present heavy traffic.  Anybody driving out of Dublin behind one of the juggernauts and trying to pass it out on the type of road we have will know what I am talking about.</P>
    <P>The Minister is not a miracle worker. The rolling stock is old.  Most of it is outdated and to find the millions necessary to bring it up to modern standards is going to be a mighty problem.  I want the Minister to take into consideration that the rail service must be brought up to the highest standard.  In Japan at the moment some trains travel at 200 miles an hour.  They are express trains.  The railway system here will never in our time be able to take trains doing 200 miles an hour.  The modern idea of welding rails does away with all the old bolts and shackles that we had previously.  The improvement must be <Col N="79" /> started and the sooner it is started the better.</P>
    <Speaker pid="ThomasAMartin" hpid="Dr. Martin Dr. Martin">
      <NameTxt>Dr. Martin</NameTxt>
      <P>I shall be very brief.  I shall begin by noting the extraordinary rhetorical skill with which Senator Lyons set out by consigning Senator Robinson to &ldquo;cloud cuckoo-land&rdquo; because she was dealing with an overall principle and how in the course of his own speech&mdash;because, I think, of the inherent honesty of the man himself &mdash;he found himself crying out in almost similar terms for an overall plan for transport and the environment and finally seeking and finding sanctuary in the coach attached to the mail train on the way back to Mayo.  That progress of Senator Lyons' speech highlights the manifold difficulties that face a Minister for Transport and Power in dealing with the extraordinarily complex problem of a transport system in Ireland today.</P>
      <P>We have seen in the course of the debate today elements of the transport system as varied and farflung as Senator Quinlan's well-placed nostalgia for the West Clare Railway of Percy French fame, and Senator Deasy's insistence on the importance of transferring to the rails a great deal of the container traffic which at the moment is threatening our entire road transport system.  That is of enormous importance.</P>
      <P>It is also of importance that the Minister has to face the fact that there our cities are being very seriously threatened.  The buses going into the centre of the city bring excessive weight on the roads.  Enormous pollution of the air is involved.  Buses have to struggle through traffic while very often one-passenger-car traffic clutters up the centres of our cities.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Any Minister for Transport and Power seeking moneys for the improvement of rail and road transport will have to come to terms with the enormous problem in the cities.  This has been mentioned already.  He should even consider the possibility of a Sunday ban on driving which they have had in Holland and with which they are very pleased.  Apparently in Holland they go out on their bicycles <Col N="80" /> on Sundays and the whole environment is cleansed.  I know the Mass-going population would have difficulty, but the ban could start from 12 o'clock onwards.  This would also help in many ancillary ways particularly in regard to what we call the power crisis at the moment.</P>
    <P>The problem that was raised by Senator Robinson, and afterwards implicitly by Senator Lyons, relates to the fact that transport and power as an area of activity involve many other areas of our entire lifestyle.  Much has been said recently about the quality of Irish life and concern has been expressed about it.  The quality of Irish life was seen largely in moral terms when applied to the Family Planning Bill.  The quality of Irish life involves the very air we breathe, the roads and the streets we walk on, and they are increasingly being polluted by noise, litter and excessive traffic.  Edmund Burke has said that if we are to love our country our country must first be beautiful.  We have a beautiful country, but it is being enormously polluted.  One of the agents in this is obviously the vehicle, the internal combustion engine, which plays such a large part in the whole problem facing the Minister for Transport and Power at present.</P>
    <P>When Senator Lyons and Senator Robinson agree to this Bill we can all agree to it, but it is unsatisfactory to agree to this loan.  We would rather know where the money is going.  We are rather like somebody with a suitcase on which there is one label, &ldquo;London&rdquo;: we know we are going as far as London.  After that another label &ldquo;Paris&rdquo; goes on and we are going as far as Paris.  Then another label may indicate that we are going to come back to Sheffield, and yet another label goes on.  In other words, the legal enactments involved seem to me to be similar to the slapping of a label on to some sort of State coach the destination of which has not been decided on.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson suggested that a way out would be to establish a Committee on State-sponsored Bodies so that we could get an overall view. I would have a different kind of view.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="81" /> It would be that it is time this country, like the North of Ireland and England, should have a Minister for the Environment.  It seems to me that a concern for the environment should dominate all other considerations or, if we like to use that other phrase, the quality of Irish life.  If we had that we could reverse an unfortunate trend which is taking place in Irish society. Everybody who has had anything to do with the Civil Service knows about that if one wants to get anything out of any Department in this country that Department has to apply to the Department of Finance.  The money is available there.  The Department of Finance seems to exercise spiritual and mercenary lordship over everything that is done.</P>
    <P>I should like to see a situation in the future where the Minister for Transport and Power would use his influence and good offices in regard to environmental matters.  I doubt if he will disagree with me on this. I should love to see that every enactment in the future that concerns transport, power or industry would ultimately have to be submitted to a Minister for the Environment.  He should be somebody who would have not just a mere grip on the pursestrings but somebody who would have an appreciation of the beauty of our country and of its potentialities&mdash;from the West Clare railway <i>á la</i> Percy French down to that coach attached to the mail train which would take Senator Lyons back in time to meet his constituents in Mayo after his triumphs here in the Seanad.</P>
    <P>Some such type of all-embracing idea would give meaning to this enactment we are going to vote on here today.  It would give us a sense of purpose as people.  One does not quite get that sense of purpose from the manner in which people are approaching this sort of <i>ad hoc</i> motion today.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JoeJMcCartin" hpid="Mr. McCartin Mr. McCartin">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McCartin</NameTxt>
      <P>I will be very brief because I know the field has been widely covered and I do not want to go over ground that has already been covered by other Senators.  A constructive discussion cannot take place in the House on a subject such as <Col N="82" /> CIE and the raising of a loan without a broader discussion on many aspects of the work done by CIE.  It is necessary to have a constructive debate on two or three various aspects of CIE.  I should like to have a discussion on the social aspect of CIE. Those parts of the service which can be regarded as a social service should be segregated from the rest and evaluated on their social advantages. There are sections of CIE which should fit into the category of a business that is economically viable, or ought to be.  In addition, there is the section which is not an economic proposition but for which there is no alternative.</P>
      <P>The Dublin city bus services, school transport and road transport in rural Ireland would all fit into the social category.  We could decide on the areas making a loss, and if a loss were justified we could decide on how far it ought to go.  CIE are doing a very good job.  They are providing a social service and there is no obvious replacement for the company.  The railway should be improved and maintained. It is a pity that so many of them were not only closed down but torn up and sold for scrap when they could have been left where they were. They might have suited changing economic needs in years to come.</P>
      <P>I recall the fight put up by Senator Martin's family in Ballinamore to save the railway.  At the time it was not economically viable but if left there it could have fulfilled a useful role in the future.  Road haulage is a part of CIE.  I have no figures for this separately, but I should like to know the position in regard to this aspect of CIE.  If this part of CIE were not protected by legislation as things are at present it could not compete with private enterprise.  If this is so, is it a good policy to maintain this part of CIE to the disadvantage of industry in many areas?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Many small industries are forced to provide transport of their own because they cannot employ local contractors because haulage plates are very limited.  That transport is taking up executive time, brains and investment in small companies which can illafford <Col N="83" /> to spend the money.  It would be better if they could give this work to local contractors.  Instead, those people are prohibited by law from doing this sort of work because the road haulage section of CIE must be protected according to Government policy.  I can see no social or economic reason for keeping that section of CIE in existence if it cannot compete openly.</P>
    <P>This point should be examined seriously in the future.  In many cases companies are forced to keep seven or eight lorries.  Even though CIE can charge double the rates of a private haulier, they can still show a loss.  On the other hand, the private haulier can be the richest man in the locality although he is working at half the rates charged by CIE.  A reappraisal of this situation need not mean a loss in jobs.  The work could be more efficiently and economically done.  This would suit the smaller industries in my area better than the system used by CIE, and would be a relief to the State in general.</P>
    <P>I should like the Minister to give serious consideration to this point.</P>
    <Speaker pid="BernardCowen" hpid="Mr. Cowen Mr. Cowen">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cowen</NameTxt>
      <P>I do not intend to detain the Minister too long.  I welcome this Bill mainly because we all realise that CIE will not survive unless they are strongly subsidised.  The purpose of this Bill is to extend their borrowing powers for capital purposes. As Senator Robinson stated, we know so little about CIE that it is doubtful if it would serve any purpose for any Senator to examine in detail the actual workings of CIE.  It is essential to maintain a public transport system.  The railway service is vastly improved and is catering for many more passengers.  Because of the present fuel crisis a great many more people will travel by train in the future.  I ask the Minister to channel through his office a directive to the management of CIE instructing them to improve the passenger services to meet the needs of the greater number of passengers.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The road freight service is the only sector within CIE which has paid <Col N="84" /> dividends during the year 1972-73. There are conflicting views in regard to this sector.  I agree with Senator McGowan that CIE are not doing an effective job in regard to this sector. There was a small profit of £22,000 in 1972-73 against a loss of £134,000 in 1971-72.  This is a significant point and shows a vast improvement over a period of 12 months.  On that score alone the Minister can see that a greater effort should be made to ensure that this sector is modernised. Senator McGowan pointed out that he did not see any CIE freight service lorries on the road when he travelled up to Dublin today though he passed many of the trucks which are now converging on Ireland from Europe. Against that, there is the argument by Senator McCartin that the main reason why this sector is doing any good is that it is protected.  I go on facts and figures.  Irrespective of what is stated in regard to private hauliers, there is need for vast improvement from CIE.</P>
    <P>It was brought to my notice recently by a man who had been employed with CIE for a period of 35 years that he had the paltry sum of £1.88p pension per week.  When he retired at 65 years of age he had something in the region of £2 5s. per week.  When he attained 70 years and received the old age pension this pension was reduced to £1 2s 6d and his present rate of pension is £1.88p.  The Minister should do something to remedy that situation.  It is desperate that a man who was employed by CIE for 35 of the best years of his life should receive a paltry sum of £1.88p pension.  I sincerely ask the Minister to look into this aspect of CIE pension schemes.</P>
    <P>I just want to say that I welcome the Bill on the basis that it will pour money into CIE to develop the social service that we cannot and I hope will never be without.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I will not detain the Minister very long.  I wish to support the general views of those who have suggested that a discussion on transport should be a general discussion on the role of transport in society.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>
      <Col N="85" /> First of all, in relation to transport, CIE and Ministers for Transport and Power have come under heavy onslaught for certain reasons.  They have come under onslaught because the operations for which they are responsible are not making money.  In an article in <i>New Society</i> in 1970, which studied transport systems in most of the modernised, if one may use that term, countries of the world, it was pointed out that one country was in fact making a profit on such systems.</P>
    <P>Who in fact benefits and who in fact does not benefit by having an adequate and well financed public transport system?  The blind cannot drive.  The very old cannot drive.  The people who are below driving age cannot drive.  There are in our society a number of significant minorities who have no great public volume, if they perhaps have a voice, in making their case for having an adequate public transport system.  For that reason the allocaton of moneys for an efficient transport system should not be judged on the criteria of market economy. In fact, the savage, historic judgment of those people who have said that the railways must make money and that buses must make money has driven these voiceless minorities into their homes and deprived them of transport.  What we should do is this. We should not be ashamed at all. We should say we will not have transport policy dictated by the norms of private enterprise economy.  We will have a transport system which will serve social necessity.  This means that if at any time the Minister says &ldquo;We have made a loss in public transport&rdquo; I, for one, will not be at all unhappy.</P>
    <P>The minorities of whom I speak&mdash; the people who are too ill to drive, the people who do not qualify for a licence by reason of age, blindness or some other disability&mdash;are entitled to the finest of transport, if we believe in a humanitarian society.  The mistaken notion of translating a private enterprise economy into the public utility service has resulted in the most savage cutting back of infrastructure in regions where it was most demanded.</P>
    <P>
      <Col N="86" /> It is whimsical to speak of the West Clare railway in some respects.  I admire people who like to listen to Percy French.  I have studied the mounds of fish carried on the railways in Connemara to the London market in the last century.  They are far larger than the fish being transported to the London market in the present century, all because of a railway system.  Therefore, I urge the Minister to increase his borrowing power.  He has noted with caution that it will be with the sanction of the Minister for Finance that he will extend the area of his borrowing to the European Investment Bank for example.</P>
    <P>This country has suffered a savage blow from the people who ravaged the railways.  The Beechings had their counterparts in this island.  I am in a charitable mood and I will not name them.  They decided that transport must be efficient at all costs.  Transport is efficient in two respects.  It is efficient when it serves all of the public well, including the most voiceless minorities of the public&mdash;the people who are too old either to get a licence or to drive a car, the people who are too young and the people who are unable to drive a car.  Transport is also justifiable and efficient when it serves the infrastructure well. The attempt at regionalisation being made at present through the Industrial Development Authority, through various agencies and through the new grant which has been allocated to Muintir na Tíre would be very much easier if the country's railways had not been so savagely struck down. Those short-term plan people in the Beeching fashion, who imagined that the best way to advance an economy was to relate its total results to a particular section of society and that you could achieve efficiency by just simply knocking off lines, were stupid and ill-informed.  This was extremely bad economics.  We may find ourselves spending more on road transport when we could have saved a great deal if we had saved our railway lines.  More than that we destroyed a way of life.</P>
    <P>Now it is my turn, perhaps, if I <Col N="87" /> might be allowed a minor whimsical note.  There were people who sometimes came to market by train when it stopped in almost inaccessible places.  The Fianna Fáil Government of the day said that all of these transport facilities would be replaced by bus facilities.  Women all over rural Ireland who used to travel carrying various commodities, from eggs to daffodils, to markets in different towns were suddenly driven to their homes and told to stay at home because that promise was never fulfilled.</P>
    <P>Let us be perfectly clear.  Certainly the Minister's borrowing powers should be extended to borrow; certainly we should spend more on transport; but never should a transport policy be evaluated by strict economic criteria. If one day the Minister comes back in here and if by some strange miracle I am here and he says &ldquo;I have made a fantastic loss on transport, but I have brought a whole host of people into the social engagement of life&rdquo; he will be applauded by me at least. For that reason I suggest, echoing as I said, at secondhand, views put far more concisely by Dickinson in an article in <i>New Society</i> in 1970, the fact that the criteria for the judgment of a transport policy are not private enterprise criteria but social policy criteria.</P>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. P. Barry) Peter Barry">
      <NameTxt>Minister for Transport and Power (Mr. P. Barry)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to thank the Seanad for the hearing they gave this Bill today and for their contributions to it.  I would not find myself greatly disagreeing with the last speaker when he said that it was not necessary on strict economic grounds that a transport system should make a profit.  Apart from the fact that it increased the morale of people employed in CIE, the greatest value of the sales gimmick with the appalling title of &ldquo;The Great Train Robbery&rdquo; was that it brought people out, made them travel, move around and mix amongst other people.  That was a tremendous social benefit to the country as a whole.  There is understandably some confusion here and in other places as to what my role is in regard <Col N="88" /> to transport.  There were some extremely intelligent and well argued suggestions here today about the relationship between public transport and the car, parking in cities and the construction of motorways for cars.  As Senator West pointed out, there is evidence in the United States the more superhighways that are built the more cars appear to overwhelm them. I should make it clear that such matters are not my function.  These are matters strictly for the Minister for Local Government.  There is an overlapping of the Departments here.</P>
      <P>In reply to a point raised by Senator West, we presented to the Government, sometime last month, a proposal for Dublin city traffic which embraced the points he made.  It included a new bridge over the Liffey and the development of the rail commuter services.  This was an effort between CIE, the Department of Transport and Power, the Department of Local Government and Dublin Corporation to find some solution to the congestion in Dublin's streets.  It is in the interests of these four bodies to come together and see how this problem can be solved.  I hope the studies conducted by An Foras Forbartha will result in some easing of the congestion in Dublin city.</P>
      <P>A number of Senators made the point that it was not sufficiently clear what the money being borrowed by CIE from the European Investment Bank was for.  In my brief I said that it was for the replacement of antiquated road and rail facilities, the modernisation and improvement of equipment, terminals and premises and the improvement of staff amenities, provision of modernised mainline rail operations to provide fast and efficient passenger and goods services and for the development of the Dublin rail commuter services.  These are broadly the heads under which the money will be spent.  Those people who are looking for various improvements in the operation of CIE would be catered for under that.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>A suggestion was made by Senator Dolan and others representing the north and north-west, who have not got a rail service, that the money now <Col N="89" /> proposed to be spent by CIE in the modernisation of the railways should be proportionately distributed to the roads in their areas so that there would be better roads to bring people to the centres of population.  That is again the function of the Department of Local Government.  Money raised by CIE could not be spent on roads.</P>
    <P>Senator Dolan also said that good communications are essential to attract industries.  I accept that point of view.  As Minister for Transport and Power, CIE are one of my responsibilities, and I can say that no other lines will be closed.  It is unfair to criticise those who closed the lines ten to 15 years ago because then there was not the volume of traffic on the roads.  There was not then&mdash;and we are probably very conscious of this at the moment because of the fuel crisis&mdash;the same necessity to carry large volumes of people and goods at the cheapest rate from one point to another.</P>
    <P>Reference was made by Senators to the fuel crisis and the possibility that this may help CIE.  I must point out that CIE are subject to the increases in the cost of fuel as well as the ordinary private individual.  They cannot shove aside costs of this nature.  There are only two sources from which CIE can get their money, that is, either by increased fares or by Government subsidy.  We&mdash;that is the Dáil and Seanad and I as Minister will have to make up our minds, annually maybe, as to how the expenses of running CIE should be apportioned between those who use CIE and the taxpayers in general. The year before last CIE operated at a loss.  This was because they had applied to the National Prices Commission in July, 1972, for an increase in fares which they did not in fact receive until 1973.  This meant that, in spite of inflation, they had to wait a full year before getting an increase. The Exchequer had to make good the losses and that, in turn, had to be passed on to the taxpayers in general. That is a matter which will have to be decided by me primarily and by the Government.  It would then become part of budgetary policy to <Col N="90" /> decide by how much we were willing to subsidise the railways, how much people who use bus and train services should be asked to pay and how much the taxpayer in general should subsidise.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson referred to the statement by the Leader of the House that it was not convenient for me to discuss the McKinsey Report here this evening.  When I said that to the Leader of the House today I did not mean in any way to be discourteous to the Seanad or to indicate that I was unwilling to discuss the McKinsey Report with the Seanad.  I said in my speech:</P>
    <P>CIE, on the basis of the general recommendations of the consultants, have been developing specific plans for the rationalisation of main line railway operations and improvements in operating practices which will involve <i>inter alia</i> increased capital investment in modernising terminals, rolling-stock, track and signalling.  These plans are at present under examination and I hope to secure the early approval of the Government for CIE to proceed on the lines proposed.</P>
    <P>My point was that it would not be right for me to discuss with the Seanad something the Government are at present considering until I had got the Government's decision on that. For that reason I asked Senator O'Higgins not to include the motion on the McKinsey Report in this discussion today.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I thank the Minister for the information he has given. Might it not be of value to the Government in coming to a decision to have the benefit of a debate in the Seanad and have the views of Senators on the McKinsey Report before the decision is taken?  What point is there in having a debate afterwards?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I think it is generally done the reverse way.  I introduce a Bill here with the approval of the Government.  The discussion then is on what the Government propose.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Col N="91" />
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept the Minister's explanation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="TimothyWest" hpid="Dr. West Dr. West">
      <NameTxt>Dr. West</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept what the Minister says but it is not the way motions are dealt with in the Seanad.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>I accept that, but when the Government are on the point of coming to a decision about it, I think that makes a difference.</P>
      <P>In an inflationary situation the losses in CIE will of course continue. If CIE did not try to modernise and improve their position, the forecast of their losses in the early 1980s would be phenomenal.  Senator Deasy, Senator Markey and Senator McCartin are appalled at what the losses are now.  But where 64 per cent of the company's outlay is in wages, you can see that there is inflation every year.  Unless there is increased Government subvention to the company or an increase in fares, then there are bound to be increased losses every year.</P>
      <P>A number of Senators made the point, Senator West included, that the Government will be not able under the EEC regulations to give this blanket subsidy to CIE and that it will be easier for the public to see exactly where the money is being spent and for what reason it is given.  This might be useful.  The Government must in future break down their subsidy to CIE under the headings of (1) payments in respect of public service obligations borne by the railways&mdash; that is regulation 1191/69; (2) payments in respect of burdens borne by CIE not borne by other transport undertakings&mdash;that is the normalisation of accounts, regulation 1192/69; and, (3), aids by the State in respect of (a) infrastructure costs, (b) public service obligations other than those covered by regulations 1191/69 and (c) the remaining deficit of CIE.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The last point&mdash;(c) of No. 3&mdash; is a let-out for the Government and will enable them make up the balance of whatever CIE lose.  However that will probably be phased out in the years to come and another regulation introduced to more tightly control the amount of money the <Col N="92" /> Government can provide for public transport.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelDHiggins" hpid="Mr. M.D. Higgins Mr. M.D. Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.D. Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>As a social utility.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Maybe that.  I cannot foresee what will happen but that is possible.</P>
      <P>Senator Moynihan made the point that in many people's minds rationalisation is equated to redundancy, and there is no doubt that that is so.  He made the point also that the management structure of CIE was inefficient, overloaded and top heavy.  In fact, the McKinsey Report found that CIE were well managed.  I assure the House, and Senator Moynihan in particular, that if rationalisation in CIE leads to redundancy, it will be, I hope, by normal wastage over the years and it certainly will be done only in consultation with the trade unions. There will be full agreement between the trade unions and the management on any redundancies that may take place.</P>
      <P>It is obvious that signalling will have to be very much modernised and coordinated in order that trains may run faster.  Senator Lyons pointed out that in Japan trains are running at 200 mph.  We probably will not see that in our time, but the railway system will have to compete with private transport.  The same applies to rail freight, to take Senator McCartin's point.  There was a loss on the road freight service the year before last and the year previous to that, but last year it made a profit.  Unless it can stand on its feet and make a profit, it should not be subsidised to compete with private companies.  If the railways, either for freight or for passengers are to compete with road transport and private cars, they must run faster, they must run more efficiently and they must be more attractive to the users.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>It seems ridiculous that in the mornings that there might be 50 cars at one set of traffic lights in any city or town and stuck in the middle of them one bus which could carry the occupants of the 50 cars at the one time.  This certainly does not seem to be the best use of transport or of <Col N="93" /> people's time.  If the buses were more efficient people would leave their cars at home and would come in the buses. Because the buses are inefficient, there are more cars on the roads. Therefore, the buses become more inefficient and you are getting into the situation of the chicken and the egg &mdash;which came first.</P>
    <P>I have always held the view that in cities and towns public transport should have priority, that it is there for the type of people Senator Higgins was talking about.  This transport should have priority in the use of roads.  This matter will require a lot of study by the Department of Local Government, and I would not like to enter into that now.  Traffic plans and parking restrictions should all be geared towards making buses run quickly, cheaply and efficiently between suburbs and city centres.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan made the point about the possibility of the fuel crisis helping to make CIE profitable.  I was interested to hear Senator Quinlan refer to &ldquo;the main line train&rdquo; as if there were no other main lines in Ireland except the one between Cork and Dublin.  There are other main line trains as well.</P>
    <P>Senator Quinlan made the point again about cutting down the number of cars coming into the city with only one passenger. Senator Quinlan and a number of other Senators strongly stressed that the measure of our support for CIE is our faith in our own future, and I think that is very true.  I do not know whether it would have been usual here ten years ago to find the same support in this House, or in the other House, for CIE as there was today. There is now quite a pride in Irish people in CIE&mdash;I see Senator West nodding assent&mdash;and I think the management and the workers in CIE will react to this and provide for us a better service and possibly for the taxpayer less of a burden.</P>
    <P>One of the most beneficial results of the sales promotion campaign a few years ago to get more people to travel by train was its effect on the morale of the people working in CIE. It improved their morale immensely, <Col N="94" /> made them proud of their job, no longer regarding themselves as on the backs of the public.  They are not. They are performing an essential service, a service it is not possible, here or anywhere else in the world, to run at a profit on the rates being paid. CIE workers and management should understand that the people and the Government fully back them, but we want to see them having faith in themselves or having, as Senator Quinlan said, the measure of the faith in their own future by having faith in themselves now and in their own organisation. I think this is possible and it is certainly desirable.</P>
    <P>Many points were made by Senator O'Brien and Senator West, suggestions to the manager of CIE, experiments that might be made to get more people interested in train and bus services.  I will see that the whole of today's debate will be given to the management of CIE.  They will study every one of these suggestions and see if it is possible to implement them, or, if there are ideas that they themselves have not already thought of, they will be applied to the benefit of their organisation.</P>
    <P>Senator Keegan spoke about the school transport service.  That is not actually the responsibility of CIE. They are merely contractors to the Department of Education for that. They run the school buses as dictated by the Department of Education.</P>
    <P>I think the last point I want to make before I explain how this Bill became so urgent&mdash;I hope I have covered everything raised by the Senators&mdash;concerns the pensions to CIE workers.  As Senator Cowen said, when people come out of CIE at 65, besides the pension they get from CIE, they also get their social welfare benefit. This is a very complicated matter. There are many different pensions schemes within CIE and they are all being examined at the moment.  I hope certainly to be able to say something about some of them in the reasonably near future.  These must be examined with the Department of Finance, the trade unions involved and with CIE and my Department. <Col N="95" /> There are a number of views that must be got together in this.</P>
    <P>Now I will explain about the urgency of this Bill.  I will begin by contradicting myself and saying that it is not urgent in one sense at all. But it is urgent in the sense that, if it is not there, there is a danger of the interest rate going up.  That is the only urgency.  It would be quite possible to leave this for another month or two.  The reason that it came here at an awkward time is that the loan was agreed to by the European Investment Bank only in December when both Houses had risen.  On the first sitting day after the Dáil came back, which was this day week, I introduced this Bill in the Dáil and it was passed there yesterday.</P>
    <P>It had to come here today because the President cannot sign it before five days and he must sign it within seven days, two days after that again. This brings us up to the 19th February, which is the date for the next meeting of the European Investment Bank.  It was better not to take the risk that the cost of the loan, which is at a very attractive interest now of 8¾ per cent, might have gone up in the meantime.  We decided it was better, with some inconvenience&mdash;and I apologise to the Seanad; the Dáil was sitting anyway&mdash;to try and get the legislation through so that we would not be deprived of the advantage over a long period of a considerable sum at what in modern money terms is a reasonable rate of interest.</P>
    <P>I should like to very sincerely thank the Senators for coming back here and for agreeing to give me this Bill to-day and perhaps more particularly, for the many useful suggestions and for the high tenor of this debate this evening.  Thank you very much.</P>
    <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    <P>Agreed to take remaining Stages to-day.</P>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Transport Bill," RHead="1974: Committee and Final Stages">
    <Title>Private Business. - Transport Bill, 1974: Committee and Final Stages.</Title>
    <P>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</P>
    <P Just="Center">
      <Col N="96" /> SECTION 3.</P>
    <P>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 3 stand part of the Bill.&rdquo;</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>On section 3, since it is an appropriate time to make this comment, I should like to make the observation that I welcome the use of the tables here to clarify the position. This is something that has recently come into legislation and I, as a lawyer, trying to assess the difference it has made when a Bill is amended, greatly welcome this presentation of a clear picture by means of the tabling of the effect the amendment has.  I should just like, having been critical at an earlier stage, to say that I welcome the approach in the Bill and this particular example of it where, when changes are made, the Bill includes a table setting out the precise position.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>Are the advances repayable under this section?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PeterBarry" hpid="Mr. P. Barry Mr. P. Barry">
      <NameTxt>Mr. P. Barry</NameTxt>
      <P>Yes; but CIE will be borrowing this money from the European Investment Bank and they will be responsible for repaying it with the guarantee of the Minister for Finance.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
      <P>Sections 4 to 8, inclusive, agreed to.</P>
      <P>Title agreed to.</P>
      <P>Bill reported without amendment, received for final consideration and passed.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Social Welfare (Agricultural" RHead="Employees) Regulations 1974: Motion">
    <Title>Private Business. - Social Welfare (Agricultural Employees) Regulations 1974: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the Social Welfare (Agricultural Employees) Regulations, 1974, proposed to be made by the Minister for Social Welfare and laid in draft before Seanad Éireann on the 20th day of December, 1973, under subsection (4) of section 10 of the Social Welfare (Pay-Related Benefit) Act, 1973, be approved.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Cluskey) Frank Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Cluskey)</NameTxt>
      <P>It might be convenient, <Col N="97" /> subject to agreement, to deal with Nos. 3 and 4 together.  The purpose of these regulations is to extend the pay-related benefit scheme to cover male and female agricultural workers.  That scheme is provided for under the Social Welfare (Pay-Related Benefit) Act, 1973, and the necessary order has been made to bring it into operation from the beginning of the next income tax year on 6th April, 1974.</P>
      <P>Pay-related benefit is designed for persons whose social insurance covers them for disability benefit, maternity allowance and unemployment benefit. It will be paid as a supplement to these flat-rate benefits at a rate calculated from the claimant's earnings in a previous income tax year.  Particulars of these earnings will be supplied to my Department by the Revenue Commissioners.</P>
      <P>The scheme will be financed by pay-related contributions levied on employers and employees.  These contributions will amount to 3 per cent of the employee's current earnings up to a ceiling of £2,500 in the year, the employer paying 2 per cent and the employee 1 per cent.  They will be collected by the Revenue Commissioners through the income tax collection machinery.</P>
      <P>It had originally been thought that the scheme would, initially, cover only persons paying the ordinary flat-rate social insurance contributions and the Act was framed accordingly.  This was due to the difficulties encountered in arranging a system of collecting pay-related contributions in respect of persons not in industrial, commercial and services-type employment.  The Act, however, provides in section 10 that other classes of employees could be brought into the scheme by regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>With the abolition from 1st April, 1974, of the remuneration limit of £1,600 for social insurance in the case of non-manual workers, all employees in those employments will be brought within the scope of the pay-related benefit scheme.  The main groups of workers who would not be included in the scheme although insured for disability benefit, maternity allowance and unemployment benefit purposes <Col N="98" /> would be male and female agricultural workers.</P>
    <P>It has always been the intention to have the coverage of the scheme as wide as possible and to bring agricultural workers in particular into the scheme as soon as it was feasible to do so.  As a result of further examination of the matter since the Act was passed the Revenue Commissioners have found it possible to agree to collect pay-related contributions from employees in the agricultural sector from 6th April next.  It is, therefore, proposed to bring agricultural workers, both male and female, into the scheme from the start and regulations for that purpose have been prepared as provided for in section 10 of the Act.  That section, however, requires that drafts of the regulations must be laid before each House of the Oireachtas and that the regulations cannot be made until the draft has been approved by resolution in each House.  The necessary resolution has been passed by Dáil Éireann.</P>
    <P>The draft regulations, which are the subject of this resolution, will apply the provisions of the 1973 Act to persons employed in agriculture for whom the special agricultural rates of social insurance contributions are payable by including pay derived from employment in agriculture in the definition of earnings reckonable for the purposes of pay-related benefit and contributions.  I recommend these regulations for the approval of Seanad Éireann.</P>
    <P>I come now to the regulations concerning the alteration of rates of social welfare contributions.  These regulations are consequential on the introduction of the pay-related benefit scheme.  Under that scheme, pay-related benefit will be payable to persons as a supplement to flat-rate disability benefit, maternity allowance or unemployment benefit.  It will also be paid with injury benefit under the occupational injuries benefit scheme where that benefit is paid in lieu of disability benefit or maternity allowance.</P>
    <P>The rate of pay-related benefit will be calculated on the part of the claimant's reckonable weekly earnings <Col N="99" /> in a previous income tax year, lying between £14 and £50.  A pay-related contribution amounting in all to 3 per cent of the employee's current earnings will be charged of which the employer will bear 2 per cent and the employee 1 per cent.  The contributions will be collected by the Collector-General of Revenue through the income tax system.  In order to facilitate this method of collection, it is necessary to charge contributions on all earnings up to the ceiling of £2,500 in the year.  This will mean that pay-related contributions will be levied on pay up to £700 in the year which is the equivalent of £14 a week for pay-related benefit purposes.  Pay up to £14 a week will not attract any pay-related benefit, and there will, thus, be what amounts to an overcharge of pay-related contributions on it.  The most practical way in which to compensate employers and employees for this overcharge is by reducing the flat-rate contributions.</P>
    <P>The purpose of these regulations is to reduce appropriately the flat-rate social insurance contributions payable in respect of persons who will be covered by the pay-related benefit scheme.  The rates being reduced are therefore the ordinary rates which are payable in general by persons in industrial, commercial and services-type employments and the special rates payable by male and female agricultural workers.</P>
    <P>The amount of the reduction proposed for the 3 per cent levied on pay up to £14 a week is 42p per week.  The employer is liable for 2 per cent of the pay-related contribution as against the employee's 1 per cent and his flat-rate contribution is being reduced by 28p per week while the employee's is being reduced by 14p per week. These reductions are of necessity flat-rate and affect all persons paying the contributions equally regardless of their earnings.</P>
    <P>The liability for pay-related contributions will commence as from Saturday, 6th April, 1974, which is the start of the 1974-75 income tax year and I propose that the reduction in the appropriate flat-rate contributions <Col N="100" /> should take effect as from Monday, 1st April, 1974, which is the start of the first contribution week in that year.</P>
    <P>The regulations for this purpose which it is proposed to make under subsection (9) of section 6 of the Social Welfare Act, 1952, may not be made until a resolution approving of the draft regulations has been passed by both Houses of the Oireachtas. The necessary resolution has been passed by Dáil Éireann.  I recommend these draft regulations for the approval of Seanad Éireann.</P>
    <Speaker pid="SeanKeegan" hpid="Mr. Keegan Mr. Keegan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Keegan</NameTxt>
      <P>I welcome these provisions. The Bill, as most of us know, has been debated here before.  It enables social welfare contributors to receive a benefit in accordance with the wages they are earning.  I am particularly pleased that agricultural workers, both male and female, have now been brought into the category from which they have been excluded for many years.  Most of us will recall that the agricultural worker has been the cinderella of all our work force.  For many years the female worker had to be ten years in employment before she could draw any benefit.</P>
      <P>While welcoming the scheme, I regret that the agricultural labour force seems to be on the decline.  I am greatly worried that that trend will continue this year because of the falling off in agricultural incomes and because of the inability of many farmers to continue to employ labour which they normally would.  However, let us hope that something brighter is on the horizon and that the farming community will be in a position to continue to give the maximum amount of employment.  The agricultural worker has been in many ways degraded, and this piece of legislation restores him to his rightful place among the work force in this country.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>Let us hope that employment opportunities will be adequate to enable the work force to enjoy full employment during this year.  If it should happen that we have unemployment or that somebody has to cease work <Col N="101" /> because of illness or anything else, he will be in a position to enjoy benefits which are related to the wages he had been earning when he was in employment. Those are the main contents of these regulations and we support them fully.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JohnHarte" hpid="Mr. Harte Mr. Harte">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Harte</NameTxt>
      <P>I was glad to hear Senator Keegan speak on behalf of the agricultural workers.  It is a sector we seldom hear about in the work context.  One would think there were no labourers in agricultural areas, just farmers and ranch owners.</P>
      <P>I should like to add the trade union voice to the debate.  I should like to make it clear that, even though I refer to representations made by the Irish Congress of Trade Unions and by trade union delegations, I do not claim they were solely responsible for having brought about the benefits under the pay-related schemes.  It is true that the trade union voice speaks not only for trade unionists, including agricultural workers, but also for the weaker sections of the community. Trade unions do not confine themselves to the question of wages and salaries.  The representations which have been made have borne fruit and for that reason we give the Pay-Related Benefits Act an unreserved welcome and hope it is the beginning of many developments in this direction.</P>
      <P>We have not only the increase in benefits but also the reduction by the Minister for Local Government of the local authority rents, subsidised mortgage interest, improved tenant purchase and so on.  This is very good social legislation.  I do not wish to wander from the point.  I am well within the rules of order by merely referring to those other points and not dealing with them as part of the Act.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should like to draw the attention of the Parliamentary Secretary to one problem.  We are all aware of the great upsurge in the cost of living. This has offset the substantial benefits we gained in social insurance as a result of the adjustment upwards in the contributions from both employers and workers.  The weaker section of the community will be hit very hard as the price increases continue <Col N="102" /> to rise.  Unlike centralised wage agreements, there is no way to introduce a clause which would safeguard people against rising prices.  We welcome the legislation to regularise the pay-related contributions, but, unless we keep ahead of them and keep looking at them in comparison with the basic rates and take-home pay of the strongly organised sections of the community, they will lose their value.</P>
    <P>Having regard to the fact that the employer-labour agreement, which provided for a minimum of £2, was rejected, the Parliamentary Secretary's thoughts should be running in that direction and the benefits which are derived from salary and wage increases should have some relationship to that minimum.</P>
    <P>In welcoming the proposals and the statements made by the Parliamentary Secretary, it is also necessary to put on record that a once-and-for-all increase in these benefits should not be the attitude.  Measuring the improvements in 1960, where we got an increase of 2s 6d in the old age pension and where the actual amount payable was 30s, against the present payment of £7.20, it is indicative of the fact that not only the present Government but also the last Government were sympathetic in relation to the problem and there was an awareness created in the people's minds of the necessity to build up social welfare.  I should like to see the good work continuing.  The last increase was the most substantial we have had.  Let us hope this will not be the end of this type of legislation and that when the increases are being talked about in the future, the Parliamentary Secretary will bear in mind that the trade unions would not claim the entire credit for these improvements. Great credit must go to the Minister and the Government in general for this legislation.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Am I correct in thinking the position is that there is a Motion on the Adjournment fixed for 9.30?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The time of 9.30 has been specified.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it inconvenience the Parliamentary Secretary <Col N="103" /> by agreeing to sit on after 10 o'clock to complete this?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>Under the Standing Orders it would not be possible to sit on after the Adjournment Debate has concluded; and equally it does not seem possible to vary the time which was specified before public business today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>It looks as though it cannot be managed.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I might refrain from looking at the clock for five minutes.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, would like to welcome these regulations.  I am glad the agricultural workers are now to benefit from these provisions.  They are a section of our labour force who are entitled to be included.  Down through the years the agricultural worker has given outstanding service to the nation.  For quite a long period in the past they gave devoted service. As any Senators who have been reared on farms know, it is not easy to measure that service in hours. Therefore the agricultural worker cannot be tied completely to time because the running of a farm cannot be regulated according to the hours on the clock.  You have to have a dedicated set of workers and certainly I will say that the agricultural workers have been very dedicated in the past. It will be vital for the success of this nation and for the future outlook of farming that we should try to ensure so far as is humanly possible that in the future the livelihood of the agricultural worker will be safeguarded. The vast majority of our exports and indeed of our industrial endeavour is based on agricultural output. That really starts on the farm. It is there you have the agricultural worker who is as much skilled as any other section of our labour force.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The skills that are necessary in modern day farming cannot be acquired in many of our secondary schools or colleges.  They are something that workers acquire themselves from the very fact of working on <Col N="104" /> farms.  They have an enormous amount of knowledge, they have a good idea of soils and crops and husbandry of animals and all that goes for making a successful business out of agriculture.  Under the new EEC regulations and farm plans, the agricultural worker will be far more important now than in the past.  It is necessary now to employ new skills, new means and new ideas in farming.</P>
    <P>Therefore, we should try to ensure that the work force we have will remain and that if possible we should be able to attract to our farms more people of the same calibre, people who would be able to understand agriculture fairly well, who would attend agricultural classes sponsored by the local agricultural committees, to equip themselves in an occupation that they will follow to the very end of their lives rather than to have a staggered type of system because of which farm workers avail of the first opportunity to emigrate to the bigger towns or cities or to go abroad.  We should encourage them to stay on the farms and make it possible for the farmer to pay them and to give them these facilities.</P>
    <P>Because of the very low incomes of farm workers, there is a very grave danger at present that many of these people may drift into industry.  They would be a very great loss to the nation.  I sincerely hope it will not happen in agriculture generally.  It is happening in the pig industry and in other branches of farming.  Apart from that, I welcome these regulations and I am glad to see that they are bringing the agricultural worker into line with other workers.</P>
    <Speaker pid="FintanKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I, too, accept and endorse these regulations.  I should like to congratulate the Parliamentary Secretary and his predecessors on the excellent work done in this direction. First of all, I think these regulations constitute a definite advance in this particular area of social welfare but more important still they introduce a principle into social welfare which I have long advocated and which is of more importance today than at any time in the past.  That is the principle <Col N="105" /> of relating benefits to earnings, therefore in some measures relating benefits to fluctuations in the consumer price index.  I would ask the Minister to bear this principle in mind when the Government are considering all future legislation in regard to social welfare. It is very important.</P>
      <P>We have to do two things.  First of all, we have to bring up as quickly as we can all social welfare benefits to EEC levels, and having done that we must ensure that those standards of benefits are increased in accordance with increases in the cost of living. The cost of living increased by 12½ per cent last year and it is estimated that in the current year the increase will be in the region of at least 15 per cent.  Some experts put it at 20 per cent or more.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid the Senator is now going outside the scope of the debate on these regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FintanKennedy" hpid="Mr. Kennedy Mr. Kennedy">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Kennedy</NameTxt>
      <P>I think I have reached the end of what I have to say.  I will conclude by repeating the request I have made that the Government should bear in mind this particular principle in all future welfare legislation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="PatrickQuinlan" hpid="Professor Quinlan Professor Quinlan">
      <NameTxt>Professor Quinlan</NameTxt>
      <P>While welcoming the Bill, is it not a fact that these pay-related benefits are largely in insurance &mdash; in other words, the group concerned are putting up the fund &mdash; and there would be relatively little Government input into it?  The 3 per cent collected is in effect what the benefits are paid from.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>This pay-related benefit scheme could be described as Fianna Fáil's greatest contribution to the weaker sections of the community &mdash; the disabled and the unemployed. It certainly should be a source of consolation for many workers who, fearing unemployment or disability, know that in the future their incomes will be supplemented to a point that will at least keep them living above the poverty line.  Since this scheme was first introduced the cost of living has leap-frogged in this country.  Is there any way under these regulations that <Col N="106" /> consideration can be given to that fact?  For example, 12 months ago a bag of coal cost less than £1 in my own county and today it is £1.80.  I notice the Parliamentary Secretary is writing.  I do not know if he is taking note of the £1.80.  That may not be the right price but that is the price that is being charged for it.  While this causes distress to most sections of the community, the greatest distress was caused to the very people we hope will benefit under this scheme.  I was very pleased when the Government announced in the budget that they were abolishing the means test for disability allowances.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid that, as in the case of Senator Kennedy, the Senator is going on to a broad social welfare discussion which is not relevant to these regulations.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMcGlinchey" hpid="Mr. McGlinchey Mr. McGlinchey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. McGlinchey</NameTxt>
      <P>The request I was about to make to the Parliamentary Secretary was if in some way these regulations could be applied to the people who are in receipt not of disability benefits but of disability allowances.  I have to confess I congratulate the Government on the help they have already given to people in this category, but a person in receipt of a maximum allowance of £5 odd per week just cannot survive in the world we are living in today.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Cluskey) Frank Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Social Welfare (Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>First of all, I should like to thank the Chair and the House for facilitating me in getting these motions through.  I will be very brief indeed in replying.  The only aspect that I should like to refer to that has been raised by a couple of Senators is the question of prices going up and not being compensated for.  There seems to be some confusion with regard to this regulation in so far as the benefits to be derived under it are confined to the insured work force. The benefits to be derived under this regulation are to be directly related to reckonable earnings.  Senators can be assured that organised workers are able to take care of increasing prices by way of seeking compensation <Col N="107" /> through increased wages.  There is a built-in safeguard against this contingency. I do not think there is any other matter to which I wish to refer.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="BernardMarkey" hpid="Mr. Markey Mr. Markey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Markey</NameTxt>
      <P>Would it be in order to ask the Parliamentary Secretary at this stage &mdash; I thought it might be covered in his reply or by some of the earlier speakers &mdash; the position of the self-employed man who has been a voluntary contributor over a period of years?  Where will he stand under this scheme?</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="FrankCluskey" hpid="Mr. Cluskey Mr. Cluskey">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Cluskey</NameTxt>
      <P>The self-employed are not covered by this particular regulation.  It is the insurance stamp.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Social Welfare (Alteration of" RHead="Rates of Contributions) Regulations 1974: Motion">
    <Title>Private Business. - Social Welfare (Alteration of Rates of Contributions) Regulations 1974: Motion.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I move:</P>
      <P>That the Social Welfare (Alteration of Rates of Contributions) Regulations, 1974, proposed to be made by the Minister for Social Welfare and laid in draft, sanctioned by the Minister for Finance, before Seanad Éireann on the 31st day of December, 1973, under subsection (9) of section 6 of the Social Welfare Act, 1952 be approved.</P>
      <P>Question put and agreed to.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
  <MainHeading Type="GD" LHead="Private Business. - Adjournment Debate:" RHead="National Library Map Collections">
    <Title>Private Business. - Adjournment Debate: National Library Map Collections.</Title>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I am grateful for the opportunity to raise this matter on the Adjournment, namely, &ldquo;The fact that the map collections of the National Library are not being made available to members of the public and particularly to scholars.&rdquo;  I am glad that the Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Education has been able to come into the House to reply to the points that I will make.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The first point I should like to make is that this is not something which happened in the last week, or last month, or last six months.  It is something that happened in January, 1973. Therefore, it is over a year since the maps were withdrawn from availability <Col N="108" /> either to the public or to scholars.  I should like to begin by referring to a letter which was circulated to each Member of the Oireachtas by the joint staffs of the Geography Departments of University College and my college, Trinity College.  This is a good example of university co-operation by joining together to draft the letter.  I propose, with your indulgence, to read the terms of the letter on to the record, because it sets out part of the grievance which was felt by these lecturers and part of the serious concern which must be felt by anybody who values learning and values scholarship and values interest in a particular area of scholarship relating to Irish life.  The letter which is dated November, 1973 is as follows:</P>
    <P>We are writing to draw your attention to the disgraceful state of affairs that exists with regard to the map collections of the National Library of Ireland.</P>
    <P>These maps are an essential part of the country's information services and few of them are available in any other Irish library.  They are also of the utmost importance to geographical and historical scholarship, contributing directly and indirectly each year to the education of hundreds of university and other students and thousands of school pupils.</P>
    <P>Since last January almost all the maps in this great national collection have been totally inaccessible to the public.  The reason given by the library authorities for their withdrawal is lack of space, a lack which became critical (the authorities say) when it was noticed that the maps were vulnerable to fire in those parts of the Library where they had been kept for the past sixteen years.</P>
    <P>Fortunately, space was found for the maps in the University College building in Earlsfort Terrace.  When their new location became known many people assumed that staff would be provided to make the collections available to the public until the Library's permanent accommodation had been enlarged. This has not happened, and there <Col N="109" /> has been no sign that it is going to happen.</P>
    <P>It is also widely assumed that room will eventually be found for the maps in an extension to the Library now being built in Kildare Street.  According to other sources, however, the whole of this new accommodation has already been earmarked for a different purpose. No official announcement has been made one way or the other on this important point.</P>
    <P>There is obviously a pressing need for adequate permanent accommodation to be provided for these maps as soon as possible.  It is equally important that some temporary arrangement should be introduced without delay to make the maps available to students in their present repository.  Further prolongation of the present sorry state of affairs will merely add to Ireland's reputation as a country incapable of looking after the records of either its past or its present.</P>
    <P>Efforts to bring these facts home to the Minister for Education have met with no response beyond a bare acknowledgement.  As professors and lecturers in the departments of geography at Trinity College and University College, Dublin, we ask for your active support in these efforts.</P>
    <P>There follow the signatures of the members of staff of the Geography Departments of the two colleges.</P>
    <P>This is a situation, indeed I would maintain a scandal, which has been the position for over a year and on which there is no terminal date. There is no indication of how long this will be the position.  In order to verify just how scandalous the position is I made inquiries in the Department of Geography in Trinity College as to the implication within the college itself.  I was informed that there are five students at the moment engaged in dissertations on historical geography who are substantially handicapped in their work this year. There are also research projects which are severely handicapped by the unavailability of these maps.  I gather <Col N="110" /> that the position varies from inconvenience to one of a total block on this form of scholarship.  Some of these maps are available less conveniently elsewhere, either in the Ordnance Survey authority or in some other venues.  Unfortunately the more important of these maps are not necessarily available elsewhere.  The National Library have a unique collection. This collection is not now available at all to the public or to scholars.</P>
    <P>One ironic factor is that the National Library has a very good catalogue of maps.  This has been compiled over the years and it is something of which the library and its staff can be justly proud.  But there is no good in having a good map catalogue if the maps themselves are not available.  When it was decided in January, 1973, to have the maps transferred to Earlsfort Terrace various questions arose.  First of all, it is hard to justify the removal of an entire collection of one type of learning.  If there was a problem of space, then surely the less important maps and the less important other items &mdash; for instance, books or something else &mdash; could have been removed from the National Library but not an entire class of learning.</P>
    <P>Secondly, if some of the maps were a fire risk those particular maps could have been either removed to a different part, where they would still be accessible but no longer a fire risk, instead of having all maps from different parts of the library swept away in one stroke.</P>
    <P>Thirdly, if some of the maps were a theft risk and were in danger of being stolen, those particular maps could have been better protected.  Also a proper determination could have been made that certain important maps, from the point of view of their significance to scholarship and from the point of view of their being solely available in the National Library would at all times be available.  None of these factors seems to have been considered when the maps were being removed.</P>
    <P>I would maintain that there was a failure in the duty owed to the <Col N="111" /> public on three counts: first of all, the library gave no warning of their intention to remove this collection in January, 1973; no sufficient advance warning to those involved in research projects, to those compiling world atlases, in which we must play our part as a country by itemising the maps which are available; no advance warning to anybody who was planning a project and wanted to use these maps. Foreign students may well have come to Ireland on the understanding they could pursue a course of studies which the unavailability of the collection would prevent.  That is the first point: no warning was given of the removal.</P>
    <P>Secondly, no adequate explanation was offered by the library at the time to explain their actions; no adequate explanation has been given, despite constant requests, made both to the library and to the Department of Education. There has been a lack of willingness to answer the anxious requests of the Geography Society, of individual scholars, of those who have written letters over the last few months in <i>The Irish Times</i> and other newspapers. That is the second point: that no adequate explanation has been offered.</P>
    <P>Thirdly, so far, despite the 13 months which have elapsed, no announcement of specific arrangements has been made to make the maps available in their temporary place.  At present, although the maps are physically contained in part of Earlsfort Terrace, there is no provision and apparently no intention to make provision that there would be even a limited access to these maps. One possibility would be that either part-time staff be recruited for the purpose, or that the staff of the library be available at certain times in Earlsfort Terrace to allow properly vouched students, scholars, lecturers and others with a particular interest to see the materials.  This would seem to me to be the bare minimum, that <i>bona fide</i> persons who could establish that they had a genuine necessity in their projects or a genuine interest in seeing the particular maps, for the purpose of pursuing their studies, would be allowed to do so at specific <Col N="112" /> times under the supervision of a member of the staff of the library. This has not been possible to date.</P>
    <P>Apart from this very minimal improvement of the temporary situation, I think it is necessary that the Government make it very clear what the long-term solution will be.  What one would hope to see would be that the Government would undertake that the library would provide a properly equipped map-room &mdash; not one shared with other items, such as newspapers and so on &mdash; containing tables of a sufficient size to look at these very large bound volumes of maps; that there would be a specialist member of the staff who would be qualified to assist students and scholars in their researches; that there would be open access to maps which are in regular demand, and that all other maps would be available within about an hour, on request; and that the map catalogue would be put to full use in this way.</P>
    <P>It is interesting that before 1900 there was a map-room, as such, in the library.  It is a sad fact that this is no longer so.  In correspondence around that period, where the library were applying for free copies of ordnance survey maps, they referred to their map-room and to the fact that the maps would be kept there.  I think we have gone backwards in that we have not had for a very long time a specific map-room, as such; and now we have an excellent catalogue but total inaccessibility of the maps themselves.</P>
    <P>Another factor which must not go by default in debating this matter is the sensibilities of the persons concerned: the feelings now of the Geography Society of Ireland, of lecturers in the subject and of students in geography.  Their interest is being ignored.  We talk about the rights of the minority: the geography departments in the two colleges and those with interests in this specific area know that they are a minority, they know that theirs is a specialised subject. They rightly feel that it is important. We ought to make it clear that any contribution to learning &mdash; particularly a contribution which relates very much to Irish life, to our <Col N="113" /> tradition, to our history, to our historical geography &mdash; is important. Those involved in it should be encouraged in their studies, should be given a sense that we do appreciate the work that they are doing; that they have the encouragement of our society, particularly of our Government, and of our institutions such as the National Library.  They should not be prevented and handicapped; they should be encouraged and facilitated.  If we try to give ourselves the reputation of being a country that is concerned with learning, and if we want to get back again the reputation of being an island of saints and scholars, we must be prepared to promote and help much more conscientiously those involved in study and research, and interested members of the public who want to further their knowledge in this particular area.</P>
    <P>That, then, is the case I want to make about the map collections.  The specific questions that I should like the Parliamentary Secretary to answer are; firstly, is there any definite date which will end this position of inaccessability of the maps stored away in Earlsfort Terrace?  Secondly, is there the intention to make a temporary improvement of the situation, even of a less satisfactory nature, by which in supervised conditions, either in Earlsfort Terrace or elsewhere, it will be possible for <i>bona fide</i> students, scholars, researchers, lecturers, who want to use these maps, to avail of them?  Thirdly, is there a long-term policy to provide proper accommodation and facilities for these maps? Specifically on that point, is it the intention of the Government to have part of the space in the building in Kildare Street &mdash; the Setanta Building &mdash; made available for this purpose, or has it, in fact, as those in the geography departments suspect, been entirely allocated for other purposes?  Are they, once again, the poor relation? I would welcome specific answers to these specific questions.  I would also welcome some explanation or some indication from the Parliamentary Secretary of how this deplorable state of affairs could have been brought <Col N="114" /> about in the first place and in such an abrupt manner, and could have been allowed to continue over 13 months to the detriment of the pursuit of studies in historical geography?</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>The Senator did not speak for the full 20 minutes. Accordingly, she may designate the time to any other Senator who wishes to speak.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>If any other Senator would like to contribute, I would be happy if they should.  Otherwise, it would be nice to go home earlier.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MichaelJosephOHiggin" hpid="Mr. M.J. O'Higgins Mr. M.J. O'Higgins">
      <NameTxt>Mr. M.J. O'Higgins</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to say briefly that I think it was well worth while that Senator Robinson raised this matter here.  I feel that the case she has made is one which certainly should get the very careful attention of the Parliamentary Secretary. I have no notion whatever as to what the Parliamentary Secretary will say with regard to this matter.  I do not know the explanation or the answer to the various queries which Senator Robinson has made, but I think she has argued a very effective case.  However, I hope the Parliamentary Secretary will be able to give an assurance to the House and to the interested parties.  As Senator Robinson pointed out, there are those not only engaged in education from a teacher's point of view but also from a student point of view who are intensely interested in being able to have these maps available.  I hope that the Parliamentary Secretary will be able to make some arrangements which will satisfy their needs.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="SeamusDolan" hpid="Mr. Dolan Mr. Dolan">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Dolan</NameTxt>
      <P>Might I say I agree with what Senator Robinson has said regarding these maps.  It is important that the State should ensure that they will be kept in safe custody and that they will be preserved and handed down to posterity, if at all possible, in their original state.  Therefore, it is necessary to ensure that proper storage be provided for them.  Perhaps that may be the reason why they are stored away.  Nevertheless, a good reason would be necessary before deciding to store them away during our lifetime and thus prevent scholars from examining <Col N="115" /> them, writing books about them and taking photostat copies of them in order to present them to the general public who are not in a position to travel to Dublin city or to go to the places where these maps are kept. They are very useful to students, and in particular to those who are interested in doing research.  There are many bodies now in the country who are interested in local history.  It is hardly possible to study local history and place names without having recourse to valuable documents such as these.</P>
      <P>Senator Robinson has referred to the lack of space in our National Museum.  That has been evident over quite a number of years.  Something should be done to rectify that position. The only way to improve the position is to provide finances for proper extensions and storage facilities.</P>
      <P>Perhaps in this very House there are old manuscripts and documents stored away to which scholars may not have access.  I think I am correct in saying that.  There are a great many manuscripts in our possession in this country which have never been edited, examined or made available to scholars over the years.  Now when there is greater emphasis on education, with greater facilities and more money for providing education at all levels, students in the future may be very interested in history and all that goes with it.  The only evidence they have of past history, apart from what is on exhibition in the museum, is old documents, old manuscripts and old maps.  The Parliamentary Secretary should try to find a way of making these available. We should be proud of the fact that there are sufficient people interested in scholarly documents coming forward and seeking out these relics of the past.  We should be proud of those who are willing to devote their time to present such documents in a manner suitable for the ordinary people.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Education (Mr. Bruton) John Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Parliamentary Secretary to the Minister for Education (Mr. Bruton)</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to thank Senator Robinson for raising this matter.  I <Col N="116" /> should like to assure her and the Seanad that this is not in our opinion a satisfactory situation that we have in relation to the maps.  I do not wish that anything I say should be seen as evidencing a spirit of complacency on my part or on the part of the Minister for Education.  I would say &mdash; and I think it is very important &mdash; that it is an integral part of a much larger problem which is the overall one of accommodation in the National Library as a whole.  It is not just a problem of maps.</P>
      <P>The National Library has been neglected by all parties in the State for many years.  In fact, apart from off-site bulk storage, no additional accommodation has been provided for the National Library since 1926.  If I could borrow a phrase used in another context solving this problem is a daunting task.</P>
      <P>I have, accordingly, taken what I hope will be the first positive step on the road to the provision of fitting accommodation for the library in convening an inter-departmental committee to examine the institutions short-term and long-term space requirements in detail and to submit recommendations as a matter of urgency.  The committee have already furnished an interim report.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>The recommendations in this report are at present under consideration.  For the information of the Seanad I should like briefly to explain the circumstances leading up to the transfer of the map collection to off-site bulk storage at Earlsfort Terrace.  Prior to 1957 the facilities for the collection were satisfactory enough within the space limitations which even then obtained.  In that year however, as a result of the expansion of departments within the library and to make room for the growing accession of manuscript material, it became necessary to remove the greater part of the map collection to the library's entrance hall.  The remainder of the collection was stored in the newspaper reading room and adjoining passages.  Although this arrangement was certainly not the most satisfactory, it had at least the advantage that the material was to some extent at that time still available to readers.  But the <Col N="117" /> situation continued to deteriorate.  This involved the continued reliance on the entrance hall as a repository for other materials in addition to the map collection. As time went by the conditions in the entrance hall became a source of worry to the library staff, to the council of trustees and to the Office of Public Works because of the fire and other hazards involved.  The situation which led up to what was described as a sudden decision in January of this year was that some of the maps which were being stored there in the entrance hall were stolen.</P>
    <P>Senator Robinson said that no warning was given of the removal of the maps.  I can assure the Senator that no warning was given of the theft.  That brought rather forcibly to the library's attention the necessity to find alternative safe storage accommodation. As Senators are aware, this is a very valuable collection of great relevance not just to this generation but to many generations in the future.  It is the responsibility therefore of the National Library, first of all, to preserve the material for posterity and it was in that context that this decision had to be reluctantly taken by the trustees.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>On that point, I accept that the maps in the entrance hall were both a fire and a theft risk; but all the maps in the library, not just those in the entrance hall, were removed.  In other words, a whole category of learning was wiped out on the very limited excuse that some of the maps were a fire risk.  Why did they not remove less important books from other areas?  Why remove an entire collection of learning.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. Bruton Mr. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>The decision was taken not by me.  It was taken by people who were technically competent to make the decision and they presumably did so using this technical competence.  I would point out that these maps are in series and keeping a few out of a series might not be much help to anybody.  The bulk of the maps were in the entrance hall. The maps which were stored in other parts of the library were not as significant in quantity.  I should add, as <Col N="118" /> Senator Robinson has mentioned, that the library was specifically warned by the Board of Works, who are competent to advise them in this matter, that the way in which the material was stored there was a fire hazard.  Senator Robinson has asked why individual maps which were not a fire hazard were not removed and others left there, but I take it that all the maps were equally flammable and therefore all the maps which were stored in the entrance hall of the National Library were equally a fire risk, so there was not much point leaving two or three and taking the rest away.</P>
      <P>Therefore, the arrangements were made by the library authorities with the authorities of University College, Dublin, for the storage of the map collection and of a considerable quantity of manuscripts and other material in the college's buildings in Earlsfort Terrace.  There they still remain in reasonable safety, but unfortunately unavailable to the public until satisfactory alternative arrangements can be made.  I should add, however, that endeavours were made, following a meeting I had with the director and trustees, to obtain space in University College for the public to consult the material.  But when that approach was made we were informed by the university authorities that no space was available in the university in which the material could be consulted.  All they could provide was off-site bulk storage.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I should mention what the collection consists of, just to illustrate to the Seanad how important it is that we preserve it.  It consists of 1,105 large bound volumes and 33,150 sheets.  It can be reduced into three main classifications. The Ordnance Survey collection covering all Ireland from the early part of the last century to date. Included are items no longer available from the Ordnance Survey office.  The second category contains maps of cities and towns and counties of Ireland and of Ireland in general from the earliest times.  Speed's maps of Ireland, the Brooking and Rocque maps of Dublin and Palhams maps of Clare are but a <Col N="119" /> few of the important 17th- and 18th-century surveys contained in these divisions.  Thirdly, the estate maps. These cover the 18th and 19th centuries. The Longfield collection of estate maps is the largest in this division and covers most of the 32 counties of Ireland.</P>
    <P>Besides these main divisions, the collection contains a large number of specialist maps, railway, canal and coastal maps.  The library holds the original manuscripts of a survey of the bogs of Ireland made at the request of a commission set up in the last century.</P>
    <P>This outline will illustrate the intrinsic value of the map collection and the concern of the trustees before all other considerations to put it in safe custody.  The Senator said these maps were not available elsewhere.  I made rather hasty inquiries about this.  I mentioned three categories. The first was the Ordnance Survey collection, which, as far as I know, in terms of volume amounts to almost half the total maps involved.  I understand that the collection of Ordnance Survey maps is available in Trinity College Library.  They would have been deposited there under the Copyright Act.</P>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>That seems to be in dispute.  I was making a similar inquiry and I did not come up with a definite conclusion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. Bruton Mr. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>I should imagine that, with the staff of Trinity College and its legal depository status, the Ordnance Survey maps are available there, too.  I also understand that a number of the maps in the second category I mentioned &mdash; namely, maps of cities, towns and counties in Ireland &mdash; would also be available in the Trinity College Library.  This, I should say, is the result of hasty inquiries on our part because we did not have much notice &mdash; we had some notice but not as much as we could have &mdash; of this motion.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <P>I am happy, however, to be able to end on a constructive note.  I referred earlier to the inter-departmental committee which is examining <Col N="120" /> the short-term and long-term accommodation requirements of the National Library and to the interim report which the committee have submitted and which is currently under consideration. While I am not yet free to give specific details, I am in a position to say that I expect some useful additional accommodation for the National Library to be available in the near future.  If this is a success it will be the first time that additional accommodation would have been made available to the National Library since 1926.</P>
    <P>I should add also that quite apart from the additional accommodation significant progress is being made in the National Library.  They will be publishing in the near future a catalogue of topographical prints and drawings.  With increased staff the manuscripts reading room has been opened again in the evening where previously it was only opened during the day.  The general catalogue, which was last revised in the 1920s, is now being remade.  Clár Litríocht na Gaeilge, which was last brought up to date in 1938, is also being revised. I should add also that, at my initiative, an inter-departmental committee is being set up to set in train an education service for all the cultural institutions such as the National Library and the National Museum to ensure that the treasures which are available there will be made available to a much wider public than were previously able to benefit from them.</P>
    <Speaker pid="JamesDooge" hpid="An Cathaoirleach An Cathaoirleach">
      <NameTxt>An Cathaoirleach</NameTxt>
      <P>I am afraid I shall have to ask the Parliamentary Secretary to come to a conclusion within the next minute.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="JohnBruton" hpid="Mr. Bruton Mr. Bruton">
      <NameTxt>Mr. Bruton</NameTxt>
      <P>In regard to student dissertations, I understand that exceptional arrangements were made at the request of a lecturer from Trinity College for two large volumes of these maps to be brought back especially to accommodate particular students who are engaged in this field. I understand that any other collection to be removed to off-site storage would have caused just as much hardship as the removal of the maps <Col N="121" /> and, therefore, it was an unfortunate choice which had to be made to remove one of the collections.  The one which had to be chosen was the map collection.  I think the Senator will see that we have in hand measures to improve the situation.  We are not satisfied with the existing situation but we are moving forward as quickly as possible to remedy what we recognise to be an unsatisfactory situation.</P>
    </Speaker>
    <Speaker pid="MaryRobinson" hpid="Mrs. Robinson Mrs. Robinson">
      <NameTxt>Mrs. Robinson</NameTxt>
      <P>I should like to thank the Parliamentary Secretary for <Col N="122" /> putting this information on the record. I am still not too happy, because neither the temporary accommodation position or the long-term position is very clear.  But I do appreciate that the Parliamentary Secretary has done a good deal of research for the purposes of replying to this motion.  I should like to thank him for that.</P>
      <P>The Seanad adjourned at 10.15 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Wednesday, 20th February, 1974.</P>
    </Speaker>
  </MainHeading>
</Debate>